<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The yong mans gleanings Gathered out of diuers most zealous and deuout fathers, and now published for the benefit of euerie Christian man, which wisheth good successe to his soule at the later day. Containing these foure subiects. 1 Of the mortality of man. 2 The poore mans harbour. 3 The mirror of vaine-glory. 4 Saint Barnards sermon on the passion of Christ. Whereunto is adioyned a most sweete and comfortable hymne, expressing the euerlasting ioy of a glorified soule. By R.B. gent.</TITLE><AUTHOR>R. B., Gent.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A00514</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 1065</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S115857</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99851074</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99851074</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">16329</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00514)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16329)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 869:19)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The yong mans gleanings Gathered out of diuers most zealous and deuout fathers, and now published for the benefit of euerie Christian man, which wisheth good successe to his soule at the later day. Containing these foure subiects. 1 Of the mortality of man. 2 The poore mans harbour. 3 The mirror of vaine-glory. 4 Saint Barnards sermon on the passion of Christ. Whereunto is adioyned a most sweete and comfortable hymne, expressing the euerlasting ioy of a glorified soule. By R.B. gent.</TITLE><AUTHOR>R. B., Gent.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Brathwaite, Richard, 1588?-1673, attributed name.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bernard, of Clairvaux, Saint, 1090 or 91-1153. aut</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 110 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>At London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Iohn Beale, for Beniamin Lightfoote: and are to bee sold at the corner shoppe at graies Inne Lane end in Holborne,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1614.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>By R. Brathwait?--STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Includes extracts from St. Bernard.</NOTE><NOTE>A variant, with different imprint date, of STC 1064.5.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Bernard, --  of Clairvaux, Saint, 1090 or 91-1153 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Fathers of the church --  Popular works --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A00514">
<STC T="S">1065</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99851074</BIBNO>
<VID>16329</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>The yong mans gleanings.</P>
<P>GATHERED OVT
<HI>OF DIVERS MOST</HI> ZEa∣lous
and Deuout Fathers, and
now published for the benefit of
euerie Christian Man, which wi∣sheth
good successe to his soule
at the later day.</P>
<P>Containing these foure Subiects.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 Of the Mortality of Man.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 The Poore Mans Harbour.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 The Mirror of Vaine-glory.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4 Saint Barnards Sermon on the passion
of Christ.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Whereunto is adioyned a most sweete
and comfortable hymne, expressing
the euerlasting Ioy of a Glo∣rified
<HI>Soule.</HI></P>
<P>By <HI>R. B.</HI> Gent.</P>
<P>AT LONDON
Printed by <HI>Iohn Beale,</HI> for <HI>Beniamin
Lightfoote: and are to bee sold at the</HI>
Corner shoppe at Graies Inne Lane
end in Holborne 1614.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN
READER.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">C</SEG>Hristian Reader (in
the absence of the Au∣thour)
I was moued
to write something in
his behalfe, to demonstrate the
zeale and entire affection he bea∣reth
to the Church in generall, and
to the comfort of thy soule in par∣ticular.
But so well were his de∣uout
intentions by these his suc∣cinct
labors expressed, as I tooke
it needelesse to set a portall before
a Building of it selfe so meriting,
<PB REF="3"/>
or a proeme before a labour so well
deseruing. Great it is not, but
it comprehends so much (I dare
say) of spirituall consolation for re∣freshing
the soule deiected, and mo∣tiue
meditations to rouse the se∣cure
and carnall soule, in the
sleepe of sinne belulled, as an am∣pler
Treatise may well yeeld to so
compendious a volume. Brieflie
I may speake so much of it, as Ci∣cero
spoke of that sententious work
of his entituled <HI>de Oratore: Est
non magnus verum aureolus
Libellus.</HI> Vse it to thy comfort, &amp;
giue thanks to the Lord, whose hand
is not onely the beginner, but per∣fecter
of euery good worke that he
in his due time may bring thee to
<PB REF="3"/>
those ineffable Ioyes in reall frui∣tion,
which whilest thou liuest here
thou onely enioyes by contempla∣tion.
Thus recommending these
meditations to thy deuout consi∣deration,
Thy selfe to the father of
all spiritual comforts, whose mercie
euer shadow thee vnder the wings
of his protection, I rest</P>
<SIGNED>Thy soules well-wisher,
R. B.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<PB REF="4"/>
<P>Workes that now adaies goe to print: are
put to a double presse, Censure and Errors:
for thy censure I hope it will bee charita∣ble;
for these errors let them be excusable.
This age like a fauourable Iurie, acquites
all errors: onely they are put to their booke,
and that saues them.</P>
<P>Errata.</P>
<P>Page 19. l. 13. for despirable reade despicable.
p. 83. l. 14. for imployed reade implied. p. 87. l. 18.
for pilgrimation reade peregrination▪ and l. 27.
for shllatory reade sallatory.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB REF="4"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB N="1" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>OF THE
MORTALITIE
OF MAN.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Hat art thou (O Man) and
from whence hadst thou
thy beginning? What
matter art thou made
of, that thou promisest
to thy selfe length of daies: or to thy
posterity continuance. I haue read the
truest computer of Times, and the best
Arithmetician that euer breathed, and
he reduceth thy dayes into a short num∣ber:
The daies of Man are threescore
and ten. That reuerend Patriarch <HI>Iacob,</HI>
(though he had liued a long and prospe∣rous
time) yet he confesseth his daies to
be few and euill: the life of Man (saith
the Prophet) is as the grasse that soone
<PB N="2" REF="6"/>
withereth: it is as swift as a Dromeda∣rie,
continuing not, but passing from
this pilgrimage of earth, aimeth at the
centre, to which all flesh is limitted,
this earthly mansion from whence we
had our Beginning; <HI>Homo abhumo na∣tus.</HI>
Man is borne of the earth, from
whence he had his birth, and shall con∣clude
the date and period of his daies.
What is it to enioy honour vpon earth,
or to be graced by the royall aspect of
Potentates, their maiestie cannot au∣thorise
thy sinnes, nor exempt thee
from the iudgement of the Almighty.
It is not the King, but the King of Kings
shall iudge, who holdeth his iron rod
in his hand, to be auenged of him that
worketh wickednesse before him. He
cannot endure the waies of the vnrigh∣teous,
but will either looke vpon thee,
with the eyes of his mercie, or giue thee
the wages of sinne, to liue with repro∣bates
and sinners in the neuer quenched
fire of his wrath, there to be punished
eternally. But remember thy mortality,
be not puffed vp with a selfe conceipt
of thine owne excellence: The Swanne
may not be more ashamed of her blacke
<PB N="3" REF="6"/>
feete, then thou of the vlcers and blemi∣shes
of thy soule distained with all im∣purities.
It was the Phylosophers say∣ing:
It were better not to be, then to be
miserable, thy being is most miserable,
thy state lamentable, and thy case irre∣parable:
if thou meditate not of thy cre∣ator,
acknowledge thy redeemer, and
haue recourse vnto thy mercifull pro∣tector:
who preserueth thee daily with
his grace, reuewing in thee his Image,
quite defaced and abolished by reason
of thy transgressions. Wherefore as
there is noe moment nor article
of time, wherein thou stands not in need
of his prouidence, so ought there to be
no time omitted wherein thou should
not ascribe all praise, and gloie to his
excellence. He created thee being no∣thing,
he recreated thee being worse
then nothing, and he preuents thee
with his grace, that art like to fal againe
to nothing. O consider wherein thou
hast offended, and how many and sun∣dry
times thou hast beene pardoned
for the selfe same sinne: let thine eyes
therefore be dissolued into an ocean of
teares, crauing remission with entire
<PB N="4" REF="7"/>
contrition. It is recorded that the teares
of the vine will cure the leprosie:
teares of hearty and vnfained repen∣tance
will cure the leprosie of sinne,
restore thee to the Throne of grace, and
in the end conduct thee to the King∣dome
of glory. Thou art farre trans∣planted
from thy natiue Country: in a
desolate and remote place: farre from
comfort or hope of rest, till this Taber∣nacle
of sinne shall be dissolued, this
roabe of flesh shall be diuided from that
spirituall stole of purity, whereby thou
may ascend the pallaces of eternall
glorie. There is none that liueth in ex∣ile,
but would haue the censure of Ba∣nishment
reuoked: thou art in a place
of exile an inhabitant with Wolues and
Tigers: for better were it (saith Dio∣genes)
to liue with Wolues, Tigers, and
all sauage Beasts of the Mountaines,
then with Sycophants, flatterers and
such tame beasts in the Citie. Thou art
inuironed with many sharpe encoun∣ters
inuaded with many turbulent passi∣ons,
thought▪ feare, desire, and the like:
all which as so many waspes doe conti∣nually
infest and annoy thee. Thou art
<PB N="5" REF="7"/>
trauelling a dangerous way, where ma∣ny
obiects seeme to seduce thee from
the high-roadeway, to the flourishing
by-paths of vanity, being neuer lesse se∣cure,
then when thou seemest most se∣cure.
Thou art sailing betwixt two pe∣rilous
rockes, two calamitous shelfs,
<HI>Scilla</HI> and <HI>Charybdis, Presumption</HI> and
<HI>Despaire.</HI> Thou hadst need of an expert
and vigilant Pilote to direct thee, a
faithfull friend to comfort thee, and a
prepared minde within thee: thou fishest
in a troubled streame, and many things
I could caution thee of, which not fore∣seene
may endanger shipwracke to thy
crasie and surcharged Barke. Oppose
not thy selfe to all extremes, but fix the
Anchor: it would hold against all tem∣pests,
and prouide a repose in time for
thy poore vessell, least vanquished and
oppressed with violence of Billowes,
and extremity of aduerse waues, shee
be enforced to split, loosing both thy
selfe and thy fraight: spread not thy
sailes too broad for the windes (thy vi∣olent
affections) are most forced, when
thy sayles, (thy ambitious thoughts) are
most extended. Ballace it light, least it
<PB N="6" REF="8"/>
sinke with her Burden: It is better to
loose the fraight then the Merchant:
and the Phylosopher <HI>Mymus</HI> chused
rather to lose his gold then himselfe.
Enter not thy Barke with any prophane
man: if his company doe not ruinate
thee, it may well depraue thee: and
when <HI>Bias</HI> came into any shippe or ves∣sell
with a wicked man, where he was
in danger of shipwrack, he would neuer
suffer the prophane man to pray, say∣ing,
take heede least the Gods heare
thee, for then wee can expect for no
mercie. But aboue all let the sterne
(the principall Organs and faculties
of the soule) bee euer with all vi∣gilancie
attended, wisely gouerne∣ned,
and industriouslie employed.
Thou art to saile by Syrens (those three
daughters of <HI>Achelous</HI> and <HI>Callyope</HI>)
a naturall euitation of that which is
good, a naturall inclination to that
which is euill, and a naturall deprauati∣on
of the will: reiect the pernicious em∣braces
of sinne and impietie, stop thine
eares to the Syrens melodie, and reduce
thy thoughts to that retired harbour
of tranquilitie, a sincere and secure con∣science:
<PB REF="8"/>
it is a Christians brasen wall,
it makes vs secure of things past, it ad∣uertiseth
vs of things present, and pre∣pareth
it selfe for things to come: No
Monument so glorious, no statue so spe∣cious:
for what will curious Sepulchers
auaile vs, when infamie perpetuates the
memorie of vs. <HI>Vita mortuorum in Me∣moria
viuentium posita est.</HI> And vertue
liueth after death; The Ancient Patri∣archs
returned to the sepulchers of their
Auncestours, but that had beene but lit∣tle,
if their vertues had not equalled
their auncestors. Desirest thou to haue
the excellencie of this painted world,
the beautie of this earthlie Theatre cha∣ractred
and displaied to thee in her co∣lors?
Thou shalt see in her many see∣ming
flourishes of happinesse, many
faire promises of a continuated emi∣nence:
but shee failes in her perfor∣mance:
her fruits are but flowers, and
her haruest soone tipe, and soone rotten.
<HI>Sodoms</HI> apples were faire to the eye,
touch them, &amp; they turne to dust. Pain∣ted
Sepulchers shew much beautie, and
seeme as if they would outliue time, yet
continuance defaceth them, remaining
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
memorable in nothing, saue that they
were once memorable. Starres fixed
shine the brightest: fix thy thoughts vp∣on
the morning Sun of righteousnesse,
and like the Sun, thou shalt shine more
bright at thy setting, then at thy rising,
at thy death then thy birth, let thy mind
be established on that which can suffice
it: no terrestriall respect of earths vani∣tie,
but an expectance of heauens eterni∣tie,
to receaue that Crowne for which it
was created, and not the wages of sinne,
for which shee was not ordained. Thou
hast many difficulties to passe in this
wildernesse, ere thou can see the Land
of promise; Thou must thirst, hunger,
and wander; thirst, but for the well of
life; hunger, but for the staffe of spirituall
Bread; wander but at last (with the good
Shunamite,) to returne from the moun∣taines
of <HI>Gilboa,</HI> to the vale of <HI>Bethlem,</HI>
the poole of <HI>Bethesda:</HI> to the vale of
<HI>Bethlem,</HI> where thou may repose, to the
poole of <HI>Bethesda,</HI> where thou may take
repast: yet must thou not murmure in
this long peregrination: Thou art but
as thy forefathers haue beene: if affli∣cted,
so was thy master Christ: if temp∣ted,
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
so was he: if persecuted, behold the
whole Colledge of those blessed Apo∣stles,
making their whole life a persecu∣tion,
a very martyrdome to propagate
their masters glorie, and to performe
that worke for which they were sent.
Thou must not make profit of thy pro∣fession
with <HI>Magus,</HI> nor make sale of
thy conscience with <HI>Demas,</HI> nor sell thy
Sauiour with <HI>Iudas.</HI> Thou art inuested
with Christs owne Garment, endewed
with more especiall priuiledges, and
prerogatiues then many of thy bre∣thren,
boast not of that thou hast recea∣ued,
he that did giue them thee, can take
them from thee, and make thee naked,
that was once garnished with such sin∣gular
ornaments, bestowing them on o∣thers
that shall better vse them, since
whilst thou hadst them, thou didst abuse
them. Enuie not anothers gifts, but ra∣ther
thanke God for his ample benefits
extended vpon thy brother: that perni∣cious
vice of enuie is the corrupter of
many singular vertues: and to describe
her more perspicuously, heare the
ancient fathers how they decypher this
vniuersall contagion of the world. En∣uie
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
consumes all vertues: by enuie was
Christ crucified, the historie whereof is
mentioned vnto thee, enuie and malice
aboue all other vices inebriate the
soule. Where there is enuie, there can
be no Brotherly loue. Who enuieth lo∣ueth
not: the law of the Diuell is in him,
because the diuell by enuie fell. There∣fore
enuie is knowne by this, that shee
is neuer in charitie. For by enuie was
Christ crucified, and consequently who
enuieth his brother, crucifieth Christ.
<HI>Aug:</HI> Enuie alwaies followeth vertue:
he is a valiant man that can conquer
enuie with humility. <HI>Hier:</HI> Hee is sure
an enuious man that taketh pleasure in
seeing another mans dammage or pu∣nishment:
<HI>Ambros:</HI> the error of enuie
doth not onely inuade the Synagogues
of the impious, but the cels of the religi∣ous.
<HI>Euseb.</HI> Enuie manifesteth that we
haue not the loue of God in vs. <HI>Ef∣frem.</HI></P>
<P>It is a rare thing to want enuie in
prosperitie. <HI>Iosephus:</HI> where the good
man profiteth, there the enuious repi∣neth:
as the Poet saith: <HI>Inuidus alterius,
&amp;c. Isidorus.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="10"/>Here thou feest enuie dismasked:
who euer with <HI>Ctesyphon</HI> kicketh a∣gainst
the Moles heeles: there is no ver∣tue
can passe vncensured: no exquisite
worke vnreproued: <HI>necesse est quôd Mo∣mum
aut Mimum habet, qui vertutem
amat.</HI> But run thou a religious course
inclining neither on the right hand, nor
on the left: on the right hand thou may
be too precise in being too regular, on
the left hand, insuccessiue, being too si∣nister.
The Goulden mediocritie, is as
good a way, and as secure as the Phylo∣sophers
<HI>Galaxia,</HI> their milke way:
here is true consolation in spirit: for
the righteous bee glad and reioyce in it:
walke in this way, and the suggestions
of Satan shall not seduce thee, for thou
art in the way that leadeth vnto life, not
intangled in the Brakes of this world,
but expecting the glorious possession
of those Ioyes aboue. Continue in per∣fect
charity with thy brother, it is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,
the fulfilling and perfecting of the
Law: it reconciles vs vnto God, appea∣seth
his indignation conceiued against
vs, and assures vs of the performance of
his promise, made vnto vs in his sonne.
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
By the loue of God is the loue to our
Neighbour ingendred, by the loue to
our Neighbour, is the loue of God nou∣rished:
here is a mutuall and reciprocall
loue: a threefold Cord is hardly broken.
But thou obiectest thou hast felt the
heauy hand of God, thou hast tasted of
the bitter cup, and drunke deepe of the
Cup of affliction: what then? where is
thy conclusion? doest thou reason
hence that thou art depriued of the fa∣uour
of God, and excluded from his
sheepfold? God forbid: these afflicti∣ons
doe rather approue and testifie his
exceeding loue towards thee: whom I
loue saith the Lord, those I chastice and
correct: he is not a father, where thou
art not a sonne, nor is he a sonne that is
incorrigible: he must bow his necke
vnto the yoke, and presse his shoulders
with the Burden, he must not argue that
the burden is heauie, or the yoke not
easie: but with all patience sustaine all,
and support all, that God may be glori∣fied
in all. This resolution will arme
thee with a serious preparation against
all difficulties, calling to minde, how
the Apostler (after the death and passi∣on
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
of Christ Iesus) were as a puissant
armie constant amidst all tribulations.
Their afflictions, their stripes, their im∣prisonments,
were experiments to trie
them not affrightments to dismay them:
By them they were proued and in their
resolution approued, because they
fought valiantly the Lords Battell, to
increase the number of the faithfull, to
breake the bread of life, to such as were
appointed vnto saluatiō: weakning the
power of Antichrist, and discomfiting
sinne. Fight thus (deere Christian) and
thou shalt raign where those victorious
champions raigne already: the vale of
this earthly habitation shall be dissol∣ued,
and thy spirituall Temple renewed,
to supplant the whole body of sinne,
and to receiue a glorious diadem of e∣ternitie,
by subiecting thy selfe to the
materiall sword, to be nourished with
that spirituall foode of Gods word vn∣to
eternall life: for whosoeuer will
raigne with Christ, must likewise suffer
with Christ. He was crucified that we
might be saued, and shall we be exemp∣ted
from that which he suffered? No,
rather let vs put on the complete Ar∣mour
<PB N="14" REF="12"/>
of righteousnesse, with slings in
our hands to wound that malicious
Goliah, that terrible Philistine in the
head: that is, vtterly to discomfit him:
that we who haue receiued so glorious
an inuestiture, the speciall indowments
of his Grace, may by the operation of
his spirit effectually working in vs ar∣riue
at the Kingdome of glorie. That
what is here inchoate, may be there
consummate; of Christ we are called
Christians: if we be Christians of Christ,
we should follow Christ: that ascending
with him to the Crosse on Mount <HI>Cal∣uarie,</HI>
we may likewise ascend with him
to his Throne exalted with maiestie.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="15" REF="12"/>
<HEAD>THE
POORE MANS
HARBOVR.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>N thy affliction haue I
heard thee and in the
bitternesse of thy sor∣rowes
haue I attended
thee: for thou descen∣dedst
down as it were into the graue, &amp;
buried thy honour in the dust. But who
euer hath cried vpon me, that I haue not
heard, or craued my helpe, whom I haue
not aided? Art thou poore, and sicke,
and hungry, and naked, crying for almes
yet art not rewarded, for one crum yet
art not satisfied? why, what of this? if
thou bee poore, so was <HI>Lazarus:</HI>
if sicke, hungry, and naked, so was
he: if despised, so was hee: character
what miseries soeuer thy miserable state
is afflicted with, and thou shalt see
<PB N="16" REF="13"/>
them personated (in more ample sort)
in disconsolate <HI>Lazarus;</HI> yet was not
he comforted? were not his rags turned
to robes, his hunger to festiuall honour,
his pensiue affliction, to extensiue con∣solation?
he was abandoned of <HI>Diues,</HI>
contemned of <HI>Diues,</HI> nay reproued and
shamefully iniured by the seruants of
<HI>Diues;</HI> yet behold the exchange: <HI>Laza∣rus</HI>
is exalted, <HI>Diues</HI> tormented, <HI>Laza∣rus</HI>
comforted, <HI>Diues</HI> afflicted: <HI>Laza∣rus</HI>
in <HI>Abrahams</HI> bosome, in ioy for e∣uer,
<HI>Diues</HI> in the fire of hell, to be deli∣uered
neuer▪ O what subiect of ioy and
comfort, what argument of diuine con∣solation
is this vnto a poore distressed
soule, that trauels vpon the pilgrimage
of earth, hungry, naked, and despised?
But there is a greater occasion then this
for him to pull vp his courage, to solace
his depressed minde; and that is the very
promise of God himselfe past (and that
by a constitution irreuocable) to the
poore and afflicted spirit. I looke to him
saith the Lord by the mouth of his
Prophet <HI>Esay,</HI> that is poore, that is bro∣ken
in spirit, and that trembleth at my
words. Here the Lord professeth him∣selfe
<PB N="17" REF="13"/>
a patron to the poore, their stength
and mighty defence in the time of their
necessity. He is none of our time-ob∣seruing
friends, our state affectors, that
rather patronise our errors (to insinuate
themselues in to the vnstedy affections
not of vs, but of our patrimonies) so
long professing amitie till our estate
(the adulterate oyle of their pretended
friendshippe) be extinguished. These are
good Mammonists augmenting their
meanes by indirect courses: running e∣uer
on the Byas of Adulation, till that
clawing humour worke to their vnhap∣pie
friend remedilesse desolation. But
God is faithfull: and whom he once
loueth, he loueth vnto the end. How
happie art thou (poore pilgrim) of such
a louer, that erects thy drowping head,
directs thy erring feet, supports thy de∣clining
faith, and placeth thee in the re∣tired
harbor of all spirituall comforts,
ministring these and the like solaces vn∣to
thee. Wipe thy eyes (poore harbor∣lesse
soule) complaine not of times ini∣quitie,
descant not of thy penury, re∣late
no more of thy miserie: I haue
heard thy voice, and am come to com∣fort
<PB N="18" REF="14"/>
thee, I haue put all thy teares vp in
a Bottell, and they shall remaine as te∣stimonies
against those obdurate and
impenitent, those remorcelesse and vn∣charitable
<HI>Nabals</HI> that haue stopped
their eares to thy cries, their eyes to thy
teares: solace thy selfe in me, for I will
receaue thee into my protection: I will
shelter thee vnder the wings of my mer∣cie,
so as no violence shall oppresse
thee, no ensewing miserie afflict thee,
no pouerty dismay thee: for why? I am
rich in mercy, and will enrich thee with
the comforts of my diuine spirit. Who
euer called vpon me, and I heard him
not, or powred his prayers vnto me and
I relieued him not? Thy pouerty is no
barre in my Court to hinder thy expe∣dition:
Thou beggest and surest <HI>informa
pauperis,</HI> yet thou shalt finde a Solici∣tour
that will not neglect thy affaires:
He it is that created thee (as well as the
mighty ones of this world) and he will
not suffer his Image, his similitude, his
Impression to be rased, defaced or con∣temned.
It is I that haue seene thee ex∣posed
to all the miseries of earth, and I
considered thy patience: for which haue
<PB N="19" REF="14"/>
I accepted thy prayers which (like sweet
and redolent persumes) ascended vp
vnto my nostrels. Be comforted, be
comforted: the extent of thy afflictions
is almost expired, the date of thy sor∣rowes
extended, and the period of thy
miseries consummate. I will cloth thee
with the Garments of eternity: Thou
shalt dwell in the mansions of my glo∣rious
City, and for thy pouerty, receaue
the rich ornaments of a celestiall inheri∣tour:
and herein shall thy ioyes be re∣doubled,
for thou that liued desperable
in the eyes of men, shalt Triumph a∣mongst
the quires of Angels, being in∣corporated
in the glorious society of
all those heaunly Cittizens which
raigne with me eternally. There shalt
thou haue for these poore rags, Gar∣ments
that shall neuer be worne. There
thou shalt feede on spirituall Manna,
and Mella, there shall be no hunger, but
eternall feasting, no sorrow, but perpe∣tuall
reioycing, no discord, but mindes
generally vniting: where fulnesse shall
not breede lothing, nor others glorie
in thee repining, nor lights perpetuitie
obscuring, nor times eternitie ending:
<PB N="20" REF="15"/>
for there will I be all vnto all, to shew
my glory more euidently towards all.
Thus will that father of all comfort,
comfort thee with his diuine consolati∣ons:
thus will he in the very middest of
thy anguishes, miraculously, infuse &amp; in∣still
into thy distressed soule, these &amp; the
like spirituall refections: he will annoint
thee with the oyle of <HI>Gilead,</HI> &amp; put vpon
thee a new raiment, and on thy finger
will he put a ring of pure Gold, with
the seale of Armes on it: with the seale
of thy election, predestined to eternall
life. O meditate of this, and the like di∣uine
comforts, and the perturbations,
billowes and afflictions of this life, will
be lightly esteemed in comparison of
that exceeding measure, and quantity
aboue all measure, of spirituall Trea∣sures,
reserued for thee in heauen. A∣lasse
thou liuest here (that I may vse the
Greeke phrase) <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,
In the very penetrals and cauernes of
the earth: farre remoued from thy cen∣tre,
farre transplanted from thy natiue
Countrie. O then be not so enthralled
with this masse of corruption, so capti∣uated
by sinne and Sathan, so deluded
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
by the vaine flourishes of earths vani∣ties:
eleuate thy spirit, erect thy minde,
liue not so long in this dangerous Cly∣mate,
as thou forget to returne into thy
Countrie. Thou hast an excellent mo∣tiue
(poore hunger-starued soule) not
to desire thy abode or residence vpon
earth: sith thou feelest within thee
nought but biting hunger, and without
thee, nought but hard hearts, that con∣sume
their daies in chambering and
wantonnesse, in securitie and careles∣nesse,
respectlesse (heauen knowes) of
their chiefest good, the aduancement
of Gods glorie, the feare of his name,
reuerence to his ministers, or any worke
which might tend to the edification of
faith or manners. <HI>Hinc illae lachrimae;</HI>
hence comes our cause of lamenting,
hence the true and efficient motiues of
sorrowing: But thou (pore man) that art
sequestred as it were out of the world,
not as much as obserued with the eie of
popular respect, seeing thy owne con∣tempt
of one side, and the impiety of
this enormious Age of the other side,
hast reason with <HI>Paul</HI> not onely to de∣sire
thy dissolution, but euen in the me∣ditation
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
of it to conceaue especiall
comfort, and delight. For the world
what is it, But a cage of vncleane Birds,
a masse of indigestion, an indisposed
frame of pollution, a sink of corruption?
True was it, that that Dominican Frier
obserued: There was in the world at
the first (saith he) <HI>conscientia,</HI> but that was
altered presently and turned to <HI>scientia,</HI>
and that too (by the foolish stupidity of
these times) is changed into <HI>mere Entia,</HI>
a poore Being indeed, when we know
not the essentiall cause of our Being:
but ledde away with either singular
conceipt of our ignorant knowledge
or besotted with the present obiects
presented and represented to vs: which
so auert and distract the intellectuall
eye of our vnderstanding, or so enthral∣led
and engaged as it were to priuate
profit, like the worldly statist, or with
the itch of honour like the Ambitious
Artist, or with the dispersing of our vi∣ctories
in forraine prouinces with the
insulting Martialist: that we forget (for
a little worldly gaine) the Gayne and
treasure of Eternitie: for a puffe or blast
of vaine glory or ambitious honour,
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
the Honour of God, and sacred mini∣sters:
for a soone perishing fame, the
fame and reputation which wee ought
to purchase of our heauenly father.
Deere pilgrim, thou seest these transito∣rie
and temporarie delights, how soone
they fade: how short their continuance
is: for thou canst see further then one
in higher place can see. We make the
Argument infallible: for demonstrati∣on
proues it: a man may see more pier∣cingly
into the beauty of the firmament
within some hollow place or pit, then
he can vpon the euen superficies of the
earth. Thou art placed in this pit; reti∣red
from the world: inferiour in order,
bereft of the cloude of honour, nay ex∣empted
of all inconueniences which
might any way seeme to darken the eye
of thy vnderstanding, here thou seest
the piecolored flagges of vanity dis∣plaied,
the poore Ostrich robbed of her
taile, to fanne a Ladies face. The sillie
wormes disbowelled to cloath a case
of corruption with a silken couer. <HI>Nec
atriora sane vidimus peccata, quam ea quae
sunt sericea;</HI> Silken sins goe with a priui∣ledge:
they haue a good couer for de∣formiti,
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
this I know (simple soule)
thou seest and admirest. Then thou
goes further, and thou sees seeming san∣ctitie
put on the roabes of holinesse:
furnisht with a little lippe labour to
mumble a few key cold deuotion-lesse
prayers, making his lippes goe as if pos∣sessed
with some spirit, as indeed he is,
for no spirit more execrable then hypo∣crisie:
there thou seest halting instice; a
Magistrate that goes on stilts to saue
his footecloth, hee ouerperes a whole
multitude, but taking so great paines
vpon his artificiall legges, he must be
annointed; theres no remedy, hee will
grow stiffe else: it is a golden potion
must restore him his sence of hearing
which was welnigh perished: applie but
this receipt to his pulse; and the vertue
is admirable, its better then Eare-salue
it will restore him the faculty of hearing
instantlie. There thou seest a great pa∣tron
of iniuries, that has erected two
Sanctuaries, dedicated to two contrary
Soueraignesses: <HI>Vertue,</HI> and <HI>Vice;</HI> Vertue
for her name, Vice for her Nature: many
such professors of vertue (poore beg∣gar)
I know thou findest, that can make
<PB N="25" REF="17"/>
externall show or appearance of vertue,
but hath vice to be vertues riuall: ver∣tues
building is easie to be discerned:
theres no superficiall cost to beautifie
her Temple: shee hath a good inside
and a bare outside: vice her opponent
boasts (and truely so shee may) of curi∣ous
edifices, rare deuises, monuments
of more honour and celebritie then
poore vertue and all her posterity euer
attained to, in the one the worlds map
is rightly charactred: in the other, there
is representation of a more glorious
pallace. But I will proceed further:
they haue beene characterised too of∣ten
to bee now vnknowne. Now thou
hast seene all this (poore pilgrim) rag∣ged
vertue, and roabed vice: thou canst
not be deceaued in their Colors. The
purple whore is easie to be discerned,
me thinkes thou should glorie much in
thy ragges: seeing vertue no better
clad: one better habilimented with
rents then rints. God hath done well
for thee to giue thee so faire a patterne
to imitate: nor is it disparagement to
be her attendant with thine owne Gar∣ment:
without adorning thy outside to
<PB N="26" REF="18"/>
grace so faire an inside, for vertue is de∣pictured
the best when hee is garnished
the least. Thus, thus consider what thou
art, and whom thou resemblest: not one
vndeseruing because of thy wants: for
the exquisitest deseruings are for most
part the vnworthiliest recompenced:
But the verie Idea of imparaleld good∣nesse,
Vertue her selfe, shee is naked, so
art thou: harborlesse so art thou: in her
selfe deseruing, yet desertlesly estee∣med,
and so art thou: your fortunes
seeme equall: doe but match her in the
mindes proprieties, and thy reward shal
be by so much more eminent, in regard
thy estate was here depressed. I will
yet draw nerer thee, thou art here pla∣ced
in a desolate forrest, farre remoued
from any either internall or externall
comfort, saue that continuall feast (a
sincere conscience:) Thou art without
friends, and no desert more solitarie
no forrest greater, then to be depriued
of friends: and in this vncouth promon∣torie
there bee many sauage Beasts
which seeke to pray vpon thee, or at
least to triumph ouer thee: and wouldst
thou not willingly retire thy selfe, and
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
purchase thy owne safety by a seque∣stred
life? or if not, <HI>Semel mori melius est,
quam semper moriendo viuere.</HI> Alasse
(deere christian pilgrim) thou art in this
state: this desert is the world repleni∣shed
with sauage beasts, with which
thou art enuironed: some lyon like con∣temne
thee for thy pouerty, others de∣ride
thee without remorse had to thy
deiected fortunes: But all triumph ouer
thee (being made as <HI>Heluius pertinax</HI>
was entitled) <HI>Pila fortunae,</HI> fortunes ball:
tossed into euery hazard, subiected to
euery calumnie, being indeed made the
very stale of disgrace: yet in all these
occurrents (if thou make right vse of
thy pouertie) thou remaines free from
any perturbation whatsoeuer: their
pride makes the more humble: their
ambition worketh in thee mortificati∣on:
their contemning thee breedeth in
thee a contempt of the world, relinqui∣shing
the garish obiects of vanitie to
reape the haruest of heauens glorie. I
will now descend and that briefly to
the discourse of such as conceiued
more entire ioy and rest in their soules,
by abandoning the world, giuing their
<PB N="28" REF="19"/>
goods vnto the poore, nay such as vo∣luntarilie
became poore, that they
might follow Christ, then if they had
possessed the inestimable treasures of
the whole Earth. The reason that indu∣ced
me hereunto was: forasmuch as I
know examples be of more force then
precepts, the exact and as it were liuely
description thereof imprints in our
mindes an ardent desire of imitating
such whose wel disposed liues made
their ends glorious Reade but the sacred
ordinances and lawes of God; Thou
shalt see the Apostles contemning all
priuate respects whatsoeuer to tast the
sweetenesse of the inestable loue of
Christ: here thou shalt see one called
from the receipt of custome, a place of
profit, to follow him, who had as little
appearance of externall happinesse as
might be: streight thou shalt behold a∣nother
(conuerted from an Arch-perse∣cutour
of Christians) one that flouri∣shed
in the height of honour and was
chosen for a patron of infidelitie, de∣spise
honour and her superficiall flou∣rishes,
and consecrate himselfe to the
supportance of truth: here another (e∣uen
<PB N="29" REF="19"/>
now a Rabbi a great Doctor of the
Law, and one in especiall esteeme with
the multitude for Christs sake) become
contemptible to tast the sweetenesse of
Christs loue in it selfe inexplicable. <HI>Za∣cheus</HI>
for this loue willingly became
poore, duiding his goods to the poore,
and making restitution for what he
had iniuriously taken: for this loue, and
for this incomparable sweetenesse did
the stones wherewith blessed <HI>Stephen</HI>
was stoned seeme sweete vnto him: for
this did Saint <HI>Laurence</HI> tast the Tor∣ments
of the Gridiron with especiall
sweetnesse: this moued <HI>Andrew</HI> to goe
pleasantly vnto the Crosse, that hee
might hasten vnto the diuine sweetnes:
for this <HI>Bartholomew</HI> willingly sustai∣ned
death, <HI>Iohn</HI> drunke poison, &amp; <HI>Peter</HI>
(as one made drunk, with the apprehen∣sion
of that supernal sweetenesse,) cried
out, let vs build here three Tabernacles,
let vs soiorne here, let vs remaine here,
since we need nothing that is necessa∣ry
for our comfort so long as we abide
here. O then deere christian if the sur∣ueigh
of these glorious professors pre∣uaile
any thing with thee to distast the
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
bitter and vnsauory affections of this
transitory life: make vse of thine owne
pouerty: thou hast no reason to stand
all the day idle, but to haue recourse to
the spirituall vineyard. It is hard for a
rich man to enter into the kingdome of
heauen, for why? he must take leaue of
his friends and fauorites, of his reue∣newes
and possessions, there be many
things oppose themselues to his inten∣ded
resolution. But thou that carriest
all thy prefserments about with thee,
hauing nothing at home but bare wals,
appendices of ruine, thou that canst not
yeeld nature her necessaries, being
made a very spectacle to triumphing
fortune: one as exposed to the inconue∣niences
of times occurrents, so de∣priued
of those externall Blessings, by
which we onely seeme to be and haue
our wellbeing: art rid of these maine
impediments which vse to hinder the
worldling from the prosecution of such
affaires as might yeeld more perfect
and accomplished content, then all the
semblances of fortune, and prosperous
successe. O how hard hath the abando∣ning
of the world seemed to such as
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
haue planted their affections already
vpon this terrestriall foundation. They
could willingly serue Christ, if they
might reserue (likewise) some retired
howers of seruice &amp; deuotion to Mam∣mon:
but wholly to giue vp their inte∣rest
in earth and earthly possessions, ne∣uer
more to call themselues masters of
their ample and commodious inheri∣tances:
O it is an hard lesson, such a bit∣ter
potion had neede of some sweete
pill to season it. Thou now seest the
high roade-way that leades thee to a
port of secure rest: hold on (deere pil∣grim)
and faint not in thy Iourney:
thou art now towards a rich inheri∣tance,
and shalt possesse those true essen∣tiall
and reall ioyes which with such
feruencie thou hast desired. But yet
ere I leaue thee in this Harbour, let me
expostulate the cause with thee, &amp; aske
thee, why thou art deiected? why so
sorrowfull? thou sustainest disgrace and
art called impudent Beggar; Beggar?
alasse what is that? who is not? doe we
not (euen the best of vs) beg from day
to day for our diurnall sustenance? in∣cluded
in that particle: <HI>Giue vs this
<PB N="32" REF="21"/>
day our daily bread:</HI> but thou art impu∣dent;
with farre more impudence are
we branded, that are euer begging, yet
neuer satisfied: nay more, presuming to
haue what we neede without asking:
and for thee (poore soule) necessitie
pleades thy cause excusable. <HI>Egenti vi∣ro
pudor nequaquam est vitilis.</HI> A shame∣fast
Beggar neuer gained by his profes∣sion.
Grieue not thy selfe then at the
strange language of the hard harted mi∣ser:
his owne words shall condemne
him when he appeares (as of necessitie
he must) before the Tribunall of Gods
iudgement: its not then the awfull re∣gard
of his authoritie (for he is then de∣graded)
nor the aboundance of his
wealth (for of that hee is depriued) nor
the generall respect had to his person
(for then he is disualewed) that shall
answere for his neglect: Thy hunger
shall witnesse against him, thy afflicti∣ons
shall condemne him, and those ma∣ny
Iniuries (which with such patience
thou in this life sustained) shall be re∣corded
in those monumentall leaues of
eternitie, and proclaime him Guiltie:
for doubt it not (poore wretch) though
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
there bee none now to comfort thee,
but such as laugh at thy miseries, when
thou shalt be let out of this poore pri∣son
of flesh, and transported to thy na∣tiue
countrey, there will be an Aduo∣cate
that will pleade thy cause freely,
and doe thee right speedily. The euill
Iudge in the Gospell was rather moued
by the widdowes importunity, then her
causes equity to doe her right. But this
Iudge will discusse thy cause, neither
drawne by importunacie, nor awed by
authority, nor subiected to partialitie:
he it is that is Iudge of heauen &amp; earth,
extending the Heauens lke a Curtaine,
and in mercie expressing his affections
to the Children of Men. Before this
Iudge shalt thou appeare, and hee that
oppressed thee: he to tast the rigour and
seuerity of iustice, thou to remain in the
comfortable embrace of his mercie:
he to reape the fruits of his own works,
to condemnation, thou to conceiue the
sweete and amiable tast of eternall con∣solation.
O what difference then be∣twixt
thy miserie, and his earthly hap∣pinesse?
where is then that great atten∣dance?
those many superficiall ceremo∣nies
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
of obsequiousnesse? vanisht, va∣nisht:
his afflictions more violent, in as∣much
his comforts in this life were
more eminent. O if the Great ones of
this world would consider this: how
little would they esteeme the insubstan∣tiall
flourishes of this world? how at∣tentiuely
would they obserue the di∣mensions
of their life, least the labyrinth
of sinne should ensnare them, the affe∣ctions
of earths vanitie surprise them:
or the gay colors of mundane allure∣ments
captiuate them. But sinne is now
mounted, her throne is erected, and
who dare censure so generall a profes∣sion?
as rare is it to finde vice without
a champion, as to finde hospitality in
an ancient house, sanctitie in a Monaste∣rie,
religion in a house of prostitution.
A man may see feasts solemnised, but
the halt, lame▪ and blind, seldome or ne∣uer
inuited; resembling those sensuall
meetings of Penelopes wooers, which
<HI>Emneus</HI> in <HI>Homer</HI> so exactly describes,
<HI>opifices Vates, Medicus seu etiam poeta
qui cantando oblectet, hi sane vocati sunt
in orbe: Egentem vero et Medicum qui si∣bimet
est in commodo nullus vocat.</HI> None
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
cals the beggar: his rags are not fit for
festiuall solemnities: alasse poore man,
then must hee feede (like Democritus)
vpon the smell of dainties, full seruices
are not for a weake stomacke, and yet
me thinkes (poore Soule) thou deseruest
better entertainement. Thy Image
should not be so lightned. Thy naturall
Garment is of as pure stuffe, and as cu∣rious
as the perfumedst Gallant of them
all: and should the couer of our shame
so much transport our affections, that
without respect vnto the image of our
Sauiour, we should disualue the instru∣ment,
and so ouerprise the couer▪ O no,
let vs not so obscure our iudgements:
let vs rather haue recourse to our be∣ginning,
and then conceiue the especi∣allest
motiues wherein we haue cause
to glorie. Sure Nature seemes as if in
the beginning shee hated all other or∣naments
then such as were natiue: be∣ing
at the first a raiment to her selfe, and
sufficient in her selfe against the incle∣mencie
of heate, the violence of cold,
&amp; all distemperatures whatsoeuer: But
when man lost himselfe, he desired to
shroude himselfe against the violent as∣saults
<PB N="36" REF="23"/>
of a troubled conscience. Hence
then wee glorie in our shame: for by
these externall habits are we put in
minde of those primitiue graces of
which wee are depriued. In this then
(sillie Beggar) may thou likewise be
comforted: Thou seest thine owne na∣kednesse,
and acknowledgest thy sinne:
But the fine creatures of this world
imitate the Pagan Idolators, they hang
vales ouer their deformities; making
their worst part the most precious. Pore
vessell of corruption what needes all
this brauery? what makes thee set out
thy enemy so gorgeouslie? she seeks thy
ruine, laies continual battery at the for∣tresse
at the fortresse of thy soule, enui∣rons
thee with hostile and fatall affe∣ctions,
and yet thou pamperest her vp
still, strengthning thy owne forces a∣gainst
thee. O madnesse! O exceeding
phrensie, doest thou not (or is it wilfull
blindnesse) perceiue with what violence
this morsell of flesh which thou bringst
vp and nourishest so carefully, sugge∣steth
into thy minde poison? making
the labour of an incurable contagion,
euen the lethargie of thy soule; and wilt
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
thou cherish yet this Snake in thine
owne Bosome? wilt thou raise so glori∣ous
an Image for so corrupt a Trunke?
Surcease, surcease: Thou hast plaid too
long with this inchantresse: it is now
high time to purchase thy liberty. Af∣ter
<HI>Calypso</HI> had so long time detained
<HI>Vlisses</HI> in miserable seruitude, at last
sought meanes for his deliuerie. These
bosome enemies are most dangerous,
they know our constitution, and can
transforme themselues vnto the distinct
habit of euery affection, to shadow their
designes more couertly; they assume
that forme which best concords with
our Nature. This thou seest (poore man)
and in this art thou eased: for this ene∣mie
of thine, thy flesh, receiues more
hard entertainement at thy hands. Thou
keepst her from rebelling, and streng∣thens
thy spirit by her weakning. In this
then hast thou aduantage of the flesh-pampering
Epicure, &amp; therein showes
pregnant testimonie of thy expert
iudgement; for who would preferre the
rinde before the pith, the Barke before
the medull, or core before the sap? But
these doe so, disesteeming the internall
<PB N="38" REF="24"/>
ornaments of the minde, the best graces
that a Christian soule can appropri∣ate
to her selfe, exalt the outward
(which God wot) like a painted Sepul∣cher,
or <HI>Sodoms</HI> apples be no sooner
touched then to ashes conuerted▪ Beau∣tie,
a flourishing vanity that soone fa∣deth:
externall pompe, honour and
magnificence lesse then bare Beings, for
soone they decline and haue no being.
Time-obseruing worse then either, ma∣king
of times an oilie Tongue the ruine
of the owner. These are the scopes are
aimed at: and yet what greater vanitie,
than the possession of such extrinsecall
shadowes? I haue oftimes seene it, and
the frequencie of it hath welnigh made
it a position, those which suddenly stept
to honour, by their vnexpected risings,
made their fall shortly to be expected:
Nor did their memorie die with their
fall: the merit of their honour was cald
in question after their death, howsoe∣uer
ill in them that cald it in question,
taking the Cynicks precept for an espe∣ciall
caueat in all my Actions: <HI>in Sepul∣chra
Mortuorum leuius calcare.</HI> But of
this digression too much: I haue retired
<PB N="39" REF="24"/>
my selfe too long from thee (poore bro∣ther)
yet I perceiue my former motiues of
consolation haue preuailed a little with
thee, which I will succinctlie conclude
with this finall comfort, that this might
minister no lesse solace in the end thē the
precedent comforts in the beginning.</P>
<P>I haue prepared this harbour for thee
(poore pilgrim,) and would haue thee
as one carefull of thy weale, to retire
thy selfe here, against the turbulent
stormes of all afflictions: that though
the pompe of this world seeme to per∣swade
thee to a kind of despaire in
thine owne estate: yet flying to this
harbour, the holes of the rocke (Christ
Iesus) thou maist finde eternall com∣fort:
<HI>intuere rupem et erige ratem.</HI> This
rocke shall defend thee from all aduerse
oppositions either of world the flesh or
the Diuell: hauing thy habitation so
firmely planted vpon those future ioies,
that the miseries of this world may
seeme small in comparison, in regard of
that exceeding measure of consolations
prepared for thee in that Sanctuary of
Eternitie: where no disturbance can
surprise thee, no pouerty afflict thee,
<PB N="40" REF="25"/>
no care depresse thee: <HI>Tranquillam se∣dem
tenes et in ea sola glorieris.</HI> Hence
maist thou conceiue perfect ioy: and
ruminate of those internall and etter∣nall
comforts which are promised thee
if thou beare vp thy selfe in thy aduersi∣ties:
the bosome of <HI>Abraham</HI> is open
vnto thee, and all patient men that de∣stitute
of mundan succour, retire to
the sacred bowels of Christs compassi∣ons:
no affliction so great which Time
will not allay: no discomfort so excee∣ding
which the exceeding comforts
of Christs passions cannot mitigate.
Time is a perfecter of all things, saith
the worldling: but if this time be not
employed in the exercise of Christs pas∣sions,
the distast of times continuance
affoords no lesse bitternesse, then the in∣crement
of afflictions. The tempests
are well calmed: thou maist sayle with∣out
an aduerse encounter of turbulent
affections. Thy Pilote is skilfull, for the
windes and seas obey him: he is merci∣full,
for hee neuer forsooke the poore
mariner nor distressed seafaring man,
till he be arriued at his port and expe∣cted
Harbour.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
<HEAD>THE
MIRROR OF
VAINE GLORIE.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Herein art thou proude
O Man? or whereto doest
thou exalt thy selfe? art
thou composed of more
then humane substance,
that thou shouldst glory in thy feature?
Thou admirest thine owne wisdome,
and reposest more confidence in thy
smooth wit and acute conceipt, then
Mammons statist. Why (foole) art thou
wise in thine own Imagination, &amp; yet
directest not thy waies to the square
of wisdome? Thou art wise because
thou canst deceiue: O spirituall follie!
how vnhappie was <HI>Achitophel</HI> in this
wisdome? how improuident &amp; impru∣dent
<PB N="42" REF="26"/>
was <HI>Haman</HI> to erect a Scaffold
for himselfe? Thou desirest some atten∣dants
(not so much to serue thee, as to
looke vpon thee) for thou esteemes not
so much a seruiceable fashion as thine
owne admiration. How foolish art
thou to thinke the world should terme
thee wise that art so phranticke? purge,
purge, thou hast a maladie within thee
will consume thee: Thou breakest the
Lepers Law: they were enioined to cry
I am vncleane, I am vncleane. But thou
that laborest of a more lothsome lepro∣sie,
will not confesse thy shame: not one
figge leafe to couer thy nakednesse. Sin
now goes with a protection, who dare
reprēd her? <HI>Nemo hercule, Nemo.</HI> None,
none. Sinnes grow habillements of Na∣ture
in which we most glory: that which
shames vs most, in that we shine most,
boasting of our vices, as if motiues of
respect. All sinnes passe with impunitie:
for who will throw the first stone? what
place from the highest to the lowest ex∣empted?
Sinne flies for Sanctuarie into
Sancturaies: what Time dispenst with,
wherein the Creature can say, I haue de∣sisted
from sinne, &amp; done that for which
<PB N="43" REF="26"/>
I was created? in what place doth not
vanity represent her selfe? Not onely
in the faire Structures (wherein we glo∣rie)
to leaue so beautifull mansions,
monuments of our care and prouidence
to our posteritie; but euen in our Beds
of earth, our Graues, and Sepulchers.
<HI>Shebna</HI> was carefull of this, and yet his
intentions were frustrate: for he built
his sepulcher in one country, and was
buried in another. Alasse, why glorie
we so much in the couer of corruption?
Tombes are not made so much for the
dead as for the liuing: and the life of the
dead consists in the memorie of the li∣uing.
All that was writ ouer that great
<HI>Pompey</HI> was this: <HI>Hic situs est magnus.</HI>
Alasse poore Greatnesse, when an am∣bicious
and incircumscribed spirit can
be confined within so straite a circum∣ference!
It was <HI>Innocontius</HI> question to
describe humane frailtie.</P>
<P>Dic mihi vas cinerum, quid prodest flos
facierum.</P>
<P>Thou hast beene present I know it,
sometime at the buriall of thy friend,
or neighbour, where thou sawest the
character or embleame, of all the sonns
<PB N="44" REF="27"/>
of Adam: and yet thou art returned
from his graue, this good commemo∣ration
of thy mortallity, (as from the
Centaures banket) more obdurate in
heart, remorceles of sinne, senceles of
shame, then before thou saw thy dead
friend interred, O conceaue remorce
and liue: let not the publicanes and
sinners condemne thee, let not pa∣gans
outstripp thee. Thou liuest in the
light of the Gospell: many preach∣ers
are sent thee, (take the opportunate
time,) now is the haruest, labor to bring
thy sheaues with thee. <HI>Qui arat, arat vt
metet, qui pugnat, pugnat vt vineat.</HI> So
sow, that that thou may reape plente∣ously;
so fight that thou may bee crow∣ned
after victorie atchieued. Cast but
thine eie (deare Christian) vpon all the
waies &amp; bypaths, which seem to lead vs
to mundane felicitie: thou shalt finde
nothing but intricate waies, vnfre∣quented
labyrinths, which menace ru∣ine
to the passenger. <HI>Aditus prospicitur,
reditum non patitur;</HI> easie is it for thee
to enter, but to come forth difficult.
The world is like <HI>Polyphemus</HI> caue: en∣tring
once into the pleasures of earths
<PB N="45" REF="27"/>
vanitie, thou art so enchained, so en∣snared
to the delights and inordinate
affections, which like merrie Sirens,
doe so solicit thee, as thou canst hard∣ly
exempt thy selfe from their serpen∣tine
embraces. Holy <HI>Athanasius</HI> saw in
his sleepe (for so the vision appeared)
the whole world encompassed about
with snares and nets: its true; what
profession but exceedingly tempted, if
not seduced? auarice, as sure an atten∣dant
vppon age, as sensuality vpon
youth. Church vsurie, Simoniacall pa∣trons,
making sale of the precious
things of Gods temple, and who re∣maines
there to whipp them out? Vsu∣rie
(as in it selfe a legall sinne, because
suffred), growes tyrannicall: shee cries
not with the false mother, neither thine
nor mine, but diuide it: but shee erects
a Monopolie for her selfe, and will
engrosse a grocerie of soules, to en∣rich
the pallace of her father <HI>Mammon▪</HI>
O poore decrepit sowle, thou that
art stepping into the wombe of thy
mother, and carriest deaths head a∣bout
thee, consider thy creation, ac∣knowledge
thy composition, weake by
<PB N="46" REF="28"/>
creation but weaker by times reuoluti∣on,
<HI>Seusim sine sensu seuescimus.</HI> O gather
spirituall riches, prouide thee a skripp
that shall neuer bee worne, but con∣tinue
euer. The rich man in the Gos∣pell
gathered much, possessed much,
enlarged his Granars, and promist to
himselfe securitie with a retired adue
from the world, now soule take thy
ease; but his Epiphonema was answe∣red
with a Threnodia; Thou foole this
night shall thy soule bee taken away.
Alas so soone? this was the first night
(it seemes) of his rest, aud must it be
his last too? yes: <HI>Esay</HI> answereth him,
There is no rest to the vngodly: hee
is euer in discontent, seeking to quench
his hydropticke thirst with getting,
but is neuer satisfied. They which
should bee Gods Amners to distri∣bute
to the necessity of the Saints,
are oppressors, beeing as sponges
which sucke vp the laborious gaines
of the poore. Let there not bee a beg∣ger
in <HI>Israell</HI> (saith God to <HI>Moses</HI>) but
these regraters, which exhaust and con∣sume
the meanes of the poore, make
many beggars in <HI>Israell.</HI> But the Lord
<PB N="47" REF="28"/>
shall come in thunder, and roote them
from the face of the earth, hee shall
raze doune their buildings▪ and make
their dwelling with Ostriches. For
the Lords delight is in the poore that
humbles himselfe beefore him: his
horne shall bee exalted with honour:
but for the mighty oppressors that
grinde the face of the poore, the Lord
will chastice them in his fury, and be
auenged of them in his mightie dis∣pleasure.
O if the rich man knew (being
Gods dispensour) how soone the sythe
of humane frailety will cut him short,
hee would not promise to himselfe
length of daies, but with all integrity
of heart, feruencie of spirit, and humi∣lity
of minde fall downe before the
Throne of Gods merie: <HI>Sicut Apes
flores quaesitant, ita Sancti misericordiam
Dei.</HI> The Saints of God and such as
are consecrate to him, will seeke the
mercie of God, and with teares of en∣tire
compassion turne to the Lord, that
it would please him to turne from their
sinnes. They will not protract the time,
nor take day with their sinnes, but
with hearty contrition, speedy conuer∣sion
<PB N="48" REF="29"/>
and firme resolution not to com∣mit
the like sinnes again, they purchase
their atonement with God, leauing off
sinne before sinne leaue them. For what
is it when the Organs and naturall fa∣culties
of the bodie through their debi∣litie
haue lost all power of sinning, then
to surcease from sinne? No, reserue the
heate of the day for the Lords vine∣yard,
let not him haue the afterlings.
The first fruits were in ancient time gi∣uen
to the Priests, and wilt thou detaine
thy first fruits from him which is the
head Priest? O dedicate thy labors vn∣to
him, and be conuerted euen in the
maturitie of thy time. Thou art now a∣ble
to cope with Antichrist: to mor∣row
it may be thou shalt be lesse able.
A valiant captaine (in the siege of any
Citty or fortresse) will apprehend euery
aduantage and occasion of attaining
his purpose: he will not intermit any
time, but with all alacritie prosecute
the charge he hath in hand, that his de∣portments
may purchase him glory:
<HI>Sub vexillo meret, &amp; moeret si non mereat.</HI>
Thou art in the same case: in a straite
siege, beleagred with impetuous and
<PB N="49" REF="29"/>
violent enemies. The world besiegeth
thee on euerie side, &amp; by those 5. Gates
or breaches, viz. thy fiue corporall sen∣ces,
eye, eare, tast, smell, and touch, he
woundeth thy soule as with most vene∣mous
Arrowes: so as death entreth in
at the verie window of thy soule. <HI>Is∣maell</HI>
plaies with thee, and deludes thee:
the flesh whom thou pamperedst rebels
against thee: thy verie housholds sinnes
begin to wrastle with thee: and <HI>Grauis
lucta Graue est periculum contra domesti∣cum
hostem pugnare,</HI> saith <HI>Barnard.</HI> Thou
must wrastle with sinne conspiring
within thee, with the flesh which enui∣rons
thee, and the voluptuous affecti∣ons
of worlds vanitie that seeke to
surprise thee. Show thy selfe resolute
in this encounter, fight a good fight,
and with the complete Armour of a
spirituall warriour raze downe the ty∣rannicall
kingdome of Antichrist. Thou
must passe many difficulties ere thou
canst obtain the victorie. Those <HI>Cyanea
saxa:</HI> those rockes of perill temptations
of euery kinde: but perseuerance will
make thy victorie most eminent. The
yong man must needes take leaue of his
<PB N="50" REF="30"/>
friends, before he can follow Christ.
But thou must abandon friends, estate,
possessions, and all encombrances, that
thou may be thought a worthy follow∣er
of Christ. <HI>Qui Christum sequi petit,
equum est vt omnia relinquat, quo Chri∣stum
arctius teneat.</HI> Riches were best
demonstrated by the Romane word <HI>Im∣pedimenta:</HI>
hinderances indeed for our
heauenly expedition: we should vse
them in necessarie respects, not to a∣dore
them: if the price of gold had not
beene knowne, <HI>Baals</HI> golden calfe had
not beene erected. It is a cause of much
false Adoration: and many I am per∣swaded
(yet timerous in perswasion)
worship the idoll in their chest, more
then their Messias in his Temple. O pro∣phanation
of Times! when an externall
appearance of tempting vanitie, can se∣duce
an Intellectuall soule from her
Creator, with the desire of a bare met∣tall
ordained for the vse of his crea∣ture.
We are wise and vnderstanding
in chymicke labours, and are profound∣lie
read in minerals: But that onely and
principall good, the select treasure of
the minde is as farre estranged from
<PB N="51" REF="30"/>
our reading, as <HI>Demas</HI> heart was from a∣ny
thing, saue what tasted of the world.
We can talke of eccentricke lines, bo∣dies,
motions, temperatures, &amp; affecti∣ons:
but which amongst vs seekes to
season the ill disposed temper of our
minde? O pittie and great pitty it is to
neglect so diuine a substance: let the
Philosophers idle axiome alone: the
body should take her temperature from
the soule, and not the soule from the
body. <HI>Corpus Ancilla est vt pareat, non
domina vt imperet.</HI> Confusion of Go∣uernors
spoile euerie well gouerned
state: and those kingdomes be most
happy where there be not the most but
the best Kings. Thou hast a monarchy
(and thats the best kinde of Gouerne∣ment)
within thy selfe: O dispose then
of thy affections like a Prince: be inue∣sted
with a roabe worthy an Emperor,
the pure stole of integrity, thy thoughts
must be eleuate, not depressed downe
to this earthly centre. It is reported
that the Emperour <HI>Augustus</HI> could see
as well by night as day; thy eyes should
be so; not obscured or darkned with
the night of error, but euer tralucent,
<PB N="52" REF="31"/>
that if there were windowes in thy
heart, the splendor of thy internall man
might show her owne dignity. But e∣specially
let me caution thee in this:
that thou be open handed, and bounti∣fully
hearted to thy neeedfull brother:
it will make thee see more cleerely into
the prouidence of God, and excite thee
to an acknowledgement of his mercies;
euer meditating of his bounty in be∣stowing,
and thy immerrited seruice in
deseruing: It will inflame in thee a per∣fect
and exact measure of charity, to
giue freely, because thou hast receiued
more amply. An affectionate charitie is
approued by God and man: making
our selues in distributiue iustice Christi∣ans,
and imitating the inimitable pat∣terne
of Christ, who sustained the weak,
supported the needy, relieued the hun∣gry,
being all to all, that he might show
his glory towards all: his humility may
asswage our pride, and caution vs to be
humble here, that wee may be exalted
elsewhere. His penurie may taxe vs of
excesse, that liue in Epicureal riot, con∣suming
our daies in security and care∣lesse
prophanation of God and his sa∣cred
<PB N="53" REF="31"/>
ministers; neither vsing reuerence
to them nor him: for in contemning
them, wee contemne him (as he the fa∣ther
of verity hath spoken.) O deere
christian! we haue too long dallied with
sinne, too long delaied the time of our
conuersion: Turne, turne from thy euill
waies: least thou be cut downe in his
fury: the vials of his wrath haue beene
long in diffusing, but so much longer
the stroke is delaied, so much it returnes
more violent. O let vs relinquish earths
vanitie, and plant our affections vpon
heauens beauty; why should we loue
such things as breede lothing: hauing
bitternesse in their tast, and producing
no fruits, but the distastfull weedes of
repentance? Who so is bewitched or
captiuated with the pie-coloured vani∣ties
of this world, deserues a pie colord
coate to describe the foole in his fol∣lies.
Learne to be wise in spirituall af∣faires,
that the commerce which thou
hast had with the factors of vanity, may
be now disualued, hauing reference to
the maine price of thy redemption
working out thy saluation with feare
and trembling. Thou seest the race
<PB N="54" REF="32"/>
thou must of necessity run, not the race
of lasciuious prodigals, whose exorbi∣tance
makes their house die in infamy,
nor the race of the Auaricious Miser,
that treasures vp vengeance for him∣selfe
and his posterity, making the issue
of his loines the heires of shame, nor the
race of adulterers that wast their estate
in the brothels of licentious delights:
but the christian race, making thy be∣ginning
a hopefull proeme of a succes∣siue
end: thy end a happy concluder of
so faire beginnings. Runne thus and
thou shalt obtaine, not a temporall re∣ward,
but the crowne of eternitie: that
God (who reclaimed thee from thy
sinne, may be glorified in thy members,
consecrated to holinesse and integrity▪
Meditate of this, contemplate this, ex∣ercise
the faculties of thy soule in these,
and the like spirituall meditations: so
shall the deceipts of Sathan be diuer∣ted,
the gracious operations of Gods
spirit renewed: and the promises of God
to thee performed in supernall <HI>Syon.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="55" REF="32"/>
<HEAD>A SERMON
of Saint Barnard vpon the
passion of the Lord.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">L</SEG>Et vs celebrate (deere
christians) with diuine ho∣nours,
Iesus of <HI>Nazareth,</HI>
by the Iewes innocently
condemned, by the Gen∣tiles
crucified. Let vs that are Christi∣ans
worshippe with all reuerence, em∣brace
with all feruentnesse, and imitate
with all faithfulnesse (as it is meet, com∣fortable
and glorious) the infirmities
of our Sauiour: for these sufferings be
those instruments, by which the omni∣potent
power and inscrutable wisdome
of God hath wrought wonderfully and
powerfully the restauration of the
whole world. For Christ our Lord hath
so wrought for vs, that he became lesse
<PB N="56" REF="33"/>
then Angels, to make vs equall vnto
Angels; And who will not humble him∣selfe
for Christs sake? Christ our Lord
was crucified for our sinnes, and hath
sweetened the bitternesse of the Crosse,
to such as loue his Crosse. He died, and
destroied death, that through him we
might liue: and who will not loue
Christ our Lord? who will thinke much
to suffer for Christ? Christ by the igno∣nimie
of his Crosse, passed to the glorie
of heauenly excellence, and all power
in heauen and in earth is giuen vnto
him (by God his father) for his reue∣rence:
All the Angels of God doe wor∣shippe
him, and in the Name of <HI>Iesus</HI>
let euery knee bow of things heauenly,
earthly, or whatsoeuer is vnder the
earth; wherein (O Christian) canst thou
glory, saue in the Name of our Lord
God crucified, and in the name of
Christ, which is aboue all names, in
which whosoeuer is blessed, shall be
blessed vpon earth? Glorie in the Name
of the Sonne your redeemer, and ascribe
honour to your Sauiour, who hath done
great things for vs, and magnifie his
name with me, saying: we worship thee
<PB N="57" REF="33"/>
O Christ thou king of <HI>Israell,</HI> and of all
Nations, King of Kings, Lord of the
whole earth, God of Sabboath, the most
sure strength of the omnipotent God.
We worshippe thee that art the preci∣ous
price of our redemption, the peace
offring, who (alone) by the inestimable
sweetenesse of thy perfumes, hast mo∣ued
thy father whose dwelling is on
high, to behold the things which are on
earth, appeasing his indignation con∣ceiued
against vs. We declare thy mer∣cies
O Christ, and we vtter the remem∣brance
of thy sweetenesse in aboun∣dance.
We offer vnto thee (O Christ)
the sacrifice of praise, for the multitude
of thy goodnesse, showen vnto vs, of a
depraued seede, wicked and rebellious
children. For when wee were thy ene∣mies
(O Lord) and death had entred
vpon all flesh, to which all the seede of
<HI>Adam</HI> became subiect, by the conditi∣on
of our originall sinne, thou remem∣bredst
thy mercie, and lookedst downe
from thy high habitation vpon this
vale of teares and miserie. Thou sawest
the affliction of thy people, and being
inwardly touched with the sweetenesse
<PB N="58" REF="34"/>
of charitie, thou conferredst the
thoughts of peace and redemption
vpon vs, and when thou was the
sonne of God, very God, coeternall and
consubstantiall with God the father, &amp;
God the holy Ghost, inhabiting an in∣accessible
light, and supporting all
things with the word of thy strength;
thou disdainedst not to bow downe
thy maiesty to this fraile prison of our
mortality, whereby thou mightest both
tast, swallow down our miserie, and ad∣uance
vs to thy glory. It had beene but
little to thy charity, to finish the worke
of our saluation, by deputing the con∣summation
thereof to some Cherubin
or Seraphin, or one of thy Angels: but
thou vouchsafedst thy self to come vnto
vs, being commanded by thy father,
whose exceeding charity we haue tried
in thee. Thou camest (I say) not by chan∣ging
thy place, but by exhibiting thy
presence vnto vs, by taking vpon thee
our flesh. Thou camest from the royall
throne of supreme glory, into the
wombe of a Virgin, humble and abiect
in her owne eyes, sealed with the religi∣ous
vow of virgins continence, in
<PB N="59" REF="34"/>
whose sacred wombe the ineffable
power alone of the holy spirit, made
thee to be conceiued, and to be borne
in the Nature of true humanity, so as
the occasion of thy birth did neither
impaire in thee the power of thy maie∣stie,
nor in thy mother the purenesse of
her virginitie. O amiable and admira∣ble
humility, that being God of infinite
glorie, became as a contemptible
worme of miserie! Thou being God
of all, became a seruant vnto all. It see∣med
too little in thy sight to be our
Lord and father, but thou vouchsafest
likewise to be our brother, and thou
Lord of the whole earth, standing in
neede of nothing, from the begin∣ning
of thy Natiuitie, refusedst not
to tast the inconueniences of pouer∣tie.
For as the Scripture saith, thou
hadst not when thou wast borne anie
place in an Inne, nor cradle, which
might receaue thee in thy tender in∣fancie:
but in the base crib of a filthy
stable. Thou which containest the
whole earth in thy selfe, art wrapped vp
in swathling clouts, and placed in a
desperable repose. Hence is it, that thy
<PB N="60" REF="35"/>
mother tooke thee from amongst the
brute beasts. Take comfort, take
comfort ye that liue in pouertie, be∣cause
God liues with you in your
pouertie, hee lies not in delicious
beds, nor is hee found in the waies of
such as liue in their delights. To
what end dost thou reioice, (O rich
man) being but clay, wallowing in thy
gorgeous and trim bed, since the King
of Kings chused rather to honour the
straw beds of the poore with his hum∣ble
repose? Why dost thou disdaine
hard straw, when a tender infant in
whose hand are all things, preferred
the hard litter of beasts before thy
silkes and fethers? But this thy tender
and weake infancie (O Christ) was
not secure from the sword of the per∣secutors:
for whilest thou yet suckt
hanging at thy mothers brest, an An∣gell
appeared vnto <HI>Ioseph</HI> in his sleepe,
saying: <HI>Arise▪ and take the child, and
flie into Aegipt, and abide there till I
shall tell thee; for it will come to passe
that Herod will seeke the child to kill it
&amp;c.</HI> Now from this time (O good Ie∣sus)
thou beginnest to suffer sharpe
<PB N="61" REF="35"/>
things: for thou sufferedst not only this
vexation in thine owne infancie, but)
the death of those little ones, many
thousands whereof by the cruelty of
<HI>Herod</HI> were put to death, being rest
from their mothers brests. Hauing past
thine infancie, thou gauest vnto vs an
example of professing the truth with
all humility: for thou satest not with
the counsell of vanitie, but in the midst
of Doctors, questioning, and hearing
them: although thou wast the Lord
of knowledge, and the wisedome of
God thy Father. But thou wast like∣wise
an example of obedience vnto vs,
when as thou being Gouernour of
the whole world subiected thy selfe
humblely vnto the will of thy parents.
When the grouth of a stronger age
came, so as thou wast to apply thy
selfe to more weightie affaires, thou
wentest forth to finish the saluation of
thy people: as a mighty Giant to run
the race of all our misery. And that
thou mightest (in humane resemblance)
frame thy selfe like vnto thy brethren,
thou the innocent lambe of God, (neuer
defiled with the lest staine of sinne)
<PB N="62" REF="36"/>
camest vnto thy seruant baptizing pe∣nitent
sinners, as if thou hadst beene
a sinner, desiring that thou mightest
bee baptized: but hee baptized not
thee in the water, but the water in
thee, sanctifying them, that they might
sanctifie vs, by thy sanctifying spirit
working in vs. From Baptisme by the
strength of thy spirit, thou wentest in∣to
the desert, giuing vs an example of
solitary life in thee. Thou sufferedst
patiently solitarines and fasting, for
the space of 40. daies, bitternesse of
hunger, temptations and illusions, to
the end thou mightest make all these
things more tollerable vnto vs. At last
thou camest to the lost sheepe of <HI>Isra∣ell,</HI>
shewing openly the lampe of thy
diuine word to illuminate all the world,
declaring thy kingdome to all such
as obeyed thy word, and followed thy
precepts; confirming with signes, and
shewing the power of thy diuinity to
all that were sicke, doing all things to
all men freely, which might conduce
to the saluation of sinners, to the end
thou mightst profit all. But the fooles
heart is darkened (O Lord) and he hath
<PB N="63" REF="36"/>
throwne thy commandements behind
him, neuer harkening vnto all those
wonderfull workes which thou hast
wrought amongst them: except a few
very noble and stout champions, which
thou hast elected out of the weake
and abiect things of the world, that
by them thou mightst wonderfully
discomfit the strong and mighty. Nei∣ther
haue they alone bin vnthankefull
vnto thee for thy benefits: but (O
Lord of Lords) they haue reproched
thee, and done vnto thee whatsoeuer
it liked them: for what said they when
thou didst those workes of God which
none else could doe? This man is not of
God: in the Prince of diuels he throwes
out diuels, he hath a diuell, he seduceth
the people, hee is a glutton and a bib∣ber
of wine, a friend of Publicanes
and sinners. Why weepest thou? why
sighest thou (O man) when thou art
iniuriously reproched? dost thou not
heare how many rebukes fell vpon
thy Lord and Sauiour for thy sake?
If they call the master of the household
Belzebub, how much more his house∣hold
seruants? But (O good Iesus)
<PB N="64" REF="37"/>
whilest they spake these and the like
blasphemies, stoning thee sometimes
with stones, thou sufferedst all things
patiently, and thou becamest as if thou
hadst not heard, hauing no rebukes in
thy mouth. Lastly they set thy iust and
vndefiled blood) betraied by thy disciple
a sonne of perdition) at the price of thir∣tie
pieces of filuer, that they might
take away thy life without a cause.
Albeit the trechery of that wicked be∣traier
was not hid from thee, when in
the supper where thou washedst thy
Disciples feete, kneeling downe on thy
knees before him, thou vouchsafedst
to handle, wash▪ and wipe his cursed
feete (swift to sheede blood) with thy
most holy hands.</P>
<P>Wherefore then (O thou dust &amp; ashes)
art thou yet so proud? doth pride yet lift
thee vp? doth impatience yet vox thee▪
Behold thy Iesus, the creator of all
things, the fearefull Iudge of the quick
and the dead, the very parerne of hu∣mility
and mercie, kneeling before
the feete of a man, and that man a
traitour. Learne, because hee is meeke
and humble in heart, and bee ashamed
<PB N="65" REF="37"/>
of thy pride, and blush at thy patience.
This was also (O Lord) an especiall
token of thy mildnesse, when thou
wouldest not discouer that disloyall
wretch in the middest of his brethren,
nor publiquely confound him; onely
bidding him doe that hee would doe
quickely. In all these his malice
ceased not towards thee, but going
forth hee perfects his mischeeuous pur∣pose.</P>
<P>O <HI>Lucifer,</HI> how fellest thou from
heauen, that shined before so brightly
in heauen, thou that once appearedst
glorious in the delicious borders of
Paradise, fellow Cittizen with the An∣gels
in Heauen, and a guest at the ta∣ble
of the diuine word: how art
thou now reckoned among the chil∣dren
of darkenesse? thou that wast
nourished with spices, wherefore doest
thou embrace filthines? Now is thy
familie (O Christ) purified, when hee
went into the world, leauing the An∣gelicall
society which in heauen remai∣ned.
Now is that happy companie
made drunke with the plentifull in∣undation
of thy diuine oracles, hauing
<PB N="66" REF="38"/>
casten him out whom thou knewest
to bee vnworthy of the infusion of so
pure a liquor. When thou hadst gi∣uen
a commandement of charity and
wholsome patience, and hadst dispo∣sed
of thy Fathers Kingdome vnto
thy brethren: thou wentest aside with
them, towards the place knowne to
thy Betrayer: knowing all things that
would come vpon thee. There thou
wast not ashamed to confesse in the
hearing of thy Apostles, the sadnes
of thy soule by the imminencie of thy
passion which voluntarily thou assu∣medst,
as also other things which
then thou sufferedst, saying: Now is
my soule heauie euen vnto death. Al∣so
kneeling vpon the ground thou fel∣lest
flat vpon thy face, praying in thine
agony, and saying: O Father (if it be
possible) let this cuppe passe from me.
And that bloody sweat did most eui∣dently
expresse the sorrowes of thy hart,
which al the time of thy prayer trickled
downe droppe by droppe vppon the
ground. O my Lord Iesus, whence
comes this thy sorrowfull supplication?
didst thou not voluntarily offer thy
<PB N="67" REF="38"/>
selfe a sacrifice vnto thy father? euen so
Lord. But we suppose that thou tooke
this vpon thee, for the comfort of thy
weake and disconsolate members, least
peraduenture some should despaire if at
any time the fraile flesh seeme to mur∣mure,
when the spirit is ready to repell
any tentation. Surely thou didst it to
this end, that we might haue continuall
motiues of loue &amp; thankfulnes towards
thee, hauing expressed the naturall infir∣mity
of our flesh by these tokens in thee.
By which we are taught, that thou hast
truely borne our infirmities, &amp; hast pas∣sed
the pricking thornes of thy passions
not without a sensible feeling of them.
For that voice seemed not to be the
voice of the spirit but of the flesh, in
that thou addest, the spirit is truely rea∣dy,
but the flesh is weake. That the spi∣rit
was ready to thy passion thou eui∣dently
demonstrated, when thou ran of
thine owne accord to meet thy betraier
&amp; such men as were giuen to shed blood
attending him, seeking to take away
thy life with lanternes and Torches and
weapons vpon the Night: and least they
should receiue any notice by the Cap∣taine
<PB N="68" REF="39"/>
of this impiety, thou manifested
thy selfe: for thou turnedst not away
from that cruell Beast comming to kisse
thy most holy mouth, but affably gaue
thy mouth (wherein was neuer deceipt
found) vnto his mouth which aboun∣ded
with all malice. <HI>O Innocent lambe
of God,</HI> what hast thou to doe with that
wolfe? what concord betwixt thee and
Belial? but this was O Lord thy great
mercy, to exhibit all such things as
might any way mollifie the pertinacie
of a depraued heart: for (as one not al
to∣gether vnmindfull of ancient friend∣shippe)
thou admonished him saying;
my friend to what end camest thou?
and willing (as it seemes) to wound the
heart of this impious Traitour, with the
horror of his sinne, thou said: <HI>Iudas</HI> do∣est
thou betray the sonne of man with a
kisse? and behold the Philistins are vpon
thee <HI>Sampson.</HI> Neither didst thou driue
them from thee intending to smite them
at the houre of thy apprehension, with
thy right hand, no not in defence of thy
selfe, that the foolish presumption of
man may know that they can doe no∣thing
against thee, but so much onely
<PB N="69" REF="39"/>
as is permitted by thee. But who can
heare without weeping how they laid
their murdering hands vpon thee, tying
thy innocent hands with cords, sweet
Iesus, who like a most meek lambe spea∣king
nothing, was carried after the man∣ner
of a theefe, contumeliously to the
slaughter. Neither ceasedst thou then
(O Christ) to shew thy mercy vpon thy
Enemies, &amp; to diffuse the honiecombe
of thy sweetnesse vpon them, reprouing
the zeale of thy defendor, and with∣holding
him from hurting such as ha∣led
thee. Their furie was cursed because
wilfull, being neither moued by the
maiesty of thy miracles, nor the great∣nes
of thy benefits. Thou wast brought
before a counsell of wicked head-priests
consulting against thee; and con∣fessing
the truth (as was seemelie) thou
wast adiudged to death for thy blasphe∣mie.
O louing Lord, how many vnwor∣thy
things hast thou suffered of thine
owne Nation? men of polluted lips be∣slubbring
with their spittle▪ thy amiable
countenance, on which the Angels
haue desired to looke, replenishing the
whole Courts of heauen with ioy; and
<PB N="70" REF="40"/>
vnto which all the rich men in the
world shall make intercession: beating
it with their sacrilegious hands, and
blindfolding thee in derision: and be∣ing
Lord of all creatures buffetted thee
as a seruant most contemptuous of all
others. But let vs now come to their
deliuering vp of thy soule, to be swal∣lowed
vp by vncircumcised flesh.
They lead thee bound before <HI>Pilate,</HI> re∣quiring
that thou maist be crucified
which knewest no sinne, &amp; that a mur∣derer
might bee let loose vnto them,
lesse esteeming of a lambe then a
wolfe; of gold, then clay. O vnworthy
and vnhappy merchandise! neither was
that wicked <HI>Pilate</HI> ignorant, how all
these things were done through enuie
against thee; yet for all that, he procee∣ded
rashly in iudgement against thee,
filling thy soule with much bitternesse
without a cause; He suffered thee to be
mocked, commanding thee to stand in
the sight of thy mockers; nor spared he
to teare thy pure virgin-skinne with
most sharpe scourgings, cruelly infli∣cting
stripes vpon stripes, and wounds
vpon wounds. O thou deere child of
<PB N="71" REF="40"/>
God, what hast thou committed, that
should deserue so great bitternesse, so
great reproch? Surely nothing. It is I,
it is I, wicked man that I am, that was
the cause of thy death. I (O Lord) haue
eaten the sower grape, and thy teeth are
on edge, paying for that which thou
neuer tooke. And yet the impiety of
the trecherous Iewes is not satisfied
with all these indignities done against
thee: but thou art now at last deliuered
ouer into the hands of vncircumcised
souldiers to be put to a most shamefull
death. It seemed but a little matter for
those sacrilegious miscreants to cruci∣fie
thee, but they must also vex thy soule
with reproches. For what saith the
Scripture of them. <HI>Then all the people
gathered together, and taking his owne
garments from him, they put vpon him a
purple coate, and they cloathed him with a
skarlet robe, and winding a crowne of
thornes they put it vpon his head, and a
reede in his right hand, and bowing vnto
him they mocked him saying, Haile, King
of the Iewes: and they buffetted him and
spit vpon him, and taking the reede in their
hands they smote him on the Head, and af∣ter
<PB N="72" REF="41"/>
they had mocked him, they put his
owne garments vpon him, to crucifie him
bearing his owne crosse; and they led him
to Golgotha, giuing him wine to drinke
mixed with mirrhe and gall: and when he
had tasted of it, he would not drinke: then
they crucified him, and two theeues with
him, the one of the right hand, and the o∣ther
of the left, and Iesus in the middest.
And Iesus said: Father forgiue them, for
they know not what they doe.</HI> Afterwards
Iesus knowing that all things might be
done, that the Scripture might be fulfil∣led,
said, <HI>I thirst: and one amongst them
running tooke a spunge and filled it with
vinegar, and put it vpon a reede and gaue
him it to drinke: assoone as he had receiued
the vinegar he said, It is finished: and cry∣ing
with a loud voice he said, Father into
thy hands I commend my spirit, and bow∣ing
downe his head he gaue vp the ghost.
Then one of the Souldiers opened his side
with a speare: and presently their issued out
water and blood for the redemption of
man.</HI> Awake O my soule, shake of the
dust of sinne, and fixe thy contem∣plation
vpon this memorable pat∣terne
of Humanitie, whom thou seest
<PB N="73" REF="41"/>
presented vnto thee in this glasse of
Gods word. Behold O my soule, who it
is that cometh in vnto thee, hauing the
image of a King, and yet reproched by
his most despicable seruants▪ treading
vpon Crownes, and yet his Crowne is
a vexation vnto him, wounding his
beautifull head with a thousand pricks:
hee is clothed with roiall purple, but in
it hee is rather despised then honoured:
hee caries a Scepter in his hand, but
with it his reuerend head is wounded:
they worshippe him with bended
knees, and call him King, but present∣ly
they besmere his amiable face with
spitting, dishonouring his cheekes
and venerable aspect with their fists.
See O my soule, how this man is afflic∣ted
and contemned of all sides. Hee
bowes himselfe vnder the burthen of
his Crosse, &amp; bearing that ignominie
which was proper vnto thee, where be∣ing
brought vnto the place of execu∣tion,
his thirst is quenched with mirrhe
and vineger vpon the Crosse, saying:
<HI>Father pardon &amp;c.</HI> What kinde of man is
this, who in all his sufferings doth not
once open his mouth, or vtter one word
<PB N="74" REF="42"/>
of complaint, or excuse, or of threat, or
of curse against those reuiling doggs:
but concludes with such mild wordes
of blessing, as haue not bin heard before.
O my soule, when hast thou seene any
one more mercifull? what can be more
curteous then this man? Behold him
with more attention, how worthy he is
of admiration, and most tender compas∣sion.
Looke at him naked, and torne
with whips, betwixt two theeues igno∣miniously
nailed vpon the Crosse,
quenching his thirst with vinegar, and
after his death wounded in the side with
a speare, sending out plentifull riuers of
blood from those woundes in his
handes, &amp; feete, and side. O my eies a∣bound
with teares, and O my soule bee
thou dissolued with the fire of compas∣sion,
in condoling so mercifull a man,
whom thou seest amidst so great biter∣nesse
to bee afflicted with sorrowes.
And now (O my soule) thou hast seene
his infirmicies, and thou dost pitty him:
now thou hast looked vpon his maiesty,
and thou dost admire him: for what
saith the Scripture; <HI>From the sixth hower
vnto the ninth hower there was darkenesse
<PB N="75" REF="42"/>
vpon the whole earth: and the Sunne was
darkened, and the vaile of the Temple rent
asunder from the toppe euen to the bot∣tom,
and there was an Earth-quake, and
the rockes cloue, and the graues opened,
and many bodies of the Saints which were
dead arose.</HI> Who is this, with whom
both Heauen and Earth doe suffer, and
whose death doth raise men from death?
Know O my soule, know that this is
the Lord God, Iesus Christ thy Sauiour,
the onely begotten sonne of God, very
God, &amp; very man: who of all men vnder
the Sunne, was onely found to be with∣out
sinne, and behold how hee is ac∣compted
amongst the wicked, and e∣steemed
as one of the Lepars, or as an
abortiue birth throwne from his mo∣thers
wombe. So is hee throwne from
the wombe of his Mother, the vnhappy
Synagogue. Hee that was the fairest a∣mongst
the children of men, how de∣formed
is hee made? hee was woun∣ded
for our iniquities, and broken for
our sinnes: he was made a burnt Sa∣crifice
of sweete incense vnto thee O
Father of eternall glorie, to pacifie thy
wrath conceaued against vs, and to
<PB N="76" REF="43"/>
place vs in the celestiall mansions of
glorie. Behold (O holy Father) from
thy Sanctuarie, and from thy high ha∣bitation,
behold this our holy sacrifice,
which our Head-priest offereth vnto
thee, thy holy Sonne, and our Lord Ie∣sus
offering himselfe vp for our sinnes:
and mercifully doe away the multitude
of our transgressions. Behold the voice
of the blood of our Iesus crieth vnto
thee from the Crosse. For what (O Lord)
what is it that hangeth thereon? hee
hangeth euen now, because things past
are as things present before thee. Take
knowledge (O Father) vnto the coat of
thy true sonne Ioseph: Behold a sa∣uage
beast hath deuoured him, and
trampled vppon his garment in his fu∣rie,
staining his bewtie with the effusion
of his blood: behold he hath made pit∣tifull
rents in it This O Lord is the gar∣ment
which thy inocent son left in the
hands of that Aegiptian harlot, think∣ing
it better to lose his coate, then his
honour, and chusing rather to be spoi∣led
of the garment of his flesh, and to
descend into the prison of death, then
for the glorie of the world to har∣ken
<PB N="77" REF="43"/>
vnto the voice of the Adultresse: to
that voice I say, where it was said vnto
him: All this will I giue thee if thou wilt
fall downe before me and worship me,
which was as if he shold haue slept with
the Adultresse. And now, O my Lord, we
know that this thy sonne liueth, and is
Gouernour ouer all <HI>Aegypt,</HI> and in eue∣rie
place of thy dominion: for hee is
aduanced from the prison of death and
of Hell, to thy Empire, and attaining
a Crowne of immortallity, hath chan∣ged
the garment of his flesh, to reflou∣rish
within the immortality of the spi∣rit,
where thou hast receiued him with
much honour. For hee hath subiected
the empire of <HI>Pharoh</HI> vnto him, and
hath triumphantly ascended Heauen by
his owne proper maiesty: &amp; behold, he
is crowned with glorie and honour,
when hee sitteth at the right hand of thy
maiesty, mediating for vs; for hee is
our flesh, and our brother. Behold (O
Lord) the face of thy Christ, who be∣came
obedient vnto thee euen vnto
death: nor let the scars of his woundes
euer depart from thy sight, that thou
maiest remember the satisfaction thou
<PB N="78" REF="44"/>
hast receiued for our sinnes. I would O
Lord thou wouldst but weigh our sins
in a balance, by which we haue deser∣ued
thy wrath, and the calamity which
thy sonne suffred to appease thy wrath.
Surely more forcible and more worthy
would the cause appeare to show thy
mercie vpon vs, then by reason of our
sinnes to powre downe the viols of thy
Ire vpon vs. Let euery tongue (O fa∣ther)
giue thankes vnto thee for the ex∣ceeding
aboundance of thy loue, in not
sparing thy onely begotten Sonne: but
giuing him ouer vnto death for vs; that
we might haue him as a faithfull Aduo∣cate
before thee in Heauen for vs. And
thou O Lord Iesus, most mighty &amp; most
zealous of mans saluation, what thanks
shall I giue vnto thee, that I may giue
thankes worthie, being but dust and the
workemanship of thy hands? for what
couldest thou doe for my saluation, and
hast not done it? from the sole of thy
foot to the crowne of thy head, thou
hast plunged thy selfe wholly into the
waters of thy passion, that thou migh∣test
draw me wholly from them: and
these passions haue entred euen vnto
<PB N="79" REF="44"/>
thy soule. For thou subiectedst thy soule
to death and desolation, to preserue my
soule from death and perdition: and
behold thou hast bound me in a double
bond vnto thee. First in that thou hast
giuen thy life for mee; and secondlie
because my soule was giuen by thee,
twice vnto me, once in my creation,
and once in my recreation; wherefore
I haue nothing that is fitter to giue thee
then my soule, which I had of thee, for
if I should in recompence of thy mercy
giue vnto thee the Heauen, the earth,
and all the excellency thereof, yet sure∣ly
could not I attaine to the measure of
that I owe thee: sith that which I owe,
and that which is possible for mee to
giue is thy gift, without which I haue
nothing to giue. Thou art to be loued
(O my Lord) with all my heart, with
all my soule; with all my strength: and
thy imitable footsteps are to be follow∣ed
by me, because thou vouchsafedst to
die for me: and how can this be done in
me, but by thee? let my soule cleaue
vnto thee, because all my power depen∣deth
on thee. And now O Lord my
redeemer, I worship thee as the true
<PB N="80" REF="45"/>
God: I put my trust in thee, I hope in
thee, and with my vtmost desires doe I
sigh after thee: helpe my many imperfe∣ctions.
I incline my selfe wholly vnto
the glorious signals of thy passion,
wherein thou hast perfected my salua∣tion.
In thy name O Christ, doe I reue∣rence
the royall Banner of thy victori∣ous
Crosse. O Christ with all humility
doe I adore and glorifie the remem∣brance
of thy thornie crowne, thy red-skarlet
nailes besmeared with blood,
thy lance drenched in thy sacred side,
thy wounds, thy blood, thy death, thy
buriall, thy glorious and victorious re∣surrection
and glorification. For the
breath of life breatheth to mee in all
these: by these liuely and redolent o∣dors
raise my spirit O Lord, from the
death of sinne: By the power of these
preserue me from the subtilties of Sa∣than,
that the yoke of thy commande∣ments
may be vnto me easie, and the
burden of thy Crosse (which thou com∣mandest
me to beare after thee) may be
light: for what is my strength, that (ac∣cording
to thy commandement) I
might be able with an inuincible spirit
<PB N="81" REF="45"/>
to sustaine so manifold afflictions in the
world. Are my feete like Hindes feete,
that like a swift courser I may be able to
runne ouer the thornes and difficulties
of thy passions? but heare my voice, and
lay thy corsse softly vpon thy feruant,
that crosse, which is the wood of life to
them that lay hold vpon it: my hope is,
I shall runne swiftlie, and shall carrie as
constantlie the crosse which is giuen me
of my enemies, to follow thee. Lay (I
say) that most diuine crosse vpon my
shoulders, the breadth whereof is chari∣tie,
the length eternitie, the height om∣nipotencie,
and the depth inscrutable
wisdome, replenished with maiestie.
Naile my feete and my hands vnto it,
and conforme thy seruant, O Lord,
whollie vnto thy passion. Grant vnto
me O Lord, that I may abstaine from all
the workes of the flesh, which thou ha∣test,
and doe those workes of righte∣ousnesse
which thou louest, and in both
to seeke thy glorie. I suppose it verie
expedient that my left hand bee nailed
vnto the crosse with the nayle of tem∣perance,
my right hand with the naile
of vprightnesse. Grant that my soule
<PB N="82" REF="46"/>
may continually meditate vpon thy
law, fixing all her cogitations vpon
thee: and fasten thou my right foote to
the same wood of life, with the naile of
wisdome. Grant that the seeming fe∣licity
of this transitory life may not en∣feeble
the operation of my spirit with a
sinister sensualitie, nor that it be trou∣bled
with this present liues infelicity,
but that both my right hand and left
may be fixed vnto the crosse with the
naile of fortitude; and that some appea∣rance
of the thornes which were plat∣ted
vpon thy head, may be resembled
in me, giue vnto my heart I beseech thee
the wholsome compunction of repen∣tance,
&amp; compassion of anothers mise∣rie,
&amp; the pricke of feruent zeale which
may be founde vpright before thee and
to turne vnto thee in my affliction,
whilest my head is crowned with this
threefold wreath of thornes. I desire
thee also to reach a spunge vnto my
mouth by a reede, and to minister the
bitternesse of gall vnto my tast. I desire
also that by thy Scriptures thou woul∣dest
illuminate my reason, that I may
tast and see how this flourishing world
<PB N="83" REF="46"/>
is as an empty spunge, and all the con∣cupiscenses
there of more bitter then
vinegar. So (my father) may that Babi∣lonian
Cuppe diffused vpon the whole
earth seeme bitter vnto me: not able
with her fruitlesse flourish to seduce
me nor with her false sweetenesse to in∣ebriate
me, as shee doth those who call
darknesse light, and light darkenesse,
that which is bitter sweete, and what is
sweete bitter. Thy wine mixed with
mirrh and gall is suspicious vnto me:
forasmuch as thou wouldest not drinke
of it, because it imploied the bitternesse
of enuie and impiety of such as crucifi∣ed
thee. Fashion thy seruant, O Lord,
after thy liuely death, so working in me
that I may die in the flesh, but liue in
the righteousnesse of the spirit But
that I may reioice in the carrying of
the whole image of Christ crucified,
expresse in me a similitude of that which▪
the insatiate malice of the wicked
Iewes exercised against thee after thy
death: let thy quicke and effectuall
word more piercing then the sharpest
lance, reaching euen vnto the diuision
of my soule wound my heart: and pro∣duce
<PB N="84" REF="47"/>
out of it as from my right side
in stead of blood and water, a loue (O
Lord) vnto thee and to thy brethren: fi∣nally
wrappe my spirit in the pure syn∣don
of my originall stole of inno∣cencie,
that I may rest there, going out
and going in into the place of thy ad∣mirable
Tabernacle, hiding me till thy
furie be ouerpast: but in the third day
after the day of my labour, the day of
punishment, early in the first sabbath
raise me (thy vnworthy seruant) and
place mee perpetually among thy chil∣dren,
that in my flesh I may see thy glo∣rie
and be satisfied with the light of thy
countenance. O my Sauiour and my
God, let the time come, let it come I
beseech thee, that what I now beleeue,
I may behold with reuealed eyes; what
I now hope for, I may at last obtaine;
that what I now desire vehemently.
I may embrace really, may kisse lo∣uingly,
being plunged in the bot∣tomlesse
sea of mercie, O my Saui∣our
and my God. But blesse thou my
Sauiour O my soule, and magnifie his
name. O how good &amp; sweet art thou O
Lord Iesus vnto the soule that seeketh
<PB N="85" REF="47"/>
thee. O Iesus the redeemer of the lost,
the sauiour of the redeemed, the hope
of the banished, the strength of the
wearied, refreshing to the distressed, &amp;
comfort to the desolate, a sweete repose
and a comfortable to the sorrowfull
soule, running O Lord speedily after
thee, till shee oreget thee the crowne of
triumph, the chiefest marchandise,
and the ioy of all the heauenly Citi∣zens;
an euer-flowing fountaine of all
spirituall graces, the onely child of
God, and the great God: Let all
things which are in Heauen aboue or
in earth below praise thee. Great art
thou, and great is thy name O thou im∣mortall
glorie of the high God, and the
pure maiestie of the light eternall, O life
that quicknest all things; O light that
enlightenest all things, O light that il∣luminatest
euerie light, and conseruest
by thy eternall splendor: Thousands
and ten thousands of lights haue shi∣ned
before the Throne of thy maiestie
from the beginning. O eternall, sub∣stantiall
and inaccessible, cleere and de∣lectable
streame of that fountaine, hid
from the eies of all mortall men, whose
<PB N="86" REF="48"/>
beginning is without beginning,
whose bottome is without bottome,
whose periodde is without period,
whose circuit is incircumscrutable,
whose puritie is imperturbable. The
heart of the Almightie hath sent
thee (O my soule) out of his im∣penetrable
Abysse. O life, from thee
haue wee in all fullnesse receiued
life, from thy light haue wee re∣ceiued
light: thou that art eter∣nall,
hast made vs eternall, thou
that art boundlesse, hast made vs
boundlesse, making vs in all things
equall to thy selfe. For thou that
art the most plentifull fountaine of
euery perfect gift, hast vouchsafed
to conuay the precious Riuer of
thy seauen fould graces into our
hearts, to enrich vs with thy se∣cret
treasures, and with the sweete∣nesse
thereof to allay the saltnesse
of this sea, (that is) of our infir∣mities.
O thou Spring of the oile
of gladnesse, thou riuer of pure
wine, thou torrent of entire zeale,
the holie Spirit our comforter, bee∣ing
sent vnto the world by the
<PB N="87" REF="48"/>
Father and thee, to both he is equall
in dignity of essence, filleth all things,
contayneth al things, being spirit of the
spirit of thy Father, one of both,
as the indiuiduall communion vniting
both: a soulder vniting, a coniunction
indissoluing, and that peace which pas∣seth
all vnderstanding. This is the well
of thy comforts, O Lord, by which
thou daily supportest, and with pleasant
obiects most abundantly refreshest that
delicate and glorious City <HI>Hierusalem</HI>
is aboue: where those glorious and
flamie Organs doe incessantly sing
Hymnes in the voice of exultation and
feasting, with the desired tunes where∣of
the hungry iawes of thy people in
the daies of this their pilgrimation
craue dayly to bee refreshed. Suffer
(O Father) the little dogges to feede on
the crums which fall from their masters
table. Send out your dewe O Heauens
from aboue, and let the cloudes raine
vpon the righteous, him O Lord whom
thou hast made zelous of thy lawes.
Purge we beseech thee O Lord with the
sallatorie of thy word, the religious first
fruits of thy people, being a testimonie
<PB N="88" REF="49"/>
of our solemne celebration of this
time: renew, illuminate, inflame, in∣spire,
confirme, and vnite the hearts of
all beleeuers vnto thee, that they may
bee one, tast one, and with all vnanimi∣tie
require, apprehend, see, and glorifie
thee our only God in <HI>Sion.</HI> Let glorie,
thankes, honour, and power be at∣tributed
to the indiuiduall Tri∣nity
for euermore.</P>
<CLOSER>Amen.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 LANG="lat" TYPE="part">
<PB N="89" REF="49"/>
<HEAD>Quaedam sententiae, eaeque vere Au∣reolae,
ad humanae mentis inti∣mam
deuotionem inflam∣mandam,
ex∣cerptae.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Qui de se humiliter sentit, haec legat.</HEAD>
<P>CHristus qui pro nobis passionem sustu∣lit,
in fructus passionis nos promouebit:
vt sicut spinarum coronâ tempora eius fi∣gebantur,
gaudiorum mercede mentes no∣strae
illustrentur. Hic viximus in dolore, illic
afficiemur Honore: Honore dei, qui mun∣dano
Honori maxime aduersatur, ille enim
a christianis (qui sub vexillo suo merue∣runt)
possidetur, Hic autem ab Ethnicis
(qui eorum famam auxerunt) petitur. O
quam incundum est in domo tua (domine)
habitare? vbi nullo metu, nulla cupiditate,
nullo motu distrahimur! videntes vero
faciem tuam meridiana luce multo clari∣orem
laeitia vultus tuisatiamur. Hic di∣lectus
est meus, quem quaerit mens mea:
quaeret nec desistet donec cum quaerendo in∣ueniet.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="90" REF="50"/>
<HEAD>A MOST DE∣VOVT
MEDITATION
of Saint Barnard entreating
of the miserie of man, and ex∣amination
of the last
Iudgement.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Ouching the outward
man, I descend from those
parents, who (ere I was
borne) made me forlorne.
Sinners beget sinners in
their sinne, nourishing them from sinne
vnto sinne: miserable man hath brought
his miserable issue to light: from my
parents I haue nothing but miserie, and
sinne, and this corruptible body which
I carrie about with me. And to them
I hasten who are departed hence by the
death of their Bodies: whose Sepul∣chers
<PB N="91" REF="50"/>
when I behold, I finde nothing
in them but dust and wormes, filthines,
and horror; what I am, haue they been:
and what they are, I shall be. What am
I (miserable man?) engendred of liquid
humour, at the time of my conception
I was conceiued of humane seed: which
seede afterwards growing thicke by
encreasing little by little, became flesh:
whence weeping and shriking, I was
exposed to the exile of this world: and
behold now I die, being full of iniqui∣ties
and abhominations. Euen now
shall I bee presented before a fearefull
Iudge, that will take an exact accompt
of all my workes. Woe is me wretch
that I am; when that day shall come,
and those bookes shall be opened
wherein all my actions and cogitations
shal be reiected in the presence of God;
O then shall I stand fearefull before the
Lord in iudgement, hanging downe my
head and confessing my shame, remem∣bring
the offences I haue committed,
and the sinceritie of a pure conscience
which I haue defiled: and when it shall
be said of me, behold the man and his
workes: then shall I set before mine
<PB N="92" REF="51"/>
eyes all my sinnes, and transgressions:
for it will come to passe (by a certaine
diuine instinct) that all our workes both
good and euill, shall come vnto our re∣membrance,
and by the piercing sight
of the minde shall be apprehended by
a wonderfull quickenesse: to the end
knowledge might accuse or excuse
conscience, and so all vniuersally and
euery one distinctly might together be
iudged, each man shall giue accompt,
what he hath done of all, to all, how en∣ded,
how begunne: for what we are
now ashamed to confesse priuately, shal
be then manifested publikely: and what
we now seeke to shadow by dissem∣bling,
shall be discussed by the fire of
reuenge euer burning. Swift flaming
fire shall scorch with boundlesse rage:
and by how much longer God hath ex∣pected
our amendment, by so much
more seuerely will he punish vs, because
we were negligent. Why therefore doe
we so greatly desire this life, wherein
the longer we liue, the more we offend:
for by how much our life is longer, by
so much bee our offences more. For
daily are euils encreased, but goodnes
diminished: daily is man changed, by
<PB N="93" REF="51"/>
prosperitie and aduersitie, yet knoweth
not he when he shall die: for as a glitte∣ring
starre coasting swiftly in heauen,
suddenly vanisheth: or as a sparke of
fire is quickely extinguished, and turnes
to ashes: so soone the dissolutiō of mans
life: for whilest man soiorneth willingly
and ioifully in this world, &amp; promiseth
himselfe to liue long, disposing many of
his affairs for succeeding times, sudden∣ly
is he surprised by death; &amp; vnawares
is his soule taken frō his body: yet with
great feare and vnmeasurable griefe is
his soule separated frō his body. For the
Angels come to take it, and bring it be∣fore
the Tribunall seat of that fearefull
Iudge: where remembring his euill
works, (nay his most impious workes)
which he hath committed night or day,
he trembleth, seeking to flie from them,
and to take truce with them, saying:
Giue me one houres respite. Then his
workes (as if speaking together) shall
answer him and say: Thou madest vs, we
are thy workes, we will not leaue thee,
but abide euer with thee, and attend on
thee to thy iudgement: his vices also
with diuers and manifold crimina∣cions
<PB N="94" REF="52"/>
shall accuse him, and shall finde
many false testimonies against him, al∣beit
one were sufficient to condemne
him. Nay, the diuels with a terrible
countenance, a dreadfull aspect, shall
terrifie his soule, persecuting her with
implacable furie, seazing on her so ter∣riblie,
and so horriblie, as they seeme
willing to detaine and take possession
of her, if there were none to deliuer
her. Then the soule finding her eyes
shut, her mouth &amp; all other sences cor∣poral
by which she vsed to be delighted,
in these outward things stopped, shall
returne to her, selfe; where seeing her
selfe desolate &amp; naked, shee shall be ex∣ceedingly
amazed languishing through
despaire in her self, &amp; falling below her
selfe. And because shee relinquished the
loue of God, for the loue of this world,
and the satisfying the pleasures of the
flesh, shal be miserably forsakē of God,
in that hower of necessitie, and shall be
deliuered ouer to the diuels to bee tor∣mented
in hell. So shall the sinfull soule
in the day which shee knoweth not,
and in the hower of which shee is igno∣ant,
bee taken away by death, separa∣ted
<PB N="95" REF="52"/>
from her body, whence shee goeth
on (full of miserie, anguish, and feare)
where hauing no excuse which shee can
iustly shew for her sinne: shee pineth,
languisheth, and growes afraid to ap∣peare
before God; shee is surprised
with great horror, and tossed with the
sundry billowes of discomforting pas∣sions:
the dissolution of the flesh enfor∣cing
her, and all meanes of assistant
comforts leauing her, shee considers
her end appproching, and after a little
reuoluing, shee findes that in this per∣petuall
state to which shee hastens, there
is no changing, shee plainely considers
with what seuerity the eternall Iudge
will come, and before the seuerity of
such iustice what reasons can shee pro∣duce
to quallifie his iustice? for if all
the workes (which shee may consider
in her selfe) either committed or omit∣ted
had bin by her auoided: yet shee
is in feare, there will such workes come
before the terrible Iudge which she ne∣uer
apprehended: her feare encreaseth
when shee conceaueth how shee could
in no wise passe the waies of this life
without sinne: nor that parte of her
<PB N="96" REF="53"/>
life which seemed most praise worthie
could be exempted of guilt, without
recourse had to Gods mercie. For
who can duely consider or exactly num∣ber
the euils wee haue committed in
euery moment, or what workes wee
haue neglected? for as sinne is the com∣mitting
of euill, so is sinne the forsa∣king
of what is good. A great depri∣uall
of sanctitie (sure) when wee nei∣ther
doe good, nor thinke that is good,
but permit our hearts to wander by
vaine and vnprofitable things. It is to
difficult a thing to restraine thy heart
and preserue it from euery vnlawfull
thought. It is also a matter of too
great difficultie to imploy our selues
in terrene affaires without sin. Where∣fore
I conclude that none can perfect∣ly
comprehend and iudge himselfe, but
being occupied with many cogitations,
hee must of necessity remaine in some∣thing
ignorant to himselfe, as not
knowing what hee doth altogether
tolerate in himselfe: wherefore neare
his end, hee is terrified with a more se∣rious
and retired feare, because that al∣beit
hee neuer remembers himselfe to
<PB N="97" REF="53"/>
haue omitted anything which hee
knew, yet hee fears himselfe to haue
neglected many things which he knew
not.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>A Meditation of the short life of man, ex∣tracted
out of the deuout and zea∣lous
meditations, of that mellifluous
Father Saint Barnard.</HEAD>
<P>THe daies of man are as a shadowe
vppon earth, there is noe stay, for
where wee seeme to stand, it is in effect
nothing. Why therefore doth man so
heape vp treasure vpon earth, sith hee
must passe without delay, both that
which is gathered, and hee that gathe∣reth
it? And thou (O man) what fruit
dost thou expect in this world, whose
fruit is destruction, and whose end is
death?</P>
<P>I wish thou wouldest bee wise, and
vnderstand, and discreetely prouide
for the day to come. I know one, who
(for many yeres) hath liued familiarly
with thee, hath sitten at thy table, ta∣ken
meate from thy hand, slept in thy
bosom, hath conferred with thee when
<PB N="98" REF="54"/>
so ere hee would, being thy seruant by
way of inheritance. But because thou
hast pampered him delicately from his
youth vp, and hast spared the rod, hee is
become stif-necked, hee hath lifted vp
his heele against thy head, and hath
brought thee into slauery, and tyranni∣cally
triumphs ouer thee. Peraduen∣ture
thou wilt aske mee who this is? It
is the old man who treadeth vnderfoote
thy spirit: who little or nothing esteemes
the desires of this earth, because it
tasteth of nothing but the distasts of
the flesh.</P>
<P>This man was blinde, deafe, dombe,
&amp; inueterate in euill from his natiuity,
a rebell to vertue &amp; truth, an enemy to
the Crosse of Christ, deriding the ino∣cent,
&amp; simple man, &amp; walking in great
and wonderfull waies, far aboue his ap∣prehension
or conceipt. His pride ex∣ceedes
his strength, hee reuerendeth
none: saying in the foolishnes of his
heart, there is no God. Hee repineth at
the prosperity of others, hee fattens
himselfe with the aduersity of others:
hee is fed with beastly and sensuall co∣gitations,
nor is he wearied with them▪
<PB N="99" REF="54"/>
transgressing securely euen to the end:
hee consumeth and scattereth his owne
estate like a prodigall, hee desireth and
deuoureth other mens estates like a co∣uetous
miser: vnder pretence of dissi∣mulation
hee gathereth to himselfe
shame and ignominie, and subtilely
prouoketh the wrath of God.</P>
<P>This man was wholy borne in sinne,
and so nourished, and brought vp with
the fiends of iniquity, the children of
death, vessels of wrath, created for
dishonour and perdition. And yet
this man being such (as you heare) de∣clareth
the iudgements of God, and ta∣keth
the testament of his word into
his mouth, hee hateth instruction, hee
casteth God behind his backe: when
hee sees a thiefe hee runs with him, and
deuideth his portion among adulte∣rers,
hee asperceth reproch vpon the
childe of his owne mother, and heapeth
vp the treasure of ire against the day of
wrath vpon himselfe, hee would glad∣ly
take thy inheritance from thee, and
quite roote thee from of the earth. And
thou reuengest not so great an iniury
done against thee, but dissemblest it, thou
<PB N="100" REF="55"/>
speakest not one hard word vnto him,
nor shewest any discontent in thy coun∣tenance,
but smilest at him flattering
thee, playing with a deceiuer. Thou
art ignorant how it is Ismael that
dallies with thee. Nor is this play of
his to bee imputed to childishnes; sim∣plicity,
or innocencie, for it is the very
illusion of the soule, persecution, death,
throwing thee headlong into the ditch
hee had made for thee. Now art thou
become altogeather effeminate, now
art thou pressed downe with the yoake
of most miserable bondage, being trod
vnder his feete miserablely and vildly.
O wreched &amp; miserable man, who shall
deliuer thee from the bonds of this en∣thrallement?
let the Lord arise, &amp; let this
armed man fall before him, let this man
(greatest enemy to man) fal, &amp; be con∣founded,
since he is a cōtemner of God,
a worshipper of himselfe, &amp; his own illi∣mited
affections, a friend to the world,
&amp; a seruant to the diuel. How doest thou
thinke of it? if thou thinke rightly, thou
wilt say with me, he is guilty of death,
let him be crucified. Doe not therefore
dissemble, do not differre, do not spare,
<PB N="101" REF="55"/>
but with celerity, magnanimity, and in∣stācy
crucifie this mā. But so, as with the
Crosse of Christ, wherein there is saluati∣on
&amp; life: for whosoeuer shal cal on Christ
intentiuely, &amp; incessantly, shall presently
haue his crucified old man, inuiting him
with all benignitie: and Christ answering
with as much mercie: <HI>To day thou shalt be
with mee in Paradice.</HI> O the exceeding
mercie of Christ! O the inopinate salua∣tion
of the wicked, made righteous by
Christ! So gratefull and approoued is the
loue of God, so admired is his sweetenes,
so vnexpected his louingnes, so immeri∣ted
his mercifulnesse, that whosoeuer cri∣eth
to him, is heard of him, for the Lord
is mercifull, and cals to minde how hee
made him. O how great is the mercie of
God, how ineffable the compassion of
the right hand of the almightie? yester∣day
was I in darkenesse, this day am I in
light: yesterday in the mouth of a Lion
most bloodie, this day in the hand of my
mediatour full of mercie, yesterday in
the gate of hell to be tormented for euer,
to day in a paradice of perpetuall plea∣sure.
But what doe these letters of admo∣nition
profit, vnlesse thou wipe from thy
<PB N="102" REF="56"/>
conscience those letters or characters of
death? what doe these writings profit,
what doe they both read and vnder∣stood
auaile, vnlesse thou both reads
and vnderstand thy selfe? applie thy
selfe therefore to inward reading, that
thou may reade, conceaue and appre∣hend
thy selfe: so reade as thou may loue
God, that thou may fight, and by fight∣ing
vanquish the world, and all thy ene∣mies
therein: that thy labour may bee
conuerted into rest, thy lamenting into
reioycing, and after the darkenesse of
this life ending, thou may see the rising
of that morning sunne of righteousnesse
euer shining, where thou may likewise
see that meridian sunne of eternitie, in
whom thou shalt see the Bridegroome
with his bride, one, and the same Lord of
glorie, who liueth and raigneth for euer∣more.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="section">
<PB N="103" REF="56"/>
<HEAD>A Meditation of Saint Barnard where∣in
he describes the method of prayer,
and how a zealous Christian should
pray.</HEAD>
<P>HAue mercie on me (O Lord) for I
sinne there the most, where I ought
to reforme my selfe the most for in the
priuate Monastery, oft times whilest I
pray, I giue not attention to that I pray:
I pray with my mouth (and implies
thereby a lippe labour) but my minde is
wandring abroade, and therefore am
worthily depriued of the fruite of my
prayer: in bodie I am inward, but in heart
outward, and therefore I lose the be∣nefit
of my speech: for little aualleth it
vs to sing onely with the voice without
the pure intention of our heart: where∣fore
it is great peruersenesse, nay, great
madnesse, when we presume to talke fa∣miliarly
with God in our prayer, being
of so exceeding Maiestie, sencelessely to
diuert our mindes from him, and prosti∣tute
our hearts to I know not what folly.
Great madnes is it likewise (&amp; greatly to
bee punished) when vile dust and ashes
<PB N="104" REF="57"/>
composed of nought but sin, disdaineth
to heare the creator of this vniuerse
speaking vnto him. But ineffable is the
humilitie of his diuine goodnesse, daily
beholding vs (vnhappie wretches) tur∣ning
our eares, hardning our hearts, yet
vouchsafeth he incessantly to crie vnto
vs, saying, returne you that be of an vn∣circumcised
heart▪ behold and see I am
your Lord and God▪ God speaketh vn∣to
me in a Psalme, and I vnto him, nei∣ther
yet when I say the Psame doe I con∣sider
whose Psalme it is: therefore doe
I a great iniurie vnto God, when I desire
him that hee would heare my prayer,
which I, when I powre it before him, doe
not heare my selfe.</P>
<P>I beseech him to incline his eare vnto
my prayer, but I incline mine eare nei∣ther
to my selfe, nor to my prayer, but
which is worse, by meditating of vnpro∣fitable
and sensuall affections, I oppose a
most filthie and horrible corruption,
in the consideration of my hearts pol∣lution,
before the eies of his all-seeing
Maiestie.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="section">
<PB N="105" REF="57"/>
<HEAD>A verie profitable prayer taken out of
Saint Barnard, intreating of the forme
and manner, how euerie one ought to
consider himselfe, no lesse sententious
then zealous.</HEAD>
<P>IF I behold not my selfe, I know not
my selfe: but if I behold my selfe, I shall
not endure my selfe: because I finde so
manie things in mee noe lesse worthie
of reprehension, then confusion and
shame: so as by how much more exact∣ly
and seriously I examine my selfe, so
manie more abhominations doe I finde
in the corners of my heart. For since the
time I first began to sinne, I could neuer
passe one day without sinne, neither as
yet doe I cease from sinne, but from day
to day adde sinne vpon sinne, which
though I haue them before mine eyes,
and consider the exceeding measure of
them, yet doe I not lament them. I see
sinnes in mee to be ashamed of, yet am
not I ashamed: I behold sinnes to be sor∣rowed
for in me, yet am not I sorrow∣full:
which is an euident signe and token
of death and damnation, for that mem∣ber
<PB N="106" REF="58"/>
which feeleth not paine is dead: and
a disease insensible, is incurable.</P>
<P>I am sensuall and dissolute, neither yet
doe I correct my selfe: but daily reiterate
those sinnes which before I confessed,
neither am I aware of the ditch, into
which (miserable soule that I am) I haue
fallen, or made another to fall, or seene
him falling. And whereas I ought to de∣plore
my sinnes and (with instancie of
supplication) pray for remission of them
(to wit) for the euils which I had comit∣ted,
and the good which I had neglected
and omitted: woe is me, I did the quite
contrarie, for first I grew luke warme, and
after chill-could in the feruour of my
praier, and now I remaine key-could,
without any sence or apprehension of
sinne: and therefore cannot bewaile the
sinne committed by mee, because the
grace of teares and remorse is departed
farre from me.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>That sinne is not to be excused.</HEAD>
<P>VVhere I ought to haue amen∣ded
my sinnes, I added sinne
vpon sinne: when I was accused of them▪
<PB N="107" REF="58"/>
I either in a sort excused them, or wholy
denied them, or which is worse, I defen∣ded
them, and with impatience answered
for them, whereas there was no sinne,
with which I was not defiled, or might
haue beene defiled. It is fit therefore, that
all occasion of delay set apart, I promise
amendment of all sides, or by whomsoe∣uer
I am accused: to the end I may bee
deliuered from the seruitude of sinne by
me committed, or which might be by me
committed.</P>
<P>Qui ver saturin atrijs Dei, oret &amp; de∣ploret:
oret, vt peccata eius remittantur:
deploret peccata que cōmittuntur: speret in
Deo vt possideat Deum in quo sperauit. I∣bid.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="108" REF="59"/>
<HEAD>A Glorious Hymne of an an∣cient
Father, expressing the
Harmonious vnion of the
heauenly Citizens.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>SAcred powers vnited euer,</L>
<L>Which no discord can disseuer,</L>
<L>So enrich'd by the heauenly giuer,</L>
<L>As empouerishd are you neuer.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Concords perfect ioyes vniting,</L>
<L>To melodious feasts inuiting,</L>
<L>Where all obiects be delighting,</L>
<L>Noe darke clouds, your day benighting.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>What one hath is not so priuate,</L>
<L>But his friend may likewise haue it,</L>
<L>And suppose he should not craue it,</L>
<L>Yet vnited loues receiue it.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There's no light that moone doth borrow,</L>
<L>All's one day, there's no morrow,</L>
<L>Perfect solace free from sorrow,</L>
<L>Yeere by yeere contented thorough</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="109" REF="59"/>
<L>Noe Ecclips of Sunne or Moone,</L>
<L>Neither of their lights be showen,</L>
<L>Heauen has tapers of her owne,</L>
<L>Which to heauenly saints are knowne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Fruites so mellow, full of pleasure,</L>
<L>Sacred mounts repleate with treasure,</L>
<L>Of which saints haue perfect seasure,</L>
<L>Reaping them at their best leasure.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There the Cedar and the Pine,</L>
<L>Fruitefull Olyue, braunchie Vine,</L>
<L>Peacefull Mirtle, Mirrhe diuine,</L>
<L>There the Rose and Eglantine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Euerie flower in seemely order,</L>
<L>Stands to beautifie her border,</L>
<L>More then Art could ere afford her,</L>
<L>Since diuinest powers haue stord her.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There loues bird sits on a spray,</L>
<L>Chaunting out her roundelay,</L>
<L>Glorious soules their ioyes display,</L>
<L>Euerie saint keepes holiday.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Clad they be in goulden clothing,</L>
<L>Ophir gould to that is nothing,</L>
<L>Full of ioy, yet without lothing,</L>
<L>Time-obseruing without soothing.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="110" REF="60"/>
<L>There the Topaz, Emerald,</L>
<L>And the Diamond, thats cald</L>
<L>The worlds beautie: Citties walld</L>
<L>Round with gould: with gemmes empalld.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There is that Bethesdas poole,</L>
<L>Which refresheth euerie soule,</L>
<L>There the bookes which doe enroule</L>
<L>Such as laugh, and such as houle.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>None must in that campe appeare</L>
<L>Conquerors, but conquerd heere,</L>
<L>Such as past their daies in feare,</L>
<L>To be cround for euer there.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Let vs fight, that we may winne,</L>
<L>Mastrie ouer death and sinne,</L>
<L>That after life we may begin</L>
<L>To renew our life with him.</L>
<L>Who has mercie still in store,</L>
<L>And doth liue foreuermore.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="60"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

