<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The apologie of the Reformed Churches of France VVherein are expressed the reasons, why they haue ioyned their armies; to those of the King of Great Britaine. Translated according to the French coppie.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Apologie ou sont deduites les raisons des eglises reformées de France. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>Eglises réformées de France.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A01180</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 11293</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S102594</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99838366</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99838366</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">2742</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01180)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2742)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1023:19)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The apologie of the Reformed Churches of France VVherein are expressed the reasons, why they haue ioyned their armies; to those of the King of Great Britaine. Translated according to the French coppie.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Apologie ou sont deduites les raisons des eglises reformées de France. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>Eglises réformées de France.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reynolds, John, fl. 1621-1650.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 55, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed [by William Stansby] for Nathaniell Butter,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1628.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Translator's preface signed: Iohn Reynolds.</NOTE><NOTE>Translation of: Apologie ou sont deduites les raisons des eglises reformées de France.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A01180">
<STC T="S">11293</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99838366</BIBNO>
<VID>2742</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE APOLOGIE OF THE REFORMED CHVRCHES OF <HI>FRANCE.</HI></P>
<P>VVherein are expressed the Reasons, why they haue Ioyned their Armies; to those of the King of Great BRITTAINE.</P>
<P><HI>Translated according to the French Coppie.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed for <HI>Nathaniell Butter.</HI> 1628.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD><HI>TO ENGLAND,</HI> IN <HI>HER REPRESEN∣TIVE BODY. The High and Illustrious Court of Parliament,</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>LORDS.</SALUTE>
<SALUTE>KNIGHTS.</SALUTE>
<SALUTE>BVRGESSES.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">Y</SEG>Ou haue here (in all hu∣militie) presented to you, the sighes &amp; teares of our sister Church of <HI>France,</HI> who is at this present miserably perse∣cuted by the bloodie power and Malice of <HI>Antichrist</HI> and his ad∣herents; as also the na∣ked grounds and mo∣tiues, why shee ioynes her Armes with those of our
<PB REF="3"/>
<HI>Soueraigne,</HI> in her lawfull Defence and preseruation; For although <HI>Rebellon</HI> be the false pretect, yet Religi∣on is the true cause why the Pope by his Champion the French King, now seekes her finall raine and exter∣mination. Shee now mournes both in teares and blood, and breathes forth her wounds and sorrowes to vs in a fainting; yea, almost in a dying eloquence; Shall wee therefore (who professe our selues to be the best of <HI>Chri∣stians,</HI> and the deerest of Gods Children) permit pro∣phannesse to preuaile ore pietie, Idolatrie to triumph ore true Religion, and the Church of Rome, ore that of God, if our Religion be theirs, must not their dan∣gers and persecutions be ours, For what Peace can we haue whiles they are oppressed with Warre, or how can our consciences be at rest and tranquilitie, whiles theirs are tovmented with all sorts of afflictions and cruelties, Can that Church of France be beaten but this of Eng∣land is threatned, or the Protestants of that Kingdome be extinguished but we are Eclipsed, yea, doe not their feares presage and predict ours, and their dangers fatally denounce and portend ours: We haue already seene and suffered Gods Church in Bohemia, the Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>atinate, Se∣lesia and Morauia to bee ruined, and shall we not there∣fore beleeue, if that of France goe next, that this of England must immediately follow, We see the Pope is as bloody in his malice, as boundlesse in his Ambition, and that with high wrestling, and an insulting brauerie, he proceedes in his Enuie and power, at one time to roote out the name and memorie of Gods Church and Chil∣dren in all places and Countries of Christendome. How powerfully hath he lately preuailed with the Emperour and the King of Spaine and Poland in this bloody qua∣rell,
<PB REF="3"/>
who with barbarous hearts and sacrilegious hands haue played their prises in oppressing and de-pressing these Churches in their Countries, and (now by a policie as subtile, as execrable) hath likewise drawne the French King to make himselfe guiltie of the same impious and bloody crimes; to ruine the Protestants of his King∣dome, whose Valours and Fidelities placed the Crowne on his Fathers head; and to exterminate those Chur∣ches which with so much Pietie and wisedome hee had established in the Meridian of their perfection and glorie.</P>
<P>The which to preuent, and oppose, God hath inspi∣red the heart of our Gracious King <HI>CHARLES</HI> to reach them out the hand and Scepter of his Royall assis∣tance, and so to proue himselfe a true Defender of the Faith, as well in Fact as Title. Knowing therefore that by the Lawes of Honour and Religion we are bound to ayde and asist them, and not to suffer the Vineyard of Gods Church to be thus miserably trampled ore, and rooted vp by the Champions of Rome and Hell, it will be a pious and a Noble worke for you Illustrious Lords and Gentlemen, the Great Senators, and Elders of our Israell, to contribute the meanes, as our King hath the Will, to the preseruation and building vp of so Religi∣ous and glorious a Worke; by affecting it tenderly in your selues, and by cheerishing it carefully and dearely in the hearts of all the parts and members of this King∣dome; For as the Protestants of France call on our King, so doth his Maiestie on you (who are the essentiall and figuratiue body thereof) and God on you all, for the speedy and vigorous assistance of this his afflicted Spouse the Church, and hee who is the searcher of all hearts the
<PB REF="4"/>
witnesse of all soules, and the Iudge of all actions, will infallibly iudge betwixt you and him, with what true Deuotion and Zeale you performe this part of his seruice and glorie.</P>
<P>Warres are made as well with Gold as Iron, there∣fore in assisting this our afflicted Sister the Church of France, wee must second our words with deedes; our promises with effects, and our Prayers with our pur∣ses. Their Enemies are strong and powerfull, their af∣flictions and dangers great, so therefore must our assis∣tance be to them. They are neere to vs by Cituation, but farre neerer in Religion, for as their cause and quarell is ours, so should the sence and feeling of their calamities, and in this sence I may iustly affirme, that they are a great part of our selues, because we generally belong all to one Church, as that Church doth particularly and pe∣culiarly to God.</P>
<P>As truth is the best eloquence to perswade vs to this assistance, so Religion is the best truth, and it would bee an act not onely of Impietie, but of shame in vs, if these our three flourishing Churches, of England, Scot∣land and Ireland, should not now powerfully assist that afflicted one of France, which sues to them for it, with teares and prayers. But Illustrious Lords and generous Gentlemen, my Iudgement prompts mee that I should wrong yours, in seeking to perswade your affections to so charitable and religious a worke, from which I know nothing is capable to direct, or disswade you, and in that behalfe I rest hopefull, if not confident, that you will at least excuse my zeale, if not pardon my presumption for proferring vp the sighes and teares of this poore perse∣cuted French Church, to your sublime Protection and
<PB REF="4"/>
Patronage, or rather to your charitable care, and reli∣gious consderacion, as esteeming it euerie way as wor∣thy of your pittie and compassion, as of your knowledge. May the sight of her afflictions, myseries and calami∣ties, teach vs how to preuent our owne, May God of his best mercie so operate with our hearts and soules, as wee may esteeme and repute them our owne, and may Eng∣land (by the Kings royall, and your Illustricus ex∣ample) stretch forth her hands, to relieue this poore French Church and people, so vn∣iustly afflicted, and so wrongfully oppressed and persecuted for God, and his Cause.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>IOHN REYNOLDS.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>The Apologie of the Reformed Churches of <HI>France;</HI> wherein are expressed the Reasons why they haue ioyned their Armes to those of his <HI>Maiestie, the King of Great</HI> BRITTAINE.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>HERE is none but will iudge that a sicke Patient is extreamely oppressed with his disease, when hee frequently takes vio∣lent Physicke, where∣of as yet hee hath his stomach wholy char∣ged and afflicted, and therefore loathes and abhorres it, were it but onely for the bitternesse thereof. Right so wee must confesse, that our wronges haue exposed and re∣duced vs to the last point of necessite; since wee are enforced to haue recourse to that remedie wherein wee haue formerly felt so many violencies, as the verie name thereof giues vs many terrours and tremblings. For if euer any People haue had iust cause to abhor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e and detest Warr, it is we aboue all others of the world, to whom it hath brought so many ruins &amp; desolations, that our Houses remaine yet either burnt or demolish∣ed,
<PB N="2" REF="6"/>
our Lands and Inheritances in prey, our Vines roo∣ted vp, our Trees cut downe, and which is worse, the verie Earth is yet red, and almost hot with our Blood. And because after all these deplorable effects of Armes, we are ag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne seene to resume them; it is iustly to be presumed, that it is the descouerie of some great or in∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>itable danger, which despight of our contrarie incli∣nations, hath enforced and drawne vs to it. For we are reduced either to perish without any hope of recoue∣rie, or else to seeke our subsistance in our lawfull de∣fence, by embracing the meanes which God giues vs by the assistance of the most Eccellent King of Great Brittaine, whose heart he hath touched with pittie and compassion of our miseries, and therefore to employ his forces to make vs enioy peace, which was sworne and consigned into his hands, and whereof his Maiestie was made the Depositor.</P>
<P>It is to iustifie this last necessitie that wee put our hands to the Pen, at the same time we doe to the Sword, and we are confident, that who soeuer will heare vs without any preiudicat enuie or passion, we will make them so apparantly see our innocencie, and so soundly proue &amp; iustifie the iniustice wherwith it is oppressed, that if they are not obdurat, or insensible Rockes, they will pittie our miseries in excusing the resolutions which we are constrayned to take, and will be the first to condemne the vniust proceedings of those who haue precipitated vs hereunto, and whom henceforth we ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> tearme no other then our Enemies.</P>
<P>At the verie entrance whereof, we solemnly protest, that wee will not comprehend vnder this Name, the sacred Maiestie of the King our Prince, and as we will not impute vnto him, the blame of infringing his Edicts, and of violating his Royall Word; so we haue no intent whatsoeuer in our Hearts which shall dero∣gate from the most humble subiection, and constant
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
fidelitie we owe him; the two essentiall Articles where∣of our Religion is composed, is, <HI>To feare God and honour the King;</HI> and if any trad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce or calamniate vs, of the contrary, blessed be God they are those who made the baracado<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s against their Soueraigne, and who tumul∣tuously and treacherously draue him out of his Capitall Citie, and neuer left before they had proditoriously and inhumanely murthered him; they are those who assembled the Estates Generall, which begat that mon∣ster the League, to take away the Crowne from the law∣full heire <HI>Hen.</HI> 4. and consequently to declare his po∣steritie incapable to succeede, which was directly to snatch away the Septer from our present King before he was borne; and who haue caused to issue from their Cloysters such execrable Paracides, to thrust their im∣poysoned kniues in the brests and hearts of our Prin∣ces, who haue beene quelled and fallen thereunder; and who in the iniquitie of such times must abandon their Estates to the first intruder, and their liues to the first Asasinate, If the Pope please to declare them Hereticks or Tyrants.</P>
<P>To haue such for our accusers results to our glory and redounds to our iustification, and indeede all Histo∣ries witnesse for vs, That although our Kings haue been of a contrary Religion to vs, haue set fire to the Tem∣ple of our Peace, and with high hands and crueltie haue persecuted and massacred vs; that yet we haue neuer thought of such accursed attempts, but contrariwise vpon the very ruines and cruelties thereof; the zeale of our prayers for them, haue triumph'd ore the feruency of their flames, and for the irreproachable approbati∣on of our fidelitie: when God permitted that the facti∣ons of <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Spaine</HI> conspired against their Crowns, they haue found no surer nor vigorous refuge then in our defence; so that if <HI>Hen.</HI> 3. could reuiue from his Tombe, Hee would giue vs the honour and glory to
<PB N="4" REF="7"/>
haue conserued his life and Septer. If a Fryer whom Hell created had not bereaud him of the one, and de∣priued him of the other: and as for <HI>Henry the Great</HI> (of glorious memory) euery one knowes how much wee haue spilt of our owne bloud at his feet, to mount and establish him on his Throne, where in all apparance of truth he had beene still raigning, if the Iesuires and their Em<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> saries had not approach'd him, or that the sacred treasure of his life were still intrusted and depo∣sited in our hands.</P>
<P>We haue not so well serued the Father to eclipse our glory in so ill seruing the Sonne; and may it please the diuine prouidence and goodnesse of God, that those who haue destoyed his royall Predecessours, and which bend their designes and monopolies against him, by the same wayes they haue done against them, doe not in the end reduce him to the same extremities and mise∣ries; and in this cause and quarrell he shall finde that we haue no wealth but we will expend, nor bloud but we will sacrifice to iustifie our fidelitie, which our E∣nemies (with as much subtiltie as malice) endeauour to make him suspect, and so to haue his Laurels still flou∣rish and continue greene, wherewith hitherto he hath beene crowned: So if griefe now draw complaints from vs, and enforce and compeil vs to take vp Armes, Wee here lift vp our voyces to make it known to all the world, that it is not against his sacred person, but onely against the impetuositie of those ministers of his, who haue beene depured by him to execute his royall words; and to make vs enioy peace according to the tenure of his Edicts; and who contrary there∣unto haue oppressed vs with all sorts of Iniustice and violence, and after whole yeares of vnprofitable pati∣ence, doe in the end constraine vs to prouide for our conseruation, by the onely meanes and remedies left vs, which are the Lawes of Nations and Nature?</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="7"/>
To the end therefore that our Innoc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ncie, and their Iniustice may appeare to all the world; we mustr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fume matters as they were at the last Peace and pacincation, and come to the Edict which was then published: There is none therefore so blinde or ignorant in matters of State, who apparantly knowes not, how preiudici∣all those conditions were to vs: If the poore Citie of <HI>Monpellier</HI> should remaine buried in silence, and so ac∣cording to the vniust maximes of our Enemies should seeme to be condemned to eternall seruitude and slane∣ry; besides, the yoke of subiection <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the pre∣cedent peace imposd vpon our Ecclesiasticali assem∣blies, which they make wholly vnprofitable vnto vs, were not taken away: and there was no right nor iustice done vnto vs, vpon an infinite number of other infractions of the said Edict, whereof we can produce whole books of iust complaints and grieuances, where∣by we foresee that our Enemies will draw them into consequence purposely to authorise them hereafter. Moreouer, in that which was one of the most impor∣tant points, and the chiefest motiues of our resumption of Armes, to wit, the subsistance of the Fort before <HI>Rochell,</HI> they would expresse nothing in the Declarati∣on touching the promise made to vs for the razing and demolishing thereof. And that promise which was yet giuen vs by the Ambassadour of the King of Great <HI>Bri∣taine,</HI> as also of the Lords States Generall, was couched in such ambiguous and generall tearmes, that it mani∣festly appeared the intent of those who gaue them, was not to obserue and keepe them: because by their artifi∣ciall prouidence they prepared the way to euasions, which they haue since practised, and would thereby in∣ferre, and pretend that they had promised vs no∣thing.</P>
<P>So that in what estate soeuer our affaires then were, finding more safetic in a weake resistance, then in a
<PB N="6" REF="8"/>
peace which publikely cuts our throats: we therefore refused to accept it vpon those conditions, which we held would infallibly draw after it our fatall ruine and destruction: But at length we found our selues obliged, yea we dare affirme almost enforced, by the vrgent and reiterated assummons which were made vs by the a∣foresaid Embassadours, who in the name of those they represented, were established vnto vs as Pledges and Sureties, that we were proceeded with sincerely, and especially for the demolition of the said Fort, where∣of they alleaged they had expresse promise and assu∣rance. As also that this peace was not of the qualitic and nature of the precedent peaces, which had beene treated onely with vs, whereas this was properly not so much with vs, as with the King of Great <HI>Britaine</HI> and the Lords States, so as whosocuer violated or in∣fringed it, the infraction and iniury thereof was pro∣perly offred to them, who would not spare either their intercession, or other meanes, to make good their words to vs.</P>
<P>And although this were very preualent and power∣full to induce vs to accept and admit thereof, they yet further represented to vs, That our Armes was the one∣ly obstacle that the King imployed not his against the inueterate Enemy of our Estate and Religion, and why he did not so soundly wed himselfe to the affaires of <HI>Germanie,</HI> with the King of Great <HI>Britaine:</HI> so that whatsoeuer ill successe betided, it would be iustly im∣puted to our obstinacy, and would occasion all those who hitherto haue wished vs well, wholly to abandon and forsake vs.</P>
<P>To these important reasons we suffred our selues to be vanquished, and although we then foretold them that they would finde themselues deceiued, as well in the assurance which was giuen them to conferue peace vnto vs, as also so to ioyne their designes and Armes
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
with them against <HI>Spaine,</HI> yet we would no longer op∣pose against their requests and instances, but sacrifized vp our selues and all our common interests to the ad∣uantages of the King of Great <HI>Britaine,</HI> and his Allyes, and so accepted the peace in the same manner and forme as it was giuen vs, onely we drew an Act from the Em∣bassadours of Great <HI>Britaine,</HI> verifying all which was formerly alleaged, the which because it is the foundati∣on of the Iustice of his and our Armes, it is requisite we doe here insert it.</P>
<P>VVE Henry Rich <HI>Lord of</HI> Kensington <HI>Earle of</HI> Holland, <HI>Captaine of the Guard to the King of Great</HI> Britaine, <HI>Knight of the Order of the Garter, and Priuie Councellour to his Maiestie, And</HI> Dudley Carle∣ton <HI>Knight, Priuie Councellour, and Vice-Chamberlaine to his said Maiestie, extraordinary Ambassadors for him to the most Christian King: to all present, or to come, Greeting, Whereas</HI> Monsieur Montmartin <HI>and</HI> Monsieur Mania<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d, <HI>Generall Deputies of the reformed Churches of</HI> France, <HI>to∣gether with other particular Deputies of my Lords the Dukes of</HI> Rhoan <HI>and</HI> Soubize, <HI>as also of many Townes and Prouinces, which haue ioyned their Armes with those of the said Lords; hauing made Peacewith the Most Chri∣stian King, by our aduice and interuentions, agreed and con∣sented by the said Most Christian King their Soueraigne, and that the said Deputies, haue yeelded to and cut off ma∣ny things which they esteemed to be most important for their safetie, euery way conformable to their Edicts and Records, which they were expresly charged to obtaine in the Treatie of peace, and wherein they had powerfully persisted, but that the Obedience which they owe, and will render to their King and Soueraigne, and the consideration and regard which they will yeeld to the expresse requests and intrauentions of the King of Great</HI> Britaine <HI>our Master; in whose name wee haue exhorted and councel'd them to condescend to the Con∣ditions</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
<HI>offred and giuen them by the said Peace in fauour, and for the prosperity of this Kingdome in particular, and the content and assistance of Christendome in generall, To which causes, Wee declare and certifie, That in the words which were heretofore giuen vnto vs, for the accomplishing of the said Treatie, and proffered by the Lord Chancellour at the acceptance of the peace, containing, that through their long seruices, and continuall obedience they may expect that from the goodnesse of the King, which they could not else ob∣taine by any other Treatie, and in those very things which they esteeme the most important and pressing, in conuenient time they might heare and prouide for their Supplications made with respect and Humilitie; There was a cleerer inter∣pretation brought vnto vs from his Maiestie, and the Lords his Ministers, by those who were the Agents and Negotiators of the peace, being Men of Honour and qualitie, ordained and established with power from his Maiestie and his Priuie Councell, whereof the sence and meaning is, That they vn∣derstand to speake of the Fort</HI> Lewes <HI>before</HI> Rochell, <HI>and therby to giue assurance of its demolition in conuenient time, and in the interim some remedies of other matters which should remaine by the said Treatie of Peace, to the preiudice of the Libertie of</HI> Rochell.</P>
<P><HI>Without the which assurance of Demolition, and the ease and exemption of Garisons, the said Deputies protested vnto vs, that they would neuer haue consented to the subsistance of the said Fort, being commanded and resolued to conserue the right of that Demolition. As they doe by this present decla∣ration, with assurance that the King of Great</HI> Britaine <HI>will labour by his intercessions, ioyn'd with their most humble supplications to hasten the time of that demolition, whereof we haue giuen them all the royall promises and words which they can desire, after we had shewed them, that they might and ought to remaine satisfied and contented. In witnesse of all which now formerly expressed, we haue signed and sealed this present with our names and armes, and haue caused it</HI>
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
<HI>likewise to be vnder-signed by one of our Secretaries, Dated in</HI> Paris <HI>the</HI> 11. <HI>day of February</HI> 1626. <HI>And so signed</HI> Holland, D. Carleton, <HI>with seales vnder euery signe, and vnderneath by the commandment of the said Lords, signed</HI> Augier.</P>
<P>This Act so dressed and finished, the Deputies carry it home to their Prouinces, to serue for comfort and consolation to our poore afflicted Churches, who wept and trembled at so preiudiciall a Treatie, and yet not∣withstanding laboured with all diligence to a punctuall accomplishment of all things which were conceded and granted by vs, to the end that calumnie might not take the least hold of our actions, and that there might not remaine the least shadow of pretext to v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e vs as ac∣customed, <HI>to wit,</HI> not to obserue or performe any thing which is solemnly promised vnto vs.</P>
<P>To which end the Citie of <HI>Rochell,</HI> contrary to the priuiledge of frontier Townes, as also of her owne in particular, doth speedily demolish a notable peece of fortification, which with much cost and labour it had built, and ioyned to her wals. They dismist the Earle of <HI>Lauall,</HI> and his troops, who had assisted them in their necessitie, and in their places receiued the Kings Com∣missioners; whose comming they well knew would proue extreamely preiudiciall to their liberties, and their residence to their safetie: and in a word, from point to point with a scrupulous curiositie, they dis∣charged all that they were enioynd to performe. The Duke of <HI>Rohan</HI> likewise dismissed all his Regiments and troopes which had followed him, and our swords fell out of our hands in all places where we had drawne them: The sorrowfull honour of warre was presently seene changed, and conuerted into Bonefires of Ioy for the peace, and into publike vowes and acclamations for the Kings long life and prosperity; and briefely,
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
our Obedience was so intire, that the most malicious research of our Enemies could finde nothing whereat either to contradict or scandalize vs.</P>
<P>So if we had had to doe with people any way iust or charitable, it had beene capable to haue molified their hearts, and to haue began to deale and agitate with vs, otherwise then formerly they had done, and faithfully to haue perform'd what they had so solemnly promi∣sed: But the onely Article of their Faith which they keepe inuiolably, is neuer to keep or performe it to vs; and at the very first abord they shewed vs effects ther∣of, when we came to inregister and verifie the Edict of Peace in the Parliaments, and (onely that of Grenoble excepted) there was none of them which would abso∣lutely doe it, some obiecting one restriction, and others alleaging another, vntill they came to point and cauill at matters of no moment, which vnprofitably shewed the peruersenesse of their auerse natures &amp; inclinations, As vpon the word of <HI>Temple,</HI> as if the places where we assembled to pray vnto God were Mosques: and again vpon that of <HI>Ecclesiasticall Assemblies,</HI> as if they were the Congregations of Pagans, or the Synogogues of Iewes.</P>
<P>But yet we belieued that we had much cause to extoll the moderation of those who haue quarrelled with vs but with words; It is easie for vs to suffer iniurie for the loue of him, who before vs, was in derision called <HI>Samaritan,</HI> howsoeuer that those contemners were wholly vnworthy, in the neglect, but much more in the violation of the Edict, custome (in that nature) hauing made vs so insensible, as we almost disdaine to open our mouthes to complaine thereof. But the ill consists in this that the greatest parts of those Modifications which haue bin vsed, do derectly concerne our safeties, and therefore makes the Kings Declaration wholly vn∣profitable.</P>
<P>This hath beene particularly seene in the Parliament of <HI>Thoulouze,</HI> whose Iurisdiction is knowne to extend
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
vpon the greatest number of those, whom necessitie had armed in these last emotions. For in two onely Ar∣ticles they almost anihilated all the substance of the E∣dict. First they placed among causes reserued and exe∣crable, the demolition of the Temples of the Romish Churches, expresly abolished by the Declara∣tion of the yeere 1622, conformable herein to the Edict of <HI>Nantes,</HI> and also then absolutely verified by them, by which meanes, the hatred which they conceiue against vs, carries them from the shame to be held factious and inconstant. But they proceed further, for they limit the abolishing of hostilities committed the 5. Febr. 1626, although the Declaration of Peace was not published vntill many dayes after we subsisted in Armes in all pla∣ces where we were constrained to resume them. So in those two turnes of the pen, they haue inwrapped vs all in the condemnation, preparing the way to all sorts of iniustice and cruelties which they haue since practised and committed vpon vs. And although his Maiestie commanded that these Modifications should bee with∣drawne, as directly opposite to his intentions, and pre∣iuditiall to the publike tranquilitie, yet notwithstanding all these reasons, this Parliament hath obstinately made good what it formerly so vniustly and so factiously re∣solued against vs, to the great preiudice and blemish of the Authoritie Royall, and for a most compleat and in∣tire iustification of our complaints and grieuances, not being able to find securitie or safetie in the words and promises of our Prince, because what good affection or intents soeuer he retaine for our behalfes, those who ought to be the executors of his Royall will, and plea∣sure, doe directly combine and band themselues against it, as triumphing and glorying in the infringing of his promises.</P>
<P>These beginnings were not to giue vs hope of any much happy success, or if any one intended or expected them, experience stayed not long to vndeceaue them,
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
the eruptions of the Peace hauing beene so grosly and presumptuously committed, with such a violent impe∣tuositie, that they feeme to be affected thereto, it being impossible to giue it any other interpretation then this, <HI>Miserie to those, who are weakest, and vanquished.</HI></P>
<P>This was manifestly seene and knowne at the refuse which was giuen to our general Deputies to send Com∣missioners through all Prouinces according as it was in∣culcated &amp; intimated by the Declaration of Peace. The necessity of their sending being extreame, to the end the Edict might be put in execution where it was infringed and violated. To reestablish the exercise of our religion in those places from whence it had been banished. To replace in their houses a numberlesse number of poore families which had beene expeled and exiled. And in a word, to preuent and remedy those disorders which drew with them the licentiousnesse of war, and to make vs feele some effects of so many promises which had been made vs. But it is that which no supplications can euer obtaine, so as most of the chiefest Churches of the Kingdome haue fainted and languished in miserie, that they are so far off that this Peace hath any way impro∣ued or bettered their condition as contrary-wise it hath disarmed vs, to expose vs naked to all manner of tor∣tures and persecutions.</P>
<P>The which to approue and iustifie, at least 60 poore Churches will vndertake with weeping hearts and voi∣ces, to whom according to the tenor of the Edict, the exercise of their Religion ought to be free, and where it was confidently hoped they should haue now beene re∣established by the peace, they yet haue remained in a pi∣tifull desolation, without that all their requests &amp; pray∣ers can any way steed them for their restoration, or produce any other fruits or effects then the immense charges of their vnprofitable solicitation. Iniustice, which hath not onely been practised in those Townes subdued by the violence of Armes, and where this hard
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
measure might peraduenture be imputed to the seuerity and sharpnesse of the Roman-Catholicks against vs for hauing committed some acts of hostilitie, but also in those places who refused to ioyne to the resistance of their brethren, and had stooped the most <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ruily vnder their yoake, and in those places also where ours haue no power to agitate any thing.</P>
<P>Particularly, we may here remember the Church of <HI>Tours,</HI> whereof the Temple hauing been burnt in the mid'st of peace before the troubles of the yeeres 1620 and 1621, and during the two Edicts of Peace which haue beene since establshed and published; they cannot hetherunto reedifie and repaire it. And although the king with his own mouth hath ordained the restablish∣ment thereof, and to that end granted out a commission to see it performed the last yeere, yet notwithstanding, the malice and wickednesse of his Officers hath rende∣red it vaine and vnprofitable to whom the execution thereof was giuen and belonged, so that for the tearme of 7 whole yeeres, more than 2000 Soules haue there languished in a miserable captiuitie of Conscience, without hauing permission or liberty to seru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> God. And for asmuch as some-times they haue assayed to assemble secretly to administer the Sacrament of Baptisme to some Children, and not to suffer so great a number of Soules without some exercise of Religion, they haue followed them closely and seuerely, haue publickly abu∣sed the Minister, and condemned him in a great Fine, for lending of his House for so piousan Action.</P>
<P>Yea so far it is that those poore troopes of Christians so pitifully dispersed, and so long time depriued of the food of their Soules, could be assembled or gathered to∣gether, that the insolencie and crueltie of our Enemies haue begat and perpetrated new dissipations. The yeere 1622, the Duke of <HI>Ventadour</HI> (formerly held to be a moderate Prince) hath in a setled peace demolished the Temple of <HI>Chailar</HI> in <HI>Vizaretz,</HI> and forbidden all this
<PB N="14" REF="12"/>
poore Towne (wherein there are not 10 Families of a contrarie religion to ours) the exercise of their religion, authorising by this remarkeable example, in regard of his dignitie, all those of his gouernment to an implaca∣ble hatred against vs, and euen to outraged with a licen∣tious furie and boldnesse. The Baron of <HI>Perant,</HI> Gouer∣nor of <HI>Beucaire</HI> in <HI>Languedoc,</HI> imboldned by this inso∣lencie, after he had taken from vs, &amp; vsurped the Tem∣ple of God, wherein we were accustomed to serue God in the Church of <HI>Vezenobre</HI> in <HI>Sezennes,</HI> he not only con∣tented himselfe to depriue vs thereof, and to dedicate it to Idols, but to leaue a perpetuall memoriall of his out∣ragious and violent iniustice, caused there a Bell to be founded with this Inscription, That <HI>Such a day he had chased Heresie thence.</HI> And not long since when the Nati∣onall Synod was held at <HI>Castres,</HI> the Cardinall of <HI>Sourdis</HI> came furiously rushing vpon a troope of harmlesse and innocent Soules, going to <HI>Montrauell,</HI> with the great in∣commodities and laboures of their bodies, to seeke the Food of their Soules, where violently he pursued the Pastor (whom it pleased God to preserue) shut vp a great number of women and small children into a barn, where he held them a long time captiues in the feares and apprehensions of death, &amp; euerie minute threatned to set fire to them and burne them, and in the end by a prophanation full of horror, conuerted to a stable this Temple where these seruants of the Lord were accusto∣med frequently to serue him, and which had continued without interruption since the furie of the Masacres.</P>
<P>And in this manner it is, that Our Enemies doe ac∣complish that which his Maiesties Declaration had promised vs, concerning the reestablishing of our dis∣sipated Churches, that is to say, by new inuented out∣rages, and performed by great and noble personages, against whom it is vnpossible for vs to obtaine any Iu∣stice, yea not lawfull to frame or exhibit a complaint.</P>
<P>Enery one may iudge of what a dangerous and per∣nicious
<PB N="15" REF="12"/>
consequence these examples are, and what we may attend or expect from people already exasperated and animated with implacable hatred against vs; hauing before their eyes, those and the like great personages, which serue for fire-brands and incendraries to their rage: and indeede they are growne to so boundlesse and licencious a rage, that they can make vs suffer no more, and in imitation of others, they triumph and glory to abuse vs, and doe openly depresse vs with their out∣rages. So that almost euery where to be knowne to be of our Religion, is to be marked and distinguished for Monsters, and those who are of the sweetest, and most temperate inclinations, doe thinke they extreamly gra∣tifie vs, if they doe but simply abhorre vs, and eschew our companies and meetings, as people who are infect∣ed with the pestilence, especially in those places where they preuaile in number, and it is almost throughout the whole Kingdome, that we cannot goe to our Di∣uine Exercises, but either in going or returning the vulgar doe assemble to hush and shout at vs with publike out-cries, throw stones at vs, and beat vs downe with iniuries; so that in the Capitall Citie of <HI>Paris</HI> it selfe, it is not long since that there were some slayne vpon the place, without that the presence of the King, &amp; the respect of that famous Parliament there resident, could preuent or hinder that this blood was not spilt before their eyes, and themselues to be almost destroyed there∣with. Yea they aduance so far in this insolencie, as they rush into particular mens houses to execute the excesse of this their crueltie. And the example is resent &amp; fresh of that which hapned in the aforesaid Church of <HI>Veze∣nobre,</HI> where a furious number of <HI>Asasins</HI> breake by night into the house of the Minister, and clapt a rope about his necke purposely to strangle him, if miracu∣lously he had not escaped their tallents by leaping out at a window, from whence he secretly crept along to som neighbouring cottage, almost dead with the blows and
<PB N="16" REF="13"/>
wounds he receiued of them. Those whom they cannot force in their houses, the seduce forth by subtiltie; as an Aduocate of <HI>Sommieres,</HI> who being fallen into some re∣uolt, during the last ciuill combustions, but then imme∣diatly after return'd againe into the Church, he was sent for to the Castle vnder a false pretext &amp; errand, &amp; there was surprised and seized on by a multitude of furious Fryers, and appointed Souldiers who there drew him into the Fryerie, where he was forced to endure all that which could be expected from the humanitie of those pitifull fathers. Our children are often surprised &amp; stol∣len from vs by publicke violence, to bring them vp in their Cloysters, as many times there remaines nothing to the poore fathers &amp; desolate mothers, but their vn∣profitable teares to haue ingendred them to Idolatry and superstition. It is a common custome now among Friers, to thrust themselues into families and houses to seduce seruants against the will of their master, &amp; chil∣dren in the sight of their fathers, and if they will haue them forsake their houses, they cry out, <HI>Murther, mur∣ther,</HI> as if they had been outraged &amp; set vpon, and find∣ing witnesses enough for their purpose, to depose that which they desire, they follow them in suits of Law, as cryminals, and many times they are very happy if they can be quit and freed of them for a great part of their goods. Others they accuse for speaking ill of their Prince, and so frame informations against them, which they presse with so much malice &amp; violence, that some finding themselues circumuented, &amp; in danger of their liues, doe leaue themselues to be drawne and seduced by them, and so wretchedly to redeeme their crymes with their reuolt and Apostacie, whereof there is as a late remarkeable example neere <HI>Naye le Fineuse,</HI> in one who had the charge of Ancient of that Church. Yea many times they very impudently enter into our Temples du∣ring the time of Sermons, &amp; there very loudly contra∣dict our Pastors to their faces, to the end they may stirr
<PB N="17" REF="13"/>
vp some mutinie, or sow some sedition among them, which hapned at St. <HI>Maixert</HI> verie few moneths since, and it is commonly practised in all parts of <HI>Poictow,</HI> the which it seemes those maleuolent Spirits doe particularie practise, thereby the more to torment them in this man∣ner. These sort of people doe againe goe and besiege the patience and braines of sicke and dying people, purpose∣ly to disturbe their wits and memories, and to engender some scruples in their Consciences, and what testimony soeuer the poore sicke patient giues, that he will receiue his consolation from his owne Pastor: If it fall out that he but once open his mouth, then they are presently vp with their insolent cries which they obstinately continue vntill such time as they see the sicke patient in the last a∣gonies of death. This Death although it be commonly tearmed the last and best remedy of all euils and afficti∣ons, yet it doth not wholly take vs away from their cru∣elty; for they raile vpon our dead bodies, persecu∣ting vs to the very tombe, permit not that we are ac∣companied or conducted, fill our graues when we are making of them, wish and desire that we were deuoured of Dogges, and constraine vs almost euery where to so∣lemnize our Funerals by night. But alas! what will you say, when in our very graues, our bones and dust cannot finde repose? for with vnmercifull and cruell hands they violate our graues, whom very Pagans would e∣steeme as sacred, and finding nothing else but pittifull dust, they are yet so barbarous as to throw it into the winde. The burning of the Temple of <HI>Towrs</HI> began by the vnburying of a dead carkase; and so haue beene vn∣buried the bones of persons of qualitic and Honour as of late <HI>Monsieur de Teligny la Nene,</HI> and very lately of <HI>Monsieur de Saint Fulgents.</HI> Not long since neere vnto <HI>Londun,</HI> as a husband had caused a graue to be made for his dead wife neere vnto the Church-yard, the rage of the Commons was such, as they would not suffer this poore body this last place of repose, but they vnburied it
<PB N="18" REF="14"/>
by night, and exposed and abandoned it to Woolues, which indeede deuoured part thereof, so that when the afflicted Husband began to make researches and exami∣nations of this inhumaine cruelty, he receiued a poore re∣ward for this his pitifull and charitable office, and was in a morning found to be slashed, and slaine.</P>
<P>And let none here belieue, that we speak by Hyperbo∣les, for they are pure and naked truths: the Sunne sees them, we feele them, our Enemies make vs suffer them, and <HI>France</HI> is the cruell Theator whereon are represented such bloudy and mournfull tragedies, and as God beholds them, so it is incompatible to his diuine Iustice that one day he doe not reuenge them.</P>
<P>But here our Enemies will not faile to obiect vnto vs, that although all this be true (as indeed the iustificati∣on thereof is cleare and apparant) yet that they are parti∣cular actions, not auowed, but disproued, and which therefore ought not to cause the infraction of the Edict of Peace, the which as much as possible we can, we ought to endeauour to preserue and maintaine. But this is the ex∣ception of our Enemies, which through their vain euasi∣ons desire to be couered with our complaints, &amp; to haue a law of themselues to condemne them as iniust. But besides that, we go on plainly to iustifie their iniustices, altogether armed with Patents, and publikely authori∣zed, they in vaine endeauour to free and wash themselues of these outrages which are committed on vs by particu∣lar persons, for that they themselues introduce them by their examples, and to embolden them thereto through their impunitie, for wherefore haue they the swords of Magistracy in their hands, but to defend and secure vs from iniuries, and to doe vs right and iustice when we haue receiued them: wherefore doe they contemne all all our complaints and grieuances? whence proceeds it, that hauing presented a full list thereof, which was yet but the abstract and compendium of more important, that we had no iustice done vs vpon any one of them, no
<PB N="19" REF="14"/>
nor so much as vouchsafe to heare or read them: so that who can otherwayes take or consider them, but as the Authors of these cruell indignities we endure and suffer, in that hauing the authority to preuent them, they abso∣lutely refuse to put their hands to it? The Edict of Peace which is giuen vs, is fraudulent and deceitfull, because those who are ordained to make vs obserue them, doe send apparant contrauentions, and permit-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>and suffer them.</P>
<P>But their iniustice stops not, at a simple tolleration of outrages, which we see them doe by their particulars, for they themselues are the first and chiefest which in∣fringe all the clauses of the Edict, which is fit for vs to cleere and iustifie; to the end, that all men being well in∣formed thereof. Detest their disloyaltie and sympathize with vs against the cruell oppression which they make vs suffer.</P>
<P>The Kings Declaration imports, that we shall be re∣established in the free exercise of our Religion, in our Goods, Offices, and Honours, and in a word, all sorts of fauourable and gracious vsage for the Generall, besides that which was couenanted and granted to some parti∣lars, as namely for the Towne of <HI>Rochell,</HI> It is therefore question that we examine or see how all these hath beene performed and executed: As for the free exercise of our Religion, besides that which hath beene formerly ob∣iected and represented of a fearefull number of poore Churches which remaine depriued, and that the Mini∣sters of the State haue scoff'd and mocked when they en∣deauoured to demand their reestablishment, which was granted them by the Edict, besides those which are newly rased and discipated, and in those very places where this exercise doth in some manner yet subsist: we are held in a cruell captiuitie, for there are Fines ordained and also corporall punishments, for those who sing Psalmes in their houses, wherein are contained the prai∣ses of God, whiles the streets regorge with blasphe∣mers,
<PB N="20" REF="15"/>
and resound with obscure and vilanous songs. We are forbidden our Schooles in diuers places, as at <HI>Niort,</HI> and in all <HI>Bearne,</HI> to the end that our Children re∣maine ignorant and without learning and instruction. The Parliament of <HI>Pau</HI> hath decreed and pronounced a sentence against consistories, which shall professe and practise that which is expresly mentioned in our Eccle∣siasticall discipline, to wit, to censure Fathers and Parents which send their children to the Schooles and Colleges of the <HI>Iesuites</HI> to be there by them instructed. Although Fryars which giue their first oath to a Stranger, I meane the Pope, who subiect Kings to him, and who maintaine and defend those paracides which they themselues haue committed; I say, although they are receiued into this Kingdome of all sorts of Nations indifferently; neuerthe∣lesse it being question of our Ministers, of whom calum∣nies hath neuer had the face to impute them the least of these horrours, we are debarred to receiue any who are strangers, and the ancient alliance of this Crowne with the Kingdome of <HI>Scotland,</HI> hath not beene considerable or valable to reobtaine the returne of Master <HI>Prymrose,</HI> in the Church of <HI>Bourdeaux,</HI> where he serued many yeeres with a singular edification, and testimony from our very aduersaries, of a most modest and temperate personage; and others, although naturall <HI>Frenchmen,</HI> are condemned to an vniust and eternall exile, because they were knowne to be excellent instruments to serue God, as <HI>Monsieur d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Moulin,</HI> whose very name was respected and admired of our Aduersaries: and likewise <HI>Monsieur Suffrein,</HI> to hin∣der whose calling backe with some pretext and colour, the most wicked and impudent imposture that could be, as the approbation of the popular esmotion, wherein the President <HI>De Cros</HI> was kill'd. As for those who yet sub∣sist in their Churches, if it be knowne that they are pro∣fitable labourers in Gods Vineyard, then there is nothing vnomitted to expell and banish them, as hath beene seene in deceased <HI>Monsieur de la Chapaliere</HI> and <HI>Monsieur Sal∣bart,</HI>
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
whom to driue and take away from <HI>Rochell,</HI> they left no stone vnremoued, whether in the Towne, or in the Prouinciall or Generall Synods, yea they went so farre therein, as they abused the Kings name, and by a publike letter from his Maiestie addressed to the body of the Towne, to driue them thence: The one and the o∣ther of them being notwithstanding knowne to be ho∣nest men, and being guilty of no other-crime, then of their zeale and affection to the Church of God, and ac∣companied with a rare experience; and for the first of the two, who is now gone to God, we haue drawn those true testimonies from our Enemies after his decease, that he was a rare and singular personage, whom no threat∣nings could shake, no offers how great or frequently rei∣terated could corrupt, whom no dangers could euer make to feare, whom no misfortune could daunt, and who trampling vnder his feet all particular interests, was wholly bent for the conseruation and good of his fiocke: That which causcth them so to praise him after hisdeath, was that which made them hate him, so during his life: but for him, he is now escaped their cruelties; but those who remaine in life, are enforced to lament vnder their tyranny: and it is not lawfull for them to speake or write that which their consciences suggest and dictate to them, betweene vs and our Aduersaries, for the long and miserable captiuity of <HI>Monsieur Constant,</HI> and of <HI>Monsieur Bellot</HI> in the Prisons of <HI>Bourdeaux,</HI> doth but too much de∣pose and confirme it; and besides that, witnesse the per∣sonall adiournments &amp; Decrees for the corporall detenti∣ons granted out against diuers of them for the same cause; among other of <HI>Monsieur de Bransillon,</HI> for hauing answe∣red to the declaration of a wretched Apostate: The Pastor of <HI>Saüne</HI> in <HI>Sauennes</HI> for hauing refuted a calumniating and railing booke, which a Iesuite set forth, and <HI>Monsieur Sauonnet</HI> in <HI>Poictou</HI> for hauing published the Acts of a Conference, which a Capuchin Fryar equally ignorant and impudent had constrained him thereto, who after he
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
had vanquished him shamefully, was yet so audatious as to publish the trophes of an imaginarie victorie. As it is not lawfull for our Minister to speake or write, so it is prohibited to our Printers to publish any Bookes of our Religion. That at <HI>Nismes</HI> he of the Academie suffered a long imprisonment for imprinting an ancient manuscript which was publickly sold in <HI>Paris</HI> of the great pardon of God opposed to that of the Popes, and another Minister in <HI>Poictou</HI> named <HI>Bureau</HI> hath been extreamly check't by the Presidiall Court of <HI>Poictues</HI> for printing the afore∣said dispute of <HI>Monsieur Saromet,</HI> and henceforth they haue made a generall Decree whereby they will exclude and insnare vs by vertue of a Declaration published <HI>Anno</HI> 1625, in the behalfe of an ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>crable Booke compo∣sed by the Iesuites, prohibiting the imprinting of any Booke without being licensed and priuiledged, which is cleerly and absolutly to defend vs from printing or publi∣shing any thing, sith we know well that this approbation and priuiledge will neuer be allowed or granted vs, so as the permission which was formerly yeelded &amp; giuen vs, will remaine void and annihilated, and the Edict which authoriseth it to vs, consequently violated and infringed.</P>
<P>And no lesse it is for our Ecclesiasticall Assemblies, wherein there is an innouation made repugnant and con∣trarie to the Edict, by this yoake which is imposed on vs to receiue Commissioners. For in those assemblies we do not frame, or exhibite any vniust complaint, for feare of being there checked, and reproued, where all things passe religiously and according to Gods Word. But it grieues vs that thereby they will traduce &amp; abuse vs, as if we had any way wronged those venerable assemblies, to make, or introduce Monopolyes. Moreouer, experience hath made vs obserue, that the aymes and intents of our Enemies is hereby to make vs vnusefull, yea preiudiciall through the election of such Commissioners which most commonly we know to be hired &amp; stipended against vs, and who in∣deed place themselues there purposely to offend &amp; abuse
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
vs. For according to their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>antasies &amp; pleasures we must assemble, or seperate our selues, make our consultations long or short, and according to their aduise &amp; relish, eue∣rie point which we treate of, is a question and maxime of estate, although it symbolize no neerer then day to night, and thereupon they rayse their sple<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne &amp; bitternesse. And although in these our affaires and assemblies they should bring but their eares to heare, yet they interpose &amp; vsurp vpon all matters that are proposed or consulted, for to speake their opinions hereof, &amp; to make them as authen∣ticall &amp; valable as if they were the most passionatest Par∣tisans. We haue obserued of many among them, some pernitious spyes to marke out in Rubrikes those who are best affected to the Church of God, to oppose good men, to support wicked, and to intimidate &amp; shake the weaker sort of people, and in fauour of some miserable reward to make them fall off from themselues. To be short, for the heaping vp of oppression in that which concernes our consciences, they will force vs to that which is more bit∣ter and insupportable then death itselfe, and which with abhomination we abhor &amp; detest, as a most expresse and grosse Idolatry, that is to bow our knees before the <HI>Host,</HI> or <HI>Agnu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> dei</HI> of the Roman-priests, I say they will inforce vs thereto, and the decrees thereof haue bin newly dated and published in many places, more particularly at <HI>Diepe,</HI> where there are so great a number of our Religion, that it is impossible they are not often engaged with this fatall meeting. And in this sort they haue performed &amp; execu∣ted the declaration of peace in regard of the chiefe point thereof which concernes the free libertie and exercise of our Religion, they haue not established it in infinite places where it ought to be, they haue expelled and banished it from diuers others where it lawfully subsisted, and if any where they haue left it, it is in the manner, and tearmes as we haue here formerly expressed.</P>
<P>As for the regard of the offices &amp; dignities whereunto we ought to be indifferently admitted with our other
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
Country men and fellow Citizens, it is this which our E∣nemies haue impugned and preuented with all sorts of passion and violence. In many places where those of our contrary Religion make not the tenth person, they haue wholly taken from vs that part and portion which we had in the Consuls Court, as at <HI>Bagnols:</HI> Or if in any place they haue left vs any thing, it hath beene the very least and meanest part, as at <HI>Montelimard.</HI> There hath beene bribery, combination, or corruption employed al∣most euery where, to introduce in the Towne houses or seats of Iustice and Iudicature: those which most maligne vs, and consequently to expell all honest men. Very lately cotrary to the exclude priuiledges of the City of <HI>Nismes,</HI> the Commissioners of the Chamber of <HI>Besiers,</HI> by a De∣cree of their Councell would there assist at the election of the Consuls, to make it fall on people wholly to their deuotion, and because the Baron of <HI>Aubais</HI> who was not of their crue, was there lawfully elected and accepted the Dignitie, they granted out a power to arrest his Body, and most cruelly ransack'd his houses. The order hither∣to inuiolably obserued calling <HI>Monsieur le Coc{que}</HI> Coun∣cellour of the Parliament of <HI>Paris</HI> to enter into the Great Chamber, the doore was shut against him, in hatred of his Religion, and the long seruices of this venerable old man, whose probity and merits are apparantly knowne to all men, could not preuaile with their passion against vs, nor secure him from their outragious Iniustice.</P>
<P>Generally there is seldome granted out any Office whatsoeuer, though it be but of a poore Sergeant to any that is of our Religion, if they doe not first abiure it, or promise those seruices which is required of them, which is, hereafter to betray vs in the midst of our selues; so that <HI>Monsieur de Russan</HI> hauing many yeeres since paid for the Office of <HI>Generall of the Court</HI> of <HI>Aydes</HI> at <HI>Mon∣pellier,</HI> hath not as yet beene receiued, because he will not performe the one, nor promise the other. And now a∣gaine in the Towne of <HI>Rochell</HI> there hauing beene many
<PB N="17" REF="17"/>
Offices and dignities vacant, whom many of the said Towne haue sought to obtaine and purchase; these suits of theirs hath beene in vaine, because they will not play false play to their consciences, in betraying their Coun∣trie, and in this manner it is that the Faith hath beene kept and practised with vs in this regard.</P>
<P>It may be, that being contented to haue bereaued and dispoyled vs of our honours, they will be then more iust to restore vsto our goods, and to secure vs from iniuries, and generally to conserue our Rights in matter of Iustice which was solemnly promised vs. So here it is that some enraged passion hath strangely blinded them, that tram∣pling vnder their feet all manner of diuine and humane Lawes, they haue wretchedly abused the authority which gaue them Lawes, euery way to afflict and oppresse vs. When grounding our selues and Actions on the Edict of Peace, we would question before Iudges, the vniust de∣tainers of our goods, whereof they so violently possessed themselues during the fury of the Warres, and so to de∣mand the Principall which was due to vs, before the ta∣king of Armes, all our Law suites and Processes haue beene reiected or adiudged against the Plaintiffes to their great cost and charges, and our Enemies the Desendants still maintaind in their vsurpation; so that to the Pro∣uince of <HI>Languedoc</HI> alone, is owing more then two milli∣ons of Livres, which is 100000. li. sterling, and to the towne of <HI>Rochell</HI> immense and infinite sums, and it is so far off from restoring vs what is due to vs, as by Acts of palpable iniustice they haue many where's condemned vs to restore those prises which we had taken during the warres, and among others there was a sentence giuen thereon, in the Chamber of the Edict at <HI>Besieres,</HI> against deceased <HI>Mrnsieur de S<SUP>t</SUP> Blancard.</HI></P>
<P>Our processes are iudged by the ticket on the bagges, so that those of a contrary religion boldly sue all manner of actions against vs how vniust so euer, being confident that the contrary Iudge of our Religion will make them gaine their Causes: And so at the Great Councell, The
<PB N="26" REF="18"/>
Earle of <HI>Beanfort</HI> was ouerthrowne in a greatl uite he fol∣lowed against some Communalites, and which imported him the greatest part of his whole Estate, although the equitie and iustice of his cause was perfectly cleere, and that in confirmation thereof he had heretofore obtaind sentence vpon sentence; but notwithstanding, the onely remembrance of troopes of assistance which he conducted into <HI>Montauban,</HI> and his perseuerance and constancy in the true Religion, haue preuailed with his Iudges that his Right was vniust.</P>
<P>But might it please God, that they did not abuse their power but in disployIing vs of our goods, and that their cruelty would at least leaue vs our liberty and liues, that their seats of Iustice were onely Courts established vn∣iustly to grant and giue away our goods to our Enemies, and that they became not scaffolds expresly erected to draw innocent bloud from vs. It is a horror of the bloudy Decrees and Iudgements which euery day they pro∣nounce against vs, and whereby they manifest and de∣monstrate to all the world, that their soules are far redder then their Scarlet gownes. The least fault which any of vs commits is a crime which can neither hope, nor obtaine pardon, and in the whitest innocency it selfe, their hatred makes them finde out lawfull causes to condemne vs. A yong man of <HI>Auignon,</HI> named <HI>William Astier,</HI> for hauing framed and collected some reasons which moued him to abandon the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> was throwne into prison, where with Geeues and fetters he miserably remained two moneths among the greatest criminals, and could not yet obtaine his liberty before he had paid a great sum of money for a fine. Another very lately at <HI>Lyons,</HI> after the miseries of a long imprisonment, receiued sentence in the same Citie, which was confirmed by the Parliament of <HI>Paris,</HI> to goe all the Citie ouer in his shirt, bare footed, with a halter about his necke, and a great burning torch in his hands, for hauing declared to one who proposed and enquired of him If he held the <HI>Pope</HI> to be <HI>Antichrist.</HI> And as euery one knowes that it is one of the Articles of
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
our Faith which we preach in our Sermons, and confirme in our Bookes; so this sentence giuen against him, doth com∣prehend and enwrap vs all in the same condemnation, and ad∣iudgeth vs to the same disgraces and torments. The Court of Parliament of <HI>Tholouse</HI> hath inflamed and armed the Popish Communalties to execute horrible outrages in the Towne of S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Paul-Lamata, Cu{que}</HI> and other pittifull reliques of forepast burnings. All <HI>France</HI> hath conceiued horrour at the fearefull iniustice vsed against an innocent man in the Isle of <HI>Ree,</HI> To whom his Iudge tearmed <HI>Briet</HI> (a name of abominable me∣morie) hauing suborned witnesses to affirme against him, that during the last commotions of <HI>An.</HI> 1622. he had broken and burnt an Image, and therein pronounced sentence of death against him. The Court of Parliament of <HI>Paris</HI> without examining his witnesses, who were easily to be conuicted of falsehood and imposture, without admitting the reproaches which he gaue them which were more then valable, without regarding that if the accusation had beene true, that it was an hostilitie committed during the warre, and which ought to haue beene abolished and buried by the Edict of peace, their passion made them to consent and conforme this vniust sen∣tence, &amp; so to charge their consciences with the bloud of this poore harmelesse childe of God, who constantly expiring his last breath in the middest of fire and flames, confirmd his in∣nocency in this action of his death: and heauen afterwards discouered it, yea this vnfortunate and fatall Image is since found againe, and to this day doth subsist, to accuse the exe∣crable wickednesse of his Accusers and Iudges, which haue lent and held vp their hands to circumuent the whitest &amp; can∣didst innocency that euer was. The fury and iniustice was not lesse but the precipitation far greater, in the person of one na∣med <HI>Roumiou,</HI> who during the wars was Prouost in the Army of the Duke of <HI>Rohan,</HI> who being at <HI>Castres</HI> in May 1626. and one of the Consuls of that Towne, a very vicious man, and wholly sold to our Enemies, comming to him &amp; occasioning him a paltry drunken quarrell, and so outraging and abusing him in the open street, necessity obliging him to put himselfe vpon his defence and resistance, he was presently seiz'd on by
<PB N="32" REF="19"/>
men placed there to the same effect (for it was a premeditated quarrell) imprisoned, &amp; sentence as soone giuen: whereby he was condemned to the Gallies, he threw in his appeale to the Chamber of <HI>Besieres,</HI> but instcad of good Iudges, from whose vertue and integritie his innocency might receiue some assi∣stance, in an Act so outragious as was offred him, he found cruell Tyrants, who cherishing the iniustice of his former Iudges, aggrauated his crime and their sentence, and so pro∣nounced iudgement of death against him, which by an vnpa∣raleld example was the very same houre executed, so that in all he staied not foure and twenty houres in their prisons: it is thevehemency of a strange passion which made them pro∣ceede with such celerity where there was question of a mans life, and it is far opposite and distant from the moderation of those ancient Iudges, which still left thirty dayes between the sentence and execution thereof, to the end that if there were any light breake forth for the innocency of the accused, they would not haue beene sorrowfull to vnderstand it so late, but because they would spare the efusion of bloud, and neuer spill it but with compassion and sorrow, whereas these are insatia∣bly thirsty thereof. And yet we may tearme these Iudges of <HI>Besicres</HI> modest and temperate in regard of that which was perpetrated lately in the Parliament of <HI>Bourdeaux,</HI> against <HI>Monsieur de S<SUP>t</SUP> Germain,</HI> a Gent. of marke and quality, but ex∣treamely hated of them because he was a man of valor &amp; ser∣uice; the Baron of <HI>Montendre</HI> who had a quarell against him, and who greatly fea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'d his generosity &amp; courage, iudged the passion of this Parliament, to be a very fit instrument for the execution of his, and so to free him of this formidable enemy; to which end he seduced a wretched Priest to become Plain∣tife a gainst the said <HI>Monsieur de S<SUP>t</SUP> Germain,</HI> &amp; so accused him for robbing of his Church, whose witnesses were not diffi∣cult to be found out, because it wasagainst one of our religion; so the informations were framed and dressed against him, but with an absolute vnheard of silence, and they are put into the hands of a Prouost, expresly chosen for such a one which was requisite for such an execution; who watching his time, sur∣pris'd this braueGentlemā when he least thought or dream'd
<PB N="33" REF="19"/>
thereof, &amp; speedily led him to <HI>Bourdeaux,</HI> where that Par∣liamēt being extraordinarily assembled, without hearing any of his iust alegations and answers, presently held him guilty, &amp; pronoūced sentence of death against him, so as in lesse then 8 hours this Iudgement was giuen, &amp; executed.</P>
<P>These are the hands which now dispose soueraignly of our liues, and thus is our Religion turned &amp; imputed to crime, and the faith which was giuen vs by the Edict of peace to lures &amp; snares, the more easily to draw vs to the scaffolds, the which we haue not ceased to oregore &amp; de∣staine with our innocent blood, euer since that vpon the assurance of this peace we put down our armes; and the number is infinite which are daily hunted after for fore∣past actions, so that within the extent and iurisdiction of the Parliament of <HI>Thoulouse,</HI> there are 2000 of vs decreed and commanded to be apprehended for the like causes, and there is nothing but flight can warrant them from the bloody hands of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>se cruell Tyrants.</P>
<P>We assure our selues there are none except they are more then barbarous, who hauing considered all this, are not touched in hart with pitie &amp; compassion towards vs, and that he will not approue our wrongs to be immense, and infinit, because notwithstanding all these most sacred and inuiolable promises which were made vs, we are still tyranized in our consciences, oppressed in our honors, ru∣ined in our goods, &amp; our liues continually exposed to the swords of those, who hauing them in their hands to doe Iustice, doe abuse them in the execution of their hatred against vs.</P>
<P>But it may be we would yet support all these outrages and persecutions more patiently, if as they are committed against some particulars now here &amp; anone there, that the generaltie could promise themselues some repose &amp; tran∣quilitie; In this case those to whom it falls out to suffer, must yet glorifie God in their sufferances, &amp; still imbrace and indure them with consolation, seeing that the rest of Gods children, doe at least yet subsist though in I know not what poore estate &amp; condition. But our greatest griefe and miserie is, That we apparantly perceiue, that the de∣signes
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
of our Enemies are wholy bent to root vs out, as also our Religion, &amp; so to giue the last blow to our ruine, what sugred words soeuer they employ to perswade and make vs beleeue the contrarie.</P>
<P>The iustification whereof is cleere and euident, by the breach of 2 Articles, which doth not simply touch the in∣trest of some particulars, but which concernes our gene∣rall subsistance. The first regards the holding, &amp; obseruing of our politike assemblies, being deuided &amp; spread as wee are in a Kingdome, whereof euerie one knows, the great∣nesse and extent, and being to liue among people who are animated against vs with ragefull furie, we shall but liue there exposed to these their iniuries, &amp; comming to mas∣sacre vs one after another in our houses, we may almost al perish before we haue knowledge thereof, or onely haue the meanes to haue recourse to the iustice of our Prince to implore his protection. One of the remedies of this our euil is, our mutual correspondence, &amp; communication one with the other, and indeed our king knowing the necessi∣tie hereof, thought it fit &amp; requisit, and therefore gaue vs expresse commission by their Edicts to assemble at least euerie 3 yeeres to consult of our common affaires, and to compile all our grieuances together, to the end to bring and prostrate them to their feet, &amp; in their iustice to find the Palladium and sanctuarie of our safetie, according whereunto it was expresly promised so the last peace, that we should haue a Pattent deliuered vs to make our assemblies, the which if it had bin performed, &amp; his M<SUP>tes</SUP> ears open to our complaints &amp; grieuances, without doubt he would haue taken pitie of the cries &amp; tears of so many thousands of his poore subiects, &amp; according to his roiall goodnes in prouiding for our wrongs, they had preuerted the calamities and miseries vnder whom <HI>Fraunce</HI> now breaths &amp; sighs. But our Enemies haue so powrfully pre∣uailed, that this promise hath bin violated to vs as well as all others, and our 2 whole yeeres patience improfitably imployed to make remonstrance thereof, hath produced vs no other fruit, but to make vs comprehend by their obstinate denials, that they intend to depriue vs of all
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
meanes to confer together for our common subsistance, thereby to worke more commodiously and surely to our ruine, as to beat downe and destroy a body, first to cut all the sinews which linck'd the members one to another.</P>
<P>The same designe to ruine vs doth furthermore plainly appear, &amp; remaines perfectly verified by the proceedings they haue obserued &amp; held to bereaue vs of those Towns and places which the Edict granted and gaue vs in euerie Prouince to assure our liues. Experience had made vs see that what Edicts soeuer our Kings could publish in our fauour, they were not bars stong enough against the furie of the people. At the first seditious Sermon (and Fryers make none others) the fire of a popular emotion wasligh∣ted, and the kniues in the hand of an enraged multitude which came to seeke vs in our beds to cut our throats, which is no lesse then all the whole world knows, &amp; that there haue bin infinite numbers of Gods children which haue felt &amp; made triall of these more then barbarous hor∣rours, within that the publike faith, the respect of Laws, and the authority of the Prince, was powerfull enough to secure vs from them, &amp; after, to oppose some more pow∣erfull remedy. Our Kings themselues haue assigned vs places to serue vs for refuge, if any should seeke to assaile or destroy vs, as formerly they had done, &amp; haue ordain∣ed that the guard &amp; keeping thereof should be wholy gi∣ued and committed to vs, euen so they haue remained in our hands not as hostages of the faith of our Princes, who haue neuer doubted of our fidelities, but as pawnes and pledges that our Enemies should containe themselues in their duties. And we kept them not, against those of whose grace we receiued &amp; held them, but against their rebellious subiects, which would presume to violate and infringe their Edicts, yea &amp; masacre vs, against the decla∣ration of their will. And this properly is the nature of these townes which for this regard haue bin names of se∣curitie &amp; assurance, of which whiles we haue bin the pos∣sessors &amp; depositors, the insolencie of the people hath bin retain'd &amp; restrain'd, and in stead of wars &amp; combustions
<PB N="36" REF="21"/>
wherewith this Kingdome hath bin long &amp; miserably af∣flicted, &amp; which made her the true theater of miserie, we haue seen her ascend to the height of all felicity &amp; glorie.</P>
<P>And it cannot be said, but that the K. hath bin truly and perfectly obeyd of vs, &amp; that the gates thereof were open at all times he pleased to enter, as indeed he was receiued into most part of them with ioy and acclamations, when he past by <HI>Saumur</HI> to his mariage, &amp; had euer bin so since, if wicked counsellors had not abused (our respects &amp; obe∣diences, and had not made vs know by many deplorable experiences) that they contriued &amp; fashioned the snares of our ruine, &amp; to draw vs from forth these places, not that the K. should be better serued, for that was impossible, but because they would find meanes to violate his Edicts with impunitie.</P>
<P>But how they haue borne themselues to bereaue vs of them, is that which it imports euery one to know, &amp; the which we will fetch from its head fountaine &amp; originall. First they would haue enterprised it by force of Armes, whereof they layd the foundations a little after the death of <HI>He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y</HI> the great of happy memorie, by the innouation which they decreed &amp; resolued to doe in <HI>Bearne,</HI> in diuer∣ting the reuenews which the deceased Q. of <HI>Nauarre</HI> and the Estates of that Country had assigned for the mainte∣nance of Ministers &amp; Colledges, and in employing them to furnish the pride of some Bishops, and the insatiable couetousnes of the Iesuits. They belieued that, that poore people would vnderstand this with griefe, as also that thereupon we would presently run to armes. But our mo∣deration deceiued them, so that we contented our selues from time to make our humble complaints and remon∣strances to his M<SUP>tie</SUP>, and the wisest of his Councell held along time these matters in suspence. The other neuerthe∣lesse push'd stil obstinatly to their former designs, &amp; after hauing obliged the assembly of <HI>Loudoun</HI> to seperate them selues in <HI>An.</HI> 1619, through hope that for 6 months after there should be no innouation in this businesse, &amp; y<SUP>t</SUP> in the interim they would consider y<SUP>e</SUP> reasons of these of <HI>Bearne,</HI>
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
long before that time was expired, they led away the King into <HI>Guyene,</HI> and then goe suddainely thundring on these poore people, where by violence they pass'd in the Par∣liament of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>an, that which formerly they had resolued and concluded; ransaking this Country with strange hostilities, cruelly beat and outraged those who could not saue themselues by flight, defiling with indignity the Temples where they were accustomed to pray vnto God, and to preach his holy Gospell, thereby to hold this miserable Country in eternall seruitude and slauery, filling all places with Garrisons, and hauing drawne the Lord of <HI>Sales</HI> out of the Towne of <HI>Navarrins,</HI> through a thousand oathes that they would leaue him the gouernment thereof, of which when they were be∣come masters, for his good seruice they payd him with scoffes and laughtres, and laugh'd at his credulity.</P>
<P>They had not so well begun, not to pursue the point of their good fortune: the Deputies of the Assembly of <HI>Loudun</HI> repaire to <HI>Rochell,</HI> at the first brute and newes of these outrages, according to the right which had beene expressely giuen them before their last separa∣tion, and there prepar'd themselues to goe againe and present their humble supplications to his Maiestie, but this is imputed to them for crime, and they haue order to disperse and deuide themselues; and because they would persist in their remonstrances, they are there held as encrimed, our enemies armed against vs, who then thought to persorme that in the middest of our other Churches, which they came from doing and exploi∣ting in <HI>Bearne,</HI> as if nothing could hold out before them, or withstand them.</P>
<P>For hauing taken <HI>Saumur</HI> by the same lure which they had <HI>Navarrins,</HI> they is by oathes presently viola∣ted, and corrupted the Gouernours of many other places, which they rendred vnto them without striking stroke, obliged others to receiue compositions, the which they as soone infringed, as at St. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ohn,</HI> and <HI>Cle∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ae,</HI>
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
they then came to <HI>Montauban,</HI> which serued as a barre to their entryes, and the yeere after, which was <HI>Anno</HI> 1622. they assailed <HI>Montpellier,</HI> where they found so vigorous resistance, that they lost all hope of becomming masters thereof, whiles <HI>Rochell</HI> for her part acted wonders at Sea, and defended her selfe so well by Land, that those before it did nothing else but con∣sume themselues.</P>
<P>But for all this they were not daunted or discouraged, and knowing that their first designe to vanquish vs by Armes, no way succeeded to their desires, they spinne a contrary threed, and clewe, and so resolue to ouer∣throw vs by a Treatie, sith they could not doe it by force: to which effect, they propose and seeke with all variety of Art and policy, and doe so industriously and obsequiously comply with the Duke of <HI>Rohan,</HI> that he suffers him selfe to be inchanted, and lull'd a sleepe with their flattering promises, who not able to perswade hims<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lfe that they could so wickedly and perfidiously breake his Maiesties word as they did, he concluded to peace with them on these conditions among others:</P>
<P>That his Maiestie entering into <HI>Montpellier,</HI> should make no change or innouation, that <HI>Marans</HI> should be rendred vp vnto vs, and that the Fort built a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ioyning to <HI>Rochell,</HI> should be demolished; and for the other places, which as then wee held and enioyed, there should no alterations at all be made.</P>
<P>Here then are our enemies drawne out of some rubs and dangers, by the onely meanes of this Treatie, but yet they haue not fallen from their first intents. The Cittie of <HI>Montpellier</HI> hauing opened her gates to the King, gaue him to braue a reception and entrance, as she thought she had thereby giuen him an eternall confi∣dence of her sidelity: but the recompence she receiued, was the Garrison which was left there against the pub∣licke faith, so solemnly sworne, with instructions to the Commanders and Officers, so to afflict the Inhabi∣tants,
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
that they themselues should be constrained there∣by to demaund that which all other people naturally detest and abhorre, that is to say, to be subjected to the tyrannous Yoke of a Cittadell, according to which or∣der, the houses of the chiefest, and most eminent, are stuffed vp and oppressed with Souldiers which eate them out, who spoile their Vines, desolate their fields, quarrell with all, assaile the honour and chastity of their wiues and daughters. Some in regard of these iniuries, consent to make this demand, and some three or foure score present the request of our Supplication: this (as they say) is not to preiudice the right of the rest of the Towne, nor to the remarkable interest which all our other Churches had therein; neuerthelesse this great tumultuous Garrison would not fayle to take them at their words: so the foundations of this Cittadell were presently laid, and in a short time brought to perfe∣ction, and then it was that with all sorts of licenciousnes, they began to grate and afflict this poore Cittie, farre more then before, all her priuiledges are annihilated, the Inhabitants disarmed to their very kniues: the chie∣fest Cittie-Virgins are snatch away from their fathers and mothers, to marry them to some vagabond Soul∣diers of a contrary Religion, many are compeld to Apo∣stasie, and in a word, once this rich Cittie, now this poore people, are made slaues to an vnheard of, and matchlesse tyranny. In, and in this manner they assured themselues of <HI>Montpellier.</HI></P>
<P>As for <HI>Marans,</HI> when the restitution thereof was pressed, it was found in the warrant which they had caused to be dispatched and expedited, that they had committed a notable imposture: for instead of that which they had shewed to the Duke of <HI>Rohan,</HI> and whence the peace was concluded, they had absolute∣ly promised, that this Towne should be restored into the hands and keeping of his first Gouernour, but in this last, they adioyned an Alternatiue, which destroyed the
<PB N="36" REF="23"/>
precedent proposition, to wit, <HI>Or recompence shall bee giuen him,</HI> whereby they euaded and eluded our de∣maund.</P>
<P>But all these are yet but small matters. As <HI>Rochell</HI> was the place which most of all crossed their designes, considering that in regard of second causes, she is as one of the Axell Trees of our Subsistance: It was to become Masters thereof, that the first and chiefest intents haue these many yeeres aymed, but not being able to pro∣cure and compasse it by Armes, not to reduce and bring them to the point of confidence, which proued so mournfull and miserable to <HI>Montpellier,</HI> to wit, to open their Gates, they attempted another way which they iudged lesse chargeable and more easie, and peraduen∣ture which might more fortunately succeed, then all that which they had formerly done during the time of Warres; there was a Fort began to be built before this Towne, which by this peace was to bee demolished, as by an expresse warrant to that effect was sent and expe∣dited as we haue formerly said: But how solemne so∣euer this promise was, they resolued not to hold or per∣forme it; and so to operate and worke by meanes of this Fort in time of peace, that which they could not haue to effect during the Warres: And as this Towne cannot subsist but by the meanes of comerce and trade: so they already preiudged that the subsistance of the said Fort, would infallibly wholy depriue and take it from them; there being no great hope or apparance that Merchants would frequent a place so neere to danger, much lesse hazard or entrust their goods: Besides, this Fort being so neere to their Towne, it might facilitate their Enemies Intelligence, and chalke out a way to sur∣prise: And put the worst, if they were inforced to come to Armes, they had therein a strong and powerfull Arcenallready to their h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nds, and therein all sorts of prepara<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>iues for a Siege. The Rochellers who careful∣ly saue these consequences, and likewise foresawe how
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
ruinous they might bee vnto them: dispatched their Deputies to the King at the very instant of the accepta∣tion of the peace, aswell to tender him their Submissions, as to procure necessary warrants for the demolition of the Fort: These Deputies find the King at <HI>Lyons,</HI> of whom they are fauourably receiued, and obtaine of his Councell as many good words and papers as they can desire: returning thus with Letters to Monsieur <HI>Ar∣naud</HI> (which commanded the Fort) which enjoyned him speedily to free the same, and to suffer it to bee demol∣lished. But he who had already the watch-word giuen him, mocked at all these their dispatches and expediti∣ons, and told them plainely, he knew the Kings inten∣tions better then they all: and so fortifying, in stead of demollishing, spared neither cost, labour, or diligence, to aduance his worke. The others haue speedy recourse to their complaints, and resound very loud the indignity and disobedience offered them, to the end they should not fly out, before the Fort were brought to perfection: they are entertaynd with good hopes, and promised they shall haue Commissioners sent them, to see if they haue performed and satisfied that which they neuer enioyed by the Declaration, and that they vpon notice thereof would giue them all content. Whiles these Commissioners adde delay to delay, and purposely tra∣uell towards <HI>Rochell</HI> by very small journeyes, the Fort is finished, and furnished with abondance of Ord∣nance, and with all sorts of prouisions of Warre and Victuals: guarded by a mighty Garrison, and with a most exact vigilancy and care: in a word, in that Estate of power, no longer to feare <HI>Rochell,</HI> but to make <HI>Rochell</HI> feare them. And then it was that arri∣ued these long expected Commissioners: who finding nothing to question or contradict with obedience wher∣unto the Towne was obliged to the King, they without giuing them any contentment, went to finish their Com∣mission in the Isle of <HI>Ree;</HI> by committing strange out∣rages
<PB N="38" REF="24"/>
and afflictions on that poore people, and by ma∣king exact and curious researches of all that had passed during the Warre. The Rochellers seeing themselues so grosely mocked and abused, doe not omit▪ neuerthe∣lesse to reiterate their complaints to the King, with such sence and passion, that hee being touched therewith, giues them againe good words: but those of whom the performance and execurion thereof depended, haue con∣trary intents and designes: so that whiles those busily pursue their complaints, these are incessantly conspiring and plotting of many Enterprises vpon the Towne. Particularly of one mannaged by a certaine fellow na∣med <HI>Courselles,</HI> who being on the very point to execute it, it pleased God so well to detect it, that the vnder∣taker thereof was taken; and others with whom he had conspired, conuicted hereof. Whereup on the Deputies of <HI>Rochell</HI> are againe in Court to demaund Iustice: but they were flatly refused, and told they were too im∣portunate in their complaints, which if they continued, they should be imputed to no lesse then crime, yea they proceeded too recriminatious; and told them that they were a mutinous and factious people. A deplorable condition of a Patient, who is forbidden to consolidate his sicknesse by his complaints and sorrowes.</P>
<P>All these proceedings cleerely demonstrate, what the designe of our Enemies was against this poore Towne: But their impatience finding all these delayes and cour∣ses too long, they againe resolue to make triall of their Armes: so they proued great and powerfull prepara∣tions by Land: but chiefely they rigge and make ready a strange Fleet at <HI>Blauet,</HI> purposely at vnawares to thunder vpon this poore Towne, which they hope can∣not escape them. Which conioyned with the other breaches of the peace euery where committed, obliged the Duke of <HI>Rohan,</HI> by whom it had beene treated and conducted to aduise of the meanes to diuert this great storme, which threatned speedily to befall our Churches:
<PB N="49" REF="24"/>
and aboue all to preuent that this Towne, which so much imports vs, were not taken from vs; who beleeued that there was no better, expedient, nor truer remedy, then to take from our Enemies the meanes which they had de∣stined to ruine vs. So Monsi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ur <HI>Soubize</HI> went and possessed himselfe of those Ships which were preparing against vs at <HI>Blauct;</HI> and came to the Isle of <HI>Ree</HI> to free them from the yoake which the aforesaid <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> had subjected them to, and after to assay to deli∣uer <HI>Rochell</HI> from this Fort which so much oppr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ssed it.</P>
<P>Our Enemies seeing their designe so preuented, and gone retrograde, they make Heauen and Earth refound with their complaints, as the disturbers of the publique peace. It is a crime to vs not to suffer our selues to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e ruined: and to preuent the blowe which was in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ended totally to ouerthrow vs. Euery where they d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>file vs with blacke calumnies, as if wee were the greatest Traitors of the world; so that through their artificiall insinuations, his most Excellent Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie of Great <HI>Brittaine,</HI> and my Lords the States, that without vs they were ready to ioy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e their Armes with theirs against the Common Enemy, and vnder pretence to haue againe re∣sumed that designe, they draw Ships from them, but employ them against vs: so as presently there was a new face on our affaires, hauing to doe with such powerfull Enemies: and the griefe hereof was the more sensible to vs, to see that our destruction approached by those, from whom we ought to haue expected all ayde and assistance.</P>
<P>And yet our enemies saw, they could not so soone arriue to the point and period of their pretences: for al∣though <HI>Rochell</HI> had receiued a checke, yet she wanted neither courage, men, or prouisions. The Duke of <HI>Rohan</HI> cut out businesse in other places, and what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rt or policy soeuer was vsed, there was no meares to seuer <HI>Montauban,</HI> and the other Communalties from the generall cause. Moreouer the King of Great <HI>Britaine,</HI>
<PB N="40" REF="25"/>
and the Lords the States, seeing how they were deluded and surprised, would no longer permit the stay of their ships against vs, which were the true motiues that made our Enemies become more flexible, to the Ouertures of accommodating and aduancing the peace made by the Ambassadours of the said King, and the Lords the States: But yet wee must not belecue that they had changed their maximes, or left off their designes, to depriue vs of <HI>Rochell,</HI> and all other places which remai∣ned, on any tearmes or rates whatsoeuer.</P>
<P>And indeed their actions and deportments since the peace, hath manifestly declared it to vs. The peace was no sooner concluded, but they enforced the Lord of <HI>Mont∣auban</HI> to depart with, and leaue his house of <HI>Meouillon,</HI> which were the inheritance of his Ancestors, because the scituation thereof being strange, it might serue as a retreat to the poore neighbouring Protestants. Since the death of the late Constable, the Marshall of <HI>Crequy</HI> hath expeld all those of the Religion from the Gouern∣ments which he held in <HI>Daulphiné;</HI> So as all the Chur∣ches of this Prouince doe now remaine without shelter or protection, and exposed to all the stormes of persecu∣tion; and there is Scarce a Towne which remaines in our hands, of any esteeme or consideration, but since the wee peace, can iustifie they haue made many designes and enterprises thereon.</P>
<P>But aboue all, there hath beene an obstinate perseue∣ration in their resolution against <HI>Rocheil,</HI> and they are so farre from demolishing the Fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t (as we haue formerly iustified) which they promised to the Ambassadours, that they haue newly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ged and fortified it, and there those haue had refuge, who either attempted to be∣tray it in the time of warre, or to surprize it in the time of peace. There is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wonderfull, yea a formidable Maga∣zin of all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for a siedge laid afore it the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> redo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d, who bear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> themselues <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gious, haue denoted
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
all the remainders, left by the last warres, and yet insolently threaten very shortly to doe worse.</P>
<P>Moreouer, all the little Townes, and Hamblets about <HI>Rochell,</HI> which by expresse Articles giuen likewise in writing to the Ambassadors, were to be discharged of Garisōs, is it yet so farre from being performed, as contrariwise they present∣ly fild them vp with new supplyes, which being placed &amp; dis∣persed neere the Towne, could in one night be there, either for a surprise, or the aduancing of a Si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ge: and yet they ex∣tremely afflict those with whom they are billi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed, and enforce them to take passeports from them, as if it were in the midst of warre, putting I axes and jmpositions on their goods: spoyling their Vines and Harucst, and keeping these poore people as prisoners in their owne houses.</P>
<P>But it is nothing for them to shut vs vp by Land, if they doe not the like by Sea: so as judgei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>g the Isle of <HI>Ree</HI> very commodious for their purpose, although they g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ue their words there should be no innouation or change: yet they send Mounsieur <HI>de Thorax</HI> to build a strong Fort there: which hauing performed, and with the very goods of the Rochel∣lers that they had in that Island, wereof he violently possessest himselfe, although by an expres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e Article of the Declaration they were to restore it: then he began to play the part of a Soueraigne, compelling all Ships which departed forth the Riuer, to attend his pleasure and permission: stayed others who would enter; but especially if they were loaden with any prouisions or victuals: and in a word, dealt with them, as if warre had beene proclaimed.</P>
<P>Hauing thus aduanced their affaires by Sea and Land without they presently after carry their malice into the very bowels of the Towne, by abusing (in aduenturing to lose it) the sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>red respect which it beares to his Maiestie in the person of his Offi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ers: He had so wrought, that his Maiestie should send Commissioners for the execution of the Peace, and accordingly they were receiued with all sorts of respect and honour: but at their very entrance they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lye at <HI>Monopo∣lyes;</HI> and there being then some grudge and diffrence be∣twixt
<PB N="42" REF="26"/>
the body of the Towne, and the other Inhabitant for some point of order and gouernment among them, they set fire to this deuision, animating the one part against the other: yet both to betray each other, to the end to ruine them all by this their proper diuisions. There was obserued a particular intelligence betweene them and the Fort, and e∣uery day they held secret conferences in their Lodgings, whereat there were none but were either knowne or sus∣pected to wish ill to the Towne: and for the full conuiction hereof, one of them was surprised as hee would haue c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r∣rupted a Townesman, who had the Office to search all Ships that came into the Harbour, and so to stop his mouth that way. And briefely, whereas their Commission might haue beene ended in two dayes: they obstinately remained in the Towne, vntill the arriuall of the warre sent them away. So because they stayed there so long without businesse, without doubt it is a strong presumption, they were sent thither to sowe some Treasons, and to introduce within the Towne, the meanes of her ruine, whiles others laboured powerfully with∣out, likewise to effect it.</P>
<P>The last blow of their pernitious designes, before we who∣ly take off the Maske, and so come to the last effects of vio∣lence, was a generall defence to transport any Corne by Sea: yea, not only to forraigne Countries, but from one harbour, to another in <HI>France:</HI> and this defence was set on foote, when <HI>France</HI> abounded and regorged with Corne: so as many who discouered not the true intent hereof, wondered to heare it published: and di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ers who had great store of Corne on their hands to traffique abroad, as accustomed, extremely murmured thereat.</P>
<P>But the true end and ayme thereof was, to preuent that <HI>Rochell</HI> should not victuall it selfe, and when they pleased to besiege it, that they might with more facility quell her by famine.</P>
<P>We doubt not but those who will please to reflect and cast their eyes vpon this Table, whereon we chalke out our griefes and wrongs, will not find it very pleasing, but that it will
<PB N="43" REF="26"/>
offend and wearie their sight, to fixe them so long vpon such distastfull and sorrowfull obiects of iniustices, di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oyalties, outrages, ransackings, oppresing of so many Townes, and of so many thousands of people, with the seuerall designes, gene∣rally to roote them out, and for euer to exterminate them. But yet we assure them, that we haue not here inserted the thousandth part of our miseries: for whosoeuer would fully and punctually represent them, his paper must be as great as <HI>France,</HI> and he must resolue to write many Volumes. It sufficeth by this small part, to iudge of the whole piece: for by this clawe they may sufficiently know these Lyons, and see into what extremitie and gulfe of miseries, they haue re∣duced vs: For in a word, they haue robd vs of our goods, wronged vs in our Honours, spilt our blood, and not spared our Tombes after our death; and all this in detestation of our Religion, the memory whereof eternally to abolish: there is no violence, but they haue imployed: no cruelty, but they haue practised: nor no faith or promise, but they haue in∣fringed and delacerated, especially of the last peace, whereof they haue wilfully broken all the Clauses and Articles, and during the time thereof, haue publiquely sought our vtter ruine and destruction.</P>
<P>To remedy all these our miseries, wee haue continually haunted: yea I may say, beseiged the Gates of our Prince his Palace, and lifted vp our voyces, thereby endeauoring to make him vnderstand our grieuances: but particularly <HI>Rochell</HI> hath still had their Deputies prostrate at his Maie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ies feete; to beseech him to shew them some good effects of his Royall promise. But we haue found deafe eares to our requests, or else taken vp &amp; preoccupated, with all that which the foulest villany of our Enemies hath beene accustomed slanderously to vomit sorth against vs: so that we haue bin sent back with reproach and judig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie, and taken from vs all hope to doe vs right and justice: yea the more we haue com∣plained of our slauery, the more we haue found them to in∣crease and aggrauate it, that now this remedy hath increased the sicknesse of our misery. And as for <HI>Rochell,</HI> as her oppres∣sion
<PB N="44" REF="27"/>
was greatest, so were her complaints, and also more frequent, till they were peremptor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ly defended to exhibite any more; and told openly that they should no longer ex∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the demolition of the Fort.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this indeed was to bee reduced to the last point of extremity, sith our Enemies lest vs not that which is com∣monly giuen to those who are mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t miserable, (to wit) <HI>Hope.</HI> Whereon, who will not presently judge, that finding nothing but dispaire of that side, nothing but all sorts of d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ialty and pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nesse, and an obstina<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> resolution to ruine vs; That the care which euery one naturally ought to haue of his pro∣per conseruation, oblieged vs to seeke out for other reme∣dies? And where should we else finde them, but in hauing our recourse to those, which were despositors and pledges to vs of the peace, which was so ill kept and obserued to vs? and if any one doubt of the right or equity we haue in this our resolution, hee will therein shew himselfe, either abso∣lutely ignorant, or wholy mal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ous.</P>
<P>For who but knowes, that when hee that is oblieged, comes to faile of his promise, that then the partie interested, hath his lawfull recourse to the Suretie, and consequently <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ust cause to call on him? for this, nature informes vs; all lawes teach vs; and daily experience in the practice of all<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>people confirm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s to vs.</P>
<P>Because therefore that the peace was giuen vs; by the meanes and mediation of the King of great <HI>Britaine,</HI> and of the Lords the States, and that they consented to giue vs as∣surance for the obseruation thereof, who sees not, that wee haue all right at the breach and contrauention thereof, to ad∣dresse our selues to them, and to seeke their refuge? And surely the difficultie was not in the right and equitie, but in the meanes to be able to doe it, especially in a publike way, the cap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tie wherein we were held being súch, that the first who had dared to haue made this proposition, had in∣fallibly<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> lost his head for the same: whereof we need no other pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> or testimonie, then that which happened in the same Towne of <HI>Rochell,</HI> where an Inhabitantnamed, <HI>La Uigne,</HI>
<PB N="45" REF="27"/>
hauing beene long suspected to haue receiued a Commission from the King of <HI>England,</HI> he was thereon imprisoned, and condemned to dye. Such was the power and authoritie of the Commissioners.</P>
<P>There remaines then one onely way, which is, That the Duke of <HI>Rohan,</HI> who in quality of chiefe Generall of our Churches, had dealt in former occasions, and who interue∣ned in the two Treaties of peace, would take on him this care. Indeed the zeale which he hath euer borne to the good of our Churches, hauing opened his eyes to see the extreme perill wherein they were, and giuen him courage enough, (notwithstanding the great dangers which threaten vs) to aduertise the King of Great <HI>Britaine</HI> thereof, God hath so singularly fauoured his good intents, giuen such an efficacy and power to his requests, and to those of Monsieur <HI>de Soubize</HI> his brother, fortified with those of many honest men, (of all conditions) of our Churches, that the heart of this great King hath beene touched with compassion and pitie of our wrongs, to employ his power, to desingage to vs his Royall faith.</P>
<P>Sith then it is for that which he is now armed, to consult if we should accept of his good will, were properly to dis∣pute, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> a sicke patient that is dying, should open the doore to a Physicion who comes to cure him; or if a poore man who is nere drowning, should refuse to take the hand of him which extends it to him, to drawe him out of the water, wherein he is panting, and neere dying. So the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ice being absolute, the necessitie extreme, and in this necessitie and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tice, the occasion so fauourable; what remaines for vs to doe, but af∣ter our most humble thankefulness and prayers to God the Author of all blessings, likewise to addresse and offer vp our humble thankes to the King of Great <HI>Brit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne,</HI> for so fit and timely assistance, (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> say) to giue a full approbation to his Armes, as raised in our fauour, to ioyne our selues to him with all our powers and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>orces, with a most humble suppli∣cation to his Maiestie, that hee will please to continue vs the effects of his Royall protection, vntill the obstinacy of our
<PB N="46" REF="28"/>
Enemies be vanquished, and that they suffer vs to approach the sacred person of the most Christian King our Prince, to obtaine of his Iustice the accomplishing of his Edicts, and the reparation and domage of the breaches which haue beene of∣fred vs, since the decease of <HI>Henry</HI> the Great, of happy and glorious memory?</P>
<P>Here doubtlesse our enemies will make tragicall exclama∣tions, to defame our proceedings, and maliciously to impute vnto vs the want of affection towards our Countrie, in ioy∣ning our Armes with Strangers: But let them iustly impute the blame hereof to themselues, because they in their con∣sciences know, that it is their cruell and obstinate oppression, which hath imposed on vs this necessitie; and therefore what∣soeuer the euents thereof be, they are their owne proper workes, not ours. But contrariwise, with what face dare they enterprise or taxe vs vpon this point, sith they haue commit∣ted those things which are still recent and fresh in our memo∣ries? Doe they beleeue that we haue forgotten their enraged furies during the <HI>League,</HI> when to defend our liues &amp; Religi∣on, we accepted ayde &amp; assistance from <HI>England?</HI> Haue we defaced the Armes of our Prince, and contemned his obe∣dience as they then did? Haue we rendred vp any one Town, as they then deliuered to the Spaniard, all those whereon they could become masters, and among others the Capitall Citic? Haue wee laid hands vpon the sacred person of our Prince, as they wickedly and damnably haue done? What resemblance is there in a defence drawne from necessitie as is ours, (alwayes in subiection, and still ready to returne to dutie) with their audacious reuolt; so long, so obstinate, so pernicious: hauing not the least pretext to charge vs of the least outrage in their persons, of the least disgrace in their honours, of the least extortion in their goods, or of the least force in their consciences, and who alleadge for their only griese and complaint, that the Prince, who became then weary of killing, was more mercifull then they would haue him, in spilling of our blood, sith from thence they haue deriued their Law to vse surious resolutions, which all men haue be∣held
<PB N="47" REF="28"/>
and seene? Are they not impudently ashamed to ac∣cuse our moate, hauing such great beames in their eyes, and to calumniat our innocency, being guilty of the same crimes?</P>
<P>Heere therefore let shame and confusion stop their mouthes, to the end that we may open ours in the true pro∣testations which we make of our innocency, and of <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he in∣uiolable fide<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y (whatsoeuer be said of vs) which wee will obserue, and beare to the King our Soueraigne; being wounded in heart (through the violence of his bad <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ruants) to be reduced to doe any thing which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him, and are all of vs ready to cast our selues at his feete, to demaund his fauour, when he will please to receiue vs, and to secure vs from their cruelties.</P>
<P>Or if there be any faithfull Seruant neere his Person; we pray him to serue vs as an Eccho, that we may make him vn∣derstand by his mouth, how false &amp; slāderous those impressi∣ons are, which cont<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ariwise are giuen to him of vs: and that in effect, after our obedience due vnto God, we breath, no∣thing but his seruice, and (our Religion set apart) will there∣in euer be ready to sacrifice our liues.</P>
<P>Wherefore wee humbly beseech him, to spare our liues, and in stead of pursui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>g vs by the violence of his Armes, that he will once seriously commaund, that we may be better vsed hereafter, then heretofore.</P>
<P>The more powerfully to induce him hereby, and so by this meanes, to perswade him to regiue a good and perdura∣ble Peace to his Subjects: hee shall doe well, to draw the picture of the desolations of his Estate, to make him see therein so great a delug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of blood sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, which properly, and truely is his: because it is that of his people: So much trea∣sure exhausted, I meane the sweat and the substance of the Artificer, and of the poore labouring Country man, who al∣ready starue with hunger: So many houses beaten downe and dimolished, whereof (to speake truth) it is he that suffe∣reth the decayes and ruincs, for that he is Lord in Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>. So many ransakings and outrages, indeed ought to touch his Royall heart: because it is his Kingdome, that fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s and
<PB N="48" REF="29"/>
endures them, and that they are his owne proper bowels which are torne in sunder.</P>
<P>Let it farther represent vnto him, the great aduantage which hee gets by these diuisions and miseries, who is the most dangerous Enemy of his Crowne, who daily encreaseth his owne Estates and Countries, and conqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>reth new, whiles he spoyleth and ruineth his owne: and who mounts to so high and sublime a degree of power, that there is no Christi∣an Prince to whom hereafter he ought not to be formidable: and <HI>France</HI> aboue any other, hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> cause to feare him: for that all the world knowes how passionately hee hath a long time hunted to possesse it; and were it not for any other cause and title, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n that which <HI>Nauarre</HI> assures him, (to wit) <HI>Vsurpation,</HI> and that it were fit and proper for him.</P>
<P>And put the case that this apprehension were yet more retired: yet let this picture still endeuour to make him <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ee, what a blemish it is to the glory and lustre of his Crowne, now to permit all his Allyes, so miserably to perish, whom his Predecessors so gloriously maintained and defended. And what will posterity say of him, when they shall vnderstand, that the <HI>Grisons,</HI> the King of <HI>Denmarke,</HI> and all <HI>Germany</HI> shall stoope vnder the yoake of the house of <HI>Austria,</HI> when <HI>Lewis</HI> 13. sate to the helme of the French Monarchie; and that in stead of assisting of them, as he was bound by his anci∣ent Alliances &amp; confederations, &amp; by his new reiterated pro∣mises, that hee hath abandoned them as a prey to the Vsur∣per, and cast away all care to assist them, to kindle a fire in his owne proper estate, and so to ouer-couer it with flames and ruines?</P>
<P>Yea, let this Picture employ it selfe, to take &amp; remoue from him all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uples of con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce, whereby they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> inflamed &amp; flesh, d him against vs. because of Religion, and so endeuour to make him comprehend that ali Soules belong to God, (in which regard, he is termed the Father of Spirits) and for him; although it be told him, his Scept<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r hath no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>risdiction. Yet say that we were in an errour: that it is a disease of the soule; which to cure, there is none but spirituall remedies that haue
<PB N="49" REF="29"/>
efficacy to performe it, and that all constraint &amp; violence offe∣red to the body, is vncapable thereof; that it hath ill succee∣ded to those who haue made triall of these violent cures, as the experiences of many of his Predecessors (without ascen∣ding higher) doe but too sufficiently make good and con∣firme.</P>
<P>That those who suggest these bloody counsels to him, and to tolerate but one Religion, doe notwithstanding practise the contrary in their owne Estates. The Pope permitting <HI>Iewes</HI> in <HI>Rome, Ancona,</HI> and <HI>Auignon,</HI> although they open∣ly blaspheme against the name of Iesus Christ: and the Spaniard (said to be so good a Catholique) was ready to al∣low the exercise of our Religion to the <HI>Netherlands,</HI> if at that time there had beene no other differences but that.</P>
<P>That by all these considerations collected together, and others which his wisedome shall dictate vnto him, this good Seruant endeuoureth to incline him to giue vs a good Peace, whose Ciment may be the inuiolable execution of his Edicts, that by the continuance and preseruation thereof, this poore Kingdome may reuiue &amp; breathe from her former mi∣series, and re-obtaine the happines of her pristine felicity, and he also may be now blest of all his Subjects, and enioying peace at home, may shew himselfe for the defence of those his Allies abroad who yet subsist; and erraise the others from the ruines and miseries wherein they are fallen for want of his Royall assistance.</P>
<P>And hereafter we haue addressed our selues to the person of our Prince, wee also inuoke all those, who although they are of a contrary Religion to vs, are yet people of good con∣sciences, and retaine still the hearts and affections of Loyall Frenchmen, to the end to speake here in presence of God, that if the first can some way consent to so many iniustices and disloyalties, which haue beene offered to vs, whereby we haue beene wronged and circumuented: And if the o∣ther make them not to ioyne in pitty and compassion, for the miseries and calamities of our common Country, wherein it is plunged and precipitated, by the enrage and furious desire
<PB N="50" REF="30"/>
they haue to ruine vs. What, our deare fellow-Citizens will you still permit your selues to be led by the Notes by your Friers, who owing their Oathes and Eyes to the Pope, and looking with their hearts towards <HI>Spaine,</HI> haue beene the fa∣tall Firebrands, and mournefull Torches of our former flames and miseries, and vnder the same pretext of those times, would now againe enkindle them? Doe you not bewaile the Raigne of <HI>Henry</HI> the Great, during which, euery one pray∣ing to God, as he vnderstood; that Peace brought vs then in plenty and abundance, and we all conspired and vnited our affections to the seruice of our Prince, and to fill and heape vp our Country with happinesse? Were you then lesse saued, and blest, then now euer since we haue begun to be persecu∣ted? What indiscrection is it in you to disturbe your Peace and tranquillity, because we beleeue not as you beleeue? Or if it should be so, are you answerable for our consciences? and is it not onely to our selues, that the preiudice and detri∣ment must accrue? Why leaue you not vs to the iudgement of him, before whom we must all appeare at the latter day, and to whom ye shall not be accountable for what we haue beleeued or done? Doe you thinke, that to wrong vs, is a good way to conuert vs? So often as you haue attempted these mercilesse and cruell courses, what hath there followed or succeeded thereof: but the same desolations and miseries which this present time presents vnto you? And what can he more desire, who is as much the Ancient Enemie of this Estate, as he feignes to be of our Religion: but to see vs armed, and bloody minded one against the other, that after he may become Master of all. In the name of God? at last be∣ginne to vndeceiue your selues. dispoyle and strip your selues of your Animosities, and contribute your wise Counsels to reclaime those, which an inconsiderate zeale hath transported to such furious emotions and combustions. Tell them (al∣though they are made to beleeue the contrary) it will bee on them, which the greatest and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>urthens of the warre will fall: they will be loaden with imposts and exa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tions, to quench the thirst of blood-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ounds, who will sucke them
<PB N="51" REF="30"/>
dry, to the very reines. Their Fields shall be the prey and pillage of Souldiers; they shall be the first obliged to expose themselues to eminent p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rils and dangers, and after all this, when those who manage these combustions, for their owne particular ends and interests, haue made vp their markets, and well filled their purses, then they shall see things tend and bend to hopes of Peace, whereof they will reape no other fruites, but griefe and sorrow for their losses, labour and paines, and also to see how they haue beene abused and fool'd through their simple credulity, by those who hauing in their mouthes the specious names of the Estate, and Religion: and yet to no other end, but to inrich themselues by the publique calamity.</P>
<P>But as for you, our most deare Brothers, who in this Kingdome professe with vs the purity of one and the same Religion, in what place or quality soeuer you are, we expect from you, that as our griefes and afflictions are common, so our feelings thereof may be. We will not heere discouer the searres and cicatrices of our wounds, by reproaching those among you, who heretofore haue beheld our calamities with dry eyes, or who thought to haue done much to bewaile them. No, no, we will impute this blame to the deceitfull Songs of the <HI>Syrens,</HI> who haue sometimes heretofore inchan∣ted and lull'd vs asleepe our selues: But now we coniure you by all that is holy and sacred, not to permit your selues to be any longer deceiued: you shall haue many Offers made you, to rent and disioyne your selues from vs. They will extort Declarations from you, that you hold vs Rebels: they will oblige you likewise to arme your selues against vs: But in the name of God, consider with your selues, that all our reb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>llion is, because we will not rebell against God; and that as by the grace of God, we remaine constant in the same Religion which you professe, so your disauowing of vs, will in effect be the renouncing of Iesus Christ, and your Armes, if you are so miserable to take them vp against vs, and to of∣fend vs, will wound our Common Sauiour and Redeemer, and againe crucifie him in his members. Know likewise, that
<PB N="52" REF="31"/>
our Enemies intend no lesse cruelty to you then to vs, be∣cause they esteeme vs as the Dike and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ences to hinder the Torrent from going to swallow downe, and submerge you. Those wild Boares haue no intent to spare any thing in the poore Vine of the Lord: but they rush vpon vs, as beleeuing that we are the hedges and inclosure. It is impossible that in our ruines, you be not bruysed to death, because we are but one house: In our Shipw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>acke, you will infallibly perish, for that we sayle in one and the same Ship. All the fauour which you can hope or expect from them, is but that of the <HI>Cyclope, to be deuoured last.</HI> As deare to you then as is our common subsistance, let vs vnite our selues together for our common defence. Be not then so faint hearted, to suffer vs to perish, except you intend immediately after to haue your throates cut in your owne houses: Remember that your par∣ticular conseruation, cannot be but in the generall, whercun∣to if you contribute with vs, it will be the truest way to se∣cure your goods, to conserue your liues, and aboue all to maintaine you in libertie to serue God: Or if yet there liue any so stupid or insensible, not to be moued for all this, then all that we can doe, is to send them to these Words of <HI>Mor∣docheus: Thinke not that you onely can escape: for i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> you hold your peace in this time, comfort and deliuerance shall appeare to</HI> Israel <HI>from another place, but you and all your houses shall perish.</HI></P>
<P>But as we expect better things of you, so doe we likewise hope the same of our brothers beyond the Seas, and parti∣cularly from those of the Vnited Prouinces: already the interest of the same Religion should make them know, that the cause is common, and if it be persecuted in the mid∣dest of vs, it is not very probable or likely, that there be any great affection to maintaine and conserue it in the middest of them, what faire shew soeuer the Pope make them to the contrary, who is the great wheele that makes all moue, and worke for our ruine, to the end to make a step and Ladder to theirs: but if they are not possessed of this seare, yet it seemes they are obliged to be sensible and compassionate of our af∣flictions,
<PB N="53" REF="31"/>
because of the affection which heretofore hath made vs lament and weepe at theirs, during the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> trou∣bles. All <HI>Europe</HI> hath seene how we haue runne by tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ands to ciment their libertie with our bloods, and particularly the Towne of <HI>Rochell</HI> held nothing too deare for their regard, at the very point of their last necessitie, and now that the tine of our calamitie is come, we againe demand them the effects of the like good will and affection.</P>
<P>But there is yet more: for if our dangers be extreme, we may say, that it is they who are the first &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> cause ther∣of, in lending their ships to our enemies, which they im∣ployed and vsed to ruine vs, &amp; although therein <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> are con∣fident, that they were politikely surprised, neuerthelesse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nce our misery proceeded from thence, what can they doe lesse then affirme and testifie, that they are sorry for it, in stretch∣ing forth their hand of assistance, to withdrawe vs from this Gulph wherin they haue made vs fall, although it were done without thinking thereof?</P>
<P>If they will, they haue the same vertue of <HI>Achi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es,</HI> and can cure our wounds, by the very same meanes and instru∣ments they made them. And say that all these reasons will not passe for current money with them (although we assure our selues they will not so judge) yet the interuention and mediation of their Ambassadours in the last peace, and their promises, that those Commissions should be performed and accomplished to vs, giues vs all right and reason, now they are broken, to addresse our selues to them, that they make good their said promises, and to disingage vs their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aith.</P>
<P>It is therfore in this regard that we haue recourse to them; and generally wee pary all Princes and Potentates, to extend their assistance and fauour to vs. We doubt not but our ene∣mies will endeuour traduce and disparage all our actions to them, and publish against vs, variety of false reports and infamous Libels: but whosoeuer hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ares only to heare accusers, then innocency, will often be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> into <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. It is the custome of the strongest, when they resolue to op∣pose
<PB N="54" REF="32"/>
the weaker, passionately to alledge, they are guiltie: as by the report of the Wolfe, the Sheepe had troubled the wa∣ter. Our enemies desame and disgrace vs, but it is only for that their Iniustice is so palpable, as they are ashamed there∣of; and because they dare not make it appeare <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aked and in the meridian of its truth; they must therefore finde out a maske, and disguize it vnder the false name of calumny.</P>
<P>We therefore besee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h the aforesaid Princes, not to condemne vs before they haue first vnderstood our defence and reasons, and cast their eyes vpon this small Epitomie of our Iusti∣fications: and we dare assure our selues, that they will after pit∣tie our innocency so vniustly oppressed: And as it is for the maintenance thereof, that God hath giuen them their power, that they will therefore please to imploy it in our defence and assistance.</P>
<P>And thou, O eternall God, who searchest the reines, and art Iudge of the intentions of our hearts, arise as witnes, and decide betwixt vs and our enemies: See whether they or we haue broken the Alliance of thy sacred name, vsed disloyalty and fraude to oppresse and ruine the innocent, Iudge who are true offenders and criminals towards the Prince which thou hast established to be thy Image to vs; either they who haue infringed vs his Edicts, and against the faith thereof, done vs all sorts of indignities and outrages, or we who haue beene constrained to suffer them as a warrant and caution of the faith. Make the violation thereof fall on the heads of those who are guilty; and as the Protector of innocnecy, shoote forth thy vengeance on those who haue oppressed it.</P>
<P>Our consciences which are pure before God, embolden vs to addresse him these our vowes, and wee doubt not but he will heare them to our aduantage, and be a just reuenger of the Faith, which hath beene perfidiously broken to vs: Of our goods vniustly stolne from vs: Of our blood inhumanely and cruelly spilt; and of our consciences which haue beene afflicted with all variety of rigors; So we hope that he will
<PB N="55" REF="32"/>
powre downe all sorts of blessings on our Armes, who is the true God of victories and Armes. And as it is only ne∣cessitie, which hath made vs to assume and take them vp: so wee protest to be ready and willing to lay them downe, as soone as we receiue lustice, and that the libertie of our Religion and liues be re-established, according to the Edicts published in our fauour, and parti∣cularly of that of <HI>Nantes.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

