<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A watch-vvorde for warre Not so new as necessary: published by reason of the disperced rumors amongst vs, and the suspected comming of the Spanyard against vs. Wherein we may learne how to prepare our selues to repell the enemie, and to behaue our selues all the tyme of that trouble. Compendious for the memorie, comfortable for the matter, profitable for the matter, profitable for the tyme.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A01371</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 11492</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S117690</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99852901</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99852901</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">18256</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01371)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18256)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 510:05)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A watch-vvorde for warre Not so new as necessary: published by reason of the disperced rumors amongst vs, and the suspected comming of the Spanyard against vs. Wherein we may learne how to prepare our selues to repell the enemie, and to behaue our selues all the tyme of that trouble. Compendious for the memorie, comfortable for the matter, profitable for the matter, profitable for the tyme.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[60] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[Cambridge] :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Iohn Legat, printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1596.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>"To the reader" signed: C.G. (i.e. Charles Gibbon).</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A-G⁴ H² .</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Spain --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Pip Willcox</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Pip Willcox</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A01371">
<STC T="S">11492</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852901</BIBNO>
<VID>18256</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<P>A
Watch-worde for
Warre.
Not so new as necessary:
Published by reason of the disperced
rumors amongst vs, and the suspected com∣ming
of the <HI>Spanyard</HI> against vs. 
Wherein we may learne how to prepare our selues
to repell the Enemie, and to behaue our selues all
the tyme of that trouble.</P>
<P>Compendious for the memorie, comfortable for the
matter, profitable for the
tyme.</P>
<BIBL>Ezekiell, 21, 12.</BIBL>
<Q>The terrors of the sword shall be vppon my
people: smyte therefore vpon thy thigh.</Q>
<P>¶Printed by <HI>Iohn Legat,</HI> Printer to the
Vniuersitie of Cambridge.
1596.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="acrostic poem">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<P><FIGURE>
<FIGDESC>Royal English blazon, or coat of arms.</FIGDESC>
</FIGURE></P>
<LG>
<L><HI>E</HI>ternall, good, and gracious God, stretch forth thy sauing hand,</L>
<L><HI>L</HI>et not our sinnes prouoke thy wrath, but looke vpon this Land,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI>n thee we doe repose our trust, as one that neuer faile,</L>
<L><HI>S</HI>ubuert both far and fawning foes, they neuer may preuaile:</L>
<L><HI>A</HI>las what are we of our selues, and want thee on our side,</L>
<L><HI>B</HI>ut euen as chaffe against the winde, not able to abide.</L>
<L><HI>E</HI>xtend therefore thy heauenly helpe, and though we were but ten,</L>
<L><HI>T</HI>hey shall repell tenne thousand foes, if thou doost say Amen.</L>
<L><HI>H</HI>ee that doth rule the harts of all, theyr bodies can subiect,</L>
<L><HI>A</HI>n arme of flesh is of no force where he doth not direct.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>R</HI>emember Lord our soueraigne Prince, thine owne annointed deere,</L>
<L><HI>E</HI>xpell her foes, increase her friends, no hurt may happen heere:</L>
<L><HI>G</HI>iue to her subiects faithfull harts, to loue her as they ought,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI>nfold all secrete trecheries, and bring them vnto nought.</L>
<L><HI>N</HI>owe for thy mercies sake good Lord, vnto our sute incline,</L>
<L><HI>A</HI>nd so direct her highnes dayes, shee may at last be thine.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="4"/>
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To the right Worshipfull, the Mayor
of the borrough of Kings Lynne, and to his Associ∣ats
or Bretheren the Aldermen of the same Towne,
C: G: wisheth much health with prosperitie,
and all happines with eternitie.</HEAD>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">P</SEG>Lato</HI> that diuine Philosopher (right Worship∣full)
dyd cast out of the common-wealth of
wise-men which he made, <HI>Homer</HI> and <HI>Hesiode</HI>
two Poets, because he perceyued some vani∣tie
in theyr Poems. <HI>Ouid</HI> neuer more iustlie
deserued exilement, then for hys lasciuious
verse, because they incline to the nourishment
of vyce.</P>
<P>If we punish such by penall lawes, which vse false waights and
measures, those are not to be permitted, vvhich diuulgate corrupt
dyscourses: for these are meanes to vitiat the minde, the other can
but defraud vs of money.</P>
<P>That vvhich is infectious to publish, must needes be infamous
to patronize; it is a credit to giue countenance to a good worke;
for that cause I haue made choyse of such a matter, as shall neyther
offend your W. for vanitie in the inuention, or for indignitie in
the protection.</P>
<P>The Subiect handled is vvarre, the rumor of it is fearefull, and
therefore the discourse of it may be fruitfull; vvhich hauing fini∣shed,
I haue presented to your W. not to that ende many ayme
at, in giuing whereof <HI>Gratian</HI> speaketh, <HI>Do vt des vel do vt facias.
Decret caus.</HI> 14. To giue to haue giuen agayne, but as a gyft pro∣ceeding
of mere good-will; and I am the rather induced heere∣vnto,
for these causes.</P>
<P>First in respect of promise; the Ciuilians say, <HI>Vir iustus est vota
et promissa praestare,</HI> I promised long since to gratifie your W. with
some grauer attempt. The Philosopher sayth, that the bird of E∣gypt
being olde, purgeth all the humors of her bodie, by eating
spyces of Arabia, and sendeth forth of her mouth a sweete breath;
so I hauing expelled the vanities of youth, by the experience of
more yeares, may haue a more rype and seasoned iudgment: for as
<HI>Euripides</HI> sayth, the second actions are more singuler; vve see that
<PB REF="5"/>
Aritificers be more excellent, in theyr second workes, then much
more are the studies of the minde, alwayes amended by future me∣ditation,
as <HI>Cicero</HI> sayth, <HI>Posteriores cogitationes sapientiores esse solent,</HI>
the latter cogitations are wont to be wiser.</P>
<P>Secondly, in regard of your kindnesse; vvhich not onely deser∣ueth
to be cannonized for a vertue by the Schoolemen, <HI>T. Aqui.
Art,</HI> 1, but to be spoken of to the reproch of many ingratefull per∣sons
in thys age: for there be some that respect not a gyft vvhen it
is giuen; others, that vvill sooner crucifie then gratifie a well-wil∣ler;
but there is in your W. both a ciuill kind of curtesie to accept,
and also, more then a common course of kindnesse to requite; now
it is true that <HI>Tully</HI> sayth, <HI>Omnes immemorem benificii oderunt,</HI> all
men hate hym who is not mindfull of a benefite, and therefore if
Heathen men vvould punish vnthankfull persons, with seruitude,
as <HI>Claudius Caesar</HI> did: <HI>Sueton, cap.</HI> 25, and vvith death, as the Per∣sians
dyd, <HI>Melanct. lib.</HI> 1, vvhat were I worthie to haue, if I should
not remember your kindnes and some-way remunerate againe.</P>
<P>These things considered (hauing neyther store of Indian trea∣sure
to bestowe, or costlie Iuels of Egypt to offer) I could doe no
lesse then dedicate my labours to your W. <HI>Ʋltra posse non est esse,</HI>
there is no defect in affection but in action; but Kings in former
tymes would not refuse gyfts of good-will, though they brought
but a handfull of vvater; Christ him selfe dyd accept the widowes
offer, though she gaue but a myte, and therefore I hope you will
not reiect my simple present, though it be but a peece of paper. So
presuming of your accustomed kindnesse, I commit the protection
heereof to your W. and the preseruation of your selues, to the
Almightie, vvho make you gloryous Cittizens in heauen, as he
hath made you graue Senators vpon earth.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Worships alwayes in the Lord, 
C. G.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>To the Reader.</HEAD>
<P>THE mutabilitie of reports had almost dismaide mee
in proceeding: for one while there runne nothing
but rumors of vvarre, an otherwhile there passe ma∣nie
speeches of peace; the same mouth that saith at one
time, the Spanyard will come, another time affirmeth, we
neede not expect his comming. There be many that wish
warrs because they cannot thriue with peace, and others
that speak of peace, because they loue not to heare of war;
but (good Reader) as there is no smoke without fire, so
there ariseth no rumor without some original, for rumors
are commonly fore-runners of warre. VVhen tydings of
vvarre were voyced in Iuda, the enemies tarried not long
after; and therefore the speeches which are giuen out of
the Spanyard, may put vs in expectation of his comming;
he which hath made so great preparation for warre, may
be suspected to weight oportunitie to effect his will.</P>
<P>There were many false Prophets amongst the Iewes,
which perswaded them of peace for some lewd pretence,
when they knew the Assyrians were ready to assault them,
Ierem, 6, 14. I pray GOD there be not some false-harted
subiects amongst vs, that giue out reports of peace for som
ill purpose, when they are perswaded the Spanyard is ap∣proching.</P>
<P>Howsoeuer it be, <HI>dubia timenda,</HI> things doubtful are to
be dreadfull; It is better to liue in feare then security: for
feare maketh vs to flie to God, as <HI>Iehoshaphat</HI> did when he
feared the Moabites to come vpon him, 2, Chro, 20, 3, but
securitie maketh vs forget God, as <HI>Dauid</HI> did when hee re∣mained
secure in Ierusalem. 2, Sam, 11. The feare of war
is to be doubted euen in the fruition of peace, for as the
wise-man sayth, There is a time of warre aswell as a time
<PB REF="6"/>
of peace, Eccles, 3, 8. Such euer tast the lesse troubles in
the tempest of warre, which sayle with a martiall foresight
in the calme of peace.</P>
<P>But admit the Spanyarde hath disperced some part of
his Nauie, or hath some other crosse occasions to hinder
his cōming hether this yere, yet let vs perswade our selues,
that as God made the Amorites and others to be as pricks
and thornes to the Israelits, Iosua, 23, 13, so he hath made
the Spaniard to be as a prick &amp; thorne to Englishmen, in∣somuch
as we shall neuer bee so assured of peace, but wee
may alwaies liue in suspition of warre: and therefore thys
treatise of warre cannot be friuolous.</P>
<P>I remember <HI>Cicero</HI> sayth, it is one poynt of policie in
peace to prepare for vvarre; now if outwarde furniture to
defend the body, is expedient to be in preparation, though
there be no vvarre; the inwarde Armour to asist the soule,
cannot be impertinent though there be peace.</P>
<P>These and some other respects haue mooued me to set
forth this Treatise, considering what <HI>Seneca</HI> saith, <HI>Non vi∣uit
qui nemini viuit,</HI> he liueth not, that liueth to none but
himselfe; therefore I thought it to bee a sinne by concea∣ling,
which might turne to a more profit by publishing.</P>
<P>Thus being loth to put any in feare of vvarre, although
it be good policie to suspect it, or in hope of peace when
the Enemie is so busie about warlike preparation, I leaue
the censuring hereof, to such as know best vnder God, and
the successe of both to him that seeth more then any man,
which is the almightie <HI>Iehouah,</HI> whom <HI>Augustine</HI> sayth to
be <HI>Totus oculus,</HI> all Eye, because hee best seeth all things,
whose purpose will take place whatsoeuer we heare,
eyther by flying reports, or by fabulous
prophecies.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>C. G.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>Warre.</HEAD>
<P>THE Latine word <HI>Bellum,</HI> is so called (saith <HI>Cicero)</HI> of
<HI>Belluis,</HI> cruell, beast-like or sauage; some suppose it
commeth of <HI>Bellona,</HI> whom the Poets fayned to be
the Goddesse of VVarre, whose felicity was in the effusi∣on
of bloode. The Etymologie of the worde dooth not
much differ from the nature of the subiect.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>There be two kinds of warre,
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>1. Bellum internum.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>2. Bellum externum.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1. <HI>Bellum internum,</HI> inward warre, is that we commonly
call the spirituall warre, therefore this life is very fitlie by
one of the Fathers called a warfare. <HI>August. 45. Ser. de tem.</HI>
For the Spirit hath many egregious enemies, which con∣tinually
combate and encounter with it.</P>
<P>The flesh is called <HI>Caro a corrupto,</HI> because it dooth cor∣rupt,
or as the Schooleman saith, it is called <HI>Caro quia cor∣ruit,</HI>
because it doth ouerthrow. This is one enemie that
impugneth against the Spirite; From whence are warres
(saith the Apostle) euen of your lustes that fight in your
members: <HI>Iam.</HI> 4. Heereupon <HI>Paule</HI> wel alludeth when he
saith, <HI>Though we walke in the flesh, we doe not warre after it.
2. Cor.</HI> 10. 3.</P>
<P>The world, as one saith wel, is called <HI>Mundus ab immun∣do,</HI>
for it shroudeth much filthines vnder a faire shew, ther∣fore
<PB REF="7"/>
<HI>Austen</HI> sayd not without cause, <HI>Si te delectat hic mun∣dus,
semper vis esse immundus:</HI> if we take pleasure in it, wee
shal alwaies be impure. This world is another enemy that
warreth against the spirite. As warre commonly precee∣deth
before victory, so the Apostle approueth the worlde
after a sort, to warre, by shewing the meanes howe to get
the victorie, in these words, <HI>This is our victory that ouer∣commeth
the world, euen our fayth. 2. Iohn.</HI> 5.</P>
<P>The deuil, he is called <HI>Dlabolus, quia est aduersus,</HI> because
he is against vs, and therefore <HI>Peter</HI> calleth him <HI>aduersarie,
1. Pet,</HI> 5, 8. Thys deuill is another enemie that warreth a∣gainst
the Spirit, for it is written of him, that hee beeing
wroth with the VVoman, went and made warre with the
remnant of her seede. <HI>Apoc, 12, 17. S. Gregory</HI> saith, that the
manifold warres of our fore-fathers, are shadowes of those
warres we must haue with the deuill. <HI>Greg: 23, quest. capit.
1. nisi bellum.</HI></P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>This VVarre is dange∣rous
in two respects,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. of the number of the enimies</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. of the nature of the enimies</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1. Of the Number: for there are three to one. The
Phylosopher sayth, <HI>Ne Hercules contra duos,</HI> hee must be a
strong man that is able to resist two, therefore three to one
is greater odds. VVhē <HI>Iosua</HI> sent but three thousand men
against the Citty of <HI>Ai,</HI> the Cittizens were able to shift
with them. <HI>Iosua,</HI> 7, 4, but when he sent thirtie thousande
strong men against it, thē the Cittie was soone sacked. <HI>Iosu.</HI>
8, 3. If the bodie be not able to withstande outward vio∣lence
where there is inequalitie of enemies, howe should
the Spirit, where there is such aduantage of the inwarde
aduersaries?</P>
<P><PB REF="7"/>
2 Of the Nature: for they practise all pollicies to pre∣uaile
with the spirit: insomuch as many times they make
a batterie and breach in the very best, as in <HI>Dauid, Peter,</HI> &amp;
diuers other. This short period of the melli-fluous father,
doth pretely describe the nature of these enemies, <HI>Mundus
clamat decipiam, Caro inficiam, diabolus interficiam, Christus
dicit reficiam: quem sequereris?</HI> the worlde crieth I will de∣ceiue,
The flesh cryeth I wil infect, the deuill cryeth I will
kill, but Christ saith I wil refresh, which of these wilt thou
followe? But as there be many mighty and vndermining
enimies against the Spirit, so God hath not left it destitute
of assistance to animate it.</P>
<P>There is no King will send foorth his subiects without
weapons in outward warres: euen so the king of al kings,
hath dealt by the Spirit in this inward warfare; for he hath
not left it naked and open to the enemies, but hath gyuen
it Armour for the defence, as the Brest-plate of righteous∣nes,
the Shielde of fayth, the Helmet of saluation, the
Sword of the Spirit. &amp;c. <HI>Ephe,</HI> 6.</P>
<P>This spirituall Armour is of greater force to subdue the
inward enemies, then politique weapons are to repell the
outward aduersaries: therfore <HI>Paule</HI> saith, the weapons of
our warfare are not carnall but mightie through God to
cast downe holds. 2, <HI>Cor,</HI> 10, 4.</P>
<P>In other warres, the Souldiers neuer goe to fight with∣out
a Captaine to conduct them, euen so hath God delt by
the Spirit, it hath Christ to be the Captaine, and therefore
wee are called Souldiers, because wee fight vnder his ban∣ner.
Now if <HI>Saule</HI> had good successe in his battels, because
<HI>Dauid</HI> being a godly Generall directed his bands, the Spi∣rite
shall speed well in this conflict, because Christ is the
Captaine, who is farre better then <HI>Dauid.</HI></P>
<P>Humaine Captaynes will sometime recoyle and shrinke
<PB REF="8"/>
from their Souldiers in extreamities, this heauenly Captaine
will persist with his Souldiers in all perills: for (as one of
the ancient writers sayth) he will ouer-looke vs fighting,
succour vs fainting, and crowne vs ouercomming.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>This spirituall VVarre
of all other warres is most
<LIST>
<ITEM>Fearefull.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Famous.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>It is most fearefull in many respects, for first, if we faint
in this fight, it is commonly the cause of all other warres,
for outward warres are sent to intimate Gods indignation
for our securitie, to the end we might be excited and for∣tified
in this spirituall fight. God would neuer sende out∣ward
enemies to afflict the bodie, but that hee perceiues
the inward enemies doe preuaile with the Spirit.</P>
<P>2 In other warres, though wee bee taken captiues, yet
we may be ransommed for money, but if wee be subdued
by the spirituall enemies, there is no hope of raunsome, as
the Psalmist sayth. <HI>Hee cannot giue his raunsome to God, Psal,</HI>
49, 7.</P>
<P>3 In other warres, we can but loose our goods, lyms,
or (at the vttermost) our lyues, though the enemies work
their wills on vs: but in this spirituall battell we loose both
bodies &amp; soules if the enemies get the vpper hand. There∣fore
S. <HI>Ierom</HI> saith wel, <HI>Septies stultior est, ego qui nudo cor∣pore
poneret se in medio hostium armatorum:</HI> that such an one
is seauen times more foolish, or in worse plight, then hee
which doth hazarde his naked body in the midst of an ar∣med
host.</P>
<P>It is most famous if the Spirite preuaileth: for in other
warres, such as gette the conquest, may perhaps purchase
some momentanie riches or renowne amongst men: but
in this inward warre, if we be victorious, we shall obtaine
a Crowne, not of gold, but of glory, not earthly, but eter∣nall.
<PB REF="8"/>
<HI>Reuel. 3.</HI></P>
<P>Men in outward battels, will venture farre to gette the
victory, in regard of peace or praise, then howe couragi∣ous
ought wee to be in this spirituall combat, to gette the
conquest, that we may attaine the celestiall paradise, where
the pleasures are inexplicable, 1, <HI>Cor,</HI> 2, 9: and indetermina∣ble,
<HI>Psalm,</HI> 16, 11. These reasons were sufficient to enforce
vs to be vigilant and valiant in this inward warre.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>2 <HI>Bellum externum,</HI> out∣ward
war is of three sorts
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 Innaturale.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Ciuile.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 Commune.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 <HI>Bellum innaturale,</HI> vnnaturall warre, is such as carrieth
vvith it a kinde of abhorrencie in nature,</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>VVhereof there be two sorts,
<LIST>
<ITEM>VVarre of ignorance.</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVar of knowledge.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>VVarre of ignorance, is that which the Heathens vsed
when they did sacrifice theyr children to the fire, or sley
them to some cerimoniall end. Therefore the VViseman
sayth, they liued in <HI>Immagno inscitiae bello,</HI> great warres of
ignorance, VVisdom, 14, 21.</P>
<P>Such was the vvarre which <HI>Paule</HI> made in persecuting
the Saints, which hee confesseth himselfe he did of igno∣raunce.</P>
<P>VVarre of knowledge, was the warre of some of the
people of Ierusalem, of whom it is saide, that they filled
that place with the blood of innocents. Ierem, 19.</P>
<P>Such was also the vvarre of bloody <HI>Boner</HI> in Queene
<HI>Maries</HI> dayes, in the destruction of so many Martyrs.</P>
<P>1 The Heathen men had no illumination but by the light
<PB REF="9"/>
of nature, and therefore their ignorance is the more to be
excused. <HI>Acts</HI> 17, 30. But as for those of <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> and that
bloodie <HI>Boner,</HI> their warres cannot be iustlie sayd to be of
ignorance: for the Prophets reproued the one often times
for the fact, and the Martirs alledged Scriptures to the o∣ther,
alwayes to disproue his proceedings.</P>
<P>2 <HI>Bellum ciuile,</HI> ciuill warre is that vvhich ariseth with∣in
a Nation it selfe.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Thys warre is eyther
<LIST>
<ITEM>Of Deuision</ITEM>
<ITEM>Of Rebellion.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Of Diuision, when a land is deuided within it selfe, as
when two striue for gouernment, such diuision was in the
land of <HI>Iuda,</HI> betweene <HI>Rehoboam</HI> and <HI>Ieroboam,</HI> as you may
reade in the 1. Kings 12, and the like diuision is, or was in
<HI>Fraunce</HI> betweene the lawfull King and <HI>Duke de Mayne.</HI></P>
<P>Of Rebellion, when subiects doe repugne or rebell a∣gainst
their King, as we reade of <HI>Absalom,</HI> how he rebelled
against King <HI>Dauid</HI> to dirept the diademe from him, and
here-vnto may be added these (not much different in na∣ture
but in name) which we call, Conspiracy, Insurrection,
Commotion, Mutinie, &amp;c. VVhereof we haue examples.
VVe reade of <HI>Zimri</HI> how he conspired against King <HI>Elah,</HI>
1. King 16. we may speake more properly of all these prac∣tises
within this land, of the sinister and sundrie conspira∣cies
against the person of our Prince, of the vnnaturall in∣surrection
in the North, of the vnkind commotion of <HI>Ket</HI>
and his confederates, but as their actions be odious, so
their endes were ignominious.</P>
<P>3 <HI>Bellum commune,</HI> common VVarre, some call it Nati∣onall,
the warre of Countries, of this warre our Sauiour
<PB REF="9"/>
Christ speaketh when hee saith, Nation shall rise agaynst
Nation, and Realme against Realme, Math. 24. 7. Of this
warre because occasion and opportunitie is offered (by
reason the Spanyard is suspected to rise against England) I
will intreat of for our comfort.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Thys kinde of VVarre brin∣geth
a feare vvithall two vvayes.
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. Auditione.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Actione.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 The very rumor or heare-say of this warre is dread∣full.
<HI>Iosephus</HI> reporteth that when it was voyced that <HI>Try∣phon</HI>
had gathered a great Host to come into the lande of
<HI>Iuda,</HI> the people were in great trembling and feare, <HI>Antiq.
13. cap.</HI> VVhen the children of Israel heard that the <HI>Phi∣listims</HI>
would come against them, the text saith they were
afraid, 1. <HI>Sam.</HI> 7. 7. VVhen tydings was brought to <HI>Ieho∣shaphat</HI>
how the <HI>Amonites</HI> intended to battell against him,
the Scripture saith that <HI>Iehoshaphat</HI> feared, 2. <HI>Chro.</HI> 20. VVe
see by experience in our selues, that when it is giuen out,
the Spanyard prepareth to come against vs, how many of
vs be smitten with a kind of feare, when we do but heare
of it.</P>
<P>2 If the rumour and report of warre bee so fearefull,
what is the very action it selfe. I remember a pritty instance
to this purpose, when <HI>Dauid</HI> was to incounter with his e∣nemies,
some of his men sayd vnto him: <HI>See wee be afrayde
heere in Iuda, how much more if we come to Kelah against the
host of the Philistims. 1, Sam.</HI> 23, 3. Let vs applie this to our
selues, if we be afrayd to heare of warres at home in our
houses, how fearefull would we be if we came in the face
of the enemie? <HI>Saule</HI> was a notable and worthy warrior:
for he had sore warres all his dayes, 2, <HI>Sam.</HI> 3, 1. Yet is it
written of him, that when he savve the host of the <HI>Phili∣stims,</HI>
he was afrayd and his heart was sore astonied, 1, <HI>Sam.</HI>
<PB REF="10"/>
28, 5. Then no maruaile though England (hauing dwelt
vvithout feare vnder our gracious Queene, as Israel did
vnder <HI>Salomon, 1, Kings 4, 25)</HI> should be somewhat feare∣full
of vvarres, because it hath beene accustomed to peace,
when <HI>Saul</HI> was so fearefull that was neuer without warre.</P>
<P>Many men are feared for many respects, some man is
feared for his godlinesse as <HI>Dauid</HI> was, an other is feared for
his vvisedome as <HI>Salomon</HI> was, but the Spanyard he is fea∣red
for his crueltie as <HI>Pharaoh</HI> was, and therefore who fea∣reth
not to be afflicted of such as haue no feare of God?</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>VVee must consider
there is a two-fold feare,
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>1 Timor laudabilis.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>2 Timor detestabilis.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 <HI>Timor laudabilis,</HI> It is a laudable feare, when men by
that meanes are exscited to looke vnto the Lord, this feare
was in <HI>Iehoshaphat</HI> a godly King, it is sayd that hee feared
and set him selfe to seeke the Lord, 2, <HI>Chro.</HI> 20, 3. Flesh and
blood is fraile, and therefore soone affrighted, but happie
are those which in their feare, can follow so good a course
as this King did.</P>
<P>There be others that are terrified by remembrance of
theyr misdeeds, and feare that God will afflict them, and so
by this meanes they are mooued to amendement; Thys
feare is laudable. VVhen iudgements were pronounced,
and impendant vppon Sion, it is sayde the Sinners were a∣fraid,
and a feare came vpon the hypocrits: Esay, 33, 14, &amp;
therefore, if thys feare vpon vs, arise by reason of our sins,
and for feare of Gods wrath wee depart from them, wee
neede not feare the Spaniard, though he put vs in feare of
vvarre.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>2 <HI>Timor detestabilis,</HI> detestable
feare proceedeth two wayes,
<LIST>
<ITEM>Of Cowardice,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Of Despayre.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><PB REF="10"/>
Of Cowardice, some are afrayd of their owne shadow,
as <HI>Gaal</HI> was, who tooke the shadow of the Mountains for
men: Iudg, 9, 36. Now, as a coward can doe little good
in the vvarres with his weapon, so he may do much hurte
with his words by discouraging others: and therfore this
martiall exhortation was made in Deut, 20, 8, VVhosoe∣uer
is afrayd and faynt-harted, let him goe and returne vn∣to
his house, least his bretherens hart faynte like his hart.
There be many such faint-harted men, which doth argue
no humanitie but effemenacie. VVhen open proclamation
was made in the warres of <HI>Gedeon</HI> that such should returne
home which were timerous or fearfull, of 32. thousande,
there departed 22. thousand men away, Iudg, 7, 3. If the
Spaniards come against vs, let vs not be fearefull, conside∣ring
our cause is so good, that wee ought to shewe our
selues couragious, and not covvards.</P>
<P>3 Of Despayre; If God casteth feare vpon a man, and
in his feare he dispaire of Gods protection, this is to bee ta∣ken
for a great punishment, because it is inflicted vpon the
wicked, as appeareth in Deut, 28, 66, Thy life shall hange
before thee, and thou shalt feare both night and day. And
in Leuit, 26, 36, I will send a faintnes into their harts. It
was the iudgement God imposed vpon the impious Ba∣bilonians,
that theyr hands shall be weakened, and theyr
harts melt, and they shal be afrayde: anguish and sorrovve
shal take them, Esay, 13, 8, and therefore, howsoeuer it
fall out, God defende vs from this feare, yea though wee
should take a little foyle of the enemie, as the Israelits dyd
of the men of <HI>Ai,</HI> farre be it from vs we should be so fear∣full
that our harts shoulde melt away like water, as theyrs
did, Iosua 7, 5, in seioyning fayth from feare.</P>
<LIST>
<PB REF="11"/>
<ITEM>VVe must consider
for our benefite ge∣nerally
three things,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 VVhat VVarre is.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 VVho is the Author of it</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 VVherefore it is sent.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="part">
<HEAD>1. What Warre is.</HEAD>
<P>THE Poets fayned VVarre to bee a Riuer running
with blood, by reason of the manifolde and misera∣ble
massacres and slaughters. VVe read in <HI>Esay,</HI> how
the Lorde threatned so great a slaughter among the Moa∣bites,
that the waters of <HI>Dimon</HI> shall be full of blood, Esay
15, 9: so merciles are men in vvarre that it may wel be true
which <HI>Homer</HI> sayth, There is some sacietie of all things,
except it be of war.</P>
<P>Some other of the Ethnick wryters, haue deemed war
to be a fire alwaies flaming, because they commonly vse to
consume Citties and Townes when they are besieged,
with fire, as Iericho was by <HI>Iosua,</HI> &amp; Ierusalem by the king
of Babel.</P>
<P>These bee rather descriptions of the fruites and effects
of vvar, then a true definition.</P>
<P>The Phylosophers define vvar to be the pride of Prin∣ces;
VVee reade of <HI>Alexander,</HI> that hee was so aspyring
minded, that he thought the whole world too little to sa∣tisfie
his lust;</P>
<P>Thys is no perfect definition; for by thys reason vvee
may define war to be a matter of ingratitude, because <HI>Da∣uid</HI>
tooke occasion by the vnkindnes of <HI>Hanun</HI> to attempt
warre, 2, Sam, 10, 7.</P>
<P>Some of the vvryters define vvar to be a forceable and
hostile discention, vndertaken by lawfull Edict for the re∣pressing
of iniuries; Thys is the inferior and actiue defini∣tion,
<PB REF="11"/>
but not the effectuall: for vvar is nothing else but a
diuine scourge for sinne; Esay 10, 26, Deut, 28.</P>
<P>IF VVarre be a scourge, wee must not laugh &amp; set light
by it: for as wee deeme that childe graceles which will
not shed teares when hee is scourged of his Maister, so
we are to be thought godles, if we will not sorrow &amp; im∣plore
vnder the scourge of God.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Thys meeteth with two contrary mo∣tions,
vvhich proceede of sinister
<LIST>
<ITEM>Greefe.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ioy.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 Sinister griefe is that, which is conceiued vpon car∣nall
occasions; as for example, it may bee there are manie
vvhen they heare of vvarrs, it is grieuous to them in tvvo
respects.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 Of theyr expence.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Of theyr seruice.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 Of theyr Expence, because they are to bee at some
charges in prouiding of Armour, and other martiall con∣tributions:
vvhat a contemptible and griple griefe is this.</P>
<P>There is no Prince in Christendome euer possessed
peace so long as our gracious Soueraigne; It is vvritten of
Iuda and Israell, they dwelt vvithout feare, euery man vn∣der
his own Vine, 1, Kin. 4, 25, the like hath been verified
by vs in England; Reade throughout all Chronicles, and
see howe many of her predecessors had the like Alcion
dayes. Search the Scriptures, and you shall find how that
beloued Lande of Israell neuer had the like fruition of
peace as Englande had, vnlesse it were in <HI>Salomons</HI> dayes;
Discend into other Countries, and you shall see hovve the
Lovve Countries haue beene afflicted with vvar 23. yeeres
together; hovve Fraunce hath neuer beene free from in∣termissiue
vvarrs; as for Spayne, I need not speake of it.</P>
<P><PB REF="12"/>
These things considered, what ingratefull and disloyall
persons are these, vvhich hauing by continuance of peace
gathered plentie, and with theyr plenty are so vncheere∣full
to part with a little to defend theyr Queene and theyr
Countrey? <HI>Tully</HI> hath a prety saying, Hee that desireth
peace, let him prepare for vvar. How can a man be sure to
possesse any thing in his owne Country, vnlesse hee proui∣deth
to repell the enemie that commeth against it; There∣fore
that is a very mellifluous saying of one of the Fathers,
<HI>Sumptus pro militia honorabilis est,</HI> the cost for vvarfare is
very honourable, for it is a meane to defend our liues, ly∣berties
and lyuings, and to preserue our wiues and chil∣dren.
Miserable are those men that will not strayne them∣selues
at a pynch to defend these, vvhen of couetousnesse
by sparing cost, they may be constrayned to forsake all.</P>
<P>2 Of their Seruice, others are grieued at VVarres, be∣cause
they must then leaue their wiues, children &amp; goods,
or rather because they must hazard theyr liues? Far better
it is for one to venture his lyfe like a man, then to be killed
in his house like a beast; Is it not better to hazard the lyfe
of one in an house, then in forbearing to fight, to bring in
daunger the whole familie? The diuine Philosopher saith,
<HI>Nascimur pro Patria,</HI> we are borne for our Countrie, and
therefore we must regard our Prince and common-weale
more then our owne priuate liues. 2, Sam. 10, 12. VVee
haue example in <HI>Iudith,</HI> who for the good of her Country,
put her life in great hazard in the host of <HI>Olofernes,</HI> let not
the courage of a woman condemne the humanitie of a
man; for that is a reproch. Ierem. 51, 30. VVho can dye a
more honorable death then for his Countrie, therfore we
shall reade that amongst the <HI>Romaynes</HI> there were the <HI>Deci∣ans,
Codrians,</HI> and the brethren called <HI>Phileni,</HI> and amongst
the <HI>Grecians,</HI> there were <HI>Marathonia, Salanina,</HI> and diuers
<PB REF="12"/>
others, who of their owne accord gaue their liues for their
Countries. <HI>D. P. Martir in Com. Rom. Brutus</HI> for the
preseruation of his Countrie, did slay his owne children.
<HI>Virgil</HI> thus writeth of him; <HI>Vicit amor patriae, &amp;c.</HI> Let not
vs which be Christians haue lesse loue and aleageance then
Heathens.</P>
<P>From hence there is a good note to be obserued of such,
who by vnequall oppressing and ill intreating, may be the
cause of this kind of griefe, therefore they are to consider
how they may for their owne priuate displeasures oppresse
and abuse men vnder colour of some lawfull busines.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Iniury &amp; anger may be of∣fered
and effected vnder.
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 Office.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Arte.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 Vnder office by these two,
<LIST>
<ITEM>A Magistrate.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Captayne.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>By a Magistrate, amongst the Romaynes, the Senators
were called <HI>Patres conscripti,</HI> appoynted Fathers: for a
Magistrate is nothing but a father of the Country, yet such
an one as hath deriued authoritie for these causes, as no
man doubteth but hee may show much fauour where he
affecteth, so all men may know if hee beareth a grudge to
one, he may meete with hym vnder colour of his Commi∣sion
many wayes; He may rayse him in the Subsedie with∣out
equalitie: he may pack him forth for a common Soul∣diour,
though he be vnfit, he may ouer-charge hym with
Supplyes, &amp;c. He may in other matters remember hym, as
in extreame taxations for the poore, in vnreasonable rate∣ments,
for a Towne, &amp;c: Albeit I knowe not (and I pray
God there be not) such, yet it may fall out to be true which
<HI>Alexander</HI> sayde to <HI>Mammea,</HI> there is nothing sometyme
<PB REF="13"/>
more pernitious to a common wealth, then to haue things
done by Deputies. <HI>D. Mar. in com. Rom. cap. 12, fol.</HI> 418.</P>
<P>VVee haue examples in the Scriptures, of such as haue
coloured their owne malice and dyspleasures, vnder pre∣tence
of some lawfull busines.</P>
<P><HI>Haman</HI> had a priuate malyce against <HI>Mordecai,</HI> because
hee would not moue hys cap or doe hym reuerence, hee
would not for shame seeme to reuenge it himselfe, though
he were in great office, but he thought he would be euen
with hym vnder colour of the Kings busines by some de∣uise
or other, as you may reade in Ester, 3, 8, &amp;c.</P>
<P>The Rulers and Gouernors had a secret spite to <HI>Daniell,</HI>
because he was far in fauor with the King, yet they would
not offer hym an immediat bad measure, but they consul∣ted
among them selues, to moue the King to make a Law,
that by colour thereof, they might haue theyr myndes of
good <HI>Daniell.</HI> Dan. 6, 8, &amp;c.</P>
<P>If any of our Magistrates should colour theyr own pry∣uate
malyce vnder the Queenes busines, although theyr
secret pretence be no more known to her Maiestie, then
the intendment of these practises were to the Kings, yet by
these examples let them feare, least their dooings come to
lyght, as the other dyd (albeit they deserue not so fearefull
a punishment as befel those) that they purchase displeasure
of theyr Prince, vvho cannot abide to bolster such abuses.</P>
<P>By a Captayne, who knoweth not how such as be ex∣perimented
professors of Armes being in office and acti∣on,
are a kind of protection for the tyme to certayne per∣sons;
for this cause when <HI>Dauid</HI> vvas a Captayne in warre,
there gathered to hym all men that were in trouble, and
all men that were in debt, and all those that vvere vexed
in mind, and he vvas their Prince or Captayne, 1, Sa. 22, 2.
Besides, it is not to be spoken howe many waies they may
<PB REF="13"/>
pleasure a man in vvar, if they be vvilling; yet on the con∣trarie
if a Captayne be offended at his Souldier and beare
hym in the splene, he may quyte it vnder colour of hys of∣fice:
hee may make martage of hym, hee may vvearie hym
with vvants and discurtesies, hee may cause him to end his
dayes in euery light skirmishe; He vvas a VVarriour that
sayd so himselfe, and no meruaile, for we haue an example
of it in the Scriptures, <HI>Ioab</HI> did of purpose place <HI>Vriah</HI> in
the fore-front of the battell, that he might be slaine by the
Philistims: <HI>Vriah</HI> and all the Host were ignorant of the
murderous intent, but <HI>Ioab</HI> did it vnder colour of his of∣fice,
because hee was a Captaine. That God which seeth
the secrets of the hart did behold this homicide, &amp; hee left
not him vnpunished which procured it; The acte vvas
doone in secrete to auoyde shame amongst men, but the
punishment was publique, that it might bee example to o∣thers.
VVhich example may be a warning to all VVarri∣ors,
to teach them to take heede how they reuenge theyr
owne priuate displeasures, vnder the colour of theyr law∣full
callings. 2, Sam, 12, 12.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>2 Vnder Art, by such as these
<LIST>
<ITEM>Chirurgi∣ans, Phisitions &amp; diuers other</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>These men, if they bee angry with a man (especiallie if
he be their patient) they may effect it vnder colour of their
Arte or practice: but because it is impertinent in this place
to speake of, I will pretermit it.</P>
<P>Ioy, as we haue heard of some which are sorry, so there
be others which reioyce to heare of vvarres.</P>
<LIST>
<PB REF="14"/>
<ITEM>This sinister Ioy is com∣monly
incident to these
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 Martiall attendants.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Desperate persons.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 Vnskilfull persons.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 Martial attendants be such as these
<LIST>
<ITEM>Decayed souldiers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vnder officers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVarlike workmē.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Decayed Souldiers, such as depende vpon warres, they
are welcome to them, for they perceiue the world is come
to this passe, that as the Phisition is but little regarded but
in time of sicknes, so Souldiers are but little set by but whē
there is neede of theyr seruice; Certes it is pittie that anie
approoued Souldier should be put to shifts. Valorous <HI>Cae∣sar</HI>
would neuer suffer it in his time; misery may constraine
a man too much; but yet for any to reioyce when there is
common cause of sorrow, and for his owne priuate com∣moditie,
to desire a generall calamitie, the one argueth his
dissolute minde to God, and the other bewrayeth him to
be a bad member to his Country. I would haue such men
as these consider, that the vse of many things may be good
though the things thēselues be naught. M. <HI>Caluin</HI> to that
effect sayth, <HI>Purus est multarum rerum vsus, quarum vitiosa
est origo. Cal. in Math. cap. 5, verse</HI> 37. The vse of manie
things is pure, whose originall is impure. From hence I
infer, that although the vse of a Souldiers is necessary, yet
to professe a souldier (as <HI>Erasmus</HI> sayth) is of it selfe the
puddle and sincke of all mischiefe; For to lyue by spoyles
and spilling of blood what life more miserable; Besides, it
is nothing delectable to God, but rather maketh any lesse
acceptable in some good action, as we reade of <HI>Dauid,</HI> who
<PB REF="14"/>
was not onely a valiant, but a vertuous warrior, but when
he went about to builde the Temple, the Lord sayde hee
should not, because he had been a man of warre, and had
shed blood. 1, Chro, 28, 3.</P>
<P>Vnder officers, such as may reape any profit in theyr
places, as Clarks of Bands, which may get some benefite
by the Booke, by entering, altering, or quitting of Soul∣diers:
these are glad of warrs for gayne sake. Notable is
that example of <HI>Gehasi</HI> for this purpose; <HI>Elisha</HI> was a good
man, hee dyd a notable cure in the Syrian Captaine for
meere good will without any gyfts, but his seruant <HI>Gehasi</HI>
without his knowledge, would needes take a brybe. VVe
haue many godly Lieuetenants and Captaines in Europe,
who although they themselues respect rewardes no more
then <HI>Elisha</HI> did, yet such as be vnder them (without theyr
priuities) perhaps like <HI>Gehasi</HI> doe looke to get some-vvhat
that way, to be gratified one way or other. But as <HI>Gehasi</HI>
for his couetous act was afterward turned away by his
Maister, with a grieuous punishment, 2, Kings 5, so let
these take heede least theyr dooings be discerned by their
Maisters, and they be put out of office with displeasure, as
<HI>Gehasi</HI> was.</P>
<P>VVarlike workmen, such as lyue by making, mending,
or selling of Armour, warres are welcome to them, for as
the Lawyers thriue best when men are most litigious, so
are they in time of warre most set to worke, for in tyme of
peace they profit not; Therefore, as some bad Lawyer
doth secretly wish that men would be contentious, that he
might haue Clyents, so it fareth vvith these kinde of men,
they vvish warres, that they may haue vvorke: they care
not vvhose house be on fire, so theyrs be safe, they grieue
not at warre, because it is sent for a punishment, but they
reioyce at it, because it is occasion of theyr profit.</P>
<P><PB REF="15"/>
2 Desperate persons, such as haue nothing to loose,
nor wyfe or chyldren to looke to, they are glad of warres,
all Countries are a lyke to them, hab, nab, fall backe, fall
edge, all is one to them, vvhether they be friendly foes to
the enemy, or deadly enemies to their Country; so they
may shift, they care not what shift they make; they laugh
when they see others lament, it doth them good to see o∣ther
men waste their goods, because they haue nothing:
they will rayle, and doe hope to raigne ouer rich me one
day; they will not let to say they looke to bee owners of
theyr lyuings, &amp; to haue their possessions when they shall
liue in pouerty; As we read of the besieging of Ierusalem,
how the rich were killed or made captiues, but as for the
poore, they were left still liuing, &amp; the enemie gaue them
the Vineyards and Fieldes of the rich men. Iere. 39, 6, 10.</P>
<P>3 Vnskilfull persons, they reioyce at war because they
know not what it is, as the Phylosopher saith, <HI>Dulce bellum
inexpertis,</HI> warre is sweete to such as neuer taste it, because
in ordinary traynings, they vse to skirmish for theyr lear∣ning:
or in theyr May-games for delight; They thinke
warre to be a matter of merriment. Alas, it is an easie mat∣ter
to play <HI>Hercules</HI> in our houses, or <HI>Alexander</HI> vppon the
stages: but it is somewhat to follow thē in the field, where
euery bullet doth threaten death.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="part">
<HEAD>2 Who is the Author of Warre.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>VVe must cōsider that there is
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 A speciall Author.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 A manuall Author.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 THE speciall Author is GOD, as appeareth by
his owne speech, when hee saith: I will sende
<PB REF="15"/>
plagues vpon them, the sword shall kill them without, and
in the Chambers feare. Deut, 32, 22, 25. It is said in the Pa∣rable,
that the King sent foorth his VVarriors. Math, 22, 7.</P>
<P>The Israelits confessed all their afflictions to come of
God: for (say they) he hath spoyled vs, and hee will heale
vs, he hath wounded vs, and he will binde vs vp. Hos. 6, 1.
He is therfore called the Lord of Hosts, because hee ruleth
and raigneth our all hosts.</P>
<P>2 The manuall Author, to our apprehension is the E∣nimy,
because wee perceiue the Spanyarde maketh great
preparation, and purposeth to come against vs; Many of
vs take him to be the Author, in that he appeareth to be
the Actor. <HI>Augustine</HI> saith well, they which make vvarre,
are not so much th Authors as the Ministers of God, <HI>Aug.
10. quest. super Iohn:</HI> for he is both the Passiue, Missiue, &amp;
motiue Author, as appeareth by pregnant examples in the
Scriptures.</P>
<P>He is the Motiue Author, for he mouth and stirreth vp
the Enemie, or els he could not come. The Philistims and
Arabians came against Iuda, to destroy it, yet they came
not of their owne accord, for it is written, the Lord styr∣red
vp against <HI>Iehoram</HI> (the King of Iuda) the spirit of the
Philistims: 2, Chro, 21, 16. The Medes &amp; Persians made
warre against Babilon, thys was not their owne voluntary
act, for the Lord had sayd before, I will styr vp the Medes
against it. Esay, 13, 17. Therefore we may gather frō these
examples, that if the Spaniard with his confederates bend
their forces to vs, it is not altogether his own seeking, but
God which exciteth him to it; For as <HI>P. Martyr</HI> sayth, It is
God that stirreth vp cruell Princes &amp; Tyrants, which may
be called the host of God. <HI>In com. Rom.</HI></P>
<P>He is the Missiue Author: for after he hath excited the
Enimy, he sendeth him, or els he could not approch. The
<PB REF="16"/>
Chaldees, Aramites, Ammonites, and Moabites besieged
Iudah, their comming consisted not in their own election,
for it is written the Lord sent against him (that is the King
of Iudah,) bands of the Chaldees, bands of the Aramits,
&amp;c. 2, Kings, 24, 2. <HI>Nabuchadnezar</HI> with his power came a∣gainst
Ierusalem to destroy it, the choyse was not in him
to tarry or retyre, for the Lord had said before, I wil send
them. Ierem, 25, 9. Now, if the Spaniard hath a purpose
to come against vs, it is in God to dispose: his comming li∣eth
not in his owne liberty, but the Lords.</P>
<P>He is the Passiue Author: for albeit he first stirreth, and
afterward sendeth the Enimy, yet he can do nothing whē
he is come, without Gods sufferance. The Israelits had
grieuously transgressed, for which cause they fell into the
hands of theyr enimy: the enemy could not haue preuai∣led
without Gods permission; for it is written that God
deliuered them into the hands of spoylers that spoyled
them. Iudg. 2, 14.</P>
<P>Sith it is God that stirreth, sendeth and suffereth the E∣nimy
to doe his good pleasure, they are but his seruants, as
the Lord termed <HI>Nabuchadnezer</HI> his seruant, Ierem, 27, 6.
Or his instruments, as <HI>Esay</HI> calleth them, the weapons of
his wrath, chap, 13, 5. And they are so fitly called, because
the Lord doth make them serue him by constraint, &amp; that
which they doe of malice, hee directeth and turneth it to
his honour and glory; so that frō hence we may conclude
that God is the speciall Author of VVar.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>In that God is the
Author, we may ob∣serue
three thinges,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 His power by the effects.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 His displeasure by the action.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 His loue by the end.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><PB REF="16"/>
1 His power by the effects, though Kings and Princes
are as Gods vpon earth, yet there is a God aboue them,
who can brydle theyr wills as hee will: this should teach
vs to relie vpon God: for admit the Spanyard hath a pur∣pose
to come against vs, yet this is our comfort, hys heart
is in the handes of God, whose power is such, that if it be
hys good pleasure, hee can alter the determination of the
Spanyard, before he setteth forth to fight, as he did by <HI>Re∣hoboam,</HI>
when hee was bent to vvarre against the <HI>Isralites.</HI>
1, Kings 12, 24: He can intercept his comming when hee
is vpon the Seas, and drowne hym, as he did <HI>Pharaoh</HI> and
hys host. VVhen hee is about our Coastes, hee can put a
hooke into hys nostrils, as hee dyd by <HI>Senacherib,</HI> and
make hym returne that vvay he came, 2, Chro. 32, or hee
can dispierce and scatter them into vnknowne Coastes, as
he dyd by the Spanyard his last viage. Such is the power of
God, as one of the auncient Fathers saith, that there is not
any thing done, but that he would haue to be done, either
suffering it to be done, or hee hym selfe doing it. <HI>August.
lib. voc. Enchiredion ad Laurentium.</HI></P>
<P>2 Hys displeasure by the action; for it is an argument
of his anger, and therfore you shall reade in the Scriptures,
that God neuer sendeth vvarre but in his vvrath, the Lord
him selfe speaking of Ierusalem vvhich vvas besieged by
the enemie, sayth: In my wrath I smote thee. Esay 60, 10.
In the 2, and 3, Chapters of the Iudges, the Lord sent and
set the Enemie against the <HI>Isralites,</HI> many tymes: It appea∣reth
in those places that hee neuer dyd it, but vvhen hys
vvrath or anger was kindled against them: Now the anger
of God is grieuous, for the Prophet sayth of hym, that he
smote the people in anger vvith a continuall plague. Isaiah
14, 6. <HI>Salomon</HI> sayth that the Kings wrath is like the roring
of a Lyon, Pro. 19, then what is his vvrath, who is King
<PB REF="17"/>
of Kings, thys should moue vs to take thys course, wee see
when the Prince is displeased vvith hys vassaile, he vvill vse
all meanes to pacifie hym, for feare hee shall be cast cleane
out of fauour, so should vve when vve perceiue the anger
of God is kinled against vs, seeke all possible wayes to ap∣pease
hym, for feare he giue vs ouer to the lust of our Ene∣myes,
and therefore let euery one of vs pray vvith <HI>Daniell,</HI>
and say as he dyd in the lyke case; O Lord according to all
thy righterusnesse, I beseech thee let thyne anger and thy
wrath be turned away, Dan. 9, 16.</P>
<P>3 Hys loue by the end, that father which doth chastise
his child for hys faults doth loue him, euen so our heauen∣lie
father which doth correct his children for theyr offen∣ces
doth affect them, and as the rod is a readie meanes to
brydle and reclayme chyldren from vntowardnes, so is
vvarre a good scourge to make vs remember our misdeeds,
and seek to God. The Lord (speaking of the <HI>Isralites)</HI> saith,
in theyr affliction they vvill seeke me diligently, Hos. 5, 15,
and the Prophet <HI>Dauid</HI> saith: it is good for me that I haue
been afflicted for this reason, that I may learn thy statutes,
Psa. 119, 71. VVe see by experience that the child vnlesse he
be sometime beaten, he falleth to all vnbrideled loosenesse,
so it fareth vvith vs, if we should not sometime feele Gods
afflictions, vvee should runne into all filthynesse, euen as
the Psalmist saith, before I was afflicted I went astray. Psal.
119, 67: Therefore let vs beare Gods punishment with pa∣tience,
for as gold is purified by the fire, so are we refined
by afflictions, and as the Bee conuerteth into honie, that
vvhich the spyder doth to poyson, so that vvhich the ene∣mie
doth of euill, God turneth it to our good.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>In that the Enemies are Gods ser∣uants
wee may note two thinges.
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 A Lymitation.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 A Reprehension.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><PB REF="17"/>
1 A Lymitation, vve commonly see that Seruants are
worse many tymes then theyr Maysters; the Steward in
Mathew dealt well with his Seruant, but he dealt extream∣lie
vvith others. Math. 18, 28: the Lord vseth the Spaniard
as a spur to prouoke vs to amendment, but it may be sayd
of hym, as of <HI>Ashur,</HI> but he thinketh not so, neyther doth
hys heart esteeme it so, but he imagineth to destroy. Isaiah,
10, 7. for he commeth with a resolute purpose, to execute
his owne crueltie, and not to the ende to please God. Yet
this is our comfort, he is but Gods Seruant, and therefore
he can doe no more then God will permit &amp; appoint him,
no, though he were as bad as the deuill: for you see howe
satan could do no more to <HI>Iob</HI> then GOD suffered him to
doe. Iob, 1.</P>
<P>2 A reprehension, this concerneth vs, wee are readie
to rayle and curse the Spanyard that molesteth vs, but in
the meane time, we do not remember he is Gods seruant,
which if we did, we woulde not so much respect the eni∣mie,
as he that sendeth him; The Spanyard no doubt ban∣neth
and curseth vs to the pit of hell, as we terme it, what
then, let vs forbeare him by the example of <HI>Dauid,</HI> who
being cursed of <HI>Shimei,</HI> a wicked man, hee put it vp pati∣ently,
because, (saith he) the Lord did bid him curse, 2, Sa.
16, 10. If a Noble mans man abuse vs in words, wee will
beare with him the more for his Lord and Maisters sake:
much more ought we to beare with the seruants of God;
VVe must not imitate euill by the example of the wicked,
though they be incited &amp; suffered to curse, we haue grea∣ter
cause to thanke GOD if he hath giuen vs grace to re∣fraine.
Besides, it is but a vvindie conquest is got vvith
words, therefore you shall reade when <HI>Dauid</HI> vvas to deale
with <HI>Goliah,</HI> this Giant did curse and scorne him in deri∣sion;
<HI>Dauid</HI> digested his words with silence, but he praied
<PB REF="18"/>
and prepared himselfe to incounter with him to some pur∣pose.
Let vs follow his course, what though the Spaniard
doth curse vs and scorne vs as <HI>Goliah</HI> dyd <HI>Dauid,</HI> let vs for∣beare
him, (for wee can speede neuer the better for our
speeches,) but let vs like <HI>Dauid</HI> prepare our selues to repell
him.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="part">
<HEAD>3 Wherfore Warre is sent.</HEAD>
<P>THere are many thinke warre to be a thing of course,
because it hath been common in all ages, whereas it
is most certaine, that God neuer sendeth any crosse
without cause.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>The cause of warre is double,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 Secondary.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Efficient.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 The Secondary cause is that we ascribe to outwarde
meanes, and instant occasions: as for example in other
things, if we haue any losse of goods, we vse to say it came
by casualtie of fire, shypwracke vpon the Seas, &amp;c. Or if
we get a sicknes, we tooke it by such a iourney, or of such
a colde &amp;c. And so in this sence we commonly say vvhen
we haue vvarrs, it is the malice, pryde or impietie of the
Enimy that causeth it. VVhen in the meane time we doe
not consider who it is that exciteth, sendeth, offereth or
suffereth such motions or meanes to effect, and for what
cause he doth it.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>2 The efficient cause of
warre is of two sorts,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 For Correction.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 For Reformation.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 For Correction, as a scourge or punishment for sin,
which the God of hosts himselfe affirmeth, when he saith,
<PB REF="18"/>
If he sinne I will chasten him with the rod of men, 2, Sam,
7, 14. And the Psalmist to that effect sayth: If they break
my statuts, then will I (speaking in the person of GOD)
visite theyr transgressions with the rod: Psal, 89, 32. It is
written in the Chronicles, that the King of Egipt came vp
against Ierusalem, because they had transgressed against
the Lord: 2, Chro, 12, 2, and so if the Spaniard commeth
against vs, we must perswade our selues that our sinnes are
the chiefe cause of it.</P>
<P>But whether God sendeth warre to vs for our ingrati∣tude,
for our last deliuery from the Spaniard, as he dyd to
<HI>Hezekiah</HI> for his vnthankfulnesse when he was deliuered
from <HI>Senacherib,</HI> 2, Chron, 32, 25, or whether it be for our
oppression and cruelty, as hee did to the Israelites for the
like sinnes, Ierem, 6, 6, or whether it be for any grosse sins
amongst vs, as he did to the Babilonians for theyr barba∣rous
beastlines, Esay 13, or whether it be for our murmu∣ring
at this Scarcitie, or for the hardnes of our harts to the
poore in this extreame time, God knowes; some grieuous
sinnes there be that prouoke the Lord, for else he would
not visite vs, two yeares together vvith Scarcitie, and the
third yeare threaten vs with warre.</P>
<P>2 For Reformation, that warre is sent to reforme and
amend vs is manifest; Behold, famine, plague, anguish &amp;
trouble, are sent as scourges for amendement: 2, Esd, 16, 15.
The father doth chastise his sonne, not because he taketh
pleasure in punishing of him, but that he may by it brydle
and amend him; Euen so GOD the Father correcteth vs
which be his children, not because hee delighteth in pu∣nishment,
but to the end he may therby reclaym vs frō our
iniquities. As the rod of wood is a meane to make the vn∣toward
childe gracious, so is the rod of warre an instigati∣on
to mooue vs to good: as it is saide of Iudah, Lorde in
<PB REF="19"/>
trouble haue they visited thee, they poured out a prayer
when thy chastening vvas open them; Esay, 26, 16. And
therfore God dealeth with vs as a Phisitian: A good Phi∣sitian
will cease from ministring phisick to his patient whē
he is recouered; or as a Maister, who will stay from stry∣king
his seruant when he is growne better by his beating.
So God, he desisteth his punishments so soone as wee are
profited by them. I will recite one example in steed of ma∣ny,
the Lord raised vp <HI>Shisshake</HI> to scourge <HI>Rehoboam</HI> for
his sinne, but the text sayth, Because he humbled himselfe
the wrath of the Lord turned from him; 2, Chro, 12, 12.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>From the matter precedent
wee may obserue two things,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 A grieuous cominatiō.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 A notable consolation.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 A grieuous comination, by the correction if wee re∣pent
not: for if we perseuere in our sins, what foloweth?</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Punishments
<LIST>
<ITEM>Temporall.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Eternall.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Temporall punishments: for the Lord sayth to such, I
will set my face against you, and yee shall fall before your e∣nimies,
and they that hate you shall raigne ouer you. Leu.
26, 17. Let vs make this case our own: what a heauy iudg∣ment
were this, if the Lord (for our committing and con∣tinuing
in sinne) should frowne vpon vs when the Spani∣ard
commeth with his force against vs, &amp; should suffer him
to preuaile as the Medes &amp; Persians did in Babilon, would
he not deale as they did, of whom it is said: their chyldren
shall be broken in peeces before theyr eyes, theyr houses
shall be spoyled, and theyr wiues rauished, Esay, 13, 16.</P>
<P><PB REF="19"/>
VVere not this a lamentable sight to beholde, and to haue
him to raigne ouer vs that hateth vs what a miserable bon∣dage
were it? vvho would not think but that this punish∣ment
were grieuous and sufficient: but if we stil perseuere,
the Lord wil stil pursue vs, for he saith; If yee will not for
these things obey me, then will I punish you seauen times
more, according to your sinnes; Leuit, 26. As we see hee
delt by <HI>Pharaoh,</HI> he neuer left of his plagues so long as hee
liued impenitent; Thys may teach vs howe grieuous a
thing sinne is with perseuerance.</P>
<P>Eternall punishments, the temporall plagues are but an
enterance to these. <HI>Hoc suspicari &amp;c.</HI> sayth <HI>Gregory,</HI> a man
cannot suspect howe extreame those paynes are. Such as
perseuere in wickednes, let them remember what <HI>Paule</HI>
sayth, They doe but heape vp wrath against the day of
iudgement, Rom, 2, 5. As <HI>D. Martir</HI> sayth vvel vpon that
place, a hard hart is that which wil not be mollified with
Gods benefits, woon with hys mercyes, broke with hys
threatnings, nor reclaymed with his punishments.</P>
<P>The Heathen men had thys naturall fore-sight for the
restraint of sinne; The Lidians would haue in theyr hou∣ses
the picture of a deuill in forme of an Ethiopian, that by
the horrible sight, they might abhor that which brought
him to it, which was sinne. The Persians would paynt an
Epicure disguised with excesse, that theyr chyldren might
auoyde the like fault, by seeing that deformitie. The La∣cedemonians
would shew theyr youths drunken and de∣sperat
men, that they might be deterred from sinne, by the
lothsomnes of that sight; If Christian men, would set be∣fore
them the horror of hell, it would make them feareful
to practise euill, much more to perseuere in it. For thys
cause <HI>Chrysostome</HI> willeth vs to talke often of hell, that wee
may take heede of it.</P>
<P><PB REF="20"/>
2 A notable Consolation, by the Reformation, if wee
take profit by this punishment, in reforming our lyues and
lyuing in the feare of God. The Spaniarde may perhaps
feare-blast vs with his Armie, but he shall neuer preuaile in
his attempt; for the Lord saith of such: the Sworde shall
not goe through your Land, yee shall chase your enimies,
and they shall fall before you vpon the sword. Leuit, 26.
Although the Lord hath prepared the Spaniard to come
against vs, and had pronounced to punish vs, yet his pe∣nall
promises are but conditionall, for if we repent, he re∣penteth;
(If (saith hee) this Nation against whom I haue
pronounced, turne from theyr wickednes, I will repent of
the plague that I thought to bring vpon them, Ierem, 18, 8,
therefore let vs all pray for the grace of repentance, and
labour to shew forth the fruites of it.</P>
<P>Such as haue oppressed and bitten their bretheren with
extreame bargaines these hard yeeres, let them make some
amends; The Ethnicks required double restitution, Zac∣cheus
made foure-fold restitution, Luke, 19. Salamon tel∣leth
vs of a seauen-fold restitution, Prou, 6, and therefore
they may do little if they make not some restitution. Such
as haue carried theyr heads as hie as Lucifer, let them now
holde downe their heads like Bulrushes. Such as haue
ground the faces of the poore, let them doe good to them
thys time of Scarcetie, not onely for commandement sake,
as <HI>Sirach</HI> sayth, Ecclus, 37, but euen for pollicie sake: for
you know what Salomon sayth: In the multitude of the
people is the honour of a King, but for the want of people
commeth the destruction of the Prince, Prou, 14, 28. If
God should send the enemie against vs, the most defenci∣ble
strength of the Land consisteth in the poore, for they
are subiect to most seruice and greatest dangers; VVee see
thys hard season that the poore begin to pine alreadie, be∣cause
<PB REF="20"/>
they want the stay and staffe of theyr strength, which
is bread; Now, if we would haue them to fight for vs, let
vs not see them famish; if we would haue them forcibly to
vse theyr weapons, let vs not infeeble them for want of
victuals; If we would haue them strong, let vs not starue
them. How can a souldier bee hardie against the enemie,
when his hart is killed for want of succour? therefore if
we loue our Prince, let vs labour to preserue the honor of
our Prince, let vs not suffer the multitude of her people to
perrish for want of sustenance, least if the Spaniarde hap∣pen
to come, wee haue misse of those men to defend vs,
which for want of our foode did famish.</P>
<P>Generally, seeing all sinne is odious, and the naming of
it tedious, let euery one of vs amend one: so by our true
contrition, we shall pacifie the Lord, and cause him to ap∣pease
the furie of our foes.</P>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="subpart">
<HEAD>1 How to debilitate and repell the
Enemie.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>The meanes which
we must vse, are two
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 Diuine,</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Humaine.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>The diuine meanes be these
<LIST>
<ITEM>Inuocation,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Abstinence.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>INuocation, as a learned vvryter sayth, is that vvhereby
we flye vnto God in all perils and aduersities, with an
assured confidence that he is able to succour and defend
vs, <HI>D. Martir in Com. Ro. cap.</HI> 1. This inuocation or pray∣er
we ought to practise as a thing most precious. First, be∣cause
<PB REF="21"/>
it is the forme to frame al our requests by: let your re∣quests
be shewed vnto God by praier, Phil. 4, 6. Secondly,
because we are willed to vse it in our distresse for ease. Call
vpon me in the time of trouble, &amp; I wil heare thee. Psal. 50,
15. Thirdly, because it effecteth many things. <HI>Moses</HI> did
more good in lyfting vp his handes, then the Israelites dyd
with theyr weapons, for when he did let down his hands,
the Amalekites preuayled. Exod. 17, 11. Fourthly, because
he wee call vpon is the God of Hostes, and therefore vve
haue many reasons to moue vs to pray to him: for first, he
must prepare our hearts therevnto, or else we cannot pray.
VVe cannot thinke a good thought, 2, Cor. 3: neyther
say that Iesus is the Lord, 1, Cor. 12, 3. Then much lesse
can vve pray vvithout hym. Secondly, his power is infalli∣ble,
and therefore he is such an one as we may stay vpon.
<HI>Abiah</HI> got the victory of <HI>Iehoram,</HI> not vvith worldly pow∣er,
but the text sayth, Iudah preuayled, because they staid
vpon the Lord God, of their fathers, 2, Chro. 13, 18. Heer∣of
<HI>Dauid</HI> sayth, blessed is the man that maketh the Lord
hys trust. Psal. 40, 4, 3. Hys prouydence is vigilant, and
therefore is alvvayes readie at hand to helpe, the Lord is
neere vnto all that call vpon hym, sayth the Psalmist, Ps.
145, 18. He maketh vs pertakers of his essentiall presence.
VVhen <HI>Iehoshaphat</HI> was to fight against his enemies, what
a comfort vvas this to him, when he heard, the Lord will
be vvith you, 2, Chro. 20, 17, and fight for you, as he did
for Israel. Iosh. 10, 14. Fourthly, without hym wee can
do nothing, and therefore we haue neede to pray to him.
The Horse is prepared against the day of battell, but salua∣tion
is of the Lord. Pro. 21, 31. There is no hope of pros∣perous
successe, if the Lord sayth the Enemie shall gather
hym selfe but vvithout me, Esay 54, 15: whereas if he be
with vs, vve are assured none can be against vs or hurt vs,
<PB REF="21"/>
2, Chro. 18, 31.</P>
<P>Thys prayer or inuocation is so heauenly a medecine
for humaine malydies, that our fore-fathers dyd flye vnto
it, as a refuge, vvhen theyr enemies afflicted them. Nowe
because we may haue the lyke occasion of trouble as they
had, it shall not be impertinent to expresse some of theyr
zealous prayers, for vs to practise in the like extreamitie.</P>
<DIV4 TYPE="prayers">
<HEAD>Examples and formes of godly prayers,
vsed in vvarres.</HEAD>
<P>WHen the Ethiopians came to vvarre against <HI>Asa,</HI>
that godly King, the text saith that he cried vnto
the Lord his God and sayd:</P>
<P>Lord it is nothing with thee to helpe with many,
or vvith no power, helpe vs ô Lord our God: for
we rest on thee, and in thy name are vvee come a∣gainst
thys multitude, ô Lord thou art our God, let
not man preuayle against thee, 2, Chro. 14, 11.</P>
<P>The Lord heard hys prayer, for it followeth in these
words. So the Lord smote the Ethiopians before <HI>Asa.</HI></P>
<P>VVhen the Assirians came to assault Israel, the Scripture
sayth that <HI>Hezekiah</HI> prayed before the Lord and sayd:</P>
<P><Q>O Lord God of Israel, vvhich dwellest betweene
the Cherubins, thou art very God alone, ouer all
the kingdomes of the earth, thou hast made the
heauen and the earth, nowe therefore ô Lord our
God, I beseech thee saue thou vs out of hys hand,
that all the kingdomes of the earth may know, that
thou ô Lord art onely God,</Q> <BIBL>2, Kings 19.</BIBL></P>
<P>His prayer preuailed with the Lord: for it is there writ∣ten,
I haue heard that vvhich thou prayedst me, verse 20.
<PB REF="22"/>
VVhen the Moabites and Ammonites dyd war against
<HI>Iehoshaphat,</HI> that vertuous King, he prayed vnto the Lord
and sayd:</P>
<P><Q>O our God, vvilt thou not iudge them: for there is
no strength in vs, to stand before this great multi∣tude
that commeth against vs, neither do we know
vvhat to doo: but our eyes are toward thee,</Q> <BIBL>2,
Chro. 20, 12.</BIBL></P>
<P>Hys prayer had good successe: for hee ouer-threw all
hys Enemyes.</P>
<P>VVhen <HI>Lysias</HI> came vvith a multitude of men against
<HI>Iudas,</HI> when he saw that mighty Army, he praied and said.</P>
<P><Q>O Lord shut vp this Armie, in the hand of thy peo∣ple,
and let them be confounded, with theyr power,
make them afrayd and consume theyr boldnesse and
strength, that they may bee astonished at theyr de∣struction.
Cast them downe by the sword of them
that loue thee, then shall all they that know thy name
prayse thee,</Q> <BIBL>1, Macch. 4, 31.</BIBL></P>
<P>Hys prayer was not neglected of the Lord: for he slew
many of the host of his Enemie.</P>
<P>Let vs follow thys course, when the Spanyards come a∣gainst
vs, and we shall receiue the like comfort, their pray∣ers
were pithie and short, vvithout vayne babling, lyke the
Heathen, or ambition lyke the Pharisies, but the profite
which came of theyr peticions vvere vnspeakeable.</P>
<P>In the time of the olde lawe, it vvas not onely a trouble
but a charge, to offer sacrifice to God; for there vvas kil∣ling
and offering of Bullockes, Calues, Sheepe, &amp;c. But
now the Lord requireth nothing of vs, but the calues of
our lips, as <HI>Hosea</HI> speaketh on, Hos. 14, 3, or the fruite of
the lips, as the Author of the Hebrewes sayth, <HI>Cap.</HI> 13, 15.
Therefore we may do little if we will not afford our lips to
<PB REF="22"/>
pray vnto God, so it proceedeth from the hart, otherwise
as <HI>Augustine</HI> sayth, <HI>Oratio sine deuotione est quasi mugitus bouis.</HI>
Prayer vvithout deuotion is as the lowing of an Oxe. But
if it be sincere, then as <HI>Caluine</HI> sayth, it is an honourable
sacrifice to God. <HI>Cal. cap. 4, 1. Epist. ad Timotheum.</HI></P>
<P>Abstinance is the second diuine meane to vse, I do not
note thys, as a distinct action by it selfe, but as a necessarie
appendant to accompanie prayer: for although prayer is
bettered by fasting, yet fasting is of no force without pray∣er,
therefore in the Scriptures they commonly concur to∣gether,
Luke 2, 36.</P>
<P>Our fore-fathers vvould vnite fasting and prayer toge∣ther
in all their afflictions, eyther priuatlie with theyr fa∣milies,
as <HI>Daniell</HI> dyd, <HI>Cap.</HI> 9, 3. and <HI>Dauid</HI> dyd, 2, Sam. 1,
12, vvhen it specially concerned them selues; or else pub∣liquelie,
when it generallie toucht a vvhole land: as vvee
reade of <HI>Iehoshaphat,</HI> how hee proclaymed a fast through
all hys dominions, vvhen the Enemies dyd threaten the
sword, 2, Chro. 20. whose example vvee ought to immi∣tate,
because he was a godly Prince.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>This Fasting ser∣ueth
for a double vse
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 To fortifie the Spyrit.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 To mortifie the flesh.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 To fortifie the Spirit, for by fasting the Spirite hath a
more free passage vnto prayer: the reason is, because the
sences beeing filled, are inclined to sluggishnes, according
to the old saying: <HI>Impletus venter quarit dormire libentur.</HI>
Therefore we shal read how <HI>Dauid</HI> in many of his psalmes
saith; Early or betimes in the morning will I direct my
prayer vnto thee ô Lord: because his prayer was most fer∣uent
when he was fasting; wherby wee may see that cor∣porall
emptines is a furtherance to spirituall exercises.</P>
<P><PB REF="23"/>
2 To mortifie the flesh from sinning; the ground the
more it is manured, it bringeth forth more weedes, so the
flesh, the more it is pampered, it is the more pron<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to wic∣kednes:
and therfore as the strongest Castle is soone taken
if the souldiers want sustenaunce, so the raging lustes are
soone subdued if the flesh be not fostered. For thys cause
the Psalmist sayth: I humbled my soule with fasting, Psal.
35, 13, which is the onely fruite of fasting. Therefore as
<HI>Bernard</HI> sayth: <HI>Si oculus offendit, ieiunat oculus:</HI> if the eye of∣fend,
let it fast: that is if it hath beene before inclined to
wanton lookes, (as <HI>Dauids</HI> was when hee beheld <HI>Bersaba)</HI>
let it now refraine; and so in the rest of the members, as
they haue done amisse to let them amend; For true fasting
(as <HI>Basil</HI> saith) requireth a suppressing of anger, and cutting
of carnall concupiscence; And then as <HI>Ierome</HI> sayth, is fa∣sting
most excellent to GOD, <HI>Cum aliquis ieiunat a vitiis,</HI>
when any doth fast or refraine from sinne.</P>
<P>The Hypocrite, he will fast for vaine-glory, the Coue∣tous
man to spare expence; the Glutton to get him a sto∣mack:
but let vs fast to crucifie the lusts of the flesh, to mi∣tigate
sinne. If <HI>Eue</HI> had fasted from the tree, we neede not
thys fast, saith <HI>Basil.</HI> VVe haue many reasons to restraine vs
from sinne, but by the imminent occasion, if the Spaniard
happen to approch, we haue 2. speciall reasons to refraine
from euill at that instant. First, our principall strength cō∣sisteth
in God, and therefore wee must sue and seeke vnto
hym by prayer. Now, if we will gladly obtaine that wee
aske, we must willingly abstaine from that hee abhorreth.
Let euery one that call vpon GOD, depart from iniquitie
sayth Paul, 2, Tim, 2, 19. so that there is nothing can hin∣der
our sute but sin. Secondly, if we desire good successe
against the Enimy, if it happen otherwise, we may impute
it to our sin. VVhen <HI>Iosua</HI> sent men to besiege <HI>Ai,</HI> some of
<PB REF="23"/>
them were slaine by the enemie, and the rest that returned
were discomforted, only for the sin of one man. Iosu, 7, 12.
The Lorde neuer suffered the enimies to preuaile against
the Isralites in time of war, but when they had committed
some notable sins: Iudg, 3, 12. And if any thing falleth out
otherwise then wel amongst vs by the Spaniard, wee must
think we haue some grieuous sinns that cause it, or els you
shall reade in the scriptures, that the godly (which ser∣ued
the true God as we do) had seldome or neuer any bad
successe in their battels when they were beset with theyr
enemies, but by occasion of some heynous actions: and
therefore it was not without cause that <HI>Moses</HI> made thys
lawe or exhortation for souldiers; VVhen thou goest out
with the Host against thine enimies, keepe thee then from
all wickednes. Deut, 23, 9.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>2 The Humaine meanes be these
<LIST>
<ITEM>Politicall,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Instrumentall,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Patheticall.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>The politicall meanes belong specially to the Prince and
high powers, for good consideration &amp; consultation to be
taken in so weighty an attempt. VVhen <HI>Hezekiah</HI> saw that
<HI>Senacherib</HI> purposed to fight against his country, thē (saith
the text) he tooke counsel with his Princes &amp; his Nobles,
2, Chro, 32, 3. For as <HI>Salomon</HI> saith, VVhere no counsell is,
the people fal, but where many Counsellers are, there is
health, Prou. 11, 14. The Parable in Luke fitlie aludeth to
thys purpose, vvhere it is sayd, vvhat King going to make
warre against an other King, sitteth not down first and ta∣keth
counsell, whether he be able with tenne thousand to
meet him that commeth against him with twentie thou∣sand,
Luke 14, 31. <HI>Iosua</HI> at the first tooke a foyle of the men
of <HI>Ai,</HI> because hee sent not aboue 3000. men: but after∣ward,
well consulting of the matter, and seeing the enimy
<PB REF="24"/>
so strong, he sent aboue thirty thousand men, and then he
vanquished them, Iosu, 7, &amp; 8. It was not amisse spoken by
a wicked King, that counsel and strength are for the vvar,
2, Kings 18, 20, for power little preuaileth without coun∣sell,
or prowesse without policie; for what weighty ex∣ployts
haue been atchiued abrode, but by good aduise at
home? the ouerthrowe of Carthage was wrought by the
aduise of <HI>Cato</HI> a Counseller; Iericho was besieged of the
Iewes by the wholsome counsel of <HI>Iosua,</HI> Ios, 6. Diuers o∣ther
examples there be in the Scriptures to thys purpose,
but I will omit them; all that I will add is thys, seeing God
standeth in the congregation of the Gods, as the Psalmist
sayth, I beseech him so to sanctifie theyr counsels, as it may
turne to our good, and his glory.</P>
<P>The instrumentall meane, as men and munition, must
not be neglected, although God can destroy the enimy im∣mediatly,
as he did the host of <HI>Senacherib,</HI> or miraculouslie,
as he did Iericho by the meanes of Rams hornes: and the
Moabites by dazeling theyr sight with the sun-shine vpon
the water, 2, Reg, 3, 22, and <HI>Pharaoh</HI> and his host by the red
Sea; yet we must vse the lawfull &amp; ordinary course of de∣fence;
for God doth not now strike immediatly, or so mi∣raculously,
but by meanes, to the end we should not con∣temne
the meanes, or altogether depend vpon the means,
Esay, 31, 1, but to vse and commende the meanes to Gods
blessing, who can giue good successe, be the meanes ne∣uer
so simple.</P>
<P>The patheticall meanes are to bee vsed by such as haue
the regiment or conduct of souldiers, to encourage and
comfort them, for flesh and blood is fearefull. The best
VVarriors of al wil somtime be abashed, and therefore no
meruaile though the common sort be somwhat timorous.
For this cause we find diuers instances in the scriptures, of
<PB REF="24"/>
Generals, Captaines, and worthy warriors, who haue vsed
very pathetical and moouing speeches, to comfort and in∣courage
theyr companies in war.</P>
<P>It is sayd of <HI>Hezekiah,</HI> that he spake comfortablie to hys
people, when the Assirians intended to assault hym, hys
wordes are these: Bee strong and couragious, feare not,
neyther be afrayd, for the King of Ashur, neyther for all
the multitude that is with hym: for there be more with
vs then with hym; vvith hym is an arme of flesh, but with
vs is the Lord our God for to helpe vs, and to fight our
battayles, 2, Chro. 32, 7, 8. The people hearing these
comfortable speeches (although before they vvere some∣what
afrighted) the next sayth, then the people vvere con∣firmed,
by the words of <HI>Hezekiah. Ioab</HI> was a valiant Cap∣tayne
vnder <HI>Dauid,</HI> and he comforted hys Souldiers in this
sort: Be strong, &amp; let vs be valiant for our people, and for
the Citties of our God, and let the Lord doo that vvhich is
good in his eyes, 2, Sam. 10, 12. Albeit <HI>Ioab</HI> was otherwise
in hys lyfe, a bloodie man, not onely in vvarre, but in time
of peace, 1, Kings 2, 5, yet who could vse a more com-mo∣uing
kind of speech, to comfort and incourage hys Soul∣diers
then this? insomuch as they all ioyned together ioy∣fullie,
and put the enemie to flyght. The lyke course did
<HI>Simon</HI> and <HI>Maccabeus,</HI> two notable vvarriors vse with their
Souldiers, vvho being terrified with the view of mightie
Armies, and other martiall accidents, by theyr apt perswa∣sions,
they proued valorous, where before they vvere ti∣morous,
and in the end discomfited theyr Enemies, as you
may reade at large in 1, Macch. 3, and 2, Mach. 8.</P>
<P>The most renowned and valiantest vvarriors amongst
the Heathen, as <HI>Caesar, Alexander,</HI> &amp;c, vvould neuer goe
into the field without Phylosophers (who in theyr tymes
were deemed the onelie vvise men) to the end they might
<PB REF="25"/>
instruct and comfort theyr Souldiers. It is none of the
least poyntes of martiall discipline, to practise all possible
and perswasiue meanes, to incourage, comfort, and corro∣borat
the hartes of the Souldiers; for most men desire to
serue vnder such a Captayne. VVhen the Iewes heard the
comfortable vvordes of <HI>Simon,</HI> they were so inclined and
affected to hym, that they forth-with burst out of these
words in a clamorous manner. Thou shalt be our Cap∣tayne
in steede of <HI>Iudas,</HI> 1, Mach. 13, 8, and wee reade of
<HI>Dauid,</HI> how he did so win the harts of hys Souldiers, that
the people more affected and famozed hym then <HI>Saul;</HI> and
yet <HI>Iudas</HI> and <HI>Saul</HI> vvere two valiant vvarriors. There is
nothing more delighteth and draweth lyking in vvarre,
then lenitie, and louing perswasions, vvhereas rash and ri∣gorous
dealing, doth more hurt in the harts of the Souldi∣ers,
then in the host of the Enemie.</P>
</DIV4>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="subpart">
<HEAD>2 How to corroborate and comfort our
selues against the Spanyard.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>In all warres wee must
consider three things.
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 The cause,</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 The persons,</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 The end.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 The cause that moueth
the Enemie, whether it be
<LIST>
<ITEM>Iust,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iniurious.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>IVst warre is that which is taken in hande at the com∣maundement
of the Magistrate, for the demaunding of
things againe, or to repulse iniuries, or to reuenge them.
<HI>Augustine,</HI> and <HI>Isidorus,</HI> define it much after thys manner.
No man doubteth, but that the Magistrate is to command:
for he beareth not the sword for nought, therefore <HI>Possi∣donius</HI>
<PB REF="25"/>
in the life of <HI>Augustine,</HI> sayth, that he in his writings
would neuer commend those, vvhich went to warre in
any place, of theyr owne accord, <HI>Poss. cap.</HI> 27. The de∣maunding
of things agayne, moued <HI>Abraham</HI> to attempt
warre, because the enemies had taken away hys brother,
and other mens substance, Gen. 14, 14. To repulse iniu∣ries,
vvas the chiefe cause, that moued all godlie Kings in
the Scriptures to vndertake warre, for the desence of their
dominions, liues, and religion. The reuenging of iniurie
was <HI>Dauids</HI> case, whose men beeing abused by <HI>Hanun,</HI> to
whom hee offered kindnesse, thys iniurie caused hym to
make vvarre against hym, to requite hys inhumanitie, 2,
Sam. 10, 7. Now let vs come to applie thys to the Spany∣ard,
we deteine nothing of hys, that he can iustly demand,
or proffer hym iniurie, that he may rightlie seeke reuenge,
therefore hys cause is not iust. Iniurious vvarre is that
which is attempted of malyce, as <HI>Saul</HI> dyd against <HI>Dauid,</HI>
2, Sam, 18, 9. Or of pryde or such like impious occasions,
it is this that dooth prouoke the Spaniard in spyte to come
against vs; therefore his cause is iniurious, for as <HI>Hostiensis</HI>
sayth, He doth ill that taketh war in hand of will, and not
of necessity.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>VVhere there is iniury, we
must obserue, whether it be
<LIST>
<ITEM>Offered,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Defended.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>If it be offered, his offence is grieuous that doth it: for
the scripture saith, woe be to him that giueth the offence.</P>
<P>If it be defended, hee doth not sin that suffereth the in∣iury;
besides, as D. <HI>Martir</HI> sayth, a Christian is not forbid
but that he may repell violence by violence, <HI>in com. Ro.</HI> 12.</P>
<P>The Spanyard he offereth iniury, wee defend it, hee as∣saulteth
vs, we withstand him, he vrgeth war voluntarily,
<PB REF="26"/>
we are prouoked of necessity; hee sinneth in offering in∣iury,
and not we in defending it, so our mindes incline to
peace, though our bodyes are constrayned to war, there∣fore
thys is our comfort, if the Spaniard commeth, hys
cause is not iust but iniurious, vvhich may make vs the
more bold to buckle with him, and hope to haue the bet∣ter
successe, because his violence is voluntary, ours, impul∣satory.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>2 The persons that make warre are
to be regarded, whether they bee
<LIST>
<ITEM>Prophane,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Godly.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>The Spaniard is a pro∣phane
person two wayes,
<LIST>
<ITEM>In Life.</ITEM>
<ITEM>In Religion.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>In his life I will note but two things, first his pride, se∣condly,
his crueltie. His insolence is well knowne to the
world, insomuch as that report of Moab may be applied to
him, which is written in Esay 15. VVee haue heard of the
pryde of Moab, he is very proude: and therefore vnlesse
God be merciful to him, hee may in the somtome of hys
pryde come to as miserable an end as Moab. Hys crueltie
is intollerable where he doth tyrannize, for he is far worse
then <HI>Nero. Nero</HI> for all his cruelty, when hee was to sub∣scribe
to a sentence of death, would wish hee could not
write, but the Spaniard, he careth no more to shed blood
then the Butcher, and therefore in his enterprize hee may
be fearefull by the example of <HI>Pharaoh,</HI> who carrying so
murderous a minde, by destroying chyldren in the water,
that in the warre where he thought to worke his will, he
was drowned himselfe by water; let him take heed, least
the Lord doth make him shed teares without mercy, as he
hath shed blood without measure.</P>
<P>In religion, the Spaniard is like the Leopard, ful of spots;
<PB REF="26"/>
A spottish and sottish profession is that which derogateth
the glory of God, for the whole action of idolatry, &amp; the
substance of superstition is common in his Country; such
crouching to crosses in the streets, such adoration of Ima∣ges
in the Churches, such mumbling of Masses, Diriges,
Trentals, and such like trumperies, which would make a
good Christian lament to looke vpon, which they delight
to practise and depend vpon. Hee is worse then <HI>Pharaoh,</HI>
for he made much of <HI>Ioseph,</HI> because hee was a good man,
but he can neither abide the person or profession of a god∣ly
man. He is worse then the Turke, for he wil not refuse
to receiue the Bible, much lesse persecute such as present
it to him; but the Spaniard is so great an enemie to God,
that he doth imprison the bodyes, confiscate the goods, &amp;
inflict other punishments vpon such as bring but a godlie
booke into hys Country; insomuch as there appeares to
be no sparke of godlines in him: because he reiecteth the
meanes that might effect some good in him.</P>
<P>Sithence the Spaniard is but a prophane person, let vs
discend to examples for our comfort, and we shal see from
time to time, how the wicked in theyr warres against the
godly, haue alwayes got repulse &amp; ouerthrow in the end.
That wicked <HI>Pharaoh</HI> which long troubled and tyranni∣zed
ouer the good Israelites, in his last assault of warre a∣gainst
them, he was so far from effecting his furie, that the
Lord drowned him &amp; all his host vpon the red Sea. VVell
woorthy was hee to be drowned in the water, who had
caused many chyldren to be cast into the Riuer, Exo, 1, 22.
That blasphemous <HI>Senacherib,</HI> who disturbed <HI>Hezekiah</HI> a
godly king, in the end the Lorde did punish him, not me∣diatly,
but immediatly, by sending his Angell into his
Camp, who smote many thousands of his men; and as for
<HI>Senacharib</HI> himselfe, as hee had dealt vnnaturally against
<PB REF="27"/>
God, so he was not long after vnnaturally put to death of
his owne chyldren.</P>
<P>That peruerse generation of the Moabites &amp; Amonits,
made warre against that vertuous King <HI>Iehoshaphat,</HI> they
vvere so far from preuailing, that GOD made one enemy
to be executioner to another; 2, Chro, 17.</P>
<P>That irreligious Ethiopian which molested <HI>Asa,</HI> that
tovvard plant and Prince, at the last hee did not onely put
the Ethiopian to flight with a fevve, but also got him by
pursute, and had his will of him. 2, Chro, 14.</P>
<P>Similitude and example, doth much moue saith <HI>Cicero,</HI>
for vvho cannot be cōforted by so godly examples. <HI>Qui∣tilian</HI>
sayth, that histories and examples be iudgements and
testimonies; for who cannot beholde the iudgements of
GOD by these examples? <HI>Augustine</HI> saith, that examples
ought to be as Sermons to vs: for as godly Sermons doe
minister matter for our edification, and consolation, so doe
these examples in thys sort.</P>
<P>First, we may learne from hence, howe the godlie are
subiect to many sorrowes, as <HI>Dauid</HI> sayth: The troubles of
the righteous are many, Psa, 34, 19, for there are euer some
ambitious and rebellious kinde of people that stir vp strife
and sedition against them, therefore wee must not thinke
much though the Spaniard set himselfe against vs.</P>
<P>Secondly, we may see from hence, although God doth
suffer the wicked to assault and disturbe the godly, yet hee
vvill not suffer the enemy to preuaile: therfore this is our
comfort, so long as wee feare God and liue in some mea∣sure
answerable to it, the Spaniard may well come, but he
shall neuer accomplish his will.</P>
<P>Thirdly, wee may behold by these examples, that albeit
God doth vse the wicked as his instruments or seruaunts,
yet he dooth not affect any euill, or fauoureth theyr mali∣tious
<PB REF="27"/>
intents. He affecteth no ill, because in the ende hee
afflicteth such as commit it: Prou, 24, 20. He doth not fa∣uour
theyr malicious intents, because hee gyueth thē bad
successe in theyr attempts.</P>
<P>3 The End, which ought to be aymed at in VVar, is
not victory but peace: for as Christians would neuer vvar
if they might possesse peace, so when they be constrayned
to warre, they desire peace; as <HI>Dauid</HI> sayth of his enemies,
I seeke peace, and when I speake thereof, they are bent to
vvarre, Psalme, 120, 7. Thys contradicteth Aristotle, who
concludeth, that as the end of phisicke is health, so the end
of vvarre is victory.</P>
<P>But let vs discend to the Spaniard, to see what end hee
aymeth at; he commeth not hether to enrich vs with his
Indian treasure, or to supply vs with his Spanish warres, or
to make amends for his proffered iniuries, or to offer con∣ditions
of peace, but the end of his comming is especially,</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>for these three causes,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 To attempt VVarre.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 To inuade the Land.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 To destroy vs.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 To attempt warre: for it may be sayd of hym, as of
<HI>Asshur,</HI> vpon vvhom hath not his malyce past continually.
Nah. 3, 19. For he warreth and disquieteth many Nations,
as he loueth, so he laboureth to shed blood: Yet in thys
action, he showes a base minde, for all he is so ambitious a
man, vve commonly say he is no man that vvill fight with
a woman: for if he doth vanquish, he can haue no great
glory, if he be ouerthrown, he taketh great shame; There
is a pretie instance for thys purpose in <HI>Abimelech,</HI> who be∣ing
about to set a Tower on fire, a woman cast a peece of
milstone vpon his head, and broke hys brayne-pan; <HI>Abi∣melech</HI>
called hastelie for hys Page, and bad hym drawe his
<PB REF="28"/>
sword to slay hym, that men might not say of hym, a vvo∣man
slewe hym, Iudg, 9, 54. If the Spanyard dyd beare
the minde of a man, he would neuer molest a woman, a
Virgine, a Queene, whose lyfe and religion is a light to all
the world, vvhose disposition and dayes requier quiet, but
as God brought <HI>Sysera</HI> that wicked person to death, by the
hand of <HI>Iael</HI> a woman, Iudg. 4, 22, and <HI>Olifernes</HI> to de∣struction,
by the hand of <HI>Iudith</HI> a woman, and <HI>Abimelech,</HI>
to hys ende, as you haue heard by a woman, so his mercy,
can make her Maiestie powerful, by some meanes or other,
to spoyle the Spanyard; hee vvhich hath deliuered her
from so many secret villanies at home, vvill protect her
from the open violence of her Enemies abroad.</P>
<P>2 To Inuade the land: hys meaning is not to view it,
but to inuade it, he carryeth a resolute intent to enter, be∣fore
he knowes the issue: for in hys last vyage he made he∣ther,
he presumed of a conceited conquest, and bewrayed
hys sinister pretence, before he was assured of his purpose.
The Iewes dyd not cast lots for Christes garments, tyll he
was crucified, but the Spanyard and hys company did cast
dyce for our lyuings, before they had tryed the euent.</P>
<P>3 To destroy vs, thys was one commendation <HI>Cicero</HI>
gaue <HI>Caesar,</HI> that when he had vanquished, hee would be
mercifull and forget iniuries, <HI>Alexander</HI> that magnanimi∣ous
minded vvarrior, when he might haue hys will of hys
Enemyes, would say it suffized hym to tryumph, though
he dyd not tyrannize. If heathen men were so inclyned to
mercie, much more ought Christians, the very law of arms
affordeth mercy to such as be submissiue, but what fauour
is to be expected of hym, whose affections be not seasoned
with the feare of God? The Spaniard pretendeth to Eng∣land,
as <HI>Pharaoh</HI> dyd to <HI>Israel,</HI> when he sayd, I will deuide
the spoyle, my lust shalbe satisfied vpon them, I will drawe
<PB REF="28"/>
my sword, myne hand shall destroy them. Exod. 15, 9.
God deliuer vs from hys malyce, we may not trust to hys
mercie: for as the ground dyd fare the vvorse for <HI>Abime∣lech,</HI>
because it was fruitfull, so shall we by the Spanyard,
because of our profession: He made the ground barren by
sowing of salte, Iudg. 9, 45, thys, hopes to hynder the
growth of the word by shedding of blood, the truth is, he
would take away our liues, to roote out our religion; but
as <HI>Salomon</HI> sayth: He that despiseth the word, he shall be
destroyed, Pro. 13, 13. So thys is our comfort, God will
take our cause in hand: for as <HI>Iehoshaphat</HI> sayd, so may we.
It is Gods battell and not our, 2, Chro. 20. Hee will not
permit such to preuayle, which haue any pretence to im∣payre
hys glorie.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="subpart">
<HEAD>3 The most fearefull obiections confu∣ted,
which make against vs.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>There be two things which
make vs doubt the vvorst,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 The power of the enimie,</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Some sinister ciuil practise</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1 THE power of the Enemie, without question is
great, it may be he shall haue the ayd of the In∣dians,
the asistance of the Pope, and perhaps
the helpe of such as haue greater cause to gratifie vs, then
be against vs. Alas good England, thou art inclosed in a
corner of the world, many are thy Enemies, because God
is thy friend; thou hast not many Nations to combyne
with thee, yet thys is thy comfort, if thou dost relie vpon
God, he is able to delyuer thee from all. There were fiue
Kinges set against <HI>Abraham,</HI> Gen. 14, and as many agaynst
<HI>Ioshua.</HI> Iosh. 10, 16: yet <HI>Abraham</HI> and <HI>Ioshua</HI> got the vic∣torie.
Some aledge that the spanish Nauie is mighty, both
<PB REF="29"/>
in regard of hys long tyme of preparation, as of hys last
euersion, which will make him come the more forceable,
for feare of a double foyle. To thys I aunswere, though
hys Nauie were innumerable, and he should arrogate this
tytle, as he dyd last time, that it is an inuincible Nauie, yet
for all his great power and pride, God can deale with him
now as hee dyd then, not onelie to dispierce and scatter
them in vnknowne Coastes, but also make the Spanyard
lyke <HI>Senacherib,</HI> returne with shame to hys owne Land, 2,
Chro. 32, 21. Admit hee comes with many millyons of
men; yet wee must consider that hee intrudeth into hys
Ships all sortes of people, some that came neuer at Sea, o∣thers
that cannot away with the Sea; now who knowes
not that such as be weather-beaten and cannot brooke the
Seas, are so infeebled, that when they come to the pynch,
they had more neede of Phisitions to looke to them, then
furniture to defend them. A more morrall reason is thys,
be he neuer so mightie, it is but an arme of flesh, they can
do no more then men; If God be with vs he can do more
then men. If we be penitent for our sinnes, and depende
vpon him, it is not the Nauie or number of men of the E∣nemie
can iniure vs: for as it is written in Leuiticus, vvee
shall be able with one thousand men, to chase away twen∣tie
thousand, Leuit. 26. VVee haue examples of it for our
comfort.</P>
<P>The Madianites, and Amalakites, and many of the East,
of whom it is vvritten, lay in valleis lyke Grashoppers in
multitude, and theyr Cammels were vvithout number, as
the Sand is by the Sea-side, Iudges 7, 12. All these came
against the Captayne of the Isralites, who had but three
hundred men, and yet he discomfited them.</P>
<P><HI>Zerah</HI> came with ten hundred thousand men, and three
hundred Charrets, against <HI>Asa,</HI> who had but fiue hundred
<PB REF="29"/>
foure-score thousand men, yet he incountred with him &amp;
ouer-came them, 2, Chro, 14.</P>
<P><HI>Augustine</HI> vpon the 13, psalme <HI>con:</HI> 2. sayth, Hee is trulie
valiant vvho is not strong in himselfe but in the Lord. Our
chiefe valure consisteth in God, but the confidence of the
wicked in theyr power, Esay, 31, 1, 2. GOD in iudgment
doth punish such as stande vpon theyr owne strength, but
in mercy he protecteth those which haue a trust in him in
theyr troubles.</P>
<P>2 Some sinister ciuill practice. Thys is the common
saying: if we be true within our selues, we neede not care
or feare the enemy. Many suspect the Papists. The wic∣ked
many times will suspect the godly, and therefore it is
not amisse for Conformolists to suspect Recusants. <HI>Pha∣raoh</HI>
that wicked tyrant, feared and suspected the Isralits,
for (sayth he,) Come let vs worke wisely with them, least
they multiply, and it come to passe that if there be vvarre,
they ioyne themselues also vnto our enemies, and fight a∣gainst
vs: Exod, 1, 10. Therefore it is good policie where
there be suspicious persons, to preuent the occasions that
may effect theyr ill pretence, by restrayning theyr libertie,
deteyning theyr armor, not admitting them to any office
in Armes, &amp;c.</P>
<P>If two dogs be stryuing for a bone, when they see the
Beare, they will both forsake the bone to flye vppon the
Beare: and certes (though the comparison be some-what
grosse) I take it, albeit the Papists iarre about matters of
Religion, yet when they see the Spanyard, they wil ioyne
with vs against him, if it were but to saue theyr liues. <HI>Pi∣late</HI>
and <HI>Herod</HI> were at great ods about priuate matters be∣tween
them, but when they had to deale with Christ, they
could then become friends, &amp; conioyne together for hys
destruction, Luke, 23, 12, then much more ought the Pa∣pists
<PB REF="30"/>
for all theyr opinions, reconcile themselues and ioyne
with vs against the Spaniard, who deserueth death more
then Christ. The dog will fawne of his Maister, but barke
at strangers, farre worse were they then dogs, if they doe
not affect theyr Prince, and fight against her enemies.</P>
<P>In Ierusalem there were some irreligious persons, as bad
as <HI>Nabuchadnezer</HI> himselfe, yet when hee besieged it, hee
killed and captiuated all sauing a fewe poore, which were
left to looke to the grounds, 2, Reg. 24, euen so let the Pa∣pists
thinke, if the worst should fall (as God defend,) the
Spaniard will deale as <HI>Nabuchadnezer</HI> did, he wil not spare
a Papist though he be a Papist: (but he will rather suppose
it is done of policie to possesse life) and therefore in this re∣gard
they should arme themselues against the enemie, be∣cause
they are like to speed no better thē we, if he preuaile.</P>
<P><HI>Themistocles</HI> had rather die then beare Armes against his
Country; VVhat more neere to any then his natiue coū∣try?
For thys cause I reade of <HI>Zeno,</HI> who being taken by a
Tyrant, and enioyned to tortures, he bit out his tongue &amp;
spit it in the Tyrants face, for feare the extreamitie of the
payne should make him confesse any thing against his
Country. Let these Heathen men excite vs to carrie true
harts to our Country, for as <HI>Paedanius</HI> saith, he that betraies
his Country, is worse then he that besiegeth it.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Treason hath been odious in all ages,
<LIST>
<ITEM>To Man,</ITEM>
<ITEM>To God.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>To Man it is odious. <HI>Antigonus</HI> the King, woulde al∣wayes
say, I loue Traytors so long as they are in betraying,
but when they haue betrayed I hate thē. <HI>Ierome</HI> to <HI>Pam∣machius</HI>
sayth: that Princes doe indeed admit treason, but
<PB REF="30"/>
they condemne the Traytors. <HI>Hier. de optimo genere in∣terpretandi.</HI></P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Many betray their
country in hope of
<LIST>
<ITEM>Preferment</ITEM>
<ITEM>Reward</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loue
<LIST>
<ITEM>of the Enemie.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Yet commonly they fayle in theyr purpose, and receiue in
steede of preferment reproch, in steede of reward, punish∣ment,
and in steed of loue, hatred.</P>
<P>As for preferment, we reade of <HI>Lasthenes,</HI> who when
he had betrayed hys Countrie to King <HI>Phillip</HI> of Macedo∣nia,
he expected to haue had some preferment and digni∣tie
for hys deede, but the common Souldiers in derysion,
called hym euer after by no other name but TRAY∣TOR:
insomuch as he complayned to King <HI>Phillip</HI> for
redresse, the King made hym thys aunswere, the Macedo∣nians
are rude and playne people, and knowe not how to
call things, but by theyr own proper name, noting heere∣by
that as he had committed treason, so he iustly deserued
no other name but Traytor.</P>
<P>As for Reward, we read of certayne Phaliscian Schole∣men,
vvho hoping of reward, went about to betray theyr
Countrie to <HI>Camillus:</HI> vvho rewarded them as they deser∣ued,
for hee commaunded that they should be brought
home agayne, into theyr owne Countrie, with the strypes
of theyr own Schollers, because they would haue betray∣ed
them. <HI>Menelaus</HI> presumed of some reward, vvhen hee
sought to betray his Countrie to <HI>Eupator,</HI> so hee had, for
he commaunded he should be put to death for his desert,
2, Mach. 13.</P>
<P>As for Loue, vvee reade of the King of the Thraciaris,
who in hope of fauour, fell from <HI>Anthonie,</HI> to <HI>Augustus,</HI>
which afterward he boasted on, in the presence of <HI>Augustus</HI>
and others; but <HI>Augustus</HI> turned hym to hys friend, and
<PB REF="31"/>
sayd, I loue the Treason but the Traytor I commend not.
<HI>Plutarch,</HI> King <HI>Pyrhus</HI> Phisition promised to the Romayns,
that he would for theyr sakes, worke treason agaynst hys
King and Countrie, they were so far from fauouring hys
ill pretence, that they dyd detect hym to his King, that he
might take heede of hym; that example of <HI>Iudas,</HI> may be
pretelie heere-vnto applyed, the Iewes made of <HI>Iudas,</HI>
whilest he was a working the Treason, but vvhen he had
done, they made no force of him; for when he told them,
he was touched and disturbed for the treacherie, vvhat is
that to vs (say they) see thou to it, Math. 27, 4. A Traytor
may haue some kind intertaynement for the tyme, but he
shall neuer haue any matter of trust committed to him, for
he that will betray hys natiue Countrie, shall liue euer su∣spected
of falsehood in a forrayne Nation.</P>
<P>To GOD. Treason is an odious thing to God, and so
odious, that although it should passe vnpunished amongst
men, yet he will pursue a traytor himselfe with his iudge∣ments,
whereof we haue many examples in the scriptures.
<HI>Absalom</HI> committed treason against <HI>Dauid</HI> hys father, and
<HI>Zimri</HI> against <HI>Elah</HI> hys Maister, yet for all that, <HI>Dauid</HI> dyd
not punish hys Sonne, nor <HI>Elah</HI> hys Seruant, the Lord
shewed hys iudgments vpon them, for one vvas hanged
by hys owne haire, 2, Sam. 28, and the other burnt hym∣selfe,
1, King, 16, 18.</P>
<P><HI>Iason</HI> was a notable Traytor to his Countrie, and raun∣ged
lyke a roge or vagobond afterward from Countrie to
Countrie, he did escape the punishment of men, but God
still pursued hym, tyll at last comming to Lacedemonia,
where he had thought to haue had reliefe, he dyed most
miserablie, vvanting the last office of humanitie, which is
buriall, 2, Mach. 5, 7, 8, &amp;c.</P>
<P>There be many, yet I will but note one other worthie
<PB REF="31"/>
example. <HI>Iehoiakim</HI> betrayed and rebelled against <HI>Nabu∣chadnezzer,</HI>
a wicked King, this action so much displeased
the Lord, that he raysed vp many bands of men agaynst
<HI>Iehoiakim,</HI> to aflict hym for his treacherie, 2, King 24, 1. If
the Lord will punish such as worke treason against theyr
King, though he be a tyrant, vvhat will hee doo to those
that betray a good Prince, which mayntaynes the Gospell.</P>
<P>Sithence treason is so odious to God and man, as <HI>Barn∣herd</HI>
sayth, <HI>Aliorum perditio tua sit cautio,</HI> let other mens de∣struction
be our permonition, and let euery one of vs car∣rie
true harts to our Queene and Countrie; If it be a pu∣nishment
to haue a Tyrant to raigne, and a double punish∣ment
to haue hym taken away, Hosea 13, 11, (for better is
a Tyrant, then no gouernour, Iudg. 17, 6,) vvhat a bles∣sing
is it to haue a godlie Prince, as we haue, and a double
blessing to enioy her dayes as we doe, but how vnspeake∣is
our punishment, if we loose her; therefore let vs vnite
our heads, harts, and hands, and venture our own liuings
and liues for the preseruation, &amp; defence of such a Prince;
Then we may be fully resolued, (if we haue had vnfeyned
repentance for onr sinnes, and make defensible preparati∣on
for our selues, and vse feruent prayers for our successe)
that God will so blesse vs with the meanes, as we shall not
neede to feare the iniurious assault of that proud <HI>Senacha∣rib</HI>
of Spayne. Let <HI>Ahab</HI> call vpon <HI>Baal;</HI> the Turke vpon
<HI>Mahumet,</HI> in their troubles, and the Spanyard vpon Idols
in hys attempts, we wil pray and depend vpon the God of
Israel; And if <HI>Symachus</HI> boasted that in his wars his wood∣den
gods did deliuer him from the <HI>Senons, D. Mar. co. Ro.</HI>
we may be assured that our immortall and liuing God, can
and wil deliuer vs from the Spaniard.</P>
<Q><L>Chrysostome.</L>
<L>Incepisse multorum est, sed perfecisse paucorum.</L></Q>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

