<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Porta pietatis, or, The port or harbour of piety Exprest in sundry triumphes, pageants, and showes, at the initiation of the Right Honourable Sir Maurice Abbot Knight, into the Majoralty of the famous and farre renowned city London. All the charge and expence of the laborious projects both by water and land, being the sole undertaking of the Right Worshipfull Company of the Drapers. Written by Thomas Heywood.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A03242</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 13359</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S104071</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99839811</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99839811</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">4266</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A03242)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4266)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1488:16)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Porta pietatis, or, The port or harbour of piety Exprest in sundry triumphes, pageants, and showes, at the initiation of the Right Honourable Sir Maurice Abbot Knight, into the Majoralty of the famous and farre renowned city London. All the charge and expence of the laborious projects both by water and land, being the sole undertaking of the Right Worshipfull Company of the Drapers. Written by Thomas Heywood.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[20] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>Printed at London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>By I. Okes,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1638.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Partly in verse.</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</NOTE><NOTE>Running title reads: Londons gate to piety.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Abbot, Maurice, --  Sir, 1565-1642.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2002-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Rekeyed and resubmitted</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A03242">
<STC T="S">13359</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99839811</BIBNO>
<VID>4266</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Porta pietatis,
OR,
The Port or Harbour of Piety. Exprest in sundry Triumphes, Page∣ants,
and Showes, at the Initiation of the
Right Honourable Sir MAVRICE ABBOT
Knight, into the Majoralty of the famous
and farre renowned City <HI>London.</HI> All the charge and expence of the laborious Projects
both by water and Land, being the sole undertaking
of the Right Worshipfull Company of
the Drapers.</P>
<P><HI>Written by</HI> Thomas Heywood.</P>
<P><HI>Redeunt Spectacula</HI></P>
<P>Printed at <HI>London</HI> by <HI>I. Okes.</HI> 1638.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Right Honorable S<SUP>r.</SUP> <HI>Maurice
Abbot,</HI> Knight, the Lord Maior of this
renowned Metropolis, <HI>London.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Right Honourable:</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>Ntiquity informes us, in the most
flourishing state of <HI>Rome,</HI> of an
Order of the <HI>Candidati,</HI> so cal∣led,
because habited in white ve∣sture,
betokning <HI>Innocence,</HI> and
those of the noblest Citizens, who in that garbe wal∣ked
the streets with humble lookes, and submisse ge∣sture,
thereby to insinuate themselves into the
grace of the people, being ambitious after honour and
Office. Great Lord, it fareth not so with You, who
though for inward Candor and sincerity, You may
compare with the best of them, yet have beene so far
from affecting such popularity, that though You in
Your great Modesty would willingly have evaded
it; yet some places by importunity, and this Your
present Praetorship hath by a generall suffrage, and
the unanimous harmony of a free Election, beene
conferd upon You.</P>
<P><PB REF="3"/>Neither can I omit the happinesse of Your de∣ceased
Father, remarkable in three most fortunate
Sonnes: the one, for many yeares together, Arch-Bishop
of <HI>Canterbury,</HI> and Metropolitane of all
<HI>England:</HI> another, a reverend Father in God,
Bishop of <HI>Salisbury:</HI> as memorable for his learned
Workes and Writings, as the other for his Epis∣copall
government in the Church, and Counsell in
State. And now lately Your Honour'd selfe, the
Lord Maior of this Metropolis, the famous City
<HI>London:</HI> In which, and of which, as you are now
<HI>Maximus,</HI> so it is expected you shall prove <HI>Opti∣mus.</HI>
Grave Sir, it is a knowne Maxime, that the
honour which is acquired by Vertue, hath a perpetu∣all
assurance: nor blame my boldnesse, if I pre∣sume
to prompt Your memory in what You have long
studied: The life of a Magistrate is the rule and
square whereby inferior persons frame their carriage
and deportment, who sooner assimulate themselves to
their Lives than their Lawes, which Lawes if not
executed are of no estimation. But I cease further to
trouble Your Lordship, leaving you to Your Honou∣rable
charge, with that of the Poet,
<Q>Qui sua metitur pondera, ferre potest.</Q></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Lordships in all observance
<HI>Thomas Heywood.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Londini Porta
Pietatis:
Londons Gate to Piety.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">L</SEG>ONDON and WESTMINSTER
are two Twin-sister-Cities; as
joyned by one Street, so wate∣red
by one streame: the first a
breeder of grave Magistrates,
the second, the buriall-place of
great Monarchs; Both famous
for their two Cathedrals: the one Dedicated to the
honour of Saint <HI>Paul,</HI> the other of Saint <HI>Peter.</HI>
These I rather concatenate, because as in the one,
the Right Honourable the Lord Major receiveth
his honour, so in the other he takes his Oath: yet
<HI>London</HI> may be presum'd to be the elder, and more
excellent in Birth, Meanes, and Issue; in the first for
her Antiquity, in the second for her Ability, in the
<PB REF="4"/>
third, for her numerous Progeny: she and her Sub∣urbs
being decored with two severall Burses or Ex∣changes,
and beautified with two eminent Gar∣dens
of Exercise, knowne by the names of <HI>Artil∣lery</HI>
and <HI>Military.</HI> I shall not need to insist much
either upon her Extension, or Dimension, nor to
compare her with other eminent Cities that were,
or are, it having beene an Argument treated of by
Authentick Authors, and the laborious project of
many learned Pennes, and frequently celebrated
upon the like dayes of Solemnity.</P>
<P>And although by the space of Tenne yeares last
past, there hath not beene any Lord Major free
of that Company, yet was there within Twelve
yeeres before that sixe Lord Majors of the same.
And it shall not bee amisse to give you a briefe
Nomination of some Honourable Praetors, and
those of prime Remarke in that Company: Sir
<HI>Henry Fitz-Alwin</HI> Draper, was the first Lord Major
of this Citie, which place hee held for foure and
twenty yeeres together, and upward; and in the
first yeere of his Majoralty, <HI>Anno 1210. London</HI>-Bridge,
which was before made of Timber, was
begun to be built of Stone. Sir <HI>William Powltney</HI>
was foure times Lord Major; 1337 he built a Chap∣pell
in <HI>Pauls,</HI> where hee lyeth buried, and erected
a Colledge neere unto the Church of St. <HI>Laurence
Powltney, London:</HI> He moreover built the Church
of little <HI>Alhallows</HI> in <HI>Thames street,</HI> with other
pious and devout Acts. <HI>Iohn Hind</HI> Draper, Lord
<PB REF="4"/>
Major 1405, built the Church of Sr. <HI>Swithen</HI> by
<HI>London-stone, &amp;c.</HI> Sir <HI>Iohn Norman</HI> was the first that
rowed in his Bardge to <HI>Westminster,</HI> when hee went
to take his Oath: Sir <HI>Richard Hardell</HI> face in the
Judicatory Seate sixe yeares together: <HI>Simon Eyre</HI>
Lord Major, built <HI>Leaden-Hall</HI> at his owne proper
costs and charges: Sir <HI>Richard Pipe, George Monox,</HI>
Lord Major 1515, and Sir <HI>Iohn Milborne,</HI> were
great Erectors of Almes-houses, Hospitalls, &amp;c.
and left liberally to the poore: Sir <HI>Richard Campion</HI>
perfected divers charitable workes, left unfinish't by
Sir <HI>Iohn Milborne</HI> before named. Sir <HI>Thomas Hayes</HI>
1615▪ Sir <HI>Iohn Iolls</HI> 1616▪ Sir <HI>Edward Barkham,</HI>
Sir <HI>Martin Lumley,</HI> Sir <HI>Allan Cotten,</HI> Sir <HI>Cuthbert
Hacket, &amp;c.</HI> To speake of them all, I should but
spend Paper in a meere capitulation of their names,
and neglect the project now in agitation.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="tableau">
<HEAD>The first Show by Water.</HEAD>
<P>THe first Show by Water, is presented by <HI>Proteus</HI>
in a beautiful Sea-Chariot: for the better Orna∣ment,
decored with divers Marine Nymphs and
Sea-goddesses▪ &amp;c. He sitteth or rideth upon a mo∣ving
Tortois, which is reckoned amongst the <HI>Am∣phibiae,
quòd in ambobus Elementis degant:</HI> That is,
One of those Creatures that live in two Elements,
the <HI>Water,</HI> and the <HI>Land;</HI> alluding to the Trading
of the Right Honourable the present Lord Major,
who is a Merchant, free of the <HI>Turkey, Italian,
French, Spanish, Muscovy,</HI> and was late Gover∣nour
of the <HI>East Indy-Company.</HI> This <HI>Proteus,</HI> or
<PB REF="5"/>
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, that is, <HI>Primus,</HI> is held to be the first, or
most ancient of the Sea-gods, the Sonne of <HI>Ocea∣nus</HI>
and <HI>Thetis,</HI> who could transhape himselfe into
any Figure whatsoever, and was skilfull in Pre∣diction:
He was call'd <HI>Vertumnus à vertendo,</HI> be∣cause
he indented or turned the course of the River
<HI>Tyber,</HI> which floweth up to <HI>Rome,</HI> as the <HI>Thames</HI> to
<HI>London;</HI> he was a King, and reigned in the <HI>Carpa∣thian</HI>
Island, which because it was full of boggs
and marish places, (as lying neere unto the maine
Ocean) he had that Title conferr'd on him to be a
<HI>Marine god:</HI> when the <HI>Scithians</HI> thought to invade
him, and by reason of the former impediments
could no way damage his Countrey, it therefore
increased their superstitious opinion to have him
Deified. He was called also <HI>Pastor populi,</HI> that is,
<HI>A Shepheard of the people;</HI> and is said also to feede
<HI>Neptunes</HI> Fishes call'd <HI>Phocae.</HI></P>
<P>It was a Custome amongst the <HI>Aegyptian</HI> Kings,
to have their Scepters insculpt with sundry Hiero∣gliphicks,
or Figures, as a Lyon, a Dragon, a
Tree, a flame of fire, &amp;c. as their fancies lead
them, for which that Proverb was conferr'd in
him, <HI>Proteo mutabilior,</HI> that is, <HI>More changeable than
Proteus.</HI> This <HI>Proteus,</HI> or <HI>Vertumnus,</HI> or <HI>Vesores,</HI>
reigned in <HI>Aegypt</HI> some foure yeeres before the <HI>Tro∣jan</HI>
Warre, that is, <HI>Anno Mundi,</HI> 2752.</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="speech">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>Proteus his Speech.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><HI>PRoteus</HI> of all the <HI>Marine gods</HI> the prime,</L>
<L>And held the noblest both for <HI>Birth</HI> and <HI>Time:</HI></L>
<L>From <HI>him</HI> who with his <HI>Trident</HI> swayes the <HI>Maine,</HI></L>
<L>And ploughs the waves in curles, or makes them plaine:</L>
<L><HI>Neptune,</HI> both Lord of <HI>Ebbe,</HI> and <HI>Inundation▪</HI></L>
<L>I come to greete your great <HI>Inauguration.</HI></L>
<L>They call me <HI>Versi-pellis,</HI> and 'tis true,</L>
<L><HI>No</HI> figure, for me, <HI>no</HI> shape <HI>to me is new;</HI></L>
<L>For I appeare what Creature I desire,</L>
<L>Sometimes a <HI>Bull,</HI> a <HI>Serpent,</HI> sometimes <HI>Fire:</HI></L>
<L>" The <HI>first</HI> denotes my <HI>strength; strong must he be,</HI></L>
<L>" And powerfull, who aspire to your Degree.</L>
<L>" You must be wise as <HI>Serpents,</HI> to decide</L>
<L>" Such <HI>doubts</HI> as <HI>Errour</HI> or <HI>Misprision</HI> hide.</L>
<L>" And next, like <HI>Fire,</HI> (of th'Elements most pure)</L>
<L>" Whose nature can no sordid stuffe endure,</L>
<L>" As in <HI>Calcining Metalls</HI> we behold,</L>
<L>" <HI>It</HI> sunders <HI>and</HI> divides <HI>the</HI> drosse <HI>from</HI> Gold,</L>
<L>And <HI>such</HI> are the <HI>Decorements</HI> that still waite</L>
<L>Vpon so <HI>grave, so great</HI> a <HI>Magistrate.</HI></L>
<L>This <HI>Tortois, double-natur'd,</HI> doth imply</L>
<L>(By the two <HI>Elements</HI> of <HI>moist</HI> and <HI>dry</HI>)</L>
<L>So much as gives the world to understand,</L>
<L>Your noble <HI>Trading</HI> both by <HI>Sea</HI> and <HI>Land.</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Porposes</HI> the vast Heards <HI>Proteus</HI> keepes,</L>
<L>And I am styl'd <HI>the Prophet of the Deepes,</HI></L>
<L>Sent to praedict <HI>good Omen:</HI> May that <HI>Fleete</HI></L>
<L>Which makes th'<HI>East Indies</HI> with our <HI>England</HI> meete,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Prosper to all your hearts desires: Their sayles</L>
<L>Be to and fro swell'd with auspicious gales:</L>
<L>May <HI>You</HI> (who of this <HI>City</HI> now take charge)</L>
<L>With all the <HI>Scarlet Senate</HI> in your Barge,</L>
<L>The Fame thereof so heighten, future Story</L>
<L>Above all other States may crowne her glory.</L>
<L>To hinder what's more weighty, I am loath,</L>
<L>Passe therefore freely on, to take your Oath.</L>
</LG>
<P>This Show is after brought off from the water, to
attend upon the rest by Land, of which the first is,</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="tableau">
<HEAD>The first Show by Land.</HEAD>
<P>A Shepheard with his Skrip and Bottle, and his
Dog by him; a sheep-hooke in his hand, round
about him are his Flocke, some feeding, others
resting in severall postures; the plat-forme adorn'd
with Flowers, Plants, and Trees bearing sundry
Fruits. And because this Worshipfull Society tra∣deth
in Cloth, it is pertinent that I should speake
something of the Sheepe, who is of all other foure-footed
beasts the most harmelesse and gentle. Those
that write of them, report, that in <HI>Arabia</HI> they have
tayles three Cubits in length: In <HI>Chios</HI> they are the
smallest, but their Milke and Cheese the sweetest,
and best. The Lambe from her yeaning knoweth
and acknowledgeth her Damme: Those are held to
be most profitable for store, whose bodies are big∣gest,
the fleece softest and thickest, and their legs
shortest. Their Age is reckoned at Tenne yeeres,
<PB REF="6"/>
they breed at Two, and cease at Nine: The Ewes
goe with their young an Hundred and fifty dayes.
<HI>Pliny</HI> saith, the best Wooll <HI>Apulia</HI> and <HI>Italy</HI> yeelds,
and next them <HI>Milesium, Tarentum, Canusium,</HI> and
<HI>Laodicea</HI> in <HI>Asia;</HI> their generall time of sheering is in
<HI>Iuly:</HI> The Poet <HI>Laberius</HI> called the Rammes of the
Flocke <HI>Reciproci-cornes,</HI> and <HI>Lanicutes,</HI> alluding
to the writhing of their Hornes and their Skinnes
bearing Wooll: The Bell-weather, or Captaine of
the Flocke is call'd <HI>Vervex sectarius, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<DIV3 TYPE="speech">
<HEAD>The Shepheards Speech.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>BY what rare frame, or in what curious Vorse</L>
<L>Can the rich profits of your Trades commerce</L>
<L>Be to the full exprest? which to explaine,</L>
<L>Lyes not in <HI>Poets</HI> Pen, or <HI>Artists</HI> braine.</L>
<L>What Beast, or Bird, for Hyde, or Feather rare,</L>
<L>(For mans use made, can with the <HI>Sheepe</HI> compare?</L>
<L>The <HI>Horse</HI> of strength or swiftnesse may be proud,</L>
<L>But yet his flesh is not for food allow'd.</L>
<L>The <HI>Heards</HI> yeeld Milke and Meate (commodious both)</L>
<L>Yet none of all their skins make <HI>Wooll</HI> for <HI>Cloth.</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Sheepe</HI> doth all: The <HI>Parrot</HI> and the <HI>Jay,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Peacock, Estridge,</HI> all in colours gay,</L>
<L>Delight the Eye, some with their Notes, the Eare,</L>
<L>But what are these unto the <HI>Cloth</HI> we weare?</L>
<L>Search Forrests, Desarts for Beasts wilde or tame,</L>
<L>The Mountaines or the Vales, search the vast frame</L>
<L>Of the wide <HI>Universe,</HI> the Earth, and Skie,</L>
<L>Nor Beast nor Bird can with the <HI>Sheepe</HI> comply:</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>No Creature under Heaven, bee't small or great,</L>
<L>But some way <HI>usefull,</HI> one affords us <HI>meate,</HI></L>
<L>Another <HI>Ornament:</HI> Shee more than this,</L>
<L>" Of <HI>Patience,</HI> and of <HI>Profit</HI> th'<HI>embleme</HI> is,</L>
<L>In former Ages by the <HI>Heroes</HI> sought:</L>
<L>After, from <HI>Greece</HI> into <HI>Hesperia</HI> brought:</L>
<L>She's cloath'd in plenteous riches, and being shorne,</L>
<L>" Her <HI>Fleece</HI> an <HI>Order,</HI> and by <HI>Emperours</HI> worne,</L>
<L>All these are knowne, yet further understand,</L>
<L>In twelve divide the profits of this Land,</L>
<L>As Hydes, Tinne, Lead; or what else you can name,</L>
<L>Tenne of those twelve the Fleece may justly claime:</L>
<L>Then how can that amongst the rest be mist,</L>
<L>By which all States, all Common Weales subsist?</L>
<L>Great honour then belongs unto this trade,</L>
<L>And you, great Lord, for whom this triumph's made.</L>
</LG>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="tableau">
<HEAD>The second Show by Land.</HEAD>
<P>THe second Show by land is an <HI>Indian</HI> Beast, called
a <HI>Rinoceros,</HI> which being presented to the life,
is for the rarenesse thereof, more fit to beautifie a
Triumph: his Head, Necke, Backe, Buttockes,
Sides, and Thighes, armed by Nature with im∣penetrable
Skales; his Hide or Skinne of the colour
of the Boxe-tree, in greatnesse equall with the
Elephant, but his Legges are somewhat shorter:
an enemy to all beasts of rapine and prey, as the
Lyon, Leopard, Beare, Wolfe, Tiger, and the
like: but to others, as the Horse, Asse, Oxe, Sheep, &amp;c.
<PB REF="7"/>
which feede not upon the life and blood of the
weaker, but of the grasse and hearbage of the field,
harmlesse and gentle, ready to succour them, when
they be any way distressed. Hee hath a short horne
growing from his nose, and being in continuall en∣mity
with the Elephant, before hee encounter him,
he sharpeneth it against a stone, and in the sight ai∣meth
to wound him in the belly, being the softest
place about him, and the soonest pierc'd: He is back't
by an <HI>Indian,</HI> the speaker.</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="speech">
<HEAD>The Indians Speech.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THe dignity of Merchants who can tell?</L>
<L>Or how much they all Traders ante-cell?</L>
<L>When others here at home securely sleepe,</L>
<L>He plowes the bosome of each unknowne deepe,</L>
<L>And in them sees heavens wonders; for he can</L>
<L>Take a full view of the <HI>Leviathan,</HI></L>
<L>Whose strength all Marine Monsters doth surpasse,</L>
<L>His Ribs as Iron, his Fins and skales as brasse.</L>
<L>His Ship like to the feather'd Fowle he wings,</L>
<L>And from all Coasts hee rich materialls brings,</L>
<L>For ornament or profit; those by which</L>
<L>Inferiour Arts subsist, and become rich;</L>
<L>By Land he makes discovery of all Nations,</L>
<L>Their Manners, and their Countries scituations,</L>
<L>And with those savage natures so complies,</L>
<L>That there's no rarity from thence can rise</L>
<L>But he makes frequent with us, and yet these</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Not without dangers, both on shores and seas:</L>
<L>The Land he pierceth, and the Ocean skowers,</L>
<L>To make them all by free transportage ours.</L>
<L>You (honourd Sir) amongst the chiefe are nam'd,</L>
<L>By whose commerce our Nation hath beene fam'd.</L>
<L>The <HI>Romans</HI> in their triumphes had before</L>
<L>Their Chariots borne or lead, (to grace the more</L>
<L>The sumptuous Show) the prime and choisest things,</L>
<L>VVhich they had taken from the Captive, Kings:</L>
<L>VVhat curious Statue▪ what strange bird, or beast</L>
<L>That Clime did yeeld (if rare above the rest)</L>
<L>Was there expos'd: Entring your civill state,</L>
<L>VVhom better may we strive to imitate?</L>
<L>This huge <HI>Rinoceros</HI> (not 'mongst us seene,</L>
<L>Yet frequent wheresome Factors oft have beene)</L>
<L>Is embleme of the Praetorship you beare,</L>
<L>Who to all Beasts of prey, who rend and teare</L>
<L>The innocent heards and flocks, is foe profest,</L>
<L>But in all just defences armes his crest.</L>
<L>You of this wildernesse are Lord, so sway,</L>
<L>The weake may be upheld, the proud obey.</L>
</LG>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="tableau">
<HEAD>The third Show by Land.</HEAD>
<P>THe third Show by land is a Ship, fully accommo∣dated
with all her Masts, Sayles, Cordage, Tack∣lings,
Cables, Anchors, Ordnance, &amp;c. in that small
Modell, figuring the greatest Vessell: But concer∣ning
Ships and Nauigation, with the honour and
benefits thence accrewing, I have lately delivered my
<PB REF="8"/>
selfe so amply in a Booke published the last Summer
of his Majesties great Shippe, called the Soveraigne
of the Seas, that to any, who desire to be better certi∣fied
concerning such things, I referre them to that
Tractate, from whence they may receive full &amp; plen∣teous
satisfaction: I come now to a yong Sailor the
Speaker.</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="speech">
<HEAD>The Speech from the Shippe.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>SHipping to our first Fathers was not knowne;</L>
<L>(Though now amongst all Nations common growne)</L>
<L>Nor trade by Sea: we read the first choise peece,</L>
<L>Was th'<HI>Argo,</HI> built to fetch the golden Fleece,</L>
<L>In which brave voyage, sixty Princes, all</L>
<L><HI>Heroës,</HI> such as we <HI>Semones</HI> call:</L>
<L>In that new Vessell to attaine the shore.</L>
<L>Where such a prize was, each tugg'd at the Oare:</L>
<L>On one bench <HI>Hercules</HI> and <HI>Hilas</HI> sate,</L>
<L><HI>Beauty</HI> and <HI>Strength;</HI> and siding iust with that</L>
<L><HI>Daunaus</HI> and <HI>Lynceus</HI> of so quicke a sight</L>
<L>No interposer, or large distance might</L>
<L>Dull his cleare Opticks: those that had the charge,</L>
<L>And the chiefe stearadge of that Princely Barge,</L>
<L><HI>Zethes</HI> and <HI>Calais,</HI> whose judgements meet,</L>
<L>Being said t'have feathers on their heads and feete:</L>
<L>We spare the rest: Grave Sir, the Merchants trade</L>
<L>Is that, for which all Shipping first was made;</L>
<L>And through an <HI>Hellespont</HI> who would but pull,</L>
<L>Steere, and hoise saile, to bring home golden Wooll?</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>For wee by that are cloath'd: In the first place</L>
<L>Sate strength and beauty: oh what a sweete grace</L>
<L>Have those united; both now yours, great Lord,</L>
<L>Your beauty is your robe, your strength the sword.</L>
<L>You must have <HI>Lynceus</HI> eyes, and further see</L>
<L>Than either you before have done, or he</L>
<L>Could ever: having now a true inspection</L>
<L>Into each strife, each cause without affection</L>
<L>To this or that party: some are sed,</L>
<L>To have had feathers on their feete and head.</L>
<L>(As those whom I late nam'd) you must have more,</L>
<L>And in your place be feather'd now all o're:</L>
<L>You must have feathers in your thoughts, your eyes,</L>
<L>Your hands, your feete; for he that's truely wise</L>
<L>Must still be of a winged apprehension</L>
<L>As well for execution, as prevention.</L>
<L>You know (Right honourd Sir) delayes and pauses,</L>
<L>In judicature, dull, if not dampe, good causes:</L>
<L>That we presume t'advise, we pardon crave,</L>
<L>It being confest, all these, and more you have.</L>
</LG>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="tableau">
<HEAD>The fourth Show by Land.</HEAD>
<P>THe fourth Show by Land beares the Title <HI>Por∣ta
Pietatis, The Gate of Piety:</HI> which is the doore
by which all zealous and devout men enter into the
fruition of their long hoped for happinesse: It is
a delicate and artificiall composed structure, built
Temple-fashion, as most genuine and proper to the
persons therein presented. The Speaker is <HI>Piety</HI>
<PB REF="9"/>
her selfe, her habit, best suiting with her condition;
upon her head are certaine beames or raies of gold,
intimating a glory belonging to sanctity; in one
hand an Angelicall staffe, with a Banner; on the o∣ther
Arme a Crosse Gules in a field Argent: upon
one hand sits a beautifull Childe, representing <HI>Re∣ligion,</HI>
upon whose Shield are figured <HI>Time,</HI> with
his daughter <HI>Truth:</HI> her Motto <HI>Vincit veritas:</HI> In
another copartment sitteth one representing the
blessed Virgin, Patronesse of this Right Worshipfull
Society, Crowned: in one hand a Fanne of Starres,
in the other a Shield, in which are inscribed three
Crownes <HI>(gradatim)</HI> ascending, being the
Armes or Escutchion of the Company, and her
Motto that which belongeth unto it: <HI>Deo soli Ho∣nor
&amp; gloria:</HI> that is, <HI>unto God onely be Honour and
Glory:</HI> Next her sit the three Theologicall Graces,
<HI>Faith, Hope,</HI> and <HI>Charity,</HI> with three Escutchions,
<HI>Faiths</HI> motto, <HI>Fidei ala, Caeli scala: The wings of
Faith are the ladder by which we scale heaven. Hopes,
Solum spernit qui Caelum sperat: hee hates the Earth,
that hopes for Heaven. Loves</HI> Motto, <HI>Vbi charitas,
non est Caritas, who giveth willingly, shall never
want wretchedly.</HI> A sixth personateth <HI>Zeale,</HI> in
whose Escutchion is a burning Hart: Her word; <HI>In
tepida, frigida, flagrans: neither luke-warme, nor
key-cold, but ever burning:</HI> A seventh figureth
<HI>Humility:</HI> Her's <HI>In terra Corpus, in Coelo Cor: the
body on earth, the heart in Heaven.</HI> And last <HI>Constan∣cies:
Metam tangenti Corona; A Crowne belongeth
<PB REF="10"/>
to him who persevereth to the end.</HI> I come to the
Speech.</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="speech">
<HEAD>Piety the Speaker.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THis Structure is a Citadell, or Tower,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Piety,</HI> plac't in her heavenly bower,</L>
<L>Poynts out the way to blisse, guirt with a ring</L>
<L>Of all those Graces that may glory bring.</L>
<L>Here sits <HI>Religion</HI> firme, (though else where torne</L>
<L>By Schismaticks, and made the Atheists scorne)</L>
<L>Shining in her pure truth, nor need she quake,</L>
<L>Affrighted with the Faggot and the stake:</L>
<L>Shee's to you deare, you unto her are tender,</L>
<L>Vnder the Scepter of the Faiths defender.</L>
<L>How am I extasi'de when I behold</L>
<L>You build new Temples, and repaire the old!</L>
<L>There's not a stone that's laid in such foundation,</L>
<L>But is a step degreeing to Salvation:</L>
<L>And not a Scaffold rear'd to that intent,</L>
<L>But mounts a Soule above the Firmament:</L>
<L>Of <HI>Merchants,</HI> we know <HI>Magistrates</HI> are made,</L>
<L>And they (of those) most happy that so Trade.</L>
<L>Your <HI>Virgin-Saint</HI> sits next <HI>Religion</HI> crown'd,</L>
<L>With her owne Hand-maids (see) inviron'd round,</L>
<L>And these are they the learned Schoole-men call,</L>
<L>The three prime Vertues Theologicall,</L>
<L><HI>Faith, Hope,</HI> and <HI>Love; Zeale</HI> all inflam'd with fire</L>
<L>Of devout acts, doth a sixt place aspire.</L>
<L>The seventh <HI>Humility,</HI> and we commend</L>
<L>The Eight to <HI>Constancy,</HI> which crownes the end.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>A Triple Crowne's th'Emblazon of your Crest,</L>
<L>But to gaine one, is to be ever blest.</L>
<L>Proceede in that faire course you have begun,</L>
<L>So when your Annuall Glasse of State is run,</L>
<L>(Nay, that of Life) <HI>Ours,</HI> but the <HI>Gate</HI> to blisse</L>
<L>Shall let you in to yon <HI>Metropolis.</HI></L>
</LG>
<P>There now remaineth onely the last Speech at
Night, spoken by <HI>Proteus,</HI> which concludes the
Tryumph.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="speech">
<HEAD>The Speech at Night.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>NOw bright <HI>Hiperion</HI> hath unloos'd his Teame,</L>
<L>And washt his Coach-Steeds in cold <HI>Isters</HI> streame:</L>
<L>Day doth to Night give place, yet e're You sleepe,</L>
<L>Remember what the Prophet of the Deepe,</L>
<L><HI>Proteus</HI> fore-told: All such as State aspire,</L>
<L>Must be as <HI>Bulls,</HI> as <HI>Serpents,</HI> and like <HI>Fire.</HI></L>
<L>The Shepheard grazing of his Flocks, displayes</L>
<L>The use and profit from the <HI>Fleece</HI> we raise.</L>
<L>That <HI>Indian Beast,</HI> (had he a tongue to speake)</L>
<L>Would say, <HI>Suppresse the proud, support the weake,</HI></L>
<L>That <HI>Ship</HI> the Merchants honour loudly tells,</L>
<L>And how all other Trades it antecells:</L>
<L>But <HI>Piety</HI> doth point You to that Starre,</L>
<L>By which good Merchants steere: too bold we are</L>
<L>To keepe you from your rest; To-morrows Sunne</L>
<L>Will raise <HI>You to new cares,</HI> not yet begun.</L>
</LG>
<P><PB REF="11"/>I will not speake much concerning the two Bro∣thers,
M<SUP>r.</SUP> <HI>Iohn</HI> and <HI>Mathias Christmas,</HI> the Model∣lers
and Composers of those severall Peeces this day
presented to a mighty confluence, (being the two
succeeding Sonnes of that most ingenious Artist
M<SUP>r.</SUP> <HI>Gerard Christmas)</HI> to whom, and to whose
Workmanship I will onely conferre that Character,
which being long since (upon the like occasion)
conferr'd upon the Father, I cannot but now me∣ritedly
bestow upon the Sonnes: Men, as they are
excellent in their Art, so they are faithfull in their
performance.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="11"/>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

