<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="5">[The abbaye of the Holy Ghost]</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A03489</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 13609</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S109454</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99845101</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99845101</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">9981</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A03489)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9981)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 44:14)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="5">[The abbaye of the Holy Ghost]</TITLE><AUTHOR>Alcock, John, 1430-1500, attributed name. aut</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[40] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[Enprynted at Westmestre :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>By Wynkyn de worde,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>[1497?]]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>An edition of: The abbaye of the Holy Ghost.</NOTE><NOTE>Sometimes erroneously attributed to John Alcock--STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Text, leaf a2r, begins: Here begynneth a matere spekynge of a place that is namid the abbaye of the holy ghost, ..</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: a-b⁶ c-d⁴.</NOTE><NOTE>Imperfect; lacks title page (leaf a1).</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Monastic and religious life of women --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A03489">
<STC T="S">13609</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845101</BIBNO>
<VID>9981</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>¶Here begynneth a ma∣tere spekynge of a place that is namid the abbaye of the holy ghost / y<SUP>t</SUP> shall be foūded or groūded in a clene conscyence / in whi¦che abbaye shall dwelle .xxix. ladyes ghostly.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>N this ab¦baye Cha¦ryte shall be Abbesse Wysdome Pryouresse. Mekenes sup¦pryouresse. And thyse ben in the Couent. Pouertee Clennesse Temperaūce Sobernesse. Penaunce. Buxumnesse Confession Ryghtwysnes Predyca∣cyon Strength Pacyence Symplenes Mercy Lar∣genesse Reason Pyte Me¦dytacyon Oryson Deuo¦cōn Contemplacōn Cha¦styte Aubylacyon Hone∣ste Curteysy Drede and Gelousy. ¶The fader of heuen is foūder of this abbaye / the sone gouer∣nour / the holy ghost vysy¦tour. But though ony ab¦bay haue neuer so good a foūder / gouernour / &amp; visy¦tour / but it haue also good chartours wherby it may holde his londe / rent &amp; fre¦dom. Perauenture eyther by happe it shall be euyll serued or elles suffre mo∣che dysease of enmyes. Therfore I woll reherce y<SUP>e</SUP> chartours wherin I wol saye whan / where and of whom this abbaye was fyrste foūded or groūded And thenne woll I saye how it was fyrst made / &amp; afterwarde w<SUP>t</SUP>in short ty¦me destroyed / &amp; in what manere / &amp; how longe ty∣me or it were made ayen as it was before. And how almyghty god hath put his foure doughters in this holy abbay ayenst the foure doughters of
<PB REF="2"/>
the fende / whom the holy ghost chaced awaye for they were so fowle.</P>
<P>¶Sciant presentes &amp; fu∣turi <ABBR>&amp;c.</ABBR> Knowe they that ben here &amp; they y<SUP>t</SUP> ben to come y<SUP>t</SUP> I almyghty god in trynyte / fader / sone / &amp; holy ghost haue gyue &amp; graūted / &amp; w<SUP>t</SUP> my worde confermed to Adam y<SUP>e</SUP> fo¦re fader of man &amp; to Eue his wyfe &amp; to theyr hey∣res a lytel precyous place that is callid Conscyence y<SUP>t</SUP> lyeth in theyr soules by¦twene a place y<SUP>t</SUP> is called Sinderesis that styred a man to goodnes / &amp; grut∣cheth ayenst euyll in that other halfe. Whose ende lyeth fast by the grace of god / thrugh whiche eue∣ry man may doo well yf he woll. And y<SUP>t</SUP> other en∣de lyeth in Ioye yf y<SUP>e</SUP> sou∣le be clene out of synne. ¶This holy place al∣mighty god gaf to Adam forsayd &amp; to Eue and to ther heyres / clenly dyght without ony wēme. In the whiche god made a noble house of religyon y<SUP>t</SUP> is called the abbaye of y<SUP>e</SUP> holy ghost. In to whiche abbaye he put many go∣ostly ladyes / y<SUP>t</SUP> is to saye / good vertues. Wherin he made charyte abbesse / &amp; wysdom pryouresse / &amp; me¦kenesse suppryouresse. He walled this abbaye abou¦te with strength y<SUP>t</SUP> no wyc¦ked thought sholde haue entrid in y<SUP>t</SUP> hous yf Adam &amp; his wyfe hadde wolde themselfe. He gaaf them lordshyp of al the worlde to maynten this holy hou¦se so ferforth that all the fysshes in the see and all the byrdes of thayre and beestes of the erthe shol∣de haue ben buxome to hym &amp; to his wyfe and to theyr heyres after them euer yf Adam &amp; his wyf
<PB REF="2"/>
had kept them fro synne in to theyr endynge daye ¶Habendū &amp; tenendū <ABBR>&amp;c.</ABBR> To haue &amp; to holde this forsayd place to y<SUP>e</SUP> forsayd Adam and to Eue &amp; to theyr heyres freely &amp; in peas without lette of ony man euer. And therwith Ioye &amp; blysse y<SUP>t</SUP> neuer shal haue ende for the seruyce &amp; custome that longeth therof to the chyef lorde of the fee. And y<SUP>t</SUP> was no more than to withstonde the temptacōn of the fen¦de and of his wyfe. And that lasted not of bothe not a myle waye space. And almyghty god shol∣de haue warrantyd to A∣dam &amp; to Eue &amp; to theyr heyres that noble place / to haue dwelled euermo∣re in more Ioye than ony tongue may telle. ¶Also that they ne her heyres sholde neuer haue suffred wo / ne sholde they neuer haue deyed / but whan al∣mighty god wolde he shol¦de haue take hym vp in body &amp; soule to the blysse of heuen / there to haue ly¦ued without ende / yf A∣dam &amp; his wyf had kept them fro synne / as I sayd one daye to thende ¶Hijs teslibz <ABBR>&amp;c.</ABBR> Of this bereth wytnes angell &amp; man / he¦uen &amp; erth / sonne &amp; mone¦sterres and all creatures. ¶Datū apud paradysū <ABBR>&amp;c.</ABBR> Yeuen at paradyse the fyrst daye that man was made. ¶Anno regni <ABBR>&amp;c.</ABBR> In the yere of the reg∣nynge of almyghty god kyng of kynges / whose kyngdom neuer began¦ne neuer shall haue en∣de.</P>
<P>¶Many men there be y<SUP>t</SUP> wolde be in relygyon / but they may not for dyuerse causes. Therfore they y<SUP>t</SUP> may not be in bodyly re∣lygyon / they may be in
<PB REF="3"/>
ghostly relygyon yf they woll / y<SUP>t</SUP> is foūded in a pla¦ce y<SUP>t</SUP> is called Conscyence. But fyrste y<SUP>e</SUP> place muste be clensed w<SUP>t</SUP> grace of the holy ghost Two maydēs y<SUP>t</SUP> be called Loue &amp; Ryght¦wysnes shall cast awaye fro conscyence all maner of fylth. Then̄e shal Me¦kenesse &amp; Pouerte make the foūdement therof / &amp; put awaye all worldely thought y<SUP>t</SUP> is though men haue worldely goodes set they not theyr loue there vpon / &amp; thenne may they well be called men poore in spyryte / to whom Cryst gyueth his blessynge.</P>
<P>¶ This abbay must also be set vpon a ryuer / y<SUP>t</SUP> is the ryuer of teeres / on whi¦che ryuer was Mawde∣leyne foūded in sorowyn∣ge for her synnes / therfor̄ the grace of god &amp; heuen¦ly ryches came all to her wyl ¶ Then̄e shal Buxū¦nesse &amp; mercy rere vp the walles in to heygth &amp; ma¦ke them stronge with al∣mesdedes / geuynge glad∣ly to poore men after thy state is / thus saith Thobi ¶Si multū tibi fuerit habūdanter tribue. si tibi sic exiguū. parū ī{per}tire stu¦de This is thus moche to meane. Yf y<SUP>u</SUP> be ryche ha∣uynge plentee of worldly godes / gyue plenteuously therof. Yf y<SUP>u</SUP> be poore be of good wyll to gyue gladly of suche thynge as y<SUP>u</SUP> hast For saynt Poule sayth. ¶Hilarē datorē diligit de{us}. That is to saye / god loueth y<SUP>e</SUP> glad gyuer Th{us} shall we buylde our hous in heuen with the loue of god &amp; of our euen crysten ¶Thenne shall Pacyen¦ce &amp; strength reyse vp all the pylars &amp; <ABBR>vndset</ABBR> them with botraces / y<SUP>t</SUP> no wyn¦de of wordes of angre ne of tempest of persecucōn / 
<PB REF="3"/>
ne of temptacōn may cast them downe. ¶Thenne we must make our cloys∣tre in this maner / y<SUP>t</SUP> shall kepe vs ghostly out of al worldly thoughts &amp; sygh∣tes / that is kepe we our eyen fro all euyll syghtes our eeres fro euyll heryn¦ge / our mouth fro euyll spekynge / fro swerynge / &amp; fro lyenge / &amp; our hertes fro all euyll thoughtes. And yf we kepe thus this foure corners / we shall buylde well our cloystre. ¶A mayde y<SUP>e</SUP> hyght Con¦fessyon shall make our chaptour hous. Predyca∣cyon the fraytour / &amp; Ory¦son the oratory. Contem∣placyon the dortour. And yf thyse shalbe reysed vp to y<SUP>e</SUP> worshyp of god / they must stonde out fro worl¦dly noyse / fro worldly be∣synesse &amp; angre. ¶Con∣templacōn is not ellis but a deuoute herte w<SUP>t</SUP> a brē∣nynge loue to god to ta∣ste somdele of y<SUP>e</SUP> blysse y<SUP>t</SUP> is ordeyned for his cho∣sen in heuen. ¶Pyte shal be our fermour Deuocōn cellerer / &amp; holy Medytacy¦on shall be garnetour. Whan all thyse offycers ben made the holy ghost is warden / w<SUP>t</SUP> god fader foūder / with god the sone wysdom of the <ABBR>fad</ABBR>. The worthy lady Charyte shal be abbesse of this hous / for all this other offycers shall obeye to Charyte. ¶Vnde oīa vrā in cari∣tate fiāt. All thynge that ye do / saye or thynke / be they done in y<SUP>e</SUP> loue of god ¶Alas yf I durste saye full many be in relygyon but fewe be relygyous y<SUP>t</SUP> do the byddynge of Poul to obeye to charyte / ther∣fore lese they moche tyme &amp; also ther mede ¶Now shall the worthy lady Wy¦sedom be our Pryouresse
<PB REF="4"/>
¶Nam prior oīm est sa∣piencia. The good lady Mekenesse y<SUP>t</SUP> alwaye lo∣ueth herselfe shall be our suppryouresse. This ab∣bay is of god blessyd that hath thyse gouernours / for all be blessyd y<SUP>t</SUP> holde them in theyr scole. For they y<SUP>t</SUP> kepe Charyte Wy∣sedom &amp; Mekenesse / the thre persones in trynyte shall gyue them heuen to mede. That soule is gre∣te &amp; hye in heuen y<SUP>t</SUP> hath thyse thre within herself. Charyte Wysdom &amp; Me¦kenesse ¶ Dyscrecōn shal be tresorer / &amp; Oryson shal be chaūtour ¶ Nā orō sa¦crificiū deo hōi solaciū di¦abolo tormentū. ¶The fende sayd to Bertilmew our lordes apostle / thy ory¦sons brenne me ¶ Saint Bernarde sayth whā we praye in good lyfe / our good angel daūcith &amp; ma¦keth therof a present to y<SUP>e</SUP> <ABBR>fad</ABBR> of heuen / &amp; then̄e our lorde cōmaūdeth hym to wryte them in the booke of lyfe. ¶Saynt Austen telleth y<SUP>e</SUP> Iubylacōn / ory∣sons felowe is a Ioye con¦ceyued in teeres w<SUP>t</SUP> a gho¦stly loue y<SUP>t</SUP> may not be she¦wed in all / ne hyde in all As it doth by them y<SUP>t</SUP> her¦tly loue y<SUP>t</SUP> gyue almesse &amp; cōtynue in theyr prayers / where soo they ben theyr hertes synge mornynge songes of loue / whan they longe inwardly with ar∣mes of loue to clyppe w<SUP>t</SUP> ghostly mouth to kysse / they loue somtyme so her¦tly y<SUP>t</SUP> they lacke wordes so theyr loue rauyssheth the∣yr hertes y<SUP>t</SUP> they wote not somtyme what they doo. ¶Deuocyon is Celerer that kepeth all the wy∣nes bothe whyte &amp; redde. That ben all the worthy thankynges the whiche we all owe to do to god / 
<PB REF="4"/>
for the endeles goodnes y<SUP>t</SUP> he hath done / dooth / and woll do to vs yf we woll ourself. This goodnes y<SUP>t</SUP> he hath do was whan we all sholde haue ben loste thrugh synne of Adam &amp; be in helle without ende / had not he of grete good¦nes &amp; pyte become man for our sake / lyuyng here many wynters in grete penaūce &amp; passyon / &amp; at y<SUP>e</SUP> laste naylled on a crosse &amp; with a spere tonge to the herte &amp; deyed / and all for loue of vs to brynge vs out of payne.</P>
<P>¶The goodnes that he doth to vs now / is whyle we ben here in body &amp; in soule / yeuynge vs al that we nede both bodyly and ghostly. Bodyly / as mete drynke &amp; clothynge Gho¦stly / as good thoughtes / good wordes / &amp; good de∣des. And therto to them y<SUP>t</SUP> ben good he graunteth a shelde of his grace &amp; myn¦de of his passyon to kepe them fro the fende. And to theym y<SUP>t</SUP> ben wycked &amp; combred w<SUP>t</SUP> synne he gy¦ueth space &amp; tyme to tor∣ne therfro &amp; to amende yf they wol. For th{us} he sayth hymselfe. ¶Nolo mortē pctōris sed magis vt <ABBR>{con}uer¦tat</ABBR> et viuat. This is to saye. I woll not the dethe of the synfull man but y<SUP>t</SUP> he torne &amp; lyue. And ther to he graunteth mercy &amp; forgyuenesse yf they woll it aske. ¶The goodnes y<SUP>t</SUP> he woll doo to vs yf we woll dwelle &amp; abyde styll in his seruyce / that is in good vertues. In herynge seenge / spekynge / goynge handlynge / &amp; in all other dedes werkynge shall be to this. In tyme of dethe whan body &amp; soule shall departe atweyne &amp; the de¦uyl appere in his owne ly¦kenesse before vs to make
<PB REF="5"/>
vs agast / &amp; yf he may to brynge vs in to mysbyle∣ue / god wolde sende his owne angell &amp; all our go¦de dedes y<SUP>t</SUP> euer we here wrought wryten to shew vs &amp; comforte vs / &amp; dryue awaye the deuyll / &amp; lede our soules to blysse. The whiche blysse our lorde graūteth &amp; gyueth to all his chosen &amp; true seruaūt whan he sayth thus ¶Ve¦nite bn̄dicti patris mei {per}∣cipite regnū <ABBR>qd</ABBR> vobis {per}a∣tū est ab origine mundi. ¶ Penaūce shall be Ker¦uer y<SUP>e</SUP> ryght well can ma¦ke many good meetes / suf¦ferynge many bytter so∣rowes for synne to make the soule mery and glad with god that before was <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lenge / for she had hym offended. ¶Temperaū∣ce shall serue in the fray¦tour &amp; loke all aboute y<SUP>t</SUP> mesure be had ouer all y<SUP>t</SUP> none haue to moche ne to lytell / neyther of etyn¦ge / drynkynge / ne of sle∣pynge. ¶Sobernes must nedes rede at the borde y<SUP>e</SUP> lyfe of holy faders / what lyfe they lyued here in er¦the / to take of them exam¦ple to do as they dyde / &amp; therby to wynne y<SUP>e</SUP> mede y<SUP>t</SUP> they haue. ¶Pyte must be the Pytaūcer y<SUP>t</SUP> dooth that good that she may. ¶Mercy must be Alme∣ner that gyueth to all &amp; no thynge can holde to herself ¶The lady Dre∣de Porter that kepeth the cloystre of the hert y<SUP>t</SUP> cha∣cyth awaye all wycked vyces &amp; called in good ver¦tues / &amp; closeth the gates of the cloystre y<SUP>t</SUP> none euyl come not in to the herte / the eyen / the mouth / the eeres / ne in to other places by the fyue wyttes ¶Ho∣neste is maystresse to teche nouyces curteysy how thei shall haue them in ther
<PB REF="5"/>
dedes / both to god ānd to man ¶Curteysy is Host∣lere to calle in noble gyft and Symplenes shall be her felowe y<SUP>t</SUP> she be not to lyberall. ¶Reason shall be Purueour y<SUP>t</SUP> there be no defaute. ¶Boūte shalbe Fermerer y<SUP>e</SUP> seke men to serue. Her felawe shall be Largenesse to gyue eue∣ryche y<SUP>t</SUP> he nedeth. ¶Me¦dytacyon Garnetour for to gadre corne togyder that men haue theyr su∣stenaunce.</P>
<P>¶Medytacōn is thought in god / of his werkes / of his wordes / &amp; of his crea∣tures / &amp; of his paynes y<SUP>t</SUP> he loued vs with. For oft a good thought is better than many Indeuowte prayers. ¶Therof spe∣keth y<SUP>e</SUP> holy bysshop De∣nys &amp; sayth. Whan the herte is caught with the loue of god / he may not saye the worde y<SUP>t</SUP> he thyn¦keth in herte. The gar∣ner is aboue y<SUP>e</SUP> cellar. So medytacōn ouer deuocōn Medytacōn garnetour &amp; deuocyon cellerer / &amp; pyte shall be pytaūcer.</P>
<P>¶Herof speketh the pro∣phete Dauid &amp; sayth ¶A fructu frumēti vini &amp; olei multiplicati sūt. Of fru¦te / of whete / of wyne &amp; of oyle ben they multeplyed God behoteth to his cho¦sen thyse thre thynges. Serue ye to me he sayth &amp; I shal gyue you plente of whete / of wyne / &amp; of oy¦le. Plente of whete is th{us} to thynke on y<SUP>e</SUP> crosse In∣wardly &amp; on Cryste <ABBR>Ihu</ABBR> that dyed theron / y<SUP>t</SUP> is to saye / medytacyon. Plente of wyne is welle of teeres for to wepe well is good deuocōn. Plente of oyle is good dylectacōn in Cryst Ihesu / y<SUP>t</SUP> is our beste com∣forte. Oyle gyueth sauou¦re to meetes &amp; lyght also
<PB REF="6"/>
to lāpes. Ryght so whan men beseche hertly god of mercy / he sendeth theym a ghostly Ioye. The oyle of comfort &amp; of mercy / y<SUP>t</SUP> is in medytacyon / where to thynke on the crosse of Cryste <ABBR>Ihu</ABBR>. And in deuo¦cōn he gyueth wyne / y<SUP>t</SUP> is the welle of teeres of byt¦ternes / &amp; after y<SUP>t</SUP> wyne of teeres of swetnes. Our lorde <ABBR>Ihu</ABBR> Cryste sendeth them the oyle of comfort &amp; of mercy y<SUP>t</SUP> gyueth the lyght of &amp; shewith his he¦uenly preuytees y<SUP>t</SUP> he hy∣deth fro men y<SUP>t</SUP> ben ful of flesshly lustes / y<SUP>t</SUP> gyue thē all to worldely wytte in dyuerse degrees / y<SUP>t</SUP> whiche is ryght grete foly ¶For the apostle Poule sayth. ¶Sapiēcia ei{us}mūdi stul¦ticia ē apud deū. That is thus moche to saye / y<SUP>t</SUP> the wysdom of this worlde is foly before god. Therfo¦re me thynketh all those that purpose &amp; trauaylle to be holde wyse in this worlde / y<SUP>t</SUP> is to <ABBR>gad</ABBR> ryches to <ABBR>gad</ABBR> for grete worshyp of themselfe here / &amp; for theyr lusty lyuynge / more than for the worshyp of god / to parte therof there as it nedeth / ben ryght ny¦ce foles &amp; grete wretches / as the apostle vs techeth And to them y<SUP>t</SUP> be his true seruauntes he gyueth the lyght of loue y<SUP>t</SUP> they some¦dele taast &amp; fele how swe¦te he is &amp; how good. But he gyueth it not all fully for no mā I trowe mygh¦te all fully it fele / y<SUP>t</SUP> for ly¦kynge and Ioye his herte sholde to braste. For saȳt Austen doctour tellith ex∣ample of an holy preest &amp; sayth thus / y<SUP>t</SUP> than whan he herde ony thȳge of god that it lyked hym to here he sholde be rauysshed so w<SUP>t</SUP> Ioye y<SUP>t</SUP> he sholde falle &amp; lye styll as he were deed
<PB REF="6"/>
And though ony man in y<SUP>t</SUP> tyme caste fyre on his flesshe he feled it no more than he had be all deed. Wherof speketh Iob &amp; sayth ¶Abscondi lucē in manibz. That is to saye god hydeth lyght within his hondes / as he y<SUP>t</SUP> hath a candell lyght betwene his two hondes / he may shewe it or hyde whether he woll. So doth our lor∣de Cryst Ihesu to his cho¦sey men / his hondes he o∣peneth whan he wol and gladdeth them w<SUP>t</SUP> heuen¦ly lyght. And whā he wol he closith his hondes &amp; w<SUP>t</SUP> dreweth his comforte / for he woll not y<SUP>t</SUP> they fele it fully / but gyueth them le¦ue to taast / &amp; in partye to fele how good he is / how swete he is / as Dauyd sayth in y<SUP>e</SUP> sawter ¶Gus¦tate &amp; videte qm̄ suauis ē dn̄s. And yf god sayd to vs / by this lykynge that y<SUP>u</SUP> hast in this short tyme of me / y<SUP>u</SUP> mayst taast how swete I am to my chosen in my blysse whan they passe hens. And thus he doth to drawe vs fro lust of flesshely &amp; worldly lo∣ue to flāme our hertes w<SUP>t</SUP> loue longynge to haue y<SUP>t</SUP> Ioye in body &amp; soule w<SUP>t</SUP> hym without ende.</P>
<P>¶A wyse lady Ielousye that is besy both nyght &amp; daye to do our lordes wyl shall kepe our Horolege to wake thyse ladyes all &amp; cause them swyftely to ryse vp to saye our lordes seruyce. This horolege of contemplacyon is to god loue longynge y<SUP>t</SUP> smyteth sooner than ony other in y<SUP>e</SUP> herte of Crystys louers that fede theyr soule w<SUP>t</SUP> good prayers / &amp; wassheth w<SUP>t</SUP> swete teeres / &amp; wipeth it with ghostly comforte / as Salomon telleth &amp; te¦cheth vs. ¶Ego dormio
<PB REF="7"/>
et cor meū vigilat. I sle∣pe he sayth my flesshe to fede / my herte is wakyn∣ge all in loue &amp; all to god longynge. ¶Whan this abbaye was al well set &amp; god therin serued / a ty∣raunt came &amp; with grete power put in his foure doughters / y<SUP>t</SUP> were all of shrewed maners / y<SUP>e</SUP> fende <ABBR>fad</ABBR> of them all. The fyr¦ste doughter pryde / y<SUP>e</SUP> o∣ther was enuye / y<SUP>e</SUP> thyrde false demynge / y<SUP>e</SUP> fourth flesshly lust. Thyse foure wenchis by coūsell of the deuyll theyr <ABBR>fad</ABBR> came to noye this abbay so nyght &amp; daye in soule the worse rest they haue Whan Cha¦ryte sawe this myscheyf &amp; other ladyes of the hou¦se they range anone theyr chapytour bell / &amp; toke coū¦sell of this thynge. And thenne sayd Dyscrecōn / y<SUP>t</SUP> they praye the holy ghost to come to helpe them w<SUP>t</SUP> his grace. And then̄e they kneled downe &amp; sange. ¶Veni creator spiritus. Thenne as it is sayd be∣fore / came our lord Cryst <ABBR>Ihu</ABBR> in to his <ABBR>mod</ABBR> &amp; resto¦red this hous better than euer it was before. To hym glory &amp; worshyp y<SUP>t</SUP> ly¦ueth without ende.</P>
<P>¶Memorandū <ABBR>qd</ABBR> pri<SUP>o</SUP> die plasmacione <ABBR>&amp;c.</ABBR> We may vnderstonde y<SUP>t</SUP> there was a fals tyraūt aposta¦ta y<SUP>t</SUP> is named Sathanas y<SUP>t</SUP> some tyme was pryour of y<SUP>e</SUP> order of angels in y<SUP>e</SUP> blysse of heuen / y<SUP>t</SUP> for pry∣de rāne out of his blysful order in to sorowfull hor∣rour of y<SUP>e</SUP> payne of helle. He had soo grete enuy to this abbay of y<SUP>e</SUP> holy ghost y<SUP>t</SUP> it was so well w<SUP>t</SUP> god / &amp; had so grete a lordshyp He bethought hym how he myght distroye y<SUP>t</SUP> noble hous / &amp; how he myght do to make y<SUP>e</SUP> noble couente
<PB REF="7"/>
of vertues to renne out of theyr order / as he ranne out of his. He came in ly¦kenes of a adder to thab∣baye gate to come in / &amp; y<SUP>e</SUP> porter / y<SUP>t</SUP> was called Dre¦de was not there redy For without doubte yf Drede had be there y<SUP>e</SUP> fende had not come in. And Eue sa¦we y<SUP>t</SUP> he was there / &amp; as a grete fole she lete hym co¦me in. Then̄e sayd y<SUP>e</SUP> fen¦de to her / why forbad god y<SUP>t</SUP> ye sholde not ete of the fruyte y<SUP>t</SUP> growith on y<SUP>e</SUP> tree y<SUP>t</SUP> stondeth in myddes of paradyse / then̄e sayd Eue yf we ete of it we shall deye. Naye sayd he. God knowith wel yf ye ete the¦re of ye shal be as goddis knowynge good &amp; euyll / buthe wolde y<SUP>t</SUP> ye were not so wyse / &amp; therfore he for∣bad ye sholde not ete of y<SUP>t</SUP> fruyte Eue herde she shol¦de be so wyse / was bothe couetous &amp; lykerous / &amp; sa¦we the fruytes delycyous to y<SUP>e</SUP> mouth / went to y<SUP>e</SUP> tree and toke &amp; ete therof and gaaf Adam y<SUP>t</SUP> other dele and he ete therof. And in the meane tyme y<SUP>t</SUP> Adam &amp; his wyf ete of the fruy¦te / the fals traytour wich his thre knyghtes. That is is to saye. Pryde. Coue¦tyse. &amp; Vaynglory / wente in this abbaye of the ho∣ly ghost &amp; bare awaye al the good y<SUP>t</SUP> there was / &amp; bare awaye the chartour y<SUP>t</SUP> god gaaf them to holde theyr place by. And ther∣fore Adam ne his wyfe neyther theyr heyres frō that daye vnto this daye had neuer right to chalen¦ge ayen lordshyp of the blysse of heuen / but oonly by goddes mercy. And not onely thyse false the∣ues brake the abbaye / but also they bare awaye the godes / that is / they draue awaye dyspytousely out
<PB REF="8"/>
of the abbaye all the no∣ble couent of vertues. So that it was .iiij.M.v.C. &amp; .xxxiij. yere after that or they myght come ayen al togyder as perfytly as they were before.</P>
<P>¶Whan Adam and his wyfe had eten of y<SUP>e</SUP> fruyte they behelde eche other / &amp; then̄e perceyued they fyrst that they were bothe rob∣bed &amp; naked &amp; were asha¦med of thēself. And went and toke leues of fygge trees to couer with theyr preuytees / for they had no other clothes Then̄e wen¦te they forth to one y<SUP>t</SUP> was thef besyde y<SUP>t</SUP> was namid wytte / and asked of hym where that holy couent was become Then̄e sayd wytte y<SUP>t</SUP> theyr abbay was destroyed &amp; all y<SUP>e</SUP> couente was renne awaye for thy foly &amp; for thy wyues. For whyle y<SUP>u</SUP> &amp; thy wyfe ete of the fruyte / the abbaye was destroyed with foure fals theues. Then̄e all y<SUP>e</SUP> couent brake theyr order &amp; ranne awaye / &amp; sayd as they went / y<SUP>t</SUP> they sholde nomore come <ABBR>togyd</ABBR> ayen as they were fyrst this .iiij M. yere &amp; more. Thenne sayd Adam &amp; his wyfe. Alas what shall we doo / we haue no clothe to doo on vs / ne hous to dwelle in / &amp; therto the couent of holy vertues y<SUP>t</SUP> were our best frendes hath forsake vs &amp; ben gone awaye So welawaye y<SUP>e</SUP> harde whyle that euer we ete the fruy¦te. Soone after they her∣de how god spake to theȳ as he went in the myddel of paradyse / &amp; they weren ashamed of themself / for they were naked. ¶Also they were aferde of hym / and went vnder a tree to hyde them God came by them &amp; sawe them / and sayd. Adam where art y<SUP>u</SUP>
<PB REF="8"/>
Lorde sayd Adam I her∣de thy voys in paradyse / and I was ashamed / for I was naked / therfore I hyd me. Adam sayd our lorde / who tolde the that thou were naked. Ony thynge elles / but for thou ete of the fruyte ayenst my forbyddynge. Adam sayd our lorde / who hath broke thabbaye of the ho¦ly ghost / &amp; who hath bore awaye all the good that there was. Where is thab¦besse &amp; her couent / wheder ben they gone. Lord sayd Adam that woman that thou yauest to me in to my wyfe lete in a false shrewe at the abbaye ga∣tes / that bad her ete of y<SUP>t</SUP> fruyte / &amp; he sayd that she sholde be as wyse as god And she toke &amp; ete therof &amp; gaaf me that other de∣le. And I wolde not dys∣please her / but ete therof also. In y<SUP>e</SUP> meane tyme that false cheyf with ma¦ny of his assent went in to the abbaye &amp; brake it downe / beerynge awaye all the good y<SUP>t</SUP> was therin and draue awaye al that noble couent. I wote not wheder. Then̄e sayd god to Eue. Why lete thou in this false theyf / and why ete thou of the fruyte / thenne sayd Eue. Lorde he came to me in lyknes of an adder and begyled me with false wordes / &amp; I lete hym in &amp; dyde as he had Thenne sayd our lorde to her. For thou lete hym in &amp; dyde as he the bad / &amp; etest of the fruyte / thou shalt bere thy chil∣dern with grete payne &amp; all wymmen that shall come after the / out take one. And yf thou hadde not so done / woman shol¦de not haue had payne in berynge of childern. And therto thou shalt be euer
<PB REF="9"/>
<ABBR>vnd</ABBR> mānes power. God then̄e sayd to Adam. For y<SUP>u</SUP> ete of that fruyte at thy wyues byddynge ayenste my forbyddynge / &amp; for y<SUP>u</SUP> letest the abbay of the ho¦ly ghost to be so foule de∣stroyed / &amp; lete thabbesse &amp; her couent to rēne awaye fro theyr order &amp; knowest not whether / this shal be thy penaūce. Thou shalt be dryue out of paradyse in to the erthe acursed for thy synne. Therin shall thou dwelle with moche sorowe &amp; woo all y<SUP>e</SUP> dayes of thy lyfe / and the erthe shall brynge forth to the thornes &amp; breres. And y<SUP>u</SUP> shalt ete grasse that gro∣weth on the erthe. In be¦synesse &amp; swete of thy fa¦ce thou shalt ete thy bre∣de tyll thou torne agayne vnto the erthe that thou came fro. For of the erthe thou were made / and to the erthe thou shalt torne agayne.</P>
<P>¶After y<SUP>t</SUP> our lorde bad an angel to dryue Adam &amp; his wyf out of y<SUP>e</SUP> blysse of paradyse in to y<SUP>e</SUP> wret∣ched worlde. He had hym go &amp; seke there the abbes¦se of the abbaye of the ho¦ly ghost. And sayd that nother he ne his wyfe ne none of theyr ofsprynge sholde come agayne in to the blysse of paradyse ne in to heuen / tyll they ha∣ue made agayne the ab∣abye of the holy ghost as well as it was before. Al∣so tyll they haue brought agayn thabbesse w<SUP>t</SUP> them and all the couent in as good poynt as they were or they wente awaye. ¶Thenne made god to Adam a cote of leder / &amp; to Eue an other cote / and put them out of paradyse And thus they went for∣the in to this wretched worlde w<SUP>t</SUP> moche sorowe
<PB REF="9"/>
and care / &amp; therof was no wonder. ¶They lyued thenne in this worlde w<SUP>t</SUP> moche woo &amp; sorowe .ix. hondred yeres and .xxx. And sought the abbesse &amp; her couent that were soo¦renne awaye.</P>
<P>¶Also he wolde haue had somwhat wherwith he myght haue made a∣gayn y<SUP>t</SUP> abbaye of y<SUP>e</SUP> holy ghost. And he myght fyn¦de therof right nought in all that longe tyme. And in y<SUP>e</SUP> meane tyme he fell seke for sorowe therof &amp; deyed and his wyfe both And theyr soules went to helle. Not onely they alo∣ne / but al those y<SUP>t</SUP> of them came by the space of .iiij. M. &amp; .vi.C. yeres to helle they went eche one. For so longe was Adam in hell &amp; that was for thabbaye of the holy ghost / y<SUP>t</SUP> was theyr conscyence / was not made ayen as fayr ne as clene as it was before. ¶Th{us} was Adam &amp; his wyfe in helle many yeres in sorowe &amp; care / tyll al∣myghty god had pyte of theyr soules / &amp; sende dow¦ne his owne dere sone / &amp; bad hym go and seke the abbesse of the abbaye of the holy ghost &amp; her co∣uent. For he wyste better where they were than A∣dam wyst Then̄e he cam downe in to this worlde &amp; sought them here ful be∣sely .xxxiij. yeres. And at y<SUP>e</SUP> last he foūde them han¦gynge on y<SUP>e</SUP> roode. And to¦ke them downe &amp; ladde them w<SUP>t</SUP> hym vnto helle &amp; spake w<SUP>t</SUP> Adam &amp; his wyfe. Whan Adam sawe hȳ come he was ful glad¦de and no wonder was. ¶Thenne Cryst goddes sone of heuen made ayen the abbaye of the holy ghost better than euer it was / &amp; toke out of helle
<PB REF="10"/>
Adam &amp; his wyfe / and ladde them agayn home in to paradyse. ¶ And ther̄ was moche Ioye ma¦de at theyr comynge ho∣me. But how &amp; in what maner Cryste foūde thab¦besse &amp; her couent / here may we lerne.</P>
<P>AFter the tyme that Adam &amp; his wyfe were departed from this transytory lyfe and put in y<SUP>e</SUP> pryson of helle / there came in to the worlde ma¦ny wyse &amp; famous men as Patryarkes and Pro∣phetes &amp; other good men many that hadde moche sorowe for the abbaye of the holy ghost and for al the couent for they were so gone awaye / they wen¦te about &amp; sought after them in many syndre cō∣trees as longe as they ly∣ued. But vnder theym al they founde theym not. Thenne amonge other men ther̄ cam four good men. Dauyd. Salomon. Ysay. &amp; Ieremy / y<SUP>t</SUP> were about daye and nyght to make this abbaye ayen &amp; to seke vp the couent. And for they myght not haue theyr wyll / they ma¦de moche sorowe &amp; moon Dauyd sayd. ¶Labora∣ui clamās rauce facte sūt fauces mee defecerūt ocli mei dū spero in deū meū I haue so traueled &amp; cry¦ed after them y<SUP>t</SUP> my che∣kes ake and ben wexe al hoores. ¶ Dn̄e inclina ce¦los tuos &amp; descende. Ther¦fore lorde he sayd bowe downe thy heuēs &amp; come downe &amp; helpe me to seke the abbesse &amp; her couent / for I may not fynde them ¶Thenne sayd Salo∣mon ¶Circuibo ciuitatē {per} vicos &amp; plateas et querā quē diligit aīa mea. I shall goo about the Cy∣te
<PB REF="10"/>
by wayes &amp; by stretes &amp; seke the abbesse &amp; her co∣uent whom my herte lo∣ueth. I sought them / but I foūde them not. I cryed but none of them wolde answere wyth a worde. Thenne I sayd mornyn¦ge thus / torne ayen y<SUP>u</SUP> swe¦te wyghte &amp; lete vs loke on the. Thou hast woū∣ded myn herte my fayre syster my fayre spouse y<SUP>u</SUP> hast woūdid myn hert w<SUP>t</SUP> the twynkelynge of thyn eyen. I haue sought by nyghtes y<SUP>e</SUP> couent whom my soule loueth. I haue sought w<SUP>t</SUP> all my myght &amp; I may not fynde them Thenne sayd he to other maydens y<SUP>t</SUP> dwelled there besyde. I praye you spe∣cyally ye maydens of Ie∣rusalem yf ye fynde ony thynge where thabbesse is of thabbaye of the holy ghost &amp; her couent / that ye woll tell them that I am seke for loue longyn∣ge after them Thus kyn¦ge Salomon made <ABBR>moch</ABBR> moon / &amp; then he sayd th{us} Lorde god sende downe out of thy holy heuēs thy dere sone y<SUP>t</SUP> he may be w<SUP>t</SUP> me &amp; trauayle with me / &amp; helpe me to make ayen the abbaye of the holy ghost in as good poynt as it sholde be. But for all y<SUP>t</SUP> he coude crye / god∣dis sone cam not yet then ¶Thenne wente Ysaye y<SUP>e</SUP> prophete &amp; sought thab¦besse of her couent many dayes &amp; longe / but he foū¦de them not. Thenne say¦de he th{us}. ¶Vtinā disrū perā celos et descenderes. y<SUP>t</SUP> is to saye wolde god lor¦de y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>u</SUP> woldest broke he∣uens &amp; come downe &amp; hel¦pe vs to make ayen thab¦baye of the holy ghost / &amp; fynde vp the couent that is gone awaye. ¶Then¦ne went Ieremy the pro∣phete
<PB REF="11"/>
&amp; sought them also but he myght not fynde them / therfore made he a ruthfull moon and sayd. ¶ Ve michi misere <ABBR>&amp;c.</ABBR> Wo to me wretche he say¦de y<SUP>t</SUP> god hath encreaced more sorowe to my soro∣we. I haue trauaylled w<SUP>t</SUP>¦out ony reste in syghynge &amp; sorowynge / &amp; I maye not fynde y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>t</SUP> I seke. He∣las he sayd y<SUP>e</SUP> fende hath dryue awaye y<SUP>e</SUP> maydens in to the erthe / &amp; defyled theyr kyngdome. The maydens be paste awaye in to wretchednes. They herde me well how I sy∣ghed &amp; made <ABBR>moch</ABBR> moon but there was none of thē y<SUP>t</SUP> wolde me comforte w<SUP>t</SUP> a worde. Therfore I ha∣ue so wepte for sorowe y<SUP>t</SUP> myn eyen be in poynt to faylle. Who shall gyue me water to my heed / &amp; who shal yeue me a welle of teeres to myn eyen. And who shall wepe for y<SUP>e</SUP> maydens y<SUP>t</SUP> be thus go∣ne away both day &amp; nygh¦te Thou noble abbesse he sayth to whom may I ly¦ken the / to whom may I assemble the / y<SUP>u</SUP> doughter of <ABBR>Ihrlm</ABBR> the wyse pryou¦resse to whom I lyken y<SUP>t</SUP> Thou mayde &amp; dough∣ter of Syon y<SUP>u</SUP> holy couent he sayth / how may I cō∣forte the / me thynke thy sorowe as grete as y<SUP>e</SUP> see / y<SUP>u</SUP> noble couent who shall be thyn helpe. I can not elles saye sayth Ieremy but the fayrest floure of our garlonde is falle a∣waye. Alas alas &amp; wela∣waye y<SUP>t</SUP> euer we dyde sȳne ¶Whan god almyghty herde th{us} thyse prophetes w<SUP>t</SUP> many other good men to make moche moon w<SUP>t</SUP> heuy chere many hūdred yeres for the destruccyon of the abbaye of the holy ghost / he had grete pyte
<PB REF="11"/>
of them that they farid so And y<SUP>t</SUP> therfore mannes soule was in pryson &amp; pay¦ne of helle / &amp; sholde haue be there w<SUP>t</SUP>out ende. He ordeyned a coūseyle of y<SUP>e</SUP> holy trynyte in the blysse of heuen / of fader / sone / &amp; holy ghost &amp; sayd. We ma¦de mānes soule to our ly¦kenes / &amp; toke hym to ke∣pe in his owne conscyen∣ce the abbaye of the holy ghost. And he of his ow∣ne propre foly lete beere awaye out of that abbay all the good y<SUP>t</SUP> there was / &amp; the abbesse and her co∣uent ranne awaye out of her order. Therfore he was take &amp; put in to the pryson of helle / and there hath be now .M. yere and vi.C. &amp; more / &amp; y<SUP>t</SUP> is grete pyte. Therfore it were a good dede to make y<SUP>e</SUP> ab∣besse &amp; her couent fayre to come ayen in to her order &amp; make ayen the abbaye of the holy ghost as well as euer it was / &amp; to dely∣uer mānes soule out of y<SUP>e</SUP> sory pryson. He hath be therin longe tyme / haue we pyte on hym. He is as one of vs made to our ly¦kenes. All y<SUP>e</SUP> holy trynyte graūtid it shold be so / but it was asked who sholde do y<SUP>e</SUP> dede. It were nede he were suche one y<SUP>t</SUP> were hol¦de to do it / &amp; also that he myght do it But no thyn¦ge was beholde to dely∣uer mānes soule but only man Ne no thyng mygh¦te delyuer hym but onely god. Therfore he y<SUP>t</SUP> shol∣de do that dede muste be both god &amp; man / and so myght no thynge be but were one of the thre per∣sones of y<SUP>e</SUP> trynyte. Ther¦fore they ordeyned y<SUP>t</SUP> the seconde persone y<SUP>t</SUP> is al∣myghty goddes sone shol¦de come in to this worlde &amp; be borne of a mayde &amp;
<PB REF="12"/>
become man / &amp; make a∣gayn the abbaye of y<SUP>e</SUP> ho¦ly ghost / &amp; deye for loue of man on y<SUP>e</SUP> rood tree / &amp; so delyuer mānes soule fro y<SUP>e</SUP> payne of helle. Then̄e were there foure dough∣ters of almyghty god / whiche ben Mercy Trou the Ryghtwysnes &amp; Peas the whiche herde telle y<SUP>t</SUP> mānes soule sholde be de¦lyuered fro helle payne / &amp; came all foure <ABBR>togyd</ABBR> be∣fore god almighty Then sayd Trouth thus to her fader almyghty god / lor∣de she sayd y<SUP>u</SUP> hast louid e∣uer well me that am thy doughter Trouth. I pray y<SUP>e</SUP> forsake my not. Thou sayd what tyme man ete of y<SUP>e</SUP> fruyte / he sholde deye &amp; go to helle. Therfore yf thou delyuer man out fro thens / thou destroyest me &amp; that were no reason For goddes trouth lastith without ende. Thenne sayd Mercy. ¶O pater mīa{rum} <ABBR>&amp;c.</ABBR> Fader of mercy &amp; god of all comforte y<SUP>t</SUP> comfortest all thynge in angre &amp; in wo / haue thou mercy on mānes soule y<SUP>t</SUP> lyeth boūde in helle / and brynge hym in to blysse. For thou sayd y<SUP>u</SUP> woldest kepe mercy to hym with¦out ende Therfore sayth thou art true / y<SUP>u</SUP> shalt ha∣ue mercy on mānes soule Thenne sayd Ryghtwys¦nes. Nay nay / it may not be so. ¶Quia iust{us} dn̄s &amp; iusticias dilexit. Lorde she sayd thou art ryghtfull / &amp; louest rightwysnes / the¦re fore y<SUP>u</SUP> shalt not ryght∣fully saue mannes soule. For it is ryght &amp; reason y<SUP>t</SUP> he haue y<SUP>t</SUP> he hath deser∣ued / for he hath forsake god y<SUP>t</SUP> hym forth brought &amp; he hath forgete his lor¦de y<SUP>t</SUP> made hym of nough¦te. Therfore it is reason that y<SUP>u</SUP> haue of hym no∣ther
<PB REF="12"/>
pyte ne mercy / for thy ryghtwysnes shal las¦te in to the worldes ende ¶Tenne sayd Mercy to Ryghtwysnes. Syster be thou styll &amp; saye not so / for it were not ryght y<SUP>u</SUP> knowest well y<SUP>t</SUP> god shol∣de forsake me. For y<SUP>e</SUP> mer¦cy of god is aboue al his werkes / &amp; the mercy of god was without begyn∣nynge &amp; shal be without endynge. Therfore yf god forsoke me / he sholde forsake both my syster &amp; the / y<SUP>t</SUP> were nother ryght ne trouth. Therfore she sayd to saue vs all thre / god shall haue of mānes soule both mercy &amp; pyte. ¶Thenne sayd Peas to her thyrde syster. ¶ Pax dm̄ exsuperat oēm sensū. The peas of god passeth al maner wytte Though it be so she sayd y<SUP>t</SUP> trouthe saye ayenst skyll why mā¦nes soule sholde not be sa¦ued / &amp; ryghtwysnes also an other. Neuertheles me thynketh y<SUP>t</SUP> mercy sayth best / that mannes soule sholde be saued. For as she soth sayth / elles god shold forsake you al thre both Ryghtwysnes Mer∣cy. &amp; Trouth. And I thyn¦ke that were grete ruthe. And not oonly he sholde forsake you thre / but also he sholde forsake me For as longe as mānes soule is so in helle / there shalbe dyscorde amōge you thre For Ryghtwysnes and Trouth shall wyll to ha¦ue hym there styll / &amp; Mer¦cy shall wyll to haue him out / so that peas amonge you shal be forsake. Also yf man were soo styll in helle / there sholde be dys∣corde betwene god &amp; man &amp; betwene angell &amp; man &amp; betwene man &amp; man / so y<SUP>t</SUP> peas sholde be forsake ouer all / whiche were no
<PB REF="13"/>
proustyte. Therfore sayd Peas do ye after my coū∣sell / &amp; praye we god all to gyder y<SUP>t</SUP> is prynce of peas y<SUP>t</SUP> he wol make peas &amp; a∣corde betwene you thre / betwene god &amp; man / be∣twene angell &amp; man / &amp; betwene man &amp; man / &amp; ordeyne suche a way that he maye kepe vs styll all foure systers. ¶All they thoughte that she sayd best. And all prayed god of heuen that he wolde so do. And thenne he sayd ¶Ego cogito cogitacio∣nes pacis et nō affliccōes I thynke sayd god thou∣ghtes of peas and not of wyckednes / &amp; I shall he sayd kepe you stylle alle foure / &amp; shal saue mānes soule and brynge hym to blysse. ¶Also he sayd I shall fynde vp thabbesse of thabbaye of the holy ghost / &amp; make ayen the abbaye &amp; the couent all togyder better than euer it was before. ¶Whan thyse systers herde this / they were glad &amp; Ioyfull ¶Mīa et veritas obuia∣uerūt sibi iusticia et pax osculate sūt. Mercy and trouth mette them <ABBR>togyd</ABBR> ryghtwysnes &amp; peas ben kyssed and made at one. ¶Tho anone almyghty god the fader sende dow∣ne his owne sone in to this worlde to become mā for vs / &amp; to seke thabbesse of thabbaye of the holy ghost &amp; her holy couent / y<SUP>t</SUP> is to saye. Charyte &amp; o∣ther noble vertues. And the fyrste daye y<SUP>t</SUP> he came he foūde a lady of y<SUP>t</SUP> ho∣ly abbaye that is called Clennesse. For he was cō¦ceyued without knowle∣gynge of ony man tho∣rugh the vertue &amp; the ope¦racyon of the holy ghost / and borne of a pure clene mayden and virgyn that
<PB REF="13"/>
neuer was defyled wyth synne.</P>
<P>¶Thus clennesse he foū¦de whan he was in his <ABBR>mods</ABBR> wombe beynge in∣carnate man by that pu∣re vyrgyn. ¶ And that noble lady he kepte with hym there .xxxix. wekes Thenne was he borne of his moder in an olde bro¦ken house at Bethleem townes ende / &amp; layed on an asses mangeer on a ly¦tel heye. And there he foū¦de an other lady of y<SUP>t</SUP> ab∣baye &amp; y<SUP>t</SUP> was Pouerte For his blessid <ABBR>mod</ABBR> had none other shetes for to wynde hym in / but toke a keuer∣chyf of her heed / &amp; kytte an olde kertyl &amp; made of it cloutes / &amp; wounde our blessyd lord therin for col¦de. And layed hym on a wyspe of heye before an oxe &amp; an asse. Thyse two ladyes Pouerte &amp; Clēnes he lad forth w<SUP>t</SUP> hym tyll he was .xij. yeres olde.</P>
<P>¶Thenne went he forth with Ioseph &amp; his moder to <ABBR>Ierlm</ABBR> to offre there in an Ester daye. And whā they had offrid &amp; were go∣ynge home ayen / our lor¦de <ABBR>Ihu</ABBR> bode styll at Ieru¦salem thre dayes / &amp; went in to the temple amonge maysters of y<SUP>e</SUP> lawe The∣re he foūde other two la∣dyes of the holy abbaye / that were. Wysdom and Ryghtwysnes.</P>
<P>¶Whan Mary &amp; Ioseph were come home &amp; wyst not where <ABBR>Ihus</ABBR> was beco¦me / they made moche so∣rowe for y<SUP>t</SUP> swete childe / &amp; went ayen to <ABBR>Ierlm</ABBR> to se¦ke hym. Thenne they foūde hym in the temple syttynge amonge doctors dysputynge of the lawe. Thenne sayd his <ABBR>mod</ABBR> to hym. Sone what hast y<SUP>u</SUP> done / thy fader &amp; I haue sought the makynge for
<PB REF="14"/>
the moche sorowe. Then¦ne sayd <ABBR>Ihus</ABBR>. How is it y<SUP>t</SUP> ye sought me / wytt ye not well that I must be besy about my <ABBR>fads</ABBR> nedes. He sende me in to this coūtre to seke vp thabbesse &amp; the couent of thabbay of the holy ghost. And therfore I went amonge y<SUP>e</SUP> may∣sters in to the temple / &amp; there foūde I two ladyes of the couent. Ryghtwys¦nes &amp; Wysdom / and so he <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>de more than all they Then̄e went he home w<SUP>t</SUP> Ioseph &amp; his moder in to Nazareth / &amp; there he foū¦de an other lady y<SUP>t</SUP> was called Buxūnes. For he y<SUP>t</SUP> is hyghest lorde was lo∣west of hert / &amp; in al thyn¦ge buxome to his moder. ¶ Then̄e went he forth xvij. yeres &amp; an half / &amp; e∣uery daye at his borde he foūde other two ladyes of that holy abbaye / &amp; theyr names were Temporaū¦ce and Sobren̄es. He lad them with hym in to de∣serte to seke mo of her fe¦lowes. And there he foū∣de other two ladyes / that one hyght Penaūce &amp; her felowe Strength. He foū¦de there penaūce ynough for he fasted .xl. dayes &amp; xl. nyght for loue of mā¦nes soule without meete &amp; drynke / &amp; thenne he be¦gan to hungre. ¶ There came the fende to hym y<SUP>t</SUP> came to Eue in paradyse in to thabbaye of the ho∣ly ghost / &amp; wolde haue o∣uercome hym in gloteny as he dyde her / &amp; lad him to an hepe of stones / and bad hym yf he were god∣des sone he shold make y<SUP>e</SUP> stones loues / &amp; ete of thē ynough. Thenne foūde he there strength / thrugh <ABBR>which</ABBR> he withstode mygh¦tly the temptacion of the fende &amp; sayd. Man lyueth not oonly by brede / but by
<PB REF="14"/>
euery worde of goddes mouth. Thenne bare the fende hym thens in to Ie¦rusalē &amp; set hym on y<SUP>e</SUP> py∣nacle of the temple / and wolde haue ouercome hȳ with pryde &amp; vaynglory. &amp; sayd. Yf thou be god∣des sone skyppe downe &amp; take none harme / and al men shall prayse the / and saye that thou hast done a grete maystry Thenne he withstode also his tēp¦tacōn with the vertue of that lady Strength / and sayd Thou shalt not tēp¦te thy lorde god / as who sayth it is no nede that I skyppe downe I may go downe well ynough by a¦nother waye. Thenne he lad hym in to an hyghe hylle &amp; shewed hym ther̄ al the rychesse of the worl¦de / &amp; wolde haue ouerco∣me hym in couetyse &amp; say¦de. I shall gyue y<SUP>t</SUP> all the goodes that thou seest / yf thou wolt knele downe &amp; worshyp me. And there he withstode myghtly w<SUP>t</SUP> the lady strength / &amp; sayd Go thy waye Sathanas and torne ayen to helle. Men shall worshyp al∣myghty god &amp; hym on̄ly serue &amp; noo thynge elles. Thenne was the fende ashamed of hymself that he was so ouercome with the lady Strength.</P>
<P>¶Tho went Ihūs in to the londe of Galyle / and there he foūde other two ladyes of that holy ab∣baye / one hyght Shryfte &amp; that other Predycacōn For there preched Cryste fyrste &amp; sayd to the peo∣ple of the coūtree. ¶Pe∣nitemini et confitemini et credite euāgelio. Shry¦ue ye you &amp; do ye penaū∣ce &amp; be ye of good byleue the kyngdom of heuen nygheth faste ¶Thenne went he forth to the see
<PB REF="15"/>
syde / &amp; there he foūde Pe¦ter &amp; Andrewe his <ABBR>brod</ABBR> castynge theyr nettes in to the see to catche fysshe And Cryste sayd to them Come ye &amp; folowe me / &amp; I shal make you fysshers of men. And they lefte theyr bote styll in the see &amp; went forth with Cryst So they went a lytel fer∣der &amp; foūde <ABBR>Iohn</ABBR> &amp; Ia∣mes his broder in an o∣ther bote drawyng theyr nettes with Zebede theyr fader / for they were fys∣shers also. And Cryste bad theym folowe him / &amp; they lefte theyr fader &amp; al that they hadde in the bote &amp; yede with Cryste. ¶ On a daye as they ye∣de by the waye Peter say¦de to Cryste. What shall we haue of the that haue forsake al that we had &amp; folowe the thus in pouer¦te. Thenne Cryste foūde an other lady of that ho¦ly abbaye called Large∣nes. Forsoth Cryst sayd / ye y<SUP>t</SUP> haue forsake al that ye had &amp; folowe me / shal haue an hūdred folde so moche therfore / &amp; therto lyf w<SUP>t</SUP>out ende ¶Then̄e came he forth on a daye fro the moūt of Olyuete in to the temple of <ABBR>Ierlm</ABBR> to preche there / &amp; whyle he was prechynge / y<SUP>e</SUP> Sar¦rasyns brought hȳ a wo∣man take in auowtry / &amp; sayd to hym. Lo mayster this woman is now take in a spousebreche / what shal we now do with her Moyses byddeth in our lawe that we sholde sto∣ne suche to deth. Cryste knewe theyr falshede y<SUP>t</SUP> they dyde it to tempte hȳ stowped downe &amp; wrote on the grounde with his fynger all theyr synnes / so y<SUP>t</SUP> eche of them myght se how synfull other was And thenne he sayde to
<PB REF="15"/>
them thus. Syth it is so that by your lawes this woman shalbe stoned to dethe / thenne whiche of you all that is without synne / caste he on her the fyrste stone. Thenne all they were ashamed of themself &amp; went out at y<SUP>e</SUP> doore eche after other / &amp; lete Cryste stonde allone w<SUP>t</SUP> the woman. Thenne came two ladyes to hym of the abbaye of the holy ghost / that were Mercy &amp; Pyte. Thenne sayd Cry¦ste to y<SUP>t</SUP> woman. Woman where ben thyn enmyes. Hath ony man condemp¦ned the to deth. Lorde she sayd no man / &amp; I wol not sayd our lorde condemp∣ne the. Fare well he sayd &amp; be in wyl nomore to do synne. Here was grete mercy &amp; pyte / for the gret¦test trespasse y<SUP>t</SUP> she dyde was ayenst hymself.</P>
<P>¶Afterwarde on a daye the Sarrasȳs sende theyr dyscyples to Cryst to ha∣ue take hym in wordes. They asked hym yf they myght by goddes lawe gyue trybute to thempe∣rour. Cryste knewe theyr malyce wel / &amp; sayd. Ye y∣pocryt what nede is it to tēpte me. Lete me se a pe∣ny of your money / &amp; they shewed hym one. Then̄e sayd Cryst / whoos coyne is this / they sayd thempe¦rours. Then̄e foūde Cry¦ste a lady of the couent / y<SUP>t</SUP> was called Reason / &amp; say¦de. Gyue ye to thempe∣rour y<SUP>t</SUP> longeth to hym / &amp; to god y<SUP>t</SUP> longeth to hym &amp; that is reason.</P>
<P>¶One daye ther̄ as Cry¦ste went by y<SUP>e</SUP> waye by hȳ¦selfe / he remembred hym on mānes soule &amp; on the abbaye of y<SUP>e</SUP> holy ghost / &amp; thenne he foūde an other lady of the same house / that men calle Gelousye
<PB REF="16"/>
Thenne toke he his dys∣cyples preuyly &amp; went to∣warde <ABBR>Ierlm</ABBR> &amp; sayd to them th{us}. I haue al thyse xxxij. yeres &amp; more be a∣bout to helpe mānes sou∣le / &amp; to kepe vp y<SUP>e</SUP> abbesse &amp; the couent y<SUP>t</SUP> wente out of thabbaye of the holy ghost / &amp; I haue foūde of them .xvi. And now I wol go to <ABBR>Ierlm</ABBR> &amp; be boūde / beten / hangen &amp; drawe / &amp; I shal deye for loue of mā¦nes soule / to fynde vp the other dele of y<SUP>e</SUP> holy couēt This was a grete Ielou¦sy &amp; a grete loue ¶ Then̄ went they forth to <ABBR>Ierlm</ABBR> to gader / &amp; on a tyme as they were at theyr souper <ABBR>togyd</ABBR> Cryst foūde two la¦dyes of y<SUP>t</SUP> abbaye / y<SUP>t</SUP> men calle Curteysy &amp; Honeste For Cryst fed there at sou¦per his dyscyples w<SUP>t</SUP> his owne flesshe and blood. Whan he had so done he wysshe theyr fete &amp; wiped them. At this offyce were foure ladyes. Curteysy &amp; Buxūnes. Honeste &amp; Me¦kenes.</P>
<P>¶Afterwarde he wente with his discyples in to a lytell towne that hyghte Gethsemany / &amp; there he toke thre of his men. Pe¦ter. Iames. &amp; <ABBR>Iohn</ABBR> / &amp; bad all the other abyde there styll tyl they came agayn As they went our lorde be¦gan to quake &amp; drad / &amp; thenne he sayd to them. Here I haue foūde an o∣ther lady of the holy co∣uent / that is called Drede I haue he sayd full mo∣che drede ayen y<SUP>t</SUP> I shall deye. Sytte ye downe he sayd &amp; wake ye / and byd your bedes tyll I come a∣yen to you Thenne went he forth fro them as fer∣re as it were a stones cas¦te / &amp; there he foūde other two ladyes. Medytacyon &amp; Oryson ¶He bethough¦te
<PB REF="16"/>
hym on mannes soule that it sholde be lost with¦out ende but yf he deyed therfore / &amp; how he sholde deye / &amp; so be harde naylid to the rode tree / &amp; he was in a grete agony / as noo <ABBR>wond</ABBR> was. And for drede of deth he swet dropes of blood y<SUP>t</SUP> fell downe in the groūde as dropes fall fro an hous euees after reyne Thenne prayed he to his <ABBR>fad</ABBR> &amp; sayd. <ABBR>Fad</ABBR> yf it may be lete me not deye thus dyspytously / netheles he sayd thy wyll be done &amp; not myn. Thenne came he ayen to his dyscyples &amp; foūde them slepynge / &amp; thenne he sayd to Peter. Mayst y<SUP>u</SUP> not one houre wake w<SUP>t</SUP> me. Wake ye he sayd &amp; praye y<SUP>t</SUP> ye fall not in to temptacōn Thenne went he ayen and foūde Oryson &amp; her syster De∣uocōn / &amp; sayd. My fader syth it may none other be but that I must nedes suf¦fre deth / be it as y<SUP>u</SUP> woll. Thenne came he ayen to his dyscyples &amp; foūde thē slepynge as he dyde befo¦re. He went ayen the thyr¦de tyme / &amp; prayed as he dyde fyrste &amp; foūde other ladyes of the holy abbay Contemplacōn Dalyan¦ce &amp; Iubylacōn. Thenne came an angell fro heuē to comforte hym / &amp; tolde how mannes soule or the thyrde daye sholde be de∣lyuerd out of helle / &amp; how by y<SUP>t</SUP> tyme he sholde fyn∣de vp all y<SUP>e</SUP> couent of the abbaye of the holy ghost &amp; al theyr place made vp ayen better then euer it was. Thenne was he me¦ry and glad in his soule though he were kyndely by his manhede agast of his dethe. ¶Thenne ca∣me he ayen to his dyscy∣ples &amp; bad them ryse vp and go with hym. And
<PB REF="17"/>
as they walked a lytell faith / they sawe there mo¦che folke comynge with lanternes &amp; drawen swer¦des &amp; staues to take our lorde. Iudas Scaryoth went before them all / and came to Cryste &amp; kyssed hym. And Cryste sayd to hym. Iudas frende shalt thou betraye goddes so∣ne with a cosse. ¶Then̄e the Iewes toke Cryste &amp; boūde hym as a theyf ful harde and sore. There he foūde an other lady of y<SUP>t</SUP> same hous / and she was named Pacyence. ¶ Pe∣ter sawe that / &amp; out with a swerde and smote of a boyes eere / that was one of y<SUP>e</SUP> bysshops men Then̄e sayd Cryste to Peter. Put vp thy swerde agayne. Trowest thou not that I myght praye my fader yf I wolde / &amp; he myght sende me mo than twelue legyons of angels. All this he sayd I woll suf∣fre with good wyll for lo¦ue of mannes soule.</P>
<P>¶Thenne the false Ie∣wes ladde forth <ABBR>Ihu</ABBR> Cry¦ste to Cayphas y<SUP>e</SUP> bysshop His dyscyples sawe that / &amp; ranne awaye for drede euerychone / &amp; lefte hym there alone. ¶Thenne came many shrewes and made playnt to y<SUP>e</SUP> bysshop on our lorde. Then̄e sayd Cayphas to our lorde. What sayst y<SUP>u</SUP> to thyse cō∣playnt &amp; trespasses that thyse men shewe ayenst y<SUP>e</SUP> ¶ Cryste foūde there an other lady that is called Symplenesse. For he an∣swered not to hym with one worde. ¶Then̄e the bysshop asked hym whe∣re he had preched / &amp; what he had taught and sayd. Thenne sayde Cryste. What demaundest y<SUP>u</SUP> me. Enquyre of them y<SUP>t</SUP> her∣de me preche what I sayd
<PB REF="17"/>
to them. Tho toke the Ie¦wes our lorde <ABBR>Ihu</ABBR> &amp; put of his clothes and boūde hym to a pylar of stone. And made scourges with knottes of lede &amp; sharpe pryckes in thendes / and with them bete his precy∣ous body tyll it ranne all on blood. Thenne they dyde on hym a streyght sylken clothe / &amp; that cle∣uid fast to y<SUP>e</SUP> flesshe whan y<SUP>e</SUP> blood was drye. Then¦ne they set a garlonde on his heed of longe &amp; shar∣pe thornes / &amp; bete it har∣de downe with staues for they wolde not prycke theyr fyngers. And toke hym a rede in his honde / and kneled downe &amp; sayd in scorne. Hayle kyng of Iewes. Whan they had so done they strypte of y<SUP>t</SUP> cote of sylke / &amp; for it cle∣uyd fast to the body / they drewe awaye therwith moche of the skynne and flesshe also. Whan they sawe that / the shrewes we¦re well pleasyd / &amp; bleryd on hym and spyt on hym And there foūde Cryste an other lady of the ab∣baye that hyght Meke∣nes. ¶Tho the false Ie∣wes made Cryste to bere his owne crosse on his backe towarde the moūt of Caluary / tyll he was in poynt to falle downe for feblynesse Whan they sawe that / they wolde not that he deyed tyll he had be hanged for grete ma∣lyce &amp; hate that they had to hym. They made an other man to bere y<SUP>e</SUP> crosse tyll they came to the pla¦ce where Cry sholde be nayled on. And euer as he wente the good lady Mekenes went with him Trowe ye not that his moder hadde thenne mo¦che sorowe whan she sa∣we her sone goo soo to∣warde
<PB REF="18"/>
his deth. Forsoth it was a pyteous syght / who y<SUP>t</SUP> had it seen. ¶ Whan they cam to Caluary they cast downe there y<SUP>e</SUP> crosse &amp; layed our lorde alonge theron / &amp; made markes &amp; holes where his hondes and fete were nayled to. Then̄e they toke a blont rough raggid nayle &amp; dro¦ue w<SUP>t</SUP> an hamour thrugh his honde to y<SUP>e</SUP> crosse. And for anguysshe therof all his body drewe there to∣warde / they wolde haue nayled y<SUP>t</SUP> other honde to y<SUP>e</SUP> crosse / &amp; it was to short to the hole y<SUP>t</SUP> they had made by half a fote &amp; more / &amp; yet wolde they make noo newe holes / but toke ro∣pes &amp; tyed to his honde &amp; drewe it tyll it was mete to the hole. And in y<SUP>e</SUP> dra¦wynge all the Ioyntes of his armes brake asondre Whan they wolde haue nayled his fete to y<SUP>e</SUP> crosse al his body was so shron¦ke vp togyder for peyne y<SUP>t</SUP> it was to short for y<SUP>e</SUP> hole y<SUP>t</SUP> they had made by a lar¦ge fote. Then̄e toke they ropes &amp; tyed to his fete / &amp; drewe hym downe harde &amp; lore tyll they were mete therfore / they brake in y<SUP>t</SUP> drawynge al the Ioyntes of his lyndes &amp; knees &amp; of his fete also. Thenne they toke suche an other raggyd rough nayle and draue it thrugh both his fete w<SUP>t</SUP> an hamour ato∣nes in to the harde tree / &amp; whyle he was th{us} nayled on y<SUP>e</SUP> crosse / came many la¦dyes of y<SUP>e</SUP> holy abbaye Po¦uerte. Buxūnes. Penaūce Symplenes. Pacyence. &amp; Mekenes / to se how he di¦de. Then̄e sayd Cryst to them / yf ye had your ab∣besse / then̄e had ye euery∣chone. ¶Whan y<SUP>e</SUP> Iewes had nayled hym on the crosse / as men do cloth on
<PB REF="18"/>
a teyntour / they lyfte vp the crosse fro y<SUP>e</SUP> groūde to set it faste in y<SUP>e</SUP> morteys y<SUP>t</SUP> was made for y<SUP>e</SUP> same pur¦poos. And in theyr grete enuyous malyce y<SUP>e</SUP> cursed Iewes lyft it vp as hygh as they myght w<SUP>t</SUP> streng¦the of men &amp; lete it falle downe sodenly in to the morteys. In y<SUP>e</SUP> fallynge all the synewes of his bo¦dy / all y<SUP>e</SUP> veynes / &amp; all the Ioyntes brake euery one. I trowe there was pe∣naūce ynough.</P>
<P>¶The lady Pouerte was there all redy / for he han¦ged all naked as he was born of his moder on the crosse for mannes soule. And whyle he hāgid ther̄ with his blody woūdes al to hurlyd &amp; all to rente. He foūde y<SUP>e</SUP> abbesse of the abbaye of the holy ghost y<SUP>t</SUP> is callid Charyte / y<SUP>e</SUP> whi¦che sayd. ¶Maiorē cari∣tatē nemo hēt {quam} vt aīam suā ponat quis {pro} amicis suis. More loue &amp; charyte may noo man haue than to gyue his lyf for his frē¦des / as Cryst dyde for mā¦nes soule. ¶Whan Cryst had foūde y<SUP>e</SUP> holy abbesse Charyte &amp; all her couent he was full glad in his herte / all though he felte moche wo of bodyly pay¦ne withoutforth. Then̄e asked he a drynke to ma¦ke with all thyse ladyes mery. And welcomed thē &amp; sayd (Scicio) I thurste Thenne the false Iewes made to him a drynke of eysell &amp; gall tempred to∣gyder with myrre / &amp; put it to his mouth vppon a spounge. Whan our lorde had smellid y<SUP>e</SUP> taste therof he wolde no more therof but he sayd thus. ¶Con∣summatū est. That is to saye. I haue done all my <ABBR>fads</ABBR> message y<SUP>t</SUP> he bad me doo on erthe. For I haue
<PB REF="19"/>
foūde vp the abbesse &amp; al the couent of the abbaye of the holy ghost / &amp; made ayen thabbay better than euer it was. Now he sayd I woll go to Adam &amp; to my frendes &amp; delyuer thē out of helle / &amp; lede them ayen to the blysse of para¦dyse y<SUP>t</SUP> neuer shall cesse.</P>
<P>¶Whan he had sayd th{us} he gaaf vp the ghost and deyed in flesshe hangyn∣ge on the crosse all to rus¦shyd &amp; all to rent / so vn∣neth ony lȳme henge by other bitwene two theuis for grete loue y<SUP>t</SUP> he had to saue mānes soule Then̄e ghostly in his godhede he went downe to helle &amp; to¦ke out Adam &amp; Eue. A∣bell &amp; Seth / &amp; other. Noe Abraham / Iacob &amp; Ysaac Ioseph. Moyses / &amp; kyng Dauyd. Patryarkes and prophetes / &amp; all his fren∣des he toke with hym / &amp; lad them w<SUP>t</SUP> thabbesse &amp; the couente of the holy ghost to y<SUP>e</SUP> blysse of heuen And there almyghty god ordenyd y<SUP>t</SUP> his four dough¦ters Mercy and Trouth Ryghtwysnes and Peas sholde dwelle in thabbay of y<SUP>e</SUP> holy ghost. And then he cōmaūded hymself / y<SUP>t</SUP> Mercy &amp; Trouth sholde be Charytees chapeleyns &amp; goo about w<SUP>t</SUP> her why∣ther y<SUP>t</SUP> she went. He bad also y<SUP>t</SUP> Ryghtwysnes shol¦de be w<SUP>t</SUP> Wysdom / for she was pryouresse &amp; Peas w<SUP>t</SUP> Mekenesse y<SUP>t</SUP> was suppry¦ouresse. He ordeyned y<SUP>t</SUP> thy¦se thre ladyes sholde haue theyr chapeleyns / for they were moost of worshyp. ¶Thenne he sayd / he y<SUP>t</SUP> woll kepe fayr &amp; wel thy¦se holy vertues / he shall fynde in this worlde by holy medytacōn / by good conuersacōn / by noble cō∣templacōn moche Ioye &amp; myrth both in body &amp; sou¦le.
<PB REF="19" MS="y"/>
And afterwarde whan he is deed / he shall haue to his mede y<SUP>e</SUP> kyngdom of heuen / y<SUP>t</SUP> is to laye mo∣re Ioye &amp; blysse than ony eye may se / or eere here / or tonge telle / or herte thynke. Almyghty god for his grete mercy gyue vs grace &amp; socour to kepe fayr &amp; well this abbaye / that is our conscyence / &amp; all the hole couent / that is to laye good vertues / in thought / in worde / &amp; in de¦de / that we may come to the blysse that god bough¦te vs to. Amen.</P>
<P>¶Now frendes &amp; brethe¦ren in Cryste <ABBR>Ihu</ABBR> that co¦ueyte crystenly to lyue in Crystis religyon Kepe ye well your abbesse Chary¦te in herte / and all thyse other noble vertues befo∣re reherced. And yf it soo befalle y<SUP>e</SUP> ony lȳme of the deuyll bodyly or ghostly be abowte to take from you this lady Charyte / rynge ye your Chaptour belle of your in wyt. And calle ye to your counsell Reason &amp; Dyscrecōn. Pa¦cyence &amp; Peas. And go ye forth to Oryson / &amp; crye ye in soule to y<SUP>e</SUP> holy ghost And in wardly praye him that he come &amp; defende charyte. That he thrugh his gracyous helpe kepe you fro euyll chaūce And he that made vs all with blysse vs auaūce. Amen.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<P>¶Enprynted at West¦mestre by Wynken de worde.</P>
<PB REF="20"/>
<PB REF="20"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

