<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The favorites chronicle</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Chronique des favoris. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>Fancan, François Dorval-Langlois, sieur de, ca. 1576-1628.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A05062</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 15203</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S108220</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99843892</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99843892</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">8654</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A05062)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8654)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 767:10)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The favorites chronicle</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Chronique des favoris. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>Fancan, François Dorval-Langlois, sieur de, ca. 1576-1628.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 41, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London] :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed according to the French copie,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>M.DC.XXI. [1621]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>A translation of: Fancan, François Dorval-Langlois, sieur de.  Chronique des favoris.</NOTE><NOTE>Place of publication from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>There are two editions; B2v line 2 has (1) "beganne" or (2) "began".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Elspeth Healey</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Elspeth Healey</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A05062">
<STC T="S">15203</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99843892</BIBNO>
<VID>8654</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
FAVOVRITES
<HI>CHRONICLE.</HI>
{inverted ⁂}</P>
<P>Printed according to the French Copie.
M.DC.XXI.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="discourse">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE
FAVOVRITES
CHRONICLE.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">C</SEG>Vrious Gentlemen, that spend your time
and take pleasure to recreate your spirits
with the consideration of the Tragedies
that are acted vpon the Theater of this
World; I cannot be perswaded but that
you haue heretofore read that which
learned <HI>Aesope</HI> rehearseth in his Fables, of certain Hares,
who running away when they heard the hounds open,
by chance past along by the side of a ditch, where there
were great store of frogs vpon the grasse, who as soone
as they saw the hares, leapt as fast as they could into the
water. This action being noted by the timorous hares,
did in such maner encourage them, that the same onely
sufficed to make them stay their running any further; at
which time, one of them (who it may be had studied the
French eloquence, practised by Master <HI>William du Vair</HI>)
told them, that from thence forward it behoued them to
esteeme more of their valours then euer they had done
before; that it was a shame for them alwayes to haue bin
held &amp; esteemed to be fearfull, and a signe of reprochfull
dastardlinesse vnto their auncestors, continually to haue
vsed to runne away, and neuer durst looke in their ene∣mies
faces, seeing they were capable to ouercome and sub∣due
others, as they might well perceiue by experience of
these croaking frogs, whose onely presence had put them
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1+ words" DISP="〈◊…〉"/>, without any stroke given.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1+ words" DISP="〈◊…〉"/> his notable oration, (as plausibly pronounced, as that
which my Lord Constable made to those of <HI>Thoulonze</HI>)
so much encouraged his companions, that presently they
resolved, not to set vpon <HI>Montaubon,</HI> but in time to come
to shew themselues more valiant, and to magnifie and ex∣alt
their generositie, and from thenceforward determi∣ned
to act some glorious enterprise against those accur∣sed
hounds, and to turne their faces against their enemies
to assaile them: which counsell put in execution, tooke
so bad effect, and fell out so vnfortunately for the authors
thereof, that thereby they were not onely taken, but torne
in peeces, to serve for a prey unto their enemies, and a
jest unto other more judicious and subtill beasts.</P>
<P>This fable, in my opinion, may properly be applied un∣to
the levying of armes at this time, whereinto so impro∣vidently
we have bin led by the plausible inducements of
certaine prating companions, that have so much advan∣ced
and magnified the Favourite Hares, that they have
made them to busie their braines about the ambitious
reach of their prowd fortunes.</P>
<P>Every man knowes what discontentment the great
personages of this Realme have had, to beholde the
Crowne of France within these foure yeares to be as it
were besieged by <HI>Luynes</HI> and his brethren; who to the
great prejudice of the Kings affaires and the Common∣wealth,
absolutely disposed both of the ordinarie and ca∣suall
matters of State, to the great desolation of the whole
monarchie: which to oppose and prevent, the greatest
part of the Princes and principall Officers of the Realme
in <HI>Anno</HI> 1620. made a kinde of league. But the number of
the Leaguers being extreme great, the businesse could not
be so securely managed as the case required: whereupon
it fell out so, that it was presently discovered, by the in∣fidelitie
of certaine persons that betrayed them. In pur∣suite
whereof, the vanquishers had the victorie without
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
combat, and the vanquished ouerthrew themselues.</P>
<P>Now appropriating the sence of this fable to my pre∣sent
discourse, I must tell you that my Masters the Favo∣rite
Hares, the last yeare being made afraid and abashed
with the apprehension that they conceived of so many
yong Princes that sought to overthrow and crosse their
insolent fortune, they were constrained to abandon the
delights of the Court, to seeke and finde out some meanes
to shadow and cover themselves from the great tempest
which as then seemed to menace them. And so shaking
and trembling with feare, they went into Normandie,
where by good fortune they met with certaine people,
that like true frogs, hid themselves in the reedes, at the
noise of their horses feete. Which made the Favorites set
up their eares, and from that time forwards to conceive
a wonderfull opinion of their affaires. But when they en∣tred
into the medowes in <HI>Angers,</HI> and perceived that at
their onely presence, the frogs of <HI>Pont de See</HI> slipt downe
from off the bridge of <HI>Pont</HI> to hide themselves in the wa∣ter,
they did then begin upon that occasion to conceive
so great an opinion of their valours, that they were of
the minde presently in a maner to set forward to fight
against the great Turke, without once staying till the
Duke <HI>de Nevers</HI> vessels were made readie, or the new
Knights of the Christian warre were prepared to fight,
imagining themselves to be three <HI>Caesars,</HI> able to over∣come
and rule over all men, whereupon they resolved to
lay hold vpon all occasions, and to command all, and so
farre, as to presume to make, not onely the Princes of the
blood, but also the Regall authoritie, to serve them for a
footstoole or a step unto their greatnesse.</P>
<P>Whereupon our neighbours (hauing <HI>Argus</HI> eyes) be∣ing
alwayes vigilant, and neuer sleepe, and with their spe∣ctacles
continually beholding our proceedings, to draw
some profit from thence, accommodating them to the
interest of their affaires, perceiving the haughty deseignes
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
of the Favorite Hares; and that the pride which they con∣ceived
in their hearts of those ridiculous victories, was
available to thrust them forward and embarke them into
some great enterprise, how dangerous soever it were, so
the perill that should be ministred were well gilded over:
they advised with themselves that a civill warre in <HI>France</HI>
would fall out well to the purpose, to be a meanes for
them to attaine to the end of the Germane revolts, and
of the vsurpation which they pretended to make vpon
the <HI>Palatinate, Inlliers</HI> and <HI>Valtolina.</HI></P>
<P>And to make them the more eagerly and easily to catch
at the baite, they practised to re-assemble all the old rags
and peeces of the holy league, therewith to make a faire
cloake of religion, finely sowed by the fathers of the Ie∣suiticall
societie, and thereof to make a rich present unto
the eldest Favorite, shewing him what a glorie it would
be vnto him to weare the same, as in times past a certaine
Duke of <HI>Guise</HI> had done; and that the onely way for him,
without any trouble to attaine the Constables office, was
to gild the scabberd of his sword with the spoiles of the
foolish hare-braind heretickes, without speaking of the
great summes of mony that he might by that meanes le∣vie
of the people, vnder pretence of so pious a quarrell,
as that of religion would be; besides the hazard that he
incurred to be canonized, according to the ordinarie ma∣ner,
with the Cardinals <HI>de Ioyense,</HI> and the Earle <HI>de Fi∣esque.</HI></P>
<P>This glorious advice, presented with as plausible words
as those of father <HI>Cotton,</HI> moved our new warriers to a
desire and great appetite to be doing somewhat: and their
deseigne was presently confirmed by the Archbishop of
<HI>Sens,</HI> and the Keeper of the Seales, to whom were shew∣ed
red Hats, woven by the hand of an Archangell, with a
letter written by <HI>Pontchartrain,</HI> containing an assurance
that those Hats were for them: for the which the Cardi∣nals
<HI>de la Rochefoucault</HI> and <HI>de Rets</HI> were sureties, upon
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
the certificate of father <HI>Berule,</HI> and of the Marquis <HI>de
Maignelay.</HI></P>
<P>Touching the execution of the ruin of the heretickes,
it was solemnly sworne by a Catholick Councell holden
in <HI>Fontainebleau</HI> by divers great persons of the Realme,
where the future Constable sat as President, apparelled
like another <HI>Alexander,</HI> holding a sword of damaske of
Genes in his hand, about the which was graven, <HI>He that
kils with the sword, shall die by the sheath.</HI> Now with more
ease to bring this enterprise to effect, <HI>Luynes</HI> like an ex∣pert
falconer, esteemed it requifite for him to haue a Duke
to draw the simpler sort of birds to the lure: and for that
certaine yeares together he had fixed both his eyes upon
the office of Constable, although long before hee had
made an offer thereof to the Duke <HI>de Lesdiguieres,</HI> to see
what the great personages would say to the reestablish∣ment
of that office; he purposed to renew that proposi∣tion
unto him againe, and caused him to come to the
Court, not with an intent to honour him with that dig∣nitie,
but on the contrary, to make him desist from it, for
his owne advantage, and ciuilly to hold him as a prisoner,
by his wives meanes, who vnder pretence of some par∣ticular
profit, hath exposed her husbands honour to the
open view of the world. Thus the said Lord Marshall be∣ing
fallen into the nets that were laid abroad for him, pre∣sently
father <HI>Arnoux</HI> was seene to sweate water &amp; blood,
to procure the conversion of the poore Huguenots; who
paying him well, he did happily bring into the lap of the
Church, thereby to warme and encourage the spirits of
those that were zealous, and to animate them with more
crueltie against the heretickes. While the Earle <HI>de Schom∣berg</HI>
had commission given unto him to furnish a masse
of treasure, to defray the charges which should be conve∣nient
(at what price soever it should cost) to seeke both
on hils and in valleys for the band which in times past
had so often and victoriously bin borne against the Sara∣cins,
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
that it might once againe be displayed in so holy
a warre. And because it could not be found, what dili∣gent
search soeuer the fathers made, they were forced to
have recourse unto some other expedient thing, agreeable
to the greatnesse of that enterprise. And behold, for want
of the banner, unexpectedly the Constables sword rose up,
which <HI>Luynes</HI> had long time hidden in the breasts of the
Dukes <HI>de Guise,</HI> and <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> and <HI>de Lesdiguieres,</HI>
from whence he puld it artificially, to lay hold on it. And
it is to be noted, that the first time that he hung it by his
side, he held it a while naked in his hand, admiring his
owne valour, esteeming it equall unto that of <HI>Caesar;</HI> and
without further consideration of the difficulties of that
warre, cried out for joy, and said like another <HI>Alexander,
Nodos virtute resolvo,</HI> and then put the sword into the
scabberd, from whence it neuer came out againe, by the
advice of <HI>Cadnet</HI> and <HI>de Branthe,</HI> that they might not be
reproched, that one of them was more valiant then the
other. In the meane time, it was resolved to go directly
to <HI>Saumur,</HI> there to do homage for that warlike sword,
to our good Ladie <HI>de Ardvilliers,</HI> for the first fruites of his
militarie actions, to sacrifice vnto her the breaking vp of
blinde <HI>Monsieur du Plessis Mornays</HI> Librarie, who for that
he was as ill sighted as the Countesse <HI>de Moret,</HI> was decei∣ved
by the intercession of <HI>Villarnoud</HI> his sonne in law; so
it may well be said, that it was the first match that set fire,
not onely in the Temples of the Huguenots, <HI>du Plessis</HI>
and <HI>les Touers,</HI> but also in all the Cantons of the Realme,
for that upon the good successe of the yeelding up of that
place, the Favorite Hares resolved to adde the conquest of
<HI>S. Iohn d' Angely</HI> unto their triumphs, into the which
Towne they had sent <HI>Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>drieres</HI> to betray his compani∣ons,
and in recompence thereof they promised to dis∣charge
him of 1000 crownes yearely rent that he ought
to the Treasurer <HI>Moran,</HI> besides 15000 crownes which
they gaue him in ready mony. Thus from place to place
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
their conquests extended so farre, till they came before
<HI>Montauban,</HI> which my Lord Constable thought to take
as easily as hee could take up his Ladies smocke, as hee
made knowne by his letters sent to diuers places, by the
which he assured his friends, that he had sowed so good
corne in that accursed place, as he made no doubt but
that it would take roote. That was the cause that <HI>Te
Deum</HI> was sung in <HI>Boulogne, Lyons</HI> and many other pla∣ces
for the yeelding up thereof, grounding upon the in∣fallible
assurance y<SUP>t</SUP> some men had, that he would take it,
because he tooke all other places but onely <HI>Montauban.</HI>
But therein he was not to be blamed, for he had sent <HI>Sau∣uage</HI>
into the Towne, who had promised to deliuer that
Towne into his hands, as he had done <HI>Clerac:</HI> but the
traitor deceiued my Lord Constable, and standing on the
walls, mockt him.</P>
<P>This device failing, divers batteries were erected, sup∣posing
by that meanes to put the inhabitants thereof in
some feare. Trenches were cast up, and furious skirmishes
were made. Father <HI>Arnoux</HI> to encourage the souldiers, as∣sured
them by his part of Paradise, that all those that died
in so holy a quarrell, should neuer go into Purgatorie.
Whereupon euery man sought and strove to shew forth
his valour. <HI>Branthe</HI> and <HI>Cadnet</HI> made a goodly shew with
their great plumes of fethers, a great many of brave gen∣tlemen
were kild, and every day more and more were
slaine.</P>
<P>The report of this siege was spread abroad throughout
all Europe; and the late deceased King <HI>Henrie</HI> the fourth
had newes thereof caried unto him in the Elizian fields:
so that as when he liued he did tenderly and fatherly loue
and nourish <HI>France;</HI> the care of the quietnesse, together
with the desire he had to know the state thereof continu∣ally
vexed his soule. For which cause he sent messengers
into every place, to discover whether any French men had
past over the river of <HI>Styx.</HI> The late Baron <HI>de Villeroy</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>
brought him newes, that by chance he had met with a
Spaniard of his old acquaintance, who had told him for
certaine, that the Constable of <HI>France</HI> had begun a glo∣rious
warre against the heretickes, wherein he had pro∣ceeded
so happily, that in lesse then two moneths he had
reduced threescore Townes vnder his obedience, batte∣red,
taken and unwalled <HI>S. Iohn, Pont Nerac, Bergerac</HI> and
<HI>Clerac,</HI> and that as then he lay before <HI>Montauban</HI> with
fortie great peeces of cannon. That the Marquis <HI>de Villars</HI>
and divers others had bin burnt before it, though they
were no heretickes. That the Marquis <HI>de Themines</HI> and
the Duke <HI>de Mayenne</HI> also had bin slaine there, besides
400 gentlemen of name and qualitie, and aboue 15000
souldiers kild. That touching the raising up of the siege,
he could say nothing, for that the reverend father <HI>Domi∣nique
de Iesus Maria</HI> had there lost the subtiltie of his re∣velations;
and that there was none but the Duke <HI>de Bran∣the,</HI>
the Duke <HI>de Cadmet,</HI> and the Duke <HI>de Luynes</HI> that
were capable to take it: but they were not men to ex∣pose
their bodies in all enterprises, because of the im∣portance
of their persons.</P>
<P>Are they Spaniards? said the King. They are, said <HI>Ville∣roy,</HI>
the onely faithfull Counsellers to the King your son,
by whose advice all the Realme is governed. Wherewith
King <HI>Henrie</HI> the fourth scratching his head, stood as if
he had bin in a dreame, and staying a great while with∣out
speaking a word, at last sighing with a sad counte∣nance
and sorrowfull voice, he said: Alas, now I see well
that these men by litle and litle will vndoe my sonne,
and that that which my enemies could not do while I li∣ved,
they will enforce themselues to effect it in his life
time, by the meanes of those three petie Kings. Let search
be made in every place, to kuow if there be any of my
old servants to be found, among all those that have bin
kild before <HI>S. Iohn, Clerac</HI> and <HI>Montauban,</HI> that I may
discourse with them touching those lamentable things
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
that are done in my poore countrey of <HI>France.</HI></P>
<P>Truly, said the Chancellor <HI>de Belieure,</HI> euen now I saw
almost 20000 persons of all sorts and qualities, which
stand on the other side of the river of <HI>Stix,</HI> desiring to
passe over; but the Boate-man <HI>Caron</HI> refused them all, vn∣till
they have bin purged in the <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of Purgatorie. They
maintaining and constantly aff<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="2+ letters" DISP="••…"/>ing, that they were ex∣empted
from it, because they ha<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ost their lives before the
heretiks forts, according to the assurance given them in
the other world, by the Iesuites <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f <HI>Thoulouse</HI> and <HI>Bour∣deaux,</HI>
and namely by father <HI>Russelay.</HI></P>
<P>That grieves me much, said the King, I could be con∣tent
to haue given 100000 crownes to marry the Nunnes
in <HI>Paris,</HI> vpon condition that this contention were ended,
I haue so great a desire to see some one Frenchman or o∣ther,
that might ease me of my care, for the apprehension
that I haue conceived of the troubles of the King my son,
of the Queene my wife, and of my children.</P>
<P>Therewith the Baron <HI>de Liencourt</HI> stept forth and said
to the King: Sir, your Grace is much troubled to know
the truth of the affaires in the other world, you need but
direct your selfe vnto some Iesuites, for they haue letters
from all places. I came but now from speaking with fa∣ther
<HI>Gontrie,</HI> hee cannot chuse but know something; if
you will haue me enquire of him, it may be my wife hath
written him a word or two thereof. No, no, said <HI>Samet,</HI>
those kind of people are too craftie and subtill, the truth
neuer comes directly out of their mouthes, you shal know
nothing that way; I know a better way, <HI>Caron</HI> the boat∣man
is my friend, he and I haue many times dranke to∣gether,
I will deale so well with him, that for my sake
he shall not make difficultie to suffer some Frenchmen
(upon my recommendation) to passe over, or else let me
go over to them, to heare what they can say touching
your Graces desire. Venture <HI>S. Gry,</HI> said the King, your
invention is very good. Wherewith <HI>M. Guilliaume,</HI>
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
who in the meane time stood attentively to heare that dis∣course,
began to say unto the King: My Lord, if you
thinke it good, I will gladly beare <HI>Sebastian Zamet</HI> com∣panie,
and will aide him finely to passe over, as the suc∣cours
did into <HI>Montauban,</HI> while he stands speaking with
old <HI>Caron,</HI> and then I will speedily make a journey to
<HI>Louviers,</HI> to know how <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll fares there, and whether the
Normands are well co<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="2+ letters" DISP="••…"/>t to be bowles of Quillibeuf,
in recompence of their service. I will not have you
stirre from thence, said the King, you shall stand sentinell
on the South side, and onely marke when the Archduke
<HI>Albertus</HI> shall leane off his Monks cowle. <HI>Zamet</HI> dis∣patched
away, went to the river side, where being arived,
he heard newes that the Cardinall <HI>de Guise</HI> was come thi∣ther
with buls, to cause all those to passe over, that died
as he did in that holy warre, but that there was some dis∣pute
happened among those that stayed to passe over; for
which cause <HI>Caron</HI> would not let them passe, for feare lest
they should fight together while they were in his boate.
Thereupon <HI>Zamet</HI> to further the businesse, gaue his ad∣vice,
that it was convenient to sprinkle all those that qua∣relled
together, with water of oblivion, before they entred
into the boate, that so forgetting their quarels, they might
passe over peaceably. This counsell was instantly follow∣ed;
but as things are full of crosses, another controversie
hapned after that, betweene the said Cardinall and the
Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> who should first go into the boate. The
strife was long, which much displeased <HI>Zamet,</HI> because it
staid him from returning backe unto the King. The dis∣pute
was maintained by reasons on either side. The Car∣dinall
said, he died first, and by consequence y<SUP>t</SUP> he ought
to go first. The Duke denied not that, but said, hee was
to be preferred before him, because he had bin slaine in
the Kings service, and that the Cardinal died onely of sick∣nes.
The Cardinall replied, that for Gods sake he had a∣bandoned
both wife and children; and to proue it, desired
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
no other witnes but the Duke <HI>de Nevers;</HI> and that he had
not done so. At last they stood vpon the difference of
their degrees and qualities; and for that the Church al∣wayes
hath the preheminence, it was iudged that the Car∣dinall
should enter first into the boate, as also because he
had brought the buls to free them to passe over the river,
without going into Purgatorie; and so all of them past o∣ver
with this decree, that those who thereafter should come
from the siege of <HI>Montauban,</HI> should enioy the like pri∣viledge.</P>
<P>When they were set on shore on the banks of the <HI>Elizian</HI>
fields, <HI>Zamet</HI> recived and saluted them, with both his arms
about their middles, jesting and sporting with them, and
assuring them that King <HI>Henrie</HI> the great would be ex∣ceeding
glad to see them, because of the desire he had to
vnderstand the state of the affaires of <HI>France.</HI></P>
<P>The impatience that troubled the spirit of that good
Prince, had moved him to walke with the greatest part of
his old servitors to the side of the riuer, to meete with <HI>Za∣met</HI>
the late Baron <HI>de la Guiche,</HI> because he was very tall,
was he that first afarre off discouered that French troupe,
and said to the King S. <HI>Fiacre:</HI> Sir, I thinke these are the
men of <HI>Montauban</HI> before vs, they are a great number, I
wonder how so many brave men have suffred themselves
to be made nestle-birds; you will say, that it is a great ar∣mie,
and I marvell that your Majestie doth not see the
foule dust which they cause to rise up into the aire with
their feete. I perceive it well, said the King, let us stay
here for them; in the meane time take your prospective
glasse (as the Constable did at <HI>Piquerox</HI>) the better to
know them afarre off.</P>
<P>And as the King walked somewhat aside, the Marshall
<HI>d' Aumont</HI> said: Sir, we shall speedily heare some newes,
for I see a carrabin among the mirtle trees, that runs as
fast as he can, to get before his fellowes; he seemes to be
some harbinger or quarter master, that seekes to come to
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
the campe before the rest, that he may take vp the best
lodging: but coming nearer, they knew him to be a Ie∣suite,
that was sent in great haste by his Generall, to per∣swade
the King, not to beleeue all that should be told him
touching the lamentable state whereinto the affaires of
<HI>France</HI> are now reduced: and he was no sooner come to
the King, but on the other side <HI>Hautefontaine</HI> suddenly was
at his heeles, who had slipt out of the company, that he
might excuse himselfe touching the miserable disorder
hapned in <HI>S. Iohn d' Angely.</HI> And as soone as he spied the
Iesuite, he suddenly cried out, and said: What doth this
Iannisarie here? doth it not suffice his Societie to haue
supported the authors of the diuision between the mother
and the sonne, but must he come hither also, to trouble
and disturbe the peace of the blessed? What noise is that
which I heare, said the King? <HI>Varenne</HI> made answer: It
is <HI>Hautefontaine</HI> that quarrels with this good father which
even now came to your Majestie. <HI>Hautefontaine,</HI> said the
King, bid him come hither that I may speake with him.
Who coming to the King-presence, he asked him, who
had sent him into these quarters? By the Lord, Sir, (ex∣cuse
me, said he, if I do not sweare as the Huguenots do,
for I am angrie) I am not come hither for mine owne
pleasure, it is true that I make no account of my life, but
I am halfe mad to see this Spanish Iannisarie presume to
speake unto you, after they have dealt with you as they
have done, and Catholikly set fire in the foure quarters
of your sonnes Realme. Why do you call them Ianni∣saries,
said the King? Do not you know, said <HI>Hautefon∣taine,</HI>
y<SUP>t</SUP> the Turks Ianisaries haue neither father nor native
country, acknowledging no Lord but the great Turke:
so the Iesuites neither respect their country nor their pa∣rents,
but onely bend their mindes and all their studies to
accomplish the will and desire of <HI>Yo el Rey,</HI> their Sove∣raigne
Lord; and the better to effect his will and pleasure
they haue troubled all Christendome, and are the cause
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
of the death of all these brave Knights which are now
coming hither to your Majestie.</P>
<P>The King looking backe saw all those that had past
over the river, who all together began to kneele downe.
Are these moale-catchers or takers of <HI>Montauban,</HI> said the
late Admiral <HI>d' Anvile?</HI> The King therwith sharply repro∣ved
him, saying, Hold you your peace, this is no spectacle
to be laught at; and therewith his heart was so much grie∣ved,
that he could hardly speake, yet he refrained not to
entertain them friendly; and then particularly embracing
the Cardinall <HI>de Guise,</HI> the Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> and the rest
of the Lords, he prayed them to go and rest themselves;
and hauing eased their bodies awhile, he would conferre
with them at leisure; and therewith he commanded <HI>Za∣met</HI>
to entertain them wel, and so drew himself aside with
his most confident friends untill the next day. While the
King spake unto them, <HI>Hautefontaine</HI> stood talking with
<HI>Beringhen</HI> touching the motives of the secret mysteries of
<HI>Bearn,</HI> and entred into so profound a discourse with him,
that they past over a great part of the night therein. At last
the King desiring to take some rest, asked for <HI>Beringhen;</HI>
and answer being made, That he was without, walking
with <HI>Hautefontaine.</HI> He commanded that they should
both come to him. And turning to <HI>Hautefonte,</HI> he asked
him, what occasions had moved them to rebell against the
King his sonne? saying hide nothing from me, but speake
boldly like a true Huguenot. Sir said he, if I should die
once againe by a musket shot at me from the wall by a
false brother of the companie, I will tell you our affaires
truly how they past, and wil not lie in any point. It is long
time since we perceived that the Spaniard doubting the
end of the truce betweene him and the Hollanders, and
that for the good of his affairs he sought to trouble <HI>France</HI>
by some civill warre, finding no better meanes then to
make us wrangle among our selves with blowes of <HI>Pater
nosters</HI> and <HI>Clement Marots</HI> Psalms, his device from y<SUP>t</SUP> time
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
effected what it could; and to give us matter and subject
to enter into the field, many things which your Majestie
had formerly granted unto us by your Edicts, were de∣nied
us. The affaires of <HI>Bearn</HI> were brought in question,
as a countrey neare bordering upon <HI>Spaine;</HI> his principall
agents there dispersed a certaine quantitie of Medales, for
marks of Catholikes, on the backe side having <HI>Iulius se∣cundus.</HI></P>
<P>The Marquis <HI>d' Ancre</HI> was no sooner slaine, but <HI>du Vair</HI>
Keeper of the Seales, author of the assembly of speciall
persons, holden in <HI>Roane</HI> in the beginning of <HI>an.</HI> 1618.
caused that notable decree of the privie Councell for the
restoring of the temporall goods and lands unto the spi∣rituall
persons in <HI>Bearn</HI> to be pronounced; but the great
difficulties touching this restitution, caused the execution
thereof to be delayed. The <HI>Spaniard,</HI> that stil sought to set
fire on <HI>France,</HI> caused the Bishop to trot up and downe
<HI>Paris,</HI> to have an end and order of their suite. Thereupon
our Ministers made a generall assembly in <HI>Loudun,</HI> in the
meane time we were undermined by all the malcontents
in the Realme, but yet they could not win us in any sort
to estrange our selves from the fidelitie which we owe
unto our King. <HI>Luynes</HI> and his brethren fearing lest we
should make a scape, promised us in the Kings name, that
within six moneths the speciall points of our complaints
should be answered, and that in the meane time nothing
should be innovated in the country of <HI>Bearn.</HI> Vpon this
assurāce we brake up our assembly, with promise by word
of mouth that we should have leave to reassemble if that
were not performed within the said time which was pro∣mised
unto us. But that word was not held with us, but
on the contrary we were mockt; and without staying till
the six moneths were expired, your old servant <HI>de la Salle</HI>
was driven out of <HI>Navarrens</HI> and at the same <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>me the Ie∣suites
were established in <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1+ words" DISP="〈◊…〉"/></HI> hereupon w<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> presented
our most humble supplications to the King your sonne,
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>
and in stead of an answer thereunto, we had a flat deniall.
Whereupon wee assembled the Deputies to renew our
complaint, but without giuing them audience, we were
proclaimed Traitors. Then we saw all the Transmontaine
faction to arise; and the better to disguise the action, in
stead of speaking openly against the heretickes, because
that would have savoured too much of the old league, it
was reported in all places that we were not good common
wealths men, and that we had called the virgin <HI>Marie, la
Guimbard,</HI> thereby to move all the Catholicks vnder that
pretence to seeke revenge against all those that aided you
against the leaguers. And in truth, Sir, your Majestie may
well note and perceive, and so may all good Frenchmen
likewise, that they have assailed and spoiled none but those
Townes which in time past served your Majestie for a re∣traict
in the time of your greatest troubles, witnes <HI>S. Iohn,
Nerac, Clerac,</HI> and the Towne <HI>Burbon de Montauban,</HI>
which beares the name of your house, to shew how much
they that caused it to be built, were affected to your blood.
This in few words, Sir, is the history of <HI>France</HI> and <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
<P>I haue heard you well, said the King, but who thrust
<HI>Luynes</HI> forward to destroy that which I haue made? A
designe to make himselfe great by our ruines, and the
decay of your state, said <HI>Hautefontaine.</HI> There is a great
apparence thereof, said the King; call <HI>Vair</HI> unto me, said
he, let me heare his reasons; <HI>Beaulide-ruze</HI> go you and
seeke him out. That's to no end, said the Marshall <HI>d' Or∣nano,</HI>
for I haue heard that he is out of his wits for griefe
that he had to have bin so unfortunate, that he could not
be at the funerall of the Chancellor <HI>de Sillery.</HI> Let that
Stoick school-master to <HI>Veron</HI> alone, you have all these
Lords and Gentlemen here, Sir, who will truly and plainly
tell you the truth of the desolations of France, to morrow
in the morning, saluting your Grace, they will let you
know more, then you would know. You say true, said
the King. The next day the Marquis <HI>de Termes</HI> was the
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>
first that shewed himselfe when the King came out of his
chamber, who with a smiling countenance bad him wel∣come,
and then asked him for <HI>Monsieur le Grand,</HI> and
what Lords and gentlemen had past over the river with
the Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> as also how many men were slaine
in those brave enterprises made by the bucklers of France.</P>
<P>Sir, said the Marquis, my brother hath alwayes bin a
most humble servant to your Majestie, and so he is still
unto the King your sonne, and to all the blood Royall▪
<HI>Luynes</HI> hath put him backe from deling with the affaires
of the State, and therefore he meddles not therewith.
Touching those that came with the Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI>
they are 400 gentlemen of good qualitie, and about
2000 souldiers.</P>
<P>Shew me particularly the originall of so many mis∣chiefes?
Sir, said he, the pride of three Falconers, whom
you placed about your sonne upon the recommendation
of <HI>Varenne,</HI> who stands there behind you, are and will be
the cause of the dissipation of your Crowne, they haue
won the King your sonnes fauour, they do not tell him
of the affaires of his Realmes, but cleane contrary, and as
they would have him know it; they have cleane altered the
whole Court; the Court is filled with their brethren, bro∣thers
and sisters in law, nephewes, nieces, cousins and al∣lies,
and all sorts of rascals, having driven out all your old
servitors, and those of the Queene mother, it being most
true, that no man (what, or whosoeuer) can haue accesse
to his Maiestie, but onely by their meanes; they keepe the
Prince brother to the King your sonne, as their servant;
they haue laid hold upon the forces of the State, drawne
the treasures thereof cleane drie, and in a word they go∣verne
all. What, said the King, doe not the Councell
speake against those disorders? In truth, Sir, said <HI>de Ter∣mes,</HI>
they have changed both the Councel and the Coun∣sellors.
Doth my wife endure that? why doth she not
oppose her selfe against it? said the King. Oppose against
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
it, said the Marquis; if she should but once opē her mouth
to speake against it, they would presently clap her up in
hold, like the Descomans. You iest, said the King; if I
were she, I would let them know that I am the Queene∣mother.
Alas, Sir, said the Marquis, if you knew how
they have used her within these foure yeares and a halfe,
there is no slave but wold rather enjoy his condition then
hers; they have driven her shamefully out of <HI>Paris,</HI> they
limited her two yeares together to stay in the castle of
<HI>Blois,</HI> they pursued her by force of armes, they haue made
her follow their armie like a Lanceknights wife; to con∣clude,
they haue in such maner made her subiect to their
dominion, that she dares not once complain of the rigor
which they vse against her. Doth the King my sonne
know that? said the King. No, Sir, said the Marquis, they
are warie enough to let him know it; on the contrary, they
seeke all the meanes they can to divert from her all the
good affection that the King beares unto her, still whis∣pering
him in the eare, that she hates him, that she seekes
to make his brother King, that she is an Italian, and other
diabolicall inventions to feare him, without once putting
him in minde that she is his mother, or what love she doth
beare unto him in that respect. Those are three villanies,
said the King, I would that <HI>Rapin</HI> had them under his
hands in the place of execution: but I wonder why the
Pope doth not take on him to stop the courses of such so∣wers
of diuision betweene the mother and the sonne; it
would be a great good for Christendome, and an honour
unto him. It is hard, said the Marquis, to make an answer
thereunto, Sir; yet I wil shew you what I have heard from
father <HI>Raude</HI> a Charterux Monke, a great friend to our
house, your Maiestie shall understand, if it please you, that
at such time as those three brethren usurped upon the au∣thoritie
Royall, they also ioyned with the body of the So∣cietie
of the name of Iesus for two causes, and the Iesuites
for two causes entred into league with them. <HI>Luynes</HI> useth
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>
their helpe, to get in the mony belonging to the Marquis
<HI>d' Ancre,</HI> which was in the Mount <HI>de Prete</HI> in <HI>Rome,</HI> and in
requitall thereof he promised to reestablish them in their
colledge in <HI>Paris,</HI> in despight of the Court of Parliament,
as he hath done; and further he hath sent the Marquis <HI>de
Quemere</HI> Ambassadour to <HI>Rome,</HI> in the Kings name, to so∣licite
their reestablishment in <HI>Venice.</HI> The Iesuites in re∣compence
promised him, that they would aide him in all
things and in every place, and that they would in such sort
obtaine his Holinesse good will towards them, that hee
should be favourable unto them during their usurpation;
and that neither the Pope nor they would exclame in any
sort against the bad dealing which they should offer un∣to
the Queene mother: and it is certaine that his Holi∣nesse
never wrote any thing thereof, neither makes any
complant against the insolencies of those Favorites. On
the contrary, the Nuncius <HI>Bentivole</HI> resident in <HI>Paris,</HI> is
wholy for <HI>Luynes,</HI> who hath made him Cardinall, and
Comprotector of the French nation in <HI>Rome,</HI> to the preju∣dice
of the Prince Cardinall of <HI>Savoy,</HI> to whom the King
had given that protection. Thus <HI>Luynes</HI> is upholden on
that side. And to the end that the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> should
not be offended to see the Queene his sister governed by
<HI>Luynes</HI> and his wife, he hath consented to let him lay
hold upon the <HI>Grisons,</HI> the <HI>Palatinate</HI> and <HI>Iuliers,</HI> which is
under the protection of <HI>France,</HI> and which the Queene
mother following your designe, hath kept out of the Spa∣niards
clawes; whereas on the contrary, that villaine suffers
so important a country bordering upon the Realme, to be
lost. He hath alienated 120000 crowns yearely rent of the
Church, whereof he hath imbursed 200000 crownes for
his part: of your sonnes revenues, he and his brethren
possesse at the least 500000 franks yearely rent, without
disbursing one penie for it.</P>
<P>How this discourse grieves me, said the King, I would
you had neuer spoken to me thereof, let us leave for this
<PB N="19" REF="11"/>
time; here comes the Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> and a great num∣ber
of Noblemen to visit me. All these, said the Mar∣quis
<HI>de Termes,</HI> will confirme that which I have said un∣to
your Majestie, and you may know of them what hath
past since I left them at <HI>Clerac.</HI></P>
<P>The Duke <HI>de Mayenne</HI> coming neare with all his com∣panie,
made humble obeysance to the King; and his Ma∣jestie
bowing his head, welcomed them with teares in his
eyes: Cousin, said the King, and all you my faithfull ser∣vants,
it grieves me that you have bin deceived by three
villaines, who, as I heare, untill this time have abused the
favour and bountie of my sonne, and generally your free
spirits. The Duke speaking for them all, said, Sir, I
know not who hath made your Grace so wel acquainted
with the pride of those three Falconers, that have used all
the meanes they can, to put all men both great and meane
out of the King your sonnes favour by their devices, sold
all <HI>France</HI> by their covetousnes, and brought all the realm
into disorder by their monstrous ambition. All men know
how litle cause I have to speake wel of the Marquis <HI>d' An∣cre,</HI>
but I may well say, that he was an Angell in respect
of these three divels incarnate, enemies both to men and
all valour, and such as never employed them but to their
overthrow: all they that have past over the river with me,
know what they are; besides that for mine owne part I
have every way tried and proved their divellish malice
in that respect. It is true, that Marquis <HI>d' Ancre</HI> was wic∣ked
as wel as they, but yet he had some humanitie in him,
he did good to many, hee was a man of his word, if hee
crost some great persons, he made much of others: but
these three plagiaries have bin a scourge to them all,
thinking it a glory by their dissembling salutations to de∣ceive
all the world with brazen faces. I will not trouble
your Majestie with the rehearsall of their detestable acti∣ons,
nor put you in minde of the rude dealing that they
have shewed to the Queene your wife, neither how they
<PB N="20" REF="12"/>
have scorned my Lord the Prince, nor of their ingrati∣tude
against my Lady the Countesse, nor what trickes
they have played with all the Nobilitie: it suffiseth, Sir,
that you generally know their proud proceedings, they
have fully gotten the government of the King your son
and of the authoritie royall into their hands, making him
beleeve, that they three onely held the Crowne upon his
head, as if those of his blood had conspired the usurpation
thereof. For the space of foure yeares they have caused all
the affaires of importance to passe under their hands; they
have made the King march with them in all places for
their owne particular interest; vpon the frontiers of the
Realme <HI>Luynes</HI> hath bin so proud as to make his entrie in∣to
townes, accompanied with a Prince of the blood, and
in rhe presence of the King his Soveraigne; he sent his
brother <HI>Cadnet</HI> into Flanders, under pretence to go seeke
his wife, where he spake with Marquis <HI>Spinola;</HI> and after
that, with a most incomparable pride, covered with pre∣cious
stones appertaining to the Crowne, he hath bene in
England, not one of the Kings Councell knowing the se∣cret
of his embassage; after that voyage he undertooke to
make himselfe Duke of <HI>Britaigne;</HI> and it is not knowne
whether since he hath bin keeper of the Seales, hee hath
dispatched letters patents for the same. In favour of <HI>Ca∣stille</HI>
he hath neglected all ancient alliances of the Crown;
he hath suffered the <HI>Palatinate</HI> and the <HI>Grisons</HI> to be lost,
to make the <HI>Spaniard</HI> favourable to him. The Queene mo∣ther
preserved <HI>Iuliers,</HI> under the protection of the King
your sonnes forces, and those three villaines have suffered
it to be besieged by <HI>Spinola.</HI> To the disgrace of your glo∣rious
memorie, <HI>Branthe</HI> a meane fellow, that never had
200 franks yearely rent, hath bin so audacious as to ravish
the heire of <HI>Luxeburg,</HI> and to force that yong Princesse
being but eleuen yeares old, and at such a time when all
<HI>France</HI> was in armes by their meanes; and if the ravishing
of a maide be punishable, as it is, her action in all circum∣stances
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>
is much more punishable. <HI>Luynes</HI> hath exposed
the King and the Prince his brother into the inconveni∣ences
of a long voyage, and into the perils of the bad aire
in the armie, in such maner that the Prince was there sick
and like to die, and yet he would not suffer him to be car∣ried
out of the infections of the campe: he hath resolved
upon the warre against the Huguenots, without taking,
yea and against the advice of your old Councellers: hee
hath bin so audacious as to keepe the Kings seales in his
hands, to promise them to many, but gives them to no
man, busying himselfe during the dangers of the siege be∣fore
<HI>Montauban,</HI> with sealing expeditions, in stead of go∣ing
to the warre, for which cause the souldiers made
these foure verses of him:
<Q><L>What shall we of this valiant Warrier say,</L>
<L>That vseth vs like slaves both night and day?</L>
<L>He that in peace the Constables office hie,</L>
<L>And in warre doth the Chancellers place supplie.</L></Q>
In such maner, that if there be any capitall crime that may
be objected against a bad servant, that is one of the most
notorious and greatest. All the mony appointed for pay∣ing
of the souldiers in the armie, he stayed in <HI>Blayes,</HI> in
such sort, that more souldiers have died of want and ne∣cessitie,
then of wounds, for want of reliefe. To be short,
their covetousnes and villanies are the cause of all the bad
successe hapned as wel during that siege as in other pub∣licke
affaires. That which I finde to be most strange,
said <HI>Balagny,</HI> is, that not one of them hath bin hurt in a∣ny
of the exploits of their conquests. I will shew you
a pertinent reason for that, said the Duke, it is because
they neuer sought after blowes, and blowes never met
with them; and that is it which <HI>Luynes</HI> Surgeon wrote to
his wife, that was in doubt lest her husband was slaine in
the armie: Wife, take no care for me, but be quiet, &amp; feare
nothing, for I incurre no danger, my Lord Constable
doth me that honour to affect me much, and to keep still
<PB N="22" REF="13"/>
neare unto his person. Thus you see how those gallants
are miraculously preserved and kept out of the danger of
blowes, while they cause others to lose their lives.</P>
<P>Our posteritie, said the King, will hardly beleeue, that
men of no degree, and voide of all valour, should in so
short a time lay hold upon the government of <HI>France.</HI>
Sir, said <HI>Pluninel,</HI> I did neuer so easily with bit and bridle
manage your Graces great horses in the stable, (without
comparison) as I have seene them manage all the Prin∣ces
of your Realme.</P>
<P>What, said the Marshall <HI>de Brisac,</HI> was not <HI>Cadnet</HI> so
bold as to threaten the Prince, that he should not go out
of <HI>Bois de Vincennes,</HI> if he did not consent to give him
the Princesse of <HI>Orange</HI> to be his wife, who died for griefe
thereof? You iest, said the King. He hath done more
then that, said he, for he was so presumptuous as to presse
the Earle <HI>de Soyssons</HI> to give over the office of high Stew∣ard
unto him. The late Earle taking the word out of
his mouth, said, If my sonne had bin wise, he should have
caused him to be well beaten for his impudencie. You
haue reason, said old <HI>Courtenay,</HI> if he had <HI>Rambure,</HI> or
such another Knight as he for his governer, but he hath
a blocke to be his schoole-master, that knowes not what
belongs to honour and courage; and therefore those com∣panions
know with whom they have to do.</P>
<P>Let us enter into some other discourse, said the King;
as I remember, one of you told me, that during all these
businesses, <HI>Luynes</HI> and his brethren carried their wives
with them unto the warre, and that they were with them
during the important siege of <HI>Montauban;</HI> if it were so, it
is very likely that their intent was no other but onely to
make their battery under curtains. At that word M. <HI>Wil∣liam</HI>
gave a nod, and said to the King, Indeed my Lord,
you have often bin told, that they play the Kings, and that
I acknowledge, they have heretofore sitting by the fire
heard how you in times past rid upon the League, and
<PB N="23" REF="13"/>
those gallants would imitate you, and thinke by riding
their wives, to ride upon the Huguenots: but those wic∣ked
heretickes have knavishly ridden upon them before
<HI>Montauban.</HI> Whereat all of them began to laugh. But
the King enquired of the miracle of the Spie, and much
desired to know it, and speaking thereof, askt, why, after
he had escaped in such maner, he was not sent into the
Towne, to convert the inhabitants. Faith of a gentle∣man,
said <HI>de Loppe,</HI> that had bin no safetie for him, for so
the people might have hangd him up in good earnest.
God is strong every where, said the King, and can defend
those that are his, at all times and in all places: but tell me
who sent father <HI>Dominicke de Iesus Maria</HI> into France?
what maner of man is he? And it please your Majestie,
said the Earle <HI>de Fiefque,</HI> he is a holy man, I yet have a
portatise cloake that he gave me; your Majestie will not
beleeve what honour the Parisians did unto him, and yet
know not wherefore; every woman cut off a peece of his
gowne; and he came thither onely to shew us that all the
Spaniards are not Saracins, and that there are some holy
men among them. If I had bin of the Kings Councell,
said the Abbot <HI>du Bois,</HI> I would in counter-change have
sent father <HI>Berule</HI> to <HI>Madril,</HI> I am sure that the women
of <HI>Castile</HI> would also have cut his fustian. That were
good, said the Marshall <HI>de Fervaques,</HI> if French cloth
were as fine as Spanish cloth; but if I were of the Coun∣cell,
as the Cardinall <HI>de Rets</HI> is, and as forward as the Earle
<HI>de Chomberg,</HI> (who is capable to redresse all <HI>Luynes</HI> faults,
so that he doth not joyne with forreine faction) I would
make the Spaniard know, that he is not a better Catholik
then I my selfe am, and would keepe him from having
secret intelligences with our Favorites, to the great de∣triment
of the Kings service and the Realme, which goes
to decay, if remedy be not speedily had therein.</P>
<P>I confesse, said the King, that since I have heard of all
the bad and perfidious practises which that gallant and his
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>
brethren have done and performed, my son never know∣ing
thereof, my spirit hath bin in continuall perplexitie,
fearing lest they should destroy their good maister and
great benefactor. Sir, said the Marquis <HI>de Villars,</HI> the
earth never bare more traiterous and ambitious villaines
then they are; they have bin so bold the last yeare to
cause a Maske to be made in <HI>Burbon</HI> hall, wherein they
presented divers mysticall figures, and among the rest, a
great Lady and divers Giants chained, whom <HI>Luynes</HI> ap∣parelled
like <HI>Phebus,</HI> drew after him, whereof the greatest
resembled the Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> upon whose head <HI>Luy∣nes</HI>
set his foote, for a signe of servitude. Truly, said the
Baron <HI>de Plancy,</HI> he made another more impudent in the
Castle of <HI>Piquerox,</HI> for there perceiving the King to be
grieved for the losse he had received by the death of the
Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> he devised a litle Comedie to make his
Majestie merrie, wherein hee presented a great <HI>Moore</HI>
making divers strange jestures; and for that he resembled
the Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> the King commanded them to leave
and act no more. Why? said <HI>Luynes.</HI> Because, said the
King, that this man in all respects resembles the Duke <HI>de
Mayenne;</HI> I cannot endure to see it. Truly Sir, said he,
his death needs not minister cause of sadnesse to your
Majestie, for he was a turbulent fellow, that troubled all
your affaires; you were no King as long as he lived; we
haue discovered and found out that he made a third par∣tie,
and since his death we have found all his practises.</P>
<P>Thus this villaine alwayes sought to divert all the good
opinion that his Majestie had of his servants, and of all
those of his blood. He did another matter, said the Se∣cretarie
of State for the Seales, he was so impudent as to
write vnto the Pope, that the Queen mother was the cause
that <HI>Montauban</HI> was not taken, thereby thinking to cover
his owne cowardlinesse; from whence it may be con∣jectured
how many false reports he hath made to the king
your sonne, seeing he was so bold to send such a message
<PB N="25" REF="14"/>
to his Holinesse. You shall never have done Sir, said the
Earle <HI>de Lude,</HI> if you will hearken unto all their arrogant
actions, who knowes them better then my selfe that
brought them up? as long as any of that race are neare a∣bout
the King your sonne, they will spoile all, there being
no kind of wickednes whereof they are not capable: and
aboue all things beleeve it, Sir, my Lord the Prince may
well offer a great candle unto God when he shall escape
out of their hands; your Majestie must foresee these
things.</P>
<P>As the King was discoursing with the Lords touching
the sorrowfull state of the affaires of <HI>France,</HI> and about the
meanes to remedie the same, all the assistants partaking
with the griefe of that good Prince, on a sudden <HI>Mon∣sieur
de Vury</HI> breaking through the prease came to his Ma∣jestie,
and to comfort him, said, <HI>Corbien</HI> Sir, you have
sufficiently lamented the miseries of the time, I must now
make you merry a while, by telling you that which I pre∣sently
saw: as I was hawking after a partridge along by
the river side, by chance I came to as merrie a combat as
ever was acted upon the Theater <HI>de Tabarim</HI> in the place
<HI>Dauphine.</HI> Betweene whom said the King. Your Ma∣jestie
must know, said <HI>Vitry,</HI> that Marshall <HI>d' Ancre</HI> walk∣ing
along by the river side with <HI>Dole,</HI> when <HI>Charon</HI> set on
shore the new Constable of France, with his sword of say.</P>
<P>What, said the King, is he here? <HI>Corbien</HI> said he, he is
there, I assure your Grace, I haue seene him, and when I
saw him, I laught for ioy, he hath the countenance of as
notable a rascall as ever I saw. But before I proceed fur∣ther,
I must tell you of the pleasant salutation of these
two combattants: Marshall <HI>d' Ancre</HI> walking as I said be∣fore,
stood still to contemplate the proud gestvre of that
new come guest, and beholding his face, he knew it was
<HI>Luynes;</HI> wherewith suddenly the blood rose in his face,
and he said to <HI>Dole,</HI> Behold the traitor that caused me to
be kild, I will now kill him; and without speaking any
<PB N="26" REF="15"/>
more words, casting his cloake over his face, went to meet
with him; and as soone as he got to him, he gave him a
great bob on the nose, saying, Traitor, now Ile make thee
pay for thy villanie. The Constable abasht thereat, said,
You are deceived, you mistake me for another, I under∣stand
no Italian. <HI>Pardieus,</HI> I undestand French well. Lay
hand on thy sword, said the Marquis. Are not single
combats forbidden here, said the Constable? Villaine,
said the Marquis, thou art afraid; and saying so, he fell
upon the Constable, and gave him divers great blowes
with the flat side of his sword, in such maner, that never
any curtall jade was so well beaten. The Archbishop of
<HI>Sens</HI> that stood hard by them, had a great desire to helpe
him, but he durst not go betweene them, still remembring
the blowes with spits which were given him in <HI>Tours</HI> by
the Marquis <HI>de Noirmontiers</HI> cookes, when he was Solici∣ter
of his house; and so for want of aide, the villanous
Constable was as well beaten as ever was <HI>Dieret Chiury,</HI>
when he imagined that the blowes with a cudgell which
were given him, were pistols shot: for Marquis <HI>d' Ancre</HI>
still laid on like <HI>Rovillac,</HI> and <HI>Luynes</HI> cried out as loud as
he could, like <HI>Ronsselay.</HI> at S. <HI>Germains</HI> Fayre: which was
the cause that <HI>Radamanthus</HI> Lackeys ran thither, and laid
hold upon those two champions, intending to carry them
before the ludge to be punished for their insolencies.</P>
<P>Marquis <HI>d' Ancre</HI> alledged that he was not the man that
first brake the peace, and spake them so faire, that they let
him go; in the meane time <HI>du Travail</HI> came thither, who
fiercely laid hold on the Constables coller, in such maner
that I thought he would have strangled him; but when he
had set his foote vpon his belly, and taken his sword from
him, he ran away, leaving him there in a maner halfe dead,
saying nothing to him, but onely, Remember thy selfe
Provinciall. I that tooke pitie to see that <HI>Rodomond</HI> fa∣vorite
so hardly used, found the meanes, that without ta∣king
the advice of <HI>de Modenne</HI> or <HI>de Contade,</HI> I puld him
<PB N="27" REF="15"/>
slily out of their clawes, and brought the gallant hither
to make your Maiestie some sport. Truly, said the King,
you have done me good service, let him come in, that we
may see that great Warrier and great Statesman all in one.
Whereupon Colonell <HI>Galatis</HI> with a <HI>das tich</HI> Gods sacra∣ment,
caused the prease to open, and therewith <HI>Vitry</HI>
brought him in, every man as well as he could fixing
their eyes upon him to behold his physiognomie. The
Poet <HI>Desportes</HI> at his entring, giving him a welcome ac∣cording
to his Art, and speaking aloud, said:
<Q><L>Give place, give place to this companion,</L>
<L>Who while he liv'd was like a great Monarchus:</L>
<L>But being borne in Champianion,</L>
<L>In Poiteiou he was cut off by Parcus.</L></Q>
Being in the middle of the companie, all of them began
to crie, saying, The fox, the fox, wherewith you never saw
villaine more ashamed; and after silence was made, the
King askt him, who he was, I am, said he, the Constable
of France, your most humble subiect and servant. Con∣stable?
said the King; by what title got you that office? it
is not aboue foure yeares since you were but a Falconer,
and in so short a time have you attained to so high a de∣gree?
you have made great haste. You must not muse
thereat, Sir, said <HI>Haeren,</HI> if hee had not put me out of
countenance, I had had as good fortune as he. Hold
your tongue, said the King. <HI>Parmafe,</HI> and it please your
Maiestie, said M. <HI>William,</HI> I could be well content to pay
his breech with a whip full of points to be revenged on
him for the pension that he tooke from me, to give it un∣to
<HI>de Mons</HI> his brother in law. Truly M. <HI>William,</HI> said
<HI>Saroque,</HI> you are misinformed to beleeve such things,
my Lord Constable was not so foolish to imagine that he
could make that small matter of <HI>Province</HI> greater then it
is, notwithstanding that he is the most valiant man of
them all, for he alone tooke <HI>Montauban,</HI> or else they of
<HI>Montauban</HI> tooke him. What extravagant words are
<PB N="26" REF="16"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="27" REF="16"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="28" REF="17"/>
these, said the King? give us leave quietly to hearken un∣to
the mysticall discourse of this new conquerour.
Sir, said the Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> he will but abuse you with
words, he is a perfect lyer, command him to go directly
to the matter, otherwise I cannot abstain from giving him
a blow on the lips at the first lie he makes. With that
the King turning to the champion, said briefly unto him,
Heare you my Lord Constable made in haste, abuse not
my leisure, tell me all your notable proceedings, without
dissimulation, if you desire to finde mercie at my hands
for your misdeeds: all these gentlemen know your acti∣ons,
and the Earle <HI>de Lude</HI> that stands here, is wholy ac∣quainted
with your life, go directly to worke, otherwise
you shall finde <HI>Lugoly</HI> ready to give you your hire.</P>
<P>Sir, said <HI>Luynes,</HI> now I perceive well that I am undone,
<HI>In manus tuas commendo spiritum meum,</HI> my processe is
made, and further all these noble gentlemen that are here,
will never pardon me, for that as many Lords as are here
about your Majesty, are as many witnesses to convince me
of all the perfidious actions that I have committed both
against the one and the other, and the worst is, that I
haue not the authoritie Royall to cover my faults any
more, nor to support my insolencies; I must needs con∣fesse,
that I haue offended God, the King my master, and
all men, and that there is no punishment great enough
to recompence my deserts: but I will gladly say with <HI>Cae∣sar,
Si violandum est ius, regnandi causa;</HI> all that I haue
done, was not effected by any wicked inclination that
was in me, but onely by a generous ambition to raigne. I
knew how easily Marquis <HI>d' Ancre</HI> obtained the govern∣ment
of the State, I beleeved and was verily perswaded,
that in that point I could doe more then a stranger, that
onely had a woman to support him, and that I possessing
the Kings heart, was the more able to dispossesse all men,
and to possesse all things: for my designe was to sur∣mount
that Italian; and if any of my good friends sought
<PB N="29" REF="17"/>
to divert me from that generous enterprise, presently <HI>du
Agent, Contade</HI> and <HI>Ronsselay,</HI> cried out in mine eares, say∣ing,
What are you afraid of? If Marquis <HI>d' Ancre</HI> could
make the Frenchmen cullions, why should not you be∣ing
a great Falconer take them for birds? <HI>Audaces fortuna
invat,</HI> said my father in law; we must draw water when
we are at the well side, said my wife; we are of the same
kind of wood whereof men make Princes, said my bre∣thren;
and I said Modene, of the same that the Marshals of
<HI>France</HI> are made. All these motions encouraged me, and
in truth my first bringing up to fowling taught me so
well to flie, that in foure yeares space I surpast all those
that medled with the affaires of State before me.</P>
<P>I caused Marquis <HI>d' Ancre</HI> to be kild, to haue his place;
I vrged the Parliament to put his wife to death, that I
might haue his goods. I kept the Queene mother as much
as I could from the presence and favour of the King her
sonne, that I might onely enioy it. I kept the Prince of
<HI>Conde</HI> prisoner, and let him not come forth, but then
when I thought he could no more hurt me, and that he
might serve my turne. I vsed charmes to trouble the spi∣rit
of the King and of the Queene, employing <HI>Boisgandrie</HI>
to that effect, whom I caused to be committed prisoner
in the Bastile, because he would have disclosed me. I set
division among the Princes, and estranged them all from
the Kings favour. I abused all those that had any thing
to do with me, with promises and faire words. All places
that were voide, I got into my hands. With the Kings
mony I bought all the governments that I could get;
and constrained some to yeeld theirs unto me. I had whole
Provinces under my obedience; there is no part of the
Realme, but therein I have townes. I have drawne <HI>France</HI>
drie of mony. The greatest part of the Kings domaines is
mine, or my brethrens. I did absolutely dispose of the sale
of offices; and as I disanulled the annuall right, I also e∣stablished
it. I made all mine enemies stoupe, and as much
<PB N="30" REF="18"/>
as I could, I made all the world know what power I had
over the genius of the King, that men might addresse
themselves vnto me, and be perswaded that the King
could do nothing without me. This, Sir, is that whereof
I may be accused: but he that will consider of that which
resteth, without passion, he shall finde that these are not
actions of a dull spirit, but of a brave courage, which ra∣ther
deserve commendation then blame, and for the
which I was never reproved by my Confessor.</P>
<P>Marquis <HI>d' Ancre</HI> could never equalize himselfe with me
in this respect; his designes were base in regard of mine;
he could not attaine to any degree, but onely to be Mar∣shall
of France, and I for my part made at least twelve
Marshals. He could neither make himselfe Knight of the
Order of the holy Ghost, nor Duke; and all you my Lords
that are here know well, that I gaue that Order to whom
I would, and that I made more Dukes then there are
sparrow-hawkes in the Kings Mewes, and so many, that
the Parliament of <HI>Paris</HI> was forced to say, it was too
much. But those foure cornerd caps know not, that my
intent was to extirpe the heretickes; and that for so dan∣gerous
a warre I had need of many Dukes, Marshals and
Knights, to honour the Constables sword which I reser∣ved
for my selfe, by the Iesuites counsel, and his Holinesse
himselfe, who assured me by his Nuncius, that if I under∣tooke
that Catholicke designe, that heauen would reserve
the diademe and the purple for me, as in effect I wanted
not the latter; and if I had not bin constrained to leaue
the siege before that cursed towne of <HI>Montauban,</HI> the ac∣complishment
of destinie had given me the Scepter.</P>
<P>I doubt not, Sir, but you haue bin entertained with a
thousand iests touching the impertinent proceedings of
my militarie exploits, and specially upon the subiect of
my approches made before <HI>ville Burbon.</HI> I take not upon
me to defend my selfe against bad speeches, it sufficeth
me that my actions seemed to be heroicall, and my de∣signes
<PB N="31" REF="18"/>
haughtie. Further, I care li<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="2+ letters" DISP="••…"/>e what the world can
say, and that is it which I wrote for an answer to a let∣ter
sent us by our most deare vncle the Duke <HI>de Modene</HI>
in <HI>France,</HI> touching the slanders that were published in
<HI>Toulouse</HI> against me and my qualitie; I could easily haue
restrained and punished the libertie of such tongues, but
like an old Courtier, I use not to be afraid of reports, as
I made it well appeare in the strongest assaults of the siege
before that filthy towne, where I refrained not from slee∣ping
sweetly in my bed, notwithstanding the roaring of
the cannons, upon the assurance that I had that they
could not hurt me. Did not the souldiers call my quar∣ter,
the place of villanie? but for all that I never made lesse
cheare. They also mockt my wife as often as she came to
visit me in the campe, in mockery saying, that she went
oftener to combat with me, then I did with the enemie:
but such reproches moved me not, seeing that my wife
and I had no other intent but to do well, as we alwayes
did well, thankes be to God; and beleeue me, Sir, that
those malicious evill speakers spake but of envie, as grie∣ved
to see us take our pleasures, while they were at blowes,
and by the eares together in the trenches like rascals, suf∣fering
themselves to be beaten, which made them vomit
out their rage, not onely against me, but also against my
brethren and their wives, who like true <HI>Amazons</HI> never
fainted in all the combats wherein they happened to be,
encouraged thereunto by the wise discourses of <HI>Madame
de Guimbarde</HI> and of my sister <HI>du Vernet</HI> the true mirrour
of chastitie, of whom I learned never to be angry for that
which men said, so I do well. This also that I shew you,
Sir, is not to give you cause to thinke that such things
grieved me not much, but onely to make my great pati∣ence,
my exceeding bountie, the force of my spirit, and
the gentlenesse of my courage apparent. Who but my
selfe (except the Duke <HI>de Vzes</HI>) would not haue sunke
under the burthen of the continual watchings and paines
<PB N="32" REF="19"/>
which I endured in the conduction of this warre? Like
another <HI>Atlas,</HI> I was forced to beare all the burthen of the
Realme vpon my shoulders, ordaine all, provide for all,
resolve upon all, and besides that was charged not onely
with the affaires of the Realme, but also with Gods cause,
which particularly was to be respected in that holy en∣terprise,
as father <HI>Arnoux</HI> assured me, and the holy Earle
of <HI>Fiasque</HI> that stands there, who oftentimes told me in
my eares, that it was revealed unto him when hee was a
Capucin, which was the cause that made him leave the ha∣bit,
once againe to employ his sword, and weare temporal
apparell, and for my particuler that was the cause that
made me imbarke my selfe therein, with so much more
zeale as I saw the successe to be easie, the conquest glori∣ous,
and the spoiles profitable for my glorie.</P>
<P>What better beginning could your Maiestie have wish∣ed,
then the first progresse of our victories? Blinde <HI>Morney</HI>
at our first arrivall did obedience unto us; we did rigo∣rously
punish the rebellion of those of <HI>S. Iohn;</HI> we powred
our curse upon <HI>Pons;</HI> we cast the arrowes of our anger
upon <HI>Clerac,</HI> where we had that good lucke to rid our
selves of that brave Marquis <HI>de Termes,</HI> upon which sub∣iect
father <HI>Arnoux</HI> and I wrote two comfortable letters
to <HI>Monsieur le Grand</HI> in most eloquent maner. In every
place they brought us the keyes of the townes. They of
<HI>Toulonze</HI> came in great haste to offer us their armes and
their lives, with a good summe of money, to move us in
all haste to besiege that execrable towne of <HI>Montauban,</HI>
which at my first arivall I thought to take with a lure, like
a hungrie sparrow-hawke; and I wil confidently tell your
Maiestie, that I had determined to have erected it in a Du∣chie
for my sonne, as to seale the letters patents my selfe,
with an addition of the Earledomes of <HI>Armagnac</HI> and <HI>Al∣bert;</HI>
that was the cause that I could not consent to the
ruine of the brave fortifications of that place, desiring to
make use of them for my selfe. And to minister some
<PB N="33" REF="19"/>
comfort to those of <HI>Toulouse</HI> for their mony which I had
sent to the Castle of <HI>Blaye,</HI> I and my brethren had devi∣sed
to take the Hugonet throne out of their feete, and to
place another Catholicke therein, which we had happily
done, if those of <HI>Montauban</HI> would have beleeved us, or
at least have suffered us to do as <HI>la Faydeau.</HI></P>
<P>To conclude, Sir, what have I not done to have an
honorable issue of that miserable siege, all the inventions
in the world were there put in practise. What have I not
promised to the third and fourth? What can men reproch
me of, but onely that I was not at the trenches? Alas, it
was my onely desire not to stirre; but these gentlemen
here present know, that it ws impossible for me, in respect
of the continuall employments that I had about the
Seales. I trusted touching the warre, to the generositie of
this valiant Duke <HI>de Mayenne,</HI> whom we have thereby
caused to see the ioyes of Paradise, and in recompence
thereof he hath made us heires of that hee left in the
camp.</P>
<P>It is true, that to lure the world like a hawke, we caused
the government of <HI>Guyenne</HI> to fall into the Prince the
Kings brothers hands, but I would never seale his letters
patents for the same, that he might still be like Lent, and
my brother <HI>Branthe</HI> like Shrovetide, that is, Lent taking
her beginning. Thus we made our profit a thousand ways,
by the hurt and disgrace of others. If we had a care of our
owne lives, we had no lesse of the soldiers; having sought
as much as possibly we might, all gentle meanes and pra∣ctises
to overcome those rebels, before we would proceed
unto extremities.</P>
<P>Did not I with great care and diligence cause father
<HI>Dominicke de Iesus Maria</HI> to come into the armie, belee∣ving
that his holy prayers would make the taking of that
place the more easie, and that he would make a second
<HI>S. Bartholmewes</HI> day of the Huguenots in <HI>Paris.</HI> And if he
hath thought much to doe as much for <HI>France</HI> before
<PB N="34" REF="20"/>
<HI>Montauban,</HI> as he did for <HI>Spaine</HI> before <HI>Prague,</HI> I could
not do withall; I did the best I could to keep him there,
that his presence might animate the souldiers, and con∣vert
those headstrong heretickes, which father <HI>Arnoux</HI> a
true spirituall mirror did not well like of, alledging that it
was sufficient to have one <HI>Charlatan</HI> in the Court, in the
meane time all is laid upon me, although I am innocent
of the unfortunate successe of the siege.</P>
<P>What shall I say more, did I not invent a subtill stra∣tageme,
therewith to mollifie the hearts of those rebels,
that is the miraculous hanging of that villanous spie, that
brake the rope three times upon the gallowes? nevertheles
they within the towne, as also a great part of the armie,
would not beleeve that miracle, because he rather com∣mended
himselfe to our Lady of <HI>Monferrat</HI> in <HI>Spaine,</HI> then
to the good Lady <HI>de Liesse</HI> in <HI>France.</HI> Further, my brethren
and I made provision of a great number of invisible re∣giments,
but it was reported that we would put them in∣to
our owne purses, whereas our designe was to serve our
turnes with them, to cast them invisibly into the towne,
thereby to take it the easier. And if we failed therein, I am
no more the cause thereof, then of the raine and sicknesse
which continually troubled the soldiers, and which made
an end of setting us forth. No, Sir, I cannot warrant men
against the works of God, no more then I can from those
which are imputed unto me, by meanes of my ambition
and villanie; but if I had lived a litle longer, I would
haue made all the world see and perceiue that I intended
to be a souldier.</P>
<P>I confesse that I was but a new beginner in the Art,
when I made my selfe Constable, and that I had never
seene siege nor battell, but I was resolved this Winter to
learne the military Art with all perfection, in stead of pra∣ctising
to dance. The Baron <HI>de Caban,</HI> otherwise called <HI>de
Maine,</HI> having promised me in three moneths space to
make me as good a Captain as himself, who of a Musition
<PB N="35" REF="20"/>
in two yeares became a great warrier, whatsoever the
Marshall <HI>de Roquelauere</HI> said, who in despight that I em∣ployed
him in the siege of <HI>Monheur,</HI> sware, cap <HI>de Bions,</HI>
that he would not go to the warre with a Musition: and
being taught by so good a maister, this Spring time I wold
have paid those of <HI>Montauban,</HI> but God did prevent me
in all my designes.</P>
<P>Truly, said the King, your discourses are notable, but
your actions are not much worth, such men as you are
alwayes punished by the hand of God; get you away out
of my presence, and let me see you no more.</P>
<P>After that, the King taking the advice of his old ser∣vants,
ordained, that as <HI>Luynes</HI> had plaid with great per∣sonages
in his life time, he would haue him serve to make
them sport after his death, and therefore appointed him
to carrie fourmes every time that they ran at the Ring, or
with their Lances; and to begin his prentiseship, that he
should be delivered into the hands of the Duke <HI>de May∣ennes</HI>
pages.</P>
<P>According to this decree he was presently laid hold on,
who then speaking to the Cardinall <HI>de Guise,</HI> shewed him
that he died without confession and receiving of the Sa∣crament,
praying him to give him absolution for his sins.</P>
<P>To whom do you speake, said the Cardinall? do you not
know that I am no Priest? Then he turned to the Bi∣shop
of <HI>Marselles,</HI> to whom he made the like request.
And he made him the like answer that the Cardinall had
done, adding further &amp; saying, Before you went out of
the other world you should have caused your selfe to be
absolved by the Cardinall <HI>de Rets</HI> your creature, or rather
by the Bishop of <HI>Lusson</HI> your kinsman, hee would never
have denied you his blessing, notwithstanding that you
put him beside the Cardinals hat, so you had promised
him upon the securitie of <HI>Marillac</HI> and <HI>le Seq.</HI> to abstaine
from making pernicious reports unto the King, thereby
to alienate the good will which his Maiestie beareth to
<PB N="36" REF="21"/>
the Queene his mother; as for me, I cannot helpe you,
save your selfe as well as you can. With that the late
Marshall <HI>de Rets</HI> went to <HI>Luynes,</HI> and speaking unto him
in his eare, said, Alas poore foole, thou shouldst have
pluckt the goose without crying like me; if with humi∣litie
thou hast honored the great personages, they would
have upholden thee, and thou hadst enioyed thy fortunes
with securitie. Then turning his head here and there
about him, hee perceived the late Earle <HI>de Lude,</HI> which
three times he called his good maister, of whom hee as∣ked
pardon for the ducale perfidiousnes which he offered
unto him being in <HI>Touraine.</HI> Then he said to the Bishop
of <HI>Carcassone, Monsieur</HI> my good benefactor, if ever you
tooke pitie on the affliction of a miserable person, I con∣iure
you to take the paines to advertise my brethren to
take example by me, that they may governe themselves
more wisely then I have done, if they desire to escape the
shipwracke that I have endured, and before all things that
they suffer not my bodie to passe through <HI>Paris,</HI> lest it
should receive the same entertainment that the body of
the Marquis <HI>d' Ancre</HI> had.</P>
<P>As he spake those last words, <HI>Losieres Themines</HI> sonne
came unto him, and said, Comfort your selfe in your mis∣fortunes,
your brethren labour for their conservation,
they yeeld not themselves, I bring you great store of news,
you are not the Keeper of the Seales, <HI>Monsieur de Virg</HI>
hath your place: all shall go well, it seemes that he &amp; his
are in some sort bound to support your house; but if the
chance should turne, I advise you in good time that I will
be suretie no longer. Further, since your departure, the
King hath benignely entertained all his friends, and loo∣keth
on his servants with a kinde countenance; there is
free accesse unto his Maiestie, he goes every day to sit with
the Councell; I could tell you more, but I must go to sa∣lute
the King; farewell, and remember that for want of
balme they have your body with long barks of trees.</P>
<P><PB N="37" REF="21"/>
The Pages that as then layd hold on the necke and
breeches of their apprentice, would suffer him to speake
no more, every one of them teaching him a lesson as they
thought good. The Parisians never tooke greater pleasure
to see the Marquis <HI>d' Ancres</HI> body drawne about the citie,
then all the spirits in the Elizian fields had to see that
brave Constable so instructed and taught by those good
schoole-masters, who in lesse then an houres space made
him a martyr at least twentie times, and yet kild him not.
To conclude, <HI>du Bourdet</HI> brought him a writing to set
vpon his backe, containing these words:
<Q><L>Long be this apprentice lived,</L>
<L>Whose spirit hath not deceived</L>
<L>The hope of our progenitors:</L>
<L>He is fit for a Porter, without doubt,</L>
<L>And in short time it will fall out,</L>
<L>He will be capable to teach his brothers.</L></Q></P>
<P>The iudgement given, all the Lords tooke their leave
of the King, and as they returned with <HI>Zamet</HI> their guide,
the Marquis <HI>de Termes</HI> espied a man that sate writing vn∣der
a great olive tree: wherewith hee asked, if in that
country there were any Sollicitors or Attourneys, that li∣ved
by pleading other mens causes. None at all, said <HI>Za∣met.</HI>
What then, said he, doth this writer here? And go∣ing
neare unto him, they knew it was Marshall <HI>de Beron,</HI>
who was so earnestly studying, that he thought upon no∣thing
else. <HI>De Termes</HI> seeing him to be in that humour,
went softly behind him, after the maner of great persona∣ges
in the Court, and laid his hand upon his shoulder.
Wherewith the Marshall in great choler, said, What is he
that toucheth me? and looking backe, saw the Marquis.
Wherewith changing his choler into gladnesse, he em∣braced
him friendly, asking him, if he were one of those
gentlemen of <HI>Montauban.</HI> No, said <HI>de Termes,</HI> I am of
<HI>Clerac.</HI> What in Gods name make you here? said the
Marshall. And what goodly passion, said <HI>de Termes,</HI> ra∣visheth
<PB N="38" REF="22"/>
you into such an extasie? <HI>Cap de Bions,</HI> said he,
I was in a deepe humour of Poetrie, and was studying to
make verses for an Epitaph to be set vpon your tombes.</P>
<P>What, are you a Poet, said <HI>de Termes?</HI> No, said <HI>Biron,</HI>
but there being no warre in this country, sometimes I have
a conceit to passe the time in Poetry, like my Lady <HI>de Ro∣sau.</HI>
I pray you then, said <HI>de Termes,</HI> let us see something
of your doing, as well as my Lady <HI>d'Entragues. Pardions</HI>
I am content, said the Marshall, I was but beginning; see
here is that which I have done; I pray you tell me truly
whether I have done it fitly or no, and heare it without
passion.</P>
<Q><L>Here lieth a company of fooles, in respect of warriers brave,</L>
<L>That in the middle of their foes did lose their lives,</L>
<L>While three cowards, authors of the warre we have,</L>
<L>Meerly past the time in riding of their wives.</L></Q>
<P>Truly, said <HI>de Termes,</HI> you use us unworthily. <HI>Morbions,</HI>
said the Marshall, what, do I not say the truth? Are you not
great fooles, that suffered your selves to be slaine for a
companie of dastards that serve their owne turnes, under
pretence of religion, to establish their future greatnesse
at your costs and charges. <HI>Cap de Bions,</HI> what blowes with
my sword would I have laid about their eares, if I had bin
in their places. <HI>Monsieur d'Espernon</HI> is a subtill Catholik,
he besieged <HI>Rochell</HI> afarre off, and upon <HI>Pont neuf</HI> there
were more overthrowes given by him, then by any o∣ther
in <HI>France;</HI> but tell me, I pray you, are not the Iesuites
ashamed that they preacht against him during the league,
in their pulpits calling him Astarot and Arch-hereticke,
and yet in the meane time they must confesse, that at this
day he is one of the pilars of the faith, although he be
the same that he was, were they exclaimed against his per∣son,
onely that in those times he was none of the com∣panie,
as he is at this present. <HI>Mafoy,</HI> said the Marquis,
I must confesse that <HI>Mousieur d'Espernon</HI> is a Mathos, and
one that can manage his affaires better then any other
<PB N="39" REF="22"/>
in the Court; it is true that <HI>Luynes</HI> hath given him many
bad nights, but the fathers have recompenced all that.</P>
<P>While these things past, the King withdrew himselfe
into his chamber, where having wept long time for the
griefe that he had for the miseries of <HI>France,</HI> praying un∣to
God to divert the stormes thereof from it; he calld for
his most confident servants, with whom he conferred
touching the disorders of the Realme, and then said with
a loud voice, God helpe the bountie of my sonne, and
give him grace speedily to roote out the pernicious facti∣ons
of such Favorites. Now I am truly informed of the
lamentable affaires, into the extremitie whereof his
Crowne is plunged, I can speake pertinently with the
experience that I have of things past.</P>
<P>This then is that which me thinkes the King my sonne
should do, as well for his owne preservation, as for the
tranquillitie of his subiects. First, he ought to respect those
that give him good counsell, which is the soule of every
monarchie. I am not of opinion, that he should give my
wife the sole direction of his affaires; neither that my ne∣phew
the Prince of <HI>Cende</HI> should have it, in that respect
he ought to shun iealousie: it is requisite that euery one,
as neare as may be, should participate both in the honors
and in the care, and that every one in generall should con∣tribute
towards the relieving of the Flowers <HI>de Lis.</HI></P>
<P>My iudgement, to prevent and withstand the continual
disorders that have troubled <HI>France</HI> since my death, is,
That my sonne should make a Councell, not of Favorites,
but of those who by blood and affection have a particular
interest in the preservation of his person and of his State.
That he commit part of the managing of the State affairs,
to the Queene his mother. That he shall hold her in good
correspondence with himselfe, and my nephewes <HI>de Con∣de</HI>
and <HI>de Soissons</HI> neare unto him. That he should manage
all things by order of the Councell, and with pluralitie of
voices. That he shall referre himselfe to the prudent ad∣vice
<PB N="40" REF="23"/>
of the old <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1+ words" DISP="〈◊…〉"/> and officers of the Crowne, that
served me. That he shall commit the ordering of his con∣science
to some good Doctor. That he should embrace
the ancient Sorbonites, and put the new Transmontaine
Theologians from him. That by litle &amp; litle he shall lessen
his great charges. That he shall protect those of his blood.
That he shall not neglect his Parliaments. That he shall
take <HI>Luynes</HI> lands and goods to supply his necessities, and
for the comfort of the poore people. That he shall cause
the citadell of <HI>Amiens</HI> to be opened on that side towards
the Town, to prevent the inconveniences which one day
that fort may cause, and take an Inventorie of the great
riches which are in that place, as also in <HI>La Fere, Calais,</HI>
and <HI>Blaye.</HI> That he shall give all the governments which
the three brethren have, unto his old &amp; faithful servants.
That he shall drive all their kindred from the Court. That
he shall by absolute authoritie hold and maintaine the E∣dicts
of Parliament. That he shall conserve the ancient al∣liances
of the Crowne. That he shall stop his eares against
factious strangers. That he shal call to mind the dangerous
publick happened within these foure yeares within <HI>Paris,</HI>
as signes sent by God to warne us of the scourges that
threaten <HI>France.</HI> That he shall take heed of, and shun civil
warre, which cannot chuse but procure the ruine of his
affaires and of his people, while his neighbour seeks all the
meanes he can to preiudice his Realme. That he must call
to minde the Ambassage of <HI>Bassompiere</HI> in <HI>Spaine,</HI> and of
the breach of promise made touching <HI>Valtolina.</HI> That he
must have an eye unto the designes of strangers, who un∣der
pretence of religion, aspire unto the dissipation of his
state. That he shall procure peace unto his people. That
he must recompence those that deserve it, and punish
those that are wicked. And doing so, God will blesse him,
the Crowne shall flourish, his country will be enriched,
his friends will love him, his subiects serve him, and his
neigbours feare him.</P>
<Q><PB N="41" REF="23"/>
<L>There's nothing in the world that perfe<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="3+ letters" DISP="•••…"/></L>
<L>For if 'twere so, nothing would be amisse:</L>
<L>This booke is not so perfect as 'tis true,</L>
<L>Which you shall finde, if you give it the due.</L></Q>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

