<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The most honorable tragedie of Sir Richard Grinuile, Knight</TITLE><AUTHOR>Markham, Gervase, 1568?-1637.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A06960</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 17385</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S109856</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99845499</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99845499</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">10404</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A06960)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10404)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 433:03)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The most honorable tragedie of Sir Richard Grinuile, Knight</TITLE><AUTHOR>Markham, Gervase, 1568?-1637.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[112] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>At London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by I. Roberts, for Richard Smith,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1595.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>In verse.</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A-G.</NOTE><NOTE>Running title reads: The tragedy of Sir Richard Grinuile.</NOTE><NOTE>The last leaf is blank.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Grenville, Richard, --  Sir, 1541?-1591 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2002-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A06960">
<STC T="S">17385</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845499</BIBNO>
<VID>10404</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
Most Honorable Tra∣gedie
of Sir Richard
Grinuile, Knight.</P>
<P><HI>Bramo assai, poco spero,
nulla chieggio.</HI></P>
<P><HI>At London,</HI>
Printed by I. Roberts,
for Richard Smith.
1595.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the right Honorable
his singuler good Lord, Charles,
Lord Montioy.</HEAD>
<P>THE zeale (most excellent Lord)
which in my soule hath euer
beene deuoted to your seruice,
intangl'd with your honorable fauors
to mine vnable deseruings, hath giuen
fier to my hart, &amp; wings to my young∣ling
Muse, to raise her leaden humor
aboue the ordinarie pitch of her dull
Anthems, and sing of a subiect, the
<PB REF="3"/>
height of whose action, might, if I
had might, make my verse most migh∣tie,
graunt then (renowned Lord) that
thine eyes may lighten on my layes,
and thy graces keepe from scandall my
poore wydowed Orphan: pyttie re∣nowned
Grinuile, in his death-re∣nowning
hower, &amp; excuse his rough
Poet, whose sences are vnshapt, for
more softer melodie, so shall hee liue
happie, and I vnfaultie; both satisfied.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Lordships eternally,
<HI>Ieruis Markham.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable,
Robert, Earle of
Sussex.</HEAD>
<L>GReat Lord, to whom infinitiues of fame</L>
<L>Flock like night starres about the siluer Moone,</L>
<L>That giuest new fier to learnings late quencht flame,</L>
<L>Sauing the Muse by stonie times vndoone,</L>
<L>Let me finde fauour in thine honord sight,</L>
<L>Daring my rimes vnto thy sacred hand:</L>
<L>And whilst their accents talke of valures might,</L>
<L>Yeeld them some splendour from thy valures brand,</L>
<L>Thou in their lines, they in thine eyes shall see,</L>
<L>Nothing but honors vncontrouled minde,</L>
<L>Thou lending, they exacting still from thee,</L>
<L>Substance, that might to mightines doth binde,</L>
<L>And for his sake whose praise my Muse hath sought</L>
<L>Fauour my worke, the image of thy thought.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>I. M.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="4"/>
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To the right Honorable, Henrie
Wriothesly, Earle of South-hampton,
and Baron of Titchfielde.</HEAD>
<L>THou glorious Laurell of the Muses hill,</L>
<L>Whose eyes doth crowne the most victorius pen,</L>
<L>Bright Lampe of Vertue, in whose sacred skill,</L>
<L>Liues all the blisse of eares-in chaunting men,</L>
<L>From grauer subiects of thy graue assayes,</L>
<L>Bend thy coragious thoughts vnto these lines,</L>
<L>The graue frō whence mine humble Muse doth raise</L>
<L>True honors spirit in her rough deseignes;</L>
<L>And when the stubborne stroke of my harsh song,</L>
<L>Shall seasonlesse glide through almightie eares,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe to sweet it with thy blessed tong,</L>
<L>VVhose wel tun'd sound stills musick in the sphears,</L>
<L>So shall my tragick layes be bleft by thee,</L>
<L>And from thy lips suck theyr eternitie.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>I. M.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>To the honorable Knight, Sir
Edward VVingfield.</HEAD>
<L>WHen <HI>Alexander</HI> read <HI>Achilles</HI> prayse,</L>
<L>VVith honours enuie, and a loftie hart,</L>
<L>He shed stout teares, in ruth of stonie dayes</L>
<L>VVhich to his acts no Musicke could impart,</L>
<L>So all my all, essence of what I am,</L>
<L>Though our <HI>Achilles</HI> praise play in thine eye,</L>
<L>Feare not records for thine inrouled name,</L>
<L>VVhich shall out-liue immortall Poesie,</L>
<L>A thousand Sirens in the worlds last age,</L>
<L>Shall sing of thee, thy valure, and thy skill,</L>
<L>And to their lines, lay Angells eares in gage,</L>
<L>With soueraign charmes sent frō a soueraigne quill;</L>
<L>Meane while, vouchsafe to grace my worke &amp; me,</L>
<L>Gracing the soule beloued of heauen and thee.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>I. M.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="argument">
<PB REF="6"/>
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>The argument of the
whole Tragedie.</HEAD>
<P>SIr Richard <HI>Grinuile,</HI> lying at
anchor neere vnto <HI>Flores,</HI> one
of the westerlie Ilands of the
<HI>Azores,</HI> the last of August in the af∣ter
noone, had inteligence by one
Captayne <HI>Midelton</HI> of the aproch
of the Spanish <HI>Armada,</HI> beeing in
number fiftie three saile of great
<PB REF="7"/>
ships, and fifteene thousand men
to man them. Sir <HI>Richard,</HI> staying
to recouer his men which were
vpon the Iland, and disdayning
to flie from his Countries enemy,
not beeing able to recouer the
winde, was instantlie inuirond
with that hudge Nauie, betweene
whom began a dreadfull fight,
continuing the space of fifteene
howers, in which conflict, Sir <HI>Ri∣chard</HI>
sunck the great <HI>San Phillip</HI>
<PB REF="7"/>
of <HI>Spaine,</HI> the <HI>Ascention</HI> of <HI>Siuel,</HI> the
Admirall of the <HI>Hulks,</HI> and two
other great <HI>Armados;</HI> about mid∣night
Sir <HI>Richard</HI> receiued a woūd
through the bodie, and as he was
in dressing, was shot againe into
the head, and his Surgion slaine.
Sir <HI>Richard</HI> mayntained the fight,
till he had not one corne of pow∣der
left, nor one whole pike, nor
fortie lyuing men; which seeing,
hee would haue sunke his owne
<PB REF="8"/>
ship, but that he was gaine-stood
by the Maister thereof, who
contrarie to his will came to com∣position
with the <HI>Spanyards,</HI> and
so saued those which were left a∣liue.
Sir <HI>Richard</HI> dyed aboard the
Admyrall of <HI>Spayne,</HI> about the
fourth day after the battaile, and
was mightelie bewaild of all men.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<PB REF="8"/>
<HEAD>Faults escaped in the
printing.</HEAD>
<P>IN B. the second page, the third stanza, and the
first line, for night eternall, read nights eternall.</P>
<P>In F. page eight, the second stanza, and the last
line, for <HI>Abrahams,</HI> read <HI>Abr'ams.</HI></P>
<P>Also, in the next stanza folowing, and the thyrd
line, for bard, read bar'd.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<DIV2 TYPE="introduction">
<PB REF="9"/>
<PB REF="9"/>
<HEAD>¶The most Honourable
Tragedie of Sir Richard Grin∣uile,
Knight.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">To the fayrest.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>A Heauenlie fier is crope into my braine,</L>
<L>A heate diuine and all celestiall,</L>
<L>A burning furie spreads through euery vaine;</L>
<L>A turret-climbing thought maiesticall,</L>
<L>All these infuse a spirit-giuing raine,</L>
<L>Vnto my humble wits great festiuall.</L>
<L>Whose reede vnpleasing hermonie hath found,</L>
<L>Thus to transforme her into warlike sound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="10"/>
<L>Of wonders, miracles, and famous chiualrie,</L>
<L>Of Honours Image, and of Vertues iarres,</L>
<L>(Things past beliefe, yet pure in certaintie)</L>
<L>Of Death dead-slaine by Death, of glorious scarres,</L>
<L>Of mortall, made immortall Dietie,</L>
<L>And all containd in Valures stainelesse warres,</L>
<L>My homelie Muse stretching her oaten string,</L>
<L>Vnlearn't to thunder, mildlie meanes to sing.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Rest thee dread boy, the night eternall Lord,</L>
<L>Faire feathered <HI>Cupid</HI> thy <HI>Licaenas</HI> ioy,</L>
<L>Of thy tryumphant Chariot richlie stord,</L>
<L>VVith bleeding harts that breathing sighes destroy,</L>
<L>Nor thee, nor of thy kingdome I record,</L>
<L>Nor louers teares, nor loue, nor loues annoy.</L>
<L>Nor ought that in the vast world may be found,</L>
<L>Where tears in sighes, &amp; sighes in tears are drownd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="10"/>
<L>Fit subiects those for Poets golden quills,</L>
<L>Such as haue trod the true <HI>Pierian</HI> race,</L>
<L>VVhose sacred braines those numbers tun'd distills,</L>
<L>VVhich giues conceit the child of heauen her grace.</L>
<L>But now this flame that all my bodie fills,</L>
<L>Is <HI>Englands</HI> weeping ioy, and <HI>Spaynes</HI> disgrace.</L>
<L>Fearefull alarums, and the wet worlds sacke,</L>
<L>Swells in my song, the Dirge for glories wracke.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>To thee faire Nymph, my loue, my life, my gaze,</L>
<L>My soules first mouer, essence of my blisse,</L>
<L>Thought-chast <HI>Dictinna,</HI> Natures onlie maze,</L>
<L>Heauen of all what euer heauenlie is,</L>
<L>More white then <HI>Atlas</HI> browe, or <HI>Pelops</HI> blaze,</L>
<L>Compleat perfection which all creatures misse.</L>
<L>More louelie then was bright <HI>Astioche,</HI></L>
<L>Or <HI>Iunos</HI> hand-mayd sacred <HI>Diope.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="11"/>
<L>To thee which neuer lifts thine eyes to heauen,</L>
<L>But harts of Kings are showred in the same,</L>
<L>Fairer then Sunne, Moone, Starres, or Planets seauen,</L>
<L>True brand of Vertue, Honours liuing flame,</L>
<L>O thou whom hate adors, whose praise is euen</L>
<L>Matcht with the glories of the greatest name,</L>
<L>Thou like thy selfe, or better much by ods,</L>
<L>Nere made without a Parliament of Gods.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>To thee this labour of my Sunne-burnt braine,</L>
<L>Ill limn'd memorials of diuinest rage,</L>
<L>I offer as oblations to detaine,</L>
<L>Thy life-inspiring sight, (my peaces gage)</L>
<L>From those celestiall mirrors which remaine,</L>
<L>Obiects made happie in thy lookes suffrage,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Grinuile,</HI> armes and honors soueraigne,</L>
<L>My sower Muse shapes this Nectar seeking straine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="11"/>
<L>Euen of that man and his almightie minde,</L>
<L>Boundlesse like heauen in magnanimitie,</L>
<L>Conuerting all things of what euer kinde,</L>
<L>VVithin his bodie held societie,</L>
<L>To glad-some starres in cleerest skyes assign'd,</L>
<L>VVanting but onely true eternitie.</L>
<L>Of him I sing <HI>(Fairest)</HI> but reade I pray,</L>
<L>Thine eyes makes happie, all y<SUP>t</SUP> thine eyes suruay.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And with her thou great Soueraigne of the earth,</L>
<L>Onelie immatchlesse Monarchesse of harts,</L>
<L>From whose faire eyes issued the Muses birth,</L>
<L>Murderd by Iron-age, and barb'rous darts,</L>
<L>Yeeld from thy beams plentie to my wits dearth,</L>
<L>That I may sing valures almightie parts,</L>
<L>And Chronicle those tropheys to thy throne,</L>
<L>VVhich from this Ile, and his great spyrit shone.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="12"/>
<L>And thou deare <HI>Soule,</HI> the portraiture of Fame,</L>
<L>For whom <HI>Ioue</HI> made a newe fourth Hirarchie,</L>
<L>Of whose lost drops millions of vertues came,</L>
<L>Extold in heauen beyond the third degree,</L>
<L>Now giue thy selfe a light in this selfe flame,</L>
<L>That thou maist liue beyond posteritie;</L>
<L>And whilst I of th'vnconquered conquest write,</L>
<L>Sit on my hand and teach me to indite.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="tragedy">
<PB REF="12"/>
<HEAD>The Tragedy of Sir Richard
Grinuile.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THat time of yeare when the inamored Sunne</L>
<L>Clad in the richest roabes of liuing fiers,</L>
<L>Courted y<SUP>e</SUP> Virgin signe, great Naturs Nunne,</L>
<L>Which barrains earth of al what earth desires</L>
<L>Euen in the month that from <HI>Augustus</HI> wonne,</L>
<L>His sacred name which vnto heauen aspires,</L>
<L>And on the last of his ten trebled dayes,</L>
<L>VVhen wearie labour new refresh assayes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Then whē the earth out-brau'd y<SUP>e</SUP> beautious Morne,</L>
<L>Boasting his cornie Mantle stird with aire,</L>
<L>Which like a golden Ocean did adorne</L>
<L>His cold drie carcasse, featurelesse, vnfaire,</L>
<L>Holding the naked shearers scithe in scorne</L>
<L>Or ought that might his borrowed pride empaire,</L>
<L>The soule of vertue seeing earth so ritch,</L>
<L>VVith his deare presence gilds the sea as mitch.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="13"/>
<L>The sea, which then was heauie, sad, and still,</L>
<L>Dull, vnapplyd to sportiue wantonnesse,</L>
<L>As if her first-borne <HI>Venus</HI> had beene ill,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Neptune</HI> seene the <HI>Sonne</HI> his loue possesse,</L>
<L>Or greater cares, that greatest comforts kill,</L>
<L>Had crownd with griefe, the worlds wet wildernesse,</L>
<L>Such was the still-foote <HI>Thetis</HI> silent paine,</L>
<L>VVhose flowing teares, ebbing fell backe againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Thetis,</HI> the mother of the pleasant springs,</L>
<L>Grandam of all the Riuers in the world,</L>
<L>To whom earths veins their moistning tribut brings,</L>
<L>Now with a mad disturbed passion hurld,</L>
<L>About her caue (the worlds great treasure) flings:</L>
<L>And with wreath'd armes, &amp; long wet hairs vncurld,</L>
<L>VVithin her selfe laments a losse, vnlost,</L>
<L>And mones her wrongs, before her ioyes be crost.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="13"/>
<L>Thus whilst diuining sorrowe ceaz'd her hart,</L>
<L><HI>Grinuile</HI> (ô melt my spyrit in that name,)</L>
<L>As sings the Swan her funerall depart,</L>
<L>And waues her wings, the ensignes of her fame,</L>
<L>So he, with vertue sweetning bitter smart,</L>
<L>VVhich from the seas long toyling seruice came:</L>
<L>For why, sixe Moones, &amp; so oft times the Sunne,</L>
<L>VVas past, and had one halfe the signes ore-runne,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Ere he the earth, our common Mother saw;</L>
<L>Now earlie greets black <HI>Flores</HI> banefull Ile,</L>
<L><HI>(Flores,</HI> from whence afflictions selfe doth draw</L>
<L>The true memorialls of a weeping stile;)</L>
<L>And with <HI>Caisters</HI> Querristers which straw</L>
<L>Descant, that might Death of his darts beguile,</L>
<L>He tunes saluting notes, sweeter then long,</L>
<L>All which are made his last liues funerall song.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="14"/>
<L>Skillesse in deaths great Parliament he cals</L>
<L>His fellowe mat's, and minions to his fame,</L>
<L>Shewes them long lookt for land, and how it brauls,</L>
<L>Repulsing backe the billowes as they came,</L>
<L>Much he triumphes, and passed griefe for-stals</L>
<L>VVith present ioy (sorrow lights pleasures flame:)</L>
<L>And whilst his hopes of <HI>Happy-fortune</HI> sings,</L>
<L><HI>Misfortune</HI> by, controls them with her wings.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Desird reliefe, and euer welcome rest,</L>
<L>The elements that forme the wearie man,</L>
<L>Began to hold a counsaile in his brest,</L>
<L>Painting his wants by sicknes pale &amp; wan;</L>
<L>VVith other griefes, that others force opprest,</L>
<L>Aduising stay, (as what is but they can,)</L>
<L>VVhilst he that fate to come, and past, nere feard,</L>
<L>Concludes to stay till strength decayd repaird.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="14"/>
<L>Then casts he Anchor hulling on the maine,</L>
<L>And all his shyps poore Cittizens recounts,</L>
<L>An hundred iust were free from sicknes paine,</L>
<L>Fourescore and ten death their redresse accounts,</L>
<L>So that of all both sicke and sound vnslaine,</L>
<L>Vnto two hundred wanting ten amounts.</L>
<L>A slender armie for so great a guide,</L>
<L>But vertue is vnknowne till it be tride.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Those whom their harts enabled to attempt,</L>
<L>He puts a shoare to make supplie for neede;</L>
<L>Those whom long sicknes taught of death cōtempt,</L>
<L>He visits, and from <HI>Ioues</HI> great Booke doth reede</L>
<L>The balme which mortall poyson doth exempt;</L>
<L>Those whō new breathing health like sucklings feed,</L>
<L>Hie to the sands, and sporting on the same,</L>
<L>Finde libertie, the liues best liuing flame.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="15"/>
<L>Looke how a troupe of Winter-prisoned Dames,</L>
<L>Pent in th' inclosure of the walled townes,</L>
<L>VVelcoms the Spring, Vsher to Somers flames,</L>
<L>Making theyr pastimes on the flowrie downes,</L>
<L>Whose beautious Arras wrought in natures frames,</L>
<L>Through eyes admire, the hart w<SUP>t</SUP> wonder crownes,</L>
<L>So these wood-walled Cittizens at sea,</L>
<L>VVelcome both Spring and Sommer in a day.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The warring byllowes, seas artillerie,</L>
<L>With long held siege, had bruz'd their beaten keele,</L>
<L>VVhich to repaire the most, most busied be,</L>
<L>Lab'ring to cure, what want in labours feele;</L>
<L>All pleasd with toyle, clothing extremitie</L>
<L>In Hopes best robes, that hang on Fortunes wheele.</L>
<L>But men, are men, in ignorance of Fate,</L>
<L>To alter chaunce, exceedeth humaine state.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="15"/>
<L>For when the Sun, towred in heauens head,</L>
<L>Downe from the siluer mountaine of the skye,</L>
<L>Bent his bright Chariot on the glassie bed,</L>
<L>Faire christall, guilded with his glorious eye,</L>
<L>Fearing some vsurpation in his stead,</L>
<L>Or least his Loue should too-long daliance spy</L>
<L>Tweene him and <HI>Virgo,</HI> whose attractiue face</L>
<L>Had newly made him leaue the <HI>Lyons</HI> chase,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In that same myd-daies hower came sayling in,</L>
<L>A thought-swift-flying Pynnase, taught by winde,</L>
<L>T'outstrip in flight Times euer-flying wing;</L>
<L>And being come where Vertue was inshrinde,</L>
<L>First vaild his plumes, and wheeling in a ring,</L>
<L>With Goat-like daūcing, stays where <HI>Grinuile</HI> shynd,</L>
<L>The while his great Cōmaunder calls the name,</L>
<L>VVhich is ador'd of all that speakes the same.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="16"/>
<L>The great commaunder of this little Barke,</L>
<L>VVhich like an Eglet armes the Eagles side,</L>
<L>VVas <HI>Midleton,</HI> the ayme of Honors marke,</L>
<L>That more had prou'd then danger durst haue tride,</L>
<L>Now seeing all good fortunes sun-shine darke,</L>
<L>Thrise calls Sir <HI>Richard,</HI> who as oft replyde,</L>
<L>Bidding him speake, and ring his newes aloude,</L>
<L>Ill, not apald, nor good could make him proude.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>O then (quoth <HI>Midelton)</HI> thou soule of all</L>
<L>VVhat euer boasts in magnanimitie,</L>
<L>Thou, whom pure Vertue her best part doth call,</L>
<L>Better then valure, stronger then dietie,</L>
<L>VVhom men adore, and all the gods exhall</L>
<L>Into the bookes of endlesse memorie,</L>
<L>I bring thee tidings of a deadly fray,</L>
<L>Begun in Heauen, to end vpon the Sea.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="16"/>
<L>The glorious Senate of the Skyes was set,</L>
<L>And all the gods were royaliz'd in state,</L>
<L>VVhen <HI>Happy-fortune</HI> and <HI>Ill-fortune</HI> met,</L>
<L>Striuing who first should enter Heauens gate,</L>
<L>The one made mad the others fame to let,</L>
<L>Neither but stirr'd with rage to wonder at,</L>
<L>Confusedly, as water-floods doe passe</L>
<L>Their common bounds, such their rude entrance was.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The gods disturb'd, admire their strange aproch,</L>
<L>Censuring their angers by their gloing eyes,</L>
<L><HI>Ill-fortune</HI> was attended by <HI>Reproch,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Good-fortune, Fame</HI> and <HI>Vertue</HI> stellefies;</L>
<L>One sweares the other doth her right incroch,</L>
<L>VVhich is the elder house, none can deuise:</L>
<L>The gods deuide, yet in the end agree</L>
<L>The Fates shall iudge each others pedegree.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="17"/>
<L><HI>Good-fortune,</HI> drawes from heauen her hye descent,</L>
<L>Making hie <HI>Ioue</HI> the roote of her large tree;</L>
<L>Shee showes from him, how many god-heads went,</L>
<L><HI>Archangells, Angells,</HI> heauens posteritie:</L>
<L>From thence, she showes the glorious thrid she lent</L>
<L>To <HI>Monarks, Emperours,</HI> and <HI>Kyngs</HI> in fee,</L>
<L>Annexing as Colatteralls to her line</L>
<L><HI>Honour, Vertue, Valure,</HI> and <HI>Endles-time.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Naithlesse, <HI>Ill-fortune</HI> will be elder borne,</L>
<L>Shee saith, she springs from <HI>Saturne, Ioues</HI> wronged Sier,</L>
<L>And heauen, and earth, &amp; hell her coate haue borne,</L>
<L>Fresh bleeding harts within a field of fier;</L>
<L>All that the world admires, she makes her scorne,</L>
<L>VVho farthest seemes, is to <HI>Ill-fortune</HI> nier,</L>
<L>And that iust proofe may her great praise cōmend,</L>
<L>All that <HI>Best-chaunce</HI> begins, <HI>Ill-chaunce</HI> doth ende.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="17"/>
<L>Thus they dispute, guilding their tongues report</L>
<L>VVith instances, and argumentall sawes,</L>
<L><HI>Ill-fortune,</HI> bids let all the worlde resort</L>
<L>And show within their Chronicles and lawes,</L>
<L>The man whose liues-line neuer did consort</L>
<L>VVith sharpe affliction, deaths first grounded cause,</L>
<L>Then will she yeeld, else, is shee victor still,</L>
<L>VVorlds good is rare, perpetuall is their ill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Euen as the racket takes the balls rebound,</L>
<L>So doth <HI>Good-fortune</HI> catch <HI>Ill-fortunes</HI> proofe,</L>
<L>Saying, she wil her in her selfe confound,</L>
<L>Making her darts, Agents for her behoofe;</L>
<L>Bow but thine eies (quoth she) whence ha'ts abound,</L>
<L>And I will show thee vnder heauens roofe</L>
<L>Th'vnconquered man whō no mischaunce importunes,</L>
<L>Crown of my kingdom, deaths mā to misfortunes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="18"/>
<L>At this, the casments of the skye broke ope,</L>
<L>Discouering all what's girdled in her frame,</L>
<L>VVhilst <HI>Happy-fortune</HI> through her eyes large scope</L>
<L>Like a Cosmographer comments on the same;</L>
<L>Three parts with praise she past and future hope,</L>
<L>Then to the fourth, the VVesterne world she came,</L>
<L>And there, with her eyes festrawe paints a storie,</L>
<L>Stranger then strange, more glorified then glorie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>See (sayd <HI>Faire-fortune,</HI> to her foule shapt <HI>Foe)</HI></L>
<L>How on the sourge which beates against the Ile</L>
<L>Of <HI>Flores,</HI> whence thy curst oblations growe,</L>
<L>A winde-taught capring ship which ayre beguiles,</L>
<L>(Making poore <HI>Cephatus</HI> for-lorne with woe,</L>
<L>Curse arte, which made arte framed saile such smiles)</L>
<L>Richlie imbrodred with the Iems of warre,</L>
<L>In thy dispight commaunds a lucky starre.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="18"/>
<L>In that faire vessell liues my garlands flower,</L>
<L><HI>Grinuile,</HI> my harts immortall arterie;</L>
<L>Of him thy dietie had neuer power,</L>
<L>Nor hath hee had of griefe one simpathie;</L>
<L>Successe attends him, all good hap doth shower</L>
<L>A golden raine of perpetuitie</L>
<L>Into his bossome, where mine Empire stands,</L>
<L>Murdring the Agents of thy blacke commands.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Say, and say true, (for what but thou wilt say,)</L>
<L>That euer <HI>Grinuils</HI> fortunes came before thee;</L>
<L>Or euer prostrate at thine Altars lay,</L>
<L>Or with one wreath of Cipresse did adore thee?</L>
<L>Proue one blacke storme in all his Sommers day,</L>
<L>Whose threatning clouds compeld him to implore thee,</L>
<L>Thē wil I staine my milkwhite vaile with weeping,</L>
<L>And as thine handmaide dye in sorrowes keeping.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="19"/>
<L>As wounds the lightning, yet preserues the skinne,</L>
<L>So did these words split <HI>Lucklesse-fortunes</HI> hart,</L>
<L>Her smiling <HI>Superficies,</HI> lockt within</L>
<L>A deepe exulcerated festring smart;</L>
<L>Heere shee perceiu'd her first disgrace begin,</L>
<L>And wordlesse from the heauens takes her depart.</L>
<L>Yet as she flewe, her wings in flying cri'd</L>
<L>On <HI>Grinuile</HI> shall my fame and power be tride.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>At her departure all the heauens were glad,</L>
<L>Triumphing in <HI>Ill-fortunes</HI> banishment,</L>
<L><HI>Apollo</HI> set new <HI>Anthems</HI> as <HI>Ioue</HI> bad,</L>
<L>VVhich spheare tunes made more then most excel∣lent;</L>
<L>No light in heauen but with new fier was clad,</L>
<L>Making next <HI>Ioue, Good-fortune</HI> president,</L>
<L>Enrowling in the Bookes of destenie,</L>
<L>This memorable famous victorie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="19"/>
<L>Onely the <HI>Fat's</HI> su'd for her backe repeale,</L>
<L>(For they <HI>Ill-fortune</HI> lou'd exceeding well)</L>
<L>Many her deedes and Tropheis they reueale,</L>
<L>And all her liues blacke legend, weeping tell;</L>
<L>Yet all they speake, cannot in heauen preuaile,</L>
<L>Which seene, in spight they follow her to hell,</L>
<L>And there inhoused with their mother <HI>Night,</HI></L>
<L>All foure deuise, how heauen and earth to spight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Hence sprang the loues of <HI>Ioue,</HI> the <HI>Sonnes</HI> exile,</L>
<L>The shame of <HI>Mars</HI> and <HI>Venus</HI> in a net;</L>
<L><HI>Iunos</HI> forsaken bed; <HI>Saturns</HI> compile</L>
<L>Of frantike, discontentment, which beset</L>
<L>All heauen with armes; <HI>Diana</HI> hence had while</L>
<L>To court her sleeping boy; whilst <HI>Thetis</HI> let</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> imbrace her in her <HI>Neptunes</HI> stead,</L>
<L>Who made complaints, breach of his bridall bed.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="20"/>
<L>Yet not content with these disparagments,</L>
<L>Much greater mischiefes issues from their minds,</L>
<L><HI>Grinuile,</HI> thy mountaine honour it augments</L>
<L>VVithin their brests, a Meteor like the winds,</L>
<L>VVhich thrall'd in earth, a reeling issue rents</L>
<L>With violent motion; and their wills combinds</L>
<L>To belch their hat's, vow'd murdrers of thy same,</L>
<L>Which to effect, thus they begin the same.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Fast to <HI>Iberia</HI> flies vntoward chaunce,</L>
<L><HI>Iberia,</HI> which we vulgar Christen <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>Vpon whose Sunne-burnt continent doth daunce</L>
<L>VVesterne <HI>Ducallidon,</HI> the greatest maine,</L>
<L>Thither shee packs, <HI>Error</HI> doth their aduaunce</L>
<L>Her coale-blacke standerd in the hands of paine;</L>
<L>And as escapt from rauishment or bale,</L>
<L>With false teares, thus shee tunes a falser tale.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="20"/>
<L>Great Empire (said shee) blessed in thy birth,</L>
<L>Beautious created for-head of this round,</L>
<L>That with thy smiles first lent to heauen mirth,</L>
<L>And bout thy temples all perfections woond,</L>
<L>Lodgd in th'immagin'd corners of the earth;</L>
<L>Thou whom our centers Monarchesse art crownd,</L>
<L>Attend my suite, baptisd in mournefull teares,</L>
<L>VVho but ere while triumphed on the spheares.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Nor for my selfe more then thine owne decay</L>
<L>Which blindfold pleasure clouds as they arise,</L>
<L>Be gracious, and retort the domefull day,</L>
<L>VVhich thee and me to shame would sacrifice.</L>
<L>Loe, on the great west-walling boistrous sea,</L>
<L>VVhich doth imbrace thy gold-inclosing eyes,</L>
<L>Of many sailes one man, of one poore Ile,</L>
<L>That will my fame, and all thy faire defile.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="21"/>
<L>His numberlesse great infinits of fame,</L>
<L>Haue shut against me heauens great christall dore,</L>
<L>The clouds, which once my feets dust had to name,</L>
<L>Hang ore my forhead, threatning euermore</L>
<L>Death to my praise, life to my infant shame,</L>
<L>Whilst I with sighes mediate a new restore.</L>
<L>And in my selfe behold my pleasures past,</L>
<L>Swimming amongst the ioyes I cannot tast.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Th'ambrosian Nectar-filled banqueting,</L>
<L>No more shall I communicate, or see,</L>
<L>Triumphes in heauen, <HI>Ioues</HI> masks, and reuelling,</L>
<L>Are cleene exempt, both from my ioyes and me.</L>
<L>The reason, for my loue to thee I bring,</L>
<L>Trimming thy locks with Iems of dietie,</L>
<L>Making the gods a dread a fatall day,</L>
<L>VVorse then the Giants warre or Centaurs fray.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="21"/>
<L>Poore goddesse, rob'd of all eternall power,</L>
<L>VVhose broken Statues, and downe razed Fan's,</L>
<L>Neuer warm'd altars, euer forgotten hower</L>
<L>VVhere any memorie of praise is tane,</L>
<L>VVitnes my fall from great <HI>Olympus</HI> tower;</L>
<L>Prostrate, implore balme for receiued bane,</L>
<L>And dyre reuenge gainst heauens impietie,</L>
<L>VVhich els in shame will make thee folow mee.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Behold these robes, maps of my fortunes world,</L>
<L>Torne, and distaind with eye-scornd beggerie;</L>
<L>These rags deuide the Zones, wherein is hurld</L>
<L>My liues distemprate, hote cold miserie;</L>
<L>These tears are points, the scale these hairs vncurld,</L>
<L>My hands the compasse, woe the emperie:</L>
<L>And these my plaints, true and auriculer,</L>
<L>Are to my Globe the perpendiculer.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="22"/>
<L>Looke how I am, such art thou like to be</L>
<L>If armes preuent not heauens intendiment,</L>
<L><HI>Grinuile,</HI> which now surfeits with dignitie,</L>
<L>Burd'ning the Sea with my disparagement;</L>
<L>Chiding the wanton winds if greedelie</L>
<L>They kisse his sailes; or els too slowlie vent,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Ioue,</HI> which bad the day be and it was,</L>
<L>So bids he Conquest warre; she brings to passe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The sole incouragement he giues his power,</L>
<L>Is Prophet-like presaging of thy death,</L>
<L>Courage he cries, euen in the dying hower,</L>
<L>And with his words, recalls departing breath;</L>
<L>O (sayes he to his Mat's) you are my glories tower,</L>
<L>Impregnable, wall'd with vnuanquisht faith,</L>
<L>You are the hands and agents of my trust,</L>
<L>I but the hart reuoluing what we must.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="22"/>
<L>Liue Saints, til we haue ript the wombe of <HI>Spayne,</HI></L>
<L>And wounded <HI>Error</HI> in the armes of hell,</L>
<L>Crushing the triple Myter in disdaine,</L>
<L>Which on y<SUP>e</SUP> seauenfold mounted Witch doth dwel,</L>
<L>Angells rewards for such dissignes remaine,</L>
<L>And on heauens face men shall your stories tell;</L>
<L>At this they shoute; as eager of the pray,</L>
<L>as Ants in winter of a sunne-shine day.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus like triumphant <HI>Caesar</HI> drawne in Rome,</L>
<L>By winged <HI>Valure,</HI> and vnconquered <HI>Chaunce,</HI></L>
<L>He plowes the Sea, (ô were it made his tombe)</L>
<L>VVhilst <HI>Happy-fortune</HI> pypes vnto his daunce.</L>
<L>Yet may thy power alternat heauens doome,</L>
<L>So pleaseth thee thy forward will t'aduaunce,</L>
<L>And cheare y<SUP>e</SUP> sinews of thy mighty arme,</L>
<L>VVhose out-strecht force shall quell his proud a∣larme,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="23"/>
<L>Then giue newe fuell to thine honours fier,</L>
<L>Least slight regard wealth-winning <HI>Error</HI> slay,</L>
<L>And so old <HI>Saturns</HI> happie world retyer,</L>
<L>Making <HI>Trueths</HI> dungion brighter then the day;</L>
<L>VVas neuer woe could wound thy kingdom nyer,</L>
<L>Or of thy borrowed beautie make display,</L>
<L>Because this vow in heauens booke doth remaine,</L>
<L>That <HI>Errors</HI> death shall consumate thy raigne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Now, for my god-heads remnant liues in thee,</L>
<L>VVhose lost successe breeds mine eternall end,</L>
<L>Take for thine ayde, afflicting <HI>Miserie,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Woe,</HI> mine attendant, and <HI>Dispayre</HI> my freend,</L>
<L>All three my greatest great <HI>Triumuerie,</HI></L>
<L>Blood-bath'd <HI>Carnifici,</HI> which will protend</L>
<L>A murdring desolation on to that will,</L>
<L>VVhich me in thee, and thee in mee would kill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="23"/>
<L>Here, with her fixed Comet-blazing eyes,</L>
<L>The damned <HI>Augurs</HI> of vntimely death,</L>
<L>Shee ends her tale, whilst from her harts caue flyes</L>
<L>A storme of winds, no gentle sighing breath,</L>
<L>All which, like euill spirits in disguise,</L>
<L>Enter <HI>Iberias</HI> eares, and to her sayth,</L>
<L>That all the substance of this damned storie,</L>
<L>VVas zealous true, coynd for her <HI>Spanish</HI> glorie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sworne to beleeue, for ill, in ill affies,</L>
<L><HI>Spayne</HI> then enamour'd with the <HI>Romane</HI> trull,</L>
<L>Calls all her forces, more then Atomies,</L>
<L>And tells <HI>Ill-fortunes</HI> storie to the full;</L>
<L>Many Parenthises shee doth deuise,</L>
<L>And frost-relenting words doth choycely cull,</L>
<L>Bewitching those whom oft shee had deceiued,</L>
<L>VVith such like Hemlock as her selfe receiued.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="24"/>
<L>The first and greatest one, commaunding, all</L>
<L>The soule of mischiefes old created mother,</L>
<L>VVas <HI>Don Alphonso Bassan,</HI> proud in brall,</L>
<L>The Marques <HI>Sancta Cruces</HI> onely brother:</L>
<L>Him shee coniures by typ's emperiall,</L>
<L>And all that falshoods seeming trueth could couer,</L>
<L>To vndertake this hie (she termd it) act,</L>
<L>VVhich craues a curse of all that reads the fact.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Her selfe (shee said) and all the flowers of <HI>Spayne,</HI></L>
<L>Should vnder his, as heauens Ensigne warre:</L>
<L>Thus from her harts foule dunghill flyes amaine</L>
<L>Grosse vapours, metamorphosd to a starre;</L>
<L>Her words in fumes like prodogies retaine</L>
<L>His hart, by her tongues witchcraft bound so farre,</L>
<L>As what shee will, that will hee vnder-take,</L>
<L>Be it to warre with heauen for her sake.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="24"/>
<L>The seeming Nectar of her poysoning speech,</L>
<L>So well shee saw surprise his licoras sence,</L>
<L>That for to reare her ill beyond ills reach,</L>
<L>VVith selfe-like tropes, decks self-like eloquence,</L>
<L>Making in <HI>Britan Dona</HI> such a breach,</L>
<L>That her arm'd wits, conqu'ring his best wits fence,</L>
<L>He vowes with <HI>Bassan</HI> to defend the broile,</L>
<L>VVhich men of praise, &amp; earth of fame shal spoile.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>To him shee giues the <HI>Biscaynnoys</HI> for guard,</L>
<L>Mechannicall Artificers for death,</L>
<L>And those which of affliction neuer hard,</L>
<L>Shee tempers with the hammer of her breath:</L>
<L>To euery act shee giues huge lyp-reward,</L>
<L>Lauish of oathes, as falshood of her faith;</L>
<L>And for the ground of her pretended right,</L>
<L>T'is hate, which enuies vertue in a Knight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="25"/>
<L>These two to her fast bound in vassailage,</L>
<L>Vnto the Marques <HI>Arumburch</HI> shee flyes,</L>
<L>Him shee prouokes, him shee finds apt to rage,</L>
<L>Imprisoning Pitties teares in flintie eyes;</L>
<L>To him the power of <HI>Siuill</HI> for a gage</L>
<L>Shee doth bequeath; bidding his prowesse ryse,</L>
<L>And clense his Countries face frō widowes tears,</L>
<L>To which he posts, like lightning frō the sphears.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Lastly, to make vp mischiefes perfect square,</L>
<L>To <HI>Luis Cutino</HI> shee takes her flight,</L>
<L>Him shee commaunds, he to her homage sware</L>
<L>To guide a Nauie to this damned fight,</L>
<L>Of Hulks and Fly-boats, such as durst to dare.</L>
<L>Shee giues him soueraigne rule, and publique right,</L>
<L>And then vniting all foure powers in one,</L>
<L>Sends them to sea, to calme <HI>Misfortunes</HI> mone.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="25"/>
<L>And now behold (diuine for valiancie)</L>
<L>Like flying Castells sayle they to this strand;</L>
<L>Fiftie three saile, strong in artillarie,</L>
<L>Best men of warre knowne in the <HI>Spanish</HI> land;</L>
<L>Fifteene Armados, Kings of soueraigntie,</L>
<L>VVhich led the lesser with a mightie hand:</L>
<L>And these in foure battalions hither flie,</L>
<L>VVith whom three dayes I saild in companie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Then gentle <HI>Grinuile, Thetis</HI> parramoure,</L>
<L>Dearer then <HI>Venus,</HI> Daughter of the flood,</L>
<L>Set sailes to wind, let not neglect deuoure</L>
<L>Thy gracious fortunes and thine Angell good,</L>
<L>Cut through the maine, compell thy keele to scoure,</L>
<L>No man his ill too timelie hath with-stoode</L>
<L>And whē <HI>Best-chaunce</HI> shal haue repaird thy fortune,</L>
<L>Time for this flight may iust reuenge importune.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="26"/>
<L>Here <HI>Midelton</HI> did end the passing peale</L>
<L>VVhich gaue the warning to a dismall end,</L>
<L>And as his words last knell began to faile,</L>
<L>The damned Nauie did a glimmering send,</L>
<L>By which Sir <HI>Richard</HI> might their power reueale,</L>
<L>VVhich seeming conquerlesse, did conquests lend:</L>
<L>At whose appearance, <HI>Midelton</HI> did cry,</L>
<L>See where they come, for fame and pitty flie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This certaine story, of too certaine ill,</L>
<L>Did not extinguish, but gaue honor fier,</L>
<L>Th' amazing prodigie, (bane of my quill,)</L>
<L>Bred not astonishment, but a strong desier,</L>
<L>By which this heauen-adopted Knights strong will,</L>
<L>Then hiest height of Fame, flew much more hier:</L>
<L>And from the boundlesse greatnes of his minde,</L>
<L>Sends back this answer through his lyps refin'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="26"/>
<L>Thanks hardie <HI>Midelton</HI> for thy dilate,</L>
<L>Perswasiue presage to auoyde my death,</L>
<L>But if thou wed my fortunes with my state,</L>
<L>This sauing health shall suffocate my breath,</L>
<L>To flye from them that holds my God in hate,</L>
<L>My Mistres, Country, me, and my sworne fayth,</L>
<L>VVere to pull of the load from <HI>Typhons</HI> back,</L>
<L>And crush my selfe, with shame &amp; seruile wrack.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Nor if my hart degenerate should yeeld,</L>
<L>To entertaine an amorus thought of life,</L>
<L>And so transport mine honour to the field,</L>
<L>VVhere seeming-valure dies by cowards knife,</L>
<L>Yet zeale and conscience shall new forces build,</L>
<L>And others soules, with my soule holdeth strife;</L>
<L>For halfe my men, &amp; all that draw sound breath,</L>
<L>Are gone on shore, for foode to conquer death.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="27"/>
<L>If I forsake them, certaine is their end,</L>
<L>If I obtaine them, doubtfull is our fall,</L>
<L>Vpon my flight, shame and their sacks depend,</L>
<L>Vpon my stay, hope of good hap doth call,</L>
<L>Equall to me, the meanest I commend;</L>
<L>Nor will I loose, but by the losse of all:</L>
<L>They are the sinewes of my life and fame,</L>
<L>Dismembred bodies perish cripple-lame.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This sayd, he sends a cock-boate to the shore,</L>
<L>To summon backe his men vnto their ship,</L>
<L>Who com'd a board, began with some vprore</L>
<L>To way their Anchors, and with care to dip</L>
<L>Their hie reuolues in doubt, and euermore</L>
<L>To paint deaths visage with a trembling lip,</L>
<L>Till he that was all fearelesse, and feare slew,</L>
<L>VVith Nectard words from thē all dangers drew.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="27"/>
<L>VVhen <HI>Midelton</HI> Saw <HI>Grinuills</HI> hie reuolue,</L>
<L>Past hope, past thought, past reach of all aspire,</L>
<L>Once more to moue him flie he doth resolue,</L>
<L>And to that purpose tips his tongue with fier;</L>
<L>Fier of sweete words, that easelie might dissolue</L>
<L>And moisten flint, though steeld in stiffe attire,</L>
<L>Had not desier of wonder, praise, and fame,</L>
<L>Extinkt the sparks, and still keepe dead the flame,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Greater, and better then inarked he,</L>
<L>VVhich in the worlds huge deluge did suruiue,</L>
<L>O let thy wings of magnanimitie,</L>
<L>Not vainelie flatter, <HI>Honour</HI> to acchiue,</L>
<L>Gainst all conceit impossibilitie,</L>
<L>By which thou murderst <HI>Vertue,</HI> keepe aliue,</L>
<L>Nor in thy seeking of diuinitie,</L>
<L>Kill not heauens fame by base mortallitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="28"/>
<L>O <HI>Grinuile,</HI> thou hast red Philosophy,</L>
<L>Nature and Arte hath made thee excellent,</L>
<L>And what thou read'st, hath grafted this in thee,</L>
<L>That to attempt hie dangers euident</L>
<L>VVithout constraine or neede, is infamie,</L>
<L>And honor turnes to rashnes in th'euent;</L>
<L>And who so darrs, not caring how he darrs,</L>
<L>Sells vertues name, to purchase foolish starrs.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Deere Knight, thou art not forst to hazard fame,</L>
<L>Heauens haue lent thee meanes to scape thine ill,</L>
<L>If thou abide, as true as is thy name,</L>
<L>So truly shall thy fault, thy death fulfill:</L>
<L>And as to loue the life for vertues flame,</L>
<L>Is the iust act of a true noble will,</L>
<L>So to contemne it, and her helps exclude,</L>
<L>Is basenes, rashnes, and no <HI>Fortitude.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="28"/>
<L>He that compard mans bodie to an hoast,</L>
<L>Sayd that y<SUP>e</SUP> hands were scouts, discouering harmes,</L>
<L>The feete, were horsemen, thundring on the coast,</L>
<L>The brest, and stomacke, footmen, huge in swarmes.</L>
<L>But for the head, in soueraigntie did boast,</L>
<L>It Captayne was, director of alarms,</L>
<L>VVhose rashnes, if it hazarded an ill,</L>
<L>Not hee alone but all the hoast did spill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Rashe <HI>Isadas,</HI> the <HI>Lacedemon</HI> Lord,</L>
<L>That naked fought against the <HI>Theban</HI> power,</L>
<L>Although they crown'd his valure by accord,</L>
<L>Yet was hee find for rashnes in that hower:</L>
<L>And those which most his carelesse praise affoard,</L>
<L>Did most condemne what follie did deuoure;</L>
<L>For in attempting, prowesse is not ment,</L>
<L>But wiselie doing what we doe attempt.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="29"/>
<L>Then sith t'is valure to abandon fight,</L>
<L>And base to darre, where no hope is to winne,</L>
<L>(Renowned man, of all renowne the light)</L>
<L>Hoyst vp thy sailes, delay attackts thy sinne,</L>
<L>Flie from ill-boding starres with all thy might,</L>
<L>Vnto thy hart let praise and pittie in.</L>
<L>This sayd, and more desirous much to crie,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Richard</HI> stayd him, with this rich replie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Captayne, I praise thy warlike eloquence,</L>
<L>And sober Axioms of Philosophie,</L>
<L>But now's no time for schoole points difference,</L>
<L>VVhen Deaths blacke Ensigne threatens miserie;</L>
<L>Yet for thy words sound of such consequence,</L>
<L>Making flight praise, and fight pale obloquie,</L>
<L>Once ere I die, Ile clense my wits from rust,</L>
<L>And proue my flying base, my stay most iust.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="29"/>
<L>Whence shall I flie? from refuge of my fame,</L>
<L>From whom? euen from my Countries mortall foe,</L>
<L>VVhither? but to the dungeon of my shame,</L>
<L>VVhy shall I flie? for feare of happie woe,</L>
<L>VVhat end of flight? to saue vild life by blame,</L>
<L>VVho ist that flies? <HI>Grinuile?</HI> Captayne no,</L>
<L>T'is <HI>England</HI> flies, faire Ile of happines,</L>
<L>And true diuine <HI>Elizas</HI> holynes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Shall then my lifes regard taynt that choyce faire?</L>
<L>First will I perrish in this liquid round,</L>
<L>Neuer shall Sunne-burnt <HI>Spanyards</HI> tongue endeare</L>
<L><HI>Iberian</HI> eares with what shall me confound,</L>
<L>The life I haue, I for my Mistris beare,</L>
<L>Curst were that life, should it her scepter wound,</L>
<L>And trebble cursed be that damned thought,</L>
<L>Which in my minde hath any fayntnes wrought.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="30"/>
<L>Now, for Philosophie defends thy theame,</L>
<L>Euen selfe Philosophie shall arme my stile,</L>
<L>Rich buskin'd <HI>Seneca,</HI> that did declaime,</L>
<L>And first in <HI>Rome</HI> our tragicke pompe compile,</L>
<L>Saith, <HI>Fortitude</HI> is that which in extreame</L>
<L>And certaine hazard all base feares exile:</L>
<L>It guides, saith he, the noble mind from farre,</L>
<L>Through frost, and fier, to conquer honors warre.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Honie-tongd <HI>Tullie,</HI> Mermaid of our eares,</L>
<L>Affirmes no force, can force true <HI>Fortitude,</HI></L>
<L>It with our bodies, no communion beares,</L>
<L>The soule and spyrit, sole doth it include;</L>
<L>It is that part of honestie which reares</L>
<L>The hart to heauen, and euer doth obtrude</L>
<L>Faint feare, and doubt, still taking his delight</L>
<L>In perrills, which exceeds all perrills might.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="30"/>
<L>Patience, Perseuerance, Greatnes, <HI>and</HI> Strong Trust,</L>
<L>These pages are to <HI>Fortitude</HI> their king,</L>
<L><HI>Patience</HI> that suffers, and esteemeth iust</L>
<L>VVhat euer woe, for vertue fortunes bring;</L>
<L><HI>Perseuerance,</HI> holds constant what we must,</L>
<L><HI>Greatnes,</HI> that still effects the greatest thing,</L>
<L>And aimed <HI>Trust,</HI> which neuer can dispaire,</L>
<L>But hopes good hap; how euer fatall deare.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The Roman <HI>Sergius,</HI> hauing lost his hand,</L>
<L>Slew with one hand foure in a single fight,</L>
<L>A thing all reason euer did with-stand,</L>
<L>But that bright <HI>Fortitude</HI> spred forth her light.</L>
<L><HI>Pompey,</HI> by storme held from <HI>th'Italyan</HI> land,</L>
<L>And all his sailours quaking in his sight,</L>
<L>First hoisted saile, and cry'd amidst the strife,</L>
<L>There's neede I goe, no neede to saue my life.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="31"/>
<L><HI>Agis</HI> that guilt the <HI>Lacedemon</HI> streete,</L>
<L>Intending one day battaile with his foes,</L>
<L>By counsaile was repeld, as thing vnmeete,</L>
<L>The enemie beeing ten to one in shoes;</L>
<L>But he reply'd, Tis needfull that his feete</L>
<L>VVhich many leads, should leade to many bloes:</L>
<L>And one being good, an Armie is for ten</L>
<L>Foes to religion, and known naughty men.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>To him that told <HI>Dienecus,</HI> his foes</L>
<L>Couer'd the Sun with darts and armed speares,</L>
<L>Hee made reply, Thy newes is ioy in woes,</L>
<L>Wee'le in the shadow fight, and conquer feares.</L>
<L>And from the <HI>Polands</HI> words my humor floes,</L>
<L>I care for naught but falling of the Spheares.</L>
<L>Thunder afrights the Infants in the schooles,</L>
<L>And threatnings are the conquerers of fooles.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="31"/>
<L>As these, my case is not so desperate,</L>
<L>And yet, then these, my darre shall be no lesse:</L>
<L>If this in them, for fame was wondred at,</L>
<L>Then this in mee, shall my desiers expresse;</L>
<L>Neuer shall <HI>Greece,</HI> nor <HI>Rome,</HI> nor Heathen state,</L>
<L>With shining honor, <HI>Albions</HI> shine depresse,</L>
<L>Though their great circuits yeelds their acts large boūds,</L>
<L>Yet shall they neuer darr for deeper wounds.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And thus resolu'd, deere <HI>Midelton</HI> depart,</L>
<L>Seeke for thy safetie in some better soyle,</L>
<L>Thy stay will be no succour in my smart,</L>
<L>Thy losse will make them boast of better spoyle.</L>
<L>And be assur'd before my last breath part,</L>
<L>Ile make the Sunne, for pittie backe recoyle,</L>
<L>And clothe the sea within a scarlet pale,</L>
<L>Iudge of their death which shall my life exhale.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="32"/>
<L>This ship which now intombs my iealious soule,</L>
<L>Honestlie enuious of aspiring laude,</L>
<L>Is cald <HI>Reuenge,</HI> the scourge which doth controule,</L>
<L>The recreants that <HI>Errors</HI> right applaud,</L>
<L>Shall like her selfe, by name and fame enroule</L>
<L>My spyrits acts, by no <HI>Misfortune</HI> aw'd,</L>
<L>VVithin eternall Bookes of happie deeds,</L>
<L>Vpon whose notes, immortall Vertue reeds.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Say if I perrish, t'was mine honours will,</L>
<L>My Countries loue, religion, and my Queene,</L>
<L>And if that enuie glorie in mine ill,</L>
<L>Say that I dyed, conqu'ring, vnconquered seene.</L>
<L>Say fiftie three strong shyps could not fulfill,</L>
<L>Gainst one poore mayden vessell their foule teene,</L>
<L>But that in spight of death, or miserie,</L>
<L>She fought, and foyld, and scapt captiuitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="32"/>
<L>Replie not <HI>Midelton,</HI> mine eares are closd,</L>
<L>Hie in heauens for-head are my vowes ingrau'd,</L>
<L>I see the banefull Nauie now disclosd,</L>
<L>Begon betime, Fate hath thy fortune sau'd;</L>
<L>To me good starres were neuer yet opposd,</L>
<L>Glorie hath crownd me when I glorie crau'd,</L>
<L>Farwel, and say how euer be my chaunce,</L>
<L>My death at honours wedding learnt to daunce.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This sayd, away sailes <HI>Midelton</HI> with speede,</L>
<L>Sad, heauie, dull, and most disconsolate,</L>
<L>Shedding stout manlie teares at valures deede,</L>
<L>Greeuing the ruine of so great estate;</L>
<L>But <HI>Grinuile,</HI> whose hope euer did exceede,</L>
<L>Making all death in daungers fortunate,</L>
<L>Gan to prouide to quell this great vprore,</L>
<L>Then which the like was neuer heard before.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="33"/>
<L>His fights set vp, and all things fit prepard,</L>
<L>Low on the ballast did he couch his sick,</L>
<L>Being fourscoore ten, in Deaths pale mantle snar'd,</L>
<L>whose want to war did most their strong harts prick.</L>
<L>The hundred, whose more sounder breaths declard</L>
<L>Their soules to enter Deaths gates should not stick,</L>
<L>Hee with diuine words of immortall glorie,</L>
<L>Makes them the wondred actors of this storie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Nothing he left vnsaid that tongue could say,</L>
<L>To breede contempt of death, or hate of thrall,</L>
<L>Honors reward, fame for a famous day,</L>
<L>VVonder of ears, that men halfe gods shall call;</L>
<L>And contrarie, a hopelesse certaine way,</L>
<L>Into a Tyrants damned fists to fall,</L>
<L>VVhere all defame, base thoughts, and infamie,</L>
<L>Shall crowne with shame their heads eternally.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="33"/>
<L>In this great thunder of his valiant speech,</L>
<L>From whence the eares-eyes honors lightning felt,</L>
<L>The <HI>Spanish</HI> Nauie came within the reach</L>
<L>Of Cannon shot, which equallie was delt</L>
<L>On eyther side, each other to impeach;</L>
<L>VVhose volleys made the pittying skyes to melt,</L>
<L>Yet with their noyse, in <HI>Grinuills</HI> hart did frame,</L>
<L>Greater desier, to conquer greater fame.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And now the sunne was past his middle way,</L>
<L>Leaning more louely to his Lemans bed,</L>
<L>And the noones third hower had attacht the day,</L>
<L>VVhen fiftie three gainst one were basely led;</L>
<L>All harts were fierd, and now the deadlie fray,</L>
<L>Began tumultuouslie to ouer-spread</L>
<L>The sea with fier, the Element with smoake</L>
<L>Which gods, &amp; monsters frō their sleepe awoake.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="34"/>
<L>In foure great battailes marcht the <HI>Spanish</HI> hoast,</L>
<L>The first of <HI>Siuill,</HI> led in two great squares,</L>
<L>Both which with courage, more then can be most,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Richard</HI> forst to giue him way with cares;</L>
<L>And as the Sea-men terme it in our coast,</L>
<L>They sprang their luffe, and vnder lee declares</L>
<L>Their manie forces feebled by this one,</L>
<L>Whose thoughts, saue him, are rightly due to none.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And now he stands amidst the thickest throngs,</L>
<L>VValld round with wooden Castels on the waue,</L>
<L>Fiftie three Tygers greedie in their wrongs,</L>
<L>Besiedge the princlie Lion in his caue:</L>
<L>Nothing sees <HI>Grinuile</HI> which to hope belongs,</L>
<L>All things are fled that any hap could saue;</L>
<L>Bright day is darkned by incurtaind light,</L>
<L>And nothing visits them but Canons night.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="34"/>
<L>Then vp to heauen he lifts his loftie hart,</L>
<L>And cryes, old <HI>Solon,</HI> I am happy made.</L>
<L>All earthie thoughts cleane frō his spirits part,</L>
<L><HI>Vertue</HI> and <HI>Valure</HI> all his sences lade,</L>
<L>His foes too fewe, too strong he holds his part,</L>
<L>Now doth he wish for millions to inuade,</L>
<L>For beeing conquerer, he would conquer all,</L>
<L>Or conquerd, with immortall honor fall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Neuer fell hayle thicker then bullets flew,</L>
<L>Neuer show'rd drops faster then showring blowes,</L>
<L>Liu'd all the <HI>Woorthies,</HI> all yet neuer knew</L>
<L>So great resolue in so great certaine woes;</L>
<L>Had <HI>Fame</HI> told <HI>Caesar</HI> what of this was true,</L>
<L>His Senate-murdred spirite would haue rose,</L>
<L>And with faire honors enuie wondred then,</L>
<L>Cursing mortalitie in mightie men.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="35"/>
<L>VVhilst thus affliction turmoyld in this brall,</L>
<L>And <HI>Grinuile</HI> still imployd his Actor death,</L>
<L>The great <HI>San-phillip,</HI> which all <HI>Spayne</HI> did call</L>
<L>Th'vnuanquisht ship, <HI>Iberias</HI> soule and faith,</L>
<L>Whose mountaine hugenes more was tearmd then tall,</L>
<L>Being twice a thousand tuns as rumor saith,</L>
<L>Came rushing in, becalming <HI>Grinuiles</HI> sailes,</L>
<L>Whose courage grew, the more his fortune failes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Hotlie on eyther side was lightning sent,</L>
<L>And steeled thunder bolts dinge men to hell,</L>
<L>Vnweldie <HI>Phillip,</HI> backt with millions lent,</L>
<L>VVorse cracks of thunder then on <HI>Phaeton</HI> fell,</L>
<L>That with the dayes fier fierd the Element;</L>
<L>And why? because within her ribs did dwell,</L>
<L>More store of shot and great artillarie,</L>
<L>Then might haue seru'd the worlds great victorie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="35"/>
<L>Three tire of Cannon lodg'd on eyther side,</L>
<L>And in each tire, eleuen stronglie lay,</L>
<L>Eyght in her chase, that shot forth right did bide,</L>
<L>And in her sterne, twice eight that howerlie play;</L>
<L>Shee lesse great shot, in infinets did hide,</L>
<L>All which were Agents for a dismall day.</L>
<L>But poore <HI>Reuenge,</HI> lesse rich, and not so great,</L>
<L>Aunswerd her cuffe for cuffe, and threat for threat.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Anon they graple eyther to the other,</L>
<L>As doth the ban-dogge with the Martins skinne,</L>
<L>And then the wombe of <HI>Phillip</HI> did vncouer,</L>
<L>Eight hundred Souldiers, which the fight beginne:</L>
<L>These board Sir <HI>Richard</HI> &amp; with thronging smother</L>
<L>The day, the ayre, the time, and neuer linne,</L>
<L>But by their entrance did instruct eight more,</L>
<L>To doe the like, on each side foure, and foure.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="36"/>
<L>Thus in one moment was our Knight assaild,</L>
<L>With one huge <HI>Argosie,</HI> and eight great ships,</L>
<L>But all in vaine, their powers naught preuaild,</L>
<L>For the <HI>Reuenge,</HI> her Canon loud-dogs ships,</L>
<L>VVhose bruzing teeth, so much the <HI>Phillip</HI> quaild,</L>
<L>That foundring in the greedie maine, he dips</L>
<L>His damned bodie in his watrie tombe,</L>
<L>Wrapt with dishonour in the Oceans wombe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The other eight, fighting, were likewise foild,</L>
<L>And driuen perforce vnto a vild retraite,</L>
<L>None durst abide, but all with shame recoild,</L>
<L>VVhilst <HI>Valures</HI> selfe, set <HI>Grinuile</HI> in her seate;</L>
<L>Onely <HI>Don Luis Saint Iohn,</HI> seeing spoild,</L>
<L>His Countries honour by this strange defaite,</L>
<L>Single encountred <HI>Grinuile</HI> in the fight,</L>
<L>Who quicklie sent his soule to endlesse night.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="36"/>
<L><HI>George de Prunaria,</HI> a Spanish Knight,</L>
<L>Euer held valiant in dispight of fate,</L>
<L>Seconded <HI>Luis,</HI> and with mortall might,</L>
<L>VVrit on Sir <HI>Richards</HI> target souldiers hate,</L>
<L>Till <HI>Grinuile,</HI> wakned with his loud rung fight,</L>
<L>Dispatcht his soules course vnto <HI>Plutos</HI> gate;</L>
<L>And after these two, sent in post all those</L>
<L>Which came within his mercie or his blowes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>By this, the sunne had spred his golden locks,</L>
<L>Vpon the pale greene carpet of the sea,</L>
<L>And opned wide the scarlet dore which locks,</L>
<L>The easefull euening from the labouring day;</L>
<L>Now Night began to leape from iron Rocks,</L>
<L>And whip her rustie wagon through the way,</L>
<L>VVhilst all the <HI>Spanish</HI> host stoode maz'd in sight,</L>
<L>None darring to assayle a second fight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="37"/>
<L>VVhen <HI>Don Alfonso,</HI> Generall of the warre,</L>
<L>Saw all his Nauie with one ship controld,</L>
<L>Hee toare his hayre, and loudlie cryd from farre,</L>
<L>For honour <HI>Spanyards,</HI> and for shame be bold;</L>
<L>Awaken Vertue, say her slumbers marre</L>
<L><HI>Iberias</HI> auncient valure, and infold</L>
<L>Her wondred pulssance, and her glorious deeds,</L>
<L>In cowards habit, and ignoble weeds.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Fie, that the spyrit of a single man,</L>
<L>Should contradict innumerable wills,</L>
<L>Fie, that infinitiues of forces can,</L>
<L>Nor may effect what one conceit fulfills;</L>
<L>VVoe to the wombe, ceaselesse the teats I ban,</L>
<L>That cherrisht life, which all our liues ioyes kills;</L>
<L>VVoe to our selues, our fortunes, and our minds,</L>
<L>Agast and scarrd, with whistling of the winds.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="37"/>
<L>See how he tryumphes in dispight of death,</L>
<L><HI>Promethean</HI> like, laden with liuing fier,</L>
<L>And in his glorie spits disdainfull breath,</L>
<L>Loathing the basenes of our backe retire;</L>
<L>Euen now me thinks in our disgrace he saith,</L>
<L>Foes to your fames, why make you Fate a lyer,</L>
<L>When heauen and she haue giuen into your hand,</L>
<L>VVhat all the world can neuer backe demaund?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Say that the God of <HI>Warre;</HI> Father of Chiualrie,</L>
<L>The <HI>Worthies, Heroes,</HI> all fam'd Conquerours,</L>
<L><HI>Centaurs, Gyants,</HI> victorious <HI>Victorie,</HI></L>
<L>VVere all this <HI>Grinuils</HI> hart-sworne paramours,</L>
<L>Yet should we fightlesse let our shyps force flie;</L>
<L>Well might we crush his keele W<SUP>t</SUP> rocklike powers,</L>
<L>And him with them ore-whelme into the maine,</L>
<L>Courage then harts, fetch honour backe againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="38"/>
<L>Heere shame, the fretting canker of the mind,</L>
<L>That fiers the face with fuell from the hart,</L>
<L>Fearing his weapons weakenes, est assignd</L>
<L>To desperate hardines his cōfounding dart,</L>
<L>And now the <HI>Spanyards</HI> made through words stone blind,</L>
<L>Desperate by shame, ashamd dispaire should part,</L>
<L>like dāned scritchowles, chimes to dead mēs hours,</L>
<L>Make vowes to fight, till fight all liues deuours.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And now the tragicke sceane of death begins,</L>
<L>Acts of the night, deeds of the ouglie darke,</L>
<L>VVhen Furies brands gaue light to furious sins,</L>
<L>And gastlie silence gaping wounds did marke;</L>
<L>Sing sadlie then my Muse (teares pittie wins)</L>
<L>Yet mount thy wings beyond the mornings Larke,</L>
<L>And wanting thunder, with thy lightnings might</L>
<L>Split eares that heares the dole of this sad night.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="38"/>
<L>The fier of <HI>Spaynes</HI> pride, quencht by <HI>Grinuils</HI> sword,</L>
<L><HI>Alfonso</HI> reinkindles with his tong,</L>
<L>And sets a batelesse edge, ground by his word,</L>
<L>Vpon their blunt harts feebled by the strong,</L>
<L>Loe animated now, they all accord,</L>
<L>To die, or ende deaths conflict held so long;</L>
<L>And thus resolud, too greedelie assay</L>
<L>His death, like hounds that hold the Hart at bay.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Blacker then night, more terrible then hell,</L>
<L>Louder then thunder, sharper then <HI>Phoebus</HI> steele,</L>
<L>Vnder whose wounds the ouglie <HI>Python</HI> fell,</L>
<L>Were bullets mantles, clowding the haplesse keele,</L>
<L>The slaughtered cryes, the words the canons tell,</L>
<L>And those which make euen rocky Mountains reele,</L>
<L>And thicker then in sunne are Atomies,</L>
<L>Flew bullets, fier, and slaughtered dead mens cries.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="39"/>
<L>At this remorsles Dirgie for the dead,</L>
<L>The siluer Moone, dread Soueraigne of the deepe,</L>
<L>That with the floods fills vp her horned head,</L>
<L>And by her waine the wayning ebbs doth keepe:</L>
<L>Taught by the Fat's how destenie was led,</L>
<L>Bids all the starres pull in their beames and weepe:</L>
<L>For twas vnfit, chast hallowed eyes should see</L>
<L>Honour confounded by impietie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Then to the night she giues all soueraigne power,</L>
<L>Th'eternall mourner for the dayes diuorce,</L>
<L>Who drowned in her owne harts killing shower,</L>
<L>Viewes others torments with a sad remorse.</L>
<L>This flintie Princesse, ayme cryes to the hower,</L>
<L>On which to looke, kinde eies no force could force.</L>
<L>And yet the sight, her dull hart so offended,</L>
<L>That from her sight a foggie dewe descended.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="39"/>
<L>Now on our Knight, raines yron, sword, and fiers,</L>
<L>Iron wrapt in smoke, swords bath'd in smoking blood,</L>
<L>Fiers, furies king, in blood &amp; smoke aspiers</L>
<L>The consumation of all liuing good;</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Grinuile,</HI> with like Agents like expires</L>
<L>His foe-mens dat's, and euermore withstood</L>
<L>Th'assaults of death, and ruins of the warre,</L>
<L>Hoping the splendour of some luckie starre.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>On eyther side him, still two <HI>Gallions</HI> lay,</L>
<L>VVhich with continuall boardings nurst the fight,</L>
<L>Two great <HI>Armados,</HI> howrelie plow'd their way,</L>
<L>And by assault, made knowne repellesse might.</L>
<L>Those which could not come neere vnto the fray,</L>
<L>Aloofe discharg'd their volleys gainst our Knight.</L>
<L>And when y<SUP>t</SUP> one shrunk back, beat with disgrace,</L>
<L>An other instantly supply'd the place.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="40"/>
<L>So that their resting, restlesse him containd,</L>
<L>And theyr supplies, deny'd him to supply:</L>
<L>The <HI>Hydra</HI> of their mightines ordaind</L>
<L>New spoile for death, when old did wounded lie:</L>
<L>But hee, <HI>Herculian</HI>-like one state retaind,</L>
<L>One to triumph, or one for all to die.</L>
<L>Heauen had onelie lent him but one hart,</L>
<L>That hart one thought, that thought no feare of smart.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And now the night grew neere her middle line,</L>
<L>Youthfully lustie in her strongest age,</L>
<L>VVhen one of <HI>Spaynes</HI> great <HI>Gallions</HI> did repine,</L>
<L>That one should many vnto death ingage,</L>
<L>And therefore with her force, halfe hold diuine,</L>
<L>At once euaporats her mortall rage,</L>
<L>Till powerfull <HI>Grinuile,</HI> yeelding power a tombe,</L>
<L>Splyt her, and sunck her in the salt waues wombe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="40"/>
<L>VVhen <HI>Cutino,</HI> the Hulks great Admirall,</L>
<L>Saw that huge Vessell drencht within the surge,</L>
<L>Enuie and shame tyerd vpon his gall,</L>
<L>And for reuenge a thousand meanes doth vrge:</L>
<L>But <HI>Grinuile,</HI> perfect in destructions fall,</L>
<L>His mischiefes with like miseries doth scourge;</L>
<L>And renting with a shot his wooden tower,</L>
<L>Made <HI>Neptunes</HI> liquid armes his all deuouer.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>These two ore-whelm'd, <HI>Siuills Ascention</HI> came,</L>
<L>A famous ship, well man'd, and strongly drest,</L>
<L><HI>Vindicta</HI> from her Cannons mouthes doth flame,</L>
<L>And more then any, our dread Knight oprest:</L>
<L>Much hurt shee did, many shee wounded lame,</L>
<L>And <HI>Valurs</HI> selfe, her valiant acts confest.</L>
<L>Yet in the end, (for warre of none takes keepe)</L>
<L><HI>Grinuile</HI> sunck her within the watry deepe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="41"/>
<L>An other great <HI>Armado,</HI> brusd and beat,</L>
<L>Sunck neere S. <HI>Michaels</HI> road, with thought to scape,</L>
<L>And one that by her men more choicely set,</L>
<L>Beeing craz'd and widow'd of her comly shape,</L>
<L>Ran gainst the shore, to pay <HI>Ill-chaunce</HI> her debt,</L>
<L>VVho desolate for desolations gape:</L>
<L>Yet these confounded, were not mist at all,</L>
<L>For new supplies made new the aged brall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This while on <HI>Grinuile</HI> ceazed no amaze,</L>
<L>No wonder, dread, nor base astonishment,</L>
<L>But true resolue, and valurs sacred blaze,</L>
<L>The crowne of heauen, and starrie ornament</L>
<L>Deckt his diuine part, and from thence did raze</L>
<L>Affects of earth, or earths intendiment.</L>
<L>And in this broyle, as cheerefull was his sight,</L>
<L>As <HI>Ioues,</HI> imbracing <HI>Danae</HI> by night.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="41"/>
<L>Looke how a wanton Bridegroome in the morne,</L>
<L>Busilie labours to make glad the day,</L>
<L>And at the noone, with wings of courage borne,</L>
<L>Recourts his bride with dauncing and with play,</L>
<L>Vntill the night which holds meane blisse in scorne,</L>
<L>By action kills imaginations sway,</L>
<L>And then, euen then, gluts &amp; cōfounds his thought,</L>
<L>VVith all the sweets, conceit or Nature wrought,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Euen so our Knight the bridegroome vnto <HI>Fame,</HI></L>
<L>Toild in this battailes morning with vnrest,</L>
<L>At noone triumph'd, &amp; daunst, &amp; made his game,</L>
<L>That vertue by no death could be deprest;</L>
<L>But when the night of his loues longings came,</L>
<L>Euen then his intelectuall soule confest</L>
<L>All other ioyes imaginarie were</L>
<L>Honour vnconquerd, heauen &amp; earth held deare.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="42"/>
<L>The bellowing shotte which wakened dead mens swounds,</L>
<L>As <HI>Dorian</HI> musick, sweetned in his cares,</L>
<L>Ryuers of blood, issuing from fountaine wounds,</L>
<L>Hee pytties, but augments not with his teares,</L>
<L>The flaming fier which mercilesse abounds,</L>
<L>Hee not so much as masking torches feares,</L>
<L>The dolefull Eccho of the soules halfe dying,</L>
<L>Quicken his courage in their banefull crying.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>VVhen foule <HI>Misfortune</HI> houering on a Rock,</L>
<L>(The stonie girdle of the <HI>Florean</HI> Ile,)</L>
<L>Had seene this conflict, and the fearefull shock,</L>
<L>VVhich all the <HI>Spanysh</HI> mischeifes did compile,</L>
<L>And saw how conquest licklie was to mock</L>
<L>The hope of <HI>Spayne,</HI> and fauster her exile,</L>
<L>Immortall she, came downe her selfe to fight,</L>
<L>And doe what else no mortall creature might.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="42"/>
<L>And as she flew the midnights waking starre,</L>
<L>Sad <HI>Cassiopea,</HI> with a heauie cheare</L>
<L>Pusht forth her forehead, to make known frō farre,</L>
<L>VVhat time the dryrie dole of earth drew neare,</L>
<L>But when shee saw <HI>Misfortune</HI> arm'd in warre,</L>
<L>VVith teares she blinds her eyes, and clouds y<SUP>e</SUP> ayre,</L>
<L>And asks the gods, why <HI>Fortune</HI> fights with man?</L>
<L>They say, to doe, what else no creature can.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>O why should such immortall enuie dwell,</L>
<L>In the inclosures of eternall mould?</L>
<L>Let Gods with Gods, and men with men rebell,</L>
<L>Vnequall warres t'vnequall shame is sould;</L>
<L>But for this damned deede came shee from hell,</L>
<L>And <HI>Ioue</HI> is sworne, to doe what dest'nie would,</L>
<L>VVeepe then my pen, the tell-tale of our woe,</L>
<L>And curse the fount frō whence our sorrows flow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="43"/>
<L>Now, now, <HI>Misfortune</HI> fronts our Knight in armes,</L>
<L>And casts her venome through the <HI>Spanysh</HI> hoast,</L>
<L>Shee salues the dead, and all the lyuing warmes</L>
<L>With vitall enuie, brought from <HI>Plutos</HI> coast;</L>
<L>Yet all in vaine, all workes not <HI>Grinuils</HI> harmes;</L>
<L>VVhich seene, shee smiles, and yet with rage imbost</L>
<L>Saith to her selfe, since men are all too weake,</L>
<L>Behold a goddesse shall thy lifes twine breake.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>VVith that shee taks a Musket in her hand,</L>
<L>Raft from a dying Souldiour newlie slaine,</L>
<L>And ayming where th' vncōquered Knight did stand,</L>
<L>Dischargd it through his bodie, and in twaine</L>
<L>Deuids the euer holie nuptiall band,</L>
<L>Which twixt his soule, &amp; worlds part shold remaine,</L>
<L>Had not his hart, stronger then <HI>Fortunes</HI> will,</L>
<L>Held life perforce to scorne <HI>Misfortunes</HI> ill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="43"/>
<L>The bubling wound from whence his blood distild,</L>
<L>Mourn'd to let fall the hallowed drops to ground,</L>
<L>And like a iealious loue by riuall illd,</L>
<L>Sucks in the sacred moisture through the wound;</L>
<L>But he, which felt deaths fatall doome fulfilld,</L>
<L>Grew fiercer valiant, and did all confound,</L>
<L>VVas not a <HI>Spanyard</HI> durst abord him rest,</L>
<L>After he felt his deaths wound in his brest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Hundreds on hundreds, dead on the maymed fall,</L>
<L>Maymed on sounde, sound in them selues lye slaine,</L>
<L>Blest was the first that to his ship could crall,</L>
<L>For wounded, he wounds multituds againe;</L>
<L>No sacrifice, but sacrifice of all,</L>
<L>Could stay his swords oblations vnto paine,</L>
<L>Nor in <HI>Phillippie,</HI> fell for <HI>Caesars</HI> death,</L>
<L>Soules thicker then for <HI>Grinuils</HI> wasting breath.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="44"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="44"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="45"/>
<L>The <HI>Nemian</HI> Lyon, <HI>Aramanthian</HI> Bore,</L>
<L>The <HI>Hircanian</HI> Tyger, nor the <HI>Cholcean</HI> Bulls,</L>
<L>Neuer extended rage with such vprore,</L>
<L>Nor in their brests mad monstrous furie lulls;</L>
<L>Now might they learne, that euer learnt before,</L>
<L>Wrath at our Knight, which all wrath disanulls,</L>
<L>For slauish death, his hands commaunded more,</L>
<L>Then Lyon, Tyger, Bull, or angrie Bore.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Had <HI>Pompey</HI> in <HI>Pharsalia</HI> held his thought,</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> had neuer wept vpon his head,</L>
<L>Had <HI>Anthonie</HI> at <HI>Actiome</HI> like him fought,</L>
<L><HI>Augustus</HI> teares had neuer drownd him dead,</L>
<L>Had braue <HI>Renaldo, Grinuiles</HI> puissance bought,</L>
<L><HI>Angelica</HI> from Fraunce had neuer fled,</L>
<L>Nor madded <HI>Rowland</HI> with inconstancie,</L>
<L>But rather slayne him wanting victorie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="45"/>
<L>Before a storme flew neuer Doues so fast,</L>
<L>As <HI>Spanyards</HI> from the furie of his fist,</L>
<L>The stout <HI>Reuenge,</HI> about whose forlorne wast,</L>
<L>Whilome so many in their moods persist,</L>
<L>Now all alone, naught but the sourge imbrast,</L>
<L>Her foes from handie combats cleane desist;</L>
<L>Yet still incirkling her within their powers,</L>
<L>From farre sent shot, as thick as winters showers.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Anger,</HI> and <HI>Enuie,</HI> enemies to <HI>Life,</HI></L>
<L>Strong smouldring <HI>Heate</HI> &amp; noisom stink of <HI>Smoke,</HI></L>
<L>With ouer-labouring <HI>Toyle, Deaths</HI> ouglie wife,</L>
<L>These all accord with <HI>Grinuiles</HI> wounded stroke,</L>
<L>To end his liues date by their ciuell strife,</L>
<L>And him vnto a blessed state inyoke,</L>
<L>But he repeld them whilst repell he might.</L>
<L>Till fainting power, was tane from power to fight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="46"/>
<L>Then downe he sat, and beat his manlie brest,</L>
<L>Not mourning death, but want of meanes to die;</L>
<L>Those which suruiu'd coragiouslie he blest,</L>
<L>Making them gods for god-like victorie;</L>
<L>Not full twice twentie soules aliue did rest,</L>
<L>Of which the most were mangled cruellie,</L>
<L>Yet still, whilst words could speake, or signes could show,</L>
<L>From death he maks eternall life to grow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The Maister-gunner, which beheld his eyes,</L>
<L>Dart fier gainst death triumphant in his face,</L>
<L>Came to sustaine him, and with courage cryes,</L>
<L>How fares my Knight? worlds glory, martiall grace?</L>
<L>Thine honour, former honours ouer-flyes,</L>
<L>And vnto <HI>Heaven</HI> and <HI>Vertue</HI> bids the bace;</L>
<L>Cheere then thy soule, &amp; if deaths wounding paine it,</L>
<L><HI>Abrahams</HI> faire bosome lyes to entertaine it.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="46"/>
<L>Maister, he sayes, euen heers the opned dore,</L>
<L>Through which my spirit bridgroome like must ride,</L>
<L>(And then he bard his wounded brest all gore)</L>
<L>To court the blessed virgine Lambe his bride,</L>
<L>VVhose innoncence the worlds afflictions bore,</L>
<L>Streaming diuine blood from his sliced side,</L>
<L>And to that heauen my soule with courage flyes,</L>
<L>Because vnconquerd, conquering it dyes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But yet, replyd the Maister once againe,</L>
<L>Great vertue of our vertues, striue with Fate,</L>
<L>Yeeld not a minute vnto death, retaine</L>
<L>Life like thy glorie, made to wonder at,</L>
<L>This wounds recouerie well may entertaine</L>
<L>A double triumph to thy conquering state,</L>
<L>And make thee liue immortall Angell blest,</L>
<L>Pleaseth thee suffer it be searcht and drest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="47"/>
<L>Descend then gentle <HI>Grinuile</HI> downe below,</L>
<L>Into my Cabbin for a breathing space,</L>
<L>In thee there let thy Surgion stanch our woe,</L>
<L>Giuing recuer to thee, our wounded case,</L>
<L>Our breaths, frō thy breaths fountaine gently flow,</L>
<L>If it be dried, our currents loose their grace:</L>
<L>Then both for vs, and thee, and for the best,</L>
<L>Descend, to haue thy wound bound vp &amp; drest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Maister, reply'd the Knight, since last the sunne</L>
<L>Lookt from the hiest period of the sky,</L>
<L>Giuing a signall of the dayes mid noone,</L>
<L>Vnto this hower of midnight, valiantly,</L>
<L>From of this vpper deck I haue not runne,</L>
<L>But fought, and freed, and welcomd victorie,</L>
<L>Then now to giue newe couert to mine head,</L>
<L>VVere to reuiue our foes halfe conquered.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="47"/>
<L>Thus with contrarie arguments they warre,</L>
<L>Diuers in their opinions and their speech,</L>
<L>One seeking means, th'other a will to darre,</L>
<L>Yet both one end, and one desire reach:</L>
<L>Both to keepe honour liuing, plyant are,</L>
<L>Hee by his fame, and he by skilfull leach,</L>
<L>At length, the Maister winnes, and hath procurd</L>
<L>The Knight discend, to haue his woundings curd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Downe when he was, and had display'd the port</L>
<L>Through which his life was martching vp to heauen,</L>
<L>Albe the mortall taint all cuers retort,</L>
<L>Yet was his Surgion not of hope bereuen,</L>
<L>But giues him valiant speech of lifes resort,</L>
<L>Sayes, longer dayes his longer fame shall euen,</L>
<L>And for the meanes of his recouerie,</L>
<L>He finds both arte and possibilitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="48"/>
<L><HI>Misfortune</HI> hearing this presage of life,</L>
<L>(For what but chimes within immortall eares)</L>
<L>VVithin her selfe kindles a home-bred strife,</L>
<L>And for those words y<SUP>e</SUP> Surgions doomes day swears</L>
<L>VVith that, her charg'd peece (<HI>Atropos</HI> keene knife,)</L>
<L>Againe she takes, and leueld with dispairs,</L>
<L>Sent a shrill bullet through the Surgions head,</L>
<L>which thence, through <HI>Grinuils</HI> tēples like was led.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Downe fel the Surgion, hope and helpe was rest,</L>
<L>His death gaue manumition to his soule,</L>
<L><HI>Misfortune</HI> smyld, and euen then shee left</L>
<L>The mournfull Ocean, mourner for this dole;</L>
<L>Away shee flyes, for all was now bereft,</L>
<L>Both hope and helpe, for life to win deaths gole;</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Grinuile</HI> vnamaz'd, with constant faith,</L>
<L>Laughing dispisd the second stroke of death.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="48"/>
<L>VVhat foole (saith he) ads to the Sea a drop,</L>
<L>Lends <HI>Etna</HI> sparks, or angry stormes his wind?</L>
<L>VVho burnes the roote whē lightning fiers the top?</L>
<L>VVho vnto hell, can worse then hell combind?</L>
<L>Pale hungry Death, thy greedy longings stop,</L>
<L>Hope of long life is banefull to my mind:</L>
<L>Yet hate not life, but lothe captiuitie,</L>
<L>Where rests no trust to purchase victorie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Then vp he came with feeble pace againe,</L>
<L>Strength frō his blood, blood frō his woūds descen∣ding,</L>
<L>Saies, here I liu'd, &amp; here wil I sustaine,</L>
<L>The worst of Deaths worst, by my fame defending,</L>
<L>And then he fell to warre with might and maine,</L>
<L>Valure on death most valiantly depending,</L>
<L>And thus continued aye coragiously,</L>
<L>Vntill the day chast shadowes from the sky.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="49"/>
<L>But when the mornings dewie locks drunke vp</L>
<L>A mistie moysture from the Oceans face,</L>
<L>Then might he see the source of sorrowes cup,</L>
<L>Plainly prefigur'd in that hatefull place:</L>
<L>And all the miseries that mortals sup</L>
<L>From their great Grandsire <HI>Adams</HI> band, disgrace;</L>
<L>For all that did in circle him, was his foe,</L>
<L>And that incircled, modell of true woe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>His masts were broken, and his tackle torne,</L>
<L>His vpper worke hew'd downe into the Sea,</L>
<L>Naught of his ship aboue the sourge was borne,</L>
<L>But euen leueld with the Ocean lay,</L>
<L>Onely the ships foundation (yet that worne)</L>
<L>Remaind a trophey in that mighty fray;</L>
<L>Nothing at all aboue the head remained,</L>
<L>Either for couert, or that force maintained.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="49"/>
<L>Powder for shot, was spent and wasted cleane,</L>
<L>Scarce seene a corne to charge a peece withall,</L>
<L>All her pykes broken, halfe of his best men slaine,</L>
<L>The rest sore wounded, on Deaths Agents call,</L>
<L>On th'other side, her foes in ranks remaine,</L>
<L>Displaying multitudes, and store of all</L>
<L>VVhat euer might auaile for victorie,</L>
<L>Had they not wanted harts true valiancie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>When <HI>Grinuile</HI> saw his desperate drierie case,</L>
<L>Meerely dispoyld of all succes-full thought,</L>
<L>Hee calls before him all within the place,</L>
<L>The Maister, Maister-gunner, and them taught</L>
<L>Rules of true hardiment to purchase grace;</L>
<L>Showes thē the end their trauailes toile had bought,</L>
<L>How sweet it is, swift <HI>Fame</HI> to ouer-goe,</L>
<L>How vile to diue in captiue ouerthrow.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="50"/>
<L>Gallants (he saith) since three a clock last noone,</L>
<L>Vntill this morning, fifteene howers by course,</L>
<L>We haue maintaind stoute warre, and still vndoone</L>
<L>Our foes assaults, and driue them to the worse,</L>
<L>Fifteene <HI>Armados</HI> boardings haue not wonne</L>
<L>Content or ease, but beene repeld by force,</L>
<L>Eight hundred Cannon shot against our side,</L>
<L>Haue not our harts in cowards colours died.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Not fifteene thousand men araungd in fight,</L>
<L>And fifteene howers lent them to atchiue,</L>
<L>VVith fifty three great ships of boundlesse might,</L>
<L>Haue had or meanes or prowesse to contriue</L>
<L>The fall of one, which mayden vertue dight,</L>
<L>Kept in despight of <HI>Spanish</HI> force aliue.</L>
<L>Then list to mee you imps of memorie,</L>
<L>Borne to assume to immortalitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="50"/>
<L>Sith loosing, we vnlost keepe strong our praise,</L>
<L>And make our glories, gaynours by our ends,</L>
<L>Let not the hope of howers (for tedious dayes</L>
<L>Vnto our liues no larger circuite lends)</L>
<L>Confound our wondred actions and assayes,</L>
<L>VVhereon the sweete of mortall eares depends,</L>
<L>But as we liue by wills victorious,</L>
<L>So let vs die victours of them and vs.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>VVee that haue mercilesse cut Mercies wings,</L>
<L>And muffeld pittie in deaths mistie vale,</L>
<L>Let vs implore no mercie; pittyings,</L>
<L>But from our God, deere fauour to exhale</L>
<L>Our soules to heauen, where all the Angells rings</L>
<L>Renowne of vs, and our deepe tragick tale;</L>
<L>Let vs that cannot liue, yet liue to dye,</L>
<L>Vnthrald by men, fit tropheys for the skye.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="51"/>
<L>And thus resolu'd since other meane is reft,</L>
<L>Sweet Maister-gunner, split our keele in twaine,</L>
<L>We cannot liue, whom hope of life hath left,</L>
<L>Dying, our deaths more glorious liues retaine,</L>
<L>Let not our ship, of shame and foile bereft,</L>
<L>Vnto our foe-men for a prize remaine;</L>
<L>Sinke her, and sinking with the <HI>Greeke</HI> wee'le cry,</L>
<L>Best not to be, or beeing soone to dye.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Scarse had his words tane wings frō his deare tong,</L>
<L>But the stout Maister-gunner, euer ritch</L>
<L>In heauenlie valure and repulsing wrong,</L>
<L>Proud that his hands by action might inritch</L>
<L>His name and nation with a worthie song,</L>
<L>Tow'rd his hart higher then Eagles pitch,</L>
<L>And instantlie indeuours to effect</L>
<L><HI>Grinuiles</HI> desier, by ending Deaths defect.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="51"/>
<L>But th'other Maister, and the other Mat's,</L>
<L>Disented from the honour of their minds,</L>
<L>And humbly praid the Knight to rue their stat's,</L>
<L>VVhom miserie to no such mischeife binds;</L>
<L>To him th'aleadge great reasons, and dilat's</L>
<L>Their foes amazements, whom their valures blinds,</L>
<L>And maks more eager t'entertaine a truce,</L>
<L>Then they to offer words for warres excuse.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>They show him diuers gallant men of might,</L>
<L>VVhose wounds not mortall, hope gaue of recuer,</L>
<L>For their saks sue they to diuorce this night</L>
<L>Of desperate chaunce, calld vnto Deaths black lure,</L>
<L>Their lēgthned liues, their coūtries cares might right,</L>
<L>And to their Prince they might good hopes assure.</L>
<L>Thē qd. the Captaine, (deere Knight) do not spill,</L>
<L>The liues whom gods and Fat's seeke not to kill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="52"/>
<L>And where thou sayst the <HI>Spanyards</HI> shall not braue,</L>
<L>T'haue tane one ship due to our virgin Queene,</L>
<L>O know, that they, nor all the world can saue,</L>
<L>This wounded Barke, whose like no age hath seene,</L>
<L>Sixe foote shee leaks in hold, three shot beneath the waue,</L>
<L>All whose repaire so insufficient beene,</L>
<L>That when the Sea shall angrie worke begin,</L>
<L>Shee cannot chuse but sinke and dye therein.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Besides, the wounds and brusings which she beares,</L>
<L>Are such, so manie, so incurable,</L>
<L>As to remoue her from this place of feares,</L>
<L>No force, no wit, no meane, nor man is able;</L>
<L>Then since that peace prostrate to vs repaires,</L>
<L>Vnlesse our selues, our selues make miserable,</L>
<L><HI>Herculeen</HI> Knight, for pittie, pittie lend,</L>
<L>No fame consists in wilfull desperat end.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="52"/>
<L>These words with emphasis and action spent,</L>
<L>Mou'd not Sir <HI>Richard,</HI> but inrag'd him more,</L>
<L>To bow or yeeld, his hart would neare relent,</L>
<L>Hee still impungs all thought of lifes restore;</L>
<L>The Maister-gunner, euer doth consent</L>
<L>To act his wish, swearing in beds of gore</L>
<L>Death is most louelie, sweete and amiable,</L>
<L>But captiu'd life for foulenes admirable.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The Captayne, seeing words could take no place,</L>
<L>Turnes backe from them vnto the liuing few,</L>
<L>Expounds what pittie is, what victors grace;</L>
<L>Bids them them selues, them selues in kindnes rew,</L>
<L>Peace if they please, will kindlie them imbrace,</L>
<L>And they may liue, from whom warres glory grew;</L>
<L>But if they will to desperate end consent,</L>
<L>Their guilty soules too late shall mourne repent.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="53"/>
<L>The sillie men, which sought but liuing ioyes,</L>
<L>Cryes to the Captaine for an honord truce,</L>
<L>Life they desire, yet no life that destroyes</L>
<L>Their wonne renownes, but such as might excuse</L>
<L>Their woes, their wounds, and all what els anoyes</L>
<L>Beautie of laude, for other they refuse;</L>
<L>All which the Captaine swears they shal obtaine,</L>
<L>Because their foes, in doubtfull states remaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>O when <HI>Sir Richard</HI> saw them start aside,</L>
<L>More chaynd to life then to a glorius graue,</L>
<L>And those whom hee so oft in dangers tryde,</L>
<L>Now trembling seeke their hatefull liues to saue,</L>
<L>Sorrow and rage, shame, and his honors pride,</L>
<L>Choking his soule, madly compeld him raue,</L>
<L>Vntill his rage with vigor did confound</L>
<L>His heauie hart, and left him in a swound.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="53"/>
<L>The Maister-gunner, likewise seeing Fate</L>
<L>Bridle his fortune, and his will to die,</L>
<L>With his sharpe sword sought to set ope the gate,</L>
<L>By which his soule might from his body flie,</L>
<L>Had not his freends perforce preseru'd his state,</L>
<L>And lockt him in his Cabbin, safe to lie,</L>
<L>Whilst others swarm'd where haplesse <HI>Grinuile</HI> lay,</L>
<L>By cryes recalling life, late runne away.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In this too restlesse turmoile of vnrest,</L>
<L>The poore <HI>Reuenges</HI> Maister stole away,</L>
<L>And to the <HI>Spanish</HI> Admirall adrest</L>
<L>The dolefull tidings of this mournfull day,</L>
<L>(The <HI>Spanish</HI> Admirall who then oprest,</L>
<L>Houering with doubt, not daring t'end the fray,)</L>
<L>And pleads for truce, w<SUP>t</SUP> souldiour-like submission,</L>
<L>Anexing to his words a straight condition.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="54"/>
<L><HI>Alfonso,</HI> willing to giue end to armes,</L>
<L>For well he knew <HI>Grinuile</HI> would neuer yeild,</L>
<L>Albe his power stoode like vnnumbred swarmes,</L>
<L>Yet daring not on stricter tearmes to build,</L>
<L>Hee offers all what may alay their harmes</L>
<L>Safetie of liues, nor any thrall to weild,</L>
<L>Free from the Gallie, prisonment, or paine,</L>
<L>And safe returne vnto their soyle againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>To this he yeelds, as well for his owne sake,</L>
<L>Whom desperate hazard might indamage sore,</L>
<L>As for desier the famous Knight to take,</L>
<L>Whom in his hart he seemed to deplore,</L>
<L>And for his valure halfe a God did make,</L>
<L>Extolling him all other men before,</L>
<L>Admiring with an honourable hart,</L>
<L>His valure, wisdome, and his Souldiours Art.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="54"/>
<L>VVith peacefull newes the Maister backe returns,</L>
<L>And rings it in the liuing remnants eares,</L>
<L>They all reioyce, but <HI>Grinuile</HI> deadly mourns,</L>
<L>He frets, he sighs, he sorrowes and despaires,</L>
<L>Hee cryes, this truce, their fame and blisse adiourns,</L>
<L>He rents his locks, and all his garments teares,</L>
<L>He vowes his hands shal rent the ship in twaine,</L>
<L>Rather then he will <HI>Spanish</HI> yoke sustaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The few reseru'd, that life esteem'd too well,</L>
<L>Knowing his words were warrants for his deede,</L>
<L>Vnkindly left him in that monstrous hell,</L>
<L>And fled vnto <HI>Alfonso</HI> with great speede.</L>
<L>To him their Chieftaines mightines they tell,</L>
<L>And how much valure on his soule doth feede,</L>
<L>That if preuention, not his actions dim,</L>
<L>Twill be too late to saue the shyp or him.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="55"/>
<L><HI>Bassan</HI> made proude, vnconquering t'ouer-come,</L>
<L>Swore the braue Knight nor ship he would not lose,</L>
<L>Should all the world in a petition come:</L>
<L>And therefore of his gallants, fortie chose</L>
<L>To board Sir <HI>Richard,</HI> charging them be dombe</L>
<L>From threatning words, from anger, &amp; from bloes,</L>
<L>But with all kindnes, honor, and admire,</L>
<L>To bring him thence, to further <HI>Fames</HI> desire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sooner they boarded not the crazed Barke,</L>
<L>But they beheld where speechlesse <HI>Grinuile</HI> lay,</L>
<L>All smeard in blood, and clouded in the darke</L>
<L>Contagious curtaine of Deaths tragick day;</L>
<L>They wept for pittie, and yet silent marke</L>
<L>VVhether his lungs sent liuing breath away,</L>
<L>VVhich when they saw in ayrie blasts to flie,</L>
<L>They striu'd who first should stanch his misery.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="55"/>
<L>Anon came life, and lift his eye-lids vp,</L>
<L>Whilst they with teares denoūce their Generals wil,</L>
<L>VVhose honord minde sought to retort the cup</L>
<L>Of Deaths sad poyson, well instruckt to kill:</L>
<L>Tells him what fame and grace his eyes might sup</L>
<L>From <HI>Bassans</HI> kindnes, and his Surgions skill,</L>
<L>Both how he lou'd him, and admir'd his fame,</L>
<L>To which he sought to lend a liuing flame.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Aye mee (quoth <HI>Grinuile)</HI> simple men, I know</L>
<L>My bodie to your Generall is a pray,</L>
<L>Take it, and as you please my lyms bestow,</L>
<L>For I respect it not, tis earth and clay:</L>
<L>But for my minde that mightier much doth grow,</L>
<L>To heauen it shall, despight of <HI>Spanish</HI> sway.</L>
<L>This said, ore-come with anguish &amp; with paine,</L>
<L>Hee swounded, and did neuer speake againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="56"/>
<L>They tooke him vp, and to theyr Generall brought</L>
<L>His mangled carkasse, but vnmaimed minde,</L>
<L>Three dayes hee breath'd, yet neuer spake he ought,</L>
<L>Albe his foes were hūble, sad, &amp; kinde;</L>
<L>The fourth, came downe the Lambe that all soules bought,</L>
<L>And his pure part, from worser parts refind,</L>
<L>Bearing his spirite vp to the loftie skyes,</L>
<L>Leauing his body, wonder to wonders eyes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>VVhen <HI>Bassan</HI> saw the Angell-spirite fled,</L>
<L>VVhich lent a mortall frame immortall thought,</L>
<L>With pittie, griefe, and admiration led,</L>
<L>He mournfully complaind what Fat's had wrought,</L>
<L>VVoe me (he cryes) but now aliue, now dead,</L>
<L>But now inuincible, now captiue brought:</L>
<L>In this, vniust are Fat's, and Death declared,</L>
<L>That mighty ones, no more thē mean are spared.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="56"/>
<L>You powers of heauen, rayne honour on his hearse,</L>
<L>And tune the Cherubins to sing his fame,</L>
<L>Let Infants in the last age him rehearse,</L>
<L>And let no more, honour be Honors name:</L>
<L>Let him that will obtaine immortall vearse,</L>
<L>Conquer the stile of <HI>Grinuile</HI> to the same.</L>
<L>For till that fire shall all the world consume,</L>
<L>Shall neuer name, with <HI>Grinuils</HI> name presume.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Rest then deere soule, in thine all-resting peace,</L>
<L>And take my teares for trophyes to thy tombe,</L>
<L>Let thy lost blood, thy vnlost fame increase,</L>
<L>Make kingly eares thy praises second wombe:</L>
<L>That when all tongues to all reports surcease,</L>
<L>Yet shall thy deeds, out-liue the day of doome.</L>
<L>For euen Angels, in the heauens shall sing,</L>
<L><HI>Grinuile</HI> vnconquerd died, still conquering.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>O vtinam.</TRAILER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="afterword">
<PB REF="57"/>
<P>WHat became of the <HI>Reuenge</HI> after Sir <HI>Richards</HI>
death, diuers report diuersly, but the most pro∣bable
and sufficient proofe sayth, that within fewe
dayes after the Knights death, there arose a great
storme from the VVest and North-west, that all the
Fleet was disperced, aswell the <HI>Indian</HI> Fleet, which
were then come vnto them, as all the rest of the
<HI>Armada,</HI> which attended their ariuall; of vvhich
fourteene sayle, together with the <HI>Reuenge,</HI> and in
her two hundred <HI>Spanyards,</HI> were cast away vppon
the Ile of S. <HI>Michaels;</HI> so it pleased them to honour
the buriall of that renowned Ship the <HI>Reuenge,</HI> not
suffering her to perrish alone, for the great honour
shee atchiued in her life time.</P>
<PB REF="57"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

