<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A bull graunted by the Pope to Doctor Harding &amp; other by reconcilement and assoyling of English Papistes, to vndermyne faith and allegeance to the Quene. With a true declaration of the intention and frutes thereof, and a warning of perils therby imminent, not to be neglected.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Norton, Thomas, 1532-1584.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A08352</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 18678</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S121749</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99856916</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99856916</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">22558</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A08352)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22558)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1283:03)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A bull graunted by the Pope to Doctor Harding &amp; other by reconcilement and assoyling of English Papistes, to vndermyne faith and allegeance to the Quene. With a true declaration of the intention and frutes thereof, and a warning of perils therby imminent, not to be neglected.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Norton, Thomas, 1532-1584.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[20] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>Imprinted at London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>By Iohn Daye dwelling ouer Aldersgate,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>[1570]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>By Thomas Norton.</NOTE><NOTE>Publication date from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Harding, Thomas, 1516-1572 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Catholic Church --  England --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Catholic Church. --  Pope (1566-1572 : Pius V) --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2002-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A08352">
<STC T="S">18678</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99856916</BIBNO>
<VID>22558</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
❧ A Bull graunted by the Pope to Doctor Har∣ding &amp; other, by reconcile∣ment and assoyling of Eng∣lish Papistes, to vndermyne faith and allegeance to the Quene. With a true decla∣ration of the intention and frutes thereof, and a war∣ning of perils therby immi∣nent, not to be neglected.</P>
<P>❧ Imprinted at London by Iohn Daye dwelling ouer Aldersgate.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 LANG="lat" TYPE="part">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">N</SEG>Oueritis quod anno, die, mense et pontificatu in∣frascriptis: in generali con∣gregatione &amp;c. pro parte Reuerendorum T. Har∣ding, et N. S. et T. P. Anglorum fuit porrectum memoriale et supplicatio, quae lecta fuerunt &amp;c. Annis abhinc tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bus &amp;c. concessit T. H. &amp;c. Episco∣palem potestatem in foro conscientiae absoluendi eos qui ad Ecclesiae gre∣mium <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Hinc potestati quia multi non credunt, petimus vt in scriptum aliquod autenticum re∣digatur. Ac etiam vlterius (monente nos temporis necessitate) humiliter petimus vt eisdem concedatur in cau∣sa irregularitatis dispesandi potosta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, exceptis ex homicidio voluntario prouenientibus seu deductis in fo∣rum contentiosum, Quibus auditis et intellectis praelibatus Sanctiss. Do∣minus noster decreuit quod preno∣minati absoluere possint in foro con∣scientiae Anglos tantum prout peti∣tur,
<PB REF="3"/>
etiam ab irregularitate incursa ra∣tione heresis et ab ea dependente e∣mergente et annexa, dummodo ab∣soluendi abstineant per triennium a ministerio altaris. In quorum fidem &amp; testimonium &amp;c. anno. 1567. die Iouis 14. Aug.</P>
<P>ET quia ego &amp;c. Notarius supra∣dictus copiam ex proprio originali suo extractam collationaui &amp; cum eodem concordare inueni, ideo subscripsi sig∣no{que} meo solito signaui in fidem pre∣missorum rogatus.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Forma absolutionis.</HEAD>
<P>Dominus noster Iesus Christus qui dedit Discipulis suis potestatem ligandi &amp; soluendi, ipse te absol∣uat, &amp; ego autoritate omnipotentis Dei &amp; beatorum Apostolorum Petri &amp; Pauli necnon sanctae matris Ecclesiae, at{que} auto∣ritate Papalis indulgentiae, in hac par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e mihi commissa &amp; concessa absoluo te a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> omni irregularitate &amp; sententia excom∣municationis maioris vel minoris a i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e
<PB REF="3"/>
vel ab homine tibi inflictis at{que} etiam ab omnibus criminibus excessibus &amp; peccatis tuis cōfessis contritis &amp; oblitis, &amp; ab om∣nibus casibus sedi Apostolicae reseruatis. Restituo te communitati fidelium &amp; Sa∣cramentis Ecclesiae, ac in illam innocenti∣am &amp; puritatem in qua eras quando bap∣tizatus fuisti, remittendo tibi omnes poe∣nas Purgatorij propter culpas &amp; offensi∣mes quas contra Deum &amp; proximum tu∣um cōmisisti, Et plenariam remissionem at{que} indulgentiam omnium peccatorum in quantum claues Ecclesiae extendunt in hac parte tibi do &amp; concedo, ita quod sis absolutus hic &amp; ante tribunal Domini nostri Iesu Christi, habeas{que} vitā aeternā, &amp; viuas in eo in saecula saeculorū. Amen. In Nomine patris. ✚ &amp;c.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 LANG="eng" TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The Bull.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">K</SEG>Now ye that y<SUP>e</SUP> day, month, and time of our Bishoprike vnderwritten, in a generall congregation &amp;c. on the behalfe of
<PB REF="4"/>
the worshipfull Thomas Har∣ding, N. S. &amp; T. P. Englishmen, was exhibited a memoriall and supplication, which were redde &amp;c. How about three yeares past, &amp;c. our holy Father hath graunted to Tho. Harding &amp;c. Bishoply power in court of conscience to assoile them that shall returne to the bo∣some of the chirch. To this power bicause many do not gene credit, we pray that it be put in writing in autenticall forme. And also further (being occasioned by necessitie of tyme) we humbly pray that to the same persons be graunted power to dispense in case of irregularitie, except in cases arising of wilfull manslaughter, or brought in cour∣tes of law. Which premisses being redde and vnderstoode, our saide most holy Lord hath decreed that the said persones may in court of conscience assoile Englishmen one∣ly, as it is prayed, euen also from
<PB REF="4"/>
irregularitie incurred by reason of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>resie and depending and arising vpon the same and annexed vnto it, so that the persons to be assoiled do for three yeares absteine from the ministerie of the altar. In cre∣dit and testimonie whereof &amp;c. an. 1567. Thursday the viiii. day of August.</P>
<P>And because I &amp;c. the Notarie aforesaid haue conferred the sayd copie drawen out of the proper originall and haue found the same to agrée therewith, being requested I haue subscribed and signed it with my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>suall signe for credit of the premisses.</P>
<P>Note that the petition was made in the name of three, but it was graūted to foure.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>¶The forme of absolution.</HEAD>
<P>OVr Lord Iesus Christ, which gaue to his Disciples power to binde and loose, he assoyle thee. And I by the au∣thoritie of almighty God, and of the blessed Apostles Peter and Paul, and al∣so of our holy Mother the Church, and
<PB REF="5"/>
by the authoritie of the Papaie indul∣gence, to me committed and graunted do assoile thee from all irregularitie &amp; sentence of excommunication both the greater and the lesser layed vppon thee by law or by man, and also from all thy crimes, transgressions, and sinnes, confessed, contrite, and forgotten, and from all cases reserued to the Aposto∣like sea. I restore thee to the communi∣on of the faithfull &amp; to the sacramentes of the church, and into the same inno∣cencie and puritie wherein thou wast when thou wert baptised, remitting thee all the paines of purgatory, for the faultes and offenses which thou hast committed agaynst God &amp; thy neigh∣bour. And I do geue and graunt to thee full remission and indulgence of all thy sinnes as farre as the keyes of the Church extend in this behalfe, so that thou shalt be absolued both here and before the iudgement seate of our Lorde Iesus Christ, and shalt haue euerlasting life, and liue in him world without end. Amen. In the name of the father ✚ &amp;c.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 LANG="eng" TYPE="part">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>¶ The declaration and warning.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">B</SEG>E it knowen to all the Quéenes true subiectes for their warning, to all false traitors and Pa∣pistes for theyr amende∣ment, &amp; to all the world <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r their example, that the Pope the com∣mon enemie of Christian truth, and of all iust crownes and dignities of kinges, hath graunted to Doctor <HI>Harding</HI> and other <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>etimes the Quenes subiectes, now fu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tiues and trompettes of treason, a cer∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne authoritie in nature of an indul∣gence or pardon, to reconcile Englishmen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o the bosome of the Romane Chirch, with a forme of absolution therto annexed in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uch: sort as here is truely set out. The partie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> to whom and at whose petition the same is graunted are Englishmen, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ch as they be. The Pope to whom the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ade, and by whom it is graunt∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, is a forene Potentate, and our Quéenes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mortall enemie, The effecte is to allu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e the Quéenes subiectes with hope of pardon and promise of the kingdome of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>en, to reuolt from acknowledging
<PB REF="6"/>
that her Maiesties supreme and vniuer∣sal aūcient authoritie in her whole realme ouer all her subiectes which they haue in Parlament and otherwise orderly and truely recognised, and to render their o∣bedience to the Pope a stranger, by whom our Quéene is not onely deadly hated, but also most iniuriously and vilely with pre∣iudice condemned. Some purpose it hath had to winne some pelting gaine to the pardoners or proctors that make marchan∣dise of the fayth and allegeance of her ma∣iesties subiectes. But (good reader) the very principall end, &amp; for disclosing wherof it is at this time published, appeareth by the date, by the forme, by the successes that haue happened, by the conuenience of time and matter with the last most tra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣terous deuises, conferences, conspiracies, knottes, alliances, attemptes, and assem∣blies, and by other circumstances that fall into vnseparable consideration with it, to haue reached a great deale further, namely to the dissoluing of the fayth, loue, and al∣legeance of the subiectes of this realme to∣ward the Quéene our most good, louing, and natural soueraigne, to the encombring of their consciences with necessitie of
<PB REF="6"/>
grudging at her and reuolting from her, and to the assaulting of her maiesties per∣son (whom God long preserue) her royall crowne and dignitie, and particularly and specially to the procuring, raising, aduaun∣cing, and strengthening this late most vile and horrible rebellion, beside the rest that are daily to be looked for with wise, ielous, and circumspect expectation.</P>
<P>It came sorth long before the Nor∣thren rebellion, as well you wote good reason it is that the childe be gotten afore it be borne, or rather that the father be borne before the childe be gotten. It is not vnknowen how for such reconcile∣mentes assemblies haue bene suspiciously made, substitutes haue bene deputed, and the like by many exercised, to crepe into deceaued subiectes hartes and draw them to be wayling of their supposed miseries, and to a desire of returning to the fansie∣full superstitions of Rome. How famous is the deliuerie of badges and tokens (with v. woundes and other superstitious deui∣ses) as it were for markes of a faction? How notorious is their byeword of their golden day? It is knowen (for the letters be yet extant in good custodie) how one of
<PB REF="7"/>
their Northren sacrificers wrote to an o∣ther of his owne faction, <HI>vz.</HI> Sir Iohn Plumtrée, to be satisfied in a matter that troubled his conscience, which was, that he had at one of the rebellious Earles com∣maundement sayd Masse before absoluti∣on obteined from the Pope in such forme as other had it. Appeareth it not euident∣ly that those receauinges to reconcilement are with admonitions or rather conditi∣ons not to returne to true Christian reli∣gion which they call schisme, nor to quiet and conformable life according to her ma∣iesties proceding, which they terme schis∣maticall? And what was this els, but to prepare mens hartes by secrete shriftes, whisperinges, exhortations, aduises, and traiterous practises, to repent their obe∣dience, to renounce it, to conceaue a pur∣pose of not returning to it, and so after such a preparatiue of a pardō, indulgence, absolution, or reconcilement, with a glister of treason to purge them cleane of all ho∣nest loyaltie, faith, and allegeance. And so the silly abused poore men (be they in worldly respect neuer so riche &amp; politike) are by degrees induced, first to abhorre the course of these times and gouernment,
<PB REF="7"/>
wherin they are borne in hand that they are out of the Chirch, as it were out of the Arke wrastling for life in the mid maine sea in perill of drowning, and this is their Contrition, which can not be with∣out lothing those whom they thinke au∣thors of their danger, of whom y<SUP>e</SUP> Quéenes maiestie is the chiefe. Secondly they are trained to conference and secrete consulta∣tion to make shift for their soules by ghost∣ly counsell, and this is their Confession, wherin many traiterous deuises are a∣gréed vpon. Thirdly to make vp perfect penance, for amendes they must enter in∣to actuall rebellion, and that is the natu∣rall Satisfaction to the sea of Rome, wher∣by the Quéene and realme are encombred.</P>
<P>But now marke (good readers) now cometh the case that ministreth good cause of consideration to you all. If you (good rea∣ders) be of great estate or beare charge in the common weale, as counsellers, lieue∣tenantes, iustices, or in any degrée of go∣uernance, now listen to matter of your charge, to awaken your care and put your duties in execution. If ye be meaner sub∣iectes without calling in office, now har∣ken to matter to moue ye to praier to God,
<PB REF="8"/>
to direct their zeale and trauailes to whom it apperteineth, or rather as he hath he∣therto done miraculously to preserue vs. This baggage, and all other of like sort; yea and some farre worse, can not well be sayd by such fine Italian, suttle, and vn∣gracious heades to remaine or be newly put in practise after the rebellion suppres∣sed, in respect of the rebellion past, but in hope of thinges to come. Such thinges as were prouided as appeareth by their date long before the rebellion actually raised, <HI>vz.</HI> before sommer was xij. monethes, and at this day watch their times, may not be construed to haue regard to time passed re∣medilesse, but to a reach of mischiefe whose successe is not yet séene. Full true it is that Papistrie hath no looking beyond this world, but is determined within worldly hopes, and therefore their deuises must be thought to tend to worldly politike endes, and so these pardons not propounded for foules health, but for hazarding of body and soule to serue a worldly fetch of trea∣son for aduancing of the Popes and Pa∣pictes worldly ambition and gaine. There is a new mischiefe in expectation. God presere our gracious Prince, and her
<PB REF="8"/>
true Counsellers, which shall be the chiefe defence and safetie of vs all. Note some likeliboodes, but with a ielous regard for so precious a iewell as our Quéene is. Our Louanistes for a good while haue written no more. What is the cause? They take them to other weapons, they hang vpon expectation of the successe of re∣bellion or some like mischiefe, which by their former bookes they haue trauailed to stirre vp and geue occasion. A number of such as finding them selues to féele some harme or lacke by popishe obstinacie made sutes &amp; gaue some hope a while of toward conformitie, now they shrinke backe, and holde out. And why so: Forsooth the men are now in hope, and in desire to sée the lucke of one chaunce more. It is well knowen that some Papicticall fellowes that of late yeares did communicate and frequent common prayer according to the order of our Church, do of late time, be∣like since their reconcilement according to this wicked order, absteine from com∣munion and common prayer. And what is the reason? <HI>Aliquid monstri alunt,</HI> they are put in new courage, and will no more stoupe till they sée more how the
<PB REF="9"/>
world will wagge, for a thing that they know, as they are borne in hand. What maketh the late flying of Papistes in such heapes, as those that tooke shipping ner<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Colchester &amp; other, afore and at other lat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> times, but a trust to returne to pleasant fruition of their desired time vpon the proofe of the mischiefs that they haue brew∣ed, and tonned and lacketh but brochyng. What intention haue they that runne a∣way, leauing letters behinde them to pray fauour of the Quéenes true officers with an intimation or inkling of promise, to be likewise good an other day to those that should shew them fauour now, but vpon a plaine reckoning of some vngraciousnesse in working, to hasten that day of their victorie, triumphe, and abilitie of recom∣pensing? Papistes flie not, stirre not, brag not, nor do any thing, nor leaue any thing vndone without hope. This geare por∣tendeth much.</P>
<P>But specially wey, why such vngra∣cious geare commeth now out that was prouided long agoe? Why after the re∣bellion it commeth, that should haue had his place before? Forsooth in the sommer 1569. the rebels were not ready, and ther∣fore
<PB REF="9"/>
the worst of this sort stayed. In the winter following, the rebels were taken <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ort afore they were ready, and then in an vnseasonable time of winter the publica∣tion of those traiterous Bulles would not helpe. Why come they now then? For∣sooth vpon their hope of that which ought to be our feare. The world is strange, treasons be venturous, no enemie to be neglected, specially nere and domesticall. There is somwhat in working that ought to moue our ialousie, to awake our hede, to sharpe our foresight and endeuour, and to make vs prouide for preuention, but specially to shield our selues by prayer vn∣der his wing that is able to defend vs, &amp; in the meane time not to omit those meanes of defence that he putteth in our handes.</P>
<P>Wherefore let vs all pray for her Ma∣iestie, that with courage she follow God in the course that he hath plainly set before her highnes for her preseruation. All ye noble counsellers goe forward in your ho∣norable seruice to defend that realme that can not in all likelihode ouerliue the safe∣tie of her most royall person. Ye Lieute∣nantes, Iustice of sheres and other offi∣cers looke to your charge, raise vp your at∣tention
<PB REF="10"/>
at euery occasion, haue good eye to rumor spreders &amp; other forerrunners o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> mischeues, take héede to Popish conuent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣cles, search the bottome where ye finde such leud tokens of Bulles and other R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣mish badges and trash, let slip no opportu∣nities. All ye the Quéenes true subiectes, looke about you, be earnest in prayer, hede∣full in vnderstanding, redy in seruice, for ye be warned, and suffer no leud tales to be caried vndisclosed in place conuenient. Ye Papistes forsake your mischeuous in∣tentions for ye be descryed, or if all be not yet foreséene, leaue yet your treasons, least ye be hanged and damned too, which i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> worse. All ye strangers of nobilitie and other of foreine partes, where your helpe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of intelligence or other good meanes may do good, omit them not, for to Christians of all nations the perill is common; and Papistrie is vniuersall and common trea∣son to all kinges &amp; states. All ye in whom it lieth to remedie, let not thinges runne past remedie. Remember noble Scander∣begs prouerb, that no beast be it neuer so fierce, can liue if the head be cut of. Consi∣der that checking without necking is mate.</P>
<P><PB REF="10"/>
God sharpen iudgement, industrie, vigor and zele, for his glorie, for his noble deputie in this Realme our most gracious Quéene, for all the good guides and the whole body thereof. The Lord be merci∣full vnto vs, and hold his holy hand ouer vs. The Lord of hostes rayse feare to sus∣spect what harmes may be attempted, where by dispensations ghostly feare is ta∣ken away, and by want of due and likely reuenging, bodely feare is remoued. And the same Lord raise courage to his mini∣sters to dispatch the cause of feare: if they that should do it do not feare, then boldly because they do not feare: and if they feare, then necessarily that they may feare no more. And God take from all men of cre∣dit the deuises to qualifie perils, to wrap <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re vnder ashes in a perilous place, or to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mpech the ser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ng of the bottome of dan∣gers that may breake out with new and doubled flame. Finally God geue vs grace that we do not by our owne negligence draw vpon vs hastily the thing that we haue cause to feare.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB REF="11"/>
<HEAD>¶ God saue our Queene Elizabeth and confound her enemies.</HEAD>
<P>None will make sleight accompt of these haynous threatnings and practises of Papistes, nor moue a∣ny other to make a laughing mat∣ter of them, or to wrappe them vp in negligence, but either such as can be content to laugh at her Ma∣iesties destruction, or be blindly led to their owne vndoing, how fayre soeuer with vaine promises they be abused or by other re∣spectes their iudgementes darke∣ned.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="license">
<P>¶Sene and allowed.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<P>* Imprinted at London by Iohn Day.</P>
<PB REF="11"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

