<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A nevve order for banqueroupts</TITLE><AUTHOR>France. Parlement (Paris)</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A08922</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 19200</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S120123</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99855323</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99855323</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">20810</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A08922)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20810)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1553:24)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A nevve order for banqueroupts</TITLE><AUTHOR>France. Parlement (Paris)</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[24] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>Imprinted at London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>At the three Cranes in the Vinetree by Thomas Dawson, for Thomas Charde,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1582.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>"A notable decree of the Lordes of the Parliament house of Paris, bearing the date the 26. of Iune, 1582. Pronounced against William Buhigue, containing a punishment for banquerouptes, namely the wearing of a greene cappe or hatte." is caption on A2r.</NOTE><NOTE>Running title reads: A greene cappe for a banqueroupt.</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A B⁴.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Buhigue, William.</TERM><TERM>Bankruptcy --  France --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A08922">
<STC T="S">19200</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99855323</BIBNO>
<VID>20810</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A
nevve order
<HI>for Banqueroupts.</HI></P>
<P>Imprinted at London at
<HI>the three Cranes in the</HI>
Vinetree by Thomas Daw∣son,
<HI>for Thomas Charde.</HI></P>
<P>1582.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="Parliamentary decree">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A notable decree of the
Lordes of the Parliament
house of Paris, bearing date <DATE>the 26.
of Iune, 1582.</DATE> Pronounced against
William Buhigue, containing a pu∣nishment
for Banquerouptes,
namely the wearing of a
greene Cappe or
Hatte.</HEAD>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">B</SEG>Efore I come to the</HI>
setting down of the sen∣tence
pronounced by the
Lieutenāt of <HI>La val,</HI> one
of the iurisdiction of the
presidentall seat of <HI>Poy∣tow▪</HI>
eyther of the confirmatiue decree of
the Parliament house of <HI>Paris,</HI> ratifiyng
the said sentence, I thought it good (gen∣tle
reader) in fewe wordes, to describe the
part of a creditor towardes his debtor, as
also the charge of a debtor towards him
that haue been beneficiall vnto him by
relieuing his want with his goods, whe∣ther
<PB REF="3"/>
goulde, siluer, or other commoditie,
to the ende, by this briefe collection and
aduertisement, each party may consider
his office and duetie, and so, better late
then neuer, reconcile himself to God and
his neighbour, during his pilgrimage in
this vayne and transitorie life, which be∣ing
ended, our God will (as all men
knowe) require an accompt howe euery
one hath delt in his vocation and office,
howe simple so euer it hath been, and in
the latter day of iudgement, yeelde the
rewarde due to his desertes, except by
speedy repentance before the saide iudge∣ment
hee reconcile himselfe. For God
being iust and perfect goodnesse, exten∣deth
his mercie vpon thousande genera∣tions
of those that vnfeinedly do loue him
and obey his commaundements which he
hath left, and willed his faithful seruants
and Apostles to preach vnto vs, and pu∣nisheth
only to the fourth generatiō such
as of set purpose do disobey &amp; transgresse
his precepts, for more acceptable is obe∣dience
then sacrifice, &amp; better it is to obey
God then man. The part therefore of a
<PB REF="3"/>
creditor towarde his debtor, consisteth in
lending vnto him that thing whereof hee
standeth in neede, and which the creditor
may w<SUP>t</SUP> least losse best spare, without loo∣king
for any amends, or requiring any re∣ward
for the time of the lone therof, ther∣in
putting in practise that Christian cha∣ritie,
whiche by God and his Churche is
taught in these wordes, <HI>Mutuum dantes,
nihil inde sperantes, <HI>lend looking for no∣thing
againe,</HI></HI> together with many other
places of the olde &amp; new Testament, and
Canonical &amp; Apostolicall epistles, conti∣nued
in the doctrine of many learned fa∣thers
of the Christian Church, both olde
and newe, wherunto euery man is bound
to conforme himselfe, in case he bee indu∣ed
with any iot of iudgemēt, or beareth a∣ny
dutifull affection vnto his saluation.</P>
<P>But such is y<SUP>e</SUP> malice of our dayes, y<SUP>t</SUP> cre∣ditors
in their lending, will so greatly re∣gard
their owne commoditie, that if they
lende, it shalbe to the ende, of their debtor
to receiue double the value, as in deliue∣ring
but mean commodities, &amp; to receiue
again y<SUP>e</SUP> best: In deliuering of rie, oats, or
<PB REF="4"/>
barley, to claime againe pure and cleane
wheat: either to deliuer their olde wines
full of all sorts of dregs, yea for the most
part soure or foystie, and agayne, to re∣quire
that whiche shall bee newe and of a
perfect good vintage.</P>
<P>They sel their clothes and other wares
at a high and deere price, when in troth
they be but litle worth, giuing their deb∣tors
so short dayes, as to their vndooing,
they be forced agayne to sell them, yea for
the most part by brokers to those of whō
they first bought them, for little or no∣thing.</P>
<P>Others there are that deliuer foorth
money, or other commodities from faire
to fayre, from 3. monethes to three mo∣nethes,
after ten in the hundred or more,
to the vtter empouerishing of their deb∣tors.
To be briefe, the Diuell and his
supposses in the shape of men, haue by
their subtiltie inuented infinite kindes of
vsury: wherewith like rauening wolues
they still deuoure their poore debtors,
that are driuen to submitte themselues to
their faith and charitable courtesies, who
<PB REF="4"/>
in the ende are thereby brought to vtter
beggerie, and vndoing without redemp∣tion,
whiche is a wofull and lamentable
cace. Yea, in the good townes and other
places, eache one maintayneth those
people, and cloke theyr offences, or at
the least dare not speake of them for feare
of being stunge by the like villanous vi∣pers
wherof the world is ful: for vsually
those be the soonest preferred to honors
and dignities whereof in trueth they bee
vtterly vnworthy: therefore for those
that are manifestly knowne to bee
such letters forth of goodes, there were
no reason theyr debtors shoulde incurre
the sentence and decree hereafter rehear∣sed,
especially when it is euident where∣in
the debtors haue by such rauening
wolues and theyr detestable broode been
circumuented, deceiued and entangled
with debt vpon debt vnto the full valewe
and extent of all theyr goodes. Oh poore,
miserable, and wretched sheepe, who ha∣uinge
yelded fleze, skinne and fleshe, doe
hardly reserue the bare bones, which rat∣tle
vp and downe the Cities, Townes,
<PB REF="5"/>
and villages, where they remayne with∣in
the reach of such wild &amp; cruell beastes,
as encroch vp the whole worlde.</P>
<P>Howebeit as suche debtors are by iu∣stice,
to be relieued and defended agaynst
that kinde of people, who in euery Citie
and towne do beare the whole sway both
in wealth, honour, and dignitie, so muste
we not therefore maintayne a number of
subtill shifters, which vsing all fayre pre∣tences
&amp; colourable flattering speeches,
doe abuse and deceiue both here and els¦where,
many well meaning marchantes,
such as being of a franck, good, &amp; vpright
disposition do thinke that all others doe
resemble them. These craftie con∣ueyars
by borowings reiterated and re∣newed
ofter then neede requireth, and
that in sundry places, and of diuers per∣sons
for feare of discrying, yea &amp; in grea∣ter
sums then their power or habilitie
wil beare, one creditor nothing knowing
of another, whē y<SUP>e</SUP> dayes of payment draw
on, will not find wherwith to satisfie euē
she smalest sum wherewith they haue bin
holpen: but then to auoyde emprisonmēt,
<PB REF="5"/>
(therein counterfeiting the glutted and
drunken Ape, which after drinke hoppeth
vp &amp; down) do leape from place to place,
and according to the prouerb, come to set
their tayles vpon the stone, which by law
&amp; iustice is appointed for the cession &amp; de∣liuery
of al their goods to their creditors,
whom to the same intent, they cause to be
summoned to the sight of that their mise∣rable
benefite: which interdiction of law,
tending to the reliefe of the good &amp; not
to the boulstering vp of such fraudulent
debtors, as are last mentioned, is founded
vpō the edict of <HI>Orleance,</HI> though in that
respect but simply executed throughout
most part of this lande, where euery one
indifferently, whiche seeketh to deceiue
his creditor, is vpon his owne onely peti∣tion,
admitted to the benefite of cession of
goods, bringing in for the true value ther∣of,
no other witnesse thē himself can chuse
among his friendes or fauourable neigh∣bours,
without other circumstaunce or so∣lemmity,
then during the sitting to assist &amp;
houlde plea barehead vppon the sayde
stone.</P>
<P><PB REF="6"/>
Hereunto hath this court at this time
had great &amp; diligent respect, to the ende,
hereafter to cutt off such shiftes and wic∣ked
dealings, for the reliefe of honest, and
in deed charitable creditors, and therefore
in confirmation of the sentence of the or∣dinarie
iudge of <HI>Laual,</HI> haue decreed y<SUP>t</SUP> frō
henceforth, euery one that will sue for
y<SUP>e</SUP> admission, to the benefite of cession of
goods, shall weare a greene Cap or Hat,
which his creditors shall buy him.</P>
<P>And for this time, <HI>William Buhigue</HI>
to beginne with the wearing of the same,
which shall bee prouided him, by <HI>Marin</HI>
the <HI>Monke,</HI> defendent and withstander
of the saide cession of goods, to the ende,
as well the saide <HI>Buhigue,</HI> as all other of
his profession may be knowne, and the
worlde thereby warned of his or their
saide cession, which by the wise aduice of
the chiefe president <HI>Thow,</HI> together with
the graue, learned, &amp; experimented Se∣nators,
his assistantes in the great cham∣ber,
who are not to seeke in the like ca∣ses
practized among the Romans, and
conteyned in their histories and secretes
<PB REF="6"/>
of lawe, is commaunded to be put in exe∣cution.
This decree is taken a <HI>simili,</HI>
namely of the auncient maner of the Ro∣manes,
practised vpon such as had incur∣red
any great losse by lād or by water, as
piracie, drowning, fire, or robbery, or any
such like, as we may in these dayes terme
those extremities, whereto our Master
vsurers by meanes and diuises aforesaid,
together with infinite others, enow, if a
man shoulde stande vpon them all, to re∣plenishe
hole vollumes, doe reduce and
driue the poore: whose practise at this
time is so manifest, that there needeth no
more but the princes commission, directed
to faithfull officers, to make generall en∣quirie
thereof, least they doe hereafter as
horseleaches, euen sucke vp the marowe
of the poore, and be drunken with their
blood, yea the prince must vse them accor∣ding
to the sence of the Embleme, where
standing with a sponge in his hande, and
wringing out of euery drop of y<SUP>e</SUP> water
therein, he giueth to vnderstand, that in
like maner he is to vse al such as fil &amp; en∣riche
themselues with his treasure, or the
<PB REF="7"/>
substaunce of his poore commons, whom
with their subtill slightes and practises,
catching at their goodes, they wring as
drye as a bone.</P>
<P>The <HI>Romanes</HI> I say, vsed playnely
and at large to paint and set out the mise∣ries,
and inconueniences or losses, which
such men had any way susteined, and thē
to cause the party endamaged, to carry
vp and downe this table, wherin his losse
was portrayed vpō his shouldiers, wher∣by
euery man might knowe his losse, and
consider of his desert, and so if need were
to relieue him, or otherwise to beware of
committing to his hand that thing which
he was not able to keepe or make accōpt
of, as the satirical Poet <HI>Persius,</HI> and after
him more at large his expositor <HI>Murme∣lius</HI>
do rehearse. Vpon this ground haue
this court at this present, in confirmation
of this sentence of the aforesaide Iudge
of <HI>La Vall</HI> of the iurisdiction of the seat of
<HI>Poitow,</HI> determined and decreed that the
Banquerupte <HI>William Buhigue</HI> shall
from henceforth weare a green Cappe or
Hat, at the cost of <HI>Marin</HI> the <HI>Monke</HI> de∣fendant,
<PB REF="7"/>
vpon the alowance of his letters
of cession, and that onely to the ende, the
saide Banqueroupt may in all places be
known, as were those mē at <HI>Rome,</HI> whi∣che
carried vpon their shouldiers the pic∣ture
of their mishap, whereby the people
might afterward know thē: Such ther∣fore
is the excellencie of this sentence,
that it deserueth confirmation through∣out
all this lande, against suche Banque∣rupts,
as forcing them to weare a green
cap or hatte, as a badge of their disorders,
yea and to be for perpetuitie inserted into
the very heart of the ciuill &amp; canon lawe,
also by vertue of the princes perpetual &amp;
irreuocable edict, for euer to bee ratified
word for word, after y<SUP>e</SUP> order &amp; forme of y<SUP>e</SUP>
said decree and sentence, as followeth.</P>
<Q><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="document">
<HEAD>An abstract out of the recordes and or∣dinarie
register of the court &amp; Iu∣risdiction
of La Vall.</HEAD>
<P>BEtweene <HI>William Bughigue,</HI> prisoner
in the castle of <HI>La Val,</HI> chalenger of the
<PB REF="8"/>
fite of cession of goods at this present, by
his Atturney <HI>M. Francis Belangier Li∣centiate</HI>
in the laws on the one part: and
<HI>Marin</HI> y<SUP>e</SUP> <HI>Monke</HI> appealāt there against,
personally and by his Atturney <HI>M. Iohn
Sercoul,</HI> likewise licenciat in the lawes
on the other part.</P>
<P>The parties heard, &amp; the said appealant
by his declaration, not able to proue any
concealement of goods, as by him hath
been into this court intimated, wee doe
debarre and condemne in costes and
damages, and in respect thereof, haue a
merced him at fourtie shillinges tour∣nois.</P>
<P>Moreouer, in as much as the sayde
appealant, cānot produce sufficient cause
why the saide <HI>Buhigue</HI> shoulde not be ad∣mitted
to the said benefite of cession, our
sentence is, that presently hee be dismis∣sed
out of prison, and so brought into this
court personally to receiue the saide be∣nefite.
Herevpon the saide <HI>Buhigue,</HI>
being come into the face of this courte▪
hath wholy resigned and made cession of
all his goodes to his creditors, and ac∣knowledgeth
<PB REF="8"/>
the whole sūme by this ap∣pealant
demaunded, faithfully promising
vpon the bettering of his estate, to satisfie
all his creditors, and affirming that hee
hath not any other goodes whatsoeuer,
then what presently hee beareth about
him. Also that fraudulently he hath not
made conueyaunce of any away. In
consideration therefore of the premisses
wee haue, and by these presentes do grant
the said benefite of cession vnto the afore∣named
<HI>William Buhigue,</HI> as well for all
summes demaunded, as for his lodging
and fees.</P>
<P>Wee do also at the instance of the ap∣pealant,
<HI>the Monke</HI> aforesaid, decree and
ordeyne, that for the manifest knowledge
hereof, the saide <HI>William Buhigue</HI> shall
from henceforth in all places, and at all
times weare a greene Cappe or hatte,
whiche the sayd <HI>the Monke</HI> shall prouid<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="over-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
for him. Also that when, or wheresoe∣uer
the saide <HI>Buhigue</HI> shalbe found with∣out
the sayde Cap or Hat, after that the
aforesaide, <HI>the Monke</HI> shall haue made
deliuerie thereof to him, it shall bee lawe∣ful
<PB REF="9"/>
for y<SUP>e</SUP> said <HI>the Monke,</HI> or any other his
creditors to commit him to prison, com∣maunding
our chiefe vsher, vpon reaso∣nable
requeste to see this our decree
fully and in all parts executed according
as is most requisite, and thereto do giue
him full power and authoritie.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Giuen at <HI>La Val,</HI> in the presence of vs,
<HI>Francis Tartrous,</HI> Licentiat in the laws,
and Lieutenant generall in the iurisdic∣tion
of the sayde place,<DATE>this 9.
of Sep∣tember.
1580.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Thus signed. Morayne.</SIGNED>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<P>FInally, this court by decree hath dis∣anulled
al appeales here against, with¦out
costs or damages, and do ordaine that
notwithstanding whatsoeuer appeale, the
said sentence shall stande in full force and
power.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Giuen in full plea <DATE>the 26. of Iune.
1582.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<PB REF="9"/>
<P>Hereby it is euident that <HI>Annuells,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Annuells &amp; Quinque∣nelles are yeerely, and fiue yeerely protections for debts.</NOTE>
<HI>Quinquennells,</HI> and cessions of goods
ought not slightly to be graunted, or per∣mitted
to euery one that will sue for the
same before a iudge, for the causes and
considerations before mentioned: for
<HI>Annuels</HI> and <HI>Quinquennels,</HI> are no other
but the two steppes whereby debtors doe
clyme to Banqerouptshippe, or cession of
goodes; endeuouring by such deuises and
priuiledges to defeat their wretched cre∣ditors
of such commodities, as simply
and on good faith they haue lent them.
Also vnder suche clokes, shadowing
their false intentes, and mayntayning
their credites to the vttermost: which is
an easie matter to doe, vnlesse the greene
Cappe or Hatte bee to the same conioy∣ned,
as an euident token thereof, accor∣ding
as by the sentence is prouided, whi∣che
together with the decree, confirma∣tiue
thereof, deserueth perpetuall re∣membrance
and honour, as the meane
whereby the posteritie may knowe such
as looke so simply to their affaires, or
fraudulently seeke to defeate their credi∣tors
<PB REF="10"/>
of their right, that they be forced to
submitte them selues to the dishonoura∣ble
wearing of a greene Cappe or Hatte
vnder paine of imprisonment on the be∣halfe
of their creditors, so often as they
bee founde destitute thereof.</P>
<P>Which neuerthelesse is not ment to
tend to any such note of infamie as there∣by
to be debarred or reiected from lawful
witnessing, or bearing such office or auto∣ritie,
as otherwise they might bee ca∣pable
of, in cace all other their behaui∣our
were correspondence. Neyther
ought any <HI>Annuels, Quinquenelles,</HI> or
cession of goodes to bee otherwise taken,
tollerated and allowed, then for mischan∣ces
happening through fire, water, wars,
or such like, when without doubt, by
some ineuitable inconuenience, the losse
of all or most parte of a mans goods doe
thereto driue and enforce the petitioner,
not his owne manifest negligence or wil∣ful
wast, and so to haue recourse to those
meanes, yea sometimes before that debt
bee due, for the whiche they sue out the
sayde <HI>Annuells, Quinquenelles,</HI> respits,
<PB REF="10"/>
or cessions of goods: during the allow∣ance
of which suites, they shall not be for∣ced
to put into the officers handes those
summs of money which they owe, except
the said suite be compassed after condem∣nation.
Neyther is the suiter to be em∣prisoned,
after hee hath procured his cre∣ditors
to be summoned to appeare at the
admission of the sayde <HI>Annuells,</HI> and
<HI>Quinquenelles,</HI> but beeing so empriso∣ned,
is to be released and set at lebertie.</P>
<P>Father, a man condemned for tres∣passe
in amendes, is not receiuable to the
Cession of goodes. Many other things
are also to be cōsidered before any be for∣ced
to the said cession in respect of the in∣terest
that sundry creditors haue thereto:
and therfore it is meete that any appeare
at the suite commenced and prosecuted a∣gainst
the debtor for deteyning his per∣son,
by reason hee hath no goods (as is
to be presupposed) wherewith to pay: but
if he haue any, thē he ought to cōfesse thē
to his creditor, to the ende, bee may there∣with
be satisfied according to reason. All
which notwithstanding, it is to bee noted,
<PB REF="11"/>
that a man giuing vp his goodes in ma∣ner
aforesayde, can not be taxed with any
spotte of infamie, reiected from witnes∣sing
on any behalfe, or made incapable
of bearing suche office as otherwise hee
might, or by right ought to enioy.</P>
<P>For cession of goods simply, is a fa∣uour
to the poore, and by lawe admitted
for sundry commendable respectes, and
therefore is not to breede contempt a∣gainst
those that by pouertie, or other in∣conuenience
are forced to submitt them∣selues
to such extremitie of lawe.</P>
<P>This therefore may be a sufficient
warning to all creditors, wisely and chri∣stianlike,
to vse their duetie as is before
specified: also to such needy debtors, that
in time they haue recourse to others ac∣cording
to reason, before they be compel∣led
to weare a greene Cappe or Hatte at
their creditors costes, as by this for∣mer
decree, confirmatiue of the sen∣tence
of the abouenamed ordinarie iudge
of <HI>La Vall,</HI> the day and yeere afore∣sayde,
it is both learnedly, circumspect∣ly,
and wisely ordeyned.</P>
<P><PB REF="11"/>
Let this therefore serue as an example
to all wis<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="over-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, discreete, and wary per∣sons
in euery common wealth.
Farewell friendly reader, and
take in good woorth this
simple discourse: groū∣ded
vpon the saide
sentence and
decree.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<PB REF="12"/>
<P>Imprinted at London at
<HI>the three Cranes in the</HI>
Vinetree by Thomas Daw∣son,
<HI>for Thomas Charde.</HI>
1582.</P>
<PB REF="12"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

