<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The sinners conuersion. By Henrie Smith</TITLE><AUTHOR>Smith, Henry, 1550?-1591.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A12389</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 22702</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S117480</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99852693</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99852693</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">18030</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A12389)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18030)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 354:2)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The sinners conuersion. By Henrie Smith</TITLE><AUTHOR>Smith, Henry, 1550?-1591.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[32] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>At London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed [by Peter Short] for William Leake, and are to be solde at his shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Crane,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1594.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Printer's name from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A-B.</NOTE><NOTE>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A.i."; the last leaf is blank.</NOTE><NOTE>Another edition has "william Leake" in imprint.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Sermons, English --  16th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12389">
<STC T="S">22702</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852693</BIBNO>
<VID>18030</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
SINNERS CON∣uersion.</P>
<P>By Henrie Smith.</P>
<BIBL>Math. 18. verse, 3.</BIBL>
<Q>Verily, I say vnto you, except yee be
conuerted, and become as little children,
y<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>all not enter into the kingdome of
Heauen.</Q>
<P><FIGURE>
<HEAD>ET VS∣QVE AD NV∣BES VERIT∣AS TVA·</HEAD>
<FIGDESC>printer's or publisher's device</FIGDESC>
<P>PS</P>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>At London printed for <HI>William
Leake,</HI> and are to be solde at his shop in
Paules Church-yard, at the
signe of the Crane.
1594.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="religious tract">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Text.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Luke, 19. verses, 1. 2. 3. 4 5.</BIBL>
<Q>¶1. Nowe when Iesus entred and passed through Ie∣richo,
2. Beholde, there was a man named Zac∣cheus,
which was the chiefe receiuer of the try∣bute,
and he was rich. 3. And hee sought to see
Iesus, who hee shoulde be, and coulde not for the
prease, because he was of a lowe stature. 4. Where∣fore
he ranne before, and climbed vp into a wilde
figge tree, that hee might see him: for hee shoulde
come that way. 5. And when Iesus came to the place,
he looked vp, and sawe him, and saide vnto him,
Zaccheus, come downe at once: for to day I must
abide at thine house.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>N the ende of
the Chapter before
going, wee may see
how Christ healed a
man, blinde in his bo∣dily
sight, namely
<HI>Bartimeus,</HI> wherby he
sheweth himselfe to be the phisition of the
body: Heere we shall see how he cured one
blind in mind, namely <HI>Zaccheus,</HI> whereby
he sheweth himselfe to be the Phisition of
the soule,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ephes. 5. 23</NOTE> and therefore the Sauiour of the
whole man.</P>
<P><PB REF="3"/>
In speaking of <HI>Zaccheus</HI> and his conuer∣sion,
wee will obserue foure circumstances.
First, the place where he was called, which
was <HI>Iericho.</HI> Secondly, the person that was
called, <HI>Zaccheus</HI> the Publican. Thirdly, by
whom and how he was called, by the voice
of Christ. And lastly, the effect and fruite of
his calling, his good confession.</P>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The first Circumstance.</HEAD>
<P>First therefore for the place where he was
conuerted, it appeareth to be <HI>Iericho,</HI> a Cit∣tie
not farre distant from <HI>Ierusalem.</HI> It was
sometime a notable Citie, till it was subuer∣ted
and ruinated by the Lordes Champion
<HI>Iosua.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iosua, 6,</NOTE> It was builded againe in the dayes of
<HI>Ahab,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Reg. 16, 34</NOTE> by <HI>Hiel</HI> the Bethelite, and remaineth
at this day with the rest of that holy-land,
vnder the Turkish Empire. Vnto this <HI>Ieri∣cho,</HI>
the Lord of heauen and earth vouch∣safeth
to come, in the likenesse of a seruaunt.
And as <HI>Iosua</HI> compassed <HI>Iericho</HI> seuen
times, minding to destroy it, so Christ the
true <HI>Iosua,</HI> resorted oftentimes to <HI>Iericho,</HI>
minding to saue it. But as in the destruction
of <HI>Iericho, Iosua</HI> spared none but <HI>Rahab</HI> the
harlot: so <HI>Iesus</HI> in his iourney to <HI>Iericho,</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
conuerted none but <HI>Zaccheus</HI> the Publican.
When <HI>Iosua</HI> had conquered and rased <HI>Ieri∣cho,</HI>
hee sowed salt in it to make it barren,
and cursed him that should attempt to build
it vp: yet in thys barren soyle Christ hath his
spirituall haiuest, and in this cursed Cytty he
hath a holy Temple a blessed building. <HI>Sa∣maria</HI>
that wicked Citty affordeth many
that belieue in Christ.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn, 4, 49.</NOTE> <HI>Iohn,</HI> 4, 39. And out of
<HI>Galile,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn, 1, 46</NOTE> from whence they thought no good
thing might come.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn, 7, 52,</NOTE> <HI>Iohn, 1, ver.</HI> 46. Christ
called diuers of his Apostelles, and euen in
<HI>Iericho</HI> this cursed Cittie, Christ hath a rich
man that is to be saued. In euerie place
Christ hath his chosen. There is neither Iewe
nor Gentile, Barbarian nor Scythian, bound
nor free,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom, 10, 12</NOTE> but Christ is all in all, to all that call
vpon him. <HI>Rom.</HI> 10, 12.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The second circumstance.</HEAD>
<P>Now followeth the description of <HI>Zac∣cheus,</HI>
which is most plainlie and fully sette
forth vnto vs. The holy Ghost speaking of
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> and his conuersion, comes in with
an <HI>Ecce, behold,</HI> as if it were a wonder that
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> shold be conuerted. <HI>Zaccheus</HI> was
a Gentile, a Publican, and a rich man, and
<PB REF="4"/>
therefore behold a miracle, as if in the con∣uersion
of <HI>Zaccheus,</HI> these three should be
conuerted al once.</P>
<P><HI>Zaccheus</HI> was a Gentile, a meruaile to see
a Gentile become a Iew:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 2. 28.</NOTE> that is, to belieue
in Christ. He was a principall Publican. A
strange thing to see a chiefe Customer to
giue ouer his office: and he was rich also, a
rare matter to see a rich man to enter into
the kingdome of God:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 19. 23.</NOTE> and therefore behold
a miracle, as if at this day, the Turck: the
Pope, and the King of Spaine, were at once
perswaded to forsake their Idolatry and su∣perstition.
Christ going to <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> con∣uerteth
a Gentile, to signifie the calling of
the Gentiles: he conuerteth a Publican, to
shewe that notorious sinners may hope to
be saued, if they repent and amend, as <HI>Zac∣cheus</HI>
did. He cōuerteth a rich man, to shew
that all rich men are not excluded from the
kingdome of heauen,</P>
<P>Hee was called <HI>Zaccheus</HI> before his con∣uersion,
but he was neuer trulie called <HI>Zac∣cheus</HI>
till Christ called him so. His name
signifieng, simple, pure honest, but his lyfe
was subtile, impure, and most detestable.
Thus manie are called by honest names,
whose deedes bewray their dishonest na∣tures,
<PB REF="4"/>
and vices oftentimes are shrowded
in the habites of vertue, like <HI>Esops</HI> Asse,
masking in the Lyons skinne, till hys long
eares detect his folly; or like the Crowe
that is decked in other plumes, till euerie
byrd doe plucke his feather.</P>
<P><HI>Zaccheus</HI> by his profession was a Publi∣can,
and therefore much detested of the
Iewes: for Publicans were the Romaine
Officers, appoynted to gather and receiue
publique custome or tribute of the Iewes,
who were at that tyme in subiection vnto
the Romaines. And amongst these Offi∣cers,
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> was the chiefe, and (as it see∣meth)
Ouer-seer of the rest that where in <HI>Ie∣rico,</HI>
and therefore in chiefe hatred among
the Iewes, as one that chiefely fauored the
Romans tiranny, and serued to abridge their
Country liberty, which ought not be subiect
to any Nation.</P>
<P>Besides, he contemned the ceremonies of
the Iewes, and regarded not their Religion,
nor liued after theyr Lawe, and therefore
with the rest of the Heathen Publicans,
was excommunicate out of theyr Sinagogue
<HI>Math.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 18.</NOTE> 18.</P>
<P>Thus was he hated for his profession, be∣cause
he was a Publican, &amp; for his religion,
<PB REF="5"/>
because he was a Heathen. Yet was hee be∣loued
for his wealth, for rich men haue ma∣nie
friends.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prou. 14, 20</NOTE> <HI>Prou.</HI> 14. 20. And though they
doe neuer so wickedly, yet haue they some
to take theyr parts. If they speake neuer so
proudly, yet are there some to prayse their
saying.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccle, 13, 23 24.</NOTE> <HI>Eccle</HI> 13, 23, 24.</P>
<P><HI>Zaccheus</HI> was a Publican, and therefore
riche: for Publicanes muste needes he rich,
and Vsurers will be welthy. But rich Pub∣licans
make poore princes, and wealthy V∣surers
make many beggers. In euery Pro∣uince
there were many Publicans, and
therefore much poore people in euery place:
for where there be many Caterpillers, the
fruit is soone consumed, and where there be
many extorcioners, beggers must needes a∣bound.</P>
<P>By the Law of God,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 15</NOTE> there might be no∣begger
in Israell, but when so many Publi∣cans
were suffered to receiue tribute of the
Iewes contrarie to Gods Law, no maruaile
though so many sate and begged, contrarie
to Gods Law.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 18</NOTE> <HI>Luke. 18. Iohn, 9. Acts.</HI> 3 By
the Lawe of God.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn, 9</NOTE> There ought to bee no
beggers among Christians.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts, 3 Psal, 37, 25</NOTE> <HI>Psal.</HI> 3. 2. 25. but
when so manie Vsurers are tollerated in a
Christian Common-wealth, contrarie to
<PB REF="5"/>
the Law of Chirst,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 6. 35.</NOTE> <HI>Luke.</HI> 6. 35. no meruaile
though we haue so many beggers,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Leuit. 25. 36. 37.</NOTE> contrarie
to the minde of Christ.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mark. 14. 7.</NOTE> <HI>The poore</HI> (sayth
Christ) <HI>yee shall haue alwaies with you, but
when you will you may doe them good:</HI> and
we shall be sure to haue the poore amongst
vs alwaies,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psalm. 37.</NOTE> but wee must make such good
prouision for them, that they be not faine to
begge theyr bread.</P>
<P>Thus was <HI>Zaccheus</HI> rich to himselfe,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 12. 21</NOTE> for
he was a Publican, but he was rich towarde
God also, for he had a desire to see Christ.
Almightie God,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ephe, 2.</NOTE> <HI>who is rich in mercie, Eph.</HI> 2.
hath so inspyred his hart with the desire of
heauenlie riches, that whereas before, hys
whole delight was in seeking of worldlie
wealth, now his greatest care is to seeke
for heauenlie treasure. He now forgetteth
what his profession is, and begins to be of a
newe profession: and he whose hart was
whollie sette vpon earthlie profit, is now like
old <HI>Simeon,</HI> most desirous to see his Sauiour.
The Tetrach <HI>Herod</HI> desired to see Christ,
and despised him when hee saw him.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 23. 8.</NOTE> <HI>Luke.</HI>
23. 8. 11. but <HI>Zaccheus</HI> the Publican, desired
to see Christ, and reioyced when hee sawe
him, like <HI>Abraham</HI> that desired to see the
day of Christ.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn, 8, 56.</NOTE> <HI>Iohn.</HI> 8. 56. and therefore of
<PB REF="6"/>
the seruant of Sathan, <HI>Zaccheus</HI> is nowe be∣come
the childe of <HI>Abraham,</HI> which reioy∣ced
to see the day of Christ. Happie were
his eyes that sawe so blessed a sight, for ma∣nie
Prophets and righteous men haue desi∣red
to see and to heare those thinges that
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> both saw and heard,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke. 10.</NOTE> and coulde
not see nor heare the same. If <HI>Iacob</HI> thought
himselfe happy,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gene. 45.</NOTE> if that hee might but see his
Sonne <HI>Ioseph</HI> before his death, then surelie
thrise happie <HI>Zaccheus,</HI> whose hap it was,
not onely to see (as <HI>Iacob</HI> did) but to reioyce
(as <HI>Marie</HI> did) in Christ his Sauiour.</P>
<P>As <HI>Zaccheus</HI> was desirous to see Christ in
earth, so I would haue the riche men of our
time, desirous to see Christ in heauen. For
although with the eies of our bodie we can∣not
see Christ as <HI>Zaccheus</HI> did, yet with the
eies of our faith wee may beholde him as
<HI>Stephen</HI> did.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts. 7.</NOTE> <HI>Actes.</HI> 7. But if our faith be so
weake sighted that wee cannot see Christ,
yet let vs haue a desire to heare Christ in his
word, whereby our faith may be increased,
for faith commeth by hearing the worde of
God.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 10.</NOTE> And as the Queene of the South desi∣red
to heare the wisedome of <HI>Salomon,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Reg. 10.</NOTE> so let
vs bee desirous to heare the wisedome of
Christ our Sauiour.</P>
<P><PB REF="6"/>
King <HI>Salomon</HI> left some bookes in wri∣ting,
wherein is seene some part of his wise∣dome,
and Christ our king, hath left vnto vs
his most sacred word, as it were a tast of his
wisedome,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn. 20. 31</NOTE> sufficient matter for our saluati∣on.
This is that heauenly foode,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 4, 4</NOTE> <HI>Math.</HI> 4.
4. whereby our soules are fedde vnto eter∣nall
life, let vs therefore labour for that hea∣uenly
foode: and as the Israelites were care∣full
to gather <HI>Manna</HI> to sustaine their bo∣dies,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 16</NOTE>
so let vs be as carefull to heare the word
to feede our soules. The people in the time
of Christ,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iobn, 6, 24</NOTE> <HI>Iohn,</HI> 6. 24. tooke great paines to
follow Christ both by land and sea, and ma∣ny
nowe a dayes (I confesse) are verie for∣ward
to follow his faithfull Ministers, but as
they followed Christ so fast to<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Ioh. 6, 26</NOTE> fill their bel∣lies,
so these frequent Sermons for fashion to
serue the time.</P>
<P><HI>Zaccheus</HI> is desirous to see Christ, a godly
care, but yet hee coulde not obtaine his pur∣pose:
a thing common, for euerie one that
hath any good motion, hath alwaies some
hinderaunce to crosse the same,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Two impe∣diments.</NOTE> and <HI>Zac∣cheus</HI>
hath a double impediment to hinder
his honest enterprise: The prease of the
people, And his little stature. Whereof the
former, that is, the multitude, is alwaies
<PB REF="7"/>
wont to be an enemie to those that woulde
come to Christ. This hindered the blinde
man from receiuing his sight.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 18</NOTE> <HI>Luke,</HI> 18. for
the people rebuked him that he should hold
his peace, till Christ called him and opened
his eyes. This hindered them that brought
the man sicke of the Palsie.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Marke, 2</NOTE> <HI>Marke,</HI> 2. for
they could not come at Christ for y<SUP>e</SUP> prease,
till they vncouered the roofe of the house,
and let downe the bed wherein the sicke of
the Palsey lay.</P>
<P>This hindered the healing of the deafe
and dumbe,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Marke, 7</NOTE> <HI>Marke,</HI> 7. till Christ tooke
him aside out of the multitude and cured
him. This hindered the raising of the Ru∣lers
daughter.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 9</NOTE> <HI>Mathew,</HI> 9. till Christ had
thrust out the Minstrels and the multitude,
and then restored the maid to life. Finally,
this hindered <HI>Zaccheus</HI> here from comming
vnto Christ, till Christ vouchsafed to call
him to himselfe. Thus alwaies a multitude
that is prone to euill, doth withdrawe and
hinder vs from approching vnto Christ: and
therefore wee must not followe a multitude
to doe euill, nor decline after many to ouer∣throw
the trueth.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 23</NOTE> <HI>Exod.</HI> 23.</P>
<P>The second impediment that hindereth
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> from seeing Christ, is his little sta∣ture.
<PB REF="7"/>
Hee was so lowe of stature, that hee
coulde not see Christ aboue the multitude:
but Christ was aboue the multitude, and
therefore coulde see <HI>Zaccheus</HI> though hee
were so lowe of stature. For God looketh
not on the countenance,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Sam. 16. 7</NOTE> nor on the height
of a mans stature, but the Lord beholdeth
the heart, and preferreth little <HI>Dauid</HI> before
<HI>Eliab</HI> his eldest brother,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Sam. 16 12.</NOTE> because he findeth
in him a better heart to serue the Lord. And
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> in his little bodie, hath a heart and
minde prepared to seeke and see the Lord.
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> was so lowe that he could not see
Christ, but many amongest vs are so high
that they will not see Christ. The common
people in the time of Christ, were so desi∣rous
to followe Christ, that neither lame∣nesse,
nor blindnes, nor sicknes, coulde staie
them from comming to him: but the Com∣mon
people in our time, are more readie to
follow their sport and pastime, then to come
to the Church to heare of Christ. And as
for our rich men, who seeth not that they
will make great hast to see a commoditie,
but will scarce come out of doores to heare
a Sermon?</P>
<P>They come to Church,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn, 32</NOTE> as <HI>Nichodemus</HI>
came to Christ by night, as if they were a∣shamed
<PB REF="8"/>
to come to Church: but they runne
after profite to gette riches,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. King. 5</NOTE> as <HI>Gehezi</HI> ran
after <HI>Naaman</HI> the Syrian to get a bribe.</P>
<P>Thus hath <HI>Zaccheus</HI> two lettes, that hee
could not see Christ, the one in the people,
the other in himselfe: and wee haue many
lettes to withdrawe vs from Christ, some are
externall and without vs, as the intice∣mentes
of the world, and some are internall
and within vs, as the lustes of our owne
fleshe. The prease of the people, hindereth
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> from seeing Christ in his humili∣tie,
and the multitude of our sinnes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Esay. 59. 2</NOTE> doe
presse vs downe that wee cannot see Christ
in glorie. <HI>Zaccheus</HI> was a man of little sta∣ture,
and that hindered him from seeing
Christ in earth, and we are men of little faith,
and that is the cause wee cannot beholde
Christ in heauen.</P>
<P>Though <HI>Zaccheus</HI> was a man of little sta∣ture,
yet it appeareth that hee was not a
man of little wit: For when hee coulde not
come to the sight of Christ for the multi∣tude,
he had the wit to runne before, and to
clime vp into a tree to obtaine his purpose.
And for the moste part it falleth out, that
men of lowe stature, are men of high con∣ceite,
and the shortest bodies, haue the
<PB REF="8"/>
sharpest wittes, God so prouiding, that the
defectes of their bodies, might bee supplied
with the giftes of their minde. Nowe <HI>Zac∣cheus</HI>
that before was loth to moue his foote
from the Custom-house for loosing his pro∣fite,
beginnes to runne after Christ for feare
of a greater losse, like <HI>Elisa</HI> that left his plow∣ing,
and ranne after <HI>Elias</HI> to followe his
newe vocation.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1, Reg. 19</NOTE> But <HI>Zaccheus</HI> doth not
onely runne, but also clymbe vp into a Tree
to see Christ: A strange thing, that <HI>Zaccheus</HI>
a rich man, and a chiefe Customer, shoulde
behaue himselfe so childishly in the sight of
so great a multitude: but the desire hee had
to see Christ, made him forget himselfe, and
to commit such thinges as were not fitting
for his state and credite. So they that wil fol∣low
Christ, must make account to doe ma∣nie
thinges contrarie to the<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Rom. 12</NOTE> fashion of the
worlde, and their owne liking. If Christ
himselfe were content to leaue the glorie
which he had with his father to come down
to vs, shall not wee be content to leaue the
reputation which wee haue with men, to go
vp to him?</P>
<P>But alas where is there any almost, that
preferreth not the fruition of this earthly pri∣son,
before the possession of that hea∣uenlie
<PB REF="9"/>
mansion: and had rather hazard the
hope which they haue of eternall glory, then
leese the present enioying of theyr fading
pleasure.</P>
<P>The ambitious man hunteth after honor,
and will not leese an inche of his estimation.
The couetous man seekes after profit, and
counts (like <HI>Iudas</HI>) all lost that comes not
to his bags. And the voluptuous man be∣stowes
his time in pleasure,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn. 12. 6.</NOTE> and thinketh
that hys chiefe felicittie. Thus euerie man
makes his heauen of that wherein he most
delighteth, &amp; is content to take great paines
to accōplish his fond desires. But here <HI>Zac∣cheus</HI>
is of another minde, for being a pub∣lique
officer, he climbes into a tree, which
stoode not with his grauitie: and being a rich
man, he runnes to see Christ, which was not
for his worldly profit; yea hee takes great
paines to see Christ, not respecting his ease
or pleasure.</P>
<P>Thus must we be affected if we desire to
come to Christ, that neither honours nor
preferments, nor profit nor pleasure, nor
kyndred nor freends, be able to holde vs
backe.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 8. 22.</NOTE> We must be readie not only to run,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luk. 14. 26.</NOTE>
but also to climbe (if need require) as <HI>Zac∣cheus</HI>
dyd: that is, to take some payne and
<PB REF="9"/>
trauaile to haue a sight of Christ.</P>
<P>The Queene of the South,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. King. 10.</NOTE> vndertooke a
great and tedious iourney, to heare the wise∣dome
of <HI>Salomon,</HI> but we are lothe to take a∣ny
paine to heare one that is greater then <HI>Sa∣lomon.</HI></P>
<P>The people in <HI>Dauids</HI> tyme, brought so
much treasure,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Chr. 29. 9.</NOTE> and so many gyfts to the buil∣ding
of Gods Temple, that the Priestes were
fayne to byd them cease, but a great part of
the people in our tyme, are so sparing of their
paynes and cost, that they thinke that very
time mispent whiche is imployed in the ser∣uice
of God: and that money ill bestowed,
which is gyuen to the maintenaunce of his
Ministers.</P>
<P>When <HI>Zaccheus</HI> could not see Christ for
the multitude, he climbes vp into a tree, that
groweth in the way where he was to passe,
that from a tree he might behold him, which
was to suffer on a tree for mans saluation. So
when wee cannot drawe neere to Christ by
reason of our sinnes that presse vs downe, we
must clymb vp by a liuely faith, whiche is the
tree of life, that groweth in the waie to eter∣nall
life, that so with the eyes of our fayth, we
may behold him that dyed for our sinnes vp∣on
a tree.</P>
<P><PB REF="10"/>
It was a wilde figge tree that <HI>Zaccheus</HI>
clymbed,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 21, 19</NOTE> but not like that vnfruitfull one
which our Sauiour cursed: for this bare most
pretious fruite, euen such as Christ himselfe
vouchsafed to plucke. A happie tree that
bare suche pretious fruite as <HI>Zaccheus</HI> was,
but thrise happie <HI>Zaccheus,</HI> that so happily
clymbed on that happie tree.</P>
<P>This tree grewe in the way that Christ
was to passe, for else <HI>Zaccheus</HI> might haue
climbed to no purpose: So if wee desire to
finde Christ, we must seeke him in the waie
where hee hath promised to shewe himselfe
vnto vs, that is, in his holy Temple, where
his word is duely preached,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 18, 20</NOTE> and his Sacra∣mentes
reuerently administred, for where
two or three are so gathered together, hee
hath promised to be present amongst them.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The third Circumstance.</HEAD>
<P>When Christ came to the place, he looked
vp and saw <HI>Zaccheus.</HI></P>
<P>As <HI>Zaccheus</HI> ranne before to see Christ,
so Christ followed after to see <HI>Zaccheus.</HI>
Sathan for his part, <HI>went about like a roaring
Lyon,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1, Pet. 5, 8</NOTE> <HI>seeking to deuoure him,</HI> but Christ for
his part,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn, 10</NOTE> goeth about like a good Sheepe∣heard,
<PB REF="10"/>
minding to saue him.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 11, 21</NOTE> And although
Sathan a strong armed man, had taken some
possession in y<SUP>e</SUP> heart of <HI>Zaccheus,</HI> yet Christ
a stronger then he, commeth vnarmed, and
taketh from him his harnesse wherein hee
trusted, and rescueth the spoyle.</P>
<P>Christ comes to the place where <HI>Zac∣cheus</HI>
was, because otherwise, it had been
vnpossible for <HI>Zaccheus</HI> to come to his pre∣sence:
for vnlesse the Lorde vouchsafe to
come vnto vs, we cannot attaine to the pre∣sence
of God. As no man might haue anie
accesse to King <HI>Assuerus,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Hester. 4</NOTE> except hee stret∣ched
out his golden Scepter, so no man may
come to Christ, vnlesse hee be called by the
golden scepter of his sacred word.</P>
<P><HI>Christ looked vp and saw Zaccheus,</HI> before
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> could looke down to behold him.
Thus doth the Lord preuent vs with his mer∣cie,
whome hee might cast off in his iustice:
and if hee perceiue in vs a willing minde
to come vnto him, he is content to come
first vnto vs. And like that good Father,
<HI>Luke,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 15</NOTE> 15. to beholde vs while wee are
yet a great way off, and to haue compassi∣on
on vs.</P>
<P>When <HI>Iobs</HI> three friends that came to vi∣site
him in his great calamitie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iob. 2. 12.</NOTE> lift vp their
<PB REF="11"/>
eyes a farre of, they knewe not <HI>Iob,</HI> because
he was so sore afflicted: but Christ who is the
myrror of true friendship, cannot so soone
forget his friendes, howsoeuer they be dis∣guised.
He knoweth his owne sheepe where
soeuer hee seethe them.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn, 10,</NOTE> <HI>Iohn</HI> 10. whether
they be vnder the figge-tree as <HI>Nathaniell</HI>
was,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn. 1.</NOTE> or vppon the figge-tree as <HI>Zaccheus</HI>
was, he hath respect vnto them. And if they
haue a desire to seeke, they shall be sure to
find.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 7.</NOTE> <HI>Math,</HI> 7. And if they labour and are
heauie laden,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 11.</NOTE> he will refresh them. <HI>Math.</HI>
11. Christ is nowe come to the place where
<HI>Zaccheus</HI> is to be called, and as <HI>Abraham,
Gene.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gene. 22.</NOTE> 22. lift vp his eyes and saw in the bushe
a Ramme that was to be sacrificed, so Christ
lifting vp his eyes, sawe in the tree, <HI>Zaccheus</HI>
the sinner that was to bee conuerted. And
now beginnes the conuersion of <HI>Zacche∣us,</HI>
for now Christ beginnes to speake vnto
him.</P>
<P><HI>Zaccheus</HI> desired onely to see Christ, but
now Christ calleth him by name, and offe∣reth
hys owne selfe vnto him. This was
more then <HI>Zaccheus</HI> expected, and yet no
more then Christ vouchsafeth, namelie, to
giue more then is desired. The sicke of the
Palsey that asked health,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke. 5.</NOTE> obtained also for∣giuenesse
<PB REF="11"/>
of sinnes. <HI>Salomon</HI> desired wise∣dome,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Kings, 3, 12. 13.</NOTE>
and the Lord gaue him wisedome &amp;
aboundance of wealth beside. <HI>Iacob</HI> asked
but meate and clothing,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 28 20.</NOTE> and God made
him a great rich man. And <HI>Zaccheus</HI> desi∣red
onely to haue a sight of Christ, and was
so happie as to entertaine him into hys
house.</P>
<P>Thus the Lord that is rich in mercy to all
that call vppon him,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 10. 12. phes. 2. 4.</NOTE> vseth oftentimes to
giue more then wee aske: and hee that is
alwaies found of them that seeke him with
their whole heart,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ierem, 29.</NOTE> is founde also sometime
of Gentiles that knew not God.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Esay, 65. 1.</NOTE> <HI>Esa.</HI> 65. 1.
Let vs therefore that were sometime sinners
of the Gentiles,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 10. 20</NOTE> seeke the Lord as <HI>Zac∣cheus</HI>
did while he may be founde,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Esay, 55.</NOTE> and call
vppon him while hee is nigh. Hee will be
found of them that seeke him heartilie, and
is nigh to all them that call vppon him faith∣fully.
<HI>Psalm.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psalm, 145,</NOTE> 145. 18.</P>
<P><HI>Zaccheus come downe at once.</HI> Now Christ
begins to call <HI>Zaccheus</HI> from the tree to be
conuerted, as God called <HI>Adam</HI> from a∣mong
the trees of the Garden to be cursed.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gene, 3.</NOTE>
<HI>Gene,</HI> 3. Before, <HI>Zaccheus</HI> was too lowe, and
therefore was faine to climbe, but nowe he
is too high, and therefore hee must come
<PB REF="12"/>
downe. And we (for the most part) are ei∣ther
too high, or too low, too hot or too cold,
too quick, or too slothfull in the Lords busi∣nes.
Somtime wee flock together to heare a
Sermon,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke. 5</NOTE> like the people <HI>Luke,</HI> 5, that pres∣sed
vpon Christ to heare the word: and a∣none
wee runne to see some pleasant past∣time,
like the <HI>Athenians,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts. 17</NOTE> whose eares al∣waies
itched to heare some newes. Who
make more shewe of conscience and religi∣on,
then they that shewe themselues most ir∣religious
and vnconscionable? Who seemed
more confident and vertuous in Christ hys
cause then <HI>Peter?</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Math, 26</NOTE> and not long after, who
more trayterous and faint-harted.</P>
<P>Many can saie with <HI>Peter,</HI> that they will
not stick to die before they will denye
Christ, but when it comes to the tryall they
are readie to abiure Christ and his religion,
before they will hazarde either life or ly∣uing.</P>
<P>He that will come to Christ, must come
at once, without delay, for delays (special∣ly
in the matter of our saluation) are most
daungerous, &amp; repentance may not be de∣ferred.
<HI>We must make no tarrying to turne vn∣to
the Lord,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccle, 5, 7</NOTE> <HI>nor put off from day to day, least
the wrath of the Lord breake forth sudainelie
<PB REF="12"/>
and we be destroyed in our securitie and perish
in the time of vengeance.</HI> When the Lord is
minded to doe vs good, he wil haue vs come
quickly like <HI>Ioseph, Gene,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gene. 45</NOTE> 45. 6. that in the
tyme of famine, would haue his Father <HI>Ia∣cob</HI>
to come downe quickly vnto him, to so∣iourne
in Egypt, where there was some plen∣tie
of foode.</P>
<P>As the children of thys world are verie
nimble to worke wickednes, so the children
of light, shoulde be as nimble to followe
goodnesse. <HI>Iudas</HI> was nimble to betraie
Christ, <HI>Iohn.</HI> 13. 27. and the badde debters,
<HI>Luke.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ioh, 13, 27</NOTE> 16.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 16</NOTE> could sitte downe quickly to mis∣reckon
their creditor: so let vs come quick∣lie
to heare of Christ, that Christ may ac∣cept
of vs quicklie, let vs be nimble to make
our account before,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 14. 28</NOTE> that we doe not (lyke
the foolish builder) come short of our rec∣koning.</P>
<P>But why must <HI>Zaccheus</HI> come downe so
hastily? euen to entertaine Christ into hys
house. <HI>For to day</HI> (sayth Christ) <HI>I must a∣bide
with thee.</HI> This was ioyfull newes to
little <HI>Zaccheus.</HI> Not long before, he wanted
meanes to see Christ, but now he hath op∣portunitie
to entertaine him into his house.
There was more humanitie in Christ then
<PB REF="13"/>
in <HI>Zaccheus,</HI> for if Christ had not bidden
himselfe to dinner, hee had not been bidden
for <HI>Zaccheus.</HI> So if Christ doe not offer
himselfe vnto vs in his afflicted members,
hee may go long enough before we will of∣fer
him any entertainment.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Math, 25, 40</NOTE> As often as the
poore craueth anie reliefe at our handes, let
vs imagine that Christ asketh something of
vs: but as <HI>Zaccheus</HI> must entertaine him
presently without delay, so let vs be readie
to helpe them presently, because they stand
in neede of present helpe. And as hee must
receiue Christ into his house, so wee must
make account to receiue his needie mem∣bers
into our houses:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke, 16.</NOTE> And as the vniust
Steward procureth himselfe friendes with
his maisters goodes, so let vs make the poore
to be our friendes, by our beneficence and
bountie towards them, that so receiuing thē
(when they haue neede) into our earthly
houses, they may receiue vs when we stand
in greatest neede, into euerlasting habitati∣ons.</P>
<P>They that were inuited to the marriage,
<HI>Math.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 22.</NOTE> 22. refused to come, but Christ is
content to come to <HI>Zaccheus</HI> house before
he was inuited. Wherein also, hee sheweth
his great humilitie, in comming before hee
<PB REF="13"/>
was requested, as they bewrayed their great
arrogancie, in refusing to come beeing so∣lemnely
bidden. It was a part of great hu∣militie,
that he that was most free from sinne,
woulde vouchsafe to come into a sinners
house: but it was a signe of greater humilitie,
that he would be wray his great necessitie, &amp;
seeke for succour at a sinners hand.</P>
<P>Alas poore humble Sauiour, who though
thou be Lord of heauen and earth, as thou art
the sonne of God, yet as thou art the sonne
of man, hast not whereon to lay thy head,
<HI>Math.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 8.</NOTE> 8. How iustly did thy Prophet <HI>Iere∣my</HI>
wonder at thy humble pouerty, saying.
<HI>O thou hope of Israell, the Sauiour thereof in
the time of trouble,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iere. 14.</NOTE> <HI>why art thou as a straunger
in the land, or as one that passeth by to tarry for
a night?</HI> The sonne of GOD vouchsafeth to
come and that vnrequested, to a sinfull mans
house, a speciall fauour: but hee disdaineth
not to make his necessity knowne vnto him,
O straunge humilitie!</P>
<P>Heere therefore appeareth the singuler
humanitie and great humilitie of Christ to
sinfull men; he offereth himselfe to bee their
guest if he finde them willing to entertaine
him for their guest. And <HI>Zaccheus</HI> no doubt
was willing to entertaine him: for although
<PB REF="14"/>
Christ heard not the voyce, yet he heard the
affection of <HI>Zaccheus</HI> inuiting him to dyn∣ner.
As therefore <HI>Zaccheus</HI> was willing to
receiue Christ into his house, so let vs be rea∣dy
to receiue him into our harts. For as Christ
sayd to <HI>Zaccheus: This day I must abide at
thy house,</HI> so he saith to euery one of vs, <HI>This
day I must abide in your harts.</HI></P>
<P>Wherefore as the Prophet <HI>Dauid</HI> sayth,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psalm, 24</NOTE>
<HI>Open your gates that the King of glorie may
come in,</HI> so I say vnto you, <HI>Open your hartes
that the word of God may enter in.</HI> This daie
the word of God may abide in your harts,
for thys day the word is preached vnto you,
and who knoweth whether he shall liue to
heare it the next Saboth.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal, 95</NOTE> <HI>To day therefore if ye
will heare his voyce, harden not your hearts:</HI> as
did y<SUP>e</SUP> Israelites, least if you harden your harts,
his voice be heard no more amōgst you. This
day you may gather this heauenlie <HI>Man∣na,</HI>
as the Isralites might gather theyr <HI>Man∣na</HI>
sixe dayes together,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod, 16</NOTE> but to morrow (per∣haps)
and sixe dayes after you, may not ga∣ther
it, as on the seauenth day <HI>Manna</HI> might
not be found.</P>
<P>The Lord graunt that you may gather
sufficient foode for the sustentation of your
soules, that as <HI>Elias</HI> the Prophet iournied in
<PB REF="14"/>
the strength of the meate that the Angell
brought him,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1, Reg. 19.</NOTE> euen vnto <HI>Horeb</HI> the Mount
of God, so you in the strength of this spiri∣tuall
meate which heere I bring you, may
be able to passe thorowe the daungerous
wayes of this troublesome worlde, vnto
Gods holy Mountaine, the Hauen of all
happinesse, whither hee bring vs that hath
deerely bought vs with his precious bloud,
euen Christ Iesus the righteous: to whome
with the Father and the holy Ghost, three
persons and one GOD, be giuen all glorie
and maiestie, world without, end <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

