<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Staffords Niobe: or His age of teares A treatise no lesse profitable, and comfortable, then the times damnable. Wherein deaths visard is pulled off, and her face discouered not to be so fearefull as the vulgar makes it: and withall it is shewed that death is only bad to the bad, good to the good.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Stafford, Anthony.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 112 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A12821</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 23129</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S106303</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99842021</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99842021</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">6644</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A12821)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6644)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 773:12)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Staffords Niobe: or His age of teares A treatise no lesse profitable, and comfortable, then the times damnable. Wherein deaths visard is pulled off, and her face discouered not to be so fearefull as the vulgar makes it: and withall it is shewed that death is only bad to the bad, good to the good.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Stafford, Anthony.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[20], 201, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>At London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Humfrey Lownes,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1611.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Page 134 misnumbered 116.</NOTE><NOTE>Considerable print show-through.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Rekeyed and resubmitted</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A12821">
<STC T="S">23129</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99842021</BIBNO>
<VID>6644</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
Staffords NIOBE: <HI>Or</HI> HIS AGE OF TEARES.</P>
<P>A Treatise no lesse profita∣<HI>ble, and comfortable, then</HI> the times damnable.</P>
<P>Wherein Deaths visard is <HI>pulled off, and her face disco∣</HI>uered not to be so feare∣<HI>full as the vulgar makes</HI> it: and withall it is shewed <HI>that death is only bad to</HI> the bad, good to <HI>the good.</HI></P>
<P>AT LONDON Printed by <HI>Humfrey Lownes,</HI> 1611.</P>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD><HI>TO THE RIGHT Honourable,</HI> Robert <HI>Earle of Salisbury, Knight of the most</HI> honourable Order of the Garter, <HI>Vicount</HI> Cranborne, <HI>Lord</HI> Cecil <HI>of</HI> Essin∣don, <HI>Lord high</HI> Threasurer <HI>of England,</HI> Chancelour of the Vniuersitie of Cam∣bridge, and one of his Maiesties most Ho∣<HI>nourable priuie Councel, A. S. wisheth the pleasures of the</HI> Kingdome of Heauen, for his paines taken in this <HI>Kingdome of</HI> the Earth.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>T may seem strange vnto you (truely honourable Lorde) that a stranger should dedi∣cate a Booke vnto you: but, wonder not. For, though I
<PB REF="3"/>
be not knowen to your Ho∣nour, yet your Honor is wel knowen vnto me: and (in∣deed) to whom not? I haue no small time (be it spoken without blasphemie) euen worshipt your Worth; and therefore now offer vp vnto it, all the reuenewes of my reuerence. I was the rather induced to dedicate it to your Honour, by reason that my father was a neigh∣bour to your Father, being much obliged vnto him; and my whole Family vnto your selfe. And next of all, to giue you thankes in the be∣halfe of all Gentrie; which is daylie bettered by your
<PB REF="3"/>
Lordships directions, and furtherances in all honest courses. Desert was fled in∣to the Desert, before your Lordship called her home from exile, &amp; clad hir wea∣ther-beaten limmes. And (which draweth neere vnto a miracle) your Lordship doth not imitate the greatest part of the hodiernall No∣bilitie, <HI>Qui beneficia in ca∣lendario seribunt.</HI> But whe∣ther goe I? knowing that your monosyllables, as also short speeches, are pleasing to GOD sometimes, and to Great-men at all times. Accept then this Leafe rather then Booke, toge∣ther
<PB REF="4"/>
with my vowed and owed seruice: which though I offer <HI>serò, tamen seriò,</HI> my e∣uer honoured Lord.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Lordships most <HI>humble seruant: to</HI> be commanded, ANTHONIE STAFFORD.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
<PB REF="4"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>TO THE Reader.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">D</SEG>ifferent, or indifferent <HI>READER,</HI> Health to thy Soule and Bodie. Knoweing vertue to bee of the na∣ture of the Sun, that is, she shines as well vpon the bad, as vpon the good; I thought the badde would claime interest in her, as
<PB REF="6"/>
well as the good. To pre∣uent which, I wrote this treatise: in which I haue layed my selfe open to the world; to the intent, that I may attract the loue of the vertuous, and the hate of all those who continue vitious: for, I hold him to be no honest man, that is beloued of all men. For, in that, he sheweth that he can apply himselfe to the time, be it neuer so viti∣ous, to the place be it neuer so infamous, to the person, be it neuer so odious. Wher∣fore I giue all men to vn∣derstand, that I am a ser∣vant to Vertue: which I
<PB REF="6"/>
proclaime to the world, by this booke, my Heraulde; and giue defiance to her foes and mine. And how∣soeuer I seeme, now and then, to lend an eare to lewdnesse; it is not that I take pleasure in it, but be∣cause I am loth to diplease the harbourers and diu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l∣gers of it. What soeuer the world thinkes of me, or thinketh me to be: yet this I am. For, being through∣ly acquainted with my¦selfe, I doe not aske ano∣ther man what I am. I pro∣test it againe and againe, that I depend on Vertue. And, if I wax poore in her
<PB REF="7"/>
seruice, I shall account my selfe richer, then all this wicked worlds wealth can make me: and, if I growe rich without her, I shall e∣steeme my self poorer then pouerty her selfe can make me. I speake not this, like a Politiciā, to purchase my selfe a greater fame then mine owne worth; No, no▪ We doe not dissemble in those things, in which he first deceiues himselfe, that would others. Wherefore he is iniurious to me, who wicked in himselfe fra∣meth a minde to me out of his owne. If my inward man excuse me, what care
<PB REF="7"/>
I, who accuse me? yet doe I not despise an honest re∣port; but, onely warne you this, that it is not in my power to tye loose tongues. And therefore Fame is to be reckoned amongst these externall accidents; as of no moment to the accom∣plishment of a quiet and a blessed life. What to be, con∣sisteth on my part; what I am said to be, on the vaine vulgars. Fame and Con∣science are of two diffe∣ring properties: the one blazeth a mans deserts; yet makes him neuer the better: the other, the bet∣ter; yet neuer the more
<PB REF="8"/>
renowned. I knowe, that my beliefe in God, and not the worlds beliefe of me, shall saue me: yet (by the way) would I not haue a∣ny man thinke, that I write this by constraint; that is, to cleare my selfe of any imputed Crime: for, I write it not to dispossesse, but to possesse the world of a good opinion of me. I ve∣rily thinke, that I haue layed my selfe too open, &amp; dealt too plainely in some things contained in this insuing treatise: but, I passe not much. For, as my birth styled me a gentleman; so I would haue my death
<PB REF="8" MS="y"/>
stile me generous. Prying Policy telleth me, that it is farre <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to knowe what a man speaks, then to speak what he knowes: but my harmelesse heart dictates to my pen, not what the world would, but what it should heare of. My soule is an Antipode, &amp; treads opposite to the present world. My intent, in wri∣ting this book, is twofolde: first, to purchase to my selfe, not so much the title of a learned, as of an ho∣nest man; and secondly (because I knowe not whe∣ther my vnfortunate for∣tunes, and vnstaied youth
<PB REF="9"/>
may leade me) that the world may be acquainted with the secrets of my soule, and may receiue from me a testimonie of my liuely faith; that so it may iudge the more chari∣tably of mee being dead. Thus much for my selfe. Now, gentle or vngentle Reader; concerning thee, I diuide thee into Learned, and Vnlearned: and the Learned I subdiuide into Iudicial, and Not-indiciall. Seneca saith, that <HI>Sum∣mū bonum in iudicio est,</HI> that <HI>mans chief felicity is in iudgement:</HI> and Seali∣ger calleth it <HI>Animamsa∣pientiae,</HI>
<PB REF="9"/>
<HI>the soule of wise∣dome.</HI> And therefore he that hath this Wisedomes soule to be the Centre of his soule, I doe not so much feare, as reuerence his cen∣sure. But hee that hath read neuer so much, and in his discourse will shoote whole Volleis of Volumes at a man, and yet wanteth iudgemente, my Booke turnes his posteriours to him, and bids him shoote there, as a marke too faire for his carping mouth, to aime at. The Vnlearned I rediuide into Prudent, and Impudent. The Pru∣dent will not let his cen∣sure
<PB REF="10"/>
flie aboue his know∣ledge; but, what he vnder∣stands not, he will with modestie either passe it o∣uer, or with discretion en∣quire after it, of some bet∣ter-knowing spirits. As for impudent asses, who will reprehende vvhat their shallowe vvits can neither apprehende, nor comprehende, and so turne despaire into iudgement, I hold them fitter to read bills, and ballads, then my Booke. And withall I must needes adde this, that I neither feare a Stage, nor the censure of a Woman. And against the Learned,
<PB REF="10"/>
and Vnlearned, Iudiciall and Not-iudiciall, Prudent and Impudent, Women, and the worlds wide Thea∣ter, I bandy that of Iob,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iob. 31. 35.</NOTE> <HI>Behold my signe, that the Almightie will witness for mee; although mine Adnersarie write a booke against mee.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<PB REF="11"/>
<HEAD>Errata.</HEAD>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL ROLE="label">Page</CELL>
<CELL ROLE="label">Line</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>81.</CELL>
<CELL>10. </CELL>
<CELL>ioy-forioyne.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>81.</CELL>
<CELL>11.</CELL>
<CELL><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> for <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>99.</CELL>
<CELL>13.</CELL>
<CELL>perfect imperfect, for perfect or imperfect.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>142.</CELL>
<CELL>8.</CELL>
<CELL> present for presents.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>154.</CELL>
<CELL>2.</CELL>
<CELL>Iesuites for <HI>Iesuitas.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>166.</CELL>
<CELL>2.</CELL>
<CELL>these for those.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>195.</CELL>
<CELL>1.</CELL>
<CELL> gift for guest.</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<P><HI>In some fewe Books,</HI> Pag. 10. li. 11. men for mens.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="11"/>
<HEAD><HI>STAFFORDS</HI> NIOBE, <HI>OR</HI> His age of teares.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ad to the very Soule, bearing in my minde a discōtent, that I could bee no more discontented; in a worde, wearie of my selfe, I on a time walked forth, ho∣ping by some diuine medi∣tation to abandon, and ex∣pell this hellish disposition.
<PB N="2" REF="12"/>
And being com to the place ordained by my selfe to this solemne exercise, I first lif∣ted vp mine eies to heauen, to see what heauen would haue done vpon earth: and then again I cast them down vpon earth, to see what earth hadde done against heauen. But loe, in the entrance <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to this my sanctified con∣templation, my olde agonie came vpon me; I meane, a conflict betwixt mine vne∣quall, disagreeing passions: which forced mee to call backe the better of my thoughts, to driue back the worse. But, finding no way, whereby I might appease
<PB N="3" REF="12"/>
these implacable furies of my minde, leauing my meditation, I thus spake vn∣to my soule. Soule, saide I, how chaunceth it, that nothing can content thee so much as discontent? Is not this rotten body, this all corruption, this worst of earth, a sufficient prison vn∣to thee, but that thou thy selfe must become a prison to thy selfe? To these my de∣maunds shee thus makes an∣swer; that the diuell, as shee thinkes, hath committed incest with his daughter, World, who is now deliue∣red of an Age, frō the which the sooner it should please
<PB N="4" REF="13"/>
God to deliuer her, the bet∣ter. Then soule, said I, take thy flight, &amp; with the sharp pearcing eyes of contem∣plation pry into the corners of the Vniverse; and see if within this spacious Round thou canst finde out some place, where thou maiest in∣ioy a pure conuersation till the houre com wherin thou shalt leaue this thine impure mansion. Shee obeyed, and after long, &amp; teadious search, shee returned like <HI>Noahs</HI> turtle, and told mee that such a deluge of sinne had ouerspread the face of the earthe, that there was no place free where vertue
<PB N="5" REF="13"/>
might treade in sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etie. If earth then, said I, affoorde thee no comfort, lett thy conuersation be in heauen, laugh at the idle pleasures of these daies, and let not thine vnlimited appetite so much couet as contemne them; following that rule, of <HI>Sene∣ca, Contemnere omnia ali∣quis potest; omnia habere ne∣mo</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Sen Epist. 62.</NOTE> <HI>potest. Some one man,</HI> saith hee▪ <HI>may contemne all things; but no man <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> haue all things.</HI> And indeed what is there in this world, on the which Enuy may not iustlie spend all her gall? For who∣soeuer shal with an inten<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine and rectified Iudgem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt,
<PB N="6" REF="14"/>
look into this worst of ages, shall finde, that the lasciui∣ous heathen Poets were but as wicked prophets of the wickednes to come in these accursed times; wee hauing turned their lewde inuenti∣ons into more lewd actions. So that it seemes wee haue anatomized vice, and laied those parts of her to the o∣pen viewe, which they in modesty let lie vndiscoue∣red. From the highest to the lowest, from the young∣est to the oldest, from the Eagle to the Wren, all haue corrupted their waies, and are becom degenerate from the purity of their ancest∣ours.
<PB N="7" REF="14"/>
Vice hath supplanted vertue: and he now a-dayes is helde the most absolute man, who is the most disso∣lute liuer. As now and then the humours of the whole bodie fall downe into the legges, and there make an issue: So hath the corrupti∣on of times past slidde down into the present, to the an∣noiance, and choaking of all that is good. This is the time foretolde by Seneca,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Sen. de benef. lib. 1. cap. 10</NOTE> <HI>Hab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bitur aliquando ebrie∣tati honor; et plurimummeri cepisse virtus erit, The time shall come,</HI> saith hee, <HI>when honour shall be ascribed to drunkennes; and to drinke</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="15"/>
<HI>much wine shall bee helde a vertue.</HI> Pride, luxury, and ribauldry haue now their reigne, and his happinesse is greatest who followeth them the soonest. As for pride, she hath so many fea∣thers added to her wings, that shee couereth all the earth with her shadowe. Our men are growen so ef∣feminate, and our women so man-like▪ that (if it might bee) I thinke they woulde exchange genders. What modest eye can with pati∣ence beholde the immodest gestures▪ and attires of our women? No sooner with them is insancie put off, but
<PB N="9" REF="15"/>
impudency is put on: they haue turned nature into art; so that a man can hardlie dis∣cerne a woman from her i∣mage. Their bodies they pinch in, as if they were an∣grie with nature for casting them in so gross a mould: but as for their looser parts, them they let loose to preie vpon whatsoeuer their lust∣darting eyes shalseize-vpon. Their brests they laye to the open viewe, like two faire apples: of which who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oeuer tasteth, shall be sure of the knowledge of euill; of good I dare not warrant him. As for our men, they equall, if not surpasse this female frail∣tie,
<PB N="10" REF="16"/>
the qualities of their mindes being as light as the substance of their bodies is heauie. Light clothes, and a light behauior is now your onely weare, and hee your greatest gallant who canne whiffe off his gallon. O, that iniquitie were here li∣mited! but alas, it is not. For mens tongues are now bee∣come trumpets or rather strumpets to their mindes: so that what soeuer they con∣ceiue, they not onely tell o∣thers<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ambros. de poenit. lib. 1. cap. 34.</NOTE> of it, but also intice them to doe it. <HI>Lust,</HI> saith Ambrose, <HI>is feade with ban∣quets, nourished with de∣lights, kindled with wine, en∣flamed</HI>
<PB N="11" REF="16"/>
<HI>with drunkennesse;</HI> but streight addeth, <HI>peiora tamen his sunt fomenta ver∣borum, quae vino quodam Sodomitanae vit is mentē ine∣briant. But worse then all these,</HI> saith hee, <HI>is that im∣purity of speach, which makes drunk the minde with the sweet tasting wine of the Sodomiticall vine.</HI> Sodome, thy sinnes were fewe in respect of ours, and our iust men fewe in respect of thine. Thou peraduenture hadst three, or foure: but happy is that citty with vs that can yeelde one; yet wee raile at thee, and seeke to be opposite to thee in al things:
<PB N="12" REF="17"/>
but in one thing wee iump with thee by following the literal sense; to weet, that be∣cause one of thy sinnes was fulnes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of bread, we hold it no sinne to be full of drinke. I cannot with methode pro∣ceed in this confusiō of wic∣kednes; nor with order, in that wher<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n is so much disor∣der. My pen, following my hearts motiō, trembleth, the paper waxeth wan, &amp; pale, &amp; the inke putteth on melan∣cholies sad hewe, when <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> go about to relate, that in the mouthes of our youth, <HI>Talas∣sio</HI> becomes a watch-word. And to put fier to this quick kindling fewell our poets haue put-to their helping
<PB N="13" REF="17"/>
hands: who therefore are rightly taxed by that last, &amp; euerlasting Worthie of the French, diuine <HI>du Bartas.</HI></P>
<LG>
<L>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u te regretter oy la perte de leur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ans,</L>
<L>Si par ces vers pipeurs leur muse trop d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>serte</L>
<L>Se perdant, ne tra not<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> des auditeurs la perte.</L>
<L>Sous les mielleus appas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s de leur doctes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>scrits,</L>
<L>Ils cachent le venin, q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e lesieunes esprits</L>
<L>Aualent a longs traicts, et du vin <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'amour yvres.</L>
<L>Leur mauuais estomach aime les mauvais viures.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>In English thus.</HEAD>
<L>Yet would I grieue their losse of time the lesse,</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="18"/>
If by their guilefull verse their too much Art</L>
<L>Made not their hearers share with them a part.</L>
<L>The sugred baits of those their learned writs,</L>
<L>Due shroude that poyson which the younger wits,</L>
<L>Quaffe downwith breathless draughtes, &amp; loues hot wine</L>
<L>(Making them homage do at Bacchus shrine)</L>
<L>Distempereth so their sto∣machs, that they feed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>On such ill meates as no good humours breed.</L>
</LG>
<P>But belike our Poets think by disguising their lasciui∣ousnesse, vnder a veile of
<PB N="15" REF="18"/>
smooth running words, to take awaie not onelie the in∣quination, but the very es∣sence of it; which they can∣not doe. For, as whether a man writeth with a coale, with chaulke, or inke, it is neuerthelesse writing: So is vice vice, vnder what words soeuer it be conueied. And these men, saith Scaliger, call<NOTE PLACE="marg">I Scalig. lib. 1. po∣etic. cap. 2</NOTE> vpon Phoebus, Iupiter, Pal∣las, together with the Muses, and inuoke diuels in stead of the true God. And the same Scaliger dooth reprehend<NOTE PLACE="marg">Scal. lib. 6. poetic. pa. 800. 801.</NOTE> Bembus▪ because in a certain verse which he made, he cal∣led Iesus Christ, Heroa. That Bembus is also censured by
<PB N="16" REF="19"/>
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lip. cent. Epist. 5<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> I. Lipsius. <HI>Ipse deus rarò in stilo, aut animo, sed prisco ritu, dij immortales: id{que} in se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ijs maximè sententijs, aut rebus. GOD himselfe,</HI> saith Lipsius, <HI>is seldome in his stile, mouth, or minde; but ac∣cording to the ancient rights of speech,</HI> the immortall gods: <HI>and this doth he in his most serious sentences.</HI> If for everie idle, for euery vnad∣uised word wee shall gine ac∣count, what shall we answer for premeditated sin? ouer which the heart a long time sitteth ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ering as if it were vnwilling to hatch so vgly a monster. To thinke euill, is a sin; &amp; that mortal: to speak
<PB N="17" REF="19"/>
euill, is yet a greater: but to write euill, is in it selfe both matchlesse, and namelesse; no word being fit to express so vnfit a worke. O that so foule a matter should be left to posteritie in so faire cha∣racters! or that a man should with his owne hand write a confession, to condemne his own heart! What should I say, or rather what should I not saie in so hopelesse, so haplesse a case? onelie this then I will saie, that for shame men should haue som feeling, some remorse in e∣ternising their owne shame, as also consider that their bodies, nay the faire frame
<PB N="18" REF="20"/>
of this spacious Rounde, shall be subiect to ruine: on∣lie the soule, and her actions are eternall. For, the soule being eternall, the actions proceeding from her, parti∣cipate of the same eternity. The bodie, being spotted, is quickly mundified: but the soule, once branded with in∣famy, euer keeps her mark, and neuer becommeth im∣maculate. O dangerous age! thou seducest many to er∣rour; but reducest none to truth: thou causest manie to fall; but raisest vp none. And indeede, how should they stand firme, when their foot∣ting is so slipperie? How
<PB N="19" REF="20"/>
should they resolue, when euerie thing giues them oc∣casion of doubt? What shal a man decree to bee truth, when hee shall see Pontius Pilate washing his handes, but not his heart? Caiphas, pretending blasphemie, to rent his garments? the new Scribes and Pharisies crying<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 27 24</NOTE> out to Iesus, master thou art good, though they thinke him to bee most had? Si∣mon Iudas selling, Simon Magus buying GOD for money? holding a trinitie of benefices in vnitie of person: and these three are, for the most part, foure. Those who should tell Israell of her sins,
<PB N="20" REF="21"/>
and Iuda of her transgressi∣ons, doe now sooth her vp in her iniquitie; nay, flatter the dead to please the liuing: in so much that <HI>Durus de Pascalo</HI> makes it one of his precepts, that the courtier ought to giue credit neither to funerall sermons, nor to Gallobelgicus, or other such idle fablers. I must confesse that the worde <HI>lye</HI> is vnde∣cent, to giue to a minister; but verie aptly applyed to Gallobelgicus, who lyeth of set purpose, and telleth truth at aduenture. Sure I am, he hath not learned, or (if lear∣ned) not practised that first, and chiefest lawe of a lawe∣full
<PB N="21" REF="21"/>
historian, which is, <HI>Vt ne quid falsi audeat, nequid veri dicere non audeat.</HI> But to my purpose, it were to be wish∣ed, that this abuse of prea∣ching might bee reformed; that so the laudable vse of it, might bee with the more applause, and profit continued. Mercy should be in the Preachers mouth, not flatterie: he should pro∣nounce pardon to others (not craue it from others) and pronounce (nay, de∣nounce) vengeance against those who renounce the or∣dained meanes of their sal∣uation. Flattery, thou base, creeping sinne, thou seducer
<PB N="22" REF="22"/>
of Princes, thou obseruer of noddes, thou impudencie clad in modesty, thou faw∣ning diuell, when shall thy dominion haue an ende? I would my ende might pro∣cure thine. But what should I talke of thine ende, who art now in thy prime? We<NOTE PLACE="marg">Athenaeus lib. 6</NOTE> haue our Clisophi, who will imitate Philip whether hee halt in minde, or in bodie: neither want we Courtiers, who though they see that<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ibidem.</NOTE> Dionisius cannot see, yet they counterfait the like in∣firmity.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ann<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l. li. 1</NOTE> <HI>Temporibus{que} Au∣gusti dicendis</HI> (they bee the words of Tacitus) <HI>non de∣fuere decora ingenia, do∣nec</HI>
<PB N="23" REF="22"/>
<HI>gliscente adulatione de∣terrerentur. Neither wanted there,</HI> saith he, <HI>worthy, and singular wits to deliuer</HI> Au∣gustus <HI>exploits, vntill they were by the ouerswarming of flatterers vtterly discoura∣ged.</HI> But what base meanes will not ambition vse, where the proposed end is honour? with her there is no impos∣sibilitie, no difficultie: with her, things to come are as present: and what shee as∣pires to, she makes no doubt to attaine to. Thou mother of discontent, thou God∣desse of m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tabilitie, dwell still in the Courts of Prin∣ces; but insinuate not thy
<PB N="24" REF="23"/>
selfe into the hearts of Pro∣phets; for, if they be tainted, all the worlde is deceiued. Their tongues perswade, where force cannot auaile: if in a bad cause, then mis∣chiefe followeth. From their tongues, for the most part, Princes frame their actions: so that the former being bad, the latter are worse▪ in as much as a bad deede out∣strippeth a bad word. Yet shal they one daie answere, both for the word, &amp; deed, of which they were procu∣rers. Is it possible that a man should looke vp to heauen, &amp; not thinke who gouernes earth, and heauen? or who
<PB N="25" REF="23"/>
is so foolish, as to thinke that God wil answere an eye of dissimulatiō with the eye of mercie? No, no: a true God cannot awaie with a false heart. Lord, that a man should think with all his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣ratory, to perswade others <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that which hee cannot per∣swade himselfe to▪ or who is such an idiot, as to thinke to haue an army well gouer∣ned or guided, without a good conductor? Why, this is meere, and absurde equi∣uocation: as for example; I say to another, Follow me: he straight obeyes; when forthwith I tell him, that he must no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> trace my steps, but
<PB N="26" REF="24"/>
my words. These men are worse then the Scribes, and<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 23. 3</NOTE> Pharisies, whom Christre∣prehended for saying, and not doing: for, these men doe not onely saie and not doe, but also doe and not say; as being indeede asha∣med to saie what they doe. All other things they know: onelie what is most worthie to be knowen, they knowe not; which is, to knowe themselues. Yet how is it possible they should not know themselues, since they know that God knoweth &amp; searcheth both the heart, and reines? though some of them, I feare, would be con∣tent
<PB N="27" REF="24"/>
that God should search their hearts, so hee would lett their reines alone. Oh prophanenesse! that the same hand which lifteth vp the Cupp in the Communi∣on, should lift vp pot after pot in an Alehouse; and of∣fer more sacrifice to Bac∣chus, then to Iehoua: a vice which whosoeuer giues him selfe ouer to, God giues him ouer to execute the inuenti∣ons of a dist<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>bed Intellect. Which I think the Lowe∣country men allude to, in calling their strongest beere <HI>double Pharaoh;</HI> their strong beere, in a lower degree, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Phar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</HI> and their
<PB N="28" REF="25"/>
small beere <HI>Israel;</HI> intima∣ting thereby that the stron∣ger the beere is, the more it makes a man to rebell a∣gainst God; and the smaller it is, the more it leaues the soule to her selfe, and ren∣ders her freer from the sen∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ualitie of the bodie, and makes a true child of Israell. Looke how a passenger in a thicke darke mist is sad, as doubtfull which waie to turn: euen so Reason being blinded by the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> wines hot vapo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> pensiue, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> knowing whether she should <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ncline to vice, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> till at length shee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="29" REF="25"/>
from vertue to vice. I haue heard a reuerend english Di∣uine, often compare a drunk arde to <HI>Mare mortu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m:</HI> for, as no fish by report can liue in the one; so no vertue in the other. Amongst the ve∣ry<NOTE PLACE="marg">In Alcor. Turc. pag. 191.</NOTE> Turkes, this vice is so o∣dious, that they reward it in whomesoeuer they finde it with 8o. stripes, making it the most detestable sinne of all, next to adultery; to which, they a lot a hundred stripes. If heathen people do this (whom errour leades hood-winked in ignorance, or rather ignorance in er∣rour) what should a Christi∣an doe? why should not hee
<PB N="30" REF="26"/>
leade a good, and sober life, whose name is written in the booke of life? But (alas!) for want of consideration this is not looked into. Vp∣on this vice depend three o∣ther (as vgly seruants vpon a deformed master) to wit, Quarelling, Whooring, and Swearing. The first of which hath more by tongue, then sworde, purchased to it selfe the name of valour; which indeeds is no neerer to va∣lour, then phrensie to wise∣dome. True valour biddeth a man fight <HI>pro patria, et pa∣tre patriae;</HI> this bastarde cou∣rage incites a man to fight <HI>cum fratre, cum patre:</HI> the
<PB N="31" REF="26"/>
former perswadeth a man to be carefull not onelie that he take no iniury, but (euen re∣ligious) that he doe none; the latter saith, that hee is worthy of iniury, that offers none. The one saith, Fight being prouoked; the other sayes, Prouoke to fight. And therefore I think, that Sene∣ca spake rather out of the greatnesse of his mind, then the depth of his wisedome, when he defined fortitude, to bee <HI>Scientia periculorum</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Sen. de benef. li. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cap. 34.</NOTE> <HI>repellendorum, excipiendo∣rum, prouocandorum:</HI> that is, <HI>a Science of repelling, of receiuing, and prouoking dangers.</HI> The latter of which
<PB N="32" REF="27"/>
is false; seeing there is no man wisely valiant, who will not rather inuoke helpe a∣gainst danger, then prouoke it.</P>
<P>Is it not a lamentable case, to see two men christ∣ned with one Baptisme, bought with one redempti∣on, for whom the blood of Christ was indifferent∣lie shedde, vppon euerye slight, and light occasion, to shedde the bloud one of another? Or is it not a harde case, for one that pro∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esseth the name of Christ Iesus, to digge for honour in the heart of a Christian▪ And this forsooth they do
<PB N="33" REF="27"/>
for reputation. What ble∣mish is it to my reputation to denye that in sobrietie, which I affirmed in drunk∣ennes? that is, to recall that as a man, which I spake as a beast? Yet these roaring gentlemen, whatsoeuer they speake, be it neuer so bad, will make it good. Surelie, I am of opiniō, that the word <HI>duel,</HI> is deriued from the French word <HI>dueil,</HI> by rea∣son that it makes so manie parents mourne for the vn∣timely death of their chil∣dren, and one friend la∣ment the decease of another. But by the way, I will giue this caution, that no man
<PB N="34" REF="28"/>
misconstrue mee, and thinke that I perswade men to cowardise: for, I am so farre from that, that I thinke a cowarde to be the basest of<NOTE PLACE="marg">A Coward who?</NOTE> all creatures: &amp; A Coward I call him, who slauishlie feareth any thing but God. For, if my Prince allow me combate, vpon dishonoura∣ble imputation of treason, and I be drawen into the lifts with a chaine of foul, dis∣gracefull words linked toge∣ther, which will so sticke to my Familie, &amp; Race, that no time can raze them out; the iniurie here becommeth more then priuate, (wherof only, I take it, Christ speaks,
<PB N="35" REF="28"/>
when he saieth; <HI>He that gi∣ueth</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 5. 39.</NOTE> <HI>thee a boxe on the one care, turne to him the other</HI> &amp;c.) For, in this case the iniurie is publike, and not mineowne: and therefore I say, standing vppon these tearmes, God refuse mee, if I refuse any man. Where∣fore I could not, without much applause, reade that <HI>Motto</HI> in the Scottish armes; <HI>In defence.</HI> For, if a man be driuen to maintaine his ho∣nour, and cleare his wrong∣ed name from perpetuall in∣famy; let him then with an vndaunted spirit, and ala∣crity of heart sing the Psalm of Dauid, <HI>If ten thousand</HI>
<PB N="36" REF="29"/>
<HI>hemme me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nde about, yet will I not feare,</HI> &amp;c. resting confident in this, that hee hath God, and so good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cause on his side. For, this infamie neuer leaues a man: insomuch that when his flesh forsaketh his bones, this cleaues fast to them, and the Sexton, digging vp his scull, saith, This was the head of a Traitour, &amp; a Co∣warde. But for a frowne, the trippe of the tongue, or the slip of a word, to quar∣rell, dominere, and sweare oathes, <HI>Que pulmo anima</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ins.</NOTE> <HI>pralarg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s anhelet,</HI> this is far from valour: for, valour is an enemie to no vertue; this
<PB N="37" REF="29"/>
to euery vertue, and a friend to all vice. Neither can I be indueed otherwise to be∣lieue, but that there are ma∣ny gentlemen, whose mo∣dest, ingenuous faces are free from scouls, and fur∣rowes of wrath; in whose hearts, notwithstanding, maiestical magnanimitie sit∣teth richlier clad, then in those of your roaring, angry boyes of London; and per∣aduenture would giue them iust cause both to roare, and houl too. The second daugh∣ter to drunkennes is whoo∣ring, the deflourer of many a virgin, and defiler of many a wife; a sinne which most
<PB N="38" REF="30"/>
men are addicted to by na∣ture, and fewest freed from by grace. For though God hath separated the male frō the female, and disioyned them; yet, I know not how, they will still desire a con∣iunction. The Cedars of Libanus haue fallen this way: the Patriarehs, Pro∣phets, Fathers, and our fore∣fathers haue here gone a∣stray. Many a Saint hath fal∣len at the feet of these saints, and hath adored their ador∣ned beautie. Yet, for men to prostrate their bodies to euerie dung-hill, and sinke into euerie sink-hole, was neuer so common, as in
<PB N="39" REF="30"/>
these later licentious times; wherein money can buy af∣fection, Beautie offering her selfe to hire. But, to keepe yout seruant brisk, and spruse, that the towne maie take notice of him, for a neate, compleate gentle∣man; and to feede vpon the answerable report the world giues of him; tush, this is no sinne. No no: it is no offence at all to allow him so much for euerie course; so causing him to spend flesh for siluer, till he become so lank, and leane, that his legs are scarce able to support their late portly young master; going still, as if hee were sitting
<PB N="40" REF="31"/>
(occasioned through the imbecillitie of his hamme∣strings) and so dry, that a marrow-bone-man, if hee should boile his bones, could scarce get out two droppes of moisture: his eyes so hollow, that they runne backe to salute his memory, least she should forget them▪ and his cheekes, denting∣in, as if he were still sucking at a bottle. And now my braue slaue beeing a neigh∣bour to death, beginneth to find, that all this while he hath mistaken, and worship∣ped a false deity, for a true: and that therefore (though ceasing, through weaknes,
<PB N="41" REF="31"/>
to burne here in lust) hee shal euer burne in neuer con∣suming fire. Where is his mistresse now? whose prai∣ses should bee written with pennes of Angels wings; whose drinke should bee Nectar, and Ambrosia. Hee now must leaue her behinde him, common to men, that shall one day bee common to diuels. It breedeth asto∣nishment in mee to heare a man stile a woman, <HI>Diuine creature of a heauenlie fea∣ture, goddess of my thoughts, natures vtter most indeuour,</HI> &amp;c. whose body he know∣eth to bee compos'd of pu∣trefaction, and shall one day
<PB N="42" REF="32"/>
come to that degree of rot∣tennels, that (as she now, in the nostri's of God) it shall stink in the nostrils both of men, and beastes. Reason and Religion teach a man (as her remembrancer) thus to court his Mistress: <HI>Faire Queene of dust and durt, will it please your euery∣hower-decaying maiestie, af∣ter some fewe yeares, or mo∣neths, or daies, to haue th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se star-shining eyes of yours ea∣ten out with wormes, and the holes become cages for cankers? when your delicate, (mooth body shall be enfolded in earths rugged armes; and your soft, swelling, moist,</HI>
<PB N="43" REF="32"/>
<HI>ruby lippes be kissed by her mouldy mouth; whē your pure red, and white, shall be tur∣ned into poore browne, and blacke; and that face which hath driuen so many into con∣sumptions, shall it selfe bee consumed to nothing.</HI> Yet, for all this, our young gen∣tlemen will not forbeare their amorous profane loue∣discourses; but yeelde as much honour to women, as to their Maker. These men are rightly taxed by a late writer, where he saith, <HI>Quo∣rum sermonis venus ipsa Ve∣nus.</HI> Reason, thou bright star which directest the wise man to the god of wisedom,
<PB N="44" REF="33"/>
thou eye of the soule, why dost thou suppress thy clear∣shining beames, and leauest the soule of man in darknes. Wert thou truelie mistress of the minde, thou wouldest neuer suffer a commandresse of elaie and clods, to subdue and conquer it. For, take this for an infallible positi∣on, that <HI>Sinne neuer enters the will of man, till defect his reason.</HI> Mens liues, toge∣ther with the states of their soules, now-adaies, depend vpon the voice of a woman: and they are more penitent for one duty omitted to∣wards her, then for a thou∣sand offences committed a∣gainst
<PB N="45" REF="33"/>
God. For the one they craue mercie: for the other they care not, but mock at iustice. <HI>Mors, et vita,</HI> saith Salomon, <HI>in manibus lin∣guae: death, and life,</HI> saith he, <HI>are in the hands of the tongue.</HI> Surely, saye these doating doltes, Salomon in this place m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th the tongue of a womā. O stupi∣dity of man! to come at the becke of a woman, stoop at her frownes, hold his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rom <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ence <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> those <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/>
<PB N="46" REF="34"/>
For the first, they (finding through their daily discourse with men, that their words are esteemed Oracles, nay, articles of faith) do challenge to themselues such a free∣dome of speach, as to vtter that without shame, which the standers-by are both ashamed &amp; abashed to hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. You shall see a wench, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thirteene, haue more au<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣city then a man, at thirtie, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him to the encounter, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>thes with him by the douzen. They haue so little grace, that they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> it a great disgrace to blush▪ and that which in those for∣mor, purer times was the
<PB N="47" REF="34"/>
badge of modesty, is now thought to bee the onely marke to knowe a foole by. Besides this, there is a lasci∣uious impudency, or rather vndecency, borne and bred in this our natiue soil, which no other Nation is acquain∣ted with; I meane, a wanton sport in publike, betweene man, and wife. Let mee perish, if more soules of our youth perish any other way; then this. For, there are but two estates of men: the one married, the other vnmarri∣ed▪ the one bound, the other free: so that the one cannot abuse his owne calling, with∣out giuing the other occasi∣on
<PB N="48" REF="35"/>
on to transgresse in his. But whether this kissing, and lap-dalliance be through the default of the husband, or the wife, it is a great offence in either. It pleaseth not me, though spoken by an Empe∣rour, <HI>Giue me leaue by the lust of others, to exercise mine owne;</HI> though a witty, yet a wicked speech. Wife is not onelie a name of plea∣sure, but of honour: though our men cannot discerne this; but rather answere with Aristippus, who being tolde that Lais loued him not; <HI>no more,</HI> saith he, <HI>doth <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> nor fish, and yet I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be vvithout them.</HI> A true
<PB N="49" REF="35"/>
beast, respecting more the sensuall pleasure, and appe∣tite of the body, then the harmonie, and vnion of the minde. A man ought not to imbrace his wife, without a flattering kinde of s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>i∣tie: for, this publike billing sheweth the way, to vnex∣perienced youth, to com∣mit riot in priuate. And Cato accused one before the Senate, <HI>for that he had kis∣sed his wife, before his neigh∣bours daughter:</HI> A short, yet wise speech and of a hidden vse. Neither by this often, and open smacking is shame onelie diminished; but by little, and little chastitie
<PB N="50" REF="36"/>
abolished. The verie Ele∣phāts crie-out against them; <HI>who,</HI> as Pliny writeth, <HI>make not the least loue one to ano∣ther, except they be couered with boughes.</HI> Wherefore when the scripture saith,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 2. 24</NOTE> <HI>Therefore shall a man leaue his father, and his mother, and shall cleaue to his wife, and they shall bee one flesh;</HI> the literall and sensuall sense is not here to bee followed: for, beasts can cleaue to one another in this obscene ma∣ner, as well as man and wife. But, if the woman be culpa∣ble in this behalfe, it is so much the more intollera∣ble, by how much (of the
<PB N="51" REF="36"/>
twaine) shee should bee the more shamefaste. She ought euer to prize a bashful coun∣tenaunce, before a paynted one that cannot blush: and should be so farre from prof∣fering these vnseemely loue-trickes; as rather, at the least lewde looke, or touch, to present the beholders eyes, with modesties red badge, in waie of mislike. To the same ende did the Romanes of olde, carrie before the married couple, fier, and water (the former represen∣ting the man; the later, the woman) what else signifying, then that the woman should expect till heate bee infused
<PB N="52" REF="37"/>
into her by her husband? it being as much against the nature of an honest spouse, as of the coldest water, to boile of her selfe; and on the contrarie side, that the bridegroome should distill warmth into his water, and heate it, but not ouer-heate it. The bashfull, and well disposed wife should repose her selfe on her pallet, and there with emulation con∣template that answer of the Lacedemonian lasse, who being asked in the morning by her friend, whether, or no, in the night she had in∣folded her husband in her armes, replied; <HI>Good words,</HI>
<PB N="53" REF="37"/>
<HI>good man: not I him, but he me.</HI> Oh diuine song of a refi∣ned creature! whose tongue vnlocked the treasure of her hearts chastiric. The next vice in women is pride, ari∣sing from the lauish, and lasciuious praises of men; which, women knowing too well how to applie to themselues, becom so proud that they scorne earth, and are scorned by heauen. <HI>For</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prou: 16</NOTE> <HI>euery one that is proude in heart, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> abhomination to the Lord.</HI> And in another place<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prou. 15 24▪</NOTE> it is said, <HI>The Lord will de∣stroy the house of the proude.</HI> But hearken, you miserable vnfortunate Dames, to that
<PB N="54" REF="38"/>
which the Lord saith in the third of Esay: <HI>Because the daughters of Sion are hautie, and walk with stretched-out necks, and with wandering eyes, walking, and minsing as they goe, and make a tink∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing with their feete; there∣fore shall the heads of the daughters of Sion be balde, and the Lord shall discouer their secret parts. In that day shall the Lord take-away the ornament of the slippers, and the calls, and the round tiers, the sweete balls, and the bracelets, and the bonets, the tires of the head, and the slops, the headbands and the tablets, the eare-rings, the</HI>
<PB N="55" REF="38"/>
<HI>rings, and the mufflers, the costly apparel, and the veiles, and the wimples, and the crisping pinnes, and the glasses, and the fine linnen, and the hoodes, and the lawnes; and in stead of sweet sauour, there shall be stink; &amp; in stead of a girdle, a rent, and in stead of dressing of the haire, baldenesse: and in stead of a stomacher, a girdle of sackecloth; and burning, in stead of beauty. Then shall her gates mourne, &amp; lament; and she being desolate shall sitte vppon the ground.</HI> A∣mongst these menaces of GOD, some haue already lighted vpon our women,
<PB N="56" REF="39"/>
as baldenesse, and burning; many of our men gaining burning in stead of beautie: and the restare as yet to fall; whose weight will bee so heauie, as that it will crush these tender offenders. O! I could lash pride, and bee bitter towards these sweets, but that I knowe my words would goe into winde, and be rather scoffed at, then re∣garded. I could tell them of setting borrowed teeth into their pale, bloudless gums; how they ouerlaie yellowe with white, in so much that in an howres space they will make a man belieue that the yellowe Iaundies is turned
<PB N="57" REF="39"/>
into the greene sickenesse; how they turne their blacke bloud <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> into faire crimson, and set that Baude, Art, to bedaube Nature. I could tel them also of their prodi∣galitie in apparell, but that it concerneth not all in ge∣nerall, but onely some in particular. Honour, as of her selfe shee is bright, and glorious; so wee allow her like raiment correspondent to her splendour, to the end that shee may be discerned from the base vulgar. But that euerye blurt (who is only a gentlewoman of two moneths standing) should be clad like a Queene; this
<PB N="58" REF="40"/>
(I thinke) is more then any wise man will yeeld to. An∣other kinde of base pride hath possessed our womē, so that they think a man poor in spirit, that is not rich in cloathing. Bring me a gen∣tleman of a great, far-famed family, whose mightie an∣cestours haue spent their bloud to crowne their bloud with vertues diademe, and left behinde them trium∣phant trophees of their vn∣controuled greatnes: and, to associate this Pirocles, bring mee a Dametas, who hath of late extracted genti∣lity out of dung; if this foist be more fine then the for∣mer,
<PB N="59" REF="40"/>
his entertainement shal bee rich, and sumptuous, the others poore and beg∣gerly. But this is not one∣lie a fault in this frailer sexe, but also in men of eminen∣cy; who though they should be the eyes of our Iland, yet their sight is dimmed with this foggy mist. If one man excell another as farre in height of knowledge, as hea∣uen earth in distance; yet hee that is the best able in purse shall be iudged worthiest of preferment, and imploy∣ment. Seneca had lied in his throate if he had saide in our time, <HI>Nemo sapientiam pau∣pertate damnauit:</HI> for, as
<PB N="60" REF="41"/>
the world goes now, the in∣version would be most true, <HI>Quiuis sapientiam opulentia approba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it.</HI> Pouerty, thou veile of wisedome, curbe to the minde, thou common enemie to vertue, through thee Natures greatest gifts passe vnrespected, and the best deserts vnrewarded. How many braue spirits <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urke, and become pliable to wretched seruitude, and all for want of meanes to declare their meaning? I haue seene a decayed mer∣chant put-on the spurs of him who in times past made clean his shooes▪ &amp; man him whose master hee was once:
<PB N="61" REF="41"/>
but he did it not without an eye of indignation. Why, pouertie fashioneth a man to any thing; <HI>Nobilium fami∣liarum</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Tacit. An∣nal. lib. 14.</NOTE> <HI>posteros egestate ve∣nales in seenam de duxit,</HI> saith Tacitus. Wherefore I can∣not but meruaile at the sot∣tishnesse of the Papists, who teach men to vow pouertie: which in it selfe is euill, as Beckermane a late dutch writer very wittilie proueth against the Stoickes; where he saith, that a free prae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣lection, is not but of good, nor a free shunning but of euil. If then they grant, saith hee (as indeede they doe) that health, riches, libertie
<PB N="62" REF="42"/>
are to be chosen, and (on the contrary) diseases, pouertie, griefe to bee auoided; they yeeld perforce, these to bee bad, those to be good. For my part, would riches come for the vowing, it should be the first vow I would make, and bless God for them as blessings bestow'd vpon the blessed; the want of them being as a punishment laied vppon man to bring him vnto God, and to the know∣ledge of himselfe: which if a man do attain-to in pros∣peritie, what needeth humi∣liation? O penury! through thy perswasions, kings think Cottages Kingdomes, and
<PB N="63" REF="42"/>
subiect themselues to their owne subiects. Thou mon∣ster, thou cunning Artist, thou transformer of men (that of a gentleman, canst make a scullian, of a prince a pesant) craule along with plebeians; but mount not the backe of vnsaddled ho∣nour, nor goe about to iade the generous: for, if thou doest hee will fling thee, though himselfe lye by it. Thus haue I assaied to swim against the current of swift, vnstaied humors: and if my labour may amend others, it shall sufficientlie commende itselfe. Yet, whether it do, or doe not, I must and will
<PB N="64" REF="43"/>
write, because my spleene is swollen. To this purpose<NOTE PLACE="marg">Sen. Epist. 29.</NOTE> speaketh Seneca, <HI>Quare ver∣bis parcam? gratuita sunt. Non possam scire an eiprofi∣turus sim, quem admoneo: illud scio, alicui me profitu∣rum, si multos admonuero. Spargenda est manus. Non potest fieri vt non aliquando succedat, multa tentanti Why should I spare wordes?</HI> saith he. <HI>I know not whether, or no, I shal profit him to whom I write: this I am sure of, that in warning many, I shall doe good to some. Much happe∣neth to him that trieth much and if this hand sprinkle, it cannot bee but other hands</HI>
<PB N="65" REF="43"/>
<HI>will gleane.</HI> By whose coun∣sell being hartned I will pro∣ceede, &amp; scourge the hard∣hearted world, and so I de∣scend to womens third frail∣tie, to weet, losse of chastiti∣tie. A losse, said I? a losse to her that loseth it, and a losse to him that gaines it. For, when a man hath with much losse of time, expense of mony, neglect of friends, chased this tame game, and made a preye of it; then, I saie, satietie of one makes him loue varietie of all, and he thinkes her easie to be lost who is no harder to bee wonne. O what seas of vne∣quall passions keepe their
<PB N="66" REF="44"/>
dailie ebbe, and flow in him? To-day hee coueteth what to-morrow he loatheth: his minde is with a little thing erected, with a less deiected: hee pursueth that with a great desire, which once ob∣tained hee abandons with a greater: one and the same thing in one, and the selfe same houre bringeth him content, and discontent: he laughs, he weeps, hee pines, hee repines, not knowing (himselfe) why. At last, he learneth, that praise is the Pandar to lust; and therefore with mellifluous speeches charmes her listning eares: and the fortresse of her
<PB N="67" REF="44"/>
eares being wonne, the bul∣warke of her heart is con∣quered. And now he hath her, hee cannot keepe her long, hee must haue sharers; for, her eares are open to flattery: and who knowes not, that complement is a sure friend to copulation? His onelie course therefore would be, to change his mis∣tresse into a master, <HI>who is</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Heb. 13. 8</NOTE> <HI>yesterday, to-day, &amp; the same for euer.</HI> But the best iest is, that some of our young no∣vices, our guls passiue, are so cheated, as that they spend the best remainder of their daies in courting mer∣cenary whoores, and make
<PB N="68" REF="45"/>
a long sute before they can obtaine. It is not onely flesh will make one of these haukes stoope to the lure; but she must haue siluer too: which, my young practician not being acquainted with, maketh his request in vaine. When hee speakes of loue, she lookes so strangely as if shee heard a miracle, swea∣ring shee neuer as yet sawe any man who could gaine the least corner of her heart. He belieues all; and (like a kinde natured man) presents her with rich gifts, desiring no gift from her but her selfe: which she (with a pit∣tifull looke) condescends
<PB N="69" REF="45"/>
to, exclaiming against For∣tune for subduing her to man; when God he knowes shee hath beene as common as a <HI>Retraict.</HI> And now my plaine, downe-right squire (who neuer before was fur∣ther then his fathers winde∣mill) in taking is taken him∣selfe with a hooke that will not easily let him goe; and many a land-knaue, and sea∣gull shall feede vpon the re∣uenewes of his purse, and he shall be called patron till all his patrimonie bee spent. <HI>Their soule dieth in youth,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iob. 36. 14.</NOTE> saith Iob, <HI>and their life a∣mong the whooremongers.</HI> But it were good heere to
<PB N="70" REF="46"/>
spurre a question, and aske whether a whoore hiring, or hired, is the more detest∣able in the sight of God?<NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 23. 18.</NOTE> The scripture determines, and iudgeth, that a woman, taking money for prostitu∣ting her body to men, is in∣famous;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezech. 16. 33.</NOTE> but she that giueth money to enioye her louer, is most infamous of all o∣thers. All are abhominable before the Lord: and there∣fore Salomon in his Pro∣uerbes saith, <HI>that the mouth of a strange woman, or an harlot, is as a deepe pit: hee</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prou. 22. 14.</NOTE> <HI>that is a detestation to the Lord shall fall therein.</HI> And in another place, hee saith;
<PB N="71" REF="46"/>
<HI>A whoore is as a deepe</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prou. 23. 17.</NOTE> <HI>ditch, and a narrowe pit.</HI> Noting thereby, that if a man be once in with an har∣lot, hee shall as hardly get out againe, as a man that is plunged into a very deepe, and narrowe pit, where he can hardlie stirre himselfe. The same Salomon, in the booke of Ecclesiastes, yeel∣deth vs the reason heereof; namely, because shee is as nets, snares, &amp; bands; where if a man be once in, he is fast enough for getting out. <HI>I finde,</HI> saith he, <HI>more bitter then death, the woman, whose heart is as nets, and snares, and her hands as bands: hee</HI>
<PB N="72" REF="47"/>
<HI>that is good before God, shall be deliuered from her; but the sinner shall be taken by her.</HI> O that flesh, and bloud would listen to the aduise of the spirite, and follow the counsell of the wise man!<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prou. 26. 5</NOTE> <HI>Desire not,</HI> saith he, <HI>her beau∣tie in thine heart; neither let her eye-lids catch thee: for, by a who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rish woman a man is brought to a morsell of bread: and the adultresse hanteth for life which is pre∣tious.</HI> Again he saith; <HI>Albeit the lippes of an harlot droppe as an hony combe, and the roofe of her mouth be softer then oyle; yet her latter end is bitter as wormewood, and</HI>
<PB N="73" REF="47"/>
<HI>as sharpe as a two-edged sword.</HI> Chastitie, art thou fledde from Christians to Pagans? Virginity (thou, in whom Antiquity did glo∣rie) canst thou finde no mo∣derne person worthy thy presence? The ancients ho∣noured the very title of vir∣gine, so much, that they thought <HI>virgo</HI> to be named <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> virtute:</HI> that as Vertue is vnspotted; so Virginitie should bee vncorrupted. They all concurred in ap∣plause of this estate: but they differed in degrees of praise; some of them think∣ing <HI>virgo</HI> to bee deriued <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>vir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI> because they hauing
<PB N="74" REF="48"/>
passed their tender yeeres, desire the societie of man. Others thought <HI>virgo</HI> to be so nominated <HI>a vigore,</HI> be∣cause they flourish most in those yeeres. Others dedu∣ced <HI>virgo à virga:</HI> not be∣cause they are scourges to men; but they called them so <HI>ab atate viridiori:</HI> because that as greennesse is a token of the spring; so those green, tender yeeres are markes of virginity. Some compared a virgin to a Lilly: the simili∣tude was this; they thought the six leaues of the Lillie did represent the heart and the fiue senses in a virgin, which (like the former six)
<PB N="75" REF="48"/>
should be kept fresh, hauing no sauour of euill: and that as those leaues are spread a∣broade; so maiden-actions should be open: not close, nor secret; but secure, as a∣ble to indure the most sear∣ching eye. How manie plantes, riuers, springs, temples, cities did they consecrate to the name <HI>Vir∣gine,</HI> and gaue them that name! They thought the same difference to bee be∣tween matrimonie, and vir∣ginity, that is betwixt to sin, and not to sinne, good, and better. And therefore Hie∣rome in his exposition of the Psal. <HI>Homines et iumen∣ta</HI>
<PB N="76" REF="49"/>
<HI>saluabis domine; Per ho∣mines, inquit, intelliguntur solae virgines, per iumenta</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Albert. Mag. de mulier. fort.</NOTE> <HI>reliqui omnes.</HI> Him followes Albertus Magnus. <HI>Conti∣nentia, inquit, habet fruc∣tum triplicem: scilicet, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en∣tesim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m in virginibus, sex∣agesimum in viduis, et tri∣cesimum in coniugatis. Con∣tinence,</HI> saith he, <HI>hath a three∣folde degree, or condition: i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> virgins it bringeth forth a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hundred, in widdowes threescore, and in the wed∣ded thirtie.</HI> Scripture run∣neth cleane, and cleare on our side: which the passages following demonstrate. 1. Corinthians, 7. 1. Kings 2.
<PB N="77" REF="49"/>
Wisedome the 3. Matth. 19. Esay 56. Syrach. 26. But, a∣mongst all these places, this one in the Reuelatiō is most<NOTE PLACE="marg">Reuel. 14.</NOTE> of all to be noted. <HI>And they sung as it were a new song before the throne, and before the foure beasts, and the el∣ders: and no man could learn that song, but the hundreth, forty, and foure thousand which were bought from the earth. These are they which are not defiled with women, for they are virgins: these followe the Lambe wheresoe∣uer he goeth; these are bought from men, beeing the first fruits to GOD and to the Lambe. And in their mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ths</HI>
<PB N="78" REF="50"/>
<HI>was found no guile: for, they are without spot before the throne of God.</HI> These are words that would inforce any sober soule to imbrace that single, simple, and sin∣cere kinde of life, approued by God, Saints, and Angels; as beeing free from all vn∣cleannesse, and voide of all cankering cares. Yet how many now-adaies, would be ranked among virgins, who indeede are ranke whoores? how manie are courted, who deserue to be carted? Had Iob liued in our houres, he neuer should haue needed <HI>to haue made a couenant with his eyes, least</HI>
<PB N="79" REF="50" MS="y"/>
<HI>at any time they should looke</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iob. 31. 1</NOTE> <HI>vpon a maide;</HI> for, he should scarce haue found any to looke vppon. So farre is Chastitity exiled, so much is shame empaired, as that impudency and women are almost become Relatiues. And the cause of this, is vaine periured man; who, notvsing his tongue to glo∣rifie him that made it, im∣ployes it to flatter, deceiue, dissemble. And when hee hath obtained his purpose, what is his victory? That he hath seduced a woman? A hot conquest surely, to enter and ouercome a citty whose gates stand open day, and
<PB N="80" REF="51"/>
night. Yet barre I not anie man, from admiring the Creatour in the creature; nor from beholding beauty: which, as one saith, is <HI>radius di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inae pulchritudinis, a</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Castilio∣naeus, in suo Auli∣co. lib. 4</NOTE> <HI>be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e darted into man from that diuine beautie.</HI> The Platonians were so enamou∣red of this amiable goddess, that they thought beautie to bee like a circle, whose center they made goodness: and they were of opinion that as a circle cannot bee without a center, no more can a faire, and comely bo∣die be without a maiesticall mind. The Hebricians con∣found fairenesse with good∣nesse,
<PB N="81" REF="51" MS="y"/>
in calling that faire which is good, that good which is faire. And there∣fore when it is said, that Sara seemed very good in the eies of the Aegyptians, the mea∣ning of the text is that shee seemed very faire. Neither did the Graecians separate this beautifull yoke, but ioy▪ <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. August. saith,<NOTE PLACE="marg">De ciuit. 15. 100. 23.</NOTE> <HI>Consuetudo scripturae est e∣tiam speciosos corpore bonos vocare. It is an ordinary thing in the holie scripture,</HI> saith he, <HI>to call the faire of body good of minde.</HI> Colu∣mella saith, that the Bees choose the fairest, and the best formed to be their king.
<PB N="82" REF="52"/>
Pythagoras was led by beau¦tie beyond reason: so that he falsely imagined the frame of the bodie to represent the state of the minde, and that the crookednesse of the bo∣dy was a signe of a wracked conscience; so that he could not be of an vpright minde who was not vpright of bo∣dy: and therefore hee cau∣sed to bee written ouer his schoole, that no dispropor∣tioned fellow should enter there; for, he would not giue countenance to any defor∣med countenance. Which sentence of his is wiselie, and iudicially contradicted by S. Bernarde. <HI>Est, inquit, ni∣gredo</HI>
<PB N="83" REF="52"/>
<HI>quaedam foelix, quae</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Bernha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Serm. 25 super can∣ticum can∣ticorum.</NOTE> <HI>mentis candorem coniunctū habet. There is, saith he, a certaine foulenesse of com∣plexion which is accompanied with fairenesse of disposition.</HI> I, I: the gifts of the minde are able to shadowe the de∣fects of the bodie; but the perfection of the bodie is no way able to hide the imper∣fections of the minde. Al∣though I thinke obstinacie her selfe will confesse, that that of virgill is most true, <HI>Gratior est pulchro veniens è corpore virtus:</HI> Yet, as true it is, that <HI>virtus et forma rarò cōueniunt: vertue, &amp; beauty seldom shake hands.</HI> One on∣lie
<PB N="84" REF="53"/>
haue I seene (since first I could see) admirable for both; in whome they so sweetly kissed each other, as that it would make Hatred her selfe loue to see them. When I first beheld this glorious Architecture, this Natures choisest Art, I straight concluded, that hea∣uens fairest Iewell was there locked vp in earths richest cabinet. Now resteth it, after a long digression, that we examine the third pro∣perty of a drunkard, to weet Swearing. This vice, of all other, carrieth the most de∣testation with it; because it bringeth least delight of all
<PB N="85" REF="53"/>
other. For all other vices, a man may wring out some excuse from Nature, to les∣sen their greatnesse: but, this admitteth no veile at all. What a desperate case is it, for a man in mirth to sweare by that bloud, the remembraunce of which would strike sorrow to the most obdurate hearts! that bloud, I say, the losse of which gained redemption to the whole world. A good Christiā would shed teares, to thinke that that bloud was shedde, a drop whereof is able to clarifie an Ocean of disturbed sinne. Mee thinkes, relenting thoughts
<PB N="86" REF="54"/>
should wound the heart of a Christian, in naming the wounds of Christ. But, where reuerence is laied a∣side, there deuotion is cold.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 28 53.</NOTE> God saith, <HI>that if we doe not feare; and dread his glorious, and fearefull name Iehoua, he will make our plagues won∣derfull.</HI> Hee saith also by<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mal. 3. 3</NOTE> his Prophet Malachy, <HI>that he will be a swift witnesse a∣gainst</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Zach 5. 2.</NOTE> <HI>swearers.</HI> The Pro∣phet Zachary saith, <HI>that the flying booke of Gods curse and vengeance shall enter in∣to the house of the swearer, and he shall be cut off:</HI> Wee may well take vp the olde complaint of the Prophet
<PB N="87" REF="54"/>
Ieremy, who saith, <HI>that in</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 23. 20</NOTE> <HI>his time the Land did mourn because of oathes.</HI> The tongue alone of man is able to worke mans condemna∣tion, without any notorious action. And let vs consider the ingratitude of man to God. God blesseth man; man curseth God: God bles∣seth the earth to man; man blasphemeth against God, and heauen: God reuealeth himselfe to man; man reui∣leth the name of God: in a word, God made not man in vaine; man taketh Gods name in vaine. And yet these swearers, when they haue searched the very entrailes
<PB N="88" REF="55"/>
of God for an oath, they can hardly gaine beliefe, except it be from some plaine mea∣ning man, or weake woman. They may couzen all sorts of men with this their dam∣ned Art, but one; and him they cannot cheate. Lett them sweare to an vsurer, that it lyeth in his power to oblige them to him; he will reply againe, that it lyeth not in his power to doe it without an obligation: for, he will haue a gage, and yet engage them too. This man is too wise to be caught by his neighbour; and yet hee catcheth at his neighbours substance. <HI>Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etonsnes,</HI> saith
<PB N="89" REF="55"/>
Saint Paul, <HI>is the roote of all</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Tim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. 6. 10.</NOTE> <HI>euill.</HI> The same Apostle saith, <HI>that the ende of all</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Phil. 3. 19</NOTE> <HI>such as minde earthly things, is damnation.</HI> They doe not rightlie vnderstande those words of Christ, when hee saith, <HI>Though a man hath a∣boundance,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Lu. 12. 15</NOTE> <HI>yet his life con∣sisteth not in the things that he hath. Doubtlesse,</HI> saith the<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 39. 6</NOTE> Prophet Dauid, <HI>man walk∣eth in a shadowe, and disqui∣eteth himselfe in vaine: he heapeth vp riches, and can∣not tel who shal gather them.</HI> But, they haue a sufficient torment laied vpon them heere in this world: which is implied in these wordes;
<PB N="90" REF="56"/>
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccl. 5. 9</NOTE> <HI>Hee that loueth Siluer, shall not bee satisfied with siluer.</HI> Hee carkes and cares, hee hoordes and rakes-vp; yet no satietie can cloy him. He hath wealth: yet hee will scarce vse it, though to pur∣chase his owne health; but sterues his poor hide-bound carcasse, and impouerisheth his bodie to enrich his purse. He is neuer secure; hee can∣not heare the winde whistle, but he thinks it to bee the call of a thiefe; &amp; if a storme com, he straight diuines the ruine of his ship at sea, or of his house on land. But, God were not iust, if he should giue content to that consci∣ence,
<PB N="91" REF="56"/>
which makes warre a∣gainst Widdowes, and Or∣phanes, and insults ouer po∣uertie. Thou sterne-fronted, hard-hearted man, thou ter∣rour of the poore, thou that sufferest the image of God to decay when one penny of thine may repaire it, thou that lettest one of those little ones sterue for a morsell of<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 18. 10.</NOTE> bread; thou little thinkest that their Angels behold the face of their heauenly Fa∣ther, and pleade for iustice against thee vniust. The voice of the beggar beggeth for reuenge against thee: Which God will heare, and pay thee with Sulphur, whē
<PB N="92" REF="57"/>
that bodie of thine shall ren∣der-vp it selfe to neuer-con∣suming flames; &amp; thy mer∣cilesse soule (which being voide of pittie, did depriue the needie of comfort) shall be depriued of the presence of him, whose absence pos∣sesseth the soule with more horrour, then the fier can the bodye with torment. Who shall receiue then the Interest of thy money? these that laugh at thee, for kee∣ping thy coyne that they might inioie it? It is better bestowed vpon them, then vpon thee: for, they reioice in it; thou hadst not it, but it had thee. Vsurie, thou
<PB N="93" REF="57"/>
bane to manie a distressed gentleman, thou deuourer of the oppressed, thou nip∣per of mirth, thou vnplea∣sant toyle, thy sinne is so weightie, that it makes pas∣sage for it selfe, through earth into hell. Yet knowe I their common caution, with which they vse to cloake these their intolera∣ble wrongs; to weet, that a man may let out money to vse, so he giue it not <HI>in mor∣sum;</HI> when Ile be sworne they giue it <HI>in dorsum,</HI> and laye on such loade that they breake the backes of manie decayed men. Sure, it was auarice which first made
<PB N="94" REF="58"/>
theft so capitall a crime; it hauing in this our Land a greater punishment allotted to it then adultery, and ma∣ny more enormous, hainous crimes. I knowe no reason why adulterie should not be rewarded with death, as well as theft, but onelie this; that whereas man ac∣counts of his wife, but one∣ly as flesh of his flesh, and bone of his bone, he esteems of his coyne, as soule of his soule. It is Auarice, that makes greedie fathers force their children to seeme to like what indeed they loath, and to take vnto them one <HI>for better for worse,</HI> then
<PB N="95" REF="58"/>
whome (indeede) they can like nothing worse. From hence it comes to passe, that age is matched with youth, fairenes with foulnes, beau∣tie with deformitie; which doubtlesse is farre from the first institution; for, <HI>In the</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 19▪ 8</NOTE> <HI>beginning</HI> (as Christ reply∣ed, concerning wiues, to the Scribes, and Pharisies) <HI>it was not so.</HI> GOD at first created man, and woman, in their full vigour, that they might be full of loue one to the other. What an vnseem∣lie sight is it, to see an olde grandsire as frostie in flesh as haire (whose eyes are rea∣die to set in his head, and
<PB N="96" REF="59"/>
whose rotten lungs scarce afford him breath) march to the Church with his young spouse, whose eyes roule in her head, whose marrow burnes in her bones, whose heate scornes colde, and in whose heart disdaine of age dooeth breede desire of youth!</P>
<P>According to GODs or∣dinance, Youth should ho∣nour, and reuerence Age: but wee no where reade, that Youth should solace it selfe in Age, or affect it. Those women, that thus marry, in my iudgement differ little or nothing from common ones: for, both
<PB N="97" REF="59"/>
sel their affection. What wil you giue me? saies one: what will you giue me? sayes the other.</P>
<P>Hauing now traced Vice by her footing as farre <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s hell, we will there leaue her, to accompanie her blacke, sinnefull sire. And now let vs suppose man to be with∣out all notorious actuall transgressions, onely con∣sidering him in his originall corruption: and wee shall finde that for all he is thus eased, hee is yet miserable euough; and that for one comfort, he hath millions of crosses. Hearken to Salo∣mon. <HI>I my selfe,</HI> saith he, <HI>am</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Wis. 7</NOTE>
<PB N="98" REF="60"/>
<HI>also mortall, and a man like all other, and am come of him that was first made of the earth. And in my mothers wombe was I fashioned to be flesh in tenne moneths: I was brought together into bloud, of the seede of man, and with the pleasure that commeth with sleepe. And when I was borne, I receiued the common ayre, and fell vpon the earth, which is of like nature, cry∣ing and weeping at the first as all other doe. I was nou∣rished in swadling clothes, &amp; with cares: for there is no King that had any other be∣ginning of birth. All men, then, haue one entrance into</HI>
<PB N="99" REF="60" MS="y"/>
<HI>life &amp; a like going out.</HI> Thus farre Salomon. It were too tedious a thing here to vn∣folde the mystery of mans conception, which in Philo∣sophy is no lesse pleasing, then strange, and wonder∣full. The first gift man re∣ceiues from Nature after his conception, is feeling; the next is moouing: and after he hath receiued the vtter∣most of his perfect, imper∣fect forme, shee giues him birth. He is no sooner borne, but his reasonablesoule (as di uining his troubles to com) makes him bawl and crie: and, hauing nothing but hu∣mour wherewith to vent his
<PB N="100" REF="61"/>
passion, he sheddeth teares. Well, as comming from a woman, he is referred to the care of a woman; who spends all her time (yet all little enough) to dresse him, to still him, to watch him, and to wipe awaie the ex∣crements of this excrement. The first word hee speakes bewraies vanitie: and as soone as his legs are able to vnderprop the burthen of his body, he goes to vanitie. He waxeth Idolatrous, and beholdes a baby made of clouts, a woodden puppie, or a paper birde, with an eye of worship &amp; adoration. He liued in his mothers wombe
<PB N="101" REF="61"/>
like a plant, came out from thence like a beast, and so still remaines, till institution fashion his Intellect, and make it capable of reason. Hauing now left to crie of himselfe, he is sent to school; where he is forced to con∣tinue, and exercise this wee∣ping trade: and there hee spendes the third part of his life, in teares, sighes, and sobs. Being thus bound in obedience, and seruitude, he desires to shake off captiui∣ty, and will bee no more commanded, but obeyed. Hauing rule ouer others, hee cannot gouerne himselfe; but pursues whatsoeuer pas∣sion,
<PB N="102" REF="62"/>
and humour, lead him to. Ifhe haue plenty, hee is riotous, luxurious, prodi∣gall, not accounting of the accounts hee shall one daie giue for it. If hee liue in scarcitie, he accuseth his pa∣rents, curseth the houre of his birth, and longeth for his buriall; and as (in his owne opinion) he came in∣to the worlde, before his time; so hee seeketh by all meanes to goe out before his time appointed. But, this by the waie is certaine, that aboundance choaketh more with riot then want killeth with despaire. Man receiues more detriment
<PB N="103" REF="62"/>
from this middle age, then either from his precedent, or subsequent. In this age he is vnruly, head-strong, vio∣lent; neither will hee hear∣ken to information, the be∣getter of reformation. And therefore the ages of man may aptly be compared to the sea: his youth may bee likened to the weather∣shore, stormy: his olde age, to the lee shore, calme: and his middle age, to the mid∣dest of the Ocean; where rough, vnmeasured, Sky∣mounting billowes carrie this light balanced Barke, now hither, now thither; and now and then driue her
<PB N="104" REF="63"/>
into helles harbour (from whence sometimes the trea∣der of waters, the comman∣der of windes, the drier-vp of cloudes, prouidences great pilot, bringeth her back into heauēs happy ha∣uen. For, now being come to liue of himselfe, hee can∣not tell how to dispose of himselfe, nor where to spend the remnant of his dayes. If in the Court, he sees that he must crouch, bow, dissem∣ble, put on a smooth front to his enemies, and euen lick the feete of the great. His generous minde telleth him, that a gentleman (who is therefore called so, because
<PB N="105" REF="63"/>
hee should not degenerate from his own nature) should not fawne, nor bend his knee when his heart rises; but (as Seneca saith) <HI>indu∣ere animi sui val<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um.</HI> Hee apprehends what basenesse it is, to put on a doggish pro∣pertie; and (as the same Se∣neca<NOTE PLACE="marg">Sen. de beat. vita▪ cap. vlt.</NOTE> saith) <HI>in consummati∣onem dignitat is per mille in∣dignitates erepere;</HI> that is, <HI>to creepe vp to honour, through a thousand dishonours.</HI> Hee perceiues, a courtier must pocket vppe many a great wrong, to come to greatness; and serue all men, that hee maie commaund all men. Fame whispers in his eare,
<PB N="106" REF="64"/>
that the Court is a Baude that will doe nothing with∣out money, a mint of fashi∣ons, an exchange of comple∣ments, a shame to shame∣fastnesse, and a Scene of all obscene actions. And now he thinkes that Machiauell was vnfortunat, only in this that he divulged his villanie to the world: for, in this place more is acted then e∣uer hee inuented. Hee was for the Theorick; these men for the Practique. Experi∣ence telleth him, that the time is long that hangs vpon desert; and the rewarde like to a womans fauour; then farthest off, when it is most
<PB N="107" REF="64"/>
expected. These poore de∣luded men, make me call to minde an olde Christmas gambole, contriued with a thredde, which being fast∣ned to some beame hath at the nether end of it a sticke, at the one ende of which is tied a candle, and at the o∣ther ende an apple; so that when a man comes to bite at the apple, the candle burnes his nose. The appli∣cation is as easie as the trick common; we hauing before our eyes dailie examples of men discarded for their ser∣uice done. After his soule hath ruminated these incon∣ueniences, he manifestly sees
<PB N="108" REF="65" MS="y"/>
that the Court is not a place suting with his disposition. Well, the Court being dis∣pleasing, he goeth into the countrey; where he disco∣uers Solitude (Melancho∣lies mute mother) sitting in a forsaken weede, stroking her child Absence on the head. Being here, he feeles this dumbe, silent life, to be a still kinde of death vnto him. Hee is heere in the world, as if he were out of the world: hee liues more like a beast then a man; pampring his body: but his nobler part (for which only he breathes) is barred from the mindes nurse, Conuer∣sation;
<PB N="109" REF="65"/>
and from the know∣ledge of strange euents, the confirmers and conformers of the minde. He learneth here, to preferre corporall exercise, before the soules re∣creation. The Papists are forced to goe to Church, and to receiue the Sacra∣ment once in a yeere, or else to vndergoe the penaltie; vvhen these voluptuous countrey-protestants neuer frequent the Church or re∣ceiue the Sacrament once in their life time. O that anie reasonable soule should va∣lewe the pleasures of the body, aboue those of the minde! betweene which
<PB N="110" REF="66"/>
there is as much inequalitie, as is betweene the substan∣ces they issue from. These pleasing motions of the soule, proceede from the Intellect: those brutish ones of the bodie, haue their birth from Sense, by which they are nourished. The former of vvhich, are by so much more noble then the latter, by how much the quicke, swift Intellect bettereth, &amp; surpasseth the slowe, and dull Sense.</P>
<P>A touch, or a taste with the body is but momentary, and abideth not a whit: but with the soule the rellish of the thing receiued remai∣neth
<PB N="111" REF="66"/>
for euer. The beasts thē∣selues haue sense: nay they haue appearing (though not apparent) vertues; but none of them euer yet mounted one degree of Contempla∣tions rising scale: by which the wise man with an as∣piring zeale, ascendes the throne of God; and seeing most things there inscruta∣ble, in humilitie descendes again vpon his foote-stoole. O! but Gentry now dege∣nerates: Nobility is now come to bee <HI>nuda relatio,</HI> a meere, bare relation, and nothing else. How manie Players haue I seene vpon a stage, fit indeede to be No∣blemen?
<PB N="112" REF="67"/>
how many that bee Noblemen, fit only to repre∣sent them? Why? this can Fortune doe; who makes some companions of her Chariot, who for desert should be lackies to her La∣diship. Let me want pittie, if I dissolue not into pittie, when I see such poore stuffe, vnder rich stuffe; that is, a bodie richly cladde, whose minde is capable of nothing but a hunting match, a rac∣ket-court, or a cock-pit, or at the most the story of Su∣sanna in an alehouse. Rise, Sidney, rise: thou Englands eternall honour, reuiue, and leade the reuolting spirits of
<PB N="113" REF="67"/>
thy countrey-men, against the soules basest foe, Igno∣rance. But what talke I of thee? heauen hath not left earth thy equall: neither do I thinke that <HI>ab orbe condito,</HI> since Nature first was, any man hath beene, in whome <HI>Genus</HI> and <HI>Genius</HI> met so right. Thou Atlas to all ver∣tues, thou Hercules to the Muses, thou Patron to the poor, thou deseruest a Quire of ancient <HI>Bardi</HI> to sing thy praises; who, with their mu∣sickes melody, might ex∣presse thy soules harmonie. Were the transmigration of soules certaine (which opi∣nion as Caesar saith, the an∣cient
<PB N="114" REF="68"/>
Brittish <HI>Druidae</HI> imbra∣ced) I would thy soule had flitted into my body, or would thou wert aliue again that we might leade an indi∣diduall life together. Thou wast not more admired at home, then famous abroade; thy pen, and sworde being the Heraldes of thy Hero∣icke deedes. A worthy wit∣nesse of thy worth, was Lip∣sius; when in amazement he cried out, <HI>Nihil tibi deest, quod aut naturae, aut Fortu∣nae adest: nothing,</HI> saith he, <HI>to thee is absent, that either to Nature, or Fortune is pre∣sent.</HI> And in another place he addeth, <HI>O tu Britanniae</HI>
<PB N="115" REF="68"/>
<HI>tuae clarum sidus, cui certa∣tim lucem affundunt Virtus, Musa, Gratia, Fortuna: O,</HI> saith he, <HI>thou bright star of thy Brittany, whose light is fedde by Vertue, the Muses, Fortune, and all graces.</HI> The verses which are extant in S. Pauls Quire at London, made in a gratefull memory of this king of knights, suf∣ficiently declare his deserts: which verses, valour, and honour command me heere to insert.</P>
<LG>
<L>England, Netherland, the heauens, and the Arts,</L>
<L>The souldiers, &amp; the world haue made sixe parts</L>
<L><PB N="116" REF="69"/>
Of the Noble Sydney: for, who will suppose</L>
<L>That a small heap of stones can Sydney inclose?</L>
<L>England hath his body; for, she it fedde:</L>
<L>Netherlande, his bloud, in her defense shed.</L>
<L>The Heauens haue his soule: the Arts haue his fame:</L>
<L>All souldiers the griefe: the World, his good name.</L>
</LG>
<P>Lord, I haue sinned against thee, and heauen, and I am not worthy to be called thy childe: yet lett thy mercy obtaine this Boone for me, from thee; that when it shall please thee that my name
<PB N="117" REF="69"/>
bee no more, it may ende in such a man, as was that <HI>Sidus Sydneyorum.</HI> What grace is it to me, when men report that a grasier of the same name (the very sound of whom leaues rust behind it in Fames trumpet) scra∣ped vp together thousands a yeere? whose greasy dignity in some two generations wii be Fly-blowne. And there∣fore I doe not enuie, but e∣mulate, the happinesse of the late Iosephus Scaliger: who being descended from Princes, and hauing all his race in his reines, fledde the societie of wanton women; fearing least he should beget
<PB N="118" REF="70"/>
one, who might one day de∣stroy his family, and take from the lustre of it: and so he himselfe, like a Semi-god, gaue a Period to his Paren∣tage. O! if a man had all his linage in his loines, it were braue smothering it there, rather then hereafter to let any crooked branch deform the beauty of the whole stocke; or any disorderlie person either in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> or death to purchase infamy to his whole family. Yet doe not I cleerely see, how a man by neuer so hainous a fact can¦taint his whole bloud, or kindred; since it is euident to all men of vnderstanding
<PB N="119" REF="70"/>
that <HI>alia est cognatio culpae, alia sanguinis:</HI> neither could Esau any way disparage Ia∣cob. But it is not a thing any way strange, if the yong gentlemen of this kingdom leaue dishonor in their hou∣ses, since their maintenance is too little to maintaine a∣ny honest course. You shall see an elder brother stalke before his traine, like Pha∣raoh before his host; and his younger brother (of the same bloud, and of a greater spirit) come sneaking after him, as if hee were the ba∣sest of his brothers retinue. What minde can frame it selfe to such meanes? what
<PB N="120" REF="71"/>
will not a daring spirit vn∣dertake, rather then bee a bondslaue to his owne bro∣ther? <HI>Non seruiam,</HI> said that Laconian lad; <HI>et praecipitem</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Sen. Epist. 26.</NOTE> <HI>se dedit:</HI> vpon which, Sene∣ca, writing, saith, <HI>Qui mori didicit, seruire dedidicit,</HI> he that hath learned to die, saith hee, hath forgot to serue.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Sen. Epist. 7.</NOTE> And the same Seneca saith, <HI>Sapiens viuit quantum de∣bet, non quantum potest.</HI> Epictetus, talking of the care men haue how they shall liue hereafter, crieth-out,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Disser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. cap. 9.</NOTE> <HI>Mancipium! si habuer is, ha∣beb is, si non habuer is, abibis. Aperta est ianua.</HI> Which sē∣tences we will not English,
<PB N="121" REF="71"/>
because the doctrine is not safe, and sound. No, no: that soule which leaues her tabernacle without a licence from her Emperour, merits condemnation. As a man who escapeth out of prison, doth not thereby cleer him∣selfe of his fault done, but augmenteth his punishmēt: euen so that soule, which stealeth out of her fleshy Iaile without a cōmand frō that supreame magistrate, in flying temporall miserie falleth into eternall anguish, and layeth her selfe open to all that seueritie can inflict. <HI>Hoc fecit illa,</HI> saith Augus∣tine,<NOTE PLACE="marg">August. de ciu. cap. 19.</NOTE> <HI>illa sic praedicata Luere∣tia;</HI>
<PB N="122" REF="72"/>
<HI>innocentem, castam, vim perpessam Lucretiam Lucre∣tia insuper interemit. Pro∣ferte sententiam, leges, iudi∣ces{que} Romani: This did,</HI> saith he, <HI>that so much re∣nowned Lucretia; innocent, chast, violated Lucretia mur∣thered Lucretia. Giue sen∣tence, O yee lawes, and Iudges of Rome.</HI> Hauing a little wan∣dered, let vs now at last take a view of man in his last, &amp; oldestage. As he brought diseases with him from his last mother: so he must car∣ry them with him to his first mother, the earth. Now commeth the Physician with his mish, mash, an hun∣dred
<PB N="123" REF="72"/>
Simples in one Com∣pound, and powreth it into this leaking vessell. If hee recouer, he standeth bound to his Doctour, for his life; and acknowledgeth him, next vnder God, his preser∣uer. Good Iesus! that a man should bee obliged to him for breathing, who de∣teines the breath in bon∣dage, and prolongeth the houre of the soules release∣ment. Seneca saith, that there are some men, who though they saue another mans life, yet they doe not any way engage him whome they saue: amongst which hee placeth Physicians, and ma∣keth
<PB N="124" REF="73"/>
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Sen. lib. 4. de ben. cap. 13.</NOTE> this his reason; <HI>Quia ad alienum commodum, pro suo veniunt; because they seeke another mans profit, for their owne.</HI> Moreouer, an olde man groweth a young childe againe; his limbs faile him; and all the faculties of his body fade. Nay, which is worse, his diuine part beginneth to nodde, and is depriued of that subtility which runneth through all things, in, and aboue nature; that is, con∣ceiueth all that is not incon∣ceiueable. And therefore Seneca thought, that it was lawfull for an aged man of an imperfect minde to kill
<PB N="125" REF="73"/>
himselfe. <HI>Non relinquam</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Sen. Epist. 58.</NOTE> <HI>senectutem, si me totum mi∣hi reseruabit: totum autem ab illa parte meliore. At si coeperit concutere mentem, si partes eius conuellere, si mihi non vitam reliquerit, sed animam; prosiliam ex aedificio p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>trido, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ruenti. I will not leaue Age,</HI> saith he, <HI>if it leaue me whole, and en∣tire to my selfe; that is, per∣fect in my better, and per∣fecter part. But if age dis∣tract my minde, and deface her fairest parts, if it leaue me a soule, and</HI> (as I may so saie) <HI>no life to solace that soule: I will then leape out of this ruined, and lothsome
<PB N="126" REF="74"/>
lodging.</HI> But this is more a∣cutely handled in Stobaeus; where Musonius, or some other saith in this manner;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Serm. 1.</NOTE> <HI>Sicut è domo exigi videmur cum locator pensione non ac∣ceptâ fores reuellit, tegulas aufert, puteum obstruit: it<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> et hoccorpusculo pelli videor, cùm natura, quae locauit, o∣culos adimit, aures, manus, pedes. Non moror igitur am∣pliùs: sed velut è conviuio discedo, nihil aegrescens. As,</HI> saith he, <HI>an angry vnpayed Land-lord seemeth to en∣force his Tenants departure, when hee taketh away the doores of the house, vntileth the whole building, stoppeth</HI>
<PB N="127" REF="74"/>
<HI>vp the Well, and barreth him from all necessaries: euenso I seeme to bee driuen out of this body, when Nature, who lent me eyes, eares, hands, feete, taketh awaie the ver∣tue and vse of them, so that I canne neither see, heare, handle, nor goe. I will not therefore abide any longer; but will goe away, as from a banquet, being no way sicke, and diseased.</HI> Besides this feeblenesse of body and minde, there is another in∣conuenience incident to old age: to weet, that it maketh a man lesse pleasing, not so∣ciable; but so peeuish, curst, and crabbed, as that milde∣nesse
<PB N="128" REF="75"/>
it selfe cannot keepe him company. His very children are wearie of him, and wish him a portion in heauen, that so they maie haue their portions on earth into their owne hands. Yet he endureth all this patient∣lie, till at last his professed foe, Death, assaulteth him: to whom (after he hath in vaine striued to maintaine life against death) hee yeel∣deth vp himselfe. Thus wee see the whole droues of ca∣lamities, which man meets with in this his earthlie pilgrimage: in which hee prooues by experience, that nothing is more true then
<PB N="129" REF="75"/>
that Italian Prouerbe,</P>
<LG>
<L>Questo mondo è fatto a scale,</L>
<L>Chi le scende, et chi le sale.</L>
<L>This same world is made with steppes:</L>
<L>One falls downe, one vp leapes.</L>
</LG>
<P>Who would think, that misery wanted so much as an inch of her height? Nay, who would imagine, that this brittle, earthen ves∣sell could stand so many knockes, and not be broken? yes, yes▪ there is yet an addi∣tion
<PB N="130" REF="76"/>
to extreamity, &amp; a plague is yet left behinde, which all the former cannot coun∣teruaile. Religion, Religion, thou sower of dissension, and reaper of hatred, thou settest soule against soule, and bodie against bodie. Man, who by thee doth excell beastes in knowledge, by thee also doth surpasse them in enuie. Christ is diuided from Christ: that is, Christi∣anitie is parted into sectes▪ But, this is not contrarie to Christs fore-warning. <HI>Think</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 10 34 &amp; 35</NOTE> <HI>not,</HI> saith he, <HI>that I am come to send peace into the earth, but the sword. For, I am come to set a man at variance</HI>
<PB N="131" REF="76"/>
<HI>against his father, and the daughter against her mother in law &amp;c.</HI> If Christ would haue descended into parti∣culars, he would haue men∣tioned also the setting of subiects against their Prin∣ces; then which, nothing is more common with the Romish Religion. This made Parsons, that false fu∣gitiue, that Romish runna∣gate, raile against his royall Queene, and Mistresse. A faire equalitie: the basest man on earth to write a∣gainst a GOD, on earth; Gods cursed, against Gods anointed. That tongue (I dare pronounce it boldly)
<PB N="132" REF="77"/>
shall burne in neuer quench∣ing fire, that defames his Princes name. This detract∣ing Traitour, with his fel∣lowes, would haue all ver∣tues in that, which in it selfe<NOTE PLACE="marg">De Benif. lib. 4. cap. 26. &amp; 27.</NOTE> is nothing but sinne. <HI>Omnia vitia sunt in omnibus,</HI> saith Seneca: yet those prying malitious men would haue <HI>omnes virtutes in singulis.</HI> Detractions eyes reflect still vpon her selfe: and shee re∣gardeth euer what is to bee approoued in her selfe, and reprooued in others: where∣as indeede she should runne this race cleane backwarde, and haue an eye to those ver∣tues which lie hid and sup∣pressed
<PB N="133" REF="77"/>
in others, and to those vices which are most eminent in her selfe. These reproachefull Reprobates should winke at the small faults in great persons, and beare away that sentence of Austine: <HI>Non statim malum, quod minus bonum,</HI> together with that other saying of a late Writer; <HI>Genus huma∣nū diuinum facimus, si vitijs carens.</HI> If our Elizabeth should haue vttered those blasphemies, which some of their Popish Princes haue belched forth, they would haue thought, that the earth could not stand with her vp∣on it. What if she should
<PB N="116" REF="78"/>
haue saide with Fridericke, the Second, <HI>tres fuisse insig∣nes impostores, qui huma∣num</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Lipsius in ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mp. po. lib. 1. cap. 4.</NOTE> <HI>genus seduxerunt; Moy∣sem, Christum, Mahumetem? That there were three won∣derfull impostours, which seduced Mankinde; to weet, Moyses; Christ, and Maho∣mete?</HI> What if shee should haue saied with Alphonsus,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Idem ibi∣dem.</NOTE> the tenth, of Spaine: <HI>Si in principio mundi ipse Deo ad∣fuisset, multa meliùs, ordi∣natiús{que} condenda fuisse; That if hee had beene with God at the beginning of the world, many things should haue beene better disposed of, and with lesse confusion!</HI>
<PB N="135" REF="78"/>
No, no: our peerelesse Prin∣cesse had nothing so horrid to lie vpon her conscience. Elizabeth, thou glorie of thy sexe, thou mirrour of Ma∣iestie and modestie, thou re∣semblance of that sacred Eli∣zabeth, look down through<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luk. 1.</NOTE> those thy Crystal spectacles, vpō thy meanest of subiects, who in defence of thine ho∣nor wold oppose himself a∣gainstal mortality, &amp; expose his life to death for thee. I lo∣ued thee more then I did all the world, or more then all the world could loue thee. Incōparable, immutable, in∣imitable Queene! I am not affraid to say, that generati∣ons<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luk. 1.</NOTE>
<PB N="136" REF="79"/>
shall call thee Blessed, although a generation of Vipers not forewarned of<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 3. v. 7</NOTE> the vengeance to come sting thy reputation, and seeke to debase thy euer ex∣alted name. The Queene of the South came to see Salo∣mon: had Salomon liued in thy time, or thou in his, hee would himselfe haue come to visit the Queene of the North; and being the wisest of men, would haue won∣dered to finde so much wise∣dome in Woman. Blessed Virgine, thou restest from thy labours, and we labour for thy rest, &amp; with ceasseless paine striue to attaine to that
<PB N="137" REF="79"/>
endlesse pleasure which now thou enioyest. Thou abidest now farre enough out of the reach of contumelious tongues, and art secure from all, that pale enuie, or mea∣ger malice can charge thee with. There is no greater signe that thou wast vertu∣ous, then that thou art ma∣ligned of all who are viti∣ous. For, as a great bodie is not without a like shadow: no more is any eminent ver∣tue without imminent de∣traction. Mee thinkes, that Calumny should ende with the carkasse of her subiect, and not haunt the graue till the last bone be consumed.
<PB N="138" REF="80"/>
Which to effect, Solō made a law, <HI>that no man should speake ill of the dead: and his reason was, for feare of im∣mortall enemies.</HI> But they will not sticke to write a∣gainst the dead, who are not affraid to write against the liuing. The same fore∣named perfidious Parsons, hath, with little reuerence, written a booke against his liuing King. O, for some coniuring lawes, to lay these rouing, rauing tongues! Is it not a madde world thinke you, when euery braine-sick, giddie-headed, pamphle∣ting companiō shal presume to vpbraide &amp; beard mighty
<PB N="139" REF="80"/>
Monarchs? Wherefore hot spirited Luther (though otherwise a stout souldier in Christs Church militant) is not to bee excused for his vnreuerent speeches of Hen∣rie the eight of England. The mildest tearmes hee v∣seth, are, <HI>Momus, mimus,</HI> and <HI>stultus:</HI> nay, at the length, his presumption swelleth so big, that he changeth the name Henry into Pharaoh, and calles all his Courtiers, Ian∣nes and Iambres. Vnlimi∣ted Luther, thou verities chiefe champion, I am al∣together as vnable to cen∣sure thee, as to equall thee: yet my neuer dying zeale to
<PB N="140" REF="81"/>
my euer liuing Princes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for∣ceth mee to tell thee, that these thy misse-beseeming words did not proceede from diuine inspiration, but from humane passion. This is a thing rare with Luther, and vnexpected from him: but nothing is more vsuall with the defenders of the Papacie. They not onlie al∣low to reuile and mocke a a King, but also to murther him. Which damnable doc∣trine François de Verone<NOTE PLACE="marg">Franc. de ver. Con. par. 2. ca. 2</NOTE> Constantine mainetaineth, when he saies: <HI>L'Action de Clement est loysible, et le coup qu'il a donnè à Henrie 3. esto∣it du mesme endroict, que</HI>
<PB N="141" REF="81"/>
<HI>celuy de lulian l'apostat, c'est a dire du ciel.</HI> The Actiō, saies he, of Clement is lawful: &amp; the blowe which he gaue to Henry the 3. was sent from whence that of Iulian the A∣postate; that is, frō heauen. Is there then no difference to be put betweene a persecu∣tour and a professour of Christ? Of the former of which, it is said, <HI>Iaculabatur sanguinem in Galilaeum:</HI> of the latter it may besaid, <HI>effu∣sit</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Socr. in vita Iul.</NOTE> <HI>sanguinem pro Galilaeo.</HI> The same Writer after he hath railed his fill at Henry the 4. in saying, that he was not <HI>l'oingt de Dieu,</HI> who was <HI>loing de Dieu,</HI> nor more
<PB N="142" REF="82"/>
rightly king of France, then he who in the Gospell is cal∣led Prince of this World; at last he bursteth out into these wordes, which point at murther, <HI>C'est vne chose louable, de sauuer tant de mil∣liers d'hommes tant presents, qu'auenir, de la damnation eternelle. It is,</HI> saith he, <HI>a thing praise worthy, to saue so many millions of men, as well present as to come, from eternall damnation.</HI> Hee saith also, that Gerard who killed the Prince of Orange did that act, <HI>Pour le bien de la vertu, for vertues good:</HI> and againe he saies, <HI>Gerard, le coeur luy estant arrachè, rendit ainsi son ame à Dieu:</HI>
<PB N="143" REF="82"/>
<HI>Gerard,</HI> saith he, <HI>his heart be∣ing torne frō out of his body, rēdred his soule vp vnto god.</HI> But, what will not this au∣thor vndertake? whose book is written in defence of Chastelet, who essayed to slaye the late murthered King of France. What odi∣ous enterprise will not a bad impudent spirite seeke to make good? I thinke, there would not bee wanting a se∣ditious turbulent soule, to write against GOD, for his vniust throwing downe of Lucifer. Surely, some penne or other wil paint forth that accursed Rauilliake for a Saint on earth, and of a monster make a Martyr.
<PB N="144" REF="83"/>
That rauenous Rauilliake glutted himselfe with the bloud of that king, in whom were eminently contained all the vertues of all the French kinges since Phara∣mond. The minutes of that houre, the houre of that day, the day of that weeke, the weeke of that moneth, the moneth of that yeere, wher∣in that nothing-fearing Pha∣etō had his downfal, France shall euer holde both omi∣nous and odious. Griefe gripes my heart when I think, that the Mars of men receiued his deaths blowe from a pen-maker, a Peda∣gogue. A late French Wri∣ter
<PB N="145" REF="83"/>
hath composed a short Treatise to prooue that the sword is more proper to the French Nation, than to any other. Which though I deny; yet I would easily yeelde vnto him, that the sworde was more proper to the late French king, then to any of his ancestors, or to his liuing equalls. He was a king of the sword, and of his word; whose word was his sword, &amp; whose sword was his word: for, where his word could not warrant, his sword bore sway. Out of the ashes of this Phoenix another bird is risen; whose fea∣thers, I feare me, will not
<PB N="146" REF="84"/>
bee able to beare him the flight and pitch his Sire so∣red. Well, France hath lost her Soueraigne: &amp; we were neere losing ours. How of∣ten hath God pulled our King, out of Treason's mur∣thering mouth, and out of the iawes of death? When that Powder-plot (a trea∣son, at the which, Fiction her selfe stoode affrighted) was readie to lay holde on him, then God deliuered him. But I do not think, if <HI>Faux,</HI> or rather <HI>Fax,</HI> had gi∣uen fire to the powder, that it could haue deuoured that sacred assembly. What? he that deliuered the children
<PB N="147" REF="84"/>
of Israell out of Egypt; hee that led them through the red sea, without wetting of their feete; he that fed them without any ordinary bread for the space of fortie yeares in the wildernesse; he that caused the Sunne to stand still; hee that caused the Sun to goe backewardes at the prayers of king Hezechiah; he that raised the dead; hee that did so many wonders and miracles; could not hee also haue changed the pro∣pertie of Powder? No doubt, but hee could and would haue sent the force of it down-wards, making a passage through the earths
<PB N="148" REF="85"/>
hollow wombe into hell, &amp; there haue blasted the black Diuell with his vnhallowed Senate of Popes, the inuen∣tours and fautours of this vnheard-of attempt. It can be none other but the diuel, that biddeth a traitour pick out GODS chosen to butcher. If the Diuell (vp∣on my soules altar I sweare it) would take me vp to the pinacle, as hee did my hea∣uenly Maister, and saie to me, all this will I giue thee to kill thy earthly Maister; had hee power to performe his promise, I would not doe it: but, rather then ten∣tation should win this fraile
<PB N="149" REF="85"/>
flesh to spill the numbred drops of that royall bloud, I would first let out all mine owne. Me thinks my Saui∣our whispereth in mine eare, and telleth mee, that his bloud shall not cleanse the polluted soule of that man, that dies with that bloudy thought. But the Iesuites are the ring-leaders to this troop of king-slay∣ers: which, whosoeuer rea∣deth their bookes shall soon perceiue. For mine owne part, I had with no small paines gathered together their doctrines, concerning this point; meaning indeed to printit: but I was pre∣uented
<PB N="150" REF="86"/>
by Anticoton; who made a discouerie of the slaughtering ambush they lay for Princes. Which book is turned into English; the Translatour being in no∣thing inferiour to the Au∣thour. But, it is nothing strange if these Iesuites bee bloudy; seeing the first of their Order was a souldier. He was a Spaniard by birth (which makes them loue that soile so well) his name <HI>Ignatius,</HI> so called <HI>ab igne,</HI> as one that should incense sub∣iects against their Soue∣raignes, and set the whole world on fire with sedition and dissension. Incredible
<PB N="151" REF="86"/>
things are reported of this man, by those of his owne coat. Ribadeneira, who hath written his life, sayes, that this Ignatius kneeling on a certaine daie before the I∣mage of the spotlesse Virgin Mary, there arose an earth∣quake. Surely, the earth trembled to feele the weight of such a Monster. One thing the Authour reports of this Ignatius; whereunto I giue credit, since his suc∣ceeders do the same: &amp; this it is; <HI>Ignatius disputauit cum Mauro de Maria Virgine: &amp; cùm ex verbo Dei hominem refutare non potuit, pugione confodere voluit aduersari∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.
<PB N="152" REF="87"/>
Ignatius,</HI> saith he, <HI>dis∣puted with a Moore concer∣ning the Virgin Marie: but, when he saw, that hee could not refute him out of the word of God, he sought with his poniard to conquer his aduersarie.</HI> This holds not onelie with the women, but also with the men of this re∣ligion: for, what they can∣not haue with disputing, they take out in railing and fighting. The Authour yet goes farther, and saies, <HI>Inter h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> rursus vehementissima hominē invadebat cogitatio, vt ex cellula, vbi erat, sese praecipitem daret. In the mid∣dest,</HI> faith he, <HI>of these occur∣rences,</HI>
<PB N="153" REF="87"/>
<HI>Ignatius was assaul∣ted by a strong temptation, to cast himselfe headlong from the place where he was.</HI> I would to GOD, he had done it, and shiuered his necke, the prop to his false hèad, into a thousand peeces, so that Christendom might not haue had so deare a tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣all of the trecherie of his fol∣lowers. They leaue a poy∣sonous leauen in the law∣lesse lumpe of their doc∣trine: so that whosoeuer swallowes it, his minde is infected and enuenomed. The Iesuites haue set-out <HI>Martialem Castratum:</HI> and it were a worthy work for
<PB N="154" REF="88" MS="y"/>
some industrious wit, to set∣out Iesuit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s <HI>Castratos,</HI> and gelde them of their guiltie doctrine. <HI>Yee liue like Gods,</HI> saith the Prophet; <HI>but yee shall die</HI> like <HI>men: you liue like Gods,</HI> saith the Iesuite, <HI>but you shall dye</HI> by <HI>men.</HI> What should moue them to set a-broach their hogs∣heads, &amp; make youth drunk with their new inuented li∣quor? Why breake they their sleepes, to breake the bond of peace betweene the people and their Prince? Why do they all this? That their seruice may bee accep∣table to the Pope their Mai∣ster; whom they exalt, a∣boucthrones and principa∣lities,
<PB N="155" REF="88"/>
and all that is called God: nay, I might almost say, that is GOD. <HI>Crux,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Baronius in parae∣nes. ad ve∣net. pag. 9<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Colin. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣ditionis.</NOTE> saith Baronius, <HI>antecellit aquilas Caesaris; gladius Petri, gladium Constan∣tini; &amp; Apostolica sedes praeiudicat imperatoriae po∣testati. The crosse,</HI> saith hee, <HI>excelleth the eagles of Caesar; the sword of Peter, the sword of Constantine; and the A∣postolike See out-strippeth the imperiall power.</HI> In my simple iudgement, common sense should giue a man this, that if Christ commanded his Apostles not to beare rule <HI>sicut reges gētium;</HI> with∣out doubt, then, <HI>non▪supr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>
<PB N="156" REF="89"/>
<HI>Reges Iudae.</HI> And therefore Princes, learning that the Pope seeketh nothing else, but to make them his vas∣sals, haue reiected his pow∣er and authoritie; as finding a great difference betweene his yoak, and that of Christ. <HI>For, Christ</HI> saith, <HI>my yoake is easie, and my burthen light:</HI> whereas it may truely bee said of the Pope, that his yoake is vneasie, and his bur∣then not to be borne. The king our Maister seemes to yeeld him more, then Saint<NOTE PLACE="marg">Agust. de baptis. contra Donat. lib. 2. cap. 20.</NOTE> Austin would, were he aliue; <HI>Ne{que} enim quisquis nostrûm,</HI> saith he, <HI>episcopūse esse episco porū cōstituit, at{que} tyrannico</HI>
<PB N="157" REF="89"/>
<HI>terrore ad obsequendi neces∣sitatem collegas suos adigit; quando habet omnis Episco∣pus, pro licentia libertatis &amp; potestatis suae, arbitrium proprium, tanquam iudicari ab alio nō possit, quomodo nee ipse potest alterumiudicare; sed expectemus vniuersi iu∣dicium Domini nostri Ies<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Christi, qui vnus est, solus habens potestatem &amp; praepo∣nendi nos in Ecclesiae suae gu∣bernatione, et de actu nostro iudicandi.</HI> But, if the Pope would be content onely to insulte ouer Bishops, it were well enough; or if hee would but onelie take the place of Kings, hee were
<PB N="158" REF="90"/>
(though hardly) to bee en∣dured: but, that he should haue the disposing of their liues, and reuenewes, no man of iudgement and ho∣nesty will allow. It cannot sinke into my head, how superstition should so bleare the eyes of so many learned men, so many yeeres toge∣ther, as that they should not spy out this vsurper, and seeke to depriue him of his stollen supremacie: But (a∣las!) in Rome now, new superstition supplies the place of ancient valour. Were Saint Paul in Rome to-day, he would vtter the same words in <HI>Campo Mar∣tio,</HI>
<PB N="159" REF="90"/>
that hee did in <HI>Mars</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts. 17 22.</NOTE> street at Athens; <HI>Men and brethren, I see that in all things you are too superstiti∣ous.</HI> The Church of Rome is built vpon superstition; and maketh more of cere∣monies, then of the sub∣stance of religion. Some of these ceremonies are so ab∣surd, as I think they onely stay the Iewes conuersion. For, as Auerrhoes, in derisiō of them, said, <HI>Sit anima mea</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Auer. in 12. Meta∣physi.</NOTE> <HI>cum Philosophis, quia Chri∣stiani adorant id quod e∣dunt; Let my soule be with the Philosophers, seeing the Christians adore that which they eate:</HI> So maie
<PB N="160" REF="91"/>
the lewes iustly say, Let our soules bee with the olde ce∣remonies, since the new ones are so foolish and ridi∣culous. Others againe of those ceremonies are so im∣pious, that it is a wonder that heauen doth not blast, or earth swallow-vppe the profane obseruers of them. They picture GOD the fa∣ther, like an olde decrepite man; and make him visible to the eye of the bodie, whom the eye of the cleerest minde cannot truely dis∣cerne. God made Man ac∣cording to his owne image, one way: and Man, in waie of recompense, makes God
<PB N="161" REF="91"/>
according to his image, an∣other way. I am so great an enemy to ceremonies, as that I would onelie wish, to haue that one ceremonie at my buriall, which I had at my birth; I mean, swadling: and yet I am indifferent for that too.</P>
<P>Tacitus saide, in his<NOTE PLACE="marg">Tacit. An∣nal. lib. 14.</NOTE> time, that Christianitie was <HI>Super stitio exitiabilis:</HI> had he liued in our time, he would haue added <HI>execrabilis.</HI> Oh that religion were once pur∣ged from the lees of the Ro∣mish grape! that so euery thir sting soule might drinke out of the fountaine of the writ∣ten Word. I would not be
<PB N="162" REF="92"/>
so presumptuous as to wish<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ma. 20. 22</NOTE> to sit either at the right, or at the left hand of my Re∣deemer: But, if I coulde obtaine my request at the hands of God, I would one∣ly desire to see my natiue countrey voide of erronious doctrine, and flourish vnder a liuely, well grounded faith. Oh! but this vnion of reli∣gions is a harder thing to ef∣fect, then an vnion of king∣domes. For, in this busi∣nesse of the soule euery pri∣uate man is a Senatour, and passeth his iudgement: No man in this can bee compel∣led to tread in the kings high way; but hee will (if it
<PB N="163" REF="92"/>
stand with his liking) haue a path-way of his owne. That man would merite eternitie, that could reconcile the long seuered Protestants &amp; Papists. But it is a bootlesse endeuour to essay it; since that of Cyprian is most true: <HI>Nulla societas fidei et</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">55. episto.</NOTE> <HI>perfidiae potest esse.</HI> The lear∣ned, on both sides, set the ignorant together by the eares; and-cast in boanes, to make them snarle one at another: their long studied distinctions, doe as much dull zeale, as they whet sub∣tiltie. They teach the peo∣ple to talke well, not to liue well; alluring them to de∣light
<PB N="164" REF="93"/>
in controuersies, the onelie Seminaries of Here∣sies. They abuse that know∣ledge and light, which they haue, infused into thē by the father of lights: and whereas they should turn it into acti∣ons, they turne it into facti∣ons. Is it not glory enough to them, that their learning placeth them almost as farre aboue ordinarie men, as or∣dinarie men aboue beasts; but that they must also clip truth, to enlarge their tri∣umphes? They inueigh deadly one against another, as being at deadly enmity, and striue to draw others to their parties; employing in∣uention,
<PB N="165" REF="93" MS="y"/>
onely to feede con∣tention. Their reasons would make a reasonable man to laugh: and their Motiues would moue a man to be of no religion, and think Chri∣stianity a meere delusion. The Papist firmely affirmes that the Protestant is dāned; the protestant doubts of the saluation of the papist: yet in my weake opinion, it should not bee so with the latter. For, though the pa∣pists iudge vncharitablie of vs; yet wee should censure more fauourably of them. It is a dangerous doctrine, which the purer sort of our diuines haue of late diuulged
<PB N="166" REF="94"/>
to the world; to weet, that all these are blotted out of the book of life, that die absolute papists. To this end saith an Eng. writer of the foremen∣tioned sect; where is, saith he, <HI>Cyrus, Darius, Xerxes, Alex∣ander, Caesar, Pompey, Seipio and Haniball? Where are the Valiant Henries and Noble Edwards of England? The wormes eat them: and what is become of their soules, is most of all to be feared.</HI> See the indiscretion of this man, in mingling Christianitie and Paganisme together. The Valiant Henries, and Noble Edwardes of Eng∣land are with him in no bet∣ter
<PB N="167" REF="94"/>
taking, then Cyrus, Da∣rius, &amp;c. and hee maketh their case common. GOD send the poore idle man to come to the place, which the Valiant Henries, and the Noble Edwards of Eng∣land inhabite. Hee and the rest of his faction, need not as they doe, complaine of their pouertie; since their owne rashnesse procures it. <HI>Rash</HI> in Hebrewe, signifieth <HI>Pauper</HI> in Latin, in English <HI>A poor man.</HI> For my part, I neuer knew a rash man▪ that dyed rich. Their tongues are theirs: who shall con∣troll them? Audacitie leads them: and out of an assumed
<PB N="168" REF="95"/>
libertie, or an ill gouerned zeale, they speake they care not what, without either feare or wit. Many things are spoken (GOD hee knowes) from the heart, which neuer came neere the head; and many things are thought to be vttered <HI>ex ani∣mo,</HI> which indeede issue <HI>ex animi morbo▪</HI> That most of our auncestours are dam∣ned, I dare not beleeue: but, I had rather determine of my successours, who liuing in the later times are more subiect to sinne, the reward of temporall and eternall death. Though our ancest∣ours were gally-slaues to the
<PB N="169" REF="95" MS="y"/>
pope, as being chained fast to Ignorance; yet their Works leaue a sufficient testimonie of their faith. <HI>Sunt,</HI> saith Cambden, <HI>vi</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Cambde∣nus epist. ad lecto∣rem.</NOTE> <HI>audio, qui monasteria, et eorum fundatores à me me∣morari indignantur; dolen∣ter audio: sed cum bona illo∣rum gratia dixerim, ijdem indignētur, imò fortasse obli∣uisci velint, et Maiores nos∣tros Christianos fuisse, &amp; nos esse.</HI> They had <HI>fidem formatam;</HI> we, <HI>fidem infor∣mem:</HI> they did more then they knew; we know more then wee doe. Their igno∣rance was the greatest fault they had: which if it did
<PB N="170" REF="96"/>
condemne them, woe be to little knowing, yet well meaning mindes. If Christ prayed for those that cru∣cified him, saying; <HI>Father forgiue them: they know not what they doe;</HI> will hee not pray for them also that praise, magnifie, and glori∣fie his euer-glorious name, yet in so doing, know not what they doe? Those that teach them, shall answere for it; according to those words of Christ: <HI>Whosoeuer</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 5. 19</NOTE> <HI>therefore shall breake one of these least commandements, and teach men so, hee shall bee called the least in the kingdome of heauen,</HI> &amp;c.
<PB N="171" REF="96"/>
where we see a punishment alloted to false teaching. Let vs defer then to censure, what shall become of them, till wee know what shall be∣come of our selues; which is onelie knowen to GOD. If all the Diuines in the world auouch that Hell is my portion, if That Diui∣nity whisper to me the con∣trarie, I will deride them. It were a braue thing, if one man could dispose of ano∣thers soule, and reward it with either paine, or plea∣sure, according to his owne will. Yet I must confesse this ingenuously; that I put so great a difference be∣tweene
<PB N="172" REF="97"/>
the ancient and mo∣derne papists, as that I re∣solue rather that the former are taken to mercy, then that the later either are, or shall be. The former in∣structed no men to destruc∣tion, with king-killing doc∣trine: the later teache<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to make-away an Hereticke (yet an Hereticke of their owne brain) by any meanes whatsoeuer. God renounce me, if I had not rather bee an Heathen, then a Christiā and holde this mercilesse <HI>Axiome</HI> for currant: for, I had rather bee an honest Turke, then a knauish Chri∣stian. Papistrie and Treason
<PB N="173" REF="97"/>
now are growen to be <HI>Acci∣dentia concomitantia;</HI> and they giue mutuall atten∣daunce one on the other. Neither did the auncient Priests so worke vpon the frailtie of silly women, as these doe: neither were they so lecherous, as these are. These are they whom Saint Paul pointeth at, saying; <HI>For of this sort, are they</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Ti. 3. 6</NOTE> <HI>which creepe into houses, and leade captiue simple women laden with sinnes, and led with diuers lusts.</HI> Yet, for all this, our Puritans ought not to giue definitiue sentence against them; but referre it to him, who <HI>will haue</HI>
<PB N="174" REF="98"/>
<HI>mercie on whom he will haue mercie.</HI> These men, whose puritie hath made them vn∣conformable to the present Discipline of the Church, though they bee guiltie of Schisme, yet they are not dangerous; but liue, and dye, without thought of slaughter: yet is there a tat∣ling Treatise, entituled <HI>He∣rode and Pilate reconciled,</HI> wherein the author striueth very hard, to proue that the Papists &amp; Puritans are both alike dangerous; as holding the same treacherous te∣nents. He spetteth-out the venome of his tongue in the faces of Caluin, and Be∣za;
<PB N="175" REF="98"/>
men, whose names his mouth should not vsurpe, without reuerence. Hee may well wrest their spee∣ches: but, well I know, hee can neuer inferre any pre∣tended treason, from them. His booke is well laboured; and hee manifesteth to the world, that hee hath read some thing: hee lacketh no∣thing but the iudgement of Tertullian; that is, that a man ought to imploy all hee hath or knoweth, <HI>in testi∣monium</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Tert. de resur. carn.</NOTE> <HI>veri, non in adiuto∣rium falsi.</HI> Sir Francis Ba∣con saith, that the way to dimmish bad bookes, is not not to burne, or teare them;
<PB N="176" REF="99"/>
but with plentie of good bookes, to make scarcitie of bad: whereas I for my part thinke, that the dailie en∣crease of triuiall trifling books, wil at the length con∣sume and annihilate the weighty and serious ones. Now-a-daies, almost euery Sect hath a seueral expositi∣on of the Text, and a diuerse application. We may well crie-out with the Prophet<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 60. 1. 2. &amp; 3.</NOTE> Dauid, <HI>O God thou hast cast vs out; thou hast scattered vs: thou hast beene angry; turne againe vnto vs. Thou hast made the Land to trem∣ble, and hast made it to gape: heale the breaches thereof;</HI>
<PB N="177" REF="99"/>
<HI>for it is shaken. Thou hast shewed thy people heauy things: thou hast made vs to drinke the wine of Giddines.</HI> It fatteth the soule of the Iewe, to see Christianitie torne in peeces by schisme and heresie. He scorneth the head the more, because hee sees the members of the bo∣die so wound one the other. Oh, that wee could, with the harmony of an vnsepa∣rable vnion, charme the eares of this Christianities serpent! But surely hee will stop his eares to our char∣ming, who disobeyeth the voice of that great charmer, charme hee neuer so wise∣lie.
<PB N="178" REF="100"/>
Thou seede of Abraham, thou house of Iacob, thou disposer of the graces and promises of the all-puissant, I bewaile from my soule thy heauie condition, and la∣ment that thou canst not repent. What grosse absur∣dities haue seized on thee, of the which beliefe is not<NOTE PLACE="marg">See the quotatiōs of Monsi∣eur du Plessis vp∣on their Thalmud, in his book en∣tituled <HI>Aduertisse∣ment aux Iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fs.</HI></NOTE> capable? As, for example, that <HI>God before he built this world, exercised himselfe a long time in setting-vp and pulling-downe, before hee could learne to finish the frame hee hadde conceiued.</HI> Thou further sayest, that <HI>God hath certaine appointed daies, wherein he afflicteth</HI>
<PB N="179" REF="100"/>
<HI>himselfe, because in choler he defaced thy citty, with thy temple: and tokens of this his felt sorrow, thou makest to be lightning and thunder.</HI> Thou saiest also, that <HI>God or∣deined a sacrifice amongst the Iewes euery new Moone, to recompence the wrong he did to the Moone, in taking light from her to giue it to the Sunne.</HI> Thou farther sayest, that <HI>he is angrie once a day, and then the crimson combes of the Cookes waxe pale and bloudlesse.</HI> Thou hast also a prophane fable, that <HI>on a day there being a disputation betweene cer∣taine Rabbins, and R. Elie∣zer,
<PB N="180" REF="101"/>
God gaue sentence on Eliezers side: for which the Rabbins excōmunicated him; and then God smiling, said, My children haue ouercome me.</HI> Thou sayest also, that <HI>he that gainsayeth the words of the Scribes, deserues more to be punished, then he that contradicts the Law of Mo∣ses: the one may be absolued; the other must absolutely die.</HI> Thou saiest also, that <HI>he is no good Rabbin which doth not hate his enemy; nay, that doth not pursue reuenge e∣uen vntill death. And hee that disalloweth of any thing in these bookes, denieth God himselfe.</HI> What God will
<PB N="181" REF="101"/>
doe with thee, I know not: this I know, that no Nation hath kept her integritie but thou. Oh, would thou hadst also kept thy sinceritie in religion! It is more then a miracle to mee, that feare doth not weigh-downe the eye-lids of the Iewe, when he offers to looke-vp to hea∣uen. <HI>Ne{que} enim,</HI> saith O∣rigen, <HI>deberent vltra coelum aspicere, qui in creatorem coeli pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>auerunt, et domi∣num Maiestatis. Neither in∣deed,</HI> saith he, <HI>ought they to beholde heauen, who haue sinned against the Creatour of heauen, and the Lord of Maiesty.</HI> The Turke con∣ceiueth
<PB N="182" REF="102"/>
more reuerently of Christ, then the Iewe: for, he accounteth of him as of a great Prophet; the Iew, as of a false Prophet. Neither hath the Turke so grosse a∣buses and absurdities, as hath the Iewe: which▪ who∣soeuer listeth to compare, shall finde. The Turke hath many riddles, which rather merite laughter then loa∣thing: and, for example sake, we will set-down some<NOTE PLACE="marg">In Alcor. Turc.</NOTE> fewe of them. <HI>What is that, which is first wood, and af∣terwards receiueth a spirit into it?</HI> It is there answered, <HI>Moses Rod. What woman is that which onely came from</HI>
<PB N="183" REF="102"/>
<HI>a man? and what man is that which onely came from a woman?</HI> It is there saide, <HI>the former to be Eue, the later to be Christ.</HI> The rehearsall of more of these friuolous fooleries would cost mee much time, and yeeld the Reader little profit: and therefore I will onelie heere insert one or two things re∣marqueable in the Turkish Phisiques. They hold, that <HI>the starres hang by golden chaines:</HI> Againe, they saie, that a <HI>Bull beares the earth vpon his hornes; so that when the Bull shakes his head, an earth-quake ensues.</HI> Modesty wil not let me enter into the
<PB N="184" REF="103"/>
Turkes paradise; where all things are vncleane, and be∣yond measure baudy. Oh my God! who is there that rightlie vnderstandes the courses of mans life; the cur∣ses due to it for the vices of it; and withall considereth the variances of religion; as also that Turkes inhabite the better halfe part of the world; Iewes and Atheists a quarter of the other halfe; Schismatickes &amp; Heretickes three quarters of that quar∣ter: who is there, I say, that weighing all these things, will not welcome, if not in∣uite death▪ specially in this age; in which, that of Tacitus
<PB N="185" REF="103"/>
is right true: <HI>et propter vir∣tutes</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Tacit. hist. lib. 1.</NOTE> <HI>certissimum exitium: And vertues,</HI> saith he, <HI>are re∣warded with certaine de∣struction.</HI> Vertue, looke to thy Essence; for, thou hast almost lost thy Existence: thou hast a Being of thy self; but, scarce any Being in any other. Wherefore I exhort all those, who either haue or loue vertue, to desire to bee dissolued, and to bee with Christ. Let them contem∣plate this, that death is the Orient of Weale, and the Occident of Woe; that is, the rising of all comforts, and the fall and setting of all crosses. Death is the sole
<PB N="186" REF="104"/>
sanctuary for sorrowe, the freedome from feare, hope's harbour, faith's faire field, the ending of a bad &amp; begin∣ning of a better life. Death is not so vgly as the world would make her; her lookes are louely: and when all the world disdaines desert, shee rewardes it. Wherefore, wee should not with such a fond childish griefe bewaile the death of our friends, whom mercy hath taken from miserie. As when we see the sunne eclipsed, wee grieue not; knowing it shall come to his former forme againe: euen so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it is heere; we should not fall into wo∣manish
<PB N="187" REF="104"/>
lamentations for the losse of them, whose bodies wee know shall rise againe; who shal see God with those eyes, with which they leaue to see the world: For, though they die to vs, they liue to the Lord. Wherefore, wee must not thinke, that Dauid lamēted the temporal death of his sonne Absolon; but, that his propheticke soule fore-sawe that eternall death due to Diuells and their mi∣nisters: for, to them, death bringes damnation. The wicked man dares not, in his greatest passion, call to God for compassion; but hides himself from his face,
<PB N="188" REF="105"/>
hauing all his time beene glutted with forbidden fruite. If hee looke vp, hee sees Gods iudgement hang ouer him: if downeward, he meditates his graue vnder him; and hell vnder it: if on both sides of him, at each hand sitteth horrour, and confusion: if before him, he beholdeth Perdition, his hangman, dragging him on to his slaughter: if behinde him, Vengeance doggeth him at the heeles; the least noise makes him expect his pursiuants: At last, he with∣draweth himselfe into his cabine, thinking to lock-out Death; who, in a moment,
<PB N="189" REF="105"/>
locketh-vp his eye-lids, ne∣uer more to open, till they shall see heauen gates shut a∣gainst their master. Oh foole! reuolt from thy irre∣ligious superstition, to a re∣ligious pietie; neither quake at that, whose power it is in thy power to conquer by an heartie penitence, and fer∣uent prayer. Shrinke not at thy fatale blowe: thy death shall be life; and that, a bles∣sed and eternall one. I, for my part, will account of death as of that which helps me to an vnualued bargaine; things eternall, for things momentarie: things truelie delightfull, for things falsely
<PB N="190" REF="106"/>
deceitfull. Oh welcome mi∣nute, that shall free this body from so long an apprentise∣ship of woe. And, indeede, what is there that should holde or delight me heere? except to satisfie the vnor∣dred appetites of the body, and vnlawfull desires of the soule. But perhaps some wil vrge, that I am as yet in my spring of youth; which I grant: Yet am I glutted, and tired as much with the trou∣bles of this Age, as a Priam, as a Nestor. The dayes are<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ecclesias∣tes. 12. 1.</NOTE> alreadie come vpon mee, wherein I may truely say, <HI>I take no pleasure in them.</HI> But, others will reply, that
<PB N="191" REF="106"/>
I haue friends for whose sake I should desire to liue. It is true indeede, that I haue friends; but, with-all, such friends as Tacitus speaketh of; <HI>Et quibus deer at inimicus,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Tacit. hist. lib. 1.</NOTE> <HI>ab amicis sunt oppressi: and they,</HI> saith he, <HI>to whom ene∣mies were wanting were op∣pressed by their friends.</HI> I long to bee acquainted with my neerer kinred, to whom I shall say, <HI>Corruption thou</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iob. 17. 14.</NOTE> <HI>art my father, and to the worme thou art my mother &amp; my sister.</HI> Salomontelleth vs, <HI>All pleasures vnder the</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccles. 1.</NOTE> <HI>sunne are vanity:</HI> I take his word; and therefore long to see what pleasures are aboue
<PB N="192" REF="107"/>
the sunne, where the Son of God sitteth at the right hand of his father, making inter∣cession for mee and all sin∣ners. And thou, Lord of hosts, grant, that when this my last and best day shall come, and those harbingers of death summon me to ap∣peare, that then I may bee readie: and grant also, that as, at the first, my body was willing to receiue my soule; so, at the last, my soule maie be willing to leaue my bo∣dy. Thou louer of soules, be thou mercifull to my soule: and when mine eyes shall grow dimme, my lips black, my mouth drawen-vp, my
<PB N="193" REF="107"/>
browes knit, my eares deaf, my hands and feerebenum∣med with cold, my pulse beating yet weakely, and when all my senses faile me, then giue me some sense of life euerlas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing. My good God, let me at that houre thinke as I do now, that it is a thing no more strange to die, the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to be borne▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>being it is an equal law of Nature, which bindeth ouer all a∣like, to their first and last ap∣pearance. I knowe, there is some paine in death: but, withal I knowe, that I owe that paine with the vantage to my mother. Who, as she endured as great paine, us
<PB N="194" REF="108"/>
euer woman did, to bring me into the world▪ so must I endure some paine to rid my selfe of this painefull life, of the which I am as weary, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are. I shallneuer be truely merry, till that day of mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th and re∣leasement commeth. All ioy h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere belowe is sinfull; and almost all delights vnlaw <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/><NOTE PLACE="marg">August. in Euang. se∣eun. Lu∣cam, serm. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>7.</NOTE> according to that of Austin▪ <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>titia est imp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>it a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> The ioy,</HI> saith he, <HI>of this Age is nothing else bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>punished.</HI> Ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> will I not seeke to hasten the hour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> of my deare deliue∣ry; but will attend Gods <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of life
<PB N="195" REF="108" MS="y"/>
as of a gift. If it will tarrie, I will not thrust it soorth of doors: if it make haste to be gone, I will not be he that shall intreate it to abide. The time I haue to liue, deuotion shall dispose of: and my chiefer pleasure shall bee in prayer. I will first pray for Christs church militāt, that it would please him to shor∣ten the time of her warfare, that so the time of her tri∣umphing may approach. Next of all, I will pray for all Gods anointed, ouer what Kingdomes, or Nations, so∣euer they bee placed; and in particular (as by the du∣ty of a subiect I am bound)
<PB N="196" REF="109"/>
for my gratious Soueraigne, Faiths great defender. Thou Ancient of daies, crown his dayes with happinesse: and as he raignes by thee; so let him raigne for thee: and, while he defends thy Truth, defend thou him from those <HI>porte-couteaux.</HI> For, in these treacherous times, it is to be<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 10. 36</NOTE> feared, that <HI>his greatest ene∣mies are those of his own<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> house.</HI> And, as for his succee∣der in the throne, gratious God let him be successeful in al his approued proceedings: that so, succeeding ages may sing &amp; say his praises. Lord, shield him rather from secret flatterers, then from open
<PB N="197" REF="109"/>
enemies: and, hauing all things, let him not want this one; A truth-teller. I will wish the same to him, which Thomas Walsing hamus re∣porteth of Henry the fift: that as he is <HI>Modest us <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> so he may be <HI>Magnanimus in actu.</HI> Last of all, I will pray for my selfe; that hee that made me, would vouchsafe to haue mercy vpon mee. Thou, that art able to throw an Angell down, ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> able to raise a sinner vp: Lord, then, raise me, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the gul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> of sin. Thou into Lambe of OOD, which dyed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t once for the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="198" REF="110"/>
mercy vpon me: and, seeing thou hast suffered for my wickednes, let not me suf∣fer for it too, nor cry for my crying sinnes. lesus, at thy Name my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ee shall bowe, my heart bend, and all my soule and body be transfor∣med into reuerence. Oh blessed, comfortable, all∣promising Nome! in which, the olde Age of new names, and (if you will haue it so) the newe Age of olde names may be included Christ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Origen, <HI>qui <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ill is or is, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Christ, saith he, who is in those <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of the earth, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>en</HI>
<PB N="199" REF="110"/>
<HI>amongst the Britannes. A∣men,</HI> Lord Iesus: and bee with vs still to the ends of the world. Mercifull mai∣ster, let mee with my last gaspe pronounce in confi∣dence those words of dying Luther; <HI>I haue serued thee, I haue belieued thee, and now I come to thee.</HI> And because there is no other way to come to thee but by death, Lord let me expect death e∣uery where, and alwaies; not knowing where, or whē it will expect me▪ and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me thinke of that often, which I must doe once. Blessed Maister, my will is thine: but, if it bee thy blessed will,
<PB N="200" REF="111"/>
take me out of this Age, be∣fore I bee aged: and let this corruption put-on incor∣ruption, this mortalitie im∣mortality, imperfectiō per∣fection; and then this impo∣tency shal see omnipotency; this nothing all things. Oh inconceiueable ioy, to be∣hold the Apostles, Patriarks, and Prophets, together with the Kings of the Earth, do∣ing homage to the King of Heauen and Earth! And till this ioyfull appointed time come, the greatest comfort I can yeeld my selfe and o∣thers, is an allusion which I tooke out of an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> French Writer: to weer,
<PB N="201" REF="111"/>
that <HI>as GOD laboured six dayes, and rested the seuenth; so man, after hee hath tur∣moiled himselfe through-out all the sex ages of the world, shall in the seuenth Age re∣pose himselfe in a better world.</HI> Which, he that crea∣ted the world, grant, for his sake that redee∣med the world,</P>
<CLOSER>Amen.</CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="112"/>
<PB REF="112"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

