<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="3">An occasionall discourse, upon an accident which befell his Maiesty in hunting. Composed in Italian, by Francis Cevolus, and thence translated into English</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Discorso d'un caso seguito à Sua Maestà nella caccia. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>Cevoli, Francesco.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A18345</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 4922</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S116846</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99852061</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99852061</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">17364</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A18345)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17364)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1373:16)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="3">An occasionall discourse, upon an accident which befell his Maiesty in hunting. Composed in Italian, by Francis Cevolus, and thence translated into English</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Discorso d'un caso seguito à Sua Maestà nella caccia. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>Cevoli, Francesco.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 8; [4], 8 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Iohn Norton, for Robert Bird, at the Bible in St. Laurence-lane,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1635.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Francis Cevolus = Francesco Cevoli.</NOTE><NOTE>English translation followed by Italian text with separate dated title page with imprint: In Londra, nella stamperia di Giovanni Norton, 1635. Register is continuous, with separate pagination.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Celeste Ng</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Celeste Ng</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A18345">
<STC T="S">4922</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852061</BIBNO>
<VID>17364</VID>
</IDG>
<GROUP>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>AN OCCASIONALL Discourse, upon an Accident which <HI>befell his MAIESTY in hunting.</HI></P>
<P>Composed in <HI>Italian,</HI> By FRANCIS CEVOLVS, <HI>and thence translated into English.</HI></P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by IOHN NORTON, for ROBERT BIRD, at the Bible in St. <HI>Laurence</HI>-lane. 1635.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="imprimatur">
<PB REF="2"/>
<P>Imprimatur hic Londini. <HI>Thomas Weekes,</HI> R. P. Episcopo Lond. à sacris.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE HO∣nourable his very good Lord, CHARLES Lord HERBERT, Sonne, and Heire to the Right Honourable, PHILIP Earle of <HI>Pembrooke,</HI> and <HI>Montgomery,</HI> Lord Chamberlaine of his Majesties Houshold.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">M</SEG>Y Lord, this Dedication can be no novelty to your Honour, who were formerly acquainted with the intention. I doe but here per∣forme what I heretofore did pro∣mise. Your owne skill in the ori∣ginall is such, that I might have spared the courtesie of the Tran∣slatour, but that I was ambitious to have more then one Countrey take notice of that service I owe unto You; who shall ever thinke it the greatest part of mine, to have had sometimes a relation to your Honour: If there be any thing in it which may deserue your perusall, it is beholding to the Subject, not to the Authour. It may have the happi∣nesse to be presented to his royall Eye, which I cannot hope for, save by the meanes of your Noble Father, or your Selfe: The strangers that were desirous to come to <HI>Christ</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
to <HI>Philip</HI> for admittance, and I know no other me∣thod, no neerer way to approach the Majesty of his An∣noynted then by him, who beares the name of that Apo∣stle, or your Noble selfe upon whom his Royall Majesty bestowed his owne Name at your baptisme: and, it may be thought, conveyed withall not a few of his vertues, whereof I here present you an imperfect picture, rudely drawne by an unskilfull hand, wherein I dare assure you of nothing good but the bare intention. May it please your Lordship to accept of it as a <HI>propempticon</HI> before that voyage you are now to make, from him who doth heartily wish you a prosperous journey, and a happy re∣turne.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Lordships most devoted Servant,
Francis Cevolus.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="discourse">
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>AN OCCASIONALL Discourse upon an Accident which befell his MAIESTIE in hunting.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">R</SEG>Everence, and obedience are due to any Prince, but the good onely have title to love, and commenda∣tions: Subjects must, and strangers may, pay both; who can plead no exemption from right, and custome. The royall vertues of the most puissant Prince CHARLES, hath made me willing to undertake, what my weakenesse tels me I am not able to performe. The custome of well-doing hath made it so naturall to his MAIESTY, that tis become a taske of more difficulty for an Oratour to relate his actions, then for him to doe them: and he is so frequent in the exercise of his vertues, that after ages will truely judge the bare history of his Acts to be no other then a continued Panegyricke. I shall not meddle withall; as neyther ambitious to be seene in His reasons of State, nor curious to peepe into his closet, but present him such as he presents himselfe in publique, and single out one particular, which once befell Him in his Royall sports: then the object of others discourse, as it hath beene since of my meditation.</P>
<P><PB N="2" REF="4"/>Hunting hath ever bene an exercise in request with the greatest Heroes. <HI>Chiron</HI> trayned <HI>Achilles</HI> up in it, and <HI>Xenophon</HI> thought it not unbefitting the compleatest Prince, when he presented it in his <HI>Cyrus,</HI> whom he propo∣seth as a patterne of persection. Nay, I have read of some people, who in the election of their Kings did especially require that he were an expert hunter. The ancient <HI>Romans,</HI> however they did not practice it at home, yet they did not dislike it abroad, and I suppose it was rather want of conve∣nience, then desire to use it, which made them refraine it. It was alwaies accounted an exercise masculine, and mili∣tary, as being the Schoole, and Theater of warre, and there∣fore the Magnanimous King CHARLES makes use of it, as a recreation, not an imployment; free enough from what was imputed to <HI>Antiochus</HI> by his Countrey Host, That his care of his game made him neglectfull of his government.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Plut</HI> in Apopth.</NOTE> He makes it but a sweet retire from his more serious affaires, solacing himselfe in the shadow that he may be inured to the shocks of warre: <NOTE PLACE="marg">Enodius.</NOTE><HI>Agit vice spectaculi, quod sequenti tempore poterit satis esse virtuti.</HI> Though he be the first borne Mo∣narch of the Christian fayth, and <HI>Salomon</HI>-like desire to possesse his Throne in peace, yet he hath a portion of <HI>Da∣vids</HI> spirit, and is not afrayd of warres. His goodnesse makes him affect peace, but his wisedome tels him the best meanes to conserue it is a preparation for warre: therefore he sets forth a royall Navy by Sea, therefore he delights in the martiall exercise of hunting by Land. <HI>Caesar</HI> carryed a Penne in the one hand, and a Sword in the other. The most Invincible CHARLES, hath in the one hand an Olive branch, the Embleme of peace; in the other a Palme, the Prognosticke of victory: proposing to his enemies the same conditions that <HI>Rome</HI> did to <HI>Carthage,</HI> to make their choyse.</P>
<P>The ancient Heathens entitled the same goddesse, <HI>Diana,</HI> both to hunting, and chastity: in both which, the King hath so deepe a share, that <HI>Hippolytus</HI> would thinke it an
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
honour to be his second. The comparison being here as ap∣posite as in the first application, to <HI>Constantinople</HI> in regard of <HI>Rome, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Suid.</NOTE>Dignius est ab hoc secundum numerari, quàm caeterorum omnium primum.</HI> For his eminency in the one vertue, I take the voyce of the publique for a sufficient proofe, and of his excellency in the other I have had no lesse then experience, When at <HI>Newmarket,</HI> anno 1633, his Majesty being attended with a glorious traine of Noble Courtiers, a pursued Hare runne for protection to his sa∣cred Person, and freed herselfe from an eminent danger by taking sanctuary under his Horses belly. An accident which howsoever to others but a nine dayes wonder, made a deepe impression in my thoughts, who imagined that little creature might afford some considerations, not mis-besee∣ming so great a Majesty.</P>
<P>Perhaps she signified the affability, and naturall cour∣tesie of the King, which makes him gracious in the eyes of all his observers: she being of old an Embleme of loveli∣nesse, and sacred to that goddesse, which it may be, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Philostrat.</HI> in <HI>iron</HI></NOTE>gave occasion to that jest put upon the Emperour <HI>Alexander Severus,</HI></P>
<Q><NOTE PLACE="marg">Lamprid.</NOTE>
<L>Venatus facit, et lepus comesus,</L>
<L>Ex quo continuum capit lepôrem.</L></Q>
<P>Perhaps she knew the justice of the King, and how much hee tenders the effusion of blood, requiring the punctuall observation of the old Rule,</P>
<Q><L>Qui gladio ferit, gladio perit.</L></Q>
<P>Witnesse that memorable accident which befell in Fleet-street, where when the Sergeants had arrested a man for debt, and were carrying him to Prison, some of his freinds or acquaintance, more transported by affection then judg∣ment, attempted to rescue him by violence, and amongst them one <HI>Stamphord,</HI> a Gentleman of good fame, but bad fortune, sometimes an appendant to the late Duke of <HI>Buckingham,</HI> being more couragious then discreet, by mis∣fortune killed one of the company; whereupon he was,
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
according to the usuall forme of justice, first apprehended, then condemned, and lastly executed. Nor could the dea∣rest memory of his deceased Master, or the humble petiti∣ons of the noblest Courtiers, and such as were in greatest favour with the King, prevaile any thing for his pardon: howbeit he were a man which both had, and might have done his Countrey better service. But offended justice must be satisfied; and the cry of blood rung so loud in the Kings eares, that it drowned those of the petitioners. He is armed with constancy against their importunity, and thinkes it not fit to bestow a courtesie which might haply cost the receivers a repentance. God himselfe is oft bountifull in denying our requests; and the flight of <HI>Fabius</HI> was accoun∣ted for fortitude. Here the King triumphed over the most intestine enemies, his passions, and made it knowne to the world that he hath a soveraignety over himselfe as well as over others: <NOTE PLACE="marg">Georg. 2.</NOTE>that his inclination to goodnesse is as sound in substance as spacious in shew, like <HI>Virgils</HI> Esculus, the roote as deepe as the branches high. A resolution which holds good against the threats of an enemy, doth often yeeld to the entreaties of a friend: No violence to that of love, it is strong as death: <NOTE PLACE="marg">Cant. 8.</NOTE>and yet he, who was never in∣exorable, if the suit were honourable, strongly denied what was earnestly desired, by those whom he most affected: and made the lawes of love give place to those of the Land. His clemency knowes how to pardon an errour, his discre∣tion how to correct a fault, and his justice how to punish a crime: which he sometimes doth for terrour to others, not because of rigour in himselfe. However he be thrifty in dispensing pardons for publique, yet he is sufficiently prodigall of private injuries: and he that will punish mur∣therers hath oft forgiven traytours: if to breake the Statutes, or deface the pictures of a petty Prince be more then petty treason, he concludes it a crime of a deeper die to deface the Image of the King of Kings: and therefore will not indulge it, lest his mercy to man should make him guilty,
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
and injurious to God. But where the fact immediately concernes himselfe, he can as freely pardon malefactours, as they offend: he hath not grudged to let those children enjoy their hereditary possessions, whose parents attempted to dispossesse him of his Throne, to let the Exchequer loose the commodity rather then he his clemency: thinking it sometimes convenient to purchase that respect by favours, which he might exact by force, that being a more proper act of his goodnesse, this of his power; and he being re∣solved by Gods example, to be more rare in the exercise of this, more frequent in that. But I feare in this long excur∣sion I have runne counter. Therefore I returne.</P>
<P>The Hare in her kind is endowed with a quicke hearing: which may well betoken the Kings facility in affording audience to the meanest suiters. <HI>Plutarke</HI> tels us the Hare was anciently the Hieroglyphicke of attention; which is a knowne vertue in the King: his hand is ever open to receive requests, and his eare to heare: nought but the unreasona∣blenesse of the demand needs feare a denyall: his distres∣sed Subjects never despaire of remedy, if he be once ac∣quainted with their malady. The appeale of <HI>Machetas</HI> hath not beene heard of in his dayes; against whom when King <HI>Philip</HI> of <HI>Macedon</HI> had by inadvertancy passed sentence, he made his appeale, <HI>a Philippo, ad Philippum,</HI> from <HI>Philip</HI> win∣king to <HI>Philip</HI> waking: his vigilancy stops all such: and thats a quality may afford another parallell.</P>
<P>The Hare is observed to sleepe with her eyes open: where∣by the Aegyptians expressed the vigilancy of a Magistrate, <HI>Video virgam vigilantem,</HI> sayth the Prophet: and the rod with the eye in it is the Embleme of the Scepter. The King never slumbers in the affaires of his people, but watcheth over them that they may sleepe secure; and buyes their rest by his owne disquiet. <HI>Iupiter</HI> told <HI>Agamemnon</HI> in <HI>Homer,</HI> it was not for a man in office to sleepe all night; fit counsell both for a god to give, and a King to take: all night he must not sleepe, lest he hazzard the publique, part he must, lest he endanger his private welfare.</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="6"/><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Lepus q. levipes Gellius ex Varrone. Firmicus, Astron.</HI> l. 8. c. 8.</NOTE>The Hare is so observable for her swiftnes that it hath got her a name in Latin, and a surname in Greeke: and the Astro∣loger gives out, that they who are borne under her name∣sakes constellation are excellent in that quality. The King of <HI>England</HI> hath naturally such a swift, and nimble gate as hath bene ever admirable, and sometimes wearisome to his followers. <HI>Pedibus velox Achilles</HI> is the running title which <HI>Homer</HI> gives that worthy Heros, and the vigorous, and lively pace of his Majesty bewrayes in him a soule truely heroicall, and borne for action, to which the body is a nimble Servant, no unweldy burthen.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Suid.</NOTE> To meet a Hare was held ominous to the ancients, <HI>Appa∣rens lepus infaust as reddit vias.</HI> But the superstition of Gen∣tilisme never enterd the heart of this Christian Prince: while he that sits on Gods right hand is auspicious to him, he needs not feare any sinister augury, whiles that Motto still holds true which he hath writ in letters of Gold, upon his Coynes, CHRISTO AVSPICE REGNO. The worst prodigies pretend no ill to good Princes: nor was this to him a forerunner of harme but rather a foreteller of danger, for so it was not long after an assassinate being carelesse of his owne did plot against the life of his Soveraigne: but the providence of God respected the piety of the King, and suffered not the malice of his enemy to goe any further then a trayterous intention.</P>
<Q><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Martial.</HI> l. 1. de <HI>Regulo.</HI></NOTE>
<L>Quis curam neget esse te deorum,</L>
<L>Propter quem fuit innocens ruina?</L></Q>
<P>was spoken of a petty King in name, but is more true of a great one indeed. It is just with God to honour them which honour him; and preserve their glory untouched who are tender of his. When the Temple of <HI>Vesta</HI> was on fire, and <HI>Metellus</HI> the Priest lost his eyes in rescuing the <HI>Palladium</HI> from the flames, it was objected to him by the Oratour, <HI>Ei propitios deos non esse, quem ne servati quidem servant.</HI> But here we may more manifestly discerne Gods mercy in the Kings delivery; which is more apparantly glorious in hel∣ping
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
out of dangers then preserving from them, <HI>Stantia non poterant tecta probare deos.</HI> And perhaps the timorous Hare was sent to forewarne him. The Fable reports, that when the Lyon the King of beasts, was advised to cast off the Hare as unserviceable for his Court, she told him she stood him instead of a swift Foot-post: and behold this Carryer comes to admonish the royall Lyon of <HI>England</HI> of his emi∣nent perill from an unnaturall Subject. So sacred is the Majesty of Princes, that even the most unarmed beasts will defend it, when men would violate it. <HI>Domitians</HI> Hare was not afrayd to play in the innocent jawes of his Lyons, which were farre more mercifull then their Master, whereupon the Poet tels her</P>
<Q><L>Si vitare canum morsus, lepus improbe, quaeris,</L>
<L>Ad quae confugias or a leonis habes.</L></Q>
<P>The case was the same with this, and the King; who hath that of his Lyons, never to insult over the prostrate, he is not cruell to the provokers of his justice, much lesse to the implorers of his mercy when he punisheth, it is the Magi∣strate, not the man; with the hand of justice, not his owne; and those that suffer under it cannot chuse but adore it, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Auson. cidy l.</NOTE><HI>Procris</HI> like, <HI>Cephali{que} cruentum</HI></P>
<Q><L>Diligit et percussa manum.</L></Q>
<P><HI>Philip</HI> of <HI>France</HI> was slaine in hunting by a wild Boare: but CHARLES King of <HI>England,</HI> and <HI>France</HI> was more miraculously preserved from a beast more savage, and not lesse pernicious, had not his power to hurt beene inferiour to his will: this being permitted, but that restrained by a greater power of him who reckons this amongst his royall prerogatives, that by him Kings raigne.</P>
<P>The Hare hath yet one most obvious quality, her feare; for this I can finde no parallell in his Majesty, unlesse it be that which <HI>Sidonius</HI> discovered in <HI>Theodoricke, timet timeri.</HI> His owne innocency, and the love of his people is a double guard which he most relies upon. He had rather, with <HI>Cyrus,</HI> to be stiled, the father of his Countrey, then with <HI>Cambyses</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
the Master. His life so strict, and unblameable, that to make a man compleatly vertuous, there needs no other law but his example, and tis sayd Courtiers are beholding to him for a great share of their goodnesse; he having set them such a faire copy, that they are ashamed not to follow it, though they despaire to attaine it: and this is it which be∣gets in them such a generall love to his person, not onely his place, which makes them like <HI>Hephaestion</HI> who loved <HI>Alex∣ander,</HI> not <HI>Craterus</HI> who loved the King. They need wish no addition to their felicity, but the continuance of it: nay for the generall good of the Common-wealth, I conceive no prayer eyther more compendious or compleat then that which is directed to God for the sole safety of the King: wherein I shall concurre with the publique votes of the people: desiring God ever to defend him who is the Defen∣der of the Fayth, and like the <HI>Cherubim</HI> with the flaming Sword, doth guard this earthly Paradise, the Church of Christ: that he may hold on in the same tenor he hath be∣gun, and reflecting upon his former Acts pray for the future in the words of that ancient acclamation,</P>
<CLOSER>DIV FACIAT ET VIV AT <HI>CAROLVS.</HI></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
<TEXT LANG="ita">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="7"/>
<P><HI>DISCORSO</HI> Dun caso seguito à sua <HI>Maestà nella caccia.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Composto da</HI> FRANCESCO CEVOLI.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>In LONDRA, Nella Stamperia di GIOVANNI NORTON, 1635.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="8"/>
<PB REF="8"/>
<HEAD>All' Ill<SUP>mo</SUP> et Ecc<SUP>mo</SUP> Sig<SUP>re</SUP> e Pro'ne mio Col<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd<SUP>mo</SUP> Il Sig<SUP>re</SUP> D CARLO HERBERT Primogenito, et Herede dell' Ecc<SUP>mo</SUP> Sig<SUP>re</SUP>, Conte di <HI>Pembroch</HI> e <HI>Montgomeri, Maestro di camera di sua Maestà.</HI></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">N</SEG>On si maraviglierà V. S. Ill<SUP>ma</SUP> della presente dedicatione, essendogli già prima noto il mio desiderio; hor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ttendo la promessa, e se ben' ella intende la lingua Italiana, ad∣ogni modo ho procurato sia trasfe∣rito il mio originale per l'ambitione tengo di palesar à piu d'uno l'osser∣uanza e debito mio verso V. S. Ill<SUP>ma</SUP> come sempre mi riputerò à grande honore hav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>la servita.</P>
<P>S'alcuna cosa ui sara che meriti d'esser riguard<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ta si dourà attribuir al sogetto e non all' autore, forsi potrebbe' ottener tanta felicita di comparir auanti gl'occhi e presenza del Rè il che sperar non posso se non con il di lei favore, ò di suo Padre. I Peregrini bramosi veder e parlar à Christo ricorre∣vano à <HI>Filippo,</HI> et io non saprei trouar piu breue strada d'esser introdotto alla Real Maestà che per mezzo di chi ha il nome di quest' Apostolo, o per V. S. Ill<SUP>ma</SUP> al quale la Sacra Maestà del Rè ha dato nel Batesimo il suo proprio nome, et insieme forsi donato molte di quelle virtù la cui tavola imperfettamente ho qui' abozzato.</P>
<P>Cofesso non esserui altro di buono che la mia intentione, e quel che con rozzo pennello ho adombrato, spero che
<PB REF="9"/>
con la penna del sottil ingegno e maestra mano del Dotto Traslatore sarà ritoccato.</P>
<P>Placcia' in tanto à V. S. Ill<SUP>ma</SUP> riceuere questo propempti∣con ericordo nel suo buon viaggio che con tutt'il cuore gli prego da Dio prospero, uada' accompagna to <HI>Virtute duce Fortuna comite</HI> con il felicissimo ritorno.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED> V. S. Ill<SUP>ma</SUP> et Ecc<SUP>ma</SUP>. Humil<SUP>mo</SUP> e Divotiss<SUP>mo</SUP> Ser.
F. Cevoli.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="discourse">
<PB REF="9"/>
<HEAD><HI>DISCORSO</HI> D'un caso seguito à sua <HI>Maestà nella caccia.</HI></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>Ciaschedun Principe si deue riverenza et obedi∣entia, ma l'amor e la lode non ad altri ch'al buo∣no I sudditi deuon di ragione pagar questi debiti, et i forestieri presentar simili tributi, mentre non sono essenti da costumi et osservanze de Popoli tra quali dimorano.</P>
<P>Le vere Reali virtùdel Potentissimo Principe <HI>Carlo</HI> hannonel mio petto inestato brama di cominciar quel che la propria debo∣lezza mi detta non poter poi ridurre al de siato fine,</P>
<P>L'oprar heroicamente s'e convertito in natura di sua Maestà in modo che quell' gl'è facile fare per <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>so, all' oratore sia dissi∣cile dire, mentre sempre piùs avanza nell' essercitio delle vir∣tù, si ch'i Posteri giustamente giudicaranno la semplice historia de suoi fatti esser un non interotto panegirico.</P>
<P>Io non mi mescolaro nelle sue gloriose attioni già che non vò ambitiosamente dietro la ragione di stato, nè con curiosit à at∣tendo il suo secreto gabinetto, má solamente tale lo rapresente<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ò qual egli stesso in publico si fà vedere, e trá tuti gl'accidenti sceglierò quello già non molto gl'auenne tra suoi, reali pàssa∣tempi nella caccia che fùcagione adaltri di parlare, et a mè di pensare.</P>
<P>Era costume di grands Heroi dilettarsi della caccia. <HI>Chirone</HI> l'insegno ad <HI>Achille,</HI> e <HI>Senofonte</HI> giudicò essere grand orna∣mento al Principe, 't a questo fine l'esorta al suo <HI>Ciro</HI> proposto per modello et Idea del Principe, anzi alcuni propoli nell'eletti∣one del Rè osservauano in particolare se fusse buon cacciatore.</P>
<P>L'antichi <HI>Romani</HI> se bene nel proprio paese per incommodit à del sito non andavano alla caccia ad ogni modo al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>roue era da essi molt' essercitata.</P>
<P><PB N="2" REF="10"/>La caccia è ombra di guerra, le fiere figure di feroci <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>emi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i, il magnanimo Rè <HI>Carlo</HI> si diletta d'essa, e non può esser tacci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣to come un vill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>no forestiero piccò il Re <HI>Antiocho</HI> dicen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ogli<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Plut</HI> in apopth.</NOTE> la diligenza della caccia render lo negligente nel governo del Regno,</P>
<P>Si serue il Re <HI>Carlo</HI> della caccia▪ per solle vamento d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mag∣giori ocupationi, ricevendo solazzo in qvesta dolce guerra per dover esser poi nell' istesso modo pronto al vero tenzone. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Enodius.</NOTE><HI>Agit vice spectaculi, quod seguenti tempore poterit satis esse virtuti.</HI></P>
<P>Ben<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Primogenito Monarca della Christiana fede, et a guisa di <HI>Salomone</HI> desideri stabilire in pace il suo <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rono, non dimeno è anco<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> herede dello spirito Davidico, nè teme la guerra, la di lui bontà fà ch' ami la pace, la prudenza gli so mi∣nistra non esser al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ro pi ù convenevol mudo per conservarla che apprestar la battaglia, quind' è <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he tiene in ordine un armata navale di sorti e ben forniti vascelli reali che rassembrano mo∣bili et inespugnabili castelli di legno in mare, quind' è che per terra si da al <HI>Martial</HI> studio della caccia.</P>
<P>Cesare in una mano haveva la spada, nell altra la penna e l Invitissimo <HI>Carlo</HI> in una ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nel' oliva Emblema di pace, nell∣altra la palma impresa di vittoria, proponendo al nemico l'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stesse conditioni che <HI>Roma</HI> già à <HI>Carthagine,</HI> accio elegga qual di due più gl aggrada.</P>
<P>L'antic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI>Gentili</HI> dic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iararono <HI>Diana</HI> Dea della castità e della caci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, delle quali prerogative talm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nte' è dotato il Rè che <HI>Hypolito</HI> si terrebbe ad honore appo luihaver' il luogo.</P>
<P>Questo paragone non disdice qui niente meno di quando già f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> fatto nel paralello tra Constantinopoli e <HI>Roma,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>id.</NOTE><HI>Dignius est ab ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> secundum numerari, quam caeterorum omnium pri∣mum.</HI> L'universal opinione e voce del popolo è assai buon testi∣monio per confermar quanto sia ammirabile in questa <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rtù, l'esperienza fà fede ancor nell' altra avanzar tutti.</P>
<P>Si ritrovava à <HI>Neuu Market l'</HI> Anno 1633. accompagnato d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> molti nobili cortegiani et <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>co un lepre seguito da cani correr all<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>lta di sua sacra Maestà e come' in franchigia ricoura<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>al <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>vallo Cos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to: enuta da gl <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ltri se ben non
<PB N="3" REF="10"/>
più di nove giorni come si suole dir per miracolo, niente dimeno <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>el mio petto più profondamente s'internò pensando che questo piccolo animalet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o dava occasione d'alcuni concetti non punto sconvenevoli alla Real grandezza.</P>
<P>Forsi accennava la grande benignit à e natural piacevolezza del Re che ne gl'occhi de riguardami non altro stampa che gratia. Il lepre già era tenuto per Emblema d'amorevolezza<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Philostrat▪</HI> in <HI>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on.</HI></NOTE> et alla Dea d'amore consecrato onde derivò il motto appropriato al Imperator <HI>Alesandro Severo</HI></P>
<Q><NOTE PLACE="marg">Lamprid.</NOTE>
<L>Venatus facit, et lepus comesus</L>
<L>Ex quo continuum capit leporem.</L></Q>
<P>Forsi gl era nota la giustitia del Rè e quanto schiv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lo spar∣gimen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o del sangue, e vuol puntualmente sia osservato il detto
<Q><L>Qui gladio ferit, gladio perit.</L></Q>
Dicalo il memorabil fatto nella strada di <HI>Fleet-street,</HI> dove li sbirri fermando un certo per debiti, mentre lo menav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>no in pri∣gione, à caso al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uni suoi amici più tosto dall' amore che dal s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o trasporta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i à viva forza contendevano liberar lo e particolar∣mente un bravo gentil huomo chiamato <HI>Stamford</HI> non molto tempo fà della famiglia del Duca di <HI>Buchingham,</HI> assai più p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onto di mano che di prudenza, mentre d'ambe le parti era gran z<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffa, non so come quest' ardito spadacino amazzo' uno di quella baruffa, ma che? prevalse la giustitia, f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> preso, condotto prigi∣one, poco dopo condennato e con la morte pagò il sio del sangue sparso. La <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>resca'e cara memoria del defonto Duca suo signore, le supplichevoli preghiere de più favoriti cortegiani non furo∣no bastanti ad impetrare dal Rè perdon al homicida che con il suo valore haurebbe potuto altresi pugnare pro Patria, mà fù di im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ri che desse sodifattione all' offesa giustitia e nell' orecchie del Rè assai più rimbombò il'grido del s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>gue the le voci de gl' efficaci oratori.</P>
<P>S'armò d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lla prop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia costanza contro Palirui instanza, nè giudicò <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>spediente dispensare <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>al favore à chi poi, se ne fusse pentito.</P>
<P>Spesse volte Dio e benigno, mentre volta le spalle alle de∣mande impertinenti, la suga di F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>o sù stimat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> per gra de fortezza.</P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="11"/>Le passioni sono i pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> potenti nemici dell' huomo, delle quali ill Rè trionfò e fece palese saper non sol' altri mà se steso domi∣nare. Insegnò ancor a l'amor della virtu dover essere non men<NOTE PLACE="marg">Georg. 2.</NOTE> bello, che sodo, conforme l'albero descritto dal Latin <HI>Homero</HI> le cui radici erano profonde tanto quanto irami in alto s'ergevano.</P>
<P>La costanza ch▪ alquando fù immobil colonna all' impetuose minacci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> de nimici, si vede poi croll<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re al sofsio dell amichevoli preghiere.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Cant. 8▪</NOTE>Non si trova maggior violenza dell' amore più forte della morte, c pur quello il quale mai fù inesorabile alle giuste do∣mande, volle questa causa tanto valorosamente negar quanto instantemente le persone piu care e favorite supplicavano con∣cederla, volle le leggi dell'amicitia cedessero à quelle della pa∣tria, ben ha saputo con la sua clemenza perdonar l'errore, con la prudenza correggere la colpa, con la giustitia punir il misfatto; è parco nel perdonare le publiche ingiurie, ma nelle private pur troppo prodigo, quello ch'a traditori piu volt e ha perdonato non perdon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r à già agli homicidi.</P>
<P>Se spezzare le statue de Regi, se seancellare i loro ritratti vien stimato delitto di lesa Maesta certo che fracassare l'huomo viva imagine vero simulachro del Re de Regi, sar à più grave Colpa e non da perdonarsi, acciò la misericordia con l'huomo, non sia onta à Dio, ma quand'i falli sono comessi contro di lui, è in∣chinato à rimeter' à delinquenti nell' ist esso modo ch'eglino su∣ron p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ti per offenderlo. I figli di <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uei Padri che tentarono disturbar lui e la sua Real casa dal trono, soffri godessero i pa∣trimonij ne si curò diminuire l'entrate del fisco purche non sce∣masse la pretiosa fama della clemenza, stimando cattivare l'animi piu per savore che per violenza, annoverando quello tra fatti di bontà, questa tra <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>attioni di podestà, et ad esem∣pio di Dio determinando in quel s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mbiant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> farsi vedere piu sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ ch'in questa fogg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a.</P>
<P>Mà io dubito che questa digressione mi tiri fuor della traccia p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>opostami▪ Il lepre per natural istinto ha <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>udito perfetissimo, figura del Rè facile in dar audienza alli homiecivoli ancor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> conditione▪</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="11"/>Il lepre anticamente secondo <HI>Plutarco</HI> era toli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> per geroli∣fico dell' attentione, questa virtu▪ è ben conosciuta nel Rè, mai ha chiuse le ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i per le suppliche e memoriali, sempre l'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rec∣chie aperte alle querele, nessuna purche giusta domanda vien ributtata, i sudditi non diffidano della salute, quando il male e noto al Rè, non si sente punto l'appelatione di <HI>Machete</HI> quan∣do <HI>Filippo Macedone</HI> non havendo ben dato orecchie alla sua causa, promulgò conseguentemente un'ingiusta sentenza, et s'appellò à <HI>Philippo</HI> ad <HI>Philippum,</HI> da <HI>Filippo</HI> addormentato a <HI>Filppo</HI> risuegliato, la vigilanza del Rè provede à questi richi∣ami e dà materia di far il seguente riscontro.</P>
<P>Il lepre ha per costume dormire con gl'occhi a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>erti, l'Egitij se <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rvivano per Emblema d'un vigilante Magistrato▪ <HI>Video virgam vigilantem</HI> disse il profeta, l'occhiuta verga è simbolo dello scettro. Non è sonnacchoso il Rè ne gl'affari del p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>polo, anzi veglia dimodo che quelli possono sicur amente dormire e con la sua vigilanza et inquietitudine compra il lor riposo.</P>
<P>Ad <HI>Agamemnone</HI> conforme rapporta <HI>Homero</HI> disse Giove non star bene ad un consigliero dormire tuta la notte, consiglio veramente a proposito che meritava esser d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>to da Dio ad un Rè, il quale non deve passar tutta la notte dormendo, accio la publica salute non sia in periglio, mà parte d'essa affin che la propriá sia sicura.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Lepus q. levipes Gellius ex Varrone. Firmi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s, Astron▪</HI> l. 8. c. 8.</NOTE>Il lepre è dodato di tanta velocita che b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n gli quadra il nome <HI>Latino</HI> e cognome <HI>Greco.</HI></P>
<P>Dicono l'Astrologi ches'uno nasce sotto la stella da essi chia▪ mata lepre sara di questa qualita assai ben forn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>to.</P>
<P>Al Rè <HI>d'Inghilterra</HI> la natura ha donato un caminar spedito e veloce e li suoi seg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aci alquando son soprapresi da maravi∣glia, et alquando arrestati da stanchezza, <HI>Pedibus velox Achilles</HI> cosi chiama sempre <HI>Homero</HI> quel grande Heroe.</P>
<P>Dal passo Real<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ripieno di vigore e vitarisalta'un anima ve∣ramente heroica nata per oprare, il cui corpo serve non per peso ma per agil ministro.</P>
<P>Havevano gl'antichi per infausto auspicio l'incontro del lepre Apparens lepus infaustas reddit vias, mà la superstitione
<PB N="6" REF="12"/>
de gl'Etnici non s'annidò nel petto del Christiano Rè. sin che quello il quale siede alla destradi D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o gli sara auspicio, sin che sarà vero quello che con lettere d'oro nelle sue monete si stampa <HI>CHRISTO AVSPICE REGNO.</HI></P>
<P>I catti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i augurij niente di male aditano al buon Principe, non fù à lui segno precedente di da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>no, mà aviso di pericolo, forsi non è vero? mentre non molto dopò un certo parricida non cu∣rando di se stesso, machinava alla vita del Rè, mà la Divina providenza non dimenticata della pieta Reale, non permise che la malignita del perfido s'avanzasse più oltre della su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> intentione</P>
<Q><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Martial.</HI> l. 1. de <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gulo.</HI></NOTE>
<L>Quis cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>am neget esse te Deorum</L>
<L>Propter quem fuit innocens ruina?</L></Q>
<P>sù detto d'un piccolo Rè mà da me molto meglio appropriato a questo Grande Rè</P>
<P>Dio è buono, e vuole render la pariglia a chi l'honora, et à chi è studioso della di lui gloria.</P>
<P>Quand' il Tempio di <HI>Vesta</HI> ardea, e <HI>Metello</HI> sacerdote si spi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se tra le voraci fiamme per salvar il <HI>Palladio</HI> rimase cieco, fù tacciato da un Oratore, <HI>Ei propitios Deos non esse, quem ne servati quidem servant.</HI></P>
<P>La misericordia di Dio più chiaramente si dim stra in haver l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>berato il Rè e più gloriosa risplende quando riscatta da peri∣col: che quando non permette incorrer in essi.</P>
<Q><L>Stantia non poterant tecta probare Deos.</L></Q>
<P>Io credo che questo timido lepre fusse mandato per aviso. Raconta unafavolach' al Leone Rè de gl'animali mentr'era persuaso cacciar il lepre dalla sua corte per esser quasi inutile schiavo, il lepre rispose ch'aurebbe servito per velocissimo corri∣ro, Ecco non so semi dica un lepretto, opur u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a staffetta spedita al nobile Leone <HI>Inglese</HI> figurato nell' armi Reali per avisarlo del sopra stante pericolo per causa d'un non più legitimo e natu∣ral maribelle vassallo.</P>
<P>Tant' è sacra la Maestà de Principi che se gl'huomini oseran∣no violarla l'istesse bestie et ancor in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rmi la diffendon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
<P>Il lepre di <HI>Domitiano</HI> non si spavento d'entrar e quasi scher∣zar
<PB N="7" REF="12"/>
uelli fauci de Leoni assai più miti del Tiranno ond' il Poeta</P>
<Q><L>Si vitare canum morsus, lepus improbe quaeris.</L>
<L>Ad quae confugias o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a leonis habes.</L></Q>
<P>Ne al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rimenté avennetra questo lepre et il Rè che hale quali∣ta de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>suoi Leoni di per donare à sommessi, non è crudele con quelli ch'attizano la sua giustitia molto meno con quelli ricorrono alla sua misericordia▪ quando punisce non si rapresenta huomo, ma Magistrato e non con il suo bra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cio, ma con la mano della giustitia, la qual ancor che p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sante la riveriscono,</P>
<Q><NOTE PLACE="marg">Auson. eidyl.</NOTE><L>Diligit et percussa manum.</L></Q>
<P><HI>Filippo</HI> Rè di <HI>Francia</HI> nella caccia fù investito miseramente da un Cinghiale, mà <HI>CARLO</HI> Rè <HI>d'Inghilterra</HI> e di Francia con non minor meraviglia fù liberato da una bestia non meno fero∣ce che nociva, se le forze fussero corrisposte al desiderio, la sou∣rana potest à per la quale Reges regnant seben permise il diseg∣no, troncò l essette.</P>
<P>Restami a dire un' assai conosciuta conditione del lepre ch' è il timore il qual non conosconel Rè, se pur non fusse quel che <HI>Sidnoio</HI> trovò in <HI>Theodorico Timet timeri.</HI></P>
<P>Non si fida d'altra guardia che della sua innocenza e dell' amor del popolo, Ama più tosto con <HI>Ciro</HI> esser chiamato Padre della Patria, che con <HI>Cambyse</HI> Signore.</P>
<P>La sua vita e si giusta et incontaminata che chi vuol vera∣mente divenir buono, non ha bisogno d'altr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> specchio che del suo es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mpio.</P>
<P>Alcuni cortegiani dicon dover riconoscere la maggiore parte delle loro virtù da lui a quali risplende con si belesempio che si vergognano di no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> seguirlo ben che non possino arrivarlo, quind' è ch accende tutti ad esser' emoli della sua persona, mà nessuno della dignit à, gli rende simili ad <HI>Hephestione</HI> che' amava <HI>Alesandro,</HI> non a <HI>Cratero</HI> ch'amava il Rè; Non bisog∣na preghino per accrescer lasua felicit à mà per eternala, anzi per il publico bene non possono essere orationi piu brevi e più efficaci, quanto pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gar per la salute del solo Rè.</P>
<P><PB N="8" REF="13"/>Dunque accompagnato dalle communi voci m'appresserò à Dio prega<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ch'egli difenda il difensore della fede ch' à guisadel <HI>Cherubino</HI> coula spada fiammeggiant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> custodis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e la Chiesa di Christo, vero Paradis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> terrestre, acciò nell'istess<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> modo che ha cominciato, seguiti' â regnare, e riguardando à passati suoi fatti, anfios<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dell' avenire con quell' antica acclamatione prego che</P>
<CLOSER>DIV FACIAT ET VIV AT <HI>CAROLVS.</HI></CLOSER>
<PB REF="13"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</GROUP>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

