<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Tvvo vvise men and all the rest fooles: or A comicall morall, censuring the follies of this age as it hath beene diverse times acted.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A18423</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 4991</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S107717</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99843413</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99843413</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">8145</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A18423)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8145)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1132:04)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Tvvo vvise men and all the rest fooles: or A comicall morall, censuring the follies of this age as it hath beene diverse times acted.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 104 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>S.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>Anno. 1619.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Sometimes attributed to George Chapman.</NOTE><NOTE>Place of publication from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2002-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A18423">
<STC T="S">4991</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99843413</BIBNO>
<VID>8145</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>TVVO
VVISE MEN
AND ALL THE
<HI>REST FOOLES:</HI>
OR
A COMICALL MORALL, CEN∣suring
the follies of this age, as it hath
<HI>beene diverse times acted.</HI></P>
<P>Anno. 1619.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Names of the Actors.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Proberio.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Antonio.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rustico.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sperato.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Insatiato.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lamia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Malingua.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Furioso▪</ITEM>
<ITEM>Purgato.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Parvagracio.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Simplo.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Securus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hortano.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Spurco.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Infaelicto.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Susanna.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mureto.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Corraso.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Stercorato.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Levitia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Noverindo.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hermito.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Acuto.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gulato.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Granato.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Phantastico.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Camerado.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ifero.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vulcano.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>PROLOGVS.</HEAD>
<P>RIGHT noble and worthy Assembly: It hath beene a
very auncient and la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dable custome, in the best go∣uerned
common-wealthes, to admit and fauourably to
allow interludes and discourses vpon the Stage for diuers
reasons; but especially two. The one, to entertaine the wel∣conditioned
people with some delightfull and fruitfull con∣ceits,
thereby as it were to deceiue idlenes of that time which
it had allotted for worse purposes. The other, for the iust
reprehension of such as with serious and more graue adui∣sings
cannot or will not be so freely admonished and corre∣cted.
The later of these two respects hath begotten this
<HI>Dialogue,</HI> ready to b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> acted, principally and specially poin∣ting
that <HI>Impe</HI> which is infortunately fostered vp to this
day, to ruine it selfe with infamy. Onely this comfort is af∣forded,
that if he be present, and withall silent, he may sup∣pose
that of all others it concernes not him. If hee be absent
(as most likely he is) then euery other that findes himselfe
parcell guilt may see the deformity, and forbeare the excesse.
Other touches and passages are, which our Author and wee
present not with minde to offend any, but to please the wel∣disposed.
And so in the name of all the rest I entreate
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ourteous <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>udience, and pardon of all faults.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB N="1" REF="3"/>TVVO VVISE MEN
AND ALL THE REST
FOOLES.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT I.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Proberio</HI> alone.</STAGE>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>Ow much wee that haue beene tra∣uailers
differ from other kindes of
people? So soone as we arriue, we
are attended to the <HI>Burse</HI> or <HI>Rande∣vou</HI>
of Merchants. There we walke
as if the whole world hath neede to
be informed, yea and directed by vs
in matters of greatest moment; such
as is trafficke and commerce with forraine nations, and the
state and disposition of those kingdomes through which we
haue passed. For it may be we can giue intelligence of pre∣parations
and invasions. We can demonstrate their strength
and munition. We can number their Captaines and Gene∣rals.
We can discouer their designes and confederates. And
finally, we can lay plots to crosse and make voide all their
purposes, and stratagems, which these home-bred and coun∣trie
spunne people can neuer attaine vnto. Therefore by
good right we are had in esteeme, and speciall request, and
courteously receiued of Councellors of state wheresoeuer
we come. Neither doe w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tye our selues to any one domini∣on
more then another, but indifferently to all states we de∣liuer
freely the condition of euery nation. And the place we
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>o is our best beloued so long as there we tarry, and
<PB REF="4"/>
not a minute longer. We oblige our selues to no Prince for
gold nor gaine, nor be pensioners to any Monarche: but
with desire to see more we passe through all gouernements,
vnchecked and vncontrolled, because we take part with
none, offend, none, nor are false to any. And this life wee
loue aboue all liues, not content with any life, but that
which seekes an other life.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Simplo <HI>and</HI> Nouerindo.</STAGE>
<P><HI>Mounsieur Proberio,</HI> you are welcome home.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's more then you know <HI>Segnieur Simplo,</HI> what
countrey shalbe my home?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you are welcome into England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes gentle <HI>Simplo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What newes? And what company came ouer
with you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Newes I haue none but ordinary to tell you. With
the state I shall haue some businesse. And in my company
came ouer an old acquaintance of yours, one <HI>Segnieur An∣tonio,</HI>
a man of extraordinary action and faction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>If it be the man I contiecture him to be▪ his name
is plaine <HI>Anthony,</HI> an English man, borne some 70 miles
from London Northwest, and hath beene beyond seas some
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>euen or twelue yeeres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's the man. But wee call him <HI>Segnieur Anto∣nio,</HI>
by reason of his trauailers in Italy and other places.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>As he hath chang'd his name and countrey, hath
he not altered his conditions? I assure you he was very ho∣nest,
and of good expectation before he went.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, vpon my word. Hee came ouer a great deale
better then he went, and well qualified: and there was no
doubt but he would continue so still, but that couetousnes,
and the diuel's on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? is he giuen to that? it were great pity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, this Sir <HI>Antonio</HI> or <HI>Anthony</HI> whether you
will▪ hath seene many countries, and learned many strange
qualities.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strange qualities! bee they as good as they bee
strange?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, doe you iudge? Ile tell you some of them.
And if you like them, wee'll put them in print, and set them
vp to be sold at the Hospitall porch, neere S. <HI>Nicholas</HI> sham∣bles,
and annexed to the great thing in <HI>magna chart<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> or
<HI>magno folio,</HI> entiuled, an <HI>Admonition to householders.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, if they deserue so, it shalbe so; and I'le be∣stow
the cost in printing, and deale with a friend for their
allowance <HI>sub pri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ilegio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>But first I'le account to thee what accidents wee
had in trauaile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I'le heare nothing till I heare them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>No? what if I should first reade a Sermon preached
within these seuen dayes at <HI>Amsterdam</HI> by a man of most
pure profession and inuention not ordinary, passing all that
liued before or behind him in the nouell straine; himselfe of
the right cut of <HI>Carolstadius:</HI> in which Sermon hee prooues
most deucutly, that it is Idolatry to fight against the Turke.
Wouldst thou not heare that first?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. What tell'st thou me of Sermons? let's haue
these qualities without any more digressions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, since you are so desirous, you shall haue them
by whole sale, retaile them at leysure when you come home.</P>
<P>Imprimis, when he liueth in a great towne like, London,
he loues to lye in a corner ouer the Kitchen, because the Iack
shall not whirle too often, to waken or distract him in pray∣er.
His dinners are for the most part ordinary, except foure
dayes in the weeke he visite his house-keeping friends. And
at supper a couple of egges, and a bit of cheese is a choyce
dyet after a liberall dinner: besides it saues fire and washing
of dishes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if I were his man, if he kept no better cheere
at his chamber▪ I would make the cheesefrye vntill the but∣ter
were spent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>But your cunning would fayle you, for hee hath a
tricke beyond your reach for preseruing his cheese. But to
the next.</P>
<P>Secondly, hee so cauils and wrangles with any man that
<PB REF="5"/>
he deales withall, that they ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er agree or loue after, and
yet euery Saterday he makes eauen with all the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou tell'st mee a wonder. How shall I beleeue
this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is so: chuse whether thou wilt beleeue me, or no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me see how these can be reconciled.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst thou not reconcile them? I see thou art a ve∣ry
barren fellow; thou hast not a spoonfull of wit. I am sor∣ry
that euer I vndertooke to teach thee these incomparable
tricks of <HI>Don Antonto,</HI> laboured for so toughly in climing
the <HI>Alpes,</HI> and so dangerously brought downe▪ Thou
look'st too neerehand, as if a man would spye for a Wood∣cocke
in the next queath of bushes; wheras thou oughtst to
eleuate thy aspect<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to thy vttermost kenning, as those doe
that lye on their backes to keepe sight of haukes which as∣pire
beyond the first region. Search me the furthest corner
of thy capacity, and there see if perhaps doe lye as in an ab∣struse
angles, some secret patterne of these proiects. Euery
<HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>zzard</HI> will prye if a mowle or a mouse shall happen in an
houres watching to creepe from a bushe right vnder her
stand: giue mee the Eagle soaring conceits, to spye what
springs before the furthest ranger a mile off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not how to diue into this bottomles secret▪
It is sure some riddle. I pre thee suspend me no longer: for if
I should beate my braines with an Iron pestle, not a sprinkle
of them will light vpon the outside of this enigmaticall pro∣position.
Nay, good now tell me, how he that palters with
euery body, should be eauen at weekes end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I will not sticke with thee for this once, but
looke not for it often; for I'le not vse you to it. Finde them
out by your owne study for me heereafter. You are of age
one would thinke. Thus it is: hearken well what I say at
first. for Ile not repeate it againe for losing of time. <HI>He i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en with all the world euery Saterday.</HI> Those were my
words, and I'le make them good; marke diligently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, pre thee dispatch, or els I cannot marke as I
was wont to doe. The marke will bee out of my mouth if
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
you come not quickly out with it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, euery Saterday night he makes eauen with all
the world, because hee wilbe the better disposed against
sonday. Hem Ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas! not yet▪ I am not able to endure it, I faint.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is euen that is to say. Ha. Ha. Hae.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my heart: not yet. A penieworth of <HI>Aquauit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI>
if I shall liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, hold: thou shalt haue it presently: tis at my
tongues end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, say on. If my sences faile not, Ile heare you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>He loues no body then, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d no body loues him.</HI> And
thus thou seest there's no oddes, but all eauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a jest is this? there's an eauen reckoning
with the diuels name. You shall be hang'd before Ile tor∣ment
my selfe with desire to heare any more of your knauish
tricks. Ile besworne I had like to mar'd all. It wrought with
me like a purgation. It has giuen mee a treble stoole at once,
though I find no fault. I haue it hot▪ and worse then any per∣fuming
pan in the world. You scuruy fellow, an twere no
for loosing land I haue <STAGE>(he layes his hand vpon his sword)</STAGE> not
maruaile though a man must be sicke at heart (I sweare) and
study so hard, and straine my wits to reach the rea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on of this
riddle. I am sure I did ouershoot it 40. yards, and had like
to put a dozen cases, how these two cases might well e∣nough
haue stood together in one subiect <HI>salua conscientia,</HI>
taken out of <HI>Scotus,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Aquinas,</HI> fully resolu'd by
them; but still I doubted I should fall short: therefore I
thought better to conceale them: and now doest thou gull
me thus grossely?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha. Ha. Hae. An thou be a good fellow rehears<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
or foure of these cases thou hadst like to haue produced; and
let's iudge how fitly they had beene applyed if neede had
beene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>To what end? for thee to mocke mee more? you
may command: but if I were willing, thou hast now put
them quite out of my minde, I know not where to beginne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke so. Thou were pockily distempered.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wil't please you to proceede? let's heare some
more of your goodly squires conditions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thirdly. When he meanes to ride to his counttey∣house,
he goes three daies before to some groomes at court.
And if from them he leatne any newes (if it be but of a posy
given the king of Fraunce by his nurse, or that a fisher man
sayling by the <HI>Barmoothes</HI> saw a fire at singing of a hog) this
carries him scot-free to all the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> gentlemens houses of his ac∣quaintance
scituate, set, lying, &amp; being within seaven miles
of the high way of any side vntill at length he set foot at his
owne stable dore <HI>pecunijs numeratis</HI> remaining entire in his
right pocket. And the like he can doe retrogrado to Lon∣don,
but by variety of friends because the same newes may
be newes forward and backward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is a very plaine tricke, and needes no such <HI>en∣comions,</HI>
and <HI>Epithets</HI> of commendation as you bestow on it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it so Sir? ther's your iudgement, and bolt soone
shot. But if I shew that it is a very difficill, ambiguous, pe∣rilous,
perplexed and involved <HI>stratagem,</HI> what will become
of your opinion hereafter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who? here's a busines about riding a few miles by
many gentlemens houses, as though it requires such ingeni∣ous
circumstances.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro,</SPEAKER>
<P>I, that it does Sir. And I vndertake to make it ap∣peare
though perhaps you haue nere a capcase to put it in.</P>
<P>First <HI>Segnior Anthony</HI> so soone as he puts foot in the stir∣rop,
is to feare least the Master &amp; Mistres should not be at
home &amp; his perplexity in that case is very hardly dissolved.</P>
<P>Secondly how to carry his tales and discourses methodi∣cally.</P>
<P>Thirdly to take heede he discover no familiarity with the
gentlemans adversary.</P>
<P>Lastly what kinde of farewell he were best to take at par∣ting.
These be matters of mighty moment (as thou seest)
which he hath to cast, and recast; to meditate, and ponder;
to tosse, and tumble; to revolue, and refolue; to put forwarde
<PB REF="6"/>
with <HI>Pro,</HI> and pull backe with <HI>contra,</HI> to obiect, and confute;
to throw doubts and mishaps like snow-bals, and against
them erect bulwarks &amp; defences, to admit wounds &amp; scars,
and to apply salues; to conclude, come what come will to
haue cordials in store, &amp; all little enough to saue his best be∣loved
in his purse. And yet thou <HI>Dunstable</HI> breed thoughtst
it as easie a matter to performe them handsomely as to make
a good posset with a quart of new like and a quantity of
cleere chamberly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I confesse all these be farre aboue my element:
and that in many yeares study I cannot comprehend one of
them, therefore, I leaue th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to your <HI>cavaglyer</HI> without <HI>Peere</HI>
in mine opinion. Hath he any more qualities of this nature?
Lets haue them, for at least I shall learne some wit out of
them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou learne wit out of them? never while thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣vest:
not honestly neither. They will rather rob thee of those
wits thou hast, he hath infinite such as these, which in verie
pitty to thee I forbeare to relate at this time▪ These are e∣nough
to conceiue at once. For if I should driue them all in∣to
thy braines togither, though it were with a tenne-penny∣naile,
thou couldst not carry them away: but rather they
would make thee madde in the case thou art now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? what case am I in thinkst thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not sit I was to receiue such potions without due
preparation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall I doe to be made fit for their operatiō?
Ile take any course thou wilt prescribe me to get perfection.
And I can imitate like an <HI>Ape.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou makst a large offer, &amp; a rash, which full soone
(I doubt) thou wilt revoke: but ile try thee. Before thou be∣gin
to professe this art, thou m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t forget all rules and instru∣ctions
of manners taught thee by thy fathers, godfathers, or
schoolemasters, and renounce all good counsaile given thee
from the beginning of the world to this day: that so being
an empty a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d voide vessell thou maist be the more apt to re∣ceiue
the tincture and impression applyed. And thus begin
<PB REF="7"/>
thy A.B.C. in <HI>matchevillaines</HI> schoole. Otherwise; if tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
shouldst reserue but so much as a secret intention to keepe
thine old honesty on the one side of thy head, and lay open
the tother side to entertaine these restlesse and still stirring
cratchets, there would be such hurly burly in thy brain, that
all the wit thou hast will not keepe them in order. Therefore,
if thou desirest to be of the cunning cure▪ and withall lov'st
thine own peace▪ come cleere without wit or honesty, weele
teach enough in a weeke to serue thee all thy life time. Il<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
bring thee acquainted, and then ile turne him loose to teach
and furni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h thee with destructions enough for a whole
country.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Destructions. What should I doe with them ex∣cept
it were to destroy others. But I doubt I shall pay deare
for my schooling, and that I like not. But for the other point
of parting with my former good lessons, faith, I can quickly
doe that for I never gain'd any thing by them, therefore I
can be content to come to him as naked as ever I was born.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's great step to your well profiting I may say
to you; and tis a great signe of grace to be obedient, and
wholly to resigne your selfe to good inspirations: but canst
thou tell when thou hast good counsell giuen thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I; more then a child: For now you hau∣made
me put off all my old learning I am become a very in∣nocent,
as if I were this day taken from my mammee: but I
trust you because you are my frend. I hope y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ule put me to
none, but such as shall teach me enough for my mony. And
you say he is wise and will giue me samples enough, &amp; then
I warrant you Ile take um like a spunge till I be twice so big
as I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, then thus farre we are agreed. And I wish you
not to stand vpon his getti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g by you, least you be penny∣wise,
and pound foolish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>How learn'd you his cunning so perfectly? hau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
you knowne him long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> why I haue knowne him these 30 yeares at
least, and convers'd with him in his best times; somewhat <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="9" REF="7"/>
cost me you must thinke, but that's past. I would not for any
thing but that I did knowne throughly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has he beene in Italy then as you said before?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that he has, and caried from thence more th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n all
the townes in Italy could spare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>what's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not tell thee, thou hast already more then
thou canst well beare: thou art almost drunke with the very
smell of his wit, or else thou wouldst never so idly aske me a
question which I told thee twentie times.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nover.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mounsieur Proberi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> I have heard all the confe∣rence
between you and <HI>Simplo:</HI> and I doe so much mislike
your discourse that I cannot chuse but oppose my selfe in my
frends behalfe whom I heare egregiously to be wrong'd by
you <HI>Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>beri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>In what <HI>Noverindo,</HI> haue I done him injury?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>In all your speech generally: and in many parti∣culars.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>O vinversall <HI>Noverindo</HI> in what particulers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis no matter. Ile tell him all when we meet next▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's not matter. but canst thou disproue me in a∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y
thing I said? or dost thou knowe any good by him that I
haue not spoken of▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, or else I knowe but little: for if you praise <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
frend on this fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hion I prethee speake the worst <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ou canst
by me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, it may be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Ile pleasure you so much: but to the
mat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er▪ canst thou disproue me in any thing I faid?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, that I can, &amp; that I will. I can disproue thee
in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aidst hee never deale<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ with any man but hee
cavills, and wrangles with him▪ which is vntrue. And I had
much adoe to keepe in my mother tongue, but could haue
found in my heart presently to haue put the lye downe thy
throat, but I did bridle my nature to heare all thou wouldst
speake. And now to demonstrat thy falshood, I say, and will
i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stifie that he is as good a 10 ith 100 man either to giue or
take as any is in London▪ and that he keeps his daies (espe∣cially
<PB REF="8"/>
of receit) as strictly to an howre as any man. And fur∣ther,
that hee cavelleth or wrangleth not with any in this
Kind: therefore you are a lying fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not to forward with your lyes <HI>Noverindo</HI> if you
loue your selfe: for though I will not fight for feare of the
proclamation yet knowe I can make you giue me satisfacti∣on
vpon your knee if I would complaine: but I will seek no
such advantage; for the cause it selfe giue mee victory e∣nough
over thee, and returnes the lie most bra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ely into thy
gullet. I can proue <HI>Nody Noverindo,</HI> that in thy owne trade
and his of <HI>decemper cent.</HI> when he lost 100<SUP>l</SUP> which the scri∣uener
deliuered his owne messenger after the bond sealed,
(who ran away with the mony) he brake his day, and sued
the scriuener striuing to recouer the whole, or some compo∣sition
by that meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>But did he recover any? or did the scriuener giue
him any thing?000?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>He re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouer'd not; nor got any thing from the scri∣uener.
But was not this a wrangle, and a shamefull cavill? yea
and with a <HI>Noverint</HI> man himselfe which thou deniest? 000
now thou lyest in thy swallowing place <HI>Noverindo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Segnieur Simpl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> Helpe me a little. Canst thou say
no good of this gentleman▪ it frets me to the heart to heare
a man of our owne making to be thus misus'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith not I, not much, sauing that I haue heard
many yeares ago<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that he was a reasonable honest man but
for's religion, and they say still hees a kinde of a Papist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a rascall stis? doe I call thee to speake in his
behalfe, and dost thou prate of religion? what has he or I to
doe with religion? I dare sweare that hees an honest man of
no religion. <STAGE>(Intrat Antonio)</STAGE> and younders the man, let's see
now who dares charge him with religion. I hope he and I
haue worke enough and neuer busie our felues about religi∣on.
So many banckrupts, and housekeepers now adaies tis
time to looke about vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? dost thou finde fault with housekeepers:
youle please him never a whit with that, for ant were not for
<PB REF="8"/>
good housekeepers he would haue many hungry meales▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>I finde fault with such housekeepers as dare not
shew their faces without their owne doores. I cannot indure
this. Ile complaine to him on you both, if euer hee light on
you within the lash of the law, ther's no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rcy: and tis no
matter, teach you to speake so evill of him behind his backe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why cockscombe; how canst thou tell his backe
was towards vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, mocke on, twas in his abs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce, thats all one:
Ile tell him if youle giue me nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue thee, yes a rope <STAGE>(Noverindo turnes toward An∣tonio)</STAGE>
these caterpillers are al for what will you giue me like
<HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>das▪</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Nov.</HI> and <HI>Anton.</HI> at severall doores
<HI>Noverrindo</HI> speakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Bonu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dies▪ Segni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur Antonio, Magnifi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>;</HI> the wor∣thiest
gentleman that ever consorted with the bankers of
this citie. Sir I hope you make no doubt <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> teneri &amp; firmi∣ter
obligari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ibi aut t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o certo attnrnato,</HI> &amp;c. And further <HI>ob∣ligamus
nos, &amp; quemlibet nostrum, heredes, &amp; exec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ores no∣stros
&amp;c.</HI> The condition is to bee ever ready at your lowest
service.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a rogue stis? he can speake nothing but obli∣gations
as <HI>Ovid</HI> did verses.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gramarcees gentle <HI>Noverindo:</HI> how goe the rates
now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir you may haue as much as you will at eight in
the hundred, others pay ten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you: then I haue a match already: a frend
of mine must vse a thousand pound and intreats my band;
Ile <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay he shall haue it by my meanes. Thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>halt haue forty
shillings in the hundred for brocage▪ and I will gaine other
fortie shillings, this is but twelue in the hundred that's dog
cheape, I knowe some pay a great deale more: And Ile haue
good land twice the worth for my counter security. Let me
alone to hamper them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are wiser sir, fast bind fast find. And if they
<PB REF="9"/>
faile yeull trice them. I trow vpon the mortgage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah ha, art avis'd of that? surely I shall doe them
good to make the fooles take heed of others. And what falt
is in me, a bargaine is a bargaine: aud if I giue them a little
more for their land when it is forfeited, they may thanke me
but no parting with the land, for it is so deep if a man would
dig it that it reacheth to hell, and ther's no redemption.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, this is agreed: and if you will haue 3000<SUP>l</SUP>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>peak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but the word, and giue three daies warning, weele
come at your whistle as your wife was wont to doe: but
theres a thing I must impart to you which (I hope) you will
take well at my hands, being but the relator.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? is any Backrupt that hath my summes put
forth▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not one, they are as safe as in your chest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it be what it will then, <HI>I</HI> care not a rush.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir it is some discredit to you if it be true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>If it be true, and discredit <HI>I</HI> weigh it not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah noble <HI>Antony</HI> <STAGE>(he imbraceth him)</STAGE> pardon me if<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
I be bold with your worship, for no man could haue spoken
more pithely, and more like our owne corporate brother
then this was: why Sir for all the world so are wee, never
mou'd say what men will: wee could not liue richly if men
had cause to speake well of vs, giue me your hand, Ile liue &amp;
die with you for that word▪ and leo here with this handof
mine I reach you the hearts of all our company; now I dare
say any thing to you without feare, or blushing. That which
I was so vnwillidg to vtter was no more but this: it is very
credibly reported that you never deale, or contract with a∣ny
but you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>avill, wrangle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, paulter, wrench, shift, chapp,
change, deny, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efuse, goe backe from your word, breake off,
and play all manner offowle play; wherevpon all men speak
evill of you, and as many as had once commerce will never
more meddle with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>All this is nothing, I haue heard twentie times so
much with my owne eares, and smile at the poore fellowes
that they spend their time with talking of me. But didst thou
<PB N="13" REF="9"/>
euer heare but I gain'd by them all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, that's certaine: they all agree on that as a
verdict.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, there's it then. Now thou seeft where wit
lodgeth, with me, or with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith 'tis true. And they haue nothing to charge
a man withall but <HI>Conscience</HI> and <HI>Religion,</HI> and such imper∣tinent
stuffe. But I thinke I haue taken downe some of the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
about the word <HI>Religion</HI> of the oldest stampe, that you
should be tainted withall, and I trow I haue so silenc'd them
that you shall not neede to trouble your selfe with studying
to reveng<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, they talke their pleasure behind my backe, but
I wish they would speake one word to ground an action v∣pon▪
Didst thou heare him (whosoeuer he was) say, I am a
Papist?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, no Sir, I warrant you, they dare not for fortie
pound say so. But that you were one, that you looke like
one, that your heart is so still, if you durst for losing some
of your goods, that you were honester when you stucke to
it. That now you dissemble. And such like words full of su∣spition,
but not to beare an action. They are crafty enough
for that. But I trow. Sir, you are too wise, and so I answered
for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou didst well. I know some of them would
gladly catch me in a trip. But Ile watch them well enough.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. I.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCENA II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Securus</HI> and <HI>Hermito</HI> at severall doores.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir <HI>Hermito.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>No man better met heere then your selfe. I
was in great care for an <HI>Associat</HI> in the affaire with this day,
and almost euery day I vndertake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir my society will afford you small contentment,
<PB REF="10"/>
if my daily taskes required not my attendance, where by
perpetual vow I haue engaged all my houres vntil my death.
For I am fit for no other imployment but my beades▪ Neuer∣thelesse
if it please you briefly to let me know your desire, I
will by my answere you reasonable satisfaction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>When I doe seriously consider the worlds present
condition: And that we which converse abroad with all
sorts of people are subject to so many mistaking, censures,
and vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure reports, that it passeth the skill of any man to
ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y himselfe vprightly, &amp; without blame, I begin to iudge
you, and your like onely happy, who chuising to leaue the
world, haue procured quietnesse to your life. But Sir <HI>Her∣mito,</HI>
I marvaile what hath remoued you from your caue to
the countrie. Are you as weary of private liuing, as I am of
too much company? The newes must needes be great, and
strange which brings you hither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>No such matter, as that my intended course of
dwelling with my selfe sequestred fro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> all resort, should
haue an end so long as my abode in this world endureth.
Farre be it from my thought euer to wish the change of my
estate. As now I am I trouble not others, nor any man of∣fendeth
me. And where no mistake is, who can thinke of al∣teration?
my resolution hath bred my contentment: the
peace which I enjoy, counter-valueth all maner of wants.
And my spiritual excercises take away tediousnes. The cause
of my comming hither (Sir <HI>Securus</HI>) is a Proclamation late∣ly
set forth by the king, that all his subject being men of
21 yeares, &amp; vpwards, living within 50 miles of the Court,
shall appeare there within 14 days after notice given them.
And about three dayes past, a pilgrim passing by my cell,
told me of this Edict, and that it was vpon alleageance. So
I being his subject (thogh seruing him to no other purpose,
but praying for him) thought it my dutie to make my ap∣pearance.
and to depart without delay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I am right to haue intercepted you (whe∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her
you be travailing to or fro the Court) because this day
<PB N="15" REF="10"/>
is appointed for hearing and determining many controver∣sies,
and censuring sundrie sorts of people: And some of
these differences beyond my learning. You therefore come
very fitly to aide me. And this whole affaire being princi∣pally
for peace making, and ending debates without suite
of Law▪ you may not refuse to ioyne with me in a worke of
so great charitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>In very deed Sir, euery ought to yeeld his best
helpe to such workes. And although I haue alreadie recor∣ded
my appearance at Court, and licenced to returne to my
poore home▪ and would willingly spend some houres with
you to so good a purpose; yet (<HI>Alas Sir</HI>) I am like to pre∣vaile
very little with any body, wanting both acquiantance
and authoritie among them whosoever they be: therefore I
entreate my fruitlesse presence may bee spared; but I will
not be wanting to you with my prayers for your successe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, for your authoritie and acquaintance it shall
not skill. All that I haue both those wayes, s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>albe confer∣red
vpon you equally with my selfe. If they despise you,
they shall contemne mee also. Onely I entreate your com∣panie
panie this day, and then I cease troubling you further what∣soeuer
neede require hereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I expect no intreatie, neither will I wrong you so
much as to make further request to my poore selfe. I stay
willingly and am at you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> service in all things.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No seruant of mine Sir, but my friend vpon equall
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>earmes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They both sit downe in chaires some distance
each from other.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. II.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Rustico, Hortano, Acuto, <HI>and</HI> Vulcano.</STAGE>
<P>Neighbour <HI>Hortano,</HI> I haue considered of the great coile
we had the last Sabouth after evening praier in the verstrie a∣bout
<PB REF="11"/>
putting downe the <HI>Holy-dayes.</HI> It hinders our busi∣nesse
much. And mee thinkes this praying in a Church a∣mong
those of high degree is nothing pleasantable, and
blushing takes away my devotion. I can pray a great deale
better, and with a more comelie grace when I whistle at
plow. And me thinkes't were a goodly matter if euery man
in's calling might follow his focation, and there doe such
devotion as his stmacke stands to.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, neighbour <HI>Rustico,</HI> I am euen of your mind.
For Ile bide by it, I ha more weeds growes in one Holyday,
then in three workie dayes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, you are a Gardner, it becomes you wel to agree
with the Husband man, if we two hold together, we shalbe
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oo hard for twentie fooles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed 'twer a gay thing if wee could put downe
these <HI>Holy-dayes,</HI> as you say. Me thinks' twer an easie mat∣ter
as well as we ha put downe the Fasting-dayes <HI>pell mell,
hand ouer head.</HI> An wee wood hang together 'twer soone
done, but when some are so arseward 'twill neuer be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>You talke you know not what. There were no rea∣son
in it: for that were the way to breake all order, and giue
our mindes altogether to toyle, and neuer serue <HI>God.</HI> For
you would not s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>here neither if you had your will, but
the Sondayes should shortly goe downe for company. You
will leaue nothing standing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, you are a Tayler, you speake for your profit▪ For
an 'twere not for <HI>Holy-dayes,</HI> which require fine cloathes,
and much change, you might begge your bread.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>You hit the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aile on the head neighbour <HI>Rustico.</HI>
Weele put them downe an you'll keepe stroke with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay <HI>Sirra,</HI> if any man hit the naile on the head, it
should be you, because you are a Smith▪ but soft, you are so
hot with your rip rapping, that you misse the nayle and An∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yle
also. For my part although I doe boldly worke on Ho∣ly▪
dayes as other taylers vse Christmasse day and all, yet
would I not misse the Holy-dayes for any good, nor would
<PB N="17" REF="11"/>
I breake the order without necessity. But is it so easie a mat∣ter
to put downe the Holy-dayes thinke you? And will
you doe it with the furious fire-forke? And you Master
Gardner that will rake vp Holy-dayes and Fasting-dayes
like weedes, and bury them all in a rrench, you are both
both fowly deceiued. For neither haue you put downe the
Fasting-dayes, because still they are bidden in Churches,
nor is the case alike▪ for Fasting is private, and cannot so
well be punished, but if you come not to Church, vp you go
not to Church, vp you goe for a <HI>Recus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t</HI> an you were my
father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why for all that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hud we be troubled with so ma∣ny
holydaies? wood not fewer serue the turne as well? I doe
not thinke our auncetrums were so pestred.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, and with many more; and kept the eues halfe
holy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>How didne a then for doing their businesse? sure a
were all beggers. And yet twood anger me that my graund∣sir
should be a begger. I it wood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so neither. They liued very well: and had not
the twentith begger that we haue: and were great house∣keepers
every man almost. They built all the Townes, Col∣ledges▪
and Religious houses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Didne a so indeed? I cha hard my grandsir, &amp; gran∣nam
tauke much of those things. Sure but I thinke they
went to plow and cart on the workydaies, and built those
things you tauke on vpon the holydaies, or else it cood ne∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er
be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no. They suffered no kind of lighter workes to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e done in those daies, much lesse such pain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>full labours as
they were.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why were the Saiuts daies kept holy at all? Tell
me some reason for it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>They did in those daies giue grea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> honour to such
as suffered death for Christian religion, although the men
were as poore as Christs fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>shermen. And therefore the daies
of their martyrdome they kept holy, and came to Church to
<PB N="18" REF="12"/>
glorifie and praise that God, for whom those Saints died,
there were people exhorted to doe the like.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I mislike the very ground, and cause of those
holydaies which (you say) is suffring death willingly. Doe
not we die fast enough (thinke you) against our wils, but we
must set vp a trade of dying with a good will▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou speakest against reason. For if thou must
needs dye, first, or last, wert not better to die for a glorious
cause, so to be sure of heauen, &amp; willingly in perfect memo∣ry,
then against thy will wrestling with death, &amp; overcome
in the end with great paine, and perhaps past thy sences.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Reason me no reasons▪ I speake as I thinke, I pro∣test
from my heart I had rather doe any worke in the world
then dye. What? never come home againe to my wife, and
my pretie barnes? Why, I haue a boy, his name is <HI>Iacke;</HI> hee
has a face as welfavor'd as any great turnippe root, with a
cracke in the mid'st, which is the very proportion of his
mouth. I will not willingly leaue that boy for all the deaths
in the world. No I will not. But if I must needs dye whether
I will or no, I wood haue death take mee asleepe, that I may
not see his face, for if I did I would run away as hard as ever
I could for my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Acuto</HI> talke with me, hee speakes like a foole. I
haue more wit then twentie such loggerheads.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then I haue more wit then thou canst get▪ for
I can make my horses turne vp the ground, and thou must
doe it with thy hands and feet, else thou canst earne no mo∣ny.
Come neighbour <HI>Vulcano,</HI> we two wise men will leaue
these two to play the fooles here vntill our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urne come a∣gaine.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Rust. &amp; Vul.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>Acuto▪</HI> let vs two conclude what shall be∣come
of these holydaies, and as we agree, I warrant it shall
goe. And thou hast almost perswaded me to let them stand.
But let vs goe and read a booke I haue at home of the liues
of Saints to furnish vs with stronger reasons against our
next encounter with these Dunce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and then wee will end
this controversie.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="19" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>How thinke you by this S. <HI>Hermito?</HI> would you
haue imagined that such plaine fellowes as these be, should
call a businesse of this nature in question? By this you may
may gesse what stirring heads we haue to deale withall, and
how easie a matter to keepe them in order.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is somewhat strange. And the more vnlearned
the men are, the harder to be satisfied. But he hope is, that
as mad men doe best service when some of their like are
most vnruly, so these men being alike vnskilfull will soone
confound each other, and so giue over the businesse.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. II.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Antonio</HI> at one dore▪ <HI>Proberio</HI> and
<HI>Simplo</HI> at another.</STAGE>
<P>It is not vnknowne to mee that very many doe censure
my deeds as wicked and not beseeming a Christian. But this
is the iniquitie of the time, because they doe not distinguish
between persons and seasons. For my actions being not or∣dinary,
are not to be iudged by ordinary, but refined wits.
For now your downe right dealing is exploded, as too sub∣iect
to every meane capacitie.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yonder is thy master that shalbe (<HI>Simplo▪</HI>) thou shalt
lose no time, weele to him sodainely. <HI>Segnieur Antonis.</HI> All
haile to your person. Here is a man desires to serue you; to
be your pupill; to imitate your actions so neere as his vessell
can hold the print. And he will doe well. For hee is made
all of wax, very pliant, emptie of all thing▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a little mony
and a tenement or two of land lying next your freehold on
the south side, worth 10<SUP>l</SUP> <HI>per annum.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is welcome. Haue you giuen him any princi∣ples,
such as you knowe are necessarie? and is he docible<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is ready for your hand Sir. I will not commit
such an errour (knowing you as I doe) but lay the foundati∣on.
You may worke vpon him as you list I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I hope you shall finde me di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igent, and accor∣ding
to your heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast a good sterne countenance, I like thee
well: if thy minde be as vntoward it will be sutable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you Sir, no man shall get any thing of
me, but I will knowe how he comes by it, except your selfe,
whom I will trust withall I haue. Deale with mee as you
please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you. Nay, if I deale not well with you, I
wish no man should deale ill with me. I heare you haue land
lying neere me, I would haue you bee a good husband, and
keepe it. Let me lay vp your writings safe least some deceaue
you of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>That you shall Sir▪ here they be. They shall be in
pawne to you for my good behaviour: for I thinke no man
will giue his word for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art the fittest man for mee that ever I met
withall: nor any man (I thinke) will vndertake I shall bee a
good master to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis no matter sir, I will stand to your gentlenesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said: and Ile even deale with thee thereafter.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt <HI>Ant.</HI> and <HI>Simp.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast a seruice a dog would not haue it, except
his taile were already so short cut to his breech that no
more could be spared. I warrant thou has<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> seene the last of
thy writings. They will pull thy land after them. And that's
but law.</P>
<STAGE>Transit terra cum onere.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI> Pro.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Hortauo <HI>and</HI> Acuto.</STAGE>
<P>Is it true that you told me (<HI>Acuto</HI>) at our last parle here
that there were <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ch valiant people in times past that wil∣lingly
and chee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efully went to their death when they might
haue in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oyed life longer.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is no question of it except wee should dis∣credit
all Historiographers, who make honorable mention
of them i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> all ages before vs. And in our owne time and
memory there haue beene many <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hort.</SPEAKER>
<P>I p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>otest it is a wonderfull courage these people
haue, and in mine opinion farre beyond the stoutnes of the
souldiers. For they goe to kill and contend, not meaning to
<PB REF="13"/>
dye, which only they strive against, and avoid by all meanes
they can▪ and provide aboue all things to bee well arm'd for
safetie of life. But the martyr with not resisting, conquers
death, and feares not that which is feared and shunned of all
others. Therefore I thinke them worthie of great honour
and p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>petuall memorie. But who are they (say you) that
giue testimonie of them? me thoght it was a very fine word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>They be Historiographers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Histornoggerfers. a braue word. Ile make a
knot of these letters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, Historiographers man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I haue it Histriagerfers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so neither: you must marke wel, &amp; pronoūce
it iust as I doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I will be sure to doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus then. Hi-sto-ri.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay there. Now gape (he gapes &amp; <HI>Hortano</HI> looks
in his mouth) lets tell, how many teeth ha you? 22. hough,
whoos within there? a paire of pincers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What to doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why to pull two teeth out a your mouth for I ha
but iust 20.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what of that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary because youle ha me say it iust as you doe, &amp;
that I cannot except you &amp; I haue the like number of teeth.
I, and Ile measure your tongue, that if it bee longer then
mine it may be cut even: for it is my dutie being a gardner,
to doe all b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> line and levell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's no matter: so that you vtter the sillables
full as I doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes I make no question, though I lack a few teeth
but I can swallow a sullebub as full as you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>A sullebub. I did not speake of a sullebub.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No? that you did. Ile be iudg'd by all this compa∣nie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No such matter. I sayd you must obserue every syl∣lable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go too then▪ I wooll: vp with it once againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst thou tell what a sillable is?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, not I more then my dog.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>How wilt thou obserue them then if thou knowe
not a sillable?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me alone for that: Ile make a shift. Doe you say
the word, and if there be ere a one there, Ile finde him I war∣rant
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ere a one there man? why the word is fram'd of
many sillables.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well: how shood I misse them then? turne me
loosse. Ile take it as soone as it peeps out of thy mouth as pa∣rats
doe bread and butter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come then marke well▪ His-to-ri-o-gra-phers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile lay ten pound to nothing, Ile not misse a straws
breadth, His-to-ri-o-gra-fers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's right indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Law, did no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I tell you so? Nay you never had an
apter scholler in your life then I am: twool doe you good to
teach me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad of it: this was soone learnt indeed: now
put together, and speake it short as I did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will: but you need not doubt that it's safe, &amp; will
never be lost. But to satisfie you Ile doe it, and that quickly,
Histor-cockafurrs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoo: the longer the worse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is your faut: that wood ha me say it so fast: &amp;
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is a very s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urvie word to hit, except a man haue a mouth
made thereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke you are fasting to day▪ and that hinders
your speech: goe play and fill your bellie▪ and weele at it
againe soone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanks gentle Master: and the next time you teach
me, weele doe it very closely ant please you. For I doe not
meane to be very lavish of my learning, when it shall bee at
the biggest in no companie but yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>So doe all cunning folkes: be daintie of your skill▪
<PB N="23" REF="14"/>
or else you shall never bee intreated at first, nor thank'd at
last.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. II.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Vulcano <HI>and</HI> Rustico.</STAGE>
<P><HI>Hortano:</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou haue beene a great while prating with that
pricking fellow and make no reckning of my neighbour
<HI>Rustico</HI> and m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ Belike you thinke to ingrosse the honour of
the wholle businesse to your selues. But I tell you plainely, if
you haue termind to put the Holidaies downe you shall not
cosen vs so: for it shall be wel knowne that I helpt to knock
vm downe as much as any man in the parish: and that I gaue
the hottest stroke about it.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir you are much mistaken. The Tailer is an honest
man, and a true man, (although it be impossible) and we are
fully agreed they shall stand, &amp; be kept as holy as they were
the last yeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you so Sir? you are but a trecherous fellow for
your labour, and a coward too: for I warrant thou hadst ra∣ther
be at a good dinner then a battle: were not wee two
worthie to be of the councell? Well; Ile bee even with thee
for this tricke▪ Ile sweare, Ile not say a prayer this twelue-month
vpon any holidaie that shall doe any liuing creature
good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a villaine is this? then thou wilt not pray for
thy selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, goodman woodcocke? as though I were a li∣ving
creature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes; a man would thinke so; art thou not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>No that I am not. And Ile proue it by an argumen,
and a sluttegim too. I tell thee, I can chop Logicke an I list.
I can proue thee an Asse, or any such h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rne beast with a trice
I learnt it at Sturbridge faire, the while I was selling hob∣nailes:
there was such argenication among the schollers
there, whether my nag which I gelt the yeare before were
<PB N="24" REF="15"/>
now a horse or no▪ I set um all one such a froth with spouting
one against the tother, that some of the slauer lighted on
my face, and yet I had my nag betweene them and mee for
feare they would fight, and pull me vnder their feet. But an
they had fought I never meant to part um. To be shor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ with
gaping vpon them, I swallowed so much Logicke as will
serue me the longest day of my life▪ And now Ile practise
vpon thee to proue my selfe no liuing creature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a goose art thou? Is it possible thou canst
speake, and yet be no liuing creature? proue this and proue
anything.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will proue this▪ and I will proue any thing by Lo∣gicke:
what a maime it is for a man to bee ignorant of the
virtue and power of Logicke. I pittie thee, and all such as be
vnlearned like thy selfe. Why man: I will proue by Logicke
<HI>that he which was the last yeare an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> yet liues, is not.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were strange. How? He that was the last yeare
and yet liues, is not. I cannot devise how this should be: for
if he liue, how can he chuse but haue a being?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now it shall appeare how short you are with want
of Logicke. But Ile teach thee a little. <HI>Hee that was the last
yeare (yea and the last weeke) an honest man, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> yet liues, is not
now an honest man.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>This may be. For I haue heard an old saying (and I
thinke it bee true) that a man may as soone depart with his
honestie, as with any thing he hath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>So then. Dost not▪ thou thinke now, that I am as
well able to proue my selfe no liuing creature?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I promise you I am in some doubt of it now: go on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Every liuing creature loues some other creature. But
I loue no other creature.</HI> Ergo <HI>I am no liuing creature.</HI> Now
<HI>Hortano</HI> take all the hearbs of thy garden &amp; stil their water
to powder, thou canst never wash out the strength of this
<HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rgomen▪</HI> I make it iust as they did theirs at <HI>Cambridg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> abou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
my nag. I remember the words, and shall doe as long as my
nag liues. For one of them spouted thus. <HI>Every horse hath
<PB N="25" REF="15"/>
stones: but this beast hath no stones;</HI> Ergo <HI>he is no horse.</HI> And
I clapt him on the backe and told him that hee spake truth.
For I gelt him the last yeare, and eat his stones to my break∣fast.
But I had like to haue mar'd all by saying so. For there
was a nimble-headed Scholler that stood by, (and yet had
nothing to doe with the question) went about to proue me
a horse, and thus he began. <HI>Euery liuing beast, or Animal,
that hath in him horse stones, is a horse. But this Animal,</HI>
(meaning me) <HI>hath horse stones in him, Ergo he is a horse.</HI> I
was striken in such a maze (knowing that I did eate the
horse stones) that I was like to sinke where I stood, and euen
presently to congeale into a horse. But there was by chance
an honest Scholler by, who saw my colour quite gone, took
pity on me, and bade me be of good cheere, I shood not be
a horse. And told the tother to his face, that there was a
<HI>flacy</HI> in his <HI>argumen.</HI> And then fetcht him about with a <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣cumbentibus,</HI>
and prou'd that the horse stones which I had
eaten, were consum'd, and became such stuffe as I cannot tel
you without Sir <HI>reuerence</HI> of your teeth; and that they did
not grow in me as they doe in horses: <HI>Ergo</HI> the case was al∣ter'd.
Then vpon this point of growing, and not growing,
there was such a sturre, that all the horse-coursers in the
Faire came about vs. One said they did grow, another de∣nyed
it▪ and such part taking on both sides, that in the end I
was content (being desirous to make them friends) to bee
search't in the open market, and so was cleer'd before them
all to haue no more stones then I shood haue. And glad was
I that I was not a horse. Had not I (thinke you good cause
to remember <HI>Logicke?</HI> Yes, I shall neuer forget it if I should
liue 100 yeares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to then: if you bee such a scholler I will not
dispute with you about the <HI>Holy dayes,</HI> but my neighbour
<HI>Acuto</HI> hath beene a scholler as well as you, and hee is able
to shew you many reasons why they ought to continue.
And he hath fully converted me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not be judg'd by <HI>Acuto,</HI> nor by a better man
<PB REF="16"/>
then he. Why, I tell you my neighbour <HI>Rus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ico</HI> and I, thinke
our selues as good men as <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uto</HI> and you, and we are two
to two. Weele neuer yeeld while the Plow and chaines
hold, and that wilbe a good long time; for as fast as they
weare, I can mend them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you referre it then to iudgement of indiffe∣rent
men? we are all neighbours, let vs not fall out about
things that none of vs haue skill in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, weele be iudg'd, but not by any braue people;
for they will all take part with the Tayler that makes their
parell gawdie, and with the Gardner that makes them plea∣sant
waukes and knots.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele giue you the choice, so that you name none
of your owne trade, and an indifferent man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say honestlie, Nay truelie we are desirous to
haue an end of it, so that none of vs be his owne carver. Here
sits a countrie Gentleman, a plaine man, a good house-kee∣per,
and peace-maker among all his neighbours: he is no
Iustice of peace, so there is no feare to speake our minde
before him, nor neede we any <HI>minerator</HI> to him, he is very
courteous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele not refuse him, nor any that is honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>God saue you Sir. Heere is a great controuersie
betweene foure neighbours, two against two. Reasons are
alleaged on both sides, and neither part will agree to other.
In the end we accorded to referre the matter to you, we be∣seech
you to consider, and order it as you please, and then so
shall it be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>The controversie is beyond my skill, it being mat∣ter
of <HI>diuinity;</HI> but mine opinion is, they ought still to bee
kept. For I perswade my selfe, that our Auncetours (which
did all things well) had speciall reasons for these daies to
be kept holy. What their reasons were, I take not vpon me
to set downe: there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>its a Religious man, he is more like to
quenche your thirst, and resolue your doubts then I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most Reverend Sir, though we be strangers to you,
<PB N="27" REF="16"/>
we are bold to aske your counsell in a busines of weight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are welcome whosoeuer you are: no marvaile
though you be strangers to me, who haue estranged my self
from all the world: but what counsell can you expect from
me, who am not like to giue wordly men any satisfaction,
since I haue alreadie given the world with all his busines an
vtter farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, our busines is not worldly, though it concerne
worldlie men, euen as your life is not worldlike, though bo∣dilie
you liue on earth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay M. <HI>Acuto,</HI> stand aside, or Ile haue you taken a∣way,
for you marre the paly, you are very forward to take
the tale out of my mouth, as if you had more wit, but I think
not so. I began first to speake vnto this man, therefore I wil
haue the last word. Sir, our busines with you shalbe short▪
for I am a hot fellow, and I strike thick and short. This Tai∣ler
takes long and wide stitches, and drawes out the time to
make his worke seeme much. Our difference is for the <HI>Ho∣ly-dayes</HI>
as they stand in the Kalender, whether it were fitter
they should be retourn'd into working-daies as they were
at the first, or remaine to the worlds end. If you iudge they
ought to stand, we are content, and will worke harder at o∣ther
times. If you will haue them downe, doe but say the
word, &amp; hold vp your finger, weele maule v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to the ground
at a blow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your questiō is not hard to decide, &amp; fit enough for
me to deliuer mine opinion in. It is true, they were all work∣ing
daies at the first. For which purpose it is said, such work
as thou doest, worke it in those six daies, and not on the sea∣uenth
day. Yet <HI>God</HI> did neuer forbid any of those six daies
to be kept holy▪ And the Christian Church hath appointed
many daies to be kept holy in memory of Saints which suf∣fered
dive<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se torments for Christs sake, who suffered all for
them, and for them all. And those to be kept to the worlds
end, that their facts and fame might neuer die, but enco<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣rage
others to treade their bloudie but <HI>Heauenly</HI> steppes.
<PB REF="17"/>
Therefore since the Church of <HI>God</HI> and custome of Christi∣an
countries haue so ordered it, let no mans private rashnes
presume such alte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ation, as to make away or put out the
<HI>Holy-dayes,</HI> but with due reverence to obserue them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gods</HI> blessing on you Sir, you haue quite <HI>confiscated
my conceite.</HI> Ile kill him that would haue them downe. Such
a sermon every day would make me keepe all the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est of the
weeke holy. Gow neighbour <HI>Rustico,</HI> you and I will hang
together, and change together. Ile neuer meddle with any
matter out of the length and bredth of my Anvile, fall back,
fall edge while I breathe▪ Me thinkes I am good enough
with this little teaching, I shall neuer need to mend heere∣after.
I could finde in my heart to goe to hanging present∣ly,
and be a martyr, if I might haue no time to thinke of the
paine, but goe aliue to <HI>Heauen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They all make obeysance to the Hermit, and turne asid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I told you so much before, you neuer needed to
haue troubled the good man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou told me so? what care I for thy telling? If
thou told me my father were dead (though I knew hee be
buried) I will not bleeue thee. And yet I would not for
fortie pound he were aliue againe. This is a graue man, and
his ver<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e countenance speakes truth. Tauke no more o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,
I am quite dissolv'd they shall stand fast: and Ile keepe them
verie devoutlie. And Ile perswade all the Parish to doe the
like.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou teach all the Parish. Wilt thou turne prea∣cher?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<P>No preacher Sir, but I hope all the Parish comes to
my shop for one thing or other. And cannot I then giue vm
part of my <HI>tal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt</HI> as well as the <HI>Coblers</HI> are wont to doe, and
I am sure it will become me as handsomelie as them.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Execunt Vul. Acut. Rust. Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="29" REF="17"/>
<HEAD>ACT. II.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Antonio, Simplo.</STAGE>
<P>Goe <HI>Simpl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> to Mistris <HI>Sylvester</HI> in <HI>Sheerelane,</HI> desire her
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o lend me a paire of sheetes, a p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lowbeere, halfe a dozen of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>apkins, and a towell.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will Sir, <STAGE>(he steps forward▪ and suddenly stoppes)</STAGE>
but now I remember me <HI>Porber<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> told me you haue linnen
enough of your owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>He was the more foole to tell you so▪ but you
must not vse to crosse me thus. Doe as you are bidden. Will
not out owne la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t the longer if wee weare of other folkes
sometimes? when we haue gone through all our friends so
often that none will lend vs, then 'tis time enough to weare
our owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vnderstand the conceit now. Ile tell her you lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
your key.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Best of all. Doe so. I perceiue thou need'st no
broker.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sir, no; such a tuitor as you will serue turne
well enough.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Proberio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>Friend Proberio.</STAGE> You come in good time. I was
beholding to you in my gre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>test necessitie: And I purpose
to requite all your deserts. At this present an accident is
fallen, which will be beneficiall to you with a little diligence
had. A messenger of mine received a hundreth pound by
my direction from a serivener in this towne, and ran away
with it into Ireland, finde him out, and get the hundreth
pound, I giue it you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you Sir, but it is a thousand to one I shall
neuer finde him; and if I doe, I know not the man, and the
money perhaps spent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="30" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>If this faile Ile giue you another as beneficiall as it▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's easily done. For I thinke this is litle worth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue an employment for you, one Sir <HI>Retlaw,</HI> &amp;
Master <HI>Eloc,</HI> his father-in-law are bound with me in divers
bonds, I for them, and they for me. The whole summe is a
thousand pound, the greater part they are to pay. I haue
their counter-bonds for all. What they haue for my debt
I know not. I would haue you be perfect in the accompts as
they stand in my booke, and then demand of them a recko∣ning
betweene vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir, this shal be done with effect.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Prob.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
<P>Sir I haue brought the linnen, she lent it willingly. So I
saued the lie; she desires you to suppe with her to night.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ha,</HI> suppe there? with all my heart. But how shal
I doe with my two egges at home? they will bee too stale,
remember soone to carrie them to the <HI>Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-house,</HI> but mea∣sure
them well in your hand with griping.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will Sir. I would desire your counsell in a mat∣ter
concernes my selfe. One <HI>Frith,</HI> a neighbour of yours
desires to buy my land, whereof you haue the writings, and
will giue me more then 'tis worth. What will you advise
met to doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke it not amisse to take his monie, and put
it out to vse, and therein I can pleasure you. My scrivener
shall doe it as for me, and he will get good men for your
monie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you Sir: then I will absolutely bargaine
with him, and send him to you for the writings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe so: but bee not long: for I haue busines in∣stantly
for you.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
<P>What an Asse is this? doth he thinke I will let any man
buy a thing so neere my nose, but I will lay hold of it with
my teeth? I will haue his land doe what he can. And I will
<PB REF="18"/>
haue it one 40<SUP>•</SUP> the cheaper for this tricke, that he will offer
to sell it from me. He thinkes belike to make a porter of me
to cary his writings from Lawyer to Lawyer; but if I be, I
wilbe well payd for my paines. I haue a device in my head,
which I will extend to the vttermost, seeing he puts me to
it. Trust? there's a trust with all my heart to serue other
mens turnes. No, I never Iou'd that. I remember to haue
learn'd that charitie begins with it selfe. And a Cooke licks
his owne fingers before he di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hes the meate for others. Doe
they not know what it is to get writings out of my hands?
It seemes they neuer entred bond to me. If they had, they
would not presume thus. If nothing els would serue to hold
them, yet this I can alleage, that they are my securitie for his
good behaviour (although I care not sixe pence for any se∣curitie,
because I neuer meane to trust him for a crownes
worth of any thing. And I haue all you to witnes, that for
his good behaviour he pawn'd them to me.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Frith.</STAGE>
<P>I am glad to meete you heere Sir, your man and I haue
bargain'd for his land not farre from me, but very neere you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome neighbour <HI>Frith.</HI> Let me speake with
you a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ide. Take heed what you doe. His title is naught, els
I would haue had it my selfe, and you know it lies <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it for me.
But let him not know I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aid so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frith.</SPEAKER>
<P>I were much to blame if I should Sir: no, I war∣rant
you. I thanke you for this <HI>caveat.</HI> I might soone haue
lost my money so.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay awhile, you shall heare more to his face.
Come hither <HI>Simplo.</HI> This honest man tels me, he is in speech
with you about your land, and I was content to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et you run
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your course. But doe you forget that it is pawn'd to me
for your good behaviour?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, such a thing there was. But my hope is you
will not be my hinderance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your hinderance. No; but if this be true (as you
<PB REF="19"/>
cannot deny it) haue you not forfeited your land and w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣tings
by your euill behaviour, offering to sell it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o a strange<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and not to me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frith.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's a plaine case Sir. Ile not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
land, nor any of my neighbours shall, for I will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them all<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Nay, I may say to you Sir, I am told he hath no good title
to it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were you told so? Well, farewell neighbour
<HI>Frith.</HI> <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Frith.</STAGE> How now <HI>Simplo.</HI> To keepe your land▪
no man will be your Tenant? and to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell it, who will dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
with you? Did you not heare him say it is reported you
haue no good title? Well; in hope you will doe me true
service, I will helpe you out of these bryers. Tell mee true▪
What should he haue given for your land?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed Sir he should haue pay'd me 150<SUP>•</SUP>. And if
you helpe me not I am vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>It had beene worth 150<SUP>•.</SUP> if it had not beene thus
disgrac'd, but now 'tis worth litle. Well, if I giue you 100<SUP>•</SUP>.
for it, what will you say?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you will giue me 100<SUP>•</SUP>. for it, I shall thinke my
selfe much bound to you while I live. And so I doubt not
but you will keepe the land safe. For the title was as good
as could be vntill you had my writings. It may be they took
wet in the last great raine, and so they did shrinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will giue thee 100<SUP>•</SUP>. And no raine will shrinke
the mony: the Sunne will doe it most hurt: for it will melt
very fast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know how to keepe it from melting better
then I. Let me intreat you to order it as your owne▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will giue thee my credit for that.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Anto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>It▪ is much to be fear'd that this greedie griper will
vtterly spoile this poore man both of money and land, h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
minde is altogether vpon dece<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> and ruine of others. Tis∣pitie
any <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onest bodie should haue to do with him that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣dieth
nothing but mischiefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sorry to see so much wickednesse in one man
as appeares in him, hee is able to infect a whole countrie.
<PB REF="19"/>
And it were a happie thing if hee were banished the com∣merce
of all Christians.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. III.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sperato</HI> with hanke and spaniels.
<HI>Spurco</HI> with hounds and <HI>Gulato.</HI></STAGE>
<P>Of all the musicke in the world there is none like to that
which is found in hauking. For, the questing of Spaniels,
the spring of pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ridges, the gingling of Haukes bels, and
thundring of horse heeles is the best consort, and pleaseth
me aboue all delights.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spur▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Comparison is too generall. Had you exce∣pted
hunting I might haue join'd hands with you against all
others, but now I am become your adversary. For it is con∣fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed
of all sorts, that the mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icke in hunting, both for con∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inuance
of the sport. for a delightfull exercise contenting
the eare, and gentle-men-like pastime the world cannot
compare with vs▪ and so we hunters cary the <HI>Bell</HI> away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sper▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed you hunter carie the <HI>Bell,</HI> but not for any
good doing, no more then you doe by carying the horne to
very mans house. What time and order your hounds ob∣serue with
their naturall harmonie, I will not dispute (they
and their keepers being seldome in order) but of this I am
sure, that there are few kennells of hounds in England▪ but
while some are in chase after Hare, or Fox, others are killing
sheep in full crie of the poore harmelesse beast: wherevpon
is growne that proverbe. <HI>The Foxkills the lambs▪ and the
hounds the old sheep.</HI> But I cannot indure you should chal∣lenge
hunting to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> better with a gentlemā then hauking.
Everie Clowne can keepe a dog, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he more carion he ea∣teth
the more egregiou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> he smelleth: but the hauke ador∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eth
a kings <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, besides the admirable conquest the faulk∣ner
maketh in a ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kes natu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, bringing the wild Haggard
hauing all the earth &amp; seas to scowre over vncontrollable,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> attend and obeie her keeper so, that at his verie voice she
<PB REF="20"/>
turnes towards and stoupes to his gloue. Hounds are so pre∣judieiall
to the common-wealth, that I dare vndertake to
proue, that (next vnto drunkards) they are the greatest spoi∣lers
of poore mens bread.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gula.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like all well enough but the last words of yours
<HI>(Sperto)</HI> for mee thinkes it is as good sport to heare the
Falconer and the Hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter fall out, as for theeues to appeache
one an other▪ Good fellowes take their liquor quietly with∣out
any of these faults, and helpe to hold vp tillage by the
swift vtterance of the surmounting graine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spe.</SPEAKER>
<P>The immoderate and excessiue disorder in drinking,
and more then swinish swallowing, that neither bellie nor
head can containe, but must recoile by the way it entred in,
is the most pernicious inconvenience that this kingdome
suffereth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gula.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your invective against good companions (for so
I must needes call them that loue drinke) is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o bee refelled
rather with a Cudgill, then with reason. When had you any
gallant Captaine, or man of resolution but would drinke
health after health, vntill themselfe were past health and
helpe?</P>
<LG>
<L>Who was more valiant then Captaine <HI>Shinke?</HI></L>
<L>Yet moore then he, who loued drinke?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Like matter, like patron was his valor in his drinke?
or was he best able to performe a noble exploite, when his
legges failed his giddie head▪</P>
<LG>
<L>No, he was euer like a Swine,</L>
<L>When strength of drink<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> clos'd his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mnes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. III.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Insatiato</HI> with his page <HI>Infaelicto.</HI></STAGE>
<P>Boy, a pipe of <HI>Tobaccho</HI> What is it a Clocke?</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infae.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is almost eleuen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insati.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doubt it be no more indeed. I am so sleepie still:
<PB N="35" REF="20"/>
goe see if <HI>Monsieur Parvagracio</HI> be stirring. <STAGE>Exit Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</STAGE>
I am verie melancholicke this morning whatsoeuer I aile. I
care not if I send for my Physician: or whether the cause be
that I lost all my monie yesternight, and now know not
where to get more vntill I haue conferred with my Agent
for discommodities, nor wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re to dine scot-free in the
meane time.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Infael<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infael.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, hee was asleepe when I came to his chamber,
but his page wak'd him. He remembers his loue, and desires
you to beat his chamber an houre hence, then his Barber
comes, as he does everie sonday in steed of praiers. Hee
charg'd mee to tell you that hee hath an ounce of the most
transcendēt <HI>Tobaccho</HI> that ever cross'd the salts, sent him by
a Ladie of his secret knowledge and yours, with whom you
both must dine this day. The propertie of this <HI>Tobaccho</HI> is
to yeeld a porringer full of <HI>Rheume</HI> everie pipefull: and pro∣cure
ventositie conveniently to descend verie odoriferous,
and secure from <HI>audibility.</HI> She reserues store of it for her
owne speciall vse in times of necessitie, as of attendance in
Court, hearing of Plaies, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itting at Cards, and the like. Fur∣ther,
that a little of it taken pill-fashion, will diffuse and di∣sperse
<HI>mixion,</HI> so that a Ladie may abide in companie fortie
eight houres, not disposed to <HI>evaporation.</HI> Besides he will'd
me to tell you▪ that this Ladie yesterday hath receiued a
booke from a friend of hers that went ouer with Sir <HI>Rob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt
Sherley</HI> in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o <HI>Persia,</HI> entitled <HI>de flatibus separandis ac dividen∣dis,
cos{que} emittendis;</HI> not forward at the face as gamers vse
to doe in warres, but <HI>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</HI> as <HI>Iacke-an-apes</HI> deliuers <HI>squibs,</HI>
written by a learned Physician doctorated by the magnifi∣cent
order of the <HI>Mountebankes</HI> there, she will anon at di∣ner
intreate you two to lay your heads together for transla∣ting
this booke into English. And where you finde any sent
worth the nothing▪ you will make stoppes vpon it, and deli∣uer
your opinion by way of comment for the better vnder∣taking
the fence, with the particular causes and effects of e∣uery
severall and distinct <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ume produced thereby. And here∣after
<PB REF="21"/>
at better leisure she will haue the subiect of the whole
booke <HI>Anatomatized</HI> by her owne Surgeon, and set forth in
due proportion and colors, and giue it a convenient roome
in her gallerie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insat.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is good newes; shall wee dine there? and
snuffe this daintie <HI>Tobaccho?</HI> that's excellent. heere's a
shilling to drinke <STAGE>(he feeles in his pocket, and finding no mony
there, saith)</STAGE> goe too, 'tis no matter now: the next time I
haue a good hand a dice Ile giue thee two shillings. Why
now I feele my selfe well againe. Goe boy, tell my Physici∣an
he shall not neede to come. <STAGE>(Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>licto is going.)</STAGE> Stay, I
haue not sent for him <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow I remember me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. III.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCENA III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Antonio Proberio <HI>and</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
<P>Haue you done my businesse (<HI>Proberio</HI>) with the Knight
and his sonne-in-law?</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue cast vp these accompts exactly, and your
share is to pay 200<SUP>•</SUP>, and no more. I haue often visi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed them▪
and put them to such a plunge as you neuer saw: for they say
you ought to pay 400<SUP>•</SUP>. and yet they cannot avoide but they
must pay 800<SUP>•</SUP>. They haue lost their notes, their seruants be
chang'd: and they are so pusled as you never knew men:
they desire respite a weeke. I gaue it them, and so it rests.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ha, ha, he.</HI> And did the fat Knight fret so? let
him fry too. I will sticke close to my counterbands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I thought good to put you in mind of one thing.
You haue my bonds of eight or nine score pounds in your
hands▪ discharg'd tenne yeares since, I pray you let me haue
them vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, take no care, they shall never hurt you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I wish I had them vp, we are all mortall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>The next time, I light on them I will cancel them.</P>
<P><HI>Simplo</HI> goe you to Mistris Boe▪ desire her to lend me halfe
a dozen egges vntill market day, look you chuse the fair<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st.
<PB N="37" REF="21"/>
<STAGE>Exit Sim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>.</STAGE>
<HI>Proberio,</HI> I would faine do somwhat for you. A
friend of mine wants a good Steward, I will helpe you with
the place: or there is a widow worth 400<SUP>•</SUP>. I thinke I can
make the march for you▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you Sir, either of them I will accept. <STAGE>(hee
turnes to the people.)</STAGE> This is like his 100<SUP>•</SUP>. offer which his
messenger ranne away withall. It will come to nothing;
but now I know he hath some busines for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would faine haue your opinion in a bargain of land
I haue made with one <HI>Pohssib,</HI> to the value of 7000<SUP>•</SUP>. drawn
into articles with both our hands to it. The chiefe motive
of our bargaine is a mariage betweene two yong children.
I pray you calculate whether the bargaine be gainefull or
no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> bargained alreadie, it i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> too late for me
to deliuer my opinion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a whit too late. There is nothing done but
the land assured to me, and 3000<SUP>•</SUP>. of mony payd. If I finde
It not fit for me, Ile rend the bargaine all to shivers. What?
two words to a bargaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why. I know you can doe it if you list, you can
play fast and loose aswell as any man. Well, you shall soone
know how I like it.</P>
<STAGE>Exi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neuer finish'd any bargaine yet, nor doe I meane
this shalbe the first.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Redit</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
<P>Goe to the Lawyer, and aske if t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e writings be ready for
your land, that you may receiue your 100<SUP>•</SUP>. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
I haue a couple of followers most vnfit for my humour. <HI>Pro∣berio</HI>
is so full of <HI>scrupulosity,</HI> that nothing passes his fingers
that savers not of <HI>conscience.</HI> Such a man would I deale with∣all,
but not dwell withall. Such a man would I haue deale
with me, but not deale for me. <HI>Simplo,</HI> he is diligent, but a∣las
his braines want salt.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Redit</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, the writings are done, when you please I am
<PB REF="22"/>
readie to seale. I thinke the Lawyer is a verie honest man,
he hath made them reasonable me thinkes: for I am but to
warrant it from all men, I haue nothing to doe with wo∣men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is well. Wee will goe presently. But I must
stay vntill <HI>Proberio</HI> come: for I doe not well know where I
am vntill he haue done a busines of mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I met him in Chauncery Lane, he promised to be
heere before me, but I made great haste to tell you the wri∣tings
were readie. I would so faine be a sealing. I am won∣derfully
fallen out with my land.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Proberio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, the bargaine with Master <HI>Pohssib</HI> is the worst
that ever was made: for if he or his wife doe liue 30 yeares,
(as by probabilitie they will) you lose 17000<SUP>l</SUP>. by the bar∣gaine
at least. And if they die sooner, you shall saue litle.
Therefore my advice is, that either you buy it absolutely for
readie monie, or yeeld it backe with reasonable considera∣tion
for your monie lent, so shall you be free from exclama∣tions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought so, I warrant thou art as fearefull of ex∣clamations,
as of thunder-bolts: there is nothing with you
but exclamations, imputations, infamie, reports, discre∣dite,
and the like. A rush, a rush, and they are all one to me.
Well, I thanke you for your paines. Now ply the Knight &amp;
his Father-in-law about the 1000<SUP>l</SUP>. accompt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will. <STAGE>(he turnes to the people)</STAGE> then vntill the next
neede I am cashier'd.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Prob. Anto. <HI>et</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is your opinion sir <HI>Hermito</HI> of this mans di∣sposition?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Alas,</HI> I could wish the poore man would consider
better of his soules state. Hee seemeth to haue a great wit,
which he bendeth wholly to gather worldly wealth, not re∣garding
how he gets it. We that haue put riches in the last
place of our care, or rather flye from them as pernicious doe
<PB REF="22"/>
indeed, condemne for follie all the carking and studie to
encrease our owne hurts as they will proue to be, especially
gotten by indirect meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you call him poore, who is reckoned very
rich, and full of money to put out for gaine? such men are
now-a-dayes highly esteemed, much sued vnto, and among
their praises that is chiefe, that he excelleth others in mony
at vse. And in the countrie among plaine fellowes it is a
speciall marke or token that he is a good man (as they call
him) if he haue 100<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>1. or tow at vse, and without that he is
not counted sound, or out of debt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>More is the pitie. It was wont to bee a thing odi∣ous
among Christians, and vsed by none but <HI>Iewes▪</HI> And
therefore we call such men poore, as being needie of good∣nes
and grace, haue they never so great aboundance so got∣ten
as they make their owners beggerly for grace.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. III.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Insatiato.</STAGE>
<P>Tis a marvailous toile and trouble that we courtiers are
put to, and litle considered by the world abroad: for it is
commonly midnight before wee can be shewed our cham∣bers.
There wee lye like dead persons vntill next day at
noone. All this while no bodie comes at vs, nor prouides
vs any supping, nor so much as moanes vs. Then are we for∣ced
to ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e for stark hunger. Thus tyed to our dinner till two
of the clocke: from that time vntill foure, we must not stirre
from our seate, one discourse after an other holdes vs fast.
Then goe we on visitation from chamber to chamber: and
before wee know perfectly how euery one had their health
since yesternight, and exchanged our complementall
tearmes, the clocke strikes seuen. Then dutie cals vs to
Court our most respected and perfumed Mistris, whereof
we are not discharged till nine. Now supper bids euery one
repair to his messe, which commonly continueth no longer
<PB REF="23"/>
then tenne. And so after a crash of two houres in play, wee
are driuen euery one to his kennell at midnight, as I said be∣fore.
And this miserable life we leade, and yet are wee en∣vyed
to haue all the pleasures in the world. But I thinke no
wise man will so iudge if he felt that we know.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Gulato <HI>and</HI> Sperato.</STAGE>
<P>Master <HI>Sperato.</HI> I haue much desired to debate with you
the matter of drinking, and necessity therof, because at our
last meeting here you were so bitter in speech as if worme-wood
had bene all night steep't in your stomacke. Therfore
I sent for you once againe to try if I can perswade you to re∣cantation
of your errour.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sper.</SPEAKER>
<P>That you may easily doe <HI>Gulato.</HI> For if singing the
same song ouer againe may pleasure you, I can doe it with
much addition of voluntary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gula.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it euen so? then I see thou want'st breeding,
that art ingratefull for a kindnes offered; and ignorant, not
sensible of the salutiferous operation of well brewed <HI>Ale:</HI>
which for thy edification, I will manifest and demonstrate
by a very familiar and apt similitude: and within the circum∣ference
of thy feeble comprehension, whereunto I wil now
accommodate my whole oration.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spe.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are growen very eloquent of late. I thinke the
<HI>Ale</HI> hath oyl'd your tongue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gula.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, thou art in the right. I tell thee I am at this
instant so inflamed with the spirit of mault, and my wits so
refined with the manifold reverberations, and continuall
posting correspondence betweene the residence of that li∣quor
in my stomacke, and the <HI>quintisencicall</HI> receites in my
head, that no particle of time passeth, but whole streames of
exusflations, and insufflations ascend to the braines, and
there worke wonders. By reason whereof it were not hard
for me to furnish <HI>Ryder</HI> himselfe with 2000 new words not
yet seene in his Dictionarie. I could turne <HI>Astronomer▪</HI> and
giue names to any starres that want. I can passe for a Physi∣cian
among many fooles, and kill as many as the best <HI>Doctor</HI>
<PB REF="23"/>
of them all. Finally, what would I not vndertake as now I
am armed? But to returne to my druggicall similitude,
from which thy way wardnes hath diverted me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, let that alone vntill an other time. I vnder∣stand
alreadie as much as I neede for that matter: I must be
gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gula.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall stay to heare it; and let mee haue your
iudgment, whether I might not with a little reading proue
a perfect <HI>vrinal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spe.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are so troublesome when you fall into this
case that I cannot skill of your companie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gula.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell thee 'tis the best Physicke that euer thou
hadst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeue it before-hand. What neede you more?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Spurco <HI>and</HI> Insatiato.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gula.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Master <HI>Spurco,</HI> you are welcome: speake your
minde freely: doe not you thinke it better to sit merily a
whole winters day, and most part of the night by a good
fire, and command (like men of authoritie) the Tapster
to fill vs <HI>an Ocean</HI> of drinke if we lift, and there among
good fellowes to heare more newes then all the world
knowes to be true, then to toyle and trash in the dirt with∣out
conversation, seldome comming neere one another as
Hunters doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spur.</SPEAKER>
<P>No certainely. I hold it a beastly thing to sit besea∣ling
vpon a bench, and suck in drinke, as pigges do dregges
in a trough: which custome although some base Huntimen,
and Falconers vse, yet if I did thinke that <HI>Hunting</HI> were as
odious and displeasing to <HI>God</HI> as drunkennesse is, I would
soone dispatch my dogges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insat.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I will free the Court from the fowle &amp; loath∣some
custome of drunkennesse. For seldome and with very
few it is vsed there. Officers, and order forbids it as vnseem∣ly
for a Princes palace. I wish we were as cleare from Idle∣nesse,
pride, disdaine, envy, lecherie, covetousnesse, flatte∣ry,
<PB REF="24"/>
lying, cosenage, oppress<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on, and vnthriftines, as we are
from drunkennesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary Sir, these are vices enow. And except you
were guilty of all the deadly sinnes, and breach of every
commandement, I know not what you could adde to these.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>The delights of hunting and hawking, as also of o∣ther
exercises, were (no doubt) ordained by God to com∣fort
man in his banishment heere, and to giue him a taste of
the vnspeakable pleasures in Heauen, (our owne c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>untire)
but the excesse and abuse of any pastime, argues the receiuer
vnreasonable, and turnes the benefite into detriment.</P>
<P>Of drunkards I say shortly and sharply; they deprave
Gods blessings, robbe and murder the poore, vndoe the
Common-wealth, bring Gods curse vpon the countrie; de∣priue
themselues of Heauen, and merite <HI>Hell.</HI></P>
<P>The Courtier (who ought to bee the square of the coun∣trie
by his civill example) puls vpon himselfe the ruine of
millions, and sinneth much with doing litle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gula.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am crushed in the head: no more drinking; fare∣well
good Ale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me thy hand. Wee are all in little better case
for any thing I heare by the iudgment of wise men.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. IIII.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Antonio, Proberio, Simplo.</STAGE>
<P>I haue had such a stirre with this same begger <HI>Pohssib,</HI> his
wife, and his friends: and so many complaints they haue
made to the King and Councill, and turne themselues into
all shapes and faces to force mee either to goe through with
the bargaine or giue it ouer, that diverse of my friends are
brought to favour his part for starke equities sake. But doe
all what they can I will haue it, and not haue it: I will hold
it, and not hold it. And I will none of the purchase, and yet
not giue it over.</P>
<SP>
<PB N="43" REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I told you Sir, what an intricate businesse it would
proue to be, and full of slander: therefore I wisht you to end
it by yeelding the bargaine backe, for that wilbe the end of
it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou knowest not what wilbe the end of it, nor
I my selfe; but I can best guesse, because I know his poore e∣state.
I haue made a priuie search into his debts; and some
creditors I haue pull'd vpon him sooner then they meant.
And in writing I haue every summe he oweth to neighbors,
to workemen, and to his very servants. And this is the
plummet I sound withall. This must bring the fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h into my
net <HI>Proberio.</HI> But what haue you done with the Knight and
his Father-in-Law Master <HI>Eloc,</HI> for the 1000<SUP>l</SUP>. accompt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, that accompt goes otherwise then you would
haue it; for they proue that there was 1200<SUP>l</SUP>. taken vp, and
of that you are to pay 400<SUP>l</SUP>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you sure of that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am so sure, that I am ashamed euer to haue spoken
in a matter so contrarie to good conscience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are so spic'd-conscienc'd, that there is no
dealing with you. Will you demand if they will sweare in
Chancery, that so is the accompt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I will doe, and I am sure they will not refuse
it. <STAGE>(he turnes to the people, and saith)</STAGE> this is but to colour his
dishonest meaning, he knoweth the truth as well and bet∣ter
then they.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Prob.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>These fellowes are so rash, that a litle thing will
satisfie them. I am partly perswaded the accompts be as he
speaketh, but it is good to be sure. Thus thou must do <HI>Sim∣plo</HI>
in <HI>like</HI> cases, if thou wilt be a wise, politicke and warie
fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I heare it well Sir, and haue lock'd it vp safely in
my <HI>memento.</HI> I giue you many thankes for the 100<SUP>l</SUP>. you
gaue me for my land, and for your carefull putting out the
money as your owne. I againe for my part haue sealed the
writings, and am ready to doe any thing els for making it
<PB N="44" REF="25"/>
sure to you. 'Tis a good hearing that Master and man agree
so well as your worship and I doe now. Now they say 'tis a
good title, and they will not make question of it, since you
haue gotten it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I thinke not: for all their babling they will
not easily beginne sui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e with me to recover it away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare nothing of that Sir, I can tell you newes.
They say now your title to it is as good as any man hath to
his land. And that you will keepe my 100<SUP>l</SUP>. as safe as the
land; and that's good for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's no newes. You may see now what it is to
be circumspect in my dealing, and to haue a name to hold
fast. Learne this against the time that you haue more land.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. IIII.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Intrant</HI> Rustico <HI>et</HI> Hortano.</STAGE>
<P>Did you euer heare (neighbour <HI>Hortano</HI>) such a broyle
betweene man and wife as yonder was betweene <HI>Porco</HI> and
his wife? you and I did very wisely to come away. For sure
they did striue before vs for their credit sake to get the vi∣ctorie
of each other by scolding; now we are gone perhpas
they will giue over. Mee thought it was very noy some to
heare such vnseemely words passe from maried folke.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure their bitternesse pass'd the bou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds of huma∣nitie.
They make me afraid of marying, if such jarres fall out
betweene those that be one flesh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it not discourage you more then it repents
me that I am maried: for it lyes in your power to haue all
well and quiet if you chance to mary euen one of the short
rib<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of the great Divell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How can that be neighbour <HI>Rustico?</HI> if you can
teach me that, you doe much. For I haue heard many say,
that it is impossible to tame a shrew by any meanes, except
by hauing no woman at all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="45" REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you talke of taming by violence, you say well,
it cannot be, for the more you striue to break their stomack▪
the more it growes; like <HI>camamile,</HI> the more you tread it, the
more it spreades; and like a tree felled, where will grow 40
springs. But take a twig by the top▪ and gently bend it by
litle and litle, it will grow in what fashion you will. A wasp
is a shrewd stinging beast by nature, but if shee light vpon
your face and hands, and creepe vp and downe, let her a∣lone,
and take her pleasure, she will doe you no harme, and
quietly passe away. So if your wife will meddle with all
things, giue her libertie to doe what she will, you shall haue
her merry els she were worse then the Divell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke this is very likely: but who can endure his
wife to doe what she listeth at all times?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>That can I, and that must you, or els you ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not
wise; for if you may haue peace vpon any conditions, is it
not your fault if you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>buse to be jarring?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I haue heard say▪ it is better to haue honorable
warres, then inconvenient peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>That is among strangers and enemies; but among
friends, and with your selfe, what peace can bee dishonou∣rable?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How commest thou to be so cunning in this kinde
of argument?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen as you may if you will take the course that I
doe. I haue a wife, the best creature that euer you saw in the
order that she takes with me. But if I should be churlish, as
perhaps you would be, and crosse her never so little, shee
would rage like a fury of Hell. She speakes, and I giue eare;
she giues counsell, and I practise; she commands, &amp; I obey;
she chides, and I hold my peace; she preaches, and I beleue;
thus we liue as lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mgly as Master and Scholler.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But who could abide his wife to teach and con∣trolle
him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euery man that loues his ease. And if all wiues be
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mine is, she shalbe thrice happy to obey her. For she is the
<PB N="46" REF="26"/>
best woman to bring vp husbands that euer was borne. She
will so instruct them in the wonderfull vertue of patience,
that if they wilbe ruled by her monitions, they shalbe as
good as martyrs, a great deale better then living Saints. I
thanke her heartily, she is my <HI>Pilcatory</HI> in this world, I shal
goe straight to <HI>Heaven</HI> whensoever I dye. Therefore left I
should lose the benefite of the blessed state I stand in by any
misdemeanour of mine. I dare not offend her in the least
matter. O 'tis a great blessing to haue such a wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But for all this it should bee long before I would
chuse such a wife, which did desire to cary such a hand over
me as she doth over thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>O neighbour <HI>Hortan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> that thou didst but taste of
the fruites of patience! <STAGE>Intrat <HI>Lamia</HI> his wife with a cud∣gill
of an ell long, and counterfeiting to be a <HI>Puritan,</HI> lifting her
eyes vpward.)</STAGE> Looke where my wife is; I know her by the
signe of the Bible. See how devout she is. She never lookes
lightly lower then the Element. You may say what you will
now, she cannot heare a word, her meditations be so fer∣vent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doth she cary that cudgill while she is pray∣ing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>(She openeth her Bible, and makes shew to reade, and
many times turnes her eyes with the white vpward.)</STAGE> That is
her rod of discipline, and a strange thing it is which now I
tell you. She is never so rapt vp in her devotions, but if I cō∣mit
the least fault (as wretched man that I am many times I
doe, and my best actions are abhominable) she perceiues it
presently (and yet is deafe to all other noise) and she come<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
to me fiercely in the heate of her charitie, and corrects mee
verie handsomely with that wand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will she correct her seruants with this cudgill?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, verie seldome, shee does not loue them so
well) except it be a verie great fault. But in me (for the en∣tire
loue she beares me) she will not suffer the least sinne vn∣punished,
lest (as she saith) any might remaine to bee rebu∣ked
<PB N="47" REF="26"/>
by hell fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I had rather be her seruant, then her husband,
if she strike with such twigges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had you so? but so had not I. For by this I am
made sure of my election, when I doe patiently endure so
great correction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doth shee bring vp thy sonne <HI>Iacke?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Admirably well: for lest he should proue an Idola∣tour
shee will not let him aske blessing vpon his knees. And
lest he should abate of his mettle and stomacke, he must ne∣ver
put off his hat to vs, nor be denied any thing he cals for:
so that being now but sixe yeares old he will fight, scratch,
and tumble himselfe vpon the ground, crying vntill his hart
breake if he may not haue his will in every thing. Then is
there no way but giue it him, or els he will die with skre∣ming.
O, he will proue a man of outragious spirit. It makes
me sometimes doubt he should not be my child, he hath so
noble a stomacke, farre beyond mine. And, but that I know
his mother to be a verie religious professour, I assure you it
would trouble me much, he discovereth s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> much furie in his
fashions, and such might by his madnesse, that I thinke ma∣ny
times some gyant got him when my wife was asleepe, for
I am sure she would never suffer it waking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nay, if your wife bee a woman of that com∣mand
as you describe he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to be, and as she makes shew of no
lesse by her part, it may well be, the Boy takes his courage
from her, and his outward personage from you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say well neighbour <HI>Hortano,</HI> that may be;
but I doe halfe mistrust my owne worth in getting such a
child: but yet I loue him as well as if he were my owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>I came hither to seeke a kinde of husband that I
haue. He wants gouerment and discipline (I am sure) ere
this time: for I haue not seene him these three dayes past: the
poore man wilbe vndone, if I light not on him shortly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, shee seekes me. What a good woman is this?
I must needes goe to her. Stand by neighbour▪ and note
<PB REF="27"/>
how zealously she will edifie me. How doe you good wife?
I knew it was you so soone as I saw you any thing neere me.
May I be so bold as to aske where you haue been these two
or three daies? My boy <HI>Iacke</HI> and I thinke long vntill you
come home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should you aske so foolish a question? you
knowe that I must frequent my contemplation: in which I
cannot be lesse then two or three daies: the fervour of spi∣rit
is such among the elect that they may not depart in short
time from their meditations, especially having such learned
Teachers among vs, that are never wearied, and willing to
accompanie and conduct vs in the darkest dangers. O the
delights, pleasures, and sweet delectations that we feele du∣ring
the time of these contemplations, that wee thinke no
time contentedly spent but when we are imployed in these
exercises. I thinke verily my goodly boy <HI>Iacke</HI> was begot∣ten
and conceiued in these deepe contemplations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>What wife; and I not there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Alas</HI> man, why should you trouble your selfe with
these matters which be so farre out of your reach? was it
not enough if my spirit did wishe you present? or that in
conceite you were with me? what if you were asleepe at
that instant, and so it were revealed to me by the spirit? or
if you had beene present, and my spirit should inwardly te∣stifie
vnto me that a teaching <HI>Saint</HI> must be preferred, ought
not you to giue place? I pray you husband giue over to
mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e on these hidden secrets, for otherwise these thoughts
ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> make you <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orne-mad.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How can you defend that to be lawfull to be got∣ten
with child by any but your husband?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Inde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d wife I cannot but thinke this reason good
that you say, but I would haue beene glad to bee father to
my owne child if it had pleas'd you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe you talke of reason? it is beyond reason.
It is matter of predestination, and preordination. Where is
now your obedience and pati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce so often inculked vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
<PB N="49" REF="27"/>
vnto you? I perceiue it is readie to flie out by your exteri∣our
parts, but I will chastise this rebellious flesh, and make it
subie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to the spirit.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>(then she beateth him soundly.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where learn'd you to beate your husband?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is lawfull &amp; possible for me to extract teares from
his f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nty hart with this rod of discipline, correcting him
as the spirit moueth me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how shall he know that a good spirit moveth
you to correct him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>That appertaines not to him to examine. It is suffi∣cient
that his wife hath that inward testimonie which ena∣b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eth
and emboldeneth her to doe her function, and to mi∣nister
disciplinary documents. And this hee is firmely to
hold, or els he loseth his election.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay wife; rather then I should not be one of the e∣lect
I pray you beate me againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are not to informe me when I shall strike. It is
the liuely spirit which directeth me: and now it telleth me
you neede not at this time more to bee humbled. Goe in
peace, and be patient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Gods blessing on thy kinde heart. See how fa∣vourable
a spirit she hath. I cannot chuse but weepe for this
loue.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Then he weepes and howles with hands before his face.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Loe now <HI>Hortano</HI> the vertue of this rod, which
bringeth so plentifull teares from this <HI>Rock<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> stomacke of
his.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But for all this I see no ground or proofe you haue,
that a wife shall take vpon her to teach and correct her hus∣band.
You alleage Scripture as farre as <HI>Rome</HI> is from <HI>Rock∣ingham,</HI>
and expound it at your pleasure, and frame it to
your owne fancie: but if I were your husband I would cud∣gill
you well, and by the word maintaine it better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>What not yet vnderstand'st thou the text? <HI>O foole,
and slow of beliefe!</HI> If thou were my husband <STAGE>(Then shee
shakes the cudgill at him)</STAGE> I would ding it into thy braine in
another fashion then by proofes. I pre thee tell mee, must
<PB REF="28"/>
not men be taught and instructed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes: but what, shall women doe it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who els I pray you▪ shall beasts doe it? Although
women may not speake in the Church (which is great pity)
yet we may preach in chambers, and men are tyed to heare
vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, nor sluts neither: but men shall instruct men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iump.</HI> And so womnn instruct women, and none of
them shall come to other. And how shall there then be pro∣creation
of the holy ones, and the <HI>Israell</HI> of God bee multi∣plied?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay neighbour <HI>Hortano,</HI> I warrant you my wife
will proue any thing she saith one way or other. But good
wife, let me intreate one thing at your hands (if your spirit
cōsent, that is, that I may call your son <HI>Iacke</HI> my boy for my
credit sake. And that he may know no other but he is mine,
and then shall I be quiet in minde, and thinke you deale ve∣rie
iustlie and liberallie with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart. And I professe vnto you that hee
shall neuer know otherwise by me: but I doubt his gene∣rous
spirit will not suffer him (after a few yeares of discre∣tion)
to tarrie long in that errour, but that he will heroical∣lie
disdaine to haue you otherwise accompted of then his
reputed father: and that he is rather the sonne of some zea∣lous
brother, who neuer sees the Relikes of Charing-crosse,
but wisheth hee were on horse-backe with a launce in his
hand, in full speed to beare it downe. And yet his mother ex∣treame
honest for all this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>All this I stedfastlic <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wprd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. And I am afraide my
owne weakenes wilbe the first discoverer, and pleade not
guiltie to getting of such a sonne. Nevertheles (good wife)
I cannot chuse but thanke you much for your kindnes, that
he shalbe called my sonne, that men may thinke so noblie
yet of me to doe such a deed. And for you wife) I will
sweare you are a verie honest woman for all this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>No husband. You shall not sweare so rashlie. I
<PB REF="28"/>
thanke you as much as though you did. Your saith shall
saue you without swearing.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Lamia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was ever man more blessed with a wife then I am?
<HI>(Then he holds his hands before his face, &amp; fals to a silent me∣ditation
a prery while, at last fetching a great sigh, hee saith)</HI>
The Lord make me thankfull. <HI>(Then he h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>des his face with
his hands againe, and so standeth a while sighing and sobbing,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntill</HI> Hortano <HI>shake him by the arme, saying).</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Rustico,</HI> what wilt thou doe: kill thy
selfe with this same foolish zeale? plucke vp a good heart,
and liue to see thy boy a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>A man. He is a man already at sixe yeares age by
his great stomacke; and I thinke in my conscience I am not
halfe his father. But I beshrew you for troubling mee, you
haue done you know not what: for I was euen melting into
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> martir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A martir. How canst thou be a martir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes, and I shall die so patiently, that I dare not
call for a posset how sicke soever I be for feare of sinning, till
the very point of death. And now I begin to be hart-sick.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you find your selfe so sicke indeed, I wish you to
make your will, and dispose of your estate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? make my will? thats the next way to die in
earnest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a whit neerer death for that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes. A will, and a toling bell are as present death
as Gods tokens. No: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le none of that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me perswade you (neighbour <HI>Rustico</HI>) to make
your will. I assure you it is superstition to thinke death to be
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erer you for that cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Superstition. The Lord defend me▪ I had rather not
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o obserue order in anie thing then to be thought superstiti∣ous.
I agree to you neighbour, and thank you for your gen∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le
perswasion. I will presently doe it while I am in perfect
memory.</P>
</SP>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> First, for my soule; I will not bequeath it to God, but let
<PB REF="29"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t goe even as it is predestinated.</P>
<P>2 My body may be buried if my executor wil pay for it, or
else let it alone, and be patient, as I was when I liued.</P>
<P>3 At my buriall I de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>re my wife to preach, and no body
to heare her but my sweet boy <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acke</HI> and I.</P>
<P>4 Fortie shillings I giue to any man that shall put me into
the booke of Martires.</P>
<P>5 My wit, &amp; such like moueables I leaue as an heireloome
to my sonne <HI>Iacke</HI> <STAGE>(then lifting his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies vpward)</STAGE> vpon whom
my desire is that the firmament may powre downe as many
ioyfull lots as there are heares vpon his fingers ends; &amp; that
his seed may multipli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> like mice in a maltheape.</P>
<P>6 All my breeches I bestow vpon my beloued wife.</P>
<P>7 My land (if any be giuen me after my death) I freely be∣stow
vpon him that shall marrie her to amend his bargaine.</P>
<P>8 The rest of my goods and chattles which cannot bee
found I will shall be equally devided (at my executors dis∣cretion)
among the poore of the parish wheresoeuer I shal
die.</P>
<P>9 And of this my last will and testament I make the long∣est
siuer in London my sole executor, because I will haue no
fighting, nor suits in law for my goods.</P>
<P>10 And you neighbour <HI>Hortano</HI> I make overseer of this
my will, and for your paines to be taken therein, I giue you
all that shall be overplus after execution of the same,</P>
<P>Now my sight failes. Lead me, lead mee good neighbour
home: and to bed, and so farwell, and good night.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. IIII.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCENA III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Intrant</HI> Antonio, Noverindo, &amp; Proberio.</STAGE>
<P>Here is more worke for vs <HI>Noverindo</HI> (and wee will not
worke for simple fees though <HI>foedum simplex</HI> bee a good te∣nure)
a frend of mine wants 2000<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>1 and I must haue it for him
within these two daies or he seekes elsewhere.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>In anie case hold him in, let him not scape, hee shall
<PB N="53" REF="29"/>
pay for his expedition. Ile about it, and Ile haue it for you
within 24 houres, or Ile giue you my head <STAGE>(heegoes forward
a little, and suddenly steps backe saying)</STAGE> I had almost forgot a
matter of waight: you are intreated by the whole compa∣nie
of our sort, that some order may bee taken to check<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the
sawcinesse of divers meane persons that enquire for monies
to be taken vp. They make no more adoe, but with hats on
their heads, aske the question thus: haue you 100<SUP>•</SUP> to lend
vpon good securitie: what a malepertnes and abuse is this?
Of my honestie Sir. (what a villain was I to sweare so deep∣lie?)
there be manie knights, and some Lords that haue not
alwaies 100<SUP>l</SUP> to lend vpon an instant. And then what reason
is there, that we which haue it at all houres should be so slē∣derly regarded?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>You saie well <HI>Noverindo:</HI> I wish it to be redres∣sed:
bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> what would the companie haue me to doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Sir: you are acquainted at Court: they intreat
that you would vse your frends to get a grant vnder the
broad seale (whatsoeuer it cost) that we may erect an office
with a master and clarks belonging to it, to the ende that e∣verie
one which wants monie may repaire thither, and vpon
request to the vnder clarks speake with the master of the of∣fice,
and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hence take directions how to proceed, and so ob∣taine
monie. This will make them knowe themselues, and
yeeld dutie to them that it appertaines: when they shall
come by degrees to the worth of monie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>This I like well; but it will be a great charge to
maintaine master and clarkes in an office, so shall wee loose
much out of our gaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir you mistake it quite. The companie hath argu∣ed
that case to and fro. The master and clarkes will pick out
a liuing well enough I warrant you out of them that take vp
m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hie, and this will free them from other brocage. As you
knowe all offices are maintain'd by the suiters, not by the
granters of the place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right: but who shall be at the charge of the pa∣tent?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="54" REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>That must be done by the companie. But weele
lose nothing by it. For wee are determined to let no monie
goe but one waie or other we will get 30 in the 100. And if
we giue commodities we will haue more: &amp; tis reason too.
The worse the bargaine is, the more they must lose that take
it. And there is another thing that we will be at the charge
of Sir. Wherein we must craue your helpe also. And that is:
some armes from the king of Heraulds appropriated to our
companie alone, and hanged vp behind the master of the
office: this will giue honour to the place, and cause suiters
to vnderstand they enter into a court of command and au∣thoritie.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Noverindo whispers Antonio in the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are while
Proberio speak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s thus to the people.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I could fit these fellowes to a haire. I could de∣vise
them a crest as fit as a fan for a for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>horse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Proberio:</HI> here is <HI>Noverindo</HI> hath a peece of im∣ploiment
for you, and thinks you can discharge it well if
you list. And Ile see you well considred. It is this. That you
moue the Heraulds to giue the companie. Crest with the
due circumstances. And goe in my name they will doe it the
more freelie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I am the onlie man for such a businesse. If the
Herauld cannot aptly conceaue it, I can instruct him. Ile vn∣dertake
to haue it speedilie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanks <HI>Proberio:</HI> and thou shalt not travaile for
vnthankfull persons.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Anteni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, it wil cost 10<SUP>l</SUP> besides somwhat for expedition:
and I must haue it readie to paie: for I will not come from
him till I bring it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is 10<SUP>l</SUP> and a peece for expedition: and ano∣ther
for thy paines: studie hard to haue it exactly done, thou
shalt haue two peeces more. <STAGE>(Proberio makes hast away, but
Nov. cals him)</STAGE> staie, one word before you goe. Let it bee
somewhat terrible to the beholders: weele make them do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
(<HI>that same</HI>) in their breeches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>But so you may scarre them quite awaie, they will
<PB REF="30"/>
come there no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warran: thee: if they were sure to goe to prison
within a while after, they will come againe for monie. They
are verie ventrous: nay desperate: nay <HI>foolchardy.</HI> O, monic
is monie, and they must haue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saie no more, Ile be your warrant, it shall bee feare∣full
enough. <STAGE>(Exit Nov.)</STAGE> and make some of you staine the
place you stand in, and looke backward what drops behind
you. Let me alone, Ile dresse you as you should bee trim'd
30 in the 100. Ile not forget that vpon my word.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. V.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Malingua <HI>the La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yer.</HI> Mureto <HI>the Merchant,
and</HI> Granato <HI>the Fariner.</HI></STAGE>
<P>It is even high time the world were at an end, for I think
all trades are decaying: when my father put me to the Innes
of Court he advised me in anie case to studie, so that I might
be called to the barre, and then (saith he) feare not to liue in
all plentie and credit. But I find it otherwise, for now that I
am exalted thither, my law serues mee not to get my com∣mons.
I wish I had beene bred a Tapster: that trade is now
more gainefull with froth then ours with all our words. And
for anie thing I see tis like to last to the worlds end, whereas
ours can be good no longer then people bee contentious.
And that is a speciall argument the ale. sellers vse against vs,
saying that we gaine by falling out of neighbours, &amp; frends
but they grow rich by meeting of good fellowes, and sit∣ting
together lovinglie. There are so manie hinderances
grownevp of late that it is impossible our raigne should
long continue although it be true (and wee complaine not)
that malice is as great among men as ever it was, and can be
wished: but the mischiefe is, their monie failes, &amp; they grow
wiser.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mure.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marvaile what will satisfie your greedie desires.
haue you not the whole kingdome at your service &amp; becke?
<PB REF="31"/>
what Lord, Knight, Gentleman, Merchant, Husbandman,
or other sort of people is not attendant at your studie dores,
with paying and praying? and glad that the fee which hee
giues is of that glorious operation, that it breeds no wrin∣cles
in your forehead, but is cheerefullie receaued? What
<HI>co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gees,</HI> and submissiue requests to peruse their case with a
little care? What troupes conduct you to the barre? What
venison sent to your feafts? What respect and entertaine∣ment
if you vouchsase to visite their countrie houses? And
finally, what honour and homage can bee done to subiects,
but you haue it in all fulnes, and yet you whine as not con∣tented.
I perceiue you would murmure if you were so hand∣led
as poore merchants are, that vnlesse we turne Vsurers,
we cannot liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>You complaine without cause <HI>Mureto.</HI> Your
case is farre better then ours: for if one countrie or commo∣ditie
afford not gaine, you can go into another, and choppe
and change as often as you list. We are tied to one countrie
and place. You may offer your wares▪ and are sure to haue
trafficke as the times and prices be. We may not tender our
service to anie, but sit gaping in our chambers, as melancho∣licke
as mice, vntill some bodie chance to knocke at the
doore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is merie when fisher-men complaine of Hering∣men.
Surelie the world might well spare of both sorts of
you a great number. Concerning you Master <HI>Mureto,</HI> it is
cleare that you play the merchant with vs, who bite and
whine at your impositions. although you lose nothing; but
the whole burden thereof falles vpon them who spend the
commodities, and must ere they buy, pay the shot of your
impositions whatsoever it be.</P>
<P>And for you Master Lawyer, that grow fat with the
drops which fals from other mens browes, and be merrie
with the frets that gall the Clyents hearts: whose griefe
is alwayes to heare of peace and charity; and reioyce with
the Fox, that the hennes fall out for their pearch: what faul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="57" REF="31"/>
finde you with this world that was never so rich with envy,
and full of suits? You are like the bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e among gamesters,
which gaines whosoever lose. But if all men were of my
temper, I would make you leape a yard high for a groate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, a whole yard? what if I were neuer at
the dauncing schoole, and cannot caper so high?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then thou shouldst haue but two pence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay; I know a tricke worth two of that. For if
our craft faile, Ile turne minister: and that I am sure will not
deca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Woe be to that P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ish that shall haue a Lawyer to
their Pastour▪ some bee already troubled sufficiently with
citations; they neede no common Law writs. And without
a <HI>capias vtlegaium,</HI> a Lawyer can never preach.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who can endure this filthie Farmer to raile as he
doth at vs two <HI>Mureto?</HI> Let vs set vpon him. Are you so
free without fault Master <HI>Granate,</HI> that you may throw your
stones so thicke at others? Belike no complaints are made
against you for hoording vp co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne against a deare yeare, for
selling to badgers at a deare rate, and not serving the mar∣ket:
for mingling bad corne with the good, and fowle dres∣sing
of the best. For deceitfull plowing your neighbours
ground that hires you at a hard rate, which makes the poore
man weepe at haruest. Besides many other countrie tricks
which breed new cases among old Lawyers, which I could
argue vpon an houre together, if I were not presently to go
to the hall to move in the Kings beneh vpon an <HI>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ectione fir∣me.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mure.</SPEAKER>
<P>By lakin (Master <HI>Granato)</HI> you had been as good
held your peace as buckl'd with a Lawyer. I swea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e he hath
in few words touch'd you to the quicke, and done you no
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rong neither in mine opinion: but wee will adiourne this
disputation vntill our next meeting, and in the meane time
provide your selfe for a better defence.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="32"/>
<HEAD>ACT. V.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Intrat <HI>Proberio &amp; Antonio</HI> at severall doores.</STAGE>
<P>Sir, Master <HI>Eloc</HI> and the Knight haue giuen me a copy of
their accompt, and according to your charge, and their de∣fence
I haue drawen bill and answer. I haue shewed it them;
they lik't it, and wishe it should be ingrossed, and put into
the Court, they will depose the answere is true.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it so? well, giue me them. If I find them in that
forwardnesse I will take their word, and end it with kind∣nes.
<HI>Proberio,</HI> you must remoue your trunkes and stuffe
presently. I will cleare my chambers from all men but my
selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? iust so soone as I haue done all your busi∣nesse
must I be gone, you might haue suffered me vntill you
goe out of towne, if then you will needes haue me remoue.
You were wont to let me lye heere a weeke after, or as long
as I needed. Mary now I finde the cause of that to be, that
you had then some busines for me to doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes; but I purpose to sell my lodgings, and I must
haue them out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where shall I lye this night, being sodainely vnpro∣vided?
and whither shall I cary my stuffe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall haue a bed at the Inne where my horses
stand. And your stuffe may be put in the out roome, neere
the garden.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>There they may be stollen; but I must bee content,
(though not pleas'd) if there be no remedie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>You owe me sixe pound; you must provide it pre∣sently,
or els I will arrest your sureties.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That sixe pound I doe not owe, although you got
my bond for it by a verie hard and vndue course. And to
this I will depose. And if I did, I hope you will not exact
it, having received such kindnesse heretofore from me when
I was able, and you in extreame neede thereof, and now do∣ing
<PB N="59" REF="32"/>
you so many services.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell me nothing of that; you haue beene satisfied
in your dyet and lodging to a better value.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>In lodging? I am ashamed to heare such a word,
(though you be not to alleage so base a reckoning) I had
alwayes my owne sheetes, except sometimes when mine
were finer, you would change with me for worse. And the
great dyet I had was sometimes a piece of cheefe, and one
egge; for which benefites, I haue travailed like a Porter, &amp;
written like a Clarke. Is this your gratitude for good turnes
past? and are all your promises thus performed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? gratitude? every begger talkes of gra∣titude.
It is for such as you to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue for mercie, not to talke of
gratitude, which is among equals.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>These were not your words to me, when you were
a begger, and a borrower from m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, and had neede of the
poorest helpe; but then you found no begger of me, but
your best friend.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>A proper reckoning. This fellow lookes for re∣compence.
Why, he had my countenance which made him
many times respected. And I could yet be content to speake
for him, but doth he expect farther? why, the fellow knowes
not the world. <HI>Simplo,</HI> tell him that if my word may doe
him any good, he shall haue it: but if he loue his libertie, let
him challenge no deeds at my hands. He never had more of
me then my word for that he now claimeth. And doth hee
thinke to build castles vpon my word? if he doe, they shall
come downe apace. Now he is gone to remoue his stuffe,
bid my Attourney take out execution against his suretie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is cold comfort for mee. Sir, you make mee
halfe afraid, you will turne mee off at the worst time of the
yeare. I am not able to deserue so well at your hands as he
hath done, and yet so lightly regarded. That is verie hardly
done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t thou feare turning off? it comes with a
feare, and ends with a fever. Thou maist goe assoone as thou
<PB N="60" REF="33"/>
wilt after him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>If it please you to giue me my 100<SUP>l</SUP>. I will take my
leaue now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft a while, where is your witnesse that I haue
100<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. of yours? And if I had, thou wert content I should
vse it as mine owne. But goe to, Ile pay thee. There was a
knaue ranne away with 100<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. of mine, Ile change with thee;
seeke him out, take the monie, and hang him▪ that's interest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>(t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rnes to the people.)</STAGE> This is a poore helpe for my
100<SUP>l</SUP>. for all this Ile not leaue his service vntil I get my 100<SUP>l</SUP>.
or somewhat for it. I wood I had my land againe at a ven∣ture.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>trat</HI> Proberio.</STAGE>
<P>Sir, I haue remoued my stuffe into your garden roome;
but there it is not safe from robbing. And at your Inne I
can haue no lodging. I must sit by my stuffe all night.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>It wilbe so much the safer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I heare besides that my suretie is in execution at
your suite for the sixe pound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>That may be. I cannot helpe it vnlesse I be paide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know I owe you nothing of that money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you haue my oath?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you referre it to friends?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>To your owne brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest vpon my faith no pennie of this monie is
due. And yet to saue my suretie I offred a fine mewed <HI>Gosse∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>auk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI>
which before good witnesse you did accept, and cau∣sed
me to keepe a whole Michaelmasse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me in London:
but at the end of that verie teat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me vnknowne to mee, you
sneak'd out of towne leaving order to haue my suretie arre∣sted,
and so followed, that now hee is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> execution vpon
that onelie suite. I say no more, but demand iudgment in
this case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Proberio,</HI> I haue done thee the grace to heare thee
to the full. And it ioies me much, that either he shall die in
<PB N="61" REF="33"/>
prison, or I shall haue that monie.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was there euer any so hard harted? Twentie
yeares past, when I was in prosperitie, and he at point of
death, by rigour of Law, I tooke many costly iourney to
Court, labouring for his pardon. I did him all the good
offices that a true friend could doe for another. And I left
nothing vndone that might doe him good. Besides, I lent
him 50<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <HI>gratis</HI> in those times, my selfe paying <HI>interest</HI> for
that money. At which time what vowes and promises he
made me, I let passe, as ingratefull to my heart in repeating,
and serue to no other purpose but for a warning, and a wō∣der
that so much ingratitude should harbour in an English
man. And now you are all witnesses of my reward.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Mureto, Granato, <HI>and</HI> Malingua.</STAGE>
<P>Now <HI>Granato,</HI> if you be content to yeeld the victorie vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o
Master <HI>Malingua</HI> this Lawyer, and confesse to haue
wronged vs merchants with the petulancie of your prating;
you may perhaps haue your punishment extenuated if wee
be your Iudges, and so quietly shut vp all among our selues.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am so farre from any such confession and submis∣sion,
that I offer to maintaine euery word spoken in our last
contention. And for iudgement I appeale from you both;
and know that I am your ancient from the time that <HI>Adam</HI>
digged the earth for his liuing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then purge your selfe <HI>Granato</HI> from the crimes
we charg'd you withall: and the end will trye if you had
not done better to take penan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> for your faults at our
hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>For the high prices of corne (which falsely and
absurdly you impute vnto husbandmen) if you had either
wit or honestie you would soone graunt that there are two
maine reasons for it which lye not in our power to redresse,
but in the States wisdome to helpe. One is, the vncontrol∣led
<PB N="62" REF="34"/>
and improvident libertie for all sorts &amp; degrees to mar∣rie,
so that many are grand-mothers at 30 yeares old. The
other is the multitude of Inclosures and decay of tillage.
And if we corne-men did not till all the ground we can get;
how deare (thinke you) would corne bee shortly? Many
other Reasons for brevity sake I omit, but these will hold
argument against you for tearme of both your liues, and
after your decease to your heires males lawfully begot∣ten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue me Master <HI>Mureto,</HI> this Farmer hath
made for himselfe a reasonable good <HI>Apologie,</HI> and put vs a
hard case. It seemes he hath studied well since our last parle.
But what say you <HI>Granato</HI> to your euill words lauish'd out
against Lawyers? therefore you must yet craue pardon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I truly. For I gaue you no worse speeches then
you giue one another at the barre, nor so euill. For there
you fall out like any skoulds: but the worst is, you wilbe
friends at dinner, yet neuer in charity I thinke. And I see
no reason I should stoope to either of you, considering the
goodnes of my cause. For I wilbe iudg'd by any indiffe∣rent
man, if I, and such as I am, be not honester and better
then both your factions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since thou hast offred it, thou shalt not escape
vntill that be tryed, Heere sit a couple that seeme very wise
by their silence, weele bee iudg'd by them. What say you
<HI>Mureto?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mure.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart. For wee can not bee worse
then we are howsoeuer we speede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>A match. Ile refuse no mans opinion that is not of
your rankes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen. We need not report the causes of our
reference vnto you. All our jarres, and wrangles you haue
heard. We intreate you to finish them with your doome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>To deale plainely with you all, mine opinion is,
that the world is generally more wronged and abused by
the Lawyer and merchant, then by the Farmer, who though
<PB N="63" REF="34"/>
he haue faults, yet gets he his liuing more honestly, and is of
necessitie to be harboured. But Sir <HI>Hermito</HI> I must referre
the full decision of their cause to your censure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>That one of them is better then the other, I doe
not see; therefore me thinkes the question should rather be
which is the worst. The Farmer that deceiues so farre as
his capacity will carry him, is condemned by his intention
to doe worse if his skill did enable him.</P>
<P>The Lawyer is a necessary member of the commonwelth
to finde and determine everie mans right. But if willingly
he oppugne right, and be enemie to peace, he is the <HI>Diuels
agent,</HI> and Christs enemie.</P>
<P>Likewise a merchant which causeth commerce and ami∣tie
betweene severed nations is a man commendable. But
if he vse fraud, then is he pestiferous, and deserueth banish∣ment
where no societie is.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Malingua, Mureto, and Granato, make obeysance vnto
Securus and Hermito, and turning together, say.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mure.</SPEAKER>
<P>I told you Master <HI>Malingua,</HI> we could not lose
by the bargaine. Now the Farmer is as bad as we. What
say you <HI>Granato</HI> to this geare?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say litle. Why? I can be content to bee as disho∣nest
as you. I am not proud of my honestie, nor doe I loue
to be singular.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>But now thou seest we may be as honest as you, if
we will our selues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who denies that? I stand not much vpon that
neither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>But hath this Hermites preaching done thee no
good? canst thou be content to mend if we doe so too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, with all my heart. And Ile bee good before
both you if you mend not the faster.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mure.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content. Let vs all amend: for I thinke in my
conscience it is euen high time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mali.</SPEAKER>
<P>All our hands wee will ioyne together in manner
of a vow that it shalbe so.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="64" REF="35"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 5.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Proberio,</HI> bringing a cloth, wherein is pictured an Vsu∣rer
bare-headed with a purse in his left hand, on the out-side
of which purse is set this inscription: 30. p. pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 100. And
behinde him the picture of the Divell, with his armes strip'd
vp, and white halfe-way, like the hangmans shirt sleeues,
putting on a halter about the Vsurers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecke, and shewing it
to the people, sayth,</STAGE>
<P>Now, could I meete my merchant <HI>Noverindo,</HI> I haue
heere a whole library for his learning. Heere he may studie
while he spend his heart-blood with struggling, yet ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er
reach the depth with his petitoes.</P>
<STAGE>He rowles it vp-againe.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Noverindo.</STAGE>
<P>How long I thinke vntill I meete <HI>Noverindo.</HI> All is readie
at our office, but the <HI>Blazonrse</HI> of our coate of <HI>Armes</HI> to be
set vp, and for want of that we lose many howres. For there
be store of suitors without, that thinke long to seale they
care not what. But wee will not open the doore vntill wee
furnish it with that gashefull spectacle to affront them. Yet
time is pretious with vs, who must accompt to an howre, els
Ile not giue a fart for a monie-monger that shall lose a mi∣nute
negligently.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>This catiffe is carefull of losing time in his wrath∣heaping
gaine; but that this time be well spent, he takes no
care<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at all. Well Sir, you shall not complaine of me for kee∣ping
you too long from the Divell, the sooner you goe, the
better for the countrie you liue in. <HI>Noverindo:</HI> why fret
you your selfe? I haue more neede to bee chollericke for
staying here this howre, waiting your leisure, while I might
haue gotten 20<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> by other imployments.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nove.</SPEAKER>
<P>I crie you mercie Master <HI>Proberio.</HI> I am sorrie for
that. And I thought you had not dispatch'd our busines.
I pray you let me see it. All our occasions are at a stand vntil
<PB N="65" REF="35"/>
it come, for it must be set vp before any be admitted thither,
or els the world will thinke it to be a new devised trick, and
not appendant to our corporation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>None but fooles will thinke so when they view it
well, they shalbe caught to acknowledge that it was due to
you long since, euen from your first denomination.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nove.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said <HI>Proberio,</HI> so would I haue it appeare
indeed. Vnfould, let me see it quickly. I am with childe till
I see it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>With childe? with the Divell you are. But soft Sir,
is there no more in the case then you make shew of? what
presently see it, and haue it, and set it vp?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. Why should there be any more circumstan∣ces
vsed? is it not ours, and belongs to vs onely?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Sir, haue you forgotten my two pieces you
promis'd mee vpon finishing the busines? I warrant you I
haue deserv'd it you neede not grudge me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nove.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I like it, I will performe your two pieces. Will
you not trust me for 44. shillings?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should you aske me such a question? Is there
any man in Christendome or in Kent, that you will trust for
40. shillings without good securitie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nove.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. But you haue good securitie: for you haue
the thing it selfe in your hand, which you may keepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I haue, and will keepe you from sight of it vn∣till
I haue my money. For what can I tell? you may be so
ouer-ioyed with the sight, that you may runne madde vpon
it. And then what guardian of yours while you liue, or ad∣ministrator
when you die will pay me 44. shillings, especi∣ally
being due for a thing that put you out of your wittes?
Therefore satisfie your selfe, you shal not see it vntill I haue
euerie pennie of my money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nove.</SPEAKER>
<P>How shall I know that it is done when I haue
pay'd you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen as I know that you will pay me 100<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. when I
and my sureties haue-seal'd the bond to your vse before I
<PB N="66" REF="36"/>
receiue a pennie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nove.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say well. Come, heere is your money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now you shall see it. <STAGE>(Then he sets it vp with some
device vpon a staffe. that with turning it all the spectators may
view it, and saith)</STAGE> Looke heere Sir, heere's roddes in pisse
for the villaines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>Noverindo lookes earnestly vpon it a long time, and
then fetching a great sigh, saith.</STAGE> What Tiburnist is this? And
what's the mysterie of all this picture?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir. this Tiburnist, or hangman is the Divell. And
this fellow that hath the purse is Iudas. the figure of 30 with
<HI>p</HI>-ioin'd to it signifies 30 pence, for which he sold his master.
That which followeth is meant of Christ, worth a hundred
worlds: for which fact the Divell put a halter about his neck
and hang'd him. So shortly this is the summe of all.</P>
<LG>
<L>Iudas who for <HI>30<SUP>d</SUP></HI> sould Christ infinitely greatest</L>
<L>Was hangd by the Divells helpe, and reputed with the basest.</L>
<L>Before you saw the history,</L>
<L>Now you heare the mystery.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a good exposition. But I wood I had my two
peeces againe. I doe not like it very well, for manie ignorant
people will take it farre otherwise: as thus, 30. p. 30<SUP>•</SUP>. for a
hundreth. And he that taketh 30<SUP>•</SUP> in the 100. is to be hangd
by the Divell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true. manie may thinke so: but your Clarks must
informe them in the sense. No man can put a secret in fi∣gures
but it may be diversly interpreted. And so be all ora∣cles
taken in sundry sences.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I wish it were made plainer to the vnderstan∣ding:
for the more part will take it as I did at first sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should you thinke so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because I cannot imagine any other meaning so
proper to those figures as that I conceaued.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's because you are parcell <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> guiltie. But I will
gather two other conceits as proper as that of yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you can doe so I am satisfied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="67" REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus 30<SUP>•</SUP> pro 100. that is, hee that giues 30 in the
100 is worthie to be hanged.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>That iudgement is very preiudiciall for vs, &amp; may
force from vs many Clients.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe but gesse at this for varietie sake, And then an∣other
is this. 30<SUP>•</SUP> in the 100. hee that will not giue 30 in the
100 is worthie to be hanged.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>O this; this. none like to this. Now I like this riddle
excellent well that yeelds so manie, &amp; so wittie cōstructiōs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay here one more comes flowing in. I tell you tis
a verie copious theame. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> could keepe you here this houre
with voluntarie varietie. I remember them as fast as they
come into my braines by huddles. 30 in the 100. and the
hangman by: that is, he that will not giue 30 in the 100. shal
bee hang'd before he get anie monie there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nov.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so he shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> warrant him. This is as good or
rather better then the other. I commend thee <HI>Proberio.</HI> ei∣ther
of these will serue our turne.</P>
<P>Here, thou shalt haue one peece more. Ile bee bigger to
thee then my word. Thou wilt make all our worships harts
merrie with this device.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you Sir. And if you knew with what alacri
tie, and willingnesse I went about it, you would thinke it
well bestowed.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Nover.</STAGE>
<P>Let him goe, he carries his owne rodde. No man that hath
his sences will coniecture otherwise then himselfe did at
first. <HI>videlicet.</HI></P>
<LG>
<L>He that takes 30 in the 100 and not a peny vnder,</L>
<L>Is worthy to be pendent till the hemp crack<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> asunder.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. V.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Antonio <HI>and</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
<P>I bad you goe to M. Thompson for my rent, haue you
brought it.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, he hath sent your rent all but 30 shillings which
<PB N="68" REF="37"/>
he abated for 80 caudles at 4<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the caudle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>What an asse art thou? I sent thee for my rent, no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
to paie for caudles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, he deducted it, then how could I helpe it?
it were a great shame not to paie for your diet in the accoūt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>You should haue left the imputation to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I did neverthelesse: but for my credit sake that
fetched them every morning I thought reason to discharge
your score.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Score? what score? is my hand at it? or did you
keepe a tallie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I kept no tallie but he is a verie honest man, &amp; his
wife chalked them vp behind the do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am as honest as they. but yet I never vse to keepe
reckning of caudles when they be eaten halfe a yeare before
and the taste washed from my throat. If hee cannot afford
his Landlord 100. caudles without monie, he is no Tenant
for me. What; no lesse then 30 shillings in caudles taken
out of my rent at a clap, who did euer heare of the like? And
the price too is monstrous: groates apeece? why, it were
enough for a supper at my chamber. Indeed they were very
sweet and good, but what of that? a man may buy gould
too deare. Tell him from me, I will not allow him a penie
for caudles, and yet I will haue my rent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, there stands a poore gentlewoman called Mi∣stris
<HI>Richardson</HI> at the doore, and desires to speak with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>A poore woman, what haue I to doe with poore
folkes? bid her come in, she shal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>be neuer the richer for me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Simpl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Intrat <HI>Susanna Richardson,</HI> makes cursie with a
paper in her hand, and a seale to it, saith,</STAGE>
<P>Sir, a kinsman of yours and mine, a knight, when he went
to travaile had no money to spare, but bestowed on me 10<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
which you owe him by this your bill. I beseech you to pay
me, for now I am in want.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me see the bill. If it be mine I will discharge
<PB N="69" REF="37"/>
it. <HI>She giues him the bill, and after well viewing, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> off
the seale, and saith▪</HI> I owe him nothing, nor will pay thee a∣ny
thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you teare the bill <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> if you will not pay
it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did not you say it was my bill? if it be mine, why
may not I doe with it as I list my selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susan.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you promised to discharge it; and doing so,
it is at your pleasure to teare or burne it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue I not discharg'd it thinkst thou? I warrant
thee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is sure enough for euer charging me agai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Susa.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>O heauens!</HI> was there euer such a monster hatch'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
what age but this could haue fostered so degenerous, so
shamelesse, so frontlesse a beast as thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t? It had beene
happie for manie that haue had to do with thee if that <HI>Skin∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>
this had beene flead from that impudent face of thine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be gone; Thy tongue is left thee to raile at large,
but thy meanes be short to revenge thy selfe by law. There∣fore
feede vpon thy woes, and teares, money thou gettest
none of me.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Anto.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Susanna</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> contrary way wringing her hands.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="6" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. VI.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Furioso</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> souldier, with his company
<HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orraso</HI> the Intelligencer, and <HI>Phan∣tastico</HI>
the Musician.</STAGE>
<P>Courage my companions. Plucke vp your hearts, mee
thinkes I heare the sound of <HI>trumpets</HI> and <HI>drummes</HI> within
my brest. Whether I wake or sleepe nothing but <HI>Alarums</HI>
beset my thoughts: warres cannot be farre off. Euerie thing
prognosticates stirres and broiles. The verie children <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u∣fler
in the streetes. We haue liu'd a great while like <HI>meta∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orphised</HI>
men. It is such a sight for souldiers to walke in
Pawles with long cloakes and graue attire as if they were
turn'd <HI>Civilians.</HI> Whie should we alter our proper habits
<PB N="68" REF="38"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="69" REF="38"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="70" REF="39"/>
being ensignes of honour? Hath not the whole need of vs
by turnes, and fits? And to one place or other we are still in∣vited.
VVe succour the besieged, and relieue the distressed.
VVe restore kingdomes, and set captiues at freedome. VVe
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>osse and tennis Crownes and Monarchies, &amp; bestow them
at pleasure. Finallie we make the earth tremble, and disco∣lour
the running streames.</P>
<P>Some few faults we haue, but not worthie to be so general∣lie
condemned.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corra.</SPEAKER>
<P>The life of a souldier as now adaies it is vsed, is
of all occupations the worst: and in a word is the high way
to Hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furio.</SPEAKER>
<P>You need not bend your selfe so stif<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y against a∣nie
sorts of people, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e they never so wicked, being your self<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
one of the basest and most vnnecessarie <HI>fruitspillers</HI> that e∣ver
made themselues mercenarie. <HI>An Intelligencer, a spie, an
Euesdropper</HI> is hated, and shunned of all the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corra.</SPEAKER>
<P>As true as I liue, it were a good deed to appre∣hend
you. Ile laie my life you are an enemi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to the state.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes to your state. doe you kicke alreadie? nay
Ile gale you better yet. with thy borrowed braverie thou
perkest, and insinuatest thy selfe into the best companie, &amp;
vnderminest their thoughts with thy lavish and warranted
impeaching of states proceedings. And if anie perhaps se∣cond
thee in thy fained murmurin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> him thou pursuest, and
becomest first his animater, and then his accuse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. such a one
was D. <HI>Pary</HI> vntill the snare hee laid for others compassed
his owne necke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you doe vs vnsufferable iniurie: we are busi∣ed
onlie in our Countries service, and certifie all things of∣fensiue
to it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats the intent of your mission, and cause of
your entertainement. But you (to seeme diligent) attend
ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e times to bables and toies, and the better to packe a∣wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e
paper you send your owne surmises when waightier
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffaires either happen not, or escape you. And so least you
<PB REF="39"/>
seeme to neglect your service, you returne tri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an.</SPEAKER>
<P>For anie thing I see you are both pernicious mē∣bers,
and never to bee nourished but in cases of necessitie.
We Musitians are fortunate who hurt none, and covet to
please none. We driue away melancholie, We recreate the
mind, and reviue the benummed spirits, and are welcome to
all sorts. Such souldiers as you are <HI>Segnieur Furioso</HI> I make
no more account of, then of so manie fowle thistles in a me∣dowe
at Midsommer, whose heads everie child will whipp
off with a wand And I will haue a still, plaine, temperate lad
shall breake thy bones with his blow, when such <HI>ay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e bea∣ters</HI>
will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>carce peirce the skinne. I will my selfe bee one of
the six Musitians that with the helpe of a few vnarmed sillie
folkes shall kill 100 such souldiers in an houre: and yet we
Musitians will haue no weapons but instruments of musick.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furio.</SPEAKER>
<P>How shall this come to passe, I desire to heare for
my learning?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus. I will assemble a few falre women as honest
as I would haue them, and wine enough. You shall haue
your bellies full of all your desires. They shall daunce you
faint, and kisse you wearie. And when you cannot feele a
needle thrust through your noses they shal cut your throats
with ease. And we musicall mates will celebrate your <HI>In∣fernalls</HI>
with bells vpon our fiddles.</P>
<P>Now with you Sir <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecke. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>pper,</HI> or M. <HI>Corraso</HI> (if so you
be stiled) I will be briefe. While you doe your prince and
countrie good service, I wish you rewarded: but the first
time you be trecherous you should be well guarded.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furio.</SPEAKER>
<P>What now foolish fidler, do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t thou thinke freely
to carie awaie these exorbitant and opprobrious t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>armes?
Ile haue thee banisht all howses of my acquaintance. It is
not long since you were teaching the lute to a pretie wench
and wittie, and were fingring her frets vnfit for your di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tie.
Its best for you to be quiet, least I tel the rest which I know.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Hermito▪</HI> If you bee no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. I am wearie with hea∣ring
such varietie of vice. The <HI>souldier</HI> that was wont to be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB REF="40"/>
the honour of everie countrie he came in, and a glorie of
his owne, is now become odious abroad, and intollerable
at home. The intelligencer might doe good service if you
could devise to keepe him from doing hurt, which is as
hard as to restraine a man of warre hauing letters of Mart
from robbing his owne countrie men.</P>
<P>The Musician that ought to present nothing euill foun∣ding,
is now the setter of all vnsauerie sonnets. His office
was to teach the measures and daunces of order and come∣lines,
not the loftie <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>valto</HI> and tricks of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntemperance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>I assure you Master <HI>Securus</HI> those things are as dis∣tastefull
to me as to anie other. And I am so much the safer
that I liue from their sight and knowledge. The Souldier,
the Spie, and the Musician haue their severall abuses much
degenerating from their first institutions; if anie man can
perswade them to repaire vnto my <HI>cell,</HI> I will doe my best
to reforme them.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Furio, Corraso.
<HI>and</HI> Phantastico, <HI>doing reverence to</HI> Securus <HI>and</HI> Hermito.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. VI.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Antonio.</HI> and Simplo at severall dores, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>amping,
chasing and throwing downe his hat.</STAGE>
<P>How now <HI>Simple,</HI> what's the newes now?</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marrie I was never in such a scurvie case in my
life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is it? hast thou the pox?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, tis worse. that's but a toy, tis the plague. I
am so pestred with yonder woman <HI>Susanna Richardson.</HI> She
saies you did teare lier bill of 10<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. she scoulds, she tailes; she
threatens to dwell with you, to lay her child at your doore,
and set vp the cause vpon your gate: and everie thing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee
will doe vntill she be agreed withall. She makes me wearie
of my life: she followes me like a ghost: and now she stands
at dore. If you had not beene heere shee had neuer left m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,
but she cannot abide to see you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>All this I little care for; but there's a thing in it. I
feare the <HI>Sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>er</HI> because shee hath wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nes (or els I
would not care neither) I must agree with her, bid her
come in.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>er <HI>Susanna,</HI> makes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<P>You shewed me an old rotten note tother day. Tis not
worth two pence. What would you haue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I owe you no∣thing.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>The note was worth 10<SUP>•</SUP> till you fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gred it, now tis
not worth a halfe-penie indeed: but if you will giue me no∣thing,
I will tell the King. I am a poor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> widow, he will help
me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>The King woman? Alas, he hath great businesse,
neuer trouble him with this toy. Ile giue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee somewhat in
charitie, but not a penie of duetie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Charitie? that would I faine see from you. Pay first
the 10<SUP>•</SUP> which is due, and then bestow your charitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, woman, heere is 50 shillings with a good
will: take this, or get more anie way you can.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should haue had an ounce, heere is but a quarter.
I am poore, therefore I am constrained to take this, but I
leaue the rest vpon your conscience still.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then I care not, we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'l doe well enough with
conscience <HI>Simple.</HI> I am glad tis at an end in Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>So am I Sir, now I shall bee quiet. An you mark'd
Sir, I neuer intreated you for conscience sake to giue her a∣nie
thing, but for my trouble. Nay I haue learn'd to stretch
a conscience with any man since I came to you. And tis
soone learn'd if a man will giue his mind to it: for the good
will of a jade<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> all. What a foole was I that began no sooner
to studie it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
<P>But I haue mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> newes to tell you Sir. As I came by the
Chancerie office I was call'd in to see a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rie foule bill, put
in against you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t M. <HI>Thompso<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> suit, for things which you
did take (not altogether steale) out of his house. And for a
lease parell hee challengeth from you: and there a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e also
<PB REF="41"/>
your fourescore and ten cawdles in a rowe: in everie line a
Cawdle, spic'd and sweet, &amp; as hot as ever they went down
your throat: and some saie they shall be still vpon record <HI>in
perpetuam rei memoriam,</HI> if it bee true, it shal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> goe hard but
ever<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e morning in tearme times as long as I liue Ile spend
my penie at one of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath he seru'd me so? well. tis a maxime with mee
<HI>Simplo</HI> to be asham'd of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>othing (as thou knowest) but yet
Ile be even with him. He shall out of his house whatsoeuer
it cost me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simplo.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is also another bill against you by your
wiues neere cosen, wherein you are charged (not directly
with stealing, but taking without the owners privitie or cō∣sent)
a picture, a map, and other houshold stuffe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I make no more reckning of that imputation then
of the rest. For if the worst fall I shall haue them as they bee
praised.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, if you care not for the manner of taking thē,
the matter is not great otherwise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a rush <HI>Simplo,</HI> sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and thinke what they will,
I am sorie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tooke no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>But one thing made me laugh hartelie, and in my
conceit it was a wittie tricke that was told me latelie, that
you borrowed 100<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of a gentlewoman called <HI>Mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ris Fer∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers
Gratis,</HI> and put it out for 10 in the 100. And after a
yeare and a halfe with much ado<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> paid her: and so you got
15<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> handsomelie. I would I could tell whereto borrow two
or three 1000<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in that sort. Me thinks I haue wit enough to
thriue on this fashion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a fine way indeed, and cleanelie (so that a m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>̄
looke to his securitie) And comes in without stoc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of his
owne: a verie begger may grow rich thus: and everie paul∣trie
knaue may thriue so, if he take heed. Millers vse this
tricke to lend a bushell of another mans corne ground into
meale to be paid againe in wheate, so he takes tole twice of
one bushell, and no cost of his owne, It is but making the
<PB N="75" REF="41"/>
first <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay so much the longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>There are yet two other things obiected, but both
of our nature therefore though it were a huddle, it makes
but a single game. One was this that you picked the first le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣ter
out of a truncke ful of linnen, (the letter for the surname
seruing your name as well as the owners youle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> stand) and
put on A. insteed of R. which was picked out. And this was
M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Rellips</HI> linnen. The other was that you marked pillowes,
and oth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r stuffe o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a noble mans with your own marke, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sed them as your owne. I forgot the noble mans name but
it sounds like a port towne toward the sunne when it is at
the highest. They had much of their stuffe againe, but some
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ucke in your finger<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. And reason too I thinke: shall a man
take pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nes to marke another mans goods for nothing? A
halter for him that hath no better wit then so, to thriue by.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>There was such a speech of this marking, but I de∣nie
it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what then? will that serue the turne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>It must serue. for they shall never proue directly
that I did or causd it to be done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>But they were found in your possession. and then
how can you avoid the discredit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Discredit? they may bee glad to haue their things
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gaine. who can tell but they be mine? I am sure they na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
my marke. And how shall a man know his owne but by his
marke? And howsoever these things are, time will weare
them out of memorie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>All these are well answered. What sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e you Sir to
the taking of a conveiance out of a painted boxe in your fa∣ther
in lawes studie▪ by meanes of a keye with pretence of
another businesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush. I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aid it there againe when I saw they kept
such a stirre about a paultrie peece of parchment. I will not
be beholding to them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>What an vnkindnesse was that, tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> your father in
law did threaten to sue you for 700<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you owed him? Alas
<PB REF="42"/>
Sir I see you haue beene much wronged among them. Hang
such a father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I but I dealt well enough with him: for I sent him
word that if he did sue me I would bring him in more trou∣ble
then twice so much monie could excuse him for other
matters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>And reason too I thinke. shal they make a man pay
monie before he be willing? twood make a man doe that
awood not, when they goe to extremities. I haue done for
this time Sir. the next time you call for newes I hope I shall
haue as much more. But now I remember mee there is one
thing more. Your lawyer asked mee for a fee for your last
businesse: shall I giue it him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. I am sure he did not aske you. I brought a co∣sen
of mine tother day to him that gaue him a fee. Indeed I
told him that he should goe to my lawyer and giue him no
fee. But when I had him there, and he put his case, I whis∣per'd
my cosen in the eare to offer him a fee: But I did not
whisper my lawyer to refuse it. and so verie honestlie hee
tooke it: and I knowe therefore hee will expect no fee for
my owne businesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then belike I mistooke it. perchance hee thank'd
you for bringing your cosen to giue him a fee without
cause, being well resolved before by other Councell. Well
now Sir I hope you will bestow my freedome vpon me. I
desire no more cunning then now I haue, and Ile serue you
still, and set vp for my selfe: for I had rather bee a double
knaue then a single foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not stick with thee <HI>Simplo:</HI> go to the Cham∣berlaine
there it must be done.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Ant. &amp; Simp.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 6.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Insatiato</HI> and Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>licto.</STAGE>
<P>What saist thou boy? mee thought wee had but a short
dinner to daie with yonder daintie Ladie and taried so long
<PB N="77" REF="42"/>
for it. How far'd you in the hall?</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infae.</SPEAKER>
<P>We had verie short commons. and I am hungrie
s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill: we had no meat but your revertion, and the scraps of
your trencher when I changed with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas we left nothing but bare bones. wee had but
a quarter of a necke of mutton betweene three, and <HI>Parua∣gracio</HI>
and I eat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> no meat nor bread since yesternight at 10
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> clocke: and from my trencher thou couldst get little but
the fat squiz'd from the flesh which I eat. I was so hungrie
that me thought I could haue eaten that smal Ladie, and her
great cheere all at a meale. Here goe thou to dinner at some
ordinary <STAGE>(he puts his hand in his pocket but finds nothing there)</STAGE>
staie till I haue monie: thou canst fast a litle, canst thou not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes a little, if I can get no meate.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>In<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rat</HI> Pestifero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yonder comes <HI>Pestifer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> my brother. He could ne∣ver
haue come in a better time: for I haue neither monie nor
clothes to paw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e: but boy not a word of our wants: weele
seeme to be verie flush: the offer shall come from himselfe,
else we shall haue him verie coye and deer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>By your favour Sir I am bold to see as you doe. I
heard you were evill <STAGE>(he snites his nose)</STAGE> at ease with melan∣cholie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome <HI>Pestifero:</HI> indeed I haue beene a little tro∣bled
in minde. but now I am verie merrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good time Sir, I am glad of your worships amend∣ment.
I doubted least you lack't monie, and were sad vpon
it. I came to pleasure you, if that had beene your disease.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanks for thy good will <HI>Pestifero:</HI> but I am preti∣lie
stored at this instant: I knowe not how soone I shall
want, for all things are vncertaine in this world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestif.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verie true Sir, manie changes in this age. wilt
please you then to make provision against a raini<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> daie, and
take this while it may be had?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but then you knowe interest will runne on it is
no good husbandrie to take it so long before the time it
<PB N="78" REF="43"/>
may be I shall not need it this seauen night yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>Way Sir, if you bee so provident that you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eckon
of we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kes. it is time for me to be gone: I haue other frends
to pleasure, that scorne to stand vpon two months past be∣fore
the sealing, from the time of the first be speaking the
commoditie resting from them vntill their securitie were
provided. Ile see you some other time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay ftaie: I am not covetous. I hate it with my
heart: if it may doe th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e a kindnesse I can be content to ac∣cept
thy friendly offer, so thy commoditie bee vendible. I
knowe thou comest in good will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestif.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vendible Sir? yes that it is: and you will say so
soone: no man will suffer it long in his house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>What stuffe is it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of diverse sorts: I knowe not my selfe: but they
are finelie pack't vp. I saw a car vnloading with such ware e∣ven
now as I came, it is a commoditie more sought for by
daie and night then anie I knowe. I tell you it troubles the
Lord <HI>Maior,</HI> and all the Iustices to keepe the people in or∣der
that gather these wares, they are so eager in catching at
them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what value is the commoditie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may haue 100<SUP>l</SUP> worth, or halfe, as you please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will 100<SUP>l</SUP> worth yeeld to be sold?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>At a word it will yeeld you 60<SUP>l</SUP> readilie: Ile not
dissemble.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>What securitie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your selfe and your friend such another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>What saie you M. <HI>Parvagracio?</HI> you know him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know him well I warrant you he shall be taken.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will content you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>What you please Sir, 40 shillings, Ile not ingrate
vpon you,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now let me cast vp my accompt. 40<SUP>l</SUP> lost out of the
principall at the first 10<SUP>l</SUP> the interest. 40 shillings the bro∣ker.
All this is but 52<SUP>l</SUP> in the 100, tis reasonable as the world
<PB N="79" REF="43"/>
goes now: here is my hand. As I am a gentleman Ile haue it
vpon these tearmes, so that the bargaine be no worse then
you speake of, put the bands to making. Now tell me what
call you the commoditie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>The commoditie Sir, is old ragges, such as are foūd
in street d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ghills with raking day and night as I told you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a villaine art thou? old ragges? how durst
thou presume to offer me old ragges?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Sir, I tell you they are readie monie at the pa∣per
mills.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Paper me no mills. Ile not foule my fingers with
them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall not need Sir, I wil take order for selling
them▪ and I hope you can abide to tell the monie when I
bring it. I wood your worship had 1000<SUP>l</SUP> worth of them, as
filthie things as they be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>So would I: but it shall never be said for my credit
sake that I tooke vp a commoditie of old ragges or doub∣lets.
I haue heard of manie scurvie bargaines, but never the
like to this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, tis but your fancie. And now you cannot
goe backe: here is witnesse enough you engaged your ho∣nour
to haue it. take the lesse and saue your reputation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did so indeed, the more foole I to passe my word
before I felt their stinke. I cannot abide to thinke on them.
But to saue my credit goe to, dispatch. Ile haue the whole
100<SUP>l</SUP> since I must haue some. Ile never giue my bond for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pest.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell sir, it shall be done.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Pestif.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now boy, was not this well handled? I must haue
had them vpon any tearmes: but hee never perceiued it.
Didst thou marke how <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee intreated mee with respectiue
tearmes, and pinn'd the bargaine vpon me? Those bee al∣wayes
the best penie-worths. It is a goodly thing to bee
wise. Remember boy when thou comest to yeeres, to take
this course o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="44"/>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed Sir you carried this businesse admirabli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
the end. I would rather then 40<SUP>l</SUP> for my minde sake my old
master your Worships father had st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od in a corner, and had
heard, and obserued his sonnes wisdome. I warrant it had
beene worth 1000<SUP>l</SUP> to some bodie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well. Now wee want nothing for getting this▪
th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eescore pound but <HI>Par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>agracio</HI> to seale. Goe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eeke him
out, and weele be merrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe fetch him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Insat. &amp; Infael.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke the aire is infected, that such contagious
<HI>caterpillers</HI> swarme abroad in this age to destroy vouth, that
scarse one fruite among 100 comes to bee ripe but is first
rotten. Such as this broker is are nourished by the Divel for
no cause but to waste yong men in old prisons. And these
<HI>cormorants</HI> which set them a-worke to entise youth to these
pestilent adventures me thinkes they can haue no hope that
he which receives so litle monie vpon great bonds, doth e∣uer
meane to pay them. For he deales not with one of these
gripers, but with as many as he can find wilbe content with
his owne securitie. Therefore when he comes to bee arre∣sted
he is buried aliue for all, and payeth none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wish they were all so serued. then the losse of the
monie on the one side, and the sharpe rod of imprisonment
on the other side, would bring both sorts to repentance, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
bethinke themselues of vsing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> good conscience to deceiue
on neither part. But if your Chauncellour hold on his course
i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> allowing the extortioner no more but the bare monie
made of such commodities that will shortlie end the abuse.
For this <HI>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ops</HI> dog will learne to hold the next piece better▪
then to be deluded with a shadow of double ga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. VI.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Antonio, Simplo▪ Purgato <HI>all booted.</HI> Stercorat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<HI>the bostler.</HI> Camerado <HI>chamberlaine.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ostler.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heed to my horses▪ that they bee well
<PB N="81" REF="44"/>
walked stuffed and dressed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stere.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you Sir, and your Worship may haue
provender of all sorts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Came.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will it please you to see your chamber?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes▪ but I must haue the best in the house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Came.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall Sir. What wilt please your worship to
haue to suppe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>First bring me a crustie manchet, and a single pot
of beere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Came.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shalbe done Sir <STAGE>(turnes to the people)</STAGE> heere's a
hot guest I perceiue by the single pot.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will you haue to supper Sir, that wee may
bespeake it for we are verie hungrie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is not wisedome to eate a meale when you are
hungrie, for then you eate too much and surfeite. Euen as it
is not good to fight or correct schollers when you are in
choller, for then you will doe it beyond measure. I am as
hungrie as you, yet I will eate but a manchet, and drinke
twice of one pot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Sir? will you take vp the best chamber, and
spend but two pence for your part. And this at <HI>Croyden</HI> so
neere London?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more. And but for the best chamber I would
spend but a penie, a pint of beere and a halfe penie bread.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat a shame were this if your friends should
heare it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue the disgrace to me. I can beare it. <HI>Pass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
graviora.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Purgato▪</HI> thou and I will bespeake our sup∣per.
20<SUP>d</SUP> a peece wee will spend to stoppe this current of ru∣mour.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Intr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> Camerado.</STAGE>
<P>Here is a delicate manchet Sir. what meat to your supper?</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is not crustie enough. Change it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>But we haue no better in the house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will haue it chang'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="82" REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>Came.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir, I will doe my best. what shall my Mi∣stris
provide for your supper?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>When thou hast chang'd the manchet thou shalt
know.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Camerado.</STAGE>
<P>A long journey haue I ridden, and all day fasting, except
a breake-fast at my friends house. Now if I should fill my
bellie, two shillings will not serue in sheere meate for me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and my two men. This way yet I s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue somewhat: for these
hungrie knaues out of their owne purses <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pend three shil∣lings
two pence: for I will allow but pence a p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ce. I hope
they will not compare with mee to aske two pence a peece
as I spend. O to morrow, to morrow at dinner will I carry
in for feare of fowle weather, when I come to Master <HI>Rem∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>af</HI>
his house, my continuall host and friend, whom I cannot
bauke, he is so conveniently in my way, and keepes good
cheare. Oh, by that time my stomacke will be <HI>tanquamig∣nis
accensus,</HI> a flaming fire, dispatching all meates it touch∣eth.
And it is Phys<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cke sometimes to keepe a stomacke so
fierie: for it will consume the verie wormes if anie crawle
vp to the stomacke for lacke of nutriment in the maw.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Intrat</HI> Camerado.</STAGE>
<P>Sir, I haue beene with all the bakers in the towne for a
crustie loafe.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast done well. this is as it should be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Came.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Sir, what to supper? my Mistris stands at
gaze vntill I tell her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>My friend. I haue a verie euill stomacke, it will
endure nothing toward night but bread and drinke, my
men I thinke wil haue something.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Came.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>(Turnes to the people, and saith)</STAGE> Heere is a custo∣mer
for Paltocks Inne, but weele nicke him well enough
in his horse-meate, and scurvie sheetes.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I heare the knaue well enough, but Ile watch you
for both. My horses shall haue but litle provender. Ile call
at some Farmers house to morrow, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate a p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ke in his
stable▪ and for sheetes Ile lay them by, and change with my
men▪</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="scene">
<PB N="83" REF="45"/>
<HEAD>ACT. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Intrat</HI> Insatiato &amp; Infaelicto.</STAGE>
<P>Sirra, haue you found <HI>Parvagrac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>?</HI> when will he come▪</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>To tell you the naked truth Sir I haue beene asleep
till I heard you call for your <HI>g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lasshes:</HI> for I was so hungrie,
that if I had not slept I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> committed <HI>Burglary</HI> somewhere
to get victuals: Now Ile finde him out. <STAGE>(<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee steps forwards,
and turnes againe▪ say<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>g)</STAGE> but I pray you Sir remember to
giue mee my two sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llings you promised mee for bringing
newes of your dinner. Now you shall haue monie, I speake
before it bee gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and before it be come. why dost thou tarrie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
the Scrivener will thinke v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ong; and a worse matter; per∣haps
wee shall giue them too much time to enquire of our
states.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infae.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can soone haue him if all other things were rea∣die:
you know where you left him at the Ladies, where you
both dined. He said he would follow you. I marvaile hee is
so long. But I warrant they are vp to the noses in the new
booke <HI>de flatibus.</HI> It is best for me to know if the bonds bee
readie before I fetch him, lest he be angrie to leaue the La∣dies
companie before neede require. <HI>Intrat</HI> Parvagracio.
But looke where he is come alone without carying Sir▪ you
sau'd me a labour. I was sent for you. Can you smell out
good bargaines? you come without calling. When thrift is
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n the market you are ever in the way?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>What good bargaine <HI>cracke</HI> is toward me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infae.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Master shall haue monie, and you must bee
bound with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that a good bargaine <HI>wagge?</HI> well, I haue such
an other a-bruing for your Master to bee bound with mee.
but where is he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infae.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere, at hand. Now to the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rivener and broker
goe I.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="84" REF="46"/>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad to heare of your good furniture toward,
and I come to prostrate my seale and service at you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> worthy
feete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insati.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, with all complements for such kinde loue, I
receiue your readines. And doe reciprocally promise to be
euer at your becke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Intrat</HI> Infaelicto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infae.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, the bonds be readie for the seale. I haue seene
the commoditie of ragges, and I like them well. They never
dustie you except they be stirr'd. But they are foule and hea∣vy.
I wood we had sold them by gold smiths weight for so
much in silver. I did see a fellow lift a bundle of them vp to
a carre, and he grunted hard; he made me remember my La∣dies
booke <HI>de flatibus.</HI> For I look'd euer when hee would
haue let flye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well lets goe seale the bonds, and lose no time.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="7" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 7.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Intrat <HI>Levitia</HI> cum <HI>Pedisequa.</HI> her periwigs of dogges hair<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te, and a yellow band about her necke, a glasse, and pow∣der
of an old post in a boxe or paper. And is very busie in
trimmin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> her selfe, and casting dust vpon her head vntill
her time come to speake.</STAGE>
<P><HI>Ins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tiat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> goes on saring,</HI> But what haue wee heere? Ile see
this sight for all the haste.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why tis a woman. Dost not see what it is?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>A woman? tis not a woman. The head is a dog.
tis a <HI>maremaide,</HI> halfe a dog, halfe a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>No tis but the haire of a dog in fashion, pul'd from
these Island dogges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>In fashion? there's a fashion for a foole. What's
that she casts vpon her head?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's the powder of a rotten post.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>A tale of a tub, the powder of a pudding: will you
make me beleeue that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="85" REF="46"/>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doest thou thinke it so strange? vpon my credite
I know some are spoken to for providing such powder by
Ladies. I am in earne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. I assure you tis verie common.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke they be common indeed that bee dress'd
with dust. <STAGE>(he goes prying on both sides of her, saying)</STAGE> not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
dog say you? the head is a dog. The chiefest part is a dog.
well, say what you will, you shall never make mee beleeue
but it is either a dog, or a dogged woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be she what she will in conditions, I warrant thee
tis a woman in sexe, or never trust my iudgement againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that about her neck? a pancake, or a tanzie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a band yellow starch'd▪ how canst thou thinke
it to be a tanzie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because it lookes so yellow. Marie it is not so wel
I wish it were, for then I would eat it vp, for I haue not halfe
din'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. twere pitie to devoure her▪ me thinks tis a ve∣ry
pretie creature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost thou like her so well? Ile goe wooe her: shee
has no impediment, but I may marie her, may I not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not that I knowe, except she be honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that an impediment? nay, the honester the bet∣ter.
Ile to her instantlie. I see no reason but I may fall in loue
with her on the suddaine. And happie is that wooing that
is not long in doing: but stay, are you sure she is a woman? I
am in some doubt. And I would be verie loath to mary her
except she proue a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant thee shee is a woman. why shouldst thou
feare it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue I not cause to feare it? for if I should be ma∣ried
to a beast, or a iade, I were vtterly vndone. is it not
good to be sure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistrust not that. thou maist knowe by her speech
and voice whether she be a woman or no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cannot her tongue deceaue me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes like enough, but not in this case, And if the
<PB N="86" REF="47"/>
worst fall you may easily knowe the first night you I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to∣gether.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you for nothing when it is too late.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy too late? thou maist be rid of her presently,
and be parted the next day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could like that well enough so that I had her por∣tion,
but is there such a course to be taken, that they cannot
be tied so fast, but they may easilie be vndone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>No question but the mariage is void.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's an excellent tricke. I wish I had a grant vn∣der
the great seale to vnmarrie all those that would faine be
parted. I would purchase Lordships, Townes, &amp; Countries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you had, yet must you vse discretion in it, and de∣vide
none but such as are indeed no marriages at first, but
had impediments not dispensable. Otherwise you might be
cause of great sinne, and inconvenien<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. You must examine
the reasons, and proceed iudiciallie, before you sever them
rashly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Never tell me, let them looke to that at their own
perill. It would take vp too much time if there came to me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
but 100 in a daie to examine them all. No. no. if they were
willing to be sundred, I would vncouple them: let them
range afterward which waie they will for me. Well vpon
thy word that I may be livorced from her if she proue not
a certaine woman Ile vpon her whatsoever she be. And Ile
catch her vpon a suddaine for feare least it be a dog &amp; bite
me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>(he goes stealing towards her with his hands forward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>A waie cocks-combe. I am asham'd on thee: come
backe, what dost thou meane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that same is a very suspicious head. I am afraid
of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Afraid of a dead dogge? what a cowardly thing is
that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>A dead dogge? marrie perhaps the haire is vpon <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ster snapper then the right owner was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be rul'd by me; Ile stand between thee and al dan∣gers.
<PB N="87" REF="47"/>
go orderly to her, take her by the right hand as if thou
wouldst dance with he. <HI>He daunceth toward her and singeth.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hey niny. nony no. Hey niny n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Hey noniny nonin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪
Hey ninyno. So he daunces toward her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a fellow art thou? a Courtier? a Cowdriuer,
come hither once againe. Dost thou thinke to speed &amp; goe
about It so like a Clowne▪ Thou must wooe her, as you
court your ladies in the pallace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, must I so? I thought she had beene a countrie
gentlewoman, and that the more plainely I had dealt, the
better she would like me. But all is well enough yet, for no
body saw me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art deceiued in that: for they are as fine and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urious as anie Ladie in Court, though they be not proud a
whit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is't so? well, then I can fit her, she shall haue cour∣ting
enough. And I am glad you tell me of it; for I was in
earnest to haue lou'd her beyond measure, &amp; so might haue
fallen mad, and marr'd all: but now Ile doe euen as wee doe
at Court, make many shewes of loue and service, and
intend nothing lesse. But yet thus honestlie Ile deale with
this woman (because she is a stranger) that if I loue her, and
like her, Ile loue her vntill I leaue her. Well, tis time to bee
doing, for my loue begins to coole verie fast: I must kindle
it againe. <STAGE>(with a conge he takes her by the left hand, saying)</STAGE>
Faire Lady, it becomes not gentlemen of good breeding to
talke of the weather, or time of the day, or vse such idle im∣pertinent
speech: therefore, (all preambles and digressions
s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t aside) I come to vnderstand if you bee pleased to admit
me into the list of your devoted servants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed Sir, it seemes you haue beene well bred, els
you had never growen to this stature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>(He turnes from her towards <HI>Parvagracio,</HI> and saith)</STAGE>
Did not I tell you what I should finde of her? shee snarles al∣readie.
Ile lay my life she will proue currish, her looks make
it plaine, come sweet Ladie, what answere to my question?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="88" REF="48"/>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay first I had neede to answere your complaint to
your friend, that I am so curst and churlish. What vncivill
tearme did I giue, deserving so sharpe a censure? women
know not how to speake. If merily, then our jest is tearmed
s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>offing, and quipping. I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> soberly, then our modestie is
counted coynesse, and want of curtesie. So that vnlesse wee
say nothing, we commit error. And yet silence is not clee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e:
for then are we sheepe (<HI>alias</HI>) fooles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>How could you heare what I said to him, since I
turn'd my mouth from you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you turn'd not mine eares from your mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon this fault good Ladie. I will be more care∣full
heereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>No doubt you will: to haue mee further off when
you say the worst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meane not so. but rather to speake the best of
you in all places and companies as your merites (I know)
will enforce me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing comes from you (I see then) but by con∣straint.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that you would giue over rebuking, no man
shall reforme himselfe before me. Forgiue what is past. If I
offend againe, deny me all favour.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Pestifero,</HI> and whispers <HI>Insatiato,</HI> to whom he saith,</STAGE>
<P>Tell them I will come anon.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Pestifero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, it is against nature to remit iniuries, therefore
your request is vnreasonable. But for his sake that gaue the
counsell, I will for giue my greatest enemies: yet you must
know it is lawfull to reprehend your misdemeanours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>(Turnes from her towards <HI>Parvagracio,</HI> and saith)</STAGE>
This comforts me much, for she may be a Christian for anie
thing I heare yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>You that content your selfe with no habitation
but a Princes Palace, and will serue no lesse creature then
<HI>Caesar:</HI> that no sooner passe the Porters lodge, but li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t vp
your legges and lips, as if you had commission to controule
<PB N="89" REF="48"/>
the countrie, to breathe nurture from your nostrils, and be
patrone to poore people: whose gate and gesture giue te∣stimonie
to your hearts haughtinesse: and whose counte∣nance
must outface all encounterers, how could you bee so
grossely ouer-shot, as to cast your selfe vnacquainted, vn∣friended
vncommended, and vnpresented into the compa∣nie
of a gentlewoman of fashion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cry you mercie. Of what fashion are you that I
might not doe as I did without offence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Sir? are you a courtier? and aske of what fa∣shion
I am? doe you not see that I am of the newest, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est fashion? who sees my band and perrywig, &amp; doubts
of that: I am perswaded you will proue a counterfait<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and
no courtier, that are ignorant in so generall a knowledge?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was not the newest fashion the last yeare, and
no Cronicle make▪ mention of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Therefore if any man
had written. <HI>Nihil factum est quod non fuit factum prius.</HI> I
would haue giuen his <HI>Proverbs</HI> the lye. For this <HI>saffroning</HI>
was never vs'd but in Ireland for bodily linnen, to dissipate
the companie of creepers. And for such torturing of these
Izeland Impes, with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>radicating their fleeces, therby to en∣ioy
the roots, which best will abide the basting, it hath need
to be new, for it is noy some, and makes your <HI>pretywig</HI> no∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hing
handsome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, let it suffise you that it is the newest fashion
this verie day. And if the sight and smell of it offend your
nose, you know the ordinary remedie is to remoue your
nose. Yet I suppose by your palenesse you vse to take Ta∣baccho,
then which, nothing is more fulsome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed, I want colour in my face, and wishe I had
the art to get so rosie a cheeke as you haue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>You doe but guesse that I vse art to giue grace to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y feature, so it is easie for you to be deceiued: but I will
tell you a certaine rule to know if anie woman be painted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me bee beholding to you for this cunning in∣fallible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="90" REF="49"/>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you suspect it, take a pin, and scratch her cheeke
pretie deepe to the bone, and if it b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed not, assure your selfe
she is painted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see now you are dispos'd to be pleasant with me.
I beare all kindly. Now I intreate you to proceede with
publishing my other faults, that when I know them all, I
may amend, and so appeare perfect in your sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Secondly, I charge you with flatterie, at every word
calling me <HI>Ladie:</HI> which you are verie sure I am not, seeing
me come hither on my owne feet, whereas if I were a <HI>Lady</HI>
I must of necessitie be at my <HI>Caroach</HI> with 4 horses, or els
my honour is in the dust in sommer, and in the mire in win∣ter.
This then is an vnexcusable sinne of yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas. what should I call you not knowing your
name? And you of all the women that euer I knew are an∣grie
for giuing you more then your due. But rather then I
will displease you that way, I will devise some other <HI>Epithe∣ton</HI>
of curtesie, vntill you determine to take <HI>Ladyship</HI> vpon
you, so well as it would become you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I would not haue you thinke that I am excee∣dingly
angrie for mistaking my present condition. It was a
fault, but verie veniall. Your other errours I will conceale
for this time, as vnwilling to oppresse you with penance,
sithence I finde you so freely to offer satisfaction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then now vouchsafe to receiue me into your ser∣vice,
sithence no man shall carie himselfe more dutifully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I were fit to receiue one of your sort, how could
you serue me and the king too? can you serue two masters?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. but one master and a mistresse may both bee
serued without breach of fidelitie, and with great facilitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verie hardly, respecting the persons inequalitie:
but if I should be so minded, what can you doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>All, that is not done before I come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you, and will you doe whatsoever I ent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eate
or command you without grudging?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, with all readines and alacritie, &amp; without ex∣ception.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="91" REF="49"/>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I request and command you to let me alone,
and neuer heereafter speake to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's an vnreasonable request, and iniust com∣mandement.
There ought to bee iustice and possibilitie in e∣uerie
commandement; but this hath neither of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will proue it hath both, or els I release your word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Proue that, and Ile performe your will: for I haue
vowed to serue you, and it is iniustice to breake it. And I am
in loue, and it is impossible to limite it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought so. <HI>draffe was your errant▪ but drinke you
would haue.</HI> you seeke a seruice, but you meane to be master:
this tricke will faile you: for I haue vowed before-hand, and
I am bound to keepe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>You can make no vow contrarie to mine, because
you neuer knew my intention, nor person before this day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, contrarie enough, as white is to blacke. And
to hold you no longer in suspence, my vow and purpose is
to be a Nun.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Nun? There was neuer Nun with such attire, and
in such a Cloister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Sir, I can quicklie cast off this attire, and get a
Nuns habite. If the mind be changed, the apparel will soone
be altered.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what order (if you speake in earnest) that I may
visit your Cloister? for loue hath gotten such dominion.
that I cannot so part with you. And yet to this crosse I know
not what to say: for it takes from me all libertie to mooue
further.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will it availe you to know my Cloister, and
walke without the wall? for there, all accesse &amp; entercourse
is barred.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let my loue yet bee so farre requited, as to know
your name and or<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er you enter into. It will ease my minde,
that none other inioies you. O, this loue is like a quarterne
ague, and a suite iu Law! A good day, and a bad: now hope.
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen despair. To night cō<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ort, tomorow morning al dash'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="92" REF="50"/>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I must craue respite to answere you directlie to
these questions: for I must haue my friends advice before I
resolue. And so for this t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me I take leaue.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Lev.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, let vs goe seale these bondes in the meane
space, and by that time perhaps she will come againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bonds? I am in bonds enough I thinke, bound
hand, foote, heart, minde, wit and will. Hee that is in loue
needes no other chaine to hold him▪ he is fast in prison, and
lock'd sure enough for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>scaping. O <HI>Parvagracio!</HI> dost thou
talke of going? whither should I goe? Is it not enough that
my loue is gone, and that all is gone with her? my heart is
gone with her, and she is gone away with my heart: whither
can I goe without my heart? And whither she is gone, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he hath caried my heart I know not. Sealing. what
ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thou of sealing? I haue set my hand, my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ele, my har<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and all to the loue of her. She is gone away with this deed
of gift. It is deliue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed before witnes. It is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nroll'd. I haue
acknowledged a fine. I haue suffered her to recouer against
me; and deliuered her peaceable possession. The Law is at
an end▪ what els would you haue me seale? I can giue her no
further assurance. her counsaile cannot devise it. why do you
trouble me with vnnecessarie requests?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my good friend <HI>Insatiato</HI> recall thy selfe like a
wise man. thou speakest like a man distracted. goe with me,
and take a litle rest. It will not be lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g before shee come to
this place againe. We will send your Page to find her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>A little rest I warrant you. Goe? you are still vpon
going. Goe whither you will, I will not stirre a foote from
hence. What if she come in our absence, and goe away dis∣contented?
then shall I neuer see nor heare her againe. No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
heere I lost her, heere I will finde her, or lose my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you will trouble and hinder other actors that
haue parts heere to play as well as you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Actors. what actors? Is this a stage? Is this a play?
no. tis a game in earnest. tis no iest, tis loue in sadnesse. Let
them come that come will: if anie come but my loue, I haue
<PB N="93" REF="50"/>
nothing to say to them. Doe you as you thinke good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, if you stay, I will not goe. I will not leaue my
friend so.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 7.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Intrat <HI>Antonio, Simplo, Purgato</HI> with a cloake-bag
full vnder his arme, all boo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed, spur'd,
and riding roddes.</STAGE>
<P>Haue you lock'd vp all the doores, and deliuered the foul
linnen to be wash'd▪</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim</SPEAKER>
<P>All is safe, and euerie thing done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you given the Coblers wife the 7 egges
we left at breakefast?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>She hath them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is but ill husbandrie to lose 7 egges at a
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ap, and my bellie not verie full.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, they are well bestowed, they will doe the
poore woman good, and you haue eaten pretie well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue not eaten so well as you thinke for. And
they are not fit meate for her mouth: some grosser meate
would doe her more good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you Sir, she can eate an egge without
surfeiting, as well as the finest Ladie in this Land.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come on, since tis done, let them goe: but <STAGE>(hee
steps forward, and they follow, but presently comes backe, and
saith)</STAGE> I cannot ride my iourney contentedl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e vntill I haue
these egges. <HI>Simplo,</HI> fetch them againe. Tell the woman,
she shall haue as manie or more another time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>turnes to the people, saying.</STAGE> Now must I fetch these
egges from the poore woman against my nature.
<STAGE>Exit &amp;
cito re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it with 7 egges. Anto. takes them &amp; exit. Simple go∣eth
on saying,</STAGE> I was neuer ashamed of a master before. There
are few times that we ride forth, but a rosted Rabbet, a piece
of cheefe, or a drie brest of mutton is truss'd vp in the cloak-bag,
especially when wee lye at an Inne the next night (as
<PB N="94" REF="51"/>
now we shall.) And but for fowling the cloake-bag, and
his cloathes, we had carried these egges now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is no such stuffe now in the cloake-bagge I
trow? If I thought there were, I would throw it to the dogs
rather then it should ride behinde me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is there not? tis a great chance then; &amp; I am much
deceiu'd if there be none: for there were some scrappes left
yesternight, and I finde them not in anie roome in the
house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>That shalbe tried by and by. Be these his trickes?
though I be his horse-keeper, Ile carrie no coales nor bones
neither I trow. <HI>(hee vndoeth an end of the cloake-bag, and
there takes out a napkin full of pieces of bread, a quarter of a
brest of mutton, a piece of boyl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d beefe, a pudding, a bone of a
loine of veale: that he vnpinneth, and lifting it vp by one cor∣ner,
lets all fall, and presently catcheth at them with his hands
vpon the ground, scrambling euerie way as hee would ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch at
a Rat, saying.</HI>) What's become of her? take heed gentle∣women
she get not vp. I sweare, I had almost catch'd her.
Was there not a Rat there? Masters, you below, came shee
not that way?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Langheth, and saith.</HI> How now <HI>Purgato.</HI> What, art
thou at span-counter with Rats? I perceiue thou wouldest
haue fought with any Rat in London rather then she should
haue be guil'd thee of thy provender.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>My provender? the dogs shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate it, before any
bit shall come in my mouth. How came he by these scraps,
and what would he doe with them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art but a novice <HI>Purgato.</HI> and hadst as much
wit when thou suckedst (I thinke) as now. And besides for
that thou camest to him but yesterday (in a manner) art ig∣norant
of his fashions. I will instruct thee. The night before
he rides from London, he will invite some of his acquain∣tance
to supper with him (at their owne charge more then
his) then the remnant he packeth vp thus. And at the next
Inne he lodgeth in (if it be two dayes thence) he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ates these
<PB N="95" REF="51"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ates vnder the colour of a litle joint there dressed. And by
this meanes hee is counted at his Inne a verie small meate∣man,
but everie-where els a tall trencher-man. But thou
must vnderstand the chamberlain and tapster are sent down
when these dainties are in devouring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>But doe you eate anie of this daintie trashe with
him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or els I must goe hungrie to bed, and ride emptie
the next day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>As true as I liue, hee shall never bring mee to this
geare. And the next time he makes such a messe, Ile pro∣vide
sawce: for Ile put a fresh horse-turd in the midst. And
my trotting horse will soone season it all alike.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Intrat Ant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come away, I haue eaten foure of these egges,
the rest I haue put in branne to preserue against the nex
Tearme: but what's heere? how came this meate heere? mee
thinkes I should know these pieces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be so Sir, but I did neuer see the like.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I had the cloake-bag vnder mine arme, I felt a
thing stirre within it: and in searching▪ I found these scraps,
and among them an huge Rat. And she went away invisible:
for I am sure we could not see which way she ran, nor could
I catch her, doe what I could, and yet I scambled at her with
both my hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you not gather vp the meate, and put it
vp againe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? and the Rat had piss'd on it for feare, and it
stinkes too bad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>How canst thou tell th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t a Rat had piss'd on it,
when you confesse you did see no Rat?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, not which way shee ran away. But if yonder
boy had gap'd wide enough, hee might haue catch'd her in
his mouth: and doe you thinke I saw not a Rat? I am sure
there was a Rat, for my minde gaue me so. And further, I
had like to catch'd her. All this companie can tell what a
<PB N="96" REF="52"/>
course I had at her, if you will not beleeue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to, goe to. You are a foole. Put them vp
and let vs away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>I were a foole indeed, and a beast too, if I would
put them vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>I bid you put them vp like a foole as you are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot put them vp like a foole, nor I will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt put them vp, or serue me no longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t master, Ile turne you off at this
instant. Heere is witnes enough I haue giuen̄ you lawfull
warning.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gather vp this meate <HI>Simplo,</HI> thou and I will
fare the better. Tis but sending this knaues horse downe by
the Carrier. Or els Ile driue him with his loade, he shalbe
the sumpter horse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Simplo</HI> gathers them vp, and puts them in the napkin▪
and pinnes them vp, puts them into the cloak bag.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Antonio &amp; Simplo.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 7.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. 2.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parv.</SPEAKER>
<P>How lik'st thou this sport <HI>Insatiato?</HI> hath it diver∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed
thy thoughts a little?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was some recreation I must needes say: but my
fit is comming on apace. <STAGE><HI>Intrat</HI> Levitia.</STAGE> And loo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
where she comes. Now I tremble with feare of a deadly
doome; but I must speake howsoeuer I speede. Welcome
sweet Mistresse. Now kill, or keepe me aliue with your an∣swere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your questions <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir (if I forget not) were, what
was my name, and what order I purpose to enter. My name
is <HI>Levitia.</HI> And my desire is to be a Nunne of my mothers
order. But if my virginitie were not of ful age; and Maiden-head
a dangerous burden, I would be a Nun of a straighter
order.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your mothers order? what order is that? I never
<PB N="97" REF="52"/>
heard of a Nun haue a child, no husband, and yet continue
in Cloyster, and a Nun before she had a child.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>My mother vowed chastitie, and after that had a
childe by her husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Leu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tia?</HI> this is a riddle, and a wonder to me;
yet this English I picke out of it, that you may haue a hus∣band
as your mother had. And then if it please you, I may
be your ghostlie father after the fashion of this c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>untry: but
how, or why your mother or you should vow chastitie, I
see not, no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> would I be married to such a Nun.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas <HI>Insatiato,</HI> I perceiue thou art simple in this bu∣sines,
or els not yet come to thy selfe again. <HI>Levitia</HI> speakes
well, but thy capacitie is verie muddie. Wouldst thou not
haue thy wife vow chastitie, but be an harlot? there is cha∣stity
and continencie among married folke, so long as they
be faithfull each to other. But virginitie goes further: and
that is sequestred continencie during life, not admitting
companie for procreation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vnderstand it now (thanks to thee <HI>Parvagraci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>)
but this creature would haue delayd me longer, and dull'd
my wits without mercie.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Pestifero,</HI> and whispers <HI>Insatiato,</HI> to whom in an∣ger
he answereth, either let them stay, or teare the
writings, I cannot yet come.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exit Pestif.</STAGE>
<P>But I thanke her yet for the kinde order shee hath made
to be of her mothers order. I hope (sweet Mistris <HI>Levitia</HI>)
you will heare no motion to ouerthrow this order againe.
And now tell me, what say you to my vow, which in all e∣qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tie
must be performed. You see I was content (though
much against my minde) that you should haue kept your
vow of virginitie, (if so had stood your resolution) now I
appeale to your owne court for Iustice, and hope you will
giue as good way to the fulfilling of my vow, which is ne∣ver
to leaue your service and companie.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>I heard you talke at Randon of such a thing. Ma∣ny
such (I doubt not) you haue made, and quickly brok<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n;
<PB N="98" REF="53"/>
and this of the same mettle, &amp; so will proue as bri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le. Cour∣tlers
vowes of this nature are but words, a little more stiffly
blowne out of their mouthes, then the rest of their speech,
but come no neerer their hearts. The gunner puts a little
more powder in the gun to make it carrie the shot further,
but hits the marke no whit the righter: So they driue their
vowes with a little stronger breath, but their intention i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
not the streighter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed I confesse that I haue sometimes done as
you say: but now my heart is right, and my meaning direct.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>How shall that appeare to me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>I dare vandertake (Ladie <HI>Levitia</HI>) he meanes iustly
by you: for I haue seene him in a dangerous passion when
you left our companie, which if you had heard, standing in
some secret place, you could not but haue compassion on
him. or els you were verie d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sdain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull and cruell. Besides I
know it is a great matter that would stay him so long as he
hath talked with you from dispatching a businesse of great
importance, as you may partlie perceiue by the messenger
comming so often in the meane time to haue him away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, a s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>conder of a tale makes manie times an in∣credible
thing beleeued. And for your testimonie, I giue
him credit the better, and perhaps I was within <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ght and
hearing too, when this gentleman was so loue-sicke as
you speake of, which made me in verie pitie come the soo∣ner
in to relieue him. And I would not haue you think <HI>Par∣vagracio</HI>
that I am disdainefull, for that winneth nothing
but hatred: nor am I cruel, for that is euer payed home with
extreame miserie. Now yet am I proud (which vice you
touched not) for that is derided of all wise people, but my
feare and doubt was alwayes to be deceiued.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere is my hand I will neuer deceiue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere is my hand I will never leaue you. But what
a foole was I? I should haue agreed for maintenance and
joincture before I had beene handfast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's no matter, Ile performe as well as if I were
<PB N="99" REF="53"/>
bound hand and foote. I will allow you 10<SUP>l</SUP> a yeare for
pinnes, 5<SUP>l</SUP> for shooes, 15<SUP>l</SUP> for stockings, garters, bodies, and
g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rdles, 50<SUP>l</SUP> for gownes, peticoates and such like: 20<SUP>l</SUP> for all
sorts of linnen and new fashions, this is 100<SUP>l</SUP> a yeere, and is
as much as my liuing will afford. And for performance of
this anie friend of yours shall haue a statute vpon all the
land I haue. And for your joincture, I will giue good assu∣rance,
that the longer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iuer of vs two shal possesse all I haue,
If I die not worth a groate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like all well but my allowance for pins: it is not
enough: for it is a base fashion now-a-daies to vse cufhnets
and saue pinnes. The verie warmth of our bodies, will
change their colour in three houres, and they wilbe croo∣ked
with pulling off, fie vpon them: but Ile be a good hus∣wife
otherwise▪ and get as much by other meanes as shall
piece out this pension to make it serue. Sirra, I haue skill in
Phisicke, I can cure the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> in anie man. And if hee be
neuer so leane, and rawbon'd, I can so diet him in halfe a
yeare, that he will be fed vntill he grow purse-sicke. And
for thee (sweet heart) be of good cheere, for thou shalt ne∣ver
die (without a great chance) as long as I liue. For I can
play a tricke, that if thou be never so cold, or frozen almost
to death, I can make thee luke-warme in halfe an houre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>(Imbraceth and kisseth her)</STAGE> Ha may liuelie <HI>Levitia,</HI>
we cannot chuse but thriue if thou hast these trades. But is
thy portion in sure hands?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare nothing of that, you shall haue mee and my
portion at an instant, all together readie bagg'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Best of all, then it requires no telling Heere is a to∣ken
for thee my chicken.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? kniues? O, I will not take them in anie wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,
they will cut loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no: if they cut anie thing, they will cut away
vnkindnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon mee (good Sir) you shall not giue them
me. If needes you will that I weare them, do you lose, and I
will find them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="100" REF="54"/>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's a toy of all toyes. That were fitter for a stag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
then a wedding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev,</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed you shall not denie me this first request, I
pray you lose them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, tis no newes to be made a foole by a woman.
Ile doe it, if it were worse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Then he walkes about and dropp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s
them d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ne, and she comes after and takes them vp. saying.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is as it should be: now I haue deceaued desti∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is Superstich my shooes, now he hath fooled
a fopperie. And you haue found a foolerie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>v.</SPEAKER>
<P>You mocke this <HI>Parvagracio.</HI> I warrant you do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
not thinke it evill lucke if the salt fall toward you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I doe if no bodie overthrowe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>What if a Hare crosse your way? is that nothing nei∣ther?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uill lucke indeed if I haue no dogges to
course her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Parvagracio.</HI> I prethee lead <HI>Levitia</HI> to my lodg∣ing.
I must craue pardon to goe about a speciall businesse
which concernes all my worth: but we will dispatch quick∣ly
and follow. And meet me the next way <HI>Parvagracio</HI> wee
must haue your helpe. Ile goe before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lev.</SPEAKER>
<P>In any case looke to the maine chance, for now
you haue a clogge. It is the first gift every wife giues her
husband.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Parv. &amp; Levit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now boy. wee must about these bonds sealing to
put vs in suits for this wedding Wee shall sure thriue now.
Two such bargaines gone through in one day. A stranger
for a wife▪ and ragges for our wealth. We cannot want after
the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e matches. I could haue found in my heart to asked her
some monie and mist this ragg'd monie. But what if shee
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aue none? she saith I shall haue her and all ready bagg'd.
Perhaps she meanes that herselfe is readie bagg'd to my
hand I cannot tell▪ there be such tricks in the world. I doubt
I am vtterly vndone with this foolish match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="101" REF="54"/>
<SPEAKER>Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, if you be let it not trouble you, I hope you
shall haue better lucke in greater matters, &amp; yet if she haue
a good portion you are happy, if she haue none, yet you
may be even with her if it please you al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hough she prou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
roaring girle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Insa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst thou tell which way to be even with her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary to haue as little as she. And if I were <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> you
I would serue her so, teach her to come <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mptie handed to a
man of your spending.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well: we must make the most of her that I can now
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> haue her: and take no care for any thing▪ that<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the way to
liue long and leaue nothing.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 7.</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCEN. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Intrat</HI> Simplo.</STAGE>
<P>Gentlemen (you two I meane M. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> and Sir <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI>)
my master intreats you bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h to come to his chamber
for a short space, he will go twice so faire for you any other
time.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt Insa. &amp; Infael.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke your master, we haue din'd alreadie, and
can eat nothing: another time we will see him if wee haue
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o businesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>O you mistake it Sir neither now, nor any other
time for eating: there is no meat: my Master does not vie to
quilt his frends stomack<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> with too much meat. No, hee
would speake with you about a note he hath caused to bee
drawne he will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> you to p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rvse it, and do him a favour
it is in the nature of a certificate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely he shall haue no hand of m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne to any wri∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing
nor to anie purpose, nor for my credit sake will I come
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n his companie. I doe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>agine what it is. He knoweth th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e heare so m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch evill of him that he d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ubts we will speak
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s we finde. And therefore he would haue vs giue commē∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ations
of him to some friend of our<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in some small request
which he never meanes to sue for. But this our good repor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB REF="55"/>
he will keepe by him par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly to stop our mouthes (hoping
we will not speake contrarie to our testimonie in writing,
and pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tly for his credi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to be shewed vpon every o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on
against all that haue cause to speake evill of him. Let him
content him<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elfe we ref<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se to come neere him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honest friend: I marv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll with what conscience
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rue one that is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary Sir with as wide and large a conscience as a∣ny
man hath, and as throughly tentered. My master &amp; I are
no niggards of our conscience. Besides I am bound by my
100<SUP>l</SUP> to serue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou wert as good lose thy 100<SUP>l</SUP> at first, as at la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
for he will in the end deceaue thee of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he doe then I hope hee will teach mee cunning
worth 100<SUP>l</SUP> to deceaue others. &amp; so I may double my 100<SUP>l</SUP>.
For I doe not thinke but hee hath gotten manie 100<SUP>l</SUP> with
art. And Ile never leaue him tell I get all his tricks and now
he hath made me free he will vse me as his fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>By that meanes thou wilt accompanie him to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Downe the lane to the Divell. Nay an wee goe to
no worse place <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen Hell I care not: for I doe not think but
my maste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hath craft enough for any Divell on um all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>But there he shall meet with his crafts master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? master my master in craft? that were some∣what
strange, yet Ile beleeue any thing but that. Wel I shall
tell him you will not co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e. And what's the reason you will
not co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e? I haue almost forgotten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary because at our baptisme wee vowed to r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣nounce
the infernall Spirit. And now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon our owne expe∣rience
and iudgement we abandon al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> incarnate Divells.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim</SPEAKER>
<P>Abandon? what's that? if I can obserue that word
right▪ I shall ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y the rest well. I knowe what you meane by
a carnation <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ivell.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe you iudge of these passages M. <HI>Securu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ely Sir▪ it is hard vpon the suddaine to deliuer
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rue sentence vpon so many contrarieties as this day wee
<PB REF="55"/>
haue heard. But b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eefly I thinke they o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght all to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> du∣ced
vnto two maine heads of Good and Bad. and of the
worst to chuse the least: and of the be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> take the most.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<P>In part I dissent from y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u but in part I ag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee. If we
be constrained to chuse among things whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
best to permit the least: but if a man haue freedome <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
best choice is to refuse evill be it never so little. Among <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he
severall discourses this day acted. I note many vices va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d
over with froth, and florish of words, but the same againe
vnma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ked with substantiall matter, and laid naked to di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣grace.
So it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> they are not propounded to imitate,
but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> forth to be sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed. They are pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nted in colour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but
in a map of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> some <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,
but such as runne to ruine. They are brought forth to be
rewed; but to manifest their vglinesse. They come not here
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o be liked, but lothed; not to be fau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>red, but derided. Not
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llowed in private, but in publike to be condemned. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ope that all wise hearers will a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oid the sinnes and abuse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere touched (which are many) and follow good counsell
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f they heard any. Which that they may doe my part is to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ray to the g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer of wisdome. And so Sir, wishing much pro
peritie to your charitable endeavours, I take leaue▪ and the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ext way to my poore quiet Cell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit &amp; Securus sequitur∣wit▪</STAGE>
<STAGE>Intrat Proberio.</STAGE>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="56"/>
<HEAD>EPILOGVS.</HEAD>
<P>NOw that your pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ence hath permitted vs to bring vnto
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> end this present Dialogue, wee stand in good hope of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>menci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, that no more offence will bee taken at any word
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> passed then we had meaning to gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, which wee protest
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> at all. For it were against reason and our owne ends <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
driue hence that companie, which we w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh rather <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oubled, then
out of it one to be spared. I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> resteth that we render you very
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie thanks. And that all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r hearts pray for the
K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng and his families enduring happinesse, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="56"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

