<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached at Saint Marie Spittle April. 10. 1615. By Thomas Anyan Doctour of Divinity, and president of Corpus Christi College in Oxon</TITLE><AUTHOR>Anyan, Thomas, 1580 or 81-1632.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A20573</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 698</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S115864</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99851081</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99851081</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">16336</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A20573)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16336)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 867:09)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached at Saint Marie Spittle April. 10. 1615. By Thomas Anyan Doctour of Divinity, and president of Corpus Christi College in Oxon</TITLE><AUTHOR>Anyan, Thomas, 1580 or 81-1632.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 42 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>At Oxford :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, printer to the Vniversity,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1615]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Publication date from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ali Jakobson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ali Jakobson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A20573">
<STC T="S">698</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99851081</BIBNO>
<VID>16336</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A SERMON PREACHED AT SAINT MARIE SPITTLE April. 10. 1615.</P>
<P>BY THOMAS ANYAN Doctour of Divinity, and President of Corpus Christi College in Oxon.</P>
<P>AT OXFORD, Printed by Ioseph Barnes, Printer to the Vniversity.</P>
<PB REF="2"/>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<P><PB REF="2"/>
HONORATISSIMO, ET ILLVSTRIS∣SIMO VIRO, THOMae EGERTONO, MILI∣TI AVRATO, BARONI DE ELLESMERE, TOTIVS ANGLIAE, ET ACADEMIAE OXONIENSIS CANCELLARIO SVM∣MO ET INTEGERRIMO, MVSARVM GRATIARVMQVE PATRONO SIN∣GVLARI, SACRATAE REGIAE MA∣IESTATI A SECRETIS CONSILIIS INTER PRIMOS SPECTATISSIMO, DOMINOQVE SVO OMNI OBSER∣VANTIA COLENDISSIMO, LEVI∣DENSE HOC DEVOTISSIMI OBSE∣QVII TESTIMONIVM <HI>D. D. D.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Capellanus Honori Tuo Devinctissimus
T. A.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
<PB REF="3"/>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB REF="3"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><BIBL>ACT. 10. 34. 35.</BIBL>
<P>34 <HI>Then Peter opened his mouth, and said, Of a truth I perceaue, that God is no accepter of persons.</HI></P>
<P>35 <HI>But in every nation, he that feareth him, and worketh righteousnes, is accepted with him.</HI></P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">M</SEG>Y Text is the beginning of a Sermon, endited by Him, who at his Ascension inspired the Holy Ghost, preached by that great Apostle &amp; glorious Mar∣tyr of <HI>Iesus Christ S<SUP>t</SUP> Peter,</HI> deli∣vered at <HI>Caesarea</HI> a garison town by the Sea-coast of <HI>Palaestina,</HI> occasioned by the strange and wonderfull conversi∣on of <HI>Cornelius</HI> an Italian Centurion; and is an Evan∣gelicall Speech, well suiting so blest an occasion, so divine a Speaker. Wherein I obserue,</P>
<P N="1">1 The Speaker of the Speech; <HI>Peter.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2 The Maner of his Speech; which was, not by letters, but by words, not by writing, but by preaching, not by substitution or deputation, but by teaching himselfe in his owne person.</P>
<P N="3"><PB N="2" REF="4"/>
3 The truth of his Speech, and asseveration thereof; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>In veritate comperio.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4 His confidency, and apodeicticall knowledge of what he taught; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, I plainely <HI>perceaue,</HI> or, am constantly perswaded.</P>
<P N="5">5 The Speech it selfe; <HI>God is no accepter of persons, &amp;c.</HI> Wherein we may see (as in the Vision of the Prophet <HI>Ezechiel) rotam in rotâ,</HI> two propositions, one linked within the other, which cary with them much weight, and a glorious lustre of God's vnparti∣all Iustice and Majesty.</P>
<P>The first is negatiue and generall; <HI>God is no accep∣ter, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>The second is affirmatiue, with a particular excep∣tion out of the generall negatiue. <HI>But in every nati∣on, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>In the first God's <HI>Iustice</HI> overpoiseth his <HI>Mercy:</HI> in the second his <HI>Mercy</HI> is transcendent over his <HI>Iustice.</HI> In the first hee appeares a terrible Iudge to spare none: in the second a mercifull Father to spare all, <HI>that feare him, and worke righteousnes.</HI> For they are <HI>ac∣cepted</HI> of him, not by merit, but by favour, not by workes, <HI>ex condigno,</HI> but by mercy, and <HI>ex dono.</HI> These are the parts of my Text; of which in their order.</P>
<P><HI>Peter]</HI> What <HI>Christ</HI> elsewhere promised here hee performed, &amp; makes a poore <HI>Fisher-man,</HI> to become a fisher of men. The <HI>Sea</HI> wherin he fished is the Oceā of this <HI>World, swelling</HI> with <HI>pride,</HI> livid and <HI>blew</HI> with <HI>envy, boiling</HI> with <HI>wrath, deepe</HI> with <HI>covetousnes, foa∣ming</HI> with <HI>luxury, swallowing all</HI> by <HI>oppression, dange∣rous</HI>
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
for <HI>rockes</HI> of <HI>presumption</HI> and <HI>desperation, rising</HI> with <HI>waues</HI> of <HI>passion, ebbing</HI> and <HI>flowing</HI> with <HI>incon∣stancie,</HI> and last of all, <HI>Mare amarum, bitter</HI> with all kind of <HI>misery.</HI> The chiefe <HI>fish,</HI> which at this time came to his <HI>net,</HI> was <HI>Cornelius</HI> an Italian Centurion, and with him many other <HI>Gentiles.</HI> The <HI>Net,</HI> wherewith he fi∣shed and caught him and them, was the <HI>glad tidings</HI> of the <HI>Gospell,</HI> and <HI>Faith</HI> in Iesus <HI>Christ:</HI> which is com∣pared in Scripture to a <HI>Net,</HI> and consisteth of manic <HI>Articles,</HI> as a <HI>Net</HI> of many <HI>threds.</HI> The <HI>casting</HI> of this net, was the <HI>vnfolding</HI> of the <HI>Word: Then Peter opened his mouth.</HI> The <HI>plummets</HI> that <HI>keepe</HI> such <HI>downe,</HI> as are <HI>taken</HI> in the <HI>Net,</HI> from <HI>presumptiō,</HI> are the <HI>threatnings</HI> of the <HI>Law,</HI> and the severe <HI>Iustice</HI> of God: <HI>God is no ac∣cepter of persons.</HI> The <HI>Corkes,</HI> that <HI>beare</HI> them <HI>vp</HI> in all the surges of this world, that they <HI>sinke</HI> not downe into the <HI>depth</HI> of <HI>despaire,</HI> are the <HI>promises</HI> of the <HI>Gos∣pell,</HI> and the sweete <HI>mercies</HI> of Almighty God: <HI>But in every nation, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>This great <HI>Fisher</HI> of men <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Peter,</HI> was <HI>naturâ Ho∣mo, gratiâ Christianus, abundantiore gratiâ vnus idem{que} primus Apostolus. He was by nature,</HI> saith <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Austin, but a man, by grace a Christian man, by abundant grace not only one, but a cheife Apostle.</HI> He was the first, that <HI>confessed Christ</HI> to bee <HI>consubstantiall</HI> with his Father; he was the first, that <HI>preacht Christ;</HI> the first, that <HI>bapti∣zeà</HI> in his name; and stil the forwardst man, in the ex∣ecution of his <HI>Apostoli{que}</HI> function. He was with <HI>Christ,</HI> whil'st he liu'd on earth most familiar &amp; conversant, with his secret counsailes best acquainted, most ob∣servant
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
of his words and precepts: and because, saith <HI>Cyprian, vnit as ab exordio dependet,</HI> to preserue order &amp; to <HI>avoid schisme</HI> amongst the <HI>guides</HI> of the <HI>Church,</HI> he was by <HI>Christ</HI> set <HI>before</HI> the rest, vnto whom all the rest of the same ranke and order in religious mat∣ters of importāce should haue recourse, as to a persō more honorable then the rest. <HI>Iohn</HI> indeed was that Apostle, whom <HI>Christ</HI> lou'd aboue the rest; but <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Pe∣ter</HI> was he, that lou'd <HI>Christ,</HI> more then <HI>Iohn</HI> or any of the Apostles. <HI>Ille melior qui plus diligit Christum; il∣lefeiicior, quem plus diligit Christus.</HI> In that <HI>S. Iohn</HI> was best belou'd of <HI>Christ,</HI> he was the happier man; but in that <HI>S. Peter</HI> lou'd <HI>Christ</HI> better then they all, he was the better man. <HI>Better,</HI> not in <HI>commission,</HI> but in <HI>place,</HI> and <HI>order;</HI> he was <HI>before</HI> him or the rest, not <HI>aboue</HI> him or any of the rest; he was a chiefe <HI>Pecre</HI> of the Apo∣stles, not their <HI>Prince;</HI> he was in order their <HI>Superiour,</HI> not their <HI>Soueraigne;</HI> he had a <HI>Primacy</HI> amongst them not a <HI>Supremacy</HI> ouer them; he was not <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, but <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, not a <HI>prince</HI> of the <HI>Apostles,</HI> but a <HI>fellow Elder,</HI> as he himselfe termes himselfe, 1. <HI>Pet.</HI> 5. 1.</P>
<P>There is, saith <HI>Almaine</HI> (in his <HI>Tracte de Potestate Ecclesiasticâ) a double Primacy;</HI> there is <HI>Primatus Ordi∣nis,</HI> and <HI>Primatus Iurisdictionis,</HI> a Primacy of <HI>Order,</HI> &amp; a Primacy of <HI>Power</HI> and <HI>Iurisdictiō;</HI> the former is pro∣perly <HI>Primatus,</HI> the other <HI>Potestas.</HI> The first wee yeeld vnto <HI>Peter,</HI> &amp; giue him <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the first <HI>place,</HI> the first and best <HI>imployment,</HI> the <HI>sitting</HI> and <HI>speaking</HI> first, the <HI>moderation</HI> &amp; direction of other mens spee∣ches,
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
the <HI>publishing</HI> and pronouncing of the <HI>Conclusi∣on</HI> agreed vpon by the <HI>Synode</HI> of the Apostles: but <HI>Primatum Potestatis,</HI> a <HI>power</HI> to <HI>doe</HI> any <HI>ministeriall Act,</HI> which another hath not, a <HI>power</HI> to <HI>restraine</HI> o∣thers in the performance of their <HI>Acts</HI> of <HI>Ministery,</HI> such a <HI>Primacy</HI> wee denie vnto <HI>Peter;</HI> th' Apostles all being, (as <HI>Cyprian</HI> saith) <HI>pari consortio praediti Potesta∣tis,</HI> all ioynt Commissioners endued with equal pow∣er. This <HI>Primacy</HI> of <HI>Order,</HI> which wee ascribe vnto <HI>Pe∣ter,</HI> is the originall of all the <HI>Superioritie,</HI> that <HI>Arch∣bishops</HI> &amp; <HI>Metropolitans</HI> haue over the <HI>Bishops</HI> of their <HI>Provinces;</HI> and the foundation, vpon which is built all the fabricke of Ecclesiasticke discipline, whereby the vnitie of the <HI>Church</HI> at this day remaines preser∣ved.</P>
<P>If I were to dispute with a <HI>Papist,</HI> I would not be so troublesome vnto him, as to cause him to proue that <HI>Peter was</HI> ever <HI>at Rome,</HI> that hee <HI>sate Bishop there,</HI> that he <HI>died there,</HI> or that the <HI>Pope is his lineall Succes∣sour,</HI> (which some of our <HI>Divines</HI> haue denied; and to proue them all, it is impossible) but yeelding that, yet <HI>tanquam datum, non concessum,</HI> nothing thence can be inferd, for the support of the <HI>Romane Suprema∣cie,</HI> more then may be concluded for the <HI>Sea</HI> of <HI>Anti∣och,</HI> or the <HI>Bishop</HI> of <HI>Ierusalem.</HI> For at <HI>Antioch Peter</HI> first sate <HI>Bishop,</HI> &amp; afterwards gouerned it by <HI>Evodi∣us;</HI> at <HI>Antioch</HI> the Professours of the Gospell were first called <HI>Christians,</HI> and the place <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>the City of God.</HI> And if <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Peter's</HI> death, or Martyrdome, could adde such <HI>Soveraigntie</HI> to the place, where hee <HI>died;</HI>
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
then much juster claime may be laide to this <HI>Supre¦macie</HI> by the <HI>Bishop</HI> of <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> because <HI>Christ</HI> the great Pastor and <HI>Bishop of our soules</HI> did there suffer death for the Redemption of vniversall man. But nor the one, nor the other, is a sufficient foundation to raise vp this Edifice of the <HI>Popish Hierarchie.</HI> The <HI>Cō∣mission</HI> given to <HI>Peter</HI> was not <HI>singular,</HI> but to others <HI>common</HI> with him: the rest of the Apostles were au∣thorized, as well as he, and that immediately from <HI>Christ;</HI> their preheminence of <HI>binding</HI> and <HI>loosing</HI> as ample; and as <HI>Christ</HI> was sent by his Father, so sent he them, &amp; what he said to one, he said to all, <HI>Pasce oves, Feed my sheepe.</HI> For it was a thing in the Evangelicall story with <HI>Christ</HI> vsual, sometimes to direct his speech to one private man, and no more, as <HI>Arise and walke, Lazarus come forth;</HI> sometimes to direct his speech to one in the person of al, as <HI>Vade &amp; noli ampliùs peccare,</HI> Goe and sinne no more, and to <HI>Peter, Pasce oves; Nam quod dicitur Petro, dicitur omnibus; What was said to Pe∣ter, was said to all the Apostles,</HI> saith <HI>Austin, cap.</HI> 30. <HI>de Agone Christiano.</HI> Now the reasons, why Christ dire∣cted his speech to <HI>Peter</HI> in the behalfe of them all, were these; <HI>vel quia aetate senior, vel charitate ardenti∣or, velne videretur reliquis abiectior, quia negaver at Christum,</HI> saith <HI>Occham lib.</HI> 4. <HI>Dial.</HI> 1. <HI>Tract.</HI> 3. <HI>part. c.</HI> 3. Either because he was more <HI>ancient,</HI> or in <HI>charitie</HI> more <HI>ardent,</HI> then the rest, or else lest he should <HI>seeme</HI> to bee <HI>despised</HI> for the <HI>denyall</HI> of his <HI>Master.</HI> But the <HI>Pope</HI> (the pretended Successour of this <HI>Peter)</HI> will not content himselfe with this <HI>Prioritie;</HI> he will not only
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
haue a <HI>Cheiftie</HI> of <HI>Order,</HI> but of command, and <HI>Power:</HI> and because (in all likelyhood) <HI>Christ</HI> would haue his <HI>Church</HI> gouerned in the best forme of regiment that is, and that of all States the <HI>Monarchie</HI> is best; hence <HI>Sanders,</HI> and after him <HI>Bellarmine</HI> lay it downe for a <HI>Praecognitum,</HI> that the <HI>Government</HI> of the <HI>Church</HI> must needs be <HI>Monarchicall;</HI> that <HI>this</HI> was <HI>committed</HI> vnto <HI>Peter,</HI> and <HI>continued</HI> in his <HI>Successours;</HI> whereby his <HI>Power</HI> is become <HI>illimited,</HI> his <HI>Iudgement infallible,</HI> and hee an <HI>Vniversall Bishop,</HI> whose <HI>Diocese</HI> is the whole <HI>World.</HI> The truth of this <HI>State-Maxime,</HI> on which they build the <HI>Pope</HI> so high a <HI>Throne,</HI> I will not dispute; but keepe my selfe within the sphaere of mine owne Pro∣fession; and, for an vncontroll'd Answere to them all, adde that limitation, which I finde in the fore-cited <HI>Occham</HI> (3. <HI>Part. Dial. l.</HI> 3. <HI>Tr.</HI> 1. <HI>c.</HI> 30.) <HI>Status Monarchicus est omnium optimus populo simul moranti, non autem v∣ni populo comprehendenti plures populos locis distantibus.</HI> That Government is best, where one beares Sove∣raigntie, not many, but so, that it be over but one na∣tion, &amp; not manie, or if over many, yet not farre dis∣joyned. Which limitatiō of <HI>Occham's</HI> I find strength∣ned with the authoritie of great S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Austin (lib.</HI> 4. <HI>de Civ. D. c.</HI> 15.) <HI>Feliciores essent res humanae, si omnia reg∣na essent parva, &amp; concordi vicinitate laetantia.</HI> The <HI>estate</HI> of <HI>worldly</HI> things would bee much <HI>more happy,</HI> if the whole <HI>world</HI> were <HI>divided</HI> out into <HI>small King∣domes,</HI> then if <HI>all</HI> should be <HI>sway'd</HI> by <HI>one supreme Com∣mander. That forme</HI> therefore of <HI>Gouernement</HI> is not so expedient for the <HI>whole,</HI> as for each <HI>part,</HI> for large
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
and disioyned Circuits, as for narrow bounds: and as it is impossible for <HI>one</HI> temporall <HI>Monarch</HI> to weeld the <HI>Empire</HI> of the <HI>whole world,</HI> either long, or well, so much more impossible it is for <HI>one</HI> man to manage <HI>all Ecclesiastique affaires</HI> and dispatch the weighty busi∣nesses of the <HI>Vniversall Church.</HI> Better therefore were it for <HI>Peter,</HI> or his <HI>Successours,</HI> to bee (as S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Austin</HI> tearmes him <HI>Tract.</HI> 13. <HI>in Ioh.) Oculus in corpore,</HI> an <HI>Eye</HI> of the Church, then to be so vast a <HI>Head</HI> of a body so farre dissevered: lest that bee applied vnto him in the <HI>Comedy, Hic quidem fungino genere est, capite se totum tegit;</HI> The <HI>Church</HI> of <HI>Rome</HI> is become a <HI>mushrome,</HI> or like a Toad-stoole, <HI>all Head,</HI> and no bodie.</P>
<P>Yet hath the sweet desire of Ambition so enchan∣ted the <HI>Chaire</HI> of the <HI>Scarlet Whore,</HI> that rather, then the <HI>Pope</HI> will loose this eminent <HI>Soveraigntie</HI> and command, he will become the Patrone and maintai∣ner of most enormous offenders and their offences, thereby to procure support of his <HI>Antichristian Primacy.</HI> For the best stake in the Pope's hedge is his owne <HI>Authority,</HI> to maintaine his owne <HI>Infallibilitie,</HI> and is now become stript of all, saue the naked <HI>De∣crees</HI> of <HI>Canonists,</HI> and the <HI>Dreames</HI> of wel-fed <HI>Monks:</HI> to which had he not of late annexed an omnipotent <HI>Power</HI> of <HI>Binding,</HI> and <HI>Loosing,</HI> of <HI>Approuing,</HI> and <HI>Dis∣pensing</HI> with things repugnant to all <HI>Laws</HI> as wel Na∣turall as Divine; I might by way of prediction say of the <HI>Pope's Arrogancie,</HI> that, which was said to the <HI>Tro∣ians</HI> of the <HI>Grecian</HI> Horse,<HI>—haec in vestros fabricata est Machina muros;</HI> The <HI>Pope's Supremacy</HI> had long since
<PB N="9" REF="7"/>
beene the <HI>destruction</HI> of <HI>him,</HI> his <HI>Sea,</HI> and <HI>City.</HI> Hee is but a child and ignorant in the <HI>Histories</HI> of his owne times, that doth not know, that the cheefest proppe, whereon the <HI>Pope</HI> stands, and at this houre is sustai∣ned, is his correspondency with the <HI>Spanish King,</HI> and the <HI>House</HI> of <HI>Austria;</HI> which hee first procured and now maintaineth by his <HI>dispensing</HI> and warranting of his <HI>incestuous</HI> and <HI>vnlawfull Mariages.</HI> So that if the <HI>Spaniard</HI> should revolt from the Sea of <HI>Rome,</HI> the <HI>Le∣gitimation</HI> of his <HI>Successours</HI> would be questioned &amp; his <HI>Signiories</HI> endangered. Which is the only reason of the consistencie of the <HI>Papacie,</HI> claimed vnder the title of S. <HI>Peter,</HI> which otherwise had ere this not beene at all, or else reduced into a narrowe Diocese.</P>
<P><HI>Opened his mouth] S. Peter</HI> spake not rashly, or with∣out meditation making his words to <HI>breake</HI> the <HI>pri∣son</HI> of his <HI>lips,</HI> before the <HI>doore</HI> of his mouth was <HI>ope∣ned;</HI> but he taketh the <HI>keyes</HI> of knowledge and <HI>Medita∣tion</HI> in hand, and therewith <HI>opened his mouth,</HI> and <HI>then</HI> spake. <HI>When I mused</HI> (saith <HI>David) there was a fire kind∣led, and then I spake.</HI> What was this <HI>Musing,</HI> but his <HI>Meditation?</HI> What was this <HI>fire,</HI> but the <HI>light</HI> of <HI>God's Spirit?</HI> What was the <HI>kindling</HI> therof, but the <HI>inflam∣mation</HI> of his <HI>affections?</HI> that so he might speake <HI>Igni∣ta Dei eloquia,</HI> with a tongue <HI>toucht</HI> with a <HI>cole</HI> of <HI>Me∣ditation</HI> from Gods holy <HI>Altar.</HI></P>
<P>For by <HI>opening</HI> of the <HI>mouth</HI> in this place is not to be vnderstood a bare dissevering of the lips, but a <HI>pre∣paration</HI> of the <HI>heart,</HI> out of the abundance of which the tongue should speake, and is indeed a <HI>pleonasme,</HI>
<PB N="10" REF="8"/>
or redūdancy of the <HI>Hebrew</HI> tongue, signifying to be∣gin to speak after long silence with Religiō; &amp; in this sense our <HI>Church Liturgy</HI> prayeth, <HI>O Lord open thou our Lips.</HI> So that, as <HI>Moses</HI> first spake with God, before he spake to the people: so <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Peter</HI> first speaketh with God's Spirit by Meditation, before hee delivered to <HI>Cornelius</HI> this <HI>Sermon,</HI> which is the subject of my Discourse. The greatest perfection of a man is his <HI>Wisedome,</HI> and the best herald to proclaime his wise∣dome is his <HI>Speech,</HI> and the richest treasure to adorne his speach is <HI>Meditation. Meditatio est quasi mentis ditatio,</HI> (saith <HI>Bernard)</HI> it is the enriching of the soule with the treasures of Wisedome: nay it is the chew∣ing of the food of the Soule, which maketh it taste sweeter in the mouth, &amp; digest better in the stomack; and you know those beasts, that <HI>chewed</HI> not <HI>the cudde,</HI> are reckoned among the <HI>vncleane beasts</HI> in the <HI>Arke.</HI> I know no greater difference betweene a wise man and a foole, then that one speaketh all things rashly, the other all things maturely and advisedly: the one hath his <HI>tongue in his heart,</HI> the other hath <HI>his heart in his tongue,</HI> as the <HI>Wise man</HI> speaketh. For want of which serious consideration, of the Majestie of the person, <HI>of whom</HI> they speake, and of the holynes of the place, <HI>wherein</HI> they speake; many bold and vnworthy speakers, contrary to the Law both of God and the <HI>Church,</HI> start vp into the Pulpit, and being dull and heavy bodies, contrary to the Law of Nature, they ascend vp to fill a vacuitie. These empty vessels make the greatest sound in many places of this City; and
<PB N="11" REF="8"/>
like Vessels fill'd with new wine, they wil rather break then not vent, though it be but their owne <HI>Emptines</HI> and <HI>Ignorance;</HI> their words are full of winde, and like <HI>Aeolus Windes,</HI></P>
<Q>Quâ data porta ruunt, &amp; turbas turbine perflant.</Q>
<P>Their mouth, like the Cocke of a Conduit-pipe, if it be but once opened, will run out two Howre-glas∣ses, and that twise or thrise a weeke. Before <HI>Ezechiel</HI> could haue his Commission to speake to the people, he was enioined, not to touch, to open, or to put in∣to his mouth, but to <HI>eate the roule,</HI> Ezech. 3. 1. and to <HI>receiue</HI> the <HI>wordes</HI> into his <HI>heart, Ezech.</HI> 3. 10; but these men never doe so much as <HI>touch</HI> the <HI>Roule,</HI> or o∣pen the booke. They ran from the <HI>Seminaries</HI> of <HI>lear∣ning,</HI> like Lapwings from their nests, with their shels vpon their heads: the portion of learning they brought with them was like the bread &amp; wine of the <HI>Gibeonites; their bread was hot that day they departed, &amp; therefore it was moulded and dry; &amp; their bottels because they were new, were rent, Iosh.</HI> 9. 13. These men need ne∣ver feare to bee taken for <HI>Mercury</HI> with <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Paule,</HI> be∣cause they seeke to vent their wares by number, ne∣ver weighing them. Of these too hasty Pulpit men <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Bernard</HI> saith wittyly, <HI>Quia nimis properè, minùs pro∣sperè rem peragunt.</HI></P>
<P>When the <HI>Materiall Temple</HI> was built, there was not so much as the <HI>noise of a hammer heard</HI> there, all things were so prepared before: but in the building of the <HI>Immateriall Temple</HI> of God, and edifying of mens soules in the faith of <HI>Christ, whose Temples we are,</HI> there
<PB N="17" REF="9"/>
is oft times amongst these extemporary preachers, (who never <HI>prepare</HI> what to speake, but onely to <HI>open</HI> the mouth and <HI>speake)</HI> such a stammering and <HI>hamme∣ring</HI> of words, such a rude noise of jarrings in sense, and construction; that I hold it farre better for the <HI>Church</HI> they shoulde looke grauely and say nothing, then make so many shallow, frivolous, inconse∣quent discourses. And so I come from his Maner of speech, to his asseveration; which is, <HI>In truth.]</HI></P>
<P>He was the Legate of <HI>the God of truth,</HI> the Apostle of him, in whose <HI>mouth</HI> there was <HI>found no guile;</HI> and being by <HI>Cornelius</HI> required to speak only that which God had commanded, (as it is in the verse before my text) he could not but speake <HI>the truth;</HI> and therefore doth adorne the forefront of his speech with this <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Of a truth.</HI> This is the insoluble bond of <HI>A∣mity,</HI> the safest refuge of <HI>Innocency,</HI> the surest warrant of <HI>Fidelity,</HI> the strongest sinew of <HI>humane Societie,</HI> the authenticall evidence of <HI>Iustice,</HI> the ensigne of <HI>Chri∣stianity,</HI> the soveraigne influence of God, nay it is God himselfe, for <HI>God is truth.</HI></P>
<P>Detestable therefore and more then Diabolicall is their doctrine and practise, who straine, and weaken this <HI>sinew,</HI> which holdeth peace and society together; who cancell this <HI>bond,</HI> which being made in earth is registred in the high court of heaven, subscribed and signed by God himselfe; who either vntie this ever∣lasting knot of truth by cunning <HI>Aequivocation,</HI> or cut it asunder by <HI>Papall Dispensation.</HI> How can wee better argue, that the <HI>Pope</HI> is not <HI>Peters</HI> Successour, at
<PB N="13" REF="9"/>
least in doctrine, then by vrging this one argument here in my text? <HI>Peter</HI> beginnes his Plat-forme of speech, <HI>Of a truth:</HI> but the <HI>Pope</HI> adviseth his Disciples oft times in their speech to vse a <HI>Mentall Reservation,</HI> which is in plaine tearmes <HI>a Lye;</HI> and so to begin their speech, not with S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Peter, Of a truth,</HI> but <HI>Of a lye.</HI> How could wee demonstrate the <HI>Pope</HI> to bee the man that exalteth himselfe aboue all that is called God, if hee sate not in the Temple of God, as Iudge of God's law, nay as <HI>God</HI> of GOD himselfe; whose commands he controles, by <HI>adding</HI> to, <HI>taking</HI> from, and <HI>dispensing</HI> with them. Far be it therefore from vs to hold with him that breakes with God himselfe; to joine with them in truth of doctrine, that maintaine <HI>Equivoca∣ting</HI> and forswearing; to partake of that <HI>Religion,</HI> which taketh away all religious obligation. Is that the faith of a <HI>Christian,</HI> which <HI>alloweth,</HI> and in some cases <HI>commendeth Perfidio usnesse,</HI> and vnnaturall <HI>trea∣sons?</HI> Can their doctrine be <HI>truth, qui dogmatizant mendacium,</HI> who make an <HI>equivocating lye</HI> a doctrine, and that they may verifie this their lye, belie the truth it selfe, and make IESVS himselfe (I tremble to speake it) to become a <HI>Iesuite?</HI> teaching by many ar∣guments, that <HI>Christ</HI> himselfe vsed this kinde of <HI>Equi∣vocation,</HI> both vnto the <HI>High Prtest,</HI> and his Disciples, and that all his speeches were not like vnto this of <HI>Peter's, Of a truth.</HI></P>
<Q>Tantum relligio potuit suadere malorum?</Q>
<P>Of all beasts we haue those in greatest detestatiō, which devour their own young. What are our <HI>Words</HI>
<PB N="14" REF="10"/>
&amp; <HI>Promises,</HI> what are our <HI>Oaths,</HI> &amp; <HI>Vowes,</HI> but the issue of our mind, which they that resume, and recall, what doe they else, but devoure and eate their owne of∣spring? The first that brake this bond <HI>of truth</HI> in earth was the <HI>Divell</HI> Gē. 3. whose scholers they shew themselues, who teach, that <HI>Oathes, Vowes,</HI> and <HI>Promi∣ses</HI> of <HI>truth</HI> are <HI>better broken then kept with Heretikes,</HI> &amp; that they may <HI>lawfully</HI> violate them at their plea∣sure; as <HI>Iulius</HI> 2. was not ashamed openly to pro∣fesse, <HI>fides danda omnibus, servanda nemini.</HI> And of this profession was <HI>Alex.</HI> 6. and his son <HI>Borgias,</HI> of whom it is reported that the one would never speake what he meant to doe, nor the other ever doe, what hee spake. These were two of the greatest mōsters which nature ever yet produced. For what monster can there be in nature more prodigious, then a Liar, or E∣quivocator, whose speech is not <HI>Of a truth?</HI> All other creatures in the world bring forth the same issue, which they conceaue; but a <HI>Lyar,</HI> or <HI>Equivocator</HI> brin∣geth forth of his mouth, that which hee conceaueth not, or rather a contrary issue to that which he con∣ceaueth. He <HI>conceaueth,</HI> or rather <HI>concealeth,</HI> the truth, and bringeth forth a <HI>lye,</HI> and so the issue of his mouth is contrary to the conception of his heart. The hea∣then Philosopher <HI>Zeno</HI> rather then hee would be the Father to beger, or suffer his tongue to bee the Mo∣ther to bring forth such a monster, bit of his tongue, and spit it in the face of the king of <HI>Cypres,</HI> who had a long time tortured him to tell a Lie. <HI>Pliny</HI> in his 37. <HI>Booke of Naturall History</HI> reporteth, that if a perjured
<PB N="15" REF="10"/>
person dip hand or foot into the river <HI>Olachas</HI> in <HI>Bi∣thynia,</HI> hee feeleth as great torments, as if he were throwne into a fornace of melting lead. And <HI>Solinus</HI> seconds this relation with the like of a river in <HI>Sardi∣nia, Periuros furto facto, quos lumine coecat.</HI></P>
<P>And <HI>Philostratus</HI> telleth as strange a miracle of a ri∣ver neere <HI>Tyara;</HI> in which, if a perfidious person, that hath forsworne himselfe, doe but bath, the water sin∣keth into all parts of his body, and breedeth an incu∣rable dropsie. But alas! what is <HI>Olachas</HI> in <HI>Bithynia,</HI> or any river in the earth, to that <HI>River of Brimstone</HI> in hel which boyles with a continuall fire, and much wood? In which, without long and bitter repentance they shall boyle for ever, who make no conscience of ma∣king a lye, &amp; breaking the truth. Great surely are the tortures, which <HI>Dives,</HI> and with him all the damned doe, and must suffer in hell; yet no part of <HI>Dives</HI> body was so much tortured, as his <HI>Tongue.</HI> He was prowd, and clad in fine linnen; hee was a Glutton, and fared deliciously every day, and therefore in all likelyhood a wanton too, <HI>Nam epulas comitatur voluptas;</HI> he was vncharitable to the poore, and denied <HI>Lazarus</HI> the crums that fell from his table: yet none of these sins were punished so severely as the sins hee committed with his <HI>tongue. Ex poena indicat culpā, quia illud mem∣brum maximè omniū puniebatur;</HI> they are S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Gregories</HI> words <HI>l.</HI> 1. <HI>Mor. c.</HI> 5. and may teach vs to put a watche before our lips, &amp; to make a conscience of breaking the truth, which should be the cognizance of euery <HI>Christiā</HI> mans speech; as here it is placed in the fronti∣spice
<PB N="16" REF="11"/>
of S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Peters, Of a truth.</HI></P>
<P><HI>I Perceaue]</HI> S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Peter</HI> was not till this time ignorant of God's <HI>vnpartiall Iustice</HI> to vniversal man; but now he doth see that truth cōfirmed in <HI>particulars,</HI> which before he knewe in <HI>generall;</HI> hee knewe it before, and now his knowledge was by a sensible probatiō more confirmed. <HI>Iob</HI> in his prosperity knewe, that God would not punish the innocent, yet hee would never acknowledge so much, till he had a <HI>sensible experience</HI> of it, <HI>Iob,</HI> 9. 28. The sincere affection, and filiall obe∣dience of <HI>Abraham</HI> to God, could not bee hid from God himselfe, yet there was no <HI>evidence</HI> of it expres∣sed by God, till he refused not to sacrifice his Sonne. <HI>Gen.</HI> 22. 12. And although the <HI>Apostle</HI> before this time had a <HI>notion</HI> of this truth, which here hee preacheth; yet a <HI>manifest &amp; experimentall overture</HI> he never lear∣ned, till he <HI>saw</HI> the gate of the <HI>Church</HI> now opened to the <HI>Gentiles</HI> also. The Mistresse of truth is <HI>Experiēce,</HI> &amp; the best knowledge hath it's <HI>assurance</HI> frō <HI>particulars.</HI> By a <HI>Generall</HI> knowledge we <HI>know,</HI> as he that had bin <HI>blind</HI> saw, <HI>confusedly, Men like trees:</HI> but by a <HI>collection</HI> of <HI>Particulars</HI> which are obvious to the <HI>sense</HI> (especi∣ally in matters practike, &amp; morall) our mind rests as∣sured without hesitation. The one I may call <HI>Notitia,</HI> th' other <HI>Fiducia,</HI> the one resides in the <HI>vnderstanding</HI> th' other in the <HI>will,</HI> th' one is <HI>Theoricall,</HI> th' other <HI>Pra∣cticall,</HI> the one consists in <HI>General notions,</HI> the other in <HI>Particular Experiments;</HI> the one is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the other <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, by the one wee may knowe <HI>Good</HI> from <HI>Bad,</HI> by the other <HI>Better</HI> from <HI>Good.</HI> In the knowledge there∣fore
<PB N="17" REF="11"/>
of divine verities we must not cōtent our selues with the <HI>first operations</HI> of the <HI>Spirit,</HI> which are but <HI>generall,</HI> but we must striue for particular directions, and assurances; we must not only haue our harts dis∣posed, but informed; not only ploughed vp, but sow∣en. For as all other Sciences and Professions must needs savour of much rawnesse and imperfection, if they be studied only in passage, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, to gaine popular estimation, or to content the state in which we liue: So, &amp; much more, is it with religious know∣ledge, if a man professe it only with relation, and fa∣shion <HI>superficially,</HI> not <HI>syncerely,</HI> and exactly.</P>
<P>For though that a <HI>weake faith</HI> and <HI>confused know∣ledge</HI> of Divine things be of that admirable and wor∣king nature, that the very least corne and graine of it, is able to effect the salvation of him in whom it is, &amp; to lift him vp to heaven, were he as grosse and heavy as a mountaine: yet neverthelesse this must not con∣tent a <HI>Christian man;</HI> but hee must make a continuall progresse from faith to faith, from knowledge to knowledge, till at length he be not only able <HI>in grosse</HI> to knowe, but <HI>evidently</HI> to <HI>perceaue</HI> the mysteries of religion and properties of God himselfe; whereof this is one, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, that hee is <HI>No accep∣ter of persons.]</HI></P>
<P>God is an agent infinite, whose will is nothing else, but <HI>Deus volens,</HI> as S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Austin</HI> saith, <HI>essentially God himselfe,</HI> without whom there is no mouing or effi∣cient cause of his operations: but his <HI>will</HI> is a <HI>law</HI> to himselfe, and to all things else whatsoever, &amp; the on∣ly
<PB N="18" REF="12"/>
cause of <HI>what,</HI> and <HI>why</HI> he worketh. It was his plea∣sure to create this goodly fabricke of the world wee see in <HI>time,</HI> and not before. It was his pleasure to per∣mit the lapse of the first created man, and his posteri∣tie, and being fallen, to sequester out of the corrupt∣ed masse some few, to bee the inheritors of his king∣dome, and to leaue the major part in their deserved perdition. Beyond his pleasure to make a <HI>Quaere</HI> of his actions were saucie curiositie, and yet to thinke his <HI>will</HI> to be without reason were indigne blasphe∣my. It is not the prescience of faith, or prevision of workes, that can moue the will of God, to choose one, and refuse the other, because they are not, (saith <HI>Aquinas part.</HI> 1. <HI>q.</HI> 23. <HI>a.</HI> 4.) the cause, but the effects of Gods loue. <HI>Praedestinatio est gratiae praeparatio, gratia verò praedestinationis effectus. Aug. c.</HI> 10. <HI>de praedestina∣tione sanctorū.</HI> Predestinatiō is the harbinger of grace and grace the effect of Gods loue. He first created all things, and then saw they were good: the foresight of their goodnesse was no inducement to the worke of their creation, but his creation gaue them this e∣loge, <HI>Quaecun{que} fecit erant valdè bona.</HI> God chooseth none, because they are good, but men are good, be∣cause they are chosen. <HI>Gratia Dei non invenit eligēdos, sed facit.</HI> Therefore S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Paul</HI> (saith <HI>Austin)</HI> compared together the sonnes of <HI>Isaac,</HI> twins, <HI>vno etiam concu∣bitu fusos in vtero,</HI> both yet vnborne, neither of them hauing done well or ill; <HI>Quod referendum est</HI> (saith the same <HI>Father) non ad dispensatoris iniustitiam, sed ad do∣nantis misericordiam;</HI> which wee must not impute to
<PB N="19" REF="12"/>
Gods <HI>Iniustice,</HI> or partialitie, but to his <HI>good will and pleasure:</HI> which must be the <HI>last resolution of our inqui∣ries;</HI> and whatsoever the event is, we must still say, as our Saviour did, <HI>Mat.</HI> 11. 25. <HI>Naepater, quia sic placuit tibi;</HI> Even so father, for it seemed good in thy sight. Could the master of the vineyard say, <HI>Annon possum facere de meo, quod volo?</HI> Is it not lawfull for me to doe with my owne, what I will? And shall wee deny to God the supreme cause of all things, the free dispo∣sition of any thing after his <HI>pleasure?</HI> Whose <HI>will</HI> is not only <HI>iust</HI> and <HI>full of equitie,</HI> but, as S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Basil</HI> calls it, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the very oracle and rule of iustice, who doth <HI>make</HI> things iust and right, because he <HI>wils</HI> them. There is no man reiected by God without iust cause and demerit, nor any saved but by his mercy &amp; free <HI>pleasure.</HI> Now if it be asked, why God should thus be an <HI>accepter of persōs,</HI> &amp; affoord this mercy to some, and not to all: we must with a <HI>religious ignorance</HI> cō∣tent our selues, and stand amazed at the secret and in∣explicable greatnesse of God, and satisfie our selues with this, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, it was his pleasure so to dispose of his kingdome. This is the <HI>Nonvltrà,</HI> be∣yond which wee must not wade, but hither being come, wee must make a <HI>stand,</HI> and with the blessed <HI>Apostle</HI> cry out, <HI>O altitudo divitiarum! O the depth of the riches both of the wisdome and knowledge of God! how vnsearchable are his iudgements, and his waies past fin∣ding out! Rom.</HI> 11. 33.</P>
<P>But here we may not be so injurious to the <HI>Deitie,</HI> as to conceaue God in his Decrees to be tyrannicall, as to say,
<PB N="20" REF="13"/>
<Q>Sic volo, sic iubeo, stat pro ratione voluntas;</Q>
or that the will of God is moued <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, without rea∣son: for although neither beautie of face, feature of body, honourable descent, wisdome, and the endow∣ments of the mind, or any thing else without God, cā moue his will to Election, or make him to <HI>accept</HI> of one <HI>person</HI> before another; yet is there never wan∣ting a most <HI>iust cause,</HI> and <HI>sufficient reason</HI> of his pur∣poses and <HI>Decrees.</HI> For although God worketh all things according to his <HI>will and pleasure;</HI> yet whatsoe∣ver he doth, he doth it <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> with <HI>counsell</HI> and wise resolution. <HI>Eph.</HI> 1. 11. <HI>God doth order all things sweetly and profitably. Sap.</HI> 8. 1. <HI>Omnia fecisti in sapientiâ Domi∣ne.</HI> In wisdome hast thou done all thy workes ô God, Ps. 104. 24. And shall wee thinke that this wise-crea∣ting God, who made all things for his glory, should without some proper reason determine of any thing which hee hath made? The doctrine therefore of S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Peter</HI> in my <HI>Text</HI> remaines still true, &amp; as firme as hea∣ven, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>God is no accepter of persons:</HI> because when hee determineth any thing hee hath a sufficient reason, besides his <HI>VVill</HI> and <HI>Pleasure</HI> to doe what he doth. Which reason (saith the divine <HI>Author</HI> of the <HI>Ecclesiastical Policie) because we are not worthy or, able to apprehend, we must humbly &amp; meckely adore.</HI> This secret and vnknown reason of Gods purposes is like himselfe, <HI>Eternall,</HI> before the foundations of the world were layd, and hath so effectually moved his <HI>VVill,</HI> that now it can admit of no change or variati∣on. That which God hath decreed, must still bee like
<PB N="21" REF="13"/>
God, without change, who can as well deny himselfe to be God, as not performe, what hee hath defined. Whom he loues, he loues vnto the end; &amp; to whom he giues the earnest of his spirit, they haue a <HI>continual feeling</HI> in some measure <HI>more or lesse,</HI> of his gracious presence. For the loue of God, it is not <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> va∣riable like the gifts of temporall men, which may bee granted to day and reversed to morrow, with a <HI>Non obstante priore concessione:</HI> but the loue of God and the gifts of his holy Spirit they are <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, and stand for ever without change, <HI>Rom.</HI> 11. 29. He is <HI>Triumpha∣tor Israëlis,</HI> the glory and strength of <HI>Israel,</HI> and will neither lie nor repent, nor yet can hee in the meane time be tearmed injurious to any, or <HI>an accepter of persons</HI> (as <HI>Pelagius</HI> prophanely somtime did object:) because God in giuing his grace to some and denying it to others doth not proceed (sairh <HI>Alex-Hales) iuxta dignitatem humanam, sed secundùm dignationem divi∣nam,</HI> it is a donation of bounty, not a dotation accor∣ding to the rules of Iustice. As God is in heaven, so should Gods Vicegerents bee in earth; as they <HI>sit</HI> in his <HI>chaire,</HI> so should they <HI>walke</HI> in his <HI>paths</HI> of Iustice. They should without <HI>respect of persons,</HI> as well heare the cause of poore <HI>Bartimaeus,</HI> as rich <HI>Zachaeus,</HI> as well the small, as the great, <HI>Deut.</HI> 1. 17. Their eies must al∣waies be shut, that they be not drawn by favour, their eares alwaies open, that they may heare both parties indifferently, &amp; their hands must be fast clinched vp, least otherwise they be corrupted with bribes, <HI>quae ex∣coecant prudentes, &amp; subvertunt verba iustorum,</HI> which
<PB N="22" REF="14"/>
blind the wise, and subvert the words of the righte∣ous, <HI>Exod.</HI> 23. 8. It was a provident law enacted in the time of <HI>Rich.</HI> 2. and afterwardes revived in the daies of the last <HI>Henry</HI> (and woulde God till this day it had still beene continued without violation) that no Iustice of Assize should ride his <HI>Circuit</HI> in that coun∣try, where either he was <HI>borne,</HI> or did <HI>liue:</HI> that being vnknowne to all, they might <HI>accept</HI> of the <HI>persons</HI> of none, but be indifferent vnto al; that so they might the more freely administer justice, and the more liue∣ly represent him, whose deputy Lieutenants they are; in being merciful, as he is <HI>mercifull, holy,</HI> as he is holie, no respecters of persons, because with <HI>God</HI> there <HI>is no respect of persons.</HI></P>
<P><HI>But in every nation] Cornelius</HI> an alien from the cō∣mon wealth of <HI>Israel</HI> is <HI>accepted</HI> with God, as well as <HI>Peter</HI> borne among God's <HI>owne people,</HI> and trained vp in Christs <HI>owne schoole;</HI> the <HI>poore Leper</HI> a Iew, as well as the <HI>rich Centurion</HI> that built his nation a Syna∣gogue; as well <HI>old Simeon</HI> in the temple, as <HI>young Iohn</HI> in the womb; as wel those that watcht him vnder the Crosse, as the Theefe that hung with him on the Crosse: for in <HI>Christ</HI> there is neither <HI>Iew</HI> nor <HI>Grecian,</HI> neither <HI>bond</HI> nor <HI>free, Gal.</HI> 3. 28. but he that is Lord o∣ver all, is rich vnto all, not onely to <HI>some of all nations,</HI> but <HI>to all of all</HI> nations, that <HI>feare him and worke righte∣ousnes.</HI> And if any man be not accepted of him, the fault is not in the sufficiencie of God's grace, but in the defect of efficiencie in vs. Wherevpon saith <HI>Cal∣vine Com. in</HI> 10. <HI>Act. v.</HI> 33. the words before my text,
<PB N="23" REF="14"/>
<HI>Maceriâ i am dirutâ, Deus aequali amore omnes gentes complexus est;</HI> the partition Wall being now broken downe, God embraceth all nations with an equall loue. For the will of God toward, mankinde is (if I may so speake) <HI>Orbicular,</HI> environing vniversall man, with Mercies and Iudgements, with Salvation, and Damnation: if with repentaunce and <HI>workes of righte∣ousnesse</HI> we turne to the right hand, we shall finde a <HI>Mercifull Father,</HI> and be <HI>accepted</HI> of him; but if we re∣maine obdurate in our sin, and turne to the left hand, we shall see an <HI>Angry Iudge</HI> and rue the punishments of his wrath. Which change and alteration is in vs, not in God; God doth not <HI>bow</HI> to man, but man <HI>doth come to God;</HI> nor doth God leaue any man of any na∣tion, but man doth <HI>revolt frō his Creatour.</HI> Not onely the <HI>Schooles,</HI> but <HI>Expositors</HI> both <HI>Orthodoxe</HI> &amp; <HI>Romish,</HI> stand at this day much distracted, with a diversity, or at least a divers conceit of the <HI>Will</HI> of God; of his <HI>An∣tecedent, and Consequent, Hidden</HI> and <HI>Revealed will,</HI> of <HI>his Absolute, and Conditionall Will:</HI> whereas to speake properly, Gods Wil <HI>is one and the same,</HI> nor can he be said to haue <HI>two VVils,</HI> no more then to <HI>haue two Wise∣domes,</HI> two Mercies, two Goodnesses, or a diversity of other his <HI>Essentiall Attributes.</HI> But as the <HI>Wisedome</HI> of God (to instance in that <HI>Attribute)</HI> is by <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Paule</HI> tearmed <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Eph.</HI> 3. 10. which some render <HI>Multiformis,</HI> others <HI>Multis modis varia,</HI> and our Eng∣lish <HI>Manifold;</HI> which is yet but <HI>one:</HI> so the <HI>Will</HI> of God being one and the same in it selfe, may yet in respect of vs, and the diverse effectes thereof, bee tearmed
<PB N="24" REF="15"/>
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Manifold,</HI> and <HI>Divers.</HI> The ground of all these Distinctions is taken out of <HI>Damascene,</HI> and by <HI>Damascene</HI> out of <HI>Chrysostome, Hom.</HI> 1. <HI>in Epist. ad Eph.</HI> There is in God (saith hee) <HI>a two-fold VVill,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. There is in God a two∣fold Will, a <HI>First</HI> and a <HI>Second;</HI> the <HI>first</HI> and principall will of God doth <HI>immediately</HI> proceede from God himselfe, whereby hee desireth to doe <HI>good vnto all,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, &amp; it is <HI>Voluntas simplicis com∣placentiae,</HI> and may be tearmed <HI>Voluntas benefaciendi.</HI> His secondary will doth proceede from <HI>contingent causes without God,</HI> and is occasioned by vs, and it may be tearmed <HI>Voluntas Iustitiae,</HI> which doth arise from <HI>our sinnes,</HI> which God cannot but put in execution without prejudice to his Iustice. The <HI>first</HI> is the Will of God, wherein he taketh delight and pleasure, and is by the same <HI>Father</HI> tearmed <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> the <HI>principall will</HI> of God. That which hath beene spo∣ken I thus bring home to my text. That it is the Will of God to leaue <HI>many of most nations</HI> in the corrupt masse of perdition, I well know: but that it is his <HI>prin∣cipall VVill,</HI> his <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or <HI>Voluntas simplicis complacen∣tiae,</HI> to decree the <HI>absolute reprobatiō of</HI> any man of any <HI>nation,</HI> I vtterly deny. <HI>Deus non est priùs vltor, quàm ho∣mo est peccator,</HI> saith <HI>Aug. ep.</HI> 105. Man deserues his punishment, before he hath it, &amp; God makes no man a <HI>reprobate</HI> without just cause. The word <HI>Reprobation</HI> or <HI>Reprobate</HI> is in Scripture seldome vsed to this pur∣pose, &amp; the Greeke word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> will hardly cary it,
<PB N="25" REF="15"/>
signifying as well <HI>Improbus,</HI> or <HI>Reprehensione dignus,</HI> as a <HI>Reprobate,</HI> and therefore should bee vsed more spa∣ringly, and not so absolutely determined of. In the Fathers the opposite to Predestination to life eternal is <HI>Predestination to a second death;</HI> and to <HI>Election</HI> to grace, they oppose <HI>Dereliction</HI> in the Masse of perdi∣tion, seldome <HI>Reprobation.</HI> In those parts of <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Austin,</HI> which I haue read, I never met with the word <HI>Repro∣bus</HI> as opposite to <HI>Elect,</HI> but once; &amp; whosoever hath spent most houres in reading the works of that Iudi∣cious <HI>Father,</HI> did never in that sense read it twise. I wil end this point (because I haue <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">St Maries in Oxon.</NOTE> elsewhere spokē of it more at large) with that of the <HI>Prophet, Perditio tua ex te ô Israel;</HI> there is no <HI>man of any natiō</HI> that fals, but by his owne iniquitie. <HI>Stygias vltrò quaerimus vndas,</HI> we ferry our selues over vnto hell: and like the Ostrich in <HI>Pliny, Proprijs configimur pennis,</HI> wee pricke our selues with our owne feathers, &amp; like desperate Marriners cause those ships to leake which should cary vs safe to the fortunate port of heauen.</P>
<P><HI>He that feareth him] Feare</HI> is defined by the great Master of Art <HI>Aristotle,</HI> l. 2. <HI>Rhet. c.</HI> 11. to bee nothing else, but a <HI>perturbation</HI> of the mind through an <HI>opini∣on</HI> of some <HI>imminent danger,</HI> threatning, if not the <HI>destruction,</HI> yet the <HI>annoyance</HI> of our nature, which to <HI>shunne</HI> it doth <HI>contract</HI> and <HI>deiect</HI> it selfe. For as the ob∣iect of <HI>Hope</HI> is <HI>Bonum,</HI> something that is <HI>Good,</HI> so the obiect of <HI>Feare,</HI> Hopes opposite, must needs be <HI>Ma∣lum,</HI> something <HI>being</HI> or <HI>apprehended to bee</HI> Evill. Yet not every <HI>evill,</HI> but <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, such an evil as <HI>threat∣neth</HI>
<PB N="26" REF="16"/>
vs with <HI>destruction</HI> or vexation, and that such as we haue no <HI>abilitie</HI> to <HI>resist,</HI> nor yet are <HI>vtterly disena∣bled</HI> to <HI>avoid.</HI> To <HI>feare</HI> that which we <HI>know</HI> our selues <HI>able</HI> to <HI>withstand</HI> were cowardise; to withstand that, which we <HI>knowe</HI> our selues <HI>vnable</HI> to <HI>differ</HI> or <HI>eschew,</HI> were extreame folly. The proper obiect therefore of <HI>Feare,</HI> is an <HI>Evill</HI> in our <HI>perswasion vnresistable</HI> when it comes, yet not <HI>vtterly impossible for a time,</HI> either in <HI>whole</HI> or in <HI>part,</HI> to be declined. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: <HI>Feare</HI> alwaies, saith the same <HI>Aristotle,</HI> hath some <HI>hope</HI> of <HI>escape</HI> annexed, &amp; therefore doth cause vs to <HI>consult</HI> and <HI>deliberate;</HI> which in matters <HI>past hope</HI> to doe were meere madnesse. Neither doth our na∣ture much shrinke and deiect it selfe, at such evils, except they be at the doore, ready to enter in &amp; rush vpō vs, or hanging over our heads ready to oppresse vs. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, dangers <HI>out of sight</HI> are <HI>sel∣dome feared,</HI> nor, if they <HI>be neere,</HI> do we feare them ex∣cept we <HI>thinke</HI> them to be neere. There is no man li∣uing but is assured, that <HI>once</HI> hee must pay the tribute due vnto nature, <HI>Death:</HI> but because most men put death <HI>è longinquo,</HI> farre from them, and the eldest mā that is, doth thinke hee may liue yet, <HI>yet</HI> a day <HI>longer,</HI> there is nothing in time of health <HI>lesse thought on</HI> thē <HI>sicknesse,</HI> and throughout the whole course of our life lesse feared then <HI>death.</HI></P>
<P>But when we <HI>apprehend</HI> a thing <HI>nociue,</HI> as <HI>nociue,</HI> a <HI>danger</HI> as a danger, <HI>ready at hand,</HI> for to assault vs; then doth our <HI>dastard</HI> bloud <HI>retire</HI> to the <HI>fountaine of heate,</HI> and what we cannot forcibly <HI>withstand,</HI> that we
<PB N="27" REF="16"/>
seeke warily to decline. Which <HI>eschewing of evill</HI> be∣ing a thing <HI>naturall,</HI> and ingrafted in the heart of eve∣ry man, as he is a man, is in it selfe <HI>neither good nor bad,</HI> but good or bad according to the <HI>cause</HI> for which, or the <HI>measure</HI> by which it is entertained. Now because in diverse Texts of Scripture we read this passion of <HI>Feare commended</HI> and <HI>enioyned,</HI> and else where <HI>forbid∣den</HI> and <HI>reprooued:</HI> to reconcile this seeming opposi∣tion, we must knowe, that on the one side is <HI>commen∣ded a godly</HI> and <HI>religious</HI> feare, on the other is <HI>reproued</HI> a <HI>diffident</HI> and <HI>perplexed feare;</HI> the one is a remedie a∣gainst <HI>desperation,</HI> the other against <HI>presumption;</HI> the one against <HI>diffidencie,</HI> the other against <HI>securitie;</HI> the one reprooues an <HI>anxious torturing</HI> feare, which is <HI>without hope,</HI> the other commends a <HI>cautelous</HI> and <HI>sol∣licitous feare,</HI> in every man that <HI>stands, to take heed,</HI> lest he <HI>fall.</HI></P>
<P>And if here any Auditour should demand, how God can be <HI>feared,</HI> being not only <HI>good,</HI> but <HI>essentially Goodnesse</HI> it selfe; and that nothing can bee <HI>feared</HI> but that which <HI>is evill</HI> or <HI>apprehended</HI> so to be? I answere with <HI>Aquinas</HI> 2<SUP>a</SUP>. 2. q. 19. a. 1. that as <HI>hope</HI> hath it's double obiect, the one the <HI>good</HI> we pursue in <HI>expecta∣tion,</HI> and the other the <HI>auxiliarie helpe,</HI> by which wee hope to <HI>obtaine</HI> this <HI>good:</HI> so <HI>feare</HI> hath it's double ob∣iect, the one is the <HI>evill which</HI> it <HI>eschewes</HI> and dreads, the other is something <HI>from which</HI> this evill may <HI>pro∣ceed.</HI> Now although God everlasting and blest for e∣ver, cannot in the <HI>first sense</HI> be said to bee <HI>feared,</HI> or to be the obiect of <HI>feare;</HI> yet in the <HI>second</HI> he may. For
<PB N="28" REF="17"/>
although he be <HI>goodnesse</HI> it selfe, yet something may be <HI>feared to proceed</HI> from him, which is <HI>evill;</HI> evill, not in it's <HI>owne nature,</HI> but evil in <HI>respect</HI> of <HI>him</HI> that <HI>feares;</HI> which is indeed <HI>malum poenae,</HI> not <HI>culpae,</HI> an <HI>evill</HI> of <HI>pu∣nishment,</HI> not of <HI>offence.</HI></P>
<P>And for our direction in this point, giue me leaue to note vnto you (out of <HI>Aquinas)</HI> a <HI>fourefold feare,</HI> A <HI>Naturall,</HI> a <HI>Worldly,</HI> a <HI>Servile,</HI> and a <HI>Filiall feare.</HI> A <HI>naturall</HI> feare is nothing else but a <HI>providēt shunning</HI> of those <HI>dangers</HI> and mischeefes, with which wee are not <HI>able</HI> to <HI>encounter.</HI> Which <HI>passion</HI> is entayled to all the sonnes of <HI>Adam,</HI> and made <HI>hereditary;</HI> nor from it was our <HI>Saviour</HI> himselfe freed, but as hee was a <HI>man</HI> he <HI>feared,</HI> and therefore prayed, and that often, <HI>Father, if it be possible, let this cup passe from me.</HI></P>
<P>The second is a <HI>worldly feare,</HI> when, for the safety of things <HI>temporall,</HI> we sticke not to admit of things excluding from <HI>eternall;</HI> when we more <HI>feare</HI> them, that can kill the <HI>body only,</HI> then him that can cast <HI>both body and soule</HI> into eternall fire; when we startle at the least bluster of <HI>persecution,</HI> when wee contract our selues at the <HI>touch</HI> of a pins point, being ready at the least assault to leaue <HI>Christ</HI> for the loue of the <HI>world.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>servile feare</HI> is a slavish dread of the <HI>iudgements</HI> of God, and his <HI>punishments</HI> for sinne; when not for the <HI>loue</HI> of <HI>heaven,</HI> but for <HI>feare</HI> of <HI>hell,</HI> we retaine our selues within the circle of Gods <HI>Commandements.</HI></P>
<P>The last &amp; best <HI>feare,</HI> is a <HI>filial,</HI> chast, &amp; loving feare, when we feare to commit <HI>sinne,</HI> because it is <HI>sinne,</HI> &amp; doe embrace <HI>vertue,</HI> as it is <HI>vertue; cùm non delectaret</HI>
<PB N="29" REF="17"/>
<HI>iniquitas, quamvis proponeretur impunitas,</HI> saith <HI>Am∣brose.</HI> Which <HI>feare</HI> is proper to <HI>Christs flocke; which</HI> who so hath is <HI>accepted with God</HI> and may bee assured to liue for ever. <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Austin</HI> in his 120. <HI>Epist. ad Hono∣ratum</HI> doth truely expresse and liuely effigiate the na∣ture and difference of these <HI>two feares,</HI> by the example of the <HI>two maried women,</HI> th'one an <HI>adulteresse,</HI> the o∣ther a <HI>chaste matrone.</HI> These both <HI>feare</HI> their <HI>husbands,</HI> but after a different manner. The one feares the <HI>pre∣sence</HI> of her husband, least comming home hee <HI>take</HI> her <HI>tardè,</HI> the other feares the <HI>absence</HI> of her husband, lest by his departure shee be <HI>deprived</HI> of his much de∣sired <HI>company.</HI> The one feares to <HI>commit adultery</HI> least her husband <HI>catch her,</HI> her <HI>minde</HI> neverthelesse is <HI>adul∣terous, &amp; quod deest operi inest voluntati</HI> (saith <HI>Austin)</HI> what shee wants in <HI>deed</HI> shee perfourmes in <HI>desire:</HI> th'other feares her husband, but t'is chastly &amp; loving∣ly, nothing but his displeasure or absence; <HI>Nam aman∣ti etiam absentia molesta est.</HI> So the <HI>wicked feare</HI> God with a <HI>base, servile</HI> feare, they feare him as a <HI>Iudge;</HI> the <HI>godly</HI> as a <HI>Father.</HI> The <HI>servile</HI> feare makes men to a∣voide sinne, <HI>quia nocivum,</HI> the filiall, <HI>quia prohibitum,</HI> onely because it is forbidden, saith <HI>Almaine</HI> in his <HI>Mo∣rals.</HI> He who hath a <HI>chast, filtall feare,</HI> doth not only a∣voide the <HI>act</HI> of sinne, but a <HI>desire</HI> to commit the act: but the <HI>servile feare</HI> restraines men only <HI>ab actu execu∣torio</HI> (saith <HI>Aquinas,)</HI> and leaues behinde, <HI>velle compla∣centiae,</HI> a desire to sinne. In a word, the <HI>servile</HI> feare doth tie vs vnto God with clampers of yron and fet∣ters of brasse, the <HI>filiall</HI> with bracelets of needle worke
<PB N="30" REF="18"/>
and chaines of gold; by the <HI>one</HI> we receiue the <HI>spirit of adoption</HI> and cry <HI>Abba father;</HI> by the <HI>other</HI> the <HI>spirit of bōdage</HI> againe vnto <HI>feare.</HI> The <HI>servile feare</HI> (saith <HI>Hales part.</HI> 3. <HI>q.</HI> 06.) <HI>respicit poenam aeternam, vt destructivam subiecti;</HI> the <HI>fil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>al, tanquam separativam et privativam à Deo.</HI> By the one we feare the <HI>Iudgements</HI> of God and the <HI>paines</HI> of he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, by the other the <HI>losse</HI> of his <HI>grace</HI> &amp; the <HI>ioies</HI> of heaven. The one is not <HI>Timor,</HI> but <HI>Terror,</HI> a passion mixt of <HI>horror</HI> and dismay; the other sweetly composed of <HI>loue</HI> and an <HI>awfull regard.</HI> The one is <HI>ti∣mor poenae,</HI> th'other <HI>culpae;</HI> the one the feare of the <HI>pu∣nishment,</HI> the other of the <HI>offence:</HI> th'one is the badge and brand of the <HI>reprobate;</HI> the other the proper and inseparable character of the <HI>elect;</HI> insomuch that <HI>Ia∣cob</HI> the religious Father of the Patriarcks did cal God nothing else, but the <HI>feare of his father Isaac. Gen.</HI> 31. 42.</P>
<P>This <HI>feare</HI> of God should binde vs hand and foote from sinne, &amp; make vs thinke of that heavenly Vow of <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Anselmes, Si hinc peccatum &amp; illinc infernum viderem, ac vni eorum necessariò immergi deberem, pri∣ùs me in infernum immergerem quàm peccatum cōmit∣terem.</HI> If sinne (saith he) were on th'one side and hell on the other, I had rather plunge my soule into the depth of hell, then commit a <HI>voluntary</HI> sinne. This <HI>feare</HI> of God and losse of his loue, should serue, as a strong curbe to retaine vs from <HI>sinne;</HI> whensoever ei∣ther by the corruption of our <HI>nature</HI> or allurements of the <HI>Devill</HI> we are tempted therevnto. When <HI>Io∣seph</HI> was by his wanton mistresse tempted to adulte∣ry, it was not the feare of <HI>temporall punishments,</HI> the
<PB N="31" REF="18"/>
losse of his service, or the discovery of the fact, that kept him from yeelding to hir vnlawfull desire, but the feare of <HI>offending God; How can I doe this so great wickednesse &amp; sin against God?</HI> Gen. 39. 9. But now sin hath clambred vp to that heigth of impiety; that nei∣ther the <HI>feare</HI> of God (whose <HI>wrath</HI> is a <HI>cōsuming fire)</HI> nor the terrour of punishment can restraine many from the frequent <HI>practise,</HI> scarce from the open <HI>pro∣fession</HI> of sin. There was a time, when <HI>Tamar</HI> was vay∣led and <HI>covered hir face:</HI> but now she boldly walks <HI>vn∣maskt</HI> in the broad eye of the multitude, enters the presence of the best, walkes through the midst of the citie, and makes publike profession of her lust; &amp; <HI>quod solet esse publicum incipit esse licitum,</HI> that which is done <HI>commonly</HI> by many, will ere long bee thought <HI>lawfull</HI> to be done by any. There was a time, when, those that were <HI>drunken,</HI> were drunken in the <HI>night,</HI> but now it is become a <HI>daie worke,</HI> or rather a <HI>dayly worke,</HI> and so obvious that a man can hardly balke it in the street. There was a time, when <HI>an eye</HI> required <HI>an eye,</HI> and <HI>bloud</HI> would call for bloud againe; but now <HI>murder</HI> is become the badge of <HI>manhood,</HI> and sinne is made a <HI>mockery.</HI> As <HI>Abner</HI> called <HI>fighting</HI> but a <HI>play</HI> or <HI>sport,</HI> 2. Sam. 2. which indeed procured a bloody bat∣taile (for every man kild his fellow) so <HI>Monomachies</HI> are now become but <HI>recreations,</HI> and the least but <HI>sus∣picion of disgrace</HI> is a iust cause of a <HI>single combate.</HI> But this is <HI>madnesse</HI> not <HI>manlinesse;</HI> this kinde of courage is in the head, not in the heart, it is not hardy valour, but a soft and moist <HI>enthusiasme</HI> of <HI>Bacchus, qui ad prae∣lia</HI>
<PB N="32" REF="19"/>
<HI>trudit inermes.</HI> And therefore men should as well consider of the <HI>beginning,</HI> as feare the <HI>end</HI> of such <HI>con∣tentions.</HI></P>
<P>But such men the <HI>feare</HI> of God in my Text cannot <HI>retaine,</HI> the <HI>goodnesse</HI> of God cannot <HI>allure;</HI> nothing but his <HI>Iudgements</HI> &amp; terrours can prevaile with thē. Let the first call to minde the fearefull end of <HI>Zimbri</HI> and <HI>Cozbi</HI> in the very act of <HI>Incontinency;</HI> that God sent <HI>fire</HI> and <HI>brimstone,</HI> even <HI>Hell</HI> from <HI>Heaven,</HI> to cō∣sume the people for their <HI>vncleannesse;</HI> &amp; that most times then punishment in this life is <HI>shame</HI> and <HI>penu∣ry,</HI> and in the other perpetuall <HI>torments,</HI> and extrea∣mest <HI>misery. Momentaneum est quod delectat, aeternum quod cruciat:</HI> an <HI>Oceā</HI> of torture for a <HI>drop</HI> of pleasure. Let the other knowe, that though the <HI>wine</HI> be <HI>red,</HI> &amp; <HI>goeth downe pleasantly,</HI> yet in the ende it will <HI>bite</HI> like a <HI>Serpent</HI> and hurt like a <HI>Cockatrice:</HI> and <HI>wine</HI> in the con∣veyance is most like the <HI>poyson</HI> of Serpents, whose teeth are hollow (saith <HI>Pliny)</HI> like pipes, that with more <HI>secret speed</HI> they may convey their <HI>poyson.</HI> Last of all, let the other knowe, that <HI>Clamitat in coelum vox sanguinis,</HI> the voice of bloud is loud, it pearceth the clouds, it knocks at heaven gates, and enters into the eares of the Lord of Hosts. And so I goe on.</P>
<P><HI>And worketh righteousnesse]</HI> It is the note of <HI>Cal∣vine</HI> vpon my <HI>Text;</HI> who by the <HI>feare of God</HI> vnder∣standeth the observation of al the Commandements of <HI>the first Table,</HI> and by <HI>working of righteousnesse,</HI> all the Commandements of <HI>the second Table;</HI> by the one we are <HI>iust,</HI> and <HI>righteous before God,</HI> by the other <HI>be∣fore</HI>
<PB N="33" REF="19"/>
<HI>men;</HI> the one is necessary, but not <HI>sufficient,</HI> the o∣ther is <HI>acceptable,</HI> but not perfect. Which exposition of his will serue to strike off all the hold-fast of the <HI>Divines</HI> of <HI>Rome</HI> from this <HI>place;</HI> who hence inferre the <HI>Merit of Workes,</HI> and the favour <HI>they</HI> procure vs with God: for if by <HI>working of righteousnes</HI> be vnder∣stood, only the observation of the Commādements of the <HI>second Table;</HI> then doubtlesse are they not <HI>suffi∣ciently</HI> able to make vs <HI>acceptable</HI> with God. Yet <HI>Bel∣larmine</HI> fals vpon this <HI>Text</HI> of Scripture, &amp; hence in∣fers an <HI>ability</HI> in <HI>man</HI> to <HI>make</HI> himselfe <HI>acceptable</HI> with God. I am in the <HI>Pulpit,</HI> not in the <HI>Schoole;</HI> and there∣fore will not trouble you with the <HI>Subtilties</HI> of the Question: which as well in this, as other cases, are oft times made too common to the multitude.</P>
<P>The property of <HI>Faith</HI> is to <HI>receaue</HI> and <HI>apprehende;</HI> the nature of <HI>Charity</HI> is to <HI>diffuse</HI> &amp; <HI>impart</HI> to others. <HI>Faith</HI> alone is the <HI>Iustifying instrument,</HI> whereby wee <HI>apprehend</HI> and <HI>apply Christ's merits</HI> vnto vs: but we cā∣not make any <HI>discovery</HI> or <HI>manifestation</HI> thereof vnto others, except there bee ioyned to our <HI>Faith</HI> the <HI>Workes</HI> of <HI>righteousnesse.</HI> So the <HI>inward worke</HI> of <HI>Iu∣stification</HI> we ascribe to <HI>Faith</HI> onely, but the <HI>righteous∣nesse</HI> of <HI>Sanctification,</HI> we ascribe vnto good Workes, which are by <HI>Iesus Christ</HI> to the glory and praise of God. For the more cleere vnderstanding whereof, we must obserue, that our <HI>Workes</HI> are of two sorts; ei∣ther <HI>Intrinsecall</HI> and <HI>infus'd,</HI> as <HI>Faith, Hope, &amp;c.</HI> or <HI>Ex∣trinsecall</HI> and <HI>acquisite;</HI> such are <HI>Almes-deeds</HI> &amp; <HI>Workes</HI> of <HI>Charity.</HI> Our <HI>intrinsecall</HI> Workes, they are, as it
<PB N="34" REF="20"/>
were, the <HI>Principall,</HI> and our <HI>Extrinsecall</HI> or outward workes they are the <HI>Interest,</HI> which God expects as due vnto him; as may well appeare by the <HI>Parable</HI> of the <HI>Servants</HI> in the <HI>Gospell,</HI> to whom the <HI>Talents</HI> were <HI>concredited.</HI></P>
<P>Now we shalbe <HI>rewarded</HI> by God, not according to our <HI>intrinsecall Habits,</HI> but <HI>extrinsecall Workes;</HI> not because we had a <HI>strong faith,</HI> or <HI>great hope,</HI> but for <HI>re∣leeving</HI> the <HI>poore, visiting</HI> the <HI>sicke,</HI> and performance of other workes of <HI>that</HI> quality, and <HI>nature.</HI> But the <HI>Church</HI> of <HI>Rome,</HI> proceedeth further, and doth not on∣ly make them the <HI>rule according to which,</HI> but the <HI>cause for which</HI> we are <HI>iustified.</HI> They make them <HI>Merita,</HI> we <HI>Debita,</HI> they the <HI>Cause</HI> of our salvation, and <HI>à Priori,</HI> we the <HI>Consequent,</HI> and <HI>à Posteriori;</HI> as fruit <HI>makes</HI> not the tree to be good, but only <HI>shewes</HI> it to be so. <HI>Non praecedunt iustificandum, sed sequuntur iustificatū:</HI> they are the <HI>Signes</HI> of our <HI>Sanctification,</HI> not the <HI>Causes</HI> of our <HI>Iustification.</HI> For <HI>Faith</HI> doth not <HI>spring out</HI> of <HI>Cha∣rity,</HI> (as <HI>Bellarmine</HI> falsely averres;) but true <HI>Charity</HI> is the <HI>ofspring</HI> of <HI>Faith;</HI> wherevpon it is by <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP> Paule</HI> tear∣med <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>De Iust. l.</HI> 1. <HI>c.</HI> 4.</NOTE> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the <HI>ground</HI> of things hoped for, and the foundation on which all other Theolo∣gicall vertues are erected. <HI>Credendo fundamur speran∣do erigimur, diligendo perficimur.</HI> By <HI>Faith</HI> (saith <HI>Au∣stin)</HI> we are <HI>ingrafted,</HI> by <HI>Hope</HI> we are <HI>improved,</HI> &amp; by <HI>Charity</HI> we are <HI>made perfect,</HI> God <HI>working in vs, and with vs.</HI> For our righteousnesse is rather <HI>passiue</HI> then <HI>actiue: Iustitia nostra non est in nobis, sed extra nos,</HI> saith Doctor <HI>Luther.</HI> Yet although our <HI>Workes</HI> are not the
<PB N="35" REF="20"/>
<HI>cause</HI> of our <HI>iustification,</HI> yet are they the <HI>perfection of our faith</HI> and a <HI>demonstratiue assurance,</HI> that we are iu∣stified. And although it be true that <HI>sola fides iustificat,</HI> faith onely iustifies, yet <HI>fides quae est sola non iustifi∣cat,</HI> that faith which is alone doth not iustifie. And al∣though it do <HI>iustify alone,</HI> yet doth it not <HI>saue alone;</HI> for it is one thing to be <HI>saved,</HI> and another thing to be <HI>iu∣stified.</HI> They who expect to be the sons of God must be <HI>legitimate</HI> both by the Fathers &amp; the Mothers side, and as they must be <HI>begotten</HI> of <HI>Abraham</HI> who was <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the father of the faithfull, <HI>Rom.</HI> 4. 11. so they must haue <HI>Sarah</HI> the free woman to be their <HI>mo∣ther,</HI> who was <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the mother of all that doe well, 1. <HI>Pet.</HI> 3. 6. Besides the <HI>State in fide,</HI> there must be an <HI>Ambulate in dilectione:</HI> &amp; although the crowne of glory be not given <HI>bonis operibus,</HI> yet is it given <HI>be∣nè operantibus,</HI> not for the worke, yet to the workers, for <HI>Christs</HI> sake, in whose name the worke is done.</P>
<P><HI>Aristotle (l.</HI> 2. <HI>Eth.)</HI> requires in his perfect Moralist, be∣sides <HI>knowledge</HI> and a <HI>will</HI> to worke, an <HI>actuall practise,</HI> wherein consists the life of <HI>vertue:</HI> and in every scho∣ler in <HI>Christs</HI> schoole, besides the <HI>theory</HI> of <HI>faith</HI> &amp; spe∣culation of <HI>theologicall verities,</HI> or with these a <HI>desire</HI> to doe good, there must be an <HI>actuall performance,</HI> we must <HI>worke out</HI> our salvation, and thereby <HI>make</HI> our e∣lection <HI>sure.</HI> The fountaine of saving grace I know is set wide open vnto vs all by <HI>Christ;</HI> and by the hal∣lowed waters of <HI>Baptisme,</HI> as by the waters of <HI>Iordan,</HI> we are cleansed from the leprosie of sinne. But yet this meanes <HI>alone</HI> without <HI>Workes</HI> and industrious la∣bours,
<PB N="36" REF="21"/>
without <HI>fights, races, crosses,</HI> and strict <HI>examina∣tion</HI> of <HI>Talents,</HI> will never present vs, as amiable spe∣ctacles, in the sight of God and heavenly spirits. Wee must not thinke that it is the <HI>Churches</HI> office to <HI>absolue</HI> that the <HI>Spirit</HI> must <HI>cleanse, Christ</HI> must <HI>suffer,</HI> God must <HI>saue,</HI> and that <HI>We</HI> must either <HI>sit</HI> stil or <HI>sinne</HI> still, all the while relying vpon this, <HI>I beleeue, and therefore I shall liue.</HI> It is a reason without reason to infer, that sith God saues little ones because they <HI>cannot worke righteousnesse,</HI> therefore also hee must saue <HI>great ones</HI> without <HI>workes,</HI> because they <HI>will not worke.</HI> But this must be our rule <HI>for direction;</HI> that God hath pro∣posed both himselfe and his kingdome vnto vs vnder a <HI>double title,</HI> the one of <HI>Inheritance,</HI> the other of <HI>Re∣ward;</HI> an <HI>inheritance</HI> to <HI>sons,</HI> a <HI>reward</HI> to <HI>servants.</HI> For to <HI>inherit,</HI> it sufficeth to be <HI>sonnes;</HI> but <HI>reward</HI> presup∣poseth <HI>service,</HI> which must expect it. Every man shall receiue his <HI>reward</HI> according to his <HI>labour.</HI> The <HI>first yeares</HI> of man, through the vnaptnesse of the <HI>reasona∣ble powers</HI> of his soule <HI>for action,</HI> allow him not to <HI>ex∣pect</HI> God or heauen as a <HI>reward,</HI> which yet as his <HI>in∣heritance</HI> even <HI>Baptisme</HI> doth impart vnto him. But when <HI>yeares</HI> increase, and with yeares <HI>reason</HI> groweth <HI>actiue,</HI> it will not suffice to plead for our <HI>inheritance,</HI> as <HI>sonnes,</HI> except we also endeavour for our <HI>reward</HI> as <HI>servants.</HI> God will be <HI>Abrahams</HI> reward; but <HI>Abraham</HI> must <HI>walke</HI> for it: <HI>Ambula coram me,</HI> Walke before me. And it is not said, <HI>Euge fili bone!</HI> Well done good <HI>sonne</HI> (though none but good <HI>sonnes</HI> shall enter;) but they must be <HI>good servants</HI> too, <HI>Euge serve bone! intra;</HI>
<PB N="37" REF="21"/>
Well done good <HI>servant!</HI> enter into thy masters ioy.</P>
<P>It is therefore a slanderous imputation cast by <HI>Bellarmine</HI> vpon the <HI>Reformed Churches,</HI> that their <HI>Gospell</HI> is <HI>carnall,</HI> and the high way to <HI>Epicurisme;</HI> that they inveigh against <HI>Good Workes,</HI> and by a bare and <HI>naked faith</HI> doe <HI>expect</HI> to soare vp to <HI>heauen.</HI> To which my answere is, that of S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Austins</HI> in another case <HI>Ep.</HI> 86. <HI>Nemo nos ita intelligit, nisi qui seipsum non intelli∣git.</HI> There is no man that vnderstands himselfe, or a∣ny thing else, that can so vnderstand vs. Wee make the one the <HI>tree,</HI> the other the <HI>fruit,</HI> and doe professe, with the same <HI>Father</HI> in another place, <HI>Inseparabilis est hona vita à fide, imò ea ipsa est bona vita:</HI> A good life is the inseparable companion of Faith, nay, a liuing Faith is it selfe a good life.</P>
<P>The preaching of which doctrine in our <HI>English Church</HI> warranted by the Word of God hath taken so deepe <HI>roote,</HI> and brought forth so good <HI>fruit,</HI> that since the first yeare of our late <HI>Soveraigne Queene</HI> of pious memory there haue beene more <HI>Hospitalls, Pub∣like Schooles, Libraries, Colleges,</HI> and <HI>Places</HI> for learning, <HI>built, adorned,</HI> and now <HI>in building,</HI> then ever were be∣fore in any <HI>one</HI> 60. <HI>yeares.</HI> Many of which publike <HI>Mo∣numents</HI> of Religion haue receaued their first <HI>erection</HI> and chiefest <HI>endowments</HI> from the <HI>Heroicall liberality</HI> of those, whose <HI>Successours</HI> divers <HI>here present</HI> are in <HI>Office</HI> and <HI>Dignitie.</HI> Be not, I beseech you <HI>(R. H.)</HI> their successours onely in <HI>Place,</HI> but in <HI>Pietie;</HI> passe not through this world, like an <HI>arrowe</HI> in the ayre, or <HI>ship</HI> in the sea, that <HI>leaue no impression</HI> behind them. As
<PB N="38" REF="22"/>
God hath given you meanes and handes to <HI>effect,</HI> so should you haue <HI>hearts</HI> to <HI>affect</HI> that which is good; &amp; if not to <HI>found,</HI> yet to <HI>further</HI> &amp; <HI>finish</HI> Good works for publike benefit: whereby your <HI>righteousnesse</HI> shall be recorded in heauen, and your <HI>Names</HI> preserued from rottennes on earth.</P>
<P>And if your <HI>Charity</HI> wants a fit <HI>obiect</HI> for her pra∣ctise, then cast your eyes vpon the <HI>bare Habitati∣ons</HI> of the Muses: harken after the SCHOOLES of <HI>sciences</HI> and <HI>learning,</HI> which by the beneficency and prensation of many, especially of that worthy <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">S<SUP>r</SUP> Iohn Be∣net.</NOTE> Knight the Patron of the work, (whose name shall for ever be to vs as a sweet oyntment powred out) haue <HI>crept out of the ground,</HI> and now deserue to be <HI>co∣vered</HI> by the <HI>Charitie</HI> of all that loue either learning, or learned men. This is a worke in which the <HI>Elephant</HI> may <HI>wade,</HI> as wel as the <HI>Lambe,</HI> the rich mans gift shal be welcome, &amp; the meaner mite not <HI>refused:</HI> &amp; a cō∣currency of so many <HI>founders</HI> to a work of that incō∣parable benefit, wil doubtlesse make a <HI>glorious constel∣lation</HI> of blessed starres, whereof <HI>some shalbe greater, others lesse,</HI> but al shining in the highest heavens. And if that be true which the Wise mā saith, Eccl. 40. 19. that the <HI>Building of a Citie</HI> will make a man <HI>immor∣tall;</HI> then much more the erection of a Work of this infinite benefit which shall remaine longer, then a∣ny Citty. For when the <HI>stones</HI> shall by time and long continuance be <HI>decayd,</HI> yet <HI>Iustitia manet in aeternum,</HI> the <HI>Founders</HI> &amp; <HI>Benefactors</HI> (especially with vs of that Vniversitie) shall be in everlasting remembrance.
<Q>Sola{que} non nôrunt haec monumenta mori.</Q>
<PB N="39" REF="22"/>
Of this assured I am, that neither the <HI>Plantation</HI> of <HI>Vlster</HI> in <HI>Ireland,</HI> nor the <HI>Contribution</HI> to <HI>Prage</HI> in <HI>Bo∣hemia</HI> may stand comparison with this <HI>Monument</HI> of all <HI>Arts</HI> and <HI>learning:</HI> of whose benefit, not only our owne nation, but the remotest <HI>kingdomes</HI> of the <HI>Chri∣stian</HI> world shall haue a tast. It disquieted the <HI>Wisest man,</HI> that ever was to thinke, that he should leaue his goods he knewe not to whom, peradventure <HI>Homi∣ni otioso,</HI> to one that would <HI>spend all, Eccles.</HI> 2. 19. And let it not be your sole care to leaue <HI>All</HI> to your <HI>riot∣ous Executors,</HI> who peradventure in <HI>few</HI> yeares will consume that estate, which with much care &amp; in <HI>ma∣ny</HI> yeeres you haue gathered together. You must purchase something, <HI>Alteri seculo,</HI> for the world to come: you must make your eyes <HI>in this life</HI> the <HI>over∣seers of some good workes;</HI> you must imitate <HI>Iacob,</HI> who to pacifie his brother <HI>Esau,</HI> sent a <HI>Present</HI> before, <HI>Gen.</HI> 32. 20. and before <HI>Cornelius</HI> could haue <HI>Peter</HI> sent vn∣to him, hee sent his <HI>Almes deeds</HI> to vsher him vp the way into heaven. And therefore it is not said in my Text, he <HI>who hath,</HI> or hereafter <HI>will worke righteousnes,</HI> but <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, hee that actually <HI>doth worke righte∣ousnesse.</HI></P>
<P>That new convert <HI>Zacheus</HI> did not say <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the halfe of my goods <HI>I wil giue</HI> vnto the poore <HI>whē I am dead:</HI> but <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, I <HI>now</HI> presently <HI>giue.</HI> Such as <HI>defer</HI> the performance of the <HI>workes of righteousnes,</HI> till the end of their daies, are like those that cary cādles in Lant∣hornes behind them in a darke night; whereby they <HI>direct others,</HI> and <HI>themselues</HI> in the meane time <HI>fall</HI> in∣to
<PB N="40" REF="23"/>
the ditch. It is not for men to bee like swine, <HI>good</HI> for nothing till they be <HI>dead;</HI> or like <HI>Christmas-boxes,</HI> that will afford nothing, till they be <HI>broken.</HI> Let vs ra∣ther imitate the example of the forenamed <HI>Zacheus,</HI> who gaue in the <HI>present tense,</HI> and that no small drib∣let, but <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, even the halfe of his goods and substance; and that not <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, but <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, not to <HI>one</HI> poore man, but to <HI>many;</HI> yea and maketh proclamation, that if by forged cavillation hee had wronged any man, he would restore him fourefold. Surely had <HI>Zacheus</HI> liu'd in these our daies, hee had beene an honest <HI>Master of the Custome house.</HI> For if this or the like proclamation should bee made among vs by all of his professiō, how many are there in this <HI>Ci∣ty,</HI> now in great reputation and esteeme, that would haue scarce sufficient left them in this life to main∣taine their families, and being dead to defray the ex∣pense of an ordinary <HI>Funeral!</HI> And yet these men too to sweeten the mouth of the poore, and to stop the eares of the multitude will clad some few in <HI>frize,</HI> &amp; when they die bequeath a <HI>solemne Potation</HI> to their adioyning friends, thinking by these petty <HI>posthume</HI> workes of <HI>righteousnesse</HI> to make themselues <HI>accepta∣ble with God.</HI> Such men I can compare to nothing more fitly, then to the Lion, which <HI>Sampson</HI> killed; which in his life time was <HI>ravenous</HI> and <HI>devoured</HI> all, and being dead was found to haue some <HI>little hony in his mouth.</HI> Iudg. 14.</P>
<P>And as we are to <HI>worke righteousnes, whilest we haue time,</HI> or rather <HI>continually,</HI> so we must worke our <HI>own,</HI>
<PB N="41" REF="23"/>
not <HI>other mens;</HI> we must not like <HI>Simon</HI> of <HI>Cyrene</HI> ca∣ry <HI>other mens</HI> crosses: we must not be <HI>busie Bishops in o∣ther mens Diocesses,</HI> but stand in <HI>that station,</HI> wherevn∣to we are <HI>called;</HI> and not thinke it sufficient in <HI>some respect</HI> to be good &amp; in <HI>other</HI> bad, to bring forth with <HI>one</HI> branch <HI>sound</HI> fruit, and with the other <HI>rotten,</HI> but to <HI>worke righteousnes</HI> in <HI>every</HI> respect. It is not suffi∣cient for the inferiour to be a <HI>good man,</HI> but to bee a good <HI>servingman,</HI> for the superiour to bee a good <HI>Master,</HI> but a good <HI>Magistrate.</HI> It is not sufficient to be a good <HI>Preacher,</HI> but a good <HI>Bishop;</HI> and not only a <HI>learned Lawyer,</HI> but an vpright <HI>Iudge.</HI> For vnlesse in all <HI>respects</HI> we be quadrate and <HI>perfect,</HI> we shall not bee <HI>accepted with God:</HI> which is the end of my <HI>Text,</HI> &amp; shall be the end of my speech.</P>
<P><HI>Is accepted with God]</HI> Not in strict legal <HI>rigour,</HI> but in <HI>Evangelicall mitigation,</HI> not, because we can per∣forme <HI>exact obedience</HI> to the Law of God, or <HI>worke perfect righteousnes:</HI> but because we <HI>loue, purpose, desire, endeavour,</HI> and in <HI>some measure perfourme obedience</HI> to the Law of God; and where we are deficient we <HI>sigh</HI> and <HI>groane</HI> for our defects, which at the <HI>Chauncery barre</HI> of Gods mercy is <HI>acceptable performance. Accep∣table,</HI> not for our observing what the law requires, but for our <HI>sincere desire</HI> to performe it: because, as <HI>Saint Paul</HI> saith, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the ready minde is accepted with God.</P>
<P>The <HI>benefits</HI> (saith <HI>Aristotle lib.</HI> 1. <HI>Eth. c.</HI> 14.) which men receiue from <HI>God</HI> &amp; their <HI>Parents</HI> are of that in∣finite worth and transcendent value, that wee are not
<PB N="42" REF="24"/>
able to returne for them any correspondency of de∣sert, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. The reason is, because the <HI>gifts</HI> of God and his <HI>acceptation</HI> is <HI>infinite,</HI> but the a∣ctions of man <HI>finite</HI> and determinate; the best where∣of hath many <HI>staines</HI> and <HI>imperfections.</HI> For the <HI>imme∣diate</HI> and <HI>next causes</HI> of our <HI>workes</HI> are not altogither <HI>spirituall,</HI> and <HI>totally regenerate,</HI> because there dwels yet the <HI>Iebusite</HI> in <HI>Ierusalem</HI> with the <HI>Israelites:</HI> the soule of man hath <HI>her inmates,</HI> the <HI>Old man</HI> coinhabi∣ting with the <HI>New,</HI> the <HI>flesh</HI> with the <HI>spirit,</HI> the <HI>law of sinne,</HI> with the <HI>law of the mind.</HI> Insomuch that the best of men cannot climbe vp to heaven without <HI>Iacobs ladder,</HI> the merit of <HI>Christ,</HI> and the gift of God.</P>
<P>I haue wearied my selfe &amp; am sure haue tyred you. I will therefore ende all with that devout praier of <HI>Arch-bishop Anselme; Recognosce Domine quod tuum est, &amp; absterge quod meum, ne per dat mea iniquit as quod fecit tua bonitas.</HI> Accept (O God) of what is <HI>thine</HI> owne in <HI>vs;</HI> and let not our <HI>iniquity</HI> eclipse thy gra∣cious <HI>mercy. Meritum no strum, miseratio Domint;</HI> our <HI>Merit</HI> is thy <HI>Mercy</HI> &amp; gracious acceptation; in which we repose our whole assurance. We acknowledge our selues to be <HI>naked</HI> of all <HI>righteousnes,</HI> beseeching thee to <HI>cloath</HI> vs; to be <HI>lame</HI> and impotent in the per∣formance of any <HI>Good worke,</HI> desiring thee to <HI>streng∣then</HI> vs; to be <HI>blind</HI> in our vnderstanding, desiring thee to <HI>enlighten</HI> vs; to be <HI>servants</HI> to sinne desiring thee to <HI>free</HI> vs: and we ascribe all <HI>glory</HI> vnto thee in this world, praying <HI>to be glorified</HI> of thee in the world to come.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="24"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

