<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The Army brought to the barre, legally examined, arraigned, convicted and adjudged that they are not the self-denying army, nor the restorers of our laws, liberties and priviledges, but obstructors to the happinesse of the King and people.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A25836</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing A3709</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R23376</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12068200</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12068200</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">53418</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A25836)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53418)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 49:17)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The Army brought to the barre, legally examined, arraigned, convicted and adjudged that they are not the self-denying army, nor the restorers of our laws, liberties and priviledges, but obstructors to the happinesse of the King and people.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Andrew All Truth.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 13 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1647.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>On the political struggle between Parliament and the army.</NOTE><NOTE>Signed: Andrew, All Truth.</NOTE><NOTE>Place of publication from Wing.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>England and Wales. --  Army.</TERM><TERM>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A25836">
<STC T="W">A3709</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12068200</BIBNO>
<VID>53418</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
ARMY
Brought to the
BARRE,
Legally Examined, Arraigned,
Convicted and Adjudged.</P>
<P><HI>THAT</HI>
They are not the Self-denying Army, nor the
Restorers of our Laws, Liberties, and
Priviledges, but obstructors to the
happinesse of the King and
People.</P>
<BIBL>James 3. 13, 14.</BIBL>
<Q><P>Who is a wise man, and endued with knowledge
amongst you? let him shew out of a good conversa∣tion
his works with meeknesse of wisdome.</P>
<P>But if yee have bitter envying and strife in your
hearts, glory not, and lie not against the truth.</P></Q>
<P>Printed in the yeare, 1647.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE
ARMY
Brought to the Bar.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>T hath been for these six years space and more, the
complaints of divers of the inhabitants of this
Kingdom, concerning the slavish servitude they
endured under the King and his Cavaliers; and
there be others who complain of the servile bon∣dage
they groaned under by the Parliament and their Com∣mittees,
but now 'tis justly to be feared, that there is a yoke of
servitude far worse then the two former, preparing to be put
upon the necks of all Englishmen, by an over-ruling Indepen∣dent
Army, who have assumed so much boldnesse and auda∣city
(having the power in their own hands) to controule the
Parliament, City, and whole Kingdome, meerely to drive on
their own interests and designes.</P>
<P>And our servitude is like to be very miserable, if three things
be considered.</P>
<P>1 The condition and nature of the servitude: 'Tis a mar∣tiall
servitude, the worst of all: what will not the sword in the
hands of such an ignorant multitude doe? our estates, lives,
fortunes, liberties, and Religion, will prostrate themselves at
the glittering of a naked sword, all shall be within the reach of
a swords point, to be disposed of according to their pleasures
and commands.</P>
<P>2 The qualifications wherewith the persons are endowed
who must rule us: Namely the Armies Agitators, men of trans∣cending
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
knowledge and judgement, especially one of them,
of whom (by one that knows him) I am credibly informed,
can neither write nor reade. If we were to be governed by
men found in judgement, and experienced in the Laws of the
Land, we might expect a milder servitude, but from them wee
must expect according to education, for as their breeding is,
so is their disposition, we cannot expect a gentle usage from
men of rude education, but if these and such as they be men
rightly qualified to give rules and Laws to a Parliament and
Kingdom, then I leave it all indifferent men to judge, then this
proverb shall be verified, <HI>Sus Mivervam docet:</HI> Ideots shall
teach the learned, and men scarce fit to be subject, shall become
our Rulers: But yet let the Agitators and the rest of the Coun∣sellors,
remember this, that <HI>Malum concilium consultori pessi∣mum.</HI></P>
<P>3 The third thing which will cause our servitude to be ve∣ry
miserable if it happens, (which I pray God I may never live
to see) will be the strangenesse and unwontednesse of it: Wee
were before happily governed by our King (<HI>Charles</HI> our dread
Lord and sacred Sovereign, (whose dayes God prolong,) but
now we shall be miserably governed by many Tyrants, who
would fain be Rulers and Magistrates, yet can scarce tell how to
be men. We were before governed and ruled by Monarchy,
we shal now be governed by Democracy, how wil our English
necks be accustomed to such unwonted and uneasie yoaks, sure∣ly
we must needs kick and winch, which if we doe, let them set
fast (being good-horse-men because Souldiers) lest they be cast
out of the saddle to the ground.</P>
<P><HI>Quest.</HI> But some may say (and I doe verily believe many
meerly upon that ground cleave to them) that they have been
the only Instruments under God, of our preservation and safe∣ty,
and therefore their proceedings now may be warrantable.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> 'Tis true, they have done very nobly (through God)
in what they undertook, yet one good act committed cannot
be a veil to hide all other offences: shall a villain be pardoned
for murther, because hee hath done some worthy deeds before,
God forbid? shall a man for some brave exploit before per∣formed
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
be so far exempted as to escape punishment, if hee be
guilty of a crime, No: the more Noble and brave their former
proceedings were; makes their present undertakings seem more
horrible, for <HI>Nullius viri species vehementiùs accessit, quàm quae
ab initio habuit dulcedinem:</HI> No Wine becomes more sowre
then that which was at first the sweetest: so they, so long as
they obeyed, and honoured the Commands of the Parliament,
they were most notably victorious and successfull in all their
enterprizes, and none did better, but now having revolted, and
become like sweet wine turn'd to vineger, &amp; doing things, nei∣ther
warrantable by Law nor Reason, in this none did worse.</P>
<P><HI>Quest.</HI> But again, some may say, there is no feare of any
oppression, or servitude, when as all their Declarations, Procla∣mations;
and Letters do signifie that they entend, nay, protest
they will endeavour to preserve the prerogative and honour of
the King, to uphold the priviledge of Parliament, to mayntain
the Liberty of the Subject, to establish a true and sound Reli∣gion,
and to settle a firme and lasting peace in this Kingdome,
and therefore before all these be established, 'tis not necessary
they should disband.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> 'Tis true, it cannot be denied, that all their Decla∣rations,
Remonstrances do signifie, they do really intend, or at
least pretend all these, and first they will endeavour to preserve
the honour and prerogative of the King, and to settle him in
peace and happinesse in this throne, which they will very hard∣ly
do, for the very tenents, and principles of an Independant
run crosse, and quite blank against King and Monarchy. Now
if such as go quite contrary to me, may be said to go along with
mee, and if hee be accounted my advancer, who endeavours to
pull me down, then will I believe that an Independant will pre∣serve
a King, but againe, if example may strengthen beliefe in
this particular, then this of Major <HI>Scot</HI> by name, (an Indepen∣dant
by Religion, a Villain by his actions) is most remarkable,
who (if fame hath not forgot to tell truth) being asked by Co∣lonel
<HI>Brown,</HI> whether he were come to kisse his Majesties hand,
made answer, Hee had rather follow him to the Gallows;
<HI>O monstrum horrendum, informe, ingens, cui lumen ademptum:</HI>
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
Now, if this mans opinion being an Independant may go for
the rest, (man did I call him, more fit to be termed a Devill) I
say if the rest agree with him in opinion, being of one and the
same Religion, then 'tis plainly seen which way their hearts,
and resolutions tend, although their Declarations (to delude
the World) seem and pretend to go quite contrary; this is that
Sect, who being employed as a Factor by the Clothiers of
<HI>Barfould</HI> in <HI>Suffolke,</HI> runs away at one time with the value of
1500 pounds worth of cloth (as I am credibly informed.) I
omit to recount many more (as that daring affront offered by
Cornet <HI>Joyce</HI>) in removing his Majesty from <HI>Holdenby,</HI> contra∣ry
to the pleasure of both Houses, and his own royall assent. I
omit that of <HI>Crumwel,</HI> who (when his Majesty refused to
signe a paper given him, by him) answered his Majesty, that he
had as good he had: yet in passing by these, and many more his
Royall Majesty hath shewed an incredible patience, yet though
the Lion sleeps, he is not dead, but keeps a Catalogue of all in
his sacred brest, and will repay all with much use upon the
backs of some, although hee be now their prisoner, if such as
these preserve the Prerogative of the King, then say men goe
upon their heads, when they goe upon their feet, and you may
as well,—</P>
<P>2 Their Declarations professe to uphold the priviledges of
the Parliament, but I beseech you tell me who are lesse uphol∣ders,
nay, who are greater dissolvers of the Parliament, and
confounders of the priviledges thereof, then themselves? which
is manifestly evident by severall particulars. First, What was
the impeaching the eleven Members upon a meere bare pretence
of some great thing laid to their charge, when nothing could
be proved against them, No, 'twas meerly their policy (under a
pretence of frivolous slanders and reproaches) to draw them
out of the House, and to rob them of their birthright given them
by their Countrey) whereby (by their absence) their own party
might be the more prevalent to carry on their own designes, and
upon this bare pretence they must be forthwith suspended the
House, although by the said house they were fully cleered, yet for
modesty sake (a thing very commendable in them) they upon
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
their own desire (and to satisfie the humour of the Army) ab∣sented
themselves from setting in the House, and yet for all this
some of them are threatned, some <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ought for, and some scanda∣lous hue and cries sent after in a reproachfull way, some taken,
and others searched, as Sir <HI>William Waller,</HI> who had leave (with
the rest) and passes from the Speaker, to goe beyond sea, or any
other place whether they please. Now I would fain know by
what authority they doe these things, they could not have their
authority from the Parliament (they having the Speakers passe
to goe at their pleasure,) 'Tis well known they had their au∣thority
from themselves, and the root and ground of all this
malice, and calumny, and envy against them, is because they
were not friends to their proceedings as they desired, and yet
their charge is not yet brought in (because they pretend first
to settle the more important affairs of the Kingdome, which if
it be not brought in before the Kingdom is setled by them, the
eleven Members shall never need to be afraid of their tryall, and
again, was it not an incroaching upon the priviledges of Par∣liament,
to set them a certain day, nay, a prefixt houre of the day,
by which time they should send them an answer to their de∣mands
(though unreasonable) or else they would do so and so,
march with their Army towards <HI>London,</HI> What was the re∣sult
of the Agitators of the Army, when they voted all them
to be suspended the House, and to sit there no more, or to sit at
their perill: who sate in Parl. when the Speaker &amp; the rest fled to
them? was not this a great diminution to the priviledges of Parl.
but pray why are those that set then thus censured, because they
did not (contrary to their consciences) desert the house, and
their trust, and come to them, I pray assure mee you that know
the Laws of this Land (of which I confesse my self to be who∣ly
ignorant) who have been the faithfullest Patriots, those that
sat, or those that deserted the house, I know you will say those
that sat, and mayntained their trust against all opposition what∣soever;
however if it be their fortune (I cannot say ill fortune) to
be driven frō the house (though contrary to their priviledges) by
the power of the Army, yet they will have many companions,
and <HI>foelice est miseris socios habuisse doloris,</HI> yet if it so come to
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
passe, yet confident I am, that the time will come againe, when
they shall set to do their Countrey service, and shall enjoy (in
spight of such an over-ruling Army) all their former Priviledges
and Honour, and shall at last be accounted the best lovers of
Peace, and their Countrey.</P>
<P>I admire what bloud ran then in our Nobles veins, when
they so deserted the Parliament, was all the Royall bloud which
was wont to run in our English Nobles veins then lost, by my
consent, if they commit the like act again, they shall forfeit both
their honour and dignity, if such as these (I mean not the Lords)
be the upholders of Parliaments, they are like to have good
housholders, and if such acts as these be upholding, the Privi∣ledges
of Parliament, I say no more but, <HI>ô tempora! ô mores!</HI></P>
<P>3 Their Declarations (I confesse) demonstrate how that they
will endeavour to mayntain the <HI>Liberty of the Subject,</HI> which
is a thing they as little intend as the former, else what meanes
their oppressing the Countries by their daily needlesse Quarters
(though it be not denyed, they carry themselves very orderly
where they come, 'tis true and 'tis policy so to do, for thereby
they make their actions more plausible, and their ruling longer-liv'd
then it would of it self be, for if they should carry them∣selves
any way unbeseeming, all would vie with one hand and
arme to subdue them; the fetching home of the King, and set∣ling
him in his Throne (which I know they never intended)
they declare to the world to increase their number (many fol∣lowing
the King as a Loadstone) and to colour and varnish their
unjust and unheard of proceedings, they are Politicians and will
prove the better Statesmen: and they have already a little learned
to dissemble, because they would verifie that ancient Proverbe,
<HI>Nescit imperare, qui nescit dissimulare,</HI> witnesse else <HI>Cromwel</HI>
(who being a member of the Honourable house of Commons)
(which place by his fore-mentioned unheard of authority, hath
long since unjustly forfeited) I say <HI>Cromwel</HI> in the house de∣clared
that if the houses would but send the very shadow of their
Commands to them for to lay down their Armes, they would
readily obey, and lay them down at the House of Commons
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
doore, and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow they have verified this saying upon the Houses com∣mand for their disbanding, sent to <HI>Bury,</HI> and severall commands sent
them since. Let the world judge <HI>&amp;c.</HI> And againe, if they maintain
the Liberty of the Subject, what do they meane when they force the
House (contrary to the dictates of their owne consciences) to recall
and revoke their Votes, passed in a free, and full house; and all this be∣cause
it doth not please the pallat of the sweete tooth'd Army, (as I
may justly tearm it) these be them that in all their Propositions, and
Remonstrances, speak for a free Parliament, and yet none so much doth
force the Parliament as themselves. But we may see light through the
least crevice. I would fain know what confidence, and trust, the sub∣jects
of <HI>England</HI> can repose upon any Vote the Houses passes concer∣ning
them, when as their votes are beat back again (as I may say▪) by
the sword into their own mouthes, or if they come forth, they are not
obeyed by a lawlesse, and over-ruling multitude: what fruits, and en∣joyements,
can the subject have of this Parliament, when as their votes
are made voyd, and nulled (though contrary to humaue reason, and
their own priviledges) yet by the threatning power of an Indepen∣dent
Army. And by this their actions, they not only hinder the free
course of the Parliament, but they cause the people to loath Parliaments
as long as this generation lasteth, and if the Parliament shall vote
what they desire our of feare, or condicend what they propound out of
love; what English man will ever again honour a Parliament? Fur∣thermore,
I desire to know what security, and hopes these subjects can
have who are lenders of the Publique Faith, for their mony so lent,
when as their greatest securities, the Excise, and Bishops lands, and
many other lies under the command of the sword of a revolting Army.</P>
<P>I wonder what liberty the Citizens can expect, when Sir <HI>Thomas</HI>
is the Merchants Cash-keeper, and the Tradsmens shopkeeper. (pray
God he gives a good accompt) He commands all, the Tower key is
the picklock key, whereby hee may enter every mans house at his
pleasure.</P>
<P><HI>I</HI> wonder what priviledge the Apprentices will reap by their free∣domes,
when as every tag, rag, shagd souldier will be free of any trade
in the City, by the Armies Copy-hold. Is the Liberty of the subject,
and the freedome of the City like thus to bee maintained? Iudge all
reasonable men, to reason it is impossible, that that which is deliberate∣ly
enacted by the Parliament can be of force, when it is repealed again
by violence.</P>
<P>4 Their Declarations, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Presents to the view of the world another
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>
false glasse, which is, that they will to their utmost endeavours procure
to settle a firme, and lasting Peace in this Kingdome. I believe they
they will use their utmost endeavours, and doe (but what to doe?) to
procure all into their own clurches, not to settle Peace and Vnity:
which if they do, let their military preparations speak, their daily list∣ings
of men, there fetching Armes and Ammunition from the Tower
of London, the taking of <HI>Tilbury</HI> Blockhouses in <HI>Essex,</HI> and their
possessing themselves of many strong Holds in this Kingdome, the pla∣cing
Colonell <HI>Liburne</HI> Governour of <HI>Newcastle,</HI> and yet for all that,
the City, nor Kingdome must not raise a man for their own defence,
for fear of involving this Kingdome in a second war.</P>
<P>What means such acts as these? bee such preparations for warre as
these, settlers of a happy Peace in <HI>England?</HI> O reason, speak the truth!
Fooles do you determine? Can he which comes thrusting with a na∣ked
sword at my breast, be tearmed the saver of my life? Reason saies
no, and the same reason tels me, that their present proceedings truly
considered, shall not (neither ever can) settle Peace in the land. But
if they intend to settle Peace, for what purpose do they surround and
incompasse <HI>London,</HI> (Londoners looke about you) and their having
the commands of some Forts thereof, is it to confirme Peace? be∣leive
it, they that strive to settle Peace by the sword, distract it; how∣ever
if all these be the Mother of Peace, I feare the child will be still∣born,
or if it see the light, it will not live long, but will dye before
the mother rises up, or to speak plaine, before the Armies layes down.
But if it prove contrary to expectation, and reason) that these their
actions produce Peace, it is a way newly found out, which our states∣men
never knew: but they are Politians, and Policy is but a circum∣stantiall
dissembling, pretending one thing, intending another; 'tis
like to prove such a Policy; I feare their hearts doe turne tounges, to
give their tongues the lye in this particular.</P>
<P>5. Lastly, their Declarations professe that <HI>they will be establishers
of true Religion in its purity.</HI> If they be the guardions and establishers
of our Religion, <HI>Actum est de nostra Religione,</HI> you may shake hands
with true Religion; if they settle true Religion, it will bee the cleane
contrary way, and under pretence of allowance to tender consciences,
which they desire) all Schismes, Sects, and dangerous. Opinions will
(rush in; that gap is so wide that many other Opinions destructive to
the Common-waalth will rush in unavoydably. Though <HI>I</HI> confesse in
things meerly indifferent, and no wayes prejudiciall to the Common-wealth,
a respect is necessary to bee had to tender Consciences, but in
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
things of great concernment (the word of God not sincerely construed)
is to beare more sway then a tender Conscience, for if a religion or any
thing else seises a mans genius, he wil flye to the Altar of a tender Con∣science,
though he hath not a tender Conscience, or rather none at all,
I say he will make Conscience the shelter, and refuge for his villanies,
but in any thing which the word of God distinctly commands, and
reason, and experience, and examples confirmes, in my opinion wee
must not controle, nor disobey it, under pretence, or coulor of a
tender Conscience. I pray God such ranging souldiers (used hereunto)
doe not open this gap to let in all manner of fower footed beasts, and
two legged Monsters as themselves to graze in the flourishing field of
our true Religion. But if such actors, and acts such these be the preser∣vers
of the Prerogative of the King, the upholders of the priviledges
of Parliament, the maintainers of the liberty of the subject, the setlers
of a lasting Peace, the Establishers of true Religion, I shall desire to
use but one clause of the Letany before it bids adieu to us, and gives it
<HI>Ʋltimum vale</HI> to the world. which is, from such <HI>Preservers, Ʋpholders,
Maintainers, Setlers, and Establishers, good Lord deliver us.</HI></P>
<P>But rule they will, for in reference to some Petitions presented to
them, they say, this, and this is the sense of the Army, whereby they
make their sense the supreame law of the Land.</P>
<P>And the unreasonablenesse of their proceedings is seene in two
things.</P>
<P>1. In this, the tumult of the Apprentices on the 26. of <HI>Iuly,</HI> forcing
the Parliament to unvote, what they had formerly voted, and disturb∣ing
and affronting the members of both Houses (which truly I do not allow)
must be by them tearmed a breach of the Parliaments Privi∣ledges,
and the contrivers and abbettors thereof must bee proceeded a∣gainst
according to law, and justice, and themselves (though gu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>y
of the same crime) are scot free, and escape unpunished, and escape un∣punished,
not because they have not merited any, but because the sword
sayes nay, they shall not suffer.</P>
<P>1 Now take a review of both their acts, the Apprentices came ('tis
true) in their persons, and compelled the Members of Parliament to re∣voake
what had been before voted upon the desire of the Army. But
<HI>Vollitur causa desinet effectus,</HI> there is never no effect without a cause;
if the Army had not first (by their unjust desires) compelled the Par∣liament
by their Votes to alter the old Militia, the Apprentices had ne∣ver
came in such a tumultuous manner to force them (in the same kind)
to revoake that which before upon the Armies unheard of demands had
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
been passed; so that if the Army had not first piped, and led the way,
the Apprentices would never have danced after them, for they fearce
knew the way to <HI>Westminster,</HI> so that the Army was the only cause of
that mutiny.</P>
<P>2. The Army they ('tis confessed) came not in their own persons,
but they sent their power, and command (as their subordinate deputy)
to them, and forced them to revoke, and call in their Declaration
wherein they were proclaimed Traytors (yet they will be traytors up∣on
record) or if they did not, they would do so, and so, thus, and thus,
and march with their whole Army up to London, as if they would
compell them by their presence.</P>
<P>Now the state of the cause stands thus, whether a deputy sent from
a Ruler, or an Embassador sent from a Prince, be not as effectuall, and
of as much force as the Prince, or Ruler in person, if so, then the Ar∣my
are as deep in that crime (nay deeper) then the Apprentices, seeing
they can command as much by their deputyes, as others can do by ap∣pearing
in person; however it stands with reason, that what is not
allowable in the one, cannot bee expedient in the other, and yet the
Army is not proceeded against, but <HI>Quod defertur, non offertur.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Quest.</HI> But some may say that of the Apprentices was the more un∣warrantable
in regard they forced the Speaker, and some of the other
Members to flye from the House. 'Tis true, the substance doth worke
more upon mans nature then the shadow, yet being the shadow is the
Image of the substance, and the Deputy represents the Image of his
Lord and Master, the Army is as equall guilty of the said crime as the
other, yet neither are warrantable neither by Law, nor reason, nor can
ever such clashings strike good fire to the Common-wealth: but how
can the Speaker warrant that his absence, you say he was forced and af∣frighted,
and was not they that stayed behind forced and affrighted
as well as he and the rest, if so, how then comes it to passe that they
deserted not the House as well as the other, yet for their faithfullnesse
in cleaving close to their truth, they must be subject to the Votes of a∣company
of illeterate Agitators, and a Councell of War, and to desert
the House according to their pleasure: if this be just, and to uphold,
nay if it be not to break the free priviledges of a Parliament, let
themselves be their own judges. Againe doth it become the Speaker
and the rest, being placed as Magistrates in such authority, to desert the
House upon a pretence of feare, and leave the kingdome in the lowest
ebbe, and in the greatest storme, like a ship in a tempest ready to sink,
no, 'twas not feare, I believe it was a thing called a guilty conscience
which made them flye.</P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="7"/>
2. There unreasonable proceedings are manifest in the manner of the
Impeaching the 11 honourable Members, they did not (as those which
censure aright alwayes do) examin two things before they censure: first
whether the parties censured have done good or ill: secondly whether
they themselves could have done better. But they never have these
considerations, but being turned by the wheele of their own in terests,
never regard how mens good names are as white balls, which will in∣finitely
get soyle by tossing: but their censures against these 11 wor∣thy
Impeached Members, are like the butts of Rams-hornes against
the walls of <HI>Iericho,</HI> they lay levell all their worthy deeds at once.
But for all this, the saying of a worthy writer may be fitly applyed
here. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>mutatis, mutandis, ille crucem pretium sceleris tulit, hic diadema,</HI>
it may be verified of them <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>Now a word to <HI>London:</HI> ô <HI>London, Sero sapium Phryges,</HI> the <HI>Phry∣gies</HI>
were wise too late; and so were you, tis too late (they being in)
to keep Sir <HI>Thomas</HI> and his followers out, 'tis too late (when the horse
is stollen) to shut the stable doore, yet I dare say, and <HI>I</HI> verily believe,
had the City but shewne there teeth at them, they durst not have ap∣proached;
and I believe there were steeled swords in the City, which
would have pierced <HI>Crumwells</HI> skin, in spight of his Iron sides, and
there were sturdy Mastives in the City, which would have baited that
Bull into the <HI>Isle</HI> of <HI>Ely,</HI> from whence he came, and truly it would be
a greater honour to him to turne Brewer againe in that Island, and for
Colonell <HI>Pride</HI> to assume his profession of a Brewers Clarke againe in
<HI>London,</HI> then in being such evill instruments of the Common-wealth
in the places they are for, <HI>Praest<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t in<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> esse; quàm Impium.</HI></P>
<P>I would speake one word (if without offence) to the revolted Ci∣tizens
within the City, and there erevolting Neighbours, <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI>
and I would aske them one question, what was there intention in ly∣ing
Dormant to let the Army thus subdue the City? I wonder what
mercy either would have found, if the Army had come in in fury?
they would all have been in the same shocke of calamity; and misery;
friends, and foes are both a like in the eyes of such a multitude, what
honour have you atchieved by selling and betraying the City (as <HI>Iudas</HI>
did our Saviour?) and although you have not <HI>Iudas</HI> his first wages
mony, yet you may have his last wages, and reward, (hanging) and
truly it were a thing fit in my opinion, that all those that were in this
crime of revolting, shovld have Revolter written in all there fore∣heads,
to there utter Infamy to all ages, and posterity<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="8"/>
<HI>Quest.</HI> But some say, 'tis better it is thus ended, and that they stood it
not out against the Army, a great deale of precious bloud is saved thereby?</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> To that I answer, some bloud (I confesse) must have beene
spilt, how ever, 'twere better a little were lost, then all your Liberties
lost, Come Citizens, <HI>Libertas dici inaestim abilis,</HI> you applyed a certaine
remedy to a suspected disease, you feared shedding of some bloud,
which was but suspected, and did not feare the losing of your Liberties,
which is certaine; if the City had stood out in a generall defence,
much bloud could not have been spent, for
<Q><L>Plus virtus unita valet, vis nihill vinci</L>
<L>Si meus null fides null sit, null manus.</L></Q></P>
<P>And if the City had but done so, Terme time, that Army would not
have hurt it, but they might have enjoyed their ancient freedoms, and
Liberties, which now they must bid adieu unto.</P>
<P>A word to Sir <HI>Thomas</HI> and the Army under his command, Gentle∣men
Souldiers, and Agitators; you shall scarce be warme in your ho∣nour
by these proceedings; Theeves of honour seldome find joy, in
there purchases, (stability never) you seeke honour (like <HI>Absolon</HI>) by in∣direct
meanes, but you may (like him) be pulled down with a venge∣ance,
you aspire to preferment by wrong meanes, being like them that
ascend a paire of staires on horse-back, it is tenne to one but your beasts
will cast you before you reach the top of preferment; Though <HI>Caesar</HI>
had not his equall, nor <HI>Pompey</HI> his superiour, yet <HI>Fairefax</HI> may meete
with both, and although yet no rubs crosse him in his undertakings, but
all things smile upon him with an auspicious reverence, yet before hee
attaines the Throne, many lets must encounter him. There is a King,
who when (like the Sun) hee shall arise againe in our Horison, will by
his glorious beames chase away these numerous flies: I say there is a
King, a Cavalier, a Byshop, a Presbyterian, a Round-head, and a true
Englishman, all Antipodes to Independants; therefore <HI>Fairefax</HI> hold
thy hand, the beginning of thy Reigne shall not come in our Alma∣nacks
this yeare; Agitators leave plotting, and counselling, it is bet∣ter
to desist betimes, then to be forced to it <HI>nolens, volens,</HI> A sword of
Gold will command an Englishman, more than a sword of Steele;
<HI>Fairefax</HI> take warning, beware, and look behind to what hath beene
done, you signe all that is presented to you from your Agitators, and
your Councell of Warre; your hand is upon record for all, your back
must heare all, it will sinke you if you be not strong back'd; you must
answer and appeare for all, when <HI>Crumwell</HI> and the rest of your Coun∣cellours
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
will pull there necks out of the collar, though as guilty as you
they will set you in the Front of the battle to beare the brunt, when
they thems<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lves will fall back to the Reare and be secure, o beware, be∣wise, <HI>Praestat sero, quum nunquam.</HI></P>
<P>A word to all true noble Englishmen, be patient you who have bin
grinded by the King, you that have been oppressed by the Parliament,
and now been slaves to this over-ruling revolting Army, or oppressed
by any subordinate power, derived from any of these three waits, and
be patient all you that have lost your goods and estates; <HI>Flebile prin∣cipium
melior fortunae sequata est,</HI> There will come a time when all shall
enjoy there own, when King <HI>Charles</HI> is setled agai in his throwne and
injoyes his own, which shall be my daily prayers, and that this king∣dome
may flourish againe with all the freedomes, liberties and happi∣nesse
it formerly enjoyed, <HI>which God of his infinite mercy grant, Amen.</HI></P>
<P>Now Souldiers (Gentlemen Souldiers) I would tearme you if your
proceedings were answerable; if you wynch, 'tis to be feared you are
galled, and if I have any way incensed you, you must not stirre; you
are bound to the peace, your hands are tyde behinde you in two re∣gards.
First, you goe under the notion of Saints, and Saints are not
envious nor vindictive, you allow Liberty of Conscience to doe and
speake, therefore you cannot exempt me, and in this regard, though I
thought not to have revealed my name; yet because you shall see I do
not feare, my name is,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Andrew, All Truth.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<OPENER><SALUTE>Courteous Reader;</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IF in any thing in the foregoing Discourse thou hast reaped any pro∣fit,
I shall think my selfe fully satisfied for my paines: there is no∣thing
in it, but what is as cleare as the Sun. And as my Conscience
commanded me, so have I obeyed and publisht it, though contrary
to my desire. If any thing therein displease thee, thy pardon I humbly
crave, and rest</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thine</SIGNED></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

