<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Hell illuminated, or, Sancy's Roman Catholic confession wherein are such lessons, which if studiously practis'd, 'tis much to be fear'd, the Devil himself will turn Jesuit.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Confession catholique du sieur de Sancy. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>Aubigné, Agrippa d', 1552-1630.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A26189</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing A4187</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R16534</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">11732934</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 11732934</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">48420</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A26189)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48420)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 482:15)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Hell illuminated, or, Sancy's Roman Catholic confession wherein are such lessons, which if studiously practis'd, 'tis much to be fear'd, the Devil himself will turn Jesuit.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Confession catholique du sieur de Sancy. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>Aubigné, Agrippa d', 1552-1630.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[12], 171 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for L. Curtis,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1679.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Translation of Agrippa d'Aubigne's Confession catholique du sieur de Sancy.</NOTE><NOTE>Later issued under title: "The Catholik confession of Monsieur de Sancy."</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Elspeth Healey</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Elspeth Healey</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A26189">
<STC T="W">A4187</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">11732934</BIBNO>
<VID>48420</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>HELL Illuminated.
OR, SANCY'S ROMAN CATHOLIC Confession,</P>
<P>WHEREIN Are such Lessons, which if studiously practis'd, 'tis much to be fear'd, the Devil himself will turn <HI>JESUIT.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed for <HI>L. Curtis</HI> in Goat-Court on <HI>Ludgate-Hill,</HI> 1679.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE PREFACE, By way of Dialogue be∣tween a <HI>Roman Catholic</HI> and a <HI>Protestant.</HI></HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>HAve ye heard the News?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, because 'tis to your prejudice, I'le tell it ye. The Devil having lately made public Confession, and receiv'd full ab∣solution of his sins from his Ho∣liness himself at <HI>Rome,</HI> has tak'n a Resolution, to forsake the Pomps and Vanities of his own wicked
<PB REF="3"/>
world, and in his old age to enter into one of our holy Orders, accord∣ing to the example of <HI>Charles</HI> the Fifth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I took him to have been of your Religion, ever since <HI>Con∣stantine</HI>'s time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's your mistake, He was of none at all, till now — I confess he had like to have bin converted by <HI>Martin Luther,</HI> when he was so long with him in his study; and <HI>John</HI> of <HI>Lei∣den</HI> with his back-sword Logic, made him stagger cursedly, so that he was just tumbling headlong down the Precipice of <HI>Hugueno∣tism,</HI> had not the strong hand of <HI>Ig∣natius Loyala</HI> snatch'd him from the misfortune of the fall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then, if the Devil have the least spark of Gratitude in him, that must be the Order he in∣tends to honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>In troth, you make me smile—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy so! because I see you do not perceive the Devils de∣sign— For he, having intelligence out of the <HI>Revelation,</HI> That he is to Reign a Thousand Years, upon Earth at his full swinge, and resolv∣ing to make use of the utmost ex∣tent of his Tyranny, beleives it his best way to hide his cloven feet with the Jesuits Cassock, foreseeing, that successful pretence of Mankind, <HI>Re∣ligion,</HI> to be the only way for him
<PB REF="4"/>
to carry on his intended mischief. Tho there be some that say, be does it out of Fear. For though <HI>Brough∣ton, Napier, Sedgwick,</HI> and the rest of those modern small <HI>Pro∣phets,</HI> have promis'd him a full Thousand Years upon their Ho∣nours, yet I know not what kind of mistrust over-rules him. He is loth in the full Gallop of his fury and re∣venge upon Heaven, to be cut off by the hands of an enthusiasm'd <HI>Ravilliac,</HI> or be sham'd out of five hundred of his thousand years, by a pair of perfum'd Gloves. And therefore like a Devil of Prudence and Foresight he inserts himself in∣to this Order.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>These are meer in∣ventions and reproaches cast upon
<PB REF="4"/>
honest worthy good men—Nay, you make those Actions to be Criminal which are not so, and then throw 'em upon the Jesuits. For if a man have a Capital Enemy, you'd have a man love him— 'Tis true, there's somthing of the Dove, but where's the Serpent? There's Christianity indeed, where's the Po∣licy? — where's self preser∣vation, and the Law of Nature? The Law of Nature was from the beginning written in the heart of man— the Law of God long after only cut upon two peices of stone, and by <HI>Moses</HI> broken all at one clap. Is it not a shameful thing to see a huddle of old rotten wood'n Build∣ings disgracing the modern Piles of Brick and Stone Structure? there∣fore
<PB REF="5"/>
is Fire honestly made use of there, to refine and beautifie. The Jesuits are look'd upon as the most polite and high soaring of the Ca∣tholic Orders— and therefore if they should not do extraordinary things, from whom extraordinary things are expected, their Reputa∣tion would dwindle away, and dye of a Consumption.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>But do you think it any honour to your Order, to have the Devil of your Society?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why truly; I cannot tell— If Satan will make a Con∣fession, and throw himself into the Arms of his Mother, the Church of <HI>Rome</HI>— I know that our holy Father the Pope, has forgiven many an Incarnate, worse then he— we
<PB REF="5"/>
are apt to remember whatever we think the Devil does amiss— why should we forget what he does well? And indeed, I would fain know what it is that you <HI>Huguenots</HI> rail so much at the Devil for? — You'l say that He maintains a general Antipa∣thy against Heaven; — so do the <HI>Danes</HI> maintain a National Enmi∣ty against the <HI>Suede;</HI> — the <HI>French</HI> against the <HI>Spaniards;</HI> the <HI>Imperialists</HI> against the <HI>French</HI>— And yet these National Antipathies are allowable, as mainly conducing to cherish that Pride and Animosity which defends, and many times crowns them with Victory. I would fain know, why a man might not write the Life of Satan, as well as <HI>Katherine de Medecis;</HI> unless it
<PB REF="6"/>
were out of civil respect to him, not to let the VVorld see that a VVoman could out-do him. There∣fore good Mr. <HI>Protestant</HI> be not so Captious— but read these fol∣lowing sheets. Consider what the Prince of the Air says in his own justification, weigh his Tropes, and his Figures, and if he don't argue like a Gentleman, and a Scholar.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>But hold a blow, you say this is <HI>Signior Diavolo</HI>'s Confes∣sion, when the Title says, 'tis <HI>M. Sancy</HI>'s Confession.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>For that, you know, Sir, 'tis the common practice of men of no reputation, to borrow the names of men of fame—The Devil has learning, but no fame— He knew <HI>Sancy</HI> to have both—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed I have heard much of this <HI>Sancy,</HI> that he is both a witty, &amp; an impartial Writer— which makes me wonder, that he being a man of learning, should be drawn aside to be the Devil's Confessour—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Sir, 'tis no disho∣nour to be deluded by the Devil— Popes and Emperours themselves, have frequently bin gull'd by him, that's more— but <HI>Sancy</HI> was not so— for when he heard his tale, he presently smelt him, and found his Civility to be but an act of Moral∣ty, well knowing that had the Devil bin put to have publish'd his Confes∣sion in his own name, not one in a Thousand would have believ'd the Father of lyes—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very great peice of Ci∣vility indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>R. Cath.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and I think, as I said before, of Morality too— For when he heard how <HI>Lucifer</HI> spoke his Conscience, and knew it, as he did, to be real, it had been a point of dishonesty to have hindred the discovery of such truths to the World, by the knowledg of which, the <HI>Jesuits</HI> have become a mighty Order, and the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic Religion has bin highly advanc'd▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am satisfi'd — now to the Confession it self.</P>
</SP>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="book">
<PB N="1" REF="7"/>
<HEAD>THE CATHOLIC CONFESSION OF THE Sieur <HI>de SANCY.</HI> FIRST BOOK.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. I. Of the Authority of the Church, and of its Head.</HEAD>
<P>IT has been a Controversie frequently debated in these times, whether the <HI>State</HI> be in the <HI>Church,</HI> or the <HI>Church</HI> in the <HI>State.</HI> Amongst those that would have the <HI>State</HI> to be in the <HI>Church,</HI> there are some who alledge, That it would not be universal, should it be cir∣cumscrib'd within the <HI>State.</HI> Others, ta∣king the same things for Examples, Do ye not see, say they, how the <HI>State</HI> submits it
<PB N="2" REF="8"/>
self to the <HI>Church</HI>? How this haughty King, after so many Armies vanquish'd, so many flourishing people, so many great Princes, his Enemies, layd at his feet; at length for all his Grandeur, prostrating himself at the feet of the Pope, receives his commands at the hands of his Monsieur Confessor▪ and Cardinal <HI>D' Ossat.</HI> Which two were layd upon their bellies jigg by jowl, like Macka∣rel upon a Gridiron, while you might have read half a Mass. They say moreover, That there was the same play to be play'd over again, between his Majesty and Monsieur the Legat, but that was to be done gently and under the Rose. They who would turn the Holy See quite out of doors, in∣stance the boldness of the Court, which be∣ing a <HI>Fugitive,</HI> as far as <HI>Tours,</HI> yet ventur'd to burn the Bulls of his Holiness by the hand of the common Hangman. After that, they tell of a second piece of Audacity of the Court united together, which was the Banishment of the Jesuits out of <HI>France,</HI> a high contempt of the <HI>Romish</HI> See. But I answer to that, That we have no reason to repent of it. Witness the good Catholic City of <HI>Tournon,</HI> and in imitation of her, the Parliaments of <HI>Tholouse</HI> and <HI>Bourdeaux,</HI> who both, in spight of Fate re-established these stout Champions of the Church.</P>
<P><PB N="3" REF="8"/>Thus you have the proofs of the one and the other side by Consequences and Effects. Now for proofs by reason; and let no man wonder at this way of proceeding. It has been the humor of <HI>France</HI> for many years to mind the effects, and not the reason of things. Then I must tell the Reader, that a man may sooner venture his Neck and get a hundred thousand Crowns, then disen∣gage himself out of the labyrinth of such dif∣ficult affairs. I shall therefore only say this, That I believe the Pope to be more then all the rest of the World together, nay then all the Saints, and all the Angels. I'll shew ye certain passages which Monsieur Confes∣sor gave me, to confirm me in this opinion. <HI>Bernard</HI> of <HI>Sens</HI> calls him Prince of the Bi∣shops, Heir of the Apostles; for antiquity of dignity, <HI>Abel</HI> and <HI>Noah</HI>; as a Patriarch, <HI>A∣braham</HI>; as to his Order, <HI>Melchisedec</HI>; as to his Priesthood, <HI>Aaron</HI>; as to his Sove∣raignty, <HI>Moses</HI>; in Judgment a <HI>Samuel,</HI> in power a <HI>Peter,</HI> in authority, <HI>Christ.</HI> I re∣member the words of one of the Bulls of <HI>Clement</HI> the 6th. <HI>The Pope is to be admir'd; The Pope is the astonishment of the World: Neither God nor Man, but as it were between both.</HI> The Glossary upon <HI>q. Sect.</HI> 1. <HI>cap.</HI> 17. is positive, That the <HI>Pope is no man.</HI> I have also read the <HI>Distinct. and Canon, Proposuit
<PB N="4" REF="9"/>
de con. prae.</HI> 19. <HI>c. Si humanarum.</HI> Where it is pithily observ'd, That the Pope, accor∣ding to the latitude of his Authority, has power to give a dispensation against any Law. And 5. <HI>Transub Epist.</HI> 5. <HI>in Gloss.</HI> he explains himself farther, saying, That the Pope can turn injustice into justice. Monsieur Confessor, never admire at these last passages, when I shall tell ye, by way of reinforcement, that the Pope can make <HI>infecta facta</HI>; that is, he can make <HI>Some∣thing</HI> out of <HI>Nothing,</HI> and <HI>Nothing</HI> of <HI>Some∣thing.</HI> By one History alone will I under∣take to prove, that the Pope can do all this. That high and mighty Pope, <HI>Sixtus Quin∣tus,</HI> who in his time caus'd above four thou∣sand pair of shoulders to want heads; and envy'd the Queen of <HI>England</HI> for nothing more, but that she had the Honour to cut off a Queen's Head; who put down the Bawdy houses, and consequently took away fourscore thousand Duckets of rent from the Church. He that was wont say, <HI>There's no trusting in this Religion, for it will not last.</HI> He whom the King call'd Mr. <HI>Sixtus,</HI> who was made Pope, that he might bring his Hoggs to a fair Market. This Great Perso∣nage having unfortunately entred into a Contract with the Devil, and having read how <HI>Alexander</HI> the Sixth, for that he had
<PB N="5" REF="9"/>
usurp'd the Chair by force, was couzen'd in his term of years, made his bargain abso∣lutely for seven years; but notwithstanding all his wit, the Scrivener he had to deal with, found a way to get loose from his Articles. For after he had raign'd five years very formidably, he fell sick the last day of the five years, at what time there came to his Bed-side in the sight of his chief Chamberlain, a certain grave Abby-Lubber, with whom the Pope entred into a very high Contest, insomuch that they in the next Room could hear the Pope call the t'other perfidious; asking him withal whe∣ther he had not promis'd him seven years, and whether there were any more then five past? To which the Devil's Envoy made answer with a loud voice; 'Tis true, said he, I promis'd thee seven years, and there are but five elaps'd, and yet for all that I am no perfidious Person. For do but re∣member, That when you had a desire to put to death the Son of such one—for such a Crime,—when you were inform'd by Justice, that Legally he could not be put to death, till he was Seventeen years of Age— I say then, do but remember, how you said you would lend him two of yours: Now five and two make seven, and therefore you must go, there's no remedy. By this
<PB N="6" REF="10"/>
Story we find the absolute power of the Pope, and a confirmation of the fore-men∣tion'd Characters of his Grandeur. For by putting the young Lad illegally to death, he dispens'd with Law against Law. That Justice which should have sav'd the Lad, he turn'd into Injustice. And the Devil and he made out the third point: For the Bar∣gain which was for seven years, at first im∣perfect, by the power of the Pope and the Devil became a good Contract, as the De∣vil made it out by the Pope's own Act and Deed. And therefore that buffonly Presi∣dent of <HI>Beaulieu,</HI> when the Pope had ex∣communicated the Mass which had been said when the King was crown'd, together with all that assisted at the Coronation; did not much amiss, according to his ram∣bling Divinity, to say, That where there was an Assembly of <HI>Ecclesiastics,</HI> it was such because there was a God among them. The Chancellor going about to reply, By the body of— Sir, cry'd the <HI>Belswagger,</HI> you shall grant me that God was present at that same Council. The Chancellor not daring to deny; the other demands, if any Here∣tic were there, who durst venture to bound the puissance of his Holiness? Every one shrug'd up his shoulders, choo∣sing rather to allow the Excommunica∣tion
<PB N="7" REF="10"/>
of the God of Heaven, then limit the power of a God upon Earth.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. II. Of Traditions.</HEAD>
<P>WE puzzle the Heretics infinite∣ly, when we demonstrate to them, that the Authority of the Church and Traditions teach us to acknowledge the Scriptures, although the Canonical Writings teach us not to acknowledge ei∣ther Traditions or the Authority of the Church. In truth, we must hold to the Legends of the Church, and not to Cano∣nical Scripture, otherwise the Heretics will goad us to Eternity with their Texts out of the Bible. But that I may seem to have done something more, I made use of this advice, not to reck'n for Tradition-Mongers those ancient Doctors of the six first Ages, wherein the Church was not as yet fully nobilitated; when her Sumptuous Buildings were not as yet rear'd; when the Popes liv'd up and down in Caverns, and
<PB N="8" REF="11"/>
in short might pass for the first Promoters of her troubles: at what time the Church smelt somewhat strong of <HI>Huguenotism,</HI> or rather of the Faggot. I say they wrote no∣thing boldly or over-confidently in those first times: &amp; therefore I allow for Tradi∣tions, the Books corrected by the devout Council of <HI>Trent.</HI> For some time after that, we have seen at the Court, and we have still some Doctors, who affecting squeamishness of Conscience, play the <HI>De∣mi-Huguenots,</HI> and Appointers of Religion. This ought to be a fair example to <HI>Monseiur Benedict,</HI> and his Compagnons, <HI>Berenger,</HI> and <HI>Chauveau</HI> in their Deaths of Melan∣cholie or Poyson. These Hero's would fain persuade the suppression of a Book, en∣titl'd <HI>Index Expurgatorius.</HI> Accordingly, it was one Result of the Council of <HI>Trent,</HI> whereby all Printers were commanded to expunge or correct the most boistrous passa∣ges, wherewith the holy Fathers had be∣smear'd the belief of the Church, with a Ca∣talogue of such Sentences as it was conve∣nient either to stifle or amend, to the end the Heretics might make no use of them. These Prudent Worldlings, esteeming themselves wiser then the Council, would needs have this <HI>Expurgatorie Index</HI> suppres'd, to conceal<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, as they said, the shame of
<PB N="9" REF="11"/>
the Church, which was not to plead for its self upon false Evidences. But they have display'd the shame, by thinking to hide it: For about 11. or 20. years since, the Book (I mean a copie of it, sign'd by the Coun∣cil) fell into the hands of the Family of <HI>Antwerp,</HI> and is now carefully preserv'd a∣mong the Rarities of the <HI>Elector Palatine.</HI> And which is worse, some Doctors, among the rest <HI>Baronius,</HI> who were chosen to make this Reformation, are reformed them∣selves, and have confess'd in their printed writings, that one of them had for his part alone, alter'd above sixty of those passages. Thus the design of the Coun∣cil being discover'd, in going about to sup∣press this Book, we might suppress the Authority of the Church, and make it que∣stionable, whether it be not lawful to change the Expositions of the Doctors, and something of the Text of the Anci∣ents? Certainly, the Affirmative is to be maintain'd, and that the Church ought to change both the old and new Testament, without bogling any more at the Transla∣tion of the Septuagint, then at the Trans∣lation of fifteen Score, if we would have all the main Principles on our side. The Primates of <HI>Bourges</HI> and <HI>Lyons,</HI> would dis∣card out of the number of Traditions, the
<PB N="10" REF="12"/>
Conformities of St. <HI>Francis,</HI> the <HI>Pattern</HI> of <HI>Wisdom,</HI> the <HI>Garden</HI> of <HI>disconsolate Souls, Marial</HI>; the Sermons of <HI>Menot, Manipu∣lus Curatorum, Stella, Lavacrum Conscien∣tiae, Summa Peccatorum,</HI> dedicated to the Virgin <HI>Mary</HI>; the <HI>Golden Legend,</HI> the Book of Rates, and the <HI>Life of Christ.</HI> A Preacher whose name was <HI>Christi,</HI> preach'd at <HI>Nantes</HI> to the Ladies, in these words▪ My dainty quaint Ladies, if I find a Bible or a new Testament in any of your hands, you shall tast of my Whip: but have al∣ways between your fingers the good <HI>Vita Christi,</HI> the <HI>Vita Christi,</HI> who made <HI>Vespa∣sian</HI> and <HI>Titus</HI> Christians, and brought a∣bout the design of the Siege of <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> to revenge the Death of Christ; and then he condemn'd and vilifi'd all other Histori∣ans, to establish the truth of that Book. But one of those Prelats might sooner have instructed himself to believe in God▪ then us to believe in Him; and it is as difficult a thing to make us quit our love of those Books, as to make him quit the love of his kind Sister. For those books are the only foundation of our belief. Neither do they allow the defeat of <HI>Monsieur Cayer.</HI> They say, that the Tales of St. <HI>Francis</HI> were made at <HI>Geneva.</HI> That's well for the <HI>Alco∣ran</HI> of St. <HI>Francis.</HI> However the studies
<PB N="11" REF="12"/>
of these abstemious Find-faults, are full of those books of the old Impressions. 'Twere better for them to defend them, and say that they were made with a good Intenti∣on. As when we read of St. <HI>Francis</HI> living with his Wife of Snow. We ought to speak the best, and say the good man did it to cool not only his own naturally sinful heat, but as a president to his poste∣rity. When he preaches to the flesh▪ there∣by it is intimated, that when his offspring should preach, they would require a mute Auditory. When he preach'd it up for a Miracle, that God would not suffer the flesh to be drown'd in the Deluge, thereby he insinuates that the Miracles of the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> ought to proceed from natural causes, as <HI>Richeome</HI> labours to make out. When he calls the Wolves his Bre∣thren, and stroaks them with his hand, he did it to show, that the <HI>Franciscans</HI> should be rough footed, and surprizers of the In∣nocent sheep. He calls the Swallows his Sisters, because their Brothers like them, all morning prayer time, build their nests i'the Country-mens Houses. When the Angel told St. <HI>Francis,</HI> as he was at his de∣votions, that Antichrist should be born of his Order, that was, because it should not be thought an Indignity to make the <HI>Fran∣ciscan
<PB N="12" REF="13"/>
Friers</HI> Popes. And when he disrob'd himself before the Women, and set up his Crucifix, what was that but to display the beauties of Nature, as not having eaten of the Tree of Knowledg; and to lay open, if not the understanding, yet the naked∣ness of Father <HI>Adam</HI>? When St. <HI>Germain</HI> raises a dead Ass, wherefore should not he, out of his brotherly love, and Asinine commiseration, being alive, give life to Asses, who had bin the death of so many at St. <HI>Germans de prez,</HI> and <HI>Auxer∣rois. Blase</HI> of <HI>Anjou,</HI> who threaten'd his Son with Excommunication, if he offer'd to read one line in the Scripture, especial∣ly the Commandments, at length at the intercession of <HI>Aubraye</HI> a good Catholic, gave him leave to read the <HI>Maccabees.</HI> As for Frier <HI>Jacopon,</HI> when I was a <HI>Huguenot,</HI> there was nothing made me laugh like the Legend of that pious Saint; and among the rest, how he made Confession of his sins to one of his Brethren by signs.</P>
<P>These things seem absurd; but they work this effect among the people, as to lead them into a belief that there is no ab∣surdity in the World. And therefore it is, that St. <HI>Paul</HI> calls the preaching of these things the folly of preaching. From whence <HI>Monsieur Cayer</HI> draws this notable Syllo∣gism:
<PB N="13" REF="13"/>
<HI>It pleases God to save Believers by the folly of preaching</HI>; the folly of preach∣ing is the preaching of Legends: therefore God is pleased to save believers by preaching of Legends. If any person requires the note of Universality, and insists, that no∣thing is to be concluded <HI>ex puris particular∣ribus,</HI> he may do well for the School-men: However to conclude from pure particulars is rather the Logic of a Banker, then a Scholar. The Legend of the Saints, is the Garden of the Soul. Images are the Books of the Ignorant. Yet in this Gar∣den there are certain Herbs to be found, which if they do no farther mischief, yet cause a general stupidity. A brave fellow, who understands the fashion of the World, knows what it is which the Country peo∣ple call Robbery. If he find that his dis∣consolate Soul is not able to change its way of living, he may see in the Legend, the bright example of a Knight, who without mercy rob'd the poor as well as the rich, and was acquitted for saying an <HI>Ave Marie</HI> once a day: and it is indeed the ge∣neral practice of the Souldiers at this time. If a Lady of the Court find in her disconsolate Soul, that she cannot pass for a devout Votaress, and a voluptuous Liver both at the same time, has she not where∣withal
<PB N="14" REF="14"/>
to comfort her, like the <HI>Egyptian</HI> St. <HI>Marie,</HI> who from twelve years of age till she was grown contemptibly old, ne∣ver refus'd any man in her life? Are not the ancient Chronicles full of the noble acts of St. <HI>Mandlin?</HI> Do not the Legenda∣ry Poets tell us, how many persons of good Families have been forc'd by the power of her Enchantments to sell their Estates for her sake? How many other couragious Blades have valiantly cut their own throats, being jealous of her love? and yet she was no sooner exhausted with age, but she was presently canoniz'd. If any poor Priest have not the pour to preserve his Chastity, 'tis his fault, if he make not use of the Canon, <HI>Si quis Presbyter Concu∣binam non habuerit</HI>; and thereby be as shamelessly happy as <HI>Abbot Ephraim,</HI> who made no scruple, like <HI>Diogenes,</HI> to supply his wants in the open Market-place. There's the Authority of the Chapter, <HI>inter opera Charitatis,</HI> where it is said, that he that couples with a <HI>Magdalen, multum profuit in remissionem peccatorum.</HI> If any Bishop or Cardinal becomes amorous of his Page, let him comfort himself after the Example of St. <HI>Francis,</HI> who calls his Amours with Frier <HI>Maccus,</HI> sacred. As to what the said Book affirms, that St. <HI>Francis</HI> was all
<PB N="15" REF="14"/>
inflam'd, beholding Frier <HI>Maccus,</HI> and that he often cry'd out the same day, as the one held the <HI>Chalice,</HI> and the other the little <HI>Cruises,</HI> transported with the fury of his love, <HI>praebe mihi teipsum</HI>: there is much to be collected from thence. I will tell ye bythe by, that you may hence conjecture where Monsieur Confessor lays his foundation, when he calls the Amours of <HI>Quailus,</HI> and his Master, Sacred; and whence this Title was first deriv'd. There is another book whom I have so often mention'd, which they would fain have quite extir∣pated, but the holy See would never per∣mit the loss. <HI>De Sparde</HI> was the first that labour'd in it these words, <HI>Habeat jam Roma pudorem, ejusmodi mores toto mundo prostitu∣ere desinat. Let</HI> Rome <HI>at length be asham'd, and cease to prostitute such Customes to all the World.</HI> This is the book of <HI>Rates,</HI> where a good Catholic may see the cheapness of sinning, and observe in a moment the price of forgiveness. Whoever shall deflour a Virgin, shall pay six groats. He that shall carnally know, by consent of parties, his own Mother, his Sister, his Cousin-German or his Godmother shall be acquitted for five groats; but if it be known publicly in the Church, not under six. He that kills his Father or his Mother, shall pay a Duc∣kat
<PB N="16" REF="15"/>
and and five <HI>Cartines.</HI> I could tell ye more, but I shall rather let ye know that these things are to be seen in the Chapter of perpetual Expences. The book was printed at <HI>Paris</HI> in the year 1570. by <HI>Tous∣sain Denis</HI> in St. <HI>James-street</HI> at the <HI>Woodd'n Cross,</HI> being entitl'd <HI>Cancellaria Apostolica.</HI> A <HI>Poictovin</HI> asked me one day whether I could resolve him a quaint Question, why <HI>Sodomites</HI> were more zealous against the <HI>Hu∣guenots,</HI> then any of the <HI>Roman Catholics</HI>? I laugh'd at the Question at first, but after∣wards I call'd to mind, what I had heard from the mouth of the brave Marshal <HI>d' Au∣mont</HI>; There are none, said he, that so vi∣olently persecute us, as these <HI>Sodomites,</HI> and labour the utter expulsion of the <HI>Hugue∣nots.</HI> I remember'd also, that there are not any who so earnestly solicited the King's Conversion, as those who were most sus∣pected for that Crime. Which was the reason, that I resolv<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d to understand the In∣terest of these <HI>Monsieur Catamites.</HI> You know, said the <HI>Poictovin,</HI> that there are se∣veral persons who are polluted with this <HI>peccadillo</HI>; who though they do not over-credulously believe that there is any Hell, or any Paradise, yet being still in doubts and fears, would, as the Decretalists say, <HI>make use of absolution by way of caution.</HI> Now
<PB N="17" REF="15"/>
should a man come to an honest Divine and ask him by what means, a detestable sinner may be sav'd? He would reply, by embracing the death of Christ, with a true and sincere faith; by praying with a contrite heart, and a real repentance; by relying upon the mercy of God, and put∣ting on a resolution of amendment of life, and perseverance therein. But the mischief is, that the honest people of this age, are not easily allur'd to furnish themselves ei∣ther with this same Faith or Patience. Then comes the holy See, compos'd of persons of high birth, that carry a great sway in public affairs, who observing that such Soul-physic was not at all toothsome to great Personages, and being unwilling that Beggars and Tatterdemallions should out-brave Kings and Grandees with their The∣ological vertues in the other World, have found out a more pleasing and quaint Ex∣pedient. For if you ask a Jesuit con∣cerning that nice and intricate sin of <HI>So∣domy,</HI> he'l fit your humour better then a Country Parson. He'l send you to <HI>Cardi∣nal Sourdis,</HI> who by his Bull alone, shall acquit ye both of <HI>Sodomy</HI> and <HI>Incest.</HI> He will put about your neck a wreath of the last requests by Master <HI>Jacques David,</HI> Bi∣shop of <HI>Eureux.</HI> If you are a <HI>French</HI>
<PB N="18" REF="16"/>
man, he will bestow upon ye certain grains of Paradise, out of the 19. <HI>Art.</HI> will cause ye to say certain words out of the 7. <HI>Art.</HI> as <HI>Domine Jesu, suscipe,</HI> and such like, which are printed at <HI>Paris</HI> by — And this Application rightly manag'd, gives ye a full and absolute Indulgence and Remissi∣on of all your sins, as well in reference to the Crime as to the Punishment. Which is expresly quoted by Monsieur Confessor as a new thing. For we said before, that Antiquity durst not be so hardy nor adven∣turous. Do ye think it strange then, that the Religion of the <HI>Huguenots,</HI> of which I will say what the learned <HI>Julian</HI> said of Christianism, that it was the Religion of Beggars and Vagabonds; I say, do you think it strange, that Kings, Princes, Pre∣lats, Cardinals, Popes and other Gran∣dees, should from the bottom of their hearts, abominate <HI>Huguenotism,</HI> and <HI>Hugue∣nots,</HI> and embrace a kind and favourable Religion, by the precepts and freedom whereof, the gates of Paradise are always open at a minutes warning? A Religion that affords Remedies for all transgressi∣ons and distempers, <HI>In</HI> Spain <HI>to the</HI> Cavalleros,<NOTE PLACE="inter"><HI>The</HI> Spanish <HI>Proverb.</HI></NOTE> <HI>in</HI> France <HI>to</HI> Lord <HI>and</HI> Pedant, <HI>in</HI> Germany <HI>to few, but in</HI> Italy <HI>to all in general.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="19" REF="16"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. III. Of the Intercession of He-Saints and She-Saints.</HEAD>
<P>OUr Gallants for want of Arguments prove the most part of the points in Contoversie by pleasant Similitudes, and jocular Comparisons. As for Example you shall see how we prove the Intercession of the <HI>He-Saints,</HI> and <HI>She-Saints.</HI> 'Twas ne∣ver known that all persons whatsoever went higglede pigglede to present their Petitions to the King, but by the Media∣tion of others, as Princes, Princesses, Coun∣sell<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs of State, and Masters of Request. <HI>Er∣go,</HI> we must believe that the Male and Fe∣male Saints order the Affairs of Heaven, as we order our affairs on Earth. And here I might undertake to prove that God never concerns himself with the affairs of this World, by the help of the same compari∣son. True it is, that that Heretic <HI>Rosny</HI> will have him take another course; and acts the Publican and the honest man both to∣gether, contrary to the Maxim, <HI>That two con∣traries
<PB N="20" REF="17"/>
cannot subsist in the same subject.</HI> I hope that one of the two will submit by the assistance of my Conversion, and the Inter∣cession of the Saints. Who doubts the Ef∣ficacy of Saints Intercession? Consider that no crimes have been so great within these 15 years, but that both the crime and the pu∣nishment have been quite abolish'd by their Prayers. No services have been so praise∣worthy, but that they, who thought to steal a reward, without the Intercession of these holy Persons, have been deceiv'd, and have lost their time and the acknowledgment which they deserv'd. This is that which <HI>Hortman</HI> observ'd in his Book <HI>de Regno Ʋulvarum.</HI> I shall have no great trouble to persuade them to believe this point, who have had business to do since my raigne. The General of the League having but two places that held out for him, could not re∣concile himself with this King as he did with the other on purpose to entrap him. By that he gain'd more than by catching cold in his Trenches. The Raigning Saint had given him a general pardon, and plac'd him in the highest place of the Terrestrial Paradise. Madam <HI>de Montpensier,</HI> whom we would hang in <HI>Effigie,</HI> has in the same manner expiated the Assassination of the late King. <HI>Villeroy</HI> has also luckily made
<PB N="21" REF="17"/>
his peace the same way. <HI>Sourdis</HI> the Oncle recover'd <HI>Chartres,</HI> and that head which totter'd upon his shoulders, but they did not give him the Master-ship of the Horse, because the Pages began to ride uneasily, which produc'd the following short Lam∣poon.</P>
<Q><L>And must <HI>Sourdis</HI> lose his wages?</L>
<L>What's the Crime that thus enforces?</L>
<L>Oh! he spurrs the little Pages,</L>
<L>Instead of spurring the great Horses.</L></Q>
<P>Without the help of this Saint, <HI>Le Grand</HI> had also been expell'd; but he carry'd a Candle to the Saint rather then to his me∣rits. I have tak'n away my sons from <HI>Ro∣chel,</HI> and will not have them any more to study either Greek or Hebrew; but will or∣der 'em to learn the Sciences of Monsieur <HI>de Lignerac, Varenne, Cachat,</HI> and <HI>La Bastide,</HI> who will teach them to say their <HI>Ora pro nobis's</HI> with a good Grace. Let 'em know their hours according to the Custom of <HI>Chartres</HI>; say yes, and ask what was said, and to faign being a fool, be so in good earnest. If they see any nastiness at Court, I would have them to be punish'd if they have Noses to smell it. Let 'em learn, like Monsieur <HI>d' Espernon</HI> the little Images of the
<PB N="22" REF="18"/>
Court, assist them to wipe their tayls; nay offer their tongue, if there be neither Linnen nor Paper in the way. By that means they shall obtain an Intercession, and that Inter∣cession is All-sufficient. <HI>Lignerac</HI> can do nothing but laugh; he that is the <HI>Amalga∣ma</HI> or Cement of the two houses of <HI>Estrees</HI> and <HI>Lorain. Cachat</HI> knows more than on∣ly how to speak <HI>French.</HI> He it was that made the Peace of <HI>Provence. Varenne</HI> began to learn to read but last Winter, and yet he made up the Peace of <HI>France</HI> at the same time. Intercessions thus bestow the merit, as well as the reward. And therefore we have it thus in our Prayer-Books, <HI>Da nobis ut mereamur fieri participes, &amp;c.</HI> Words which the <HI>Huguenots</HI> that laugh at them, do not understand at all.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="23" REF="18"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. IV. Of Purgatory.</HEAD>
<P>GEntlemen, since you Courtiers will have a Purgatory, we must of neces∣sity find out a place for this Purgatory, without going to seek it in St. <HI>Patrick</HI>'s hole, as <HI>Henry Stevens</HI> discourses in his A∣pology for <HI>Herodotus.</HI> I find what he says to be very smooth and pleasing, but it is not at all approv'd by the <HI>Sorbon.</HI> Tru∣ly were I to manage this business like a Divine, I fear me, I should be very much puzzl'd. I went and consulted Monsieur Confessor, who laugh'd at their Curiosity; I ask'd him, where any mention was made of Purgatory in the Holy Scriptures: But he produc'd me nothing but dark and doubt∣ful Sentences, whence there was nothing of Truth to be collected. I enquir'd con∣cerning the Fathers; he told me, St. <HI>Austin</HI> spake of Purgatory in his 11. Book upon <HI>Genesis.</HI> In his Comment upon St. <HI>John,</HI> Treat. 47. And in his Book of the City of God <HI>c.</HI> 8. And in several other places, but finding nothing to the purpose, I resolv'd to surcease all farther Theological Scrutinies.
<PB N="24" REF="19"/>
to say truth, my Divinity-reading has quite bauk'd me; and I defie the whole <HI>Sorbon</HI> to tell me where it is. I also desire to know where that <HI>third party</HI> is, so much talk'd of in <HI>France</HI>; the dread whereof strook a far∣ther stroak to the King's Conversion then that of Purgatory. Now I maintain that I find this same Purgatory, and this third Party are lodg'd both together at <HI>Nogent.</HI> Some there are that place Purgatory in <HI>Au∣vergne,</HI> where they have also confin'd the Count of <HI>Auvergne.</HI> But he is deliver'd from this Ambulatorie Purgatory at this fortunate juncture of time, when all the fair Rooms in Paradise are all richly hung, and magnificently furnish'd for the Sons of Strumpets. He has nothing but laugh'd at the overturning of his Coach-man, and is ready to re-establish in that Sacred place those <HI>Amours,</HI> of which he was instructed in his absence. There are some other little Purgatories in <HI>France,</HI> but they make no great noise, because that pardons are so cheap there. The Grand Purgatory is then at <HI>Nogent,</HI> where the Count of <HI>Soissons</HI> at his Vestals fire, purifies his own Train, which is the <HI>Third Party</HI>; there where he hears talk of the joys of the Paradise of the Court, and laughs at them after the manner of St. <HI>Medard.</HI> Some Angels or Mercuries, such
<PB N="25" REF="19"/>
as <HI>Varenne,</HI> will visit him as they pass by: and they say, he will take leave of his good Lady, and return to undergo his full suffe∣rings. The other imaginary accomplices of the <HI>Third Party,</HI> wandering thereabout, as be∣ing vagabond Souls for want of Earth and Bastions to interr them. They farther say that <HI>Nogent</HI> is a very proper place to play at Fiste-Cuffs in; and that the <HI>Third Party</HI> which constrain'd the King to his Conver∣sion, will soon compel him to persecute the <HI>Huguenots,</HI> or to make his condition alter∣native. The Count of <HI>Lude,</HI> having some∣time since tak'n me for his Chieftain, ask∣ed of me whether I did not think his for∣tune to be very good. When you ride Post, said I, do you take any pleasure in a Jade whose knees are brok'n? He answer'd me, no. Consider then, that when this great Captain quitted the Deceas'd King's Party, on purpose to turn <HI>Huguenot</HI>; and then left the <HI>Huguenots,</HI> for that they had seen him set his tayl in the Manger at <HI>Courtrac,</HI> when he mutiny'd against all the appearances of the battells, and avenues of the Duke of <HI>Parma,</HI> when he ravish'd <HI>Madam</HI> invisibly, he has a Cure for all these accidents, as having seven times clapt his knees upon the ground. Now my dear friend Monsieur <HI>Le Comte,</HI> would you lay your Saddle upon an over-ridden
<PB N="26" REF="20"/>
Hackney, with broken knees to boot? By such arguments as these have I seduc'd the Constable of the <HI>Third Party</HI> out of the Pur∣gatory of <HI>Nogent. Laverdin</HI> would have thrust his Nose in; but they demanded mo∣ney for his entrance; he told me he had made such a regulation in the first Army of the <HI>Third Party,</HI> that it should never oppress the people. And in truth I find that the Great Officers of the Exchequer and the Magazines have had leisure enough.</P>
<P>To this purpose they quote me the An∣swer which the King made, when the Count wrote to him, that he lay there to pray to God. The King to be quit with him sent him word, That he would take care to the end his prayers might be the more perfect, that they should not want fasting. The Thunder of St. <HI>Denis</HI> was found to be too violent for a Purgatory-fire, and forc'd the Thunderer to surcease his Determination. The <HI>Tayl of Bourbon,</HI> whom the <HI>Huguenots</HI> call the head of <HI>Marotte,</HI> and which Mon∣sieur <HI>William</HI> never took for a man but for a shadow; This diminutive Priest turn'd over his Breviary, and met by good fortune with this Text of the Gospel, <HI>Non habet fili∣us hominis ubi requiescat caput</HI>; and there∣upon he said to <HI>Bellozone</HI> (he for whose sake
<PB N="27" REF="20"/>
it was reported, that my Wife is fair a∣mong the Asses;) that is to say, that my Brother has no place that holds for us. But Monsieur <HI>William</HI> opposes him, and says, that there are four places still left for the <HI>Third Party,</HI> places well protected from the fire of Heaven, <HI>Sodom, Gomorra, Adma,</HI> and <HI>Iseboin.</HI> The Author of the Visions of the said Master <HI>William</HI> treats very largely upon this subject. I shall conclude this Chapter, with a Remonstrance to the Au∣thors of the <HI>Third Party,</HI> and of the third Place. Know then most zealous Catholics, that this Party is neither condemn'd nor absolv'd, as having done neither good nor harm, and therefore only reduc'd to Purga∣tory. Your misery is, that you are not authoriz'd by men of courage, but only by such as call cowardice, patience. The Pope has not establish'd Purgatory only by words. It was not your business to raise so many Disputes about the Princes of the blood; the Pope has setl'd Purgatory by fulmina∣tions, and you must have an Army of Thun∣derers for your design. He shews the Keys of St. <HI>Peter,</HI> as infallible Openers, not only of the Gates of Heaven, but of the purses of all Fools in general. There's a necessity also for the <HI>pains</HI> of St. <HI>Paul</HI> to be even with those that oppose the Decretals, and to
<PB N="28" REF="21"/>
establish the Third place. Thus when the <HI>Lutherans</HI> would dispute it out, they were made to feel the fire of Purgatory by burn∣ing them, that mis-believ'd it. When the <HI>Huguenots</HI> attacqu'd the Spiritual Ca∣nons, they made use of the Temporal. So that upon occasion I have compar'd the Third Party to <HI>Purgatory</HI> which was only in <HI>Potentia.</HI> The other was never in Act, and indeed the Question is of no great Im∣portance, witness—who at sixty years of age, marry'd a young maid of twenty, of whom he grew as jealous as a Tigre, and of a most jealous old Fool was made a most Catholic Cuckold. A∣gainst which he us'd all the Applications of <HI>Hans Carvell.</HI> His friends asking him one day, how he came to play the fool so? Af∣ter he had rubb'd his Ears, and wip'd his Fore head, scratching the hinder part of his Pole, with a down-cast look upon the Evi∣dences of his frailty; These <HI>Huguenots,</HI> said he, are the cause of my misfortunes. For in former times our Ancestors had a resting place to bait by the way, as they went to Paradise, but now these Tatterdemallions have dismantl'd Purgatory, we must go di∣rectly to Heaven, therefore I got me thi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Hackney to ride now and then, as I saw occasion, but never dreamt she would hav<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> stumbl'd at this rate.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="29" REF="21"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. V. Of Justification by Works, and of other Acts of Merit.</HEAD>
<P>ACcording to this holy method of ar∣guing points of Divinity by Simili∣tudes, there is no necessity for all Christians to trust to the Intercession of Saints. For there are a sort of honest people and of very good fashion, who gain Heaven without it, by their own brave and good deeds; as by the taking of one <HI>Rouen,</HI> to be made Com∣manders of <HI>Tholouse, Narbonne, Carcasson,</HI> and other places. Another to be made Go∣vernour of <HI>Orleance, Bourges,</HI> and the depen∣dancies, another of <HI>Poictiers</HI>; another of the three Frontiers of <HI>Bretaigne.</HI> These are works by God's Authority, which have been justifi'd; and without saying, <HI>ut mereamur,</HI> they have merited, or at least obtain'd ge∣neral pardon and favour. They that wrought these meritorious deeds have guelt the public Exchequers and are justifi'd thereby. Let the Heretics with their St. <HI>Paul</HI> preach Faith and Grace as long as they
<PB N="30" REF="22"/>
please, these with their St. <HI>James</HI> F.— St. <HI>James</HI> of <HI>Spain,</HI> have prov'd their faith by their works. Upon this ground it is, vain <HI>Huguenots,</HI> that we must not admit Ju∣stification of works to be difficult, after such works have been justifi'd. They have ob∣tain'd a Law, and this Law has been a Law of Grace; but when you shall have an oc∣casion to require a Law, yours shall be so lean and meagre, and got with so much trouble, that you shall be forc'd to confess with me, that there is a necessity of <HI>Impetus</HI> by works, and not of faith; you do not be∣lieve in the Popes Indulgences. Now mark but the Indulgencies of a King, who is not a Pope, and we shall find that these good works which you make scruple to justifie, are become so meritorious as to have gain'd poor <HI>Villars</HI> the Admiralty of <HI>France.</HI> Other Marshals, though they have no Mints of their own, yet can coyn what money they please. And whereas other superstitious Hypocrites spend their time &amp; their money to buy pardons for so many thousand years; these can shew ye thousands of Crowns got in a few months. Insomuch that the pay∣ments of the merits of the League being cast up, the whole sum amounted to above se∣ven millions, seven hundred and sixty thousand Crowns. More then this, these
<PB N="31" REF="22"/>
good works have extended their benefits and supererogations to others, who have taken lesser Towns and Villages under the chief Leader, so that the Followers have been canoniz'd for the super-abounding merit of the Commander. I do not bring into this rank, either <HI>Merceur</HI> or <HI>Espernon.</HI> They are yet to know more, what it is to trust in works. Now then let us see who they are that are so diligent in prese<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ving their faith to their King and Countrey, believing <HI>That the just shall live by faith.</HI> These are they <HI>That do deeds worthy of Repentance,</HI> but not good works, not considering that faith without works al-a-mode is a dead faith. Whence it comes to pass, that some are starv'd to death; others attend in the low Court of the <HI>Loure,</HI> mangl'd Captains, consumptive Majors, maim'd Soldiers, wooden-leg'd Engineers, Spies and Dis∣coverers, with their Stockins out at heels, that walk all together in the <HI>Switzers</HI>-Hall, and have nothing to do, but to ex∣claim against Madam Ingratitude <HI>in genere petitorio, non suasorio.</HI> Captains carrying the Basket, the poor Soldiers the Mattock; some shewing their wounds, others num∣bring the fights they have been in; the E∣states they have lost, some mutt'ring libels, others modelling a Reformation, and others
<PB N="32" REF="23"/>
studying where to get a meal upon the Coin of Reputation. But some person or other will say, have not all these poor Miscreants by your relation toil'd sufficiently? Tell us some of their works; I answer, they were works of Iniquity, in regard it is an ill thing to serve the ingrateful: And <HI>Limaille</HI> re∣proaching the King with the long continu∣ance of his services, and his patience; and how he had render'd himself irreconcileable to his neighbours for having faithfully exe∣cuted his Majestie's commands, concluded his discourse with telling him he had not wherewithal to buy himself a Dinner: <HI>Ven∣tre St. Gri,</HI> said the King, who was not wont to swear after the <HI>Roman</HI> manner, my Kingdom has been a pillaging for these so many years last past, why did not you rob something for your self? Rob as the rest do. <HI>Nothing,</HI> shews that works of that na∣ture are not works; and by consequence unworthy of reward. The poor man con∣tinu'd to his dying day, and considering his condition, carry'd off the greatest share of the honour of the Siege of <HI>Amiens,</HI> where he dy'd in the Mines of the Wall; and this is call'd <HI>doing nothing.</HI> He that would see this subject more learnedly handl'd, let him read the King's Apology, compos'd by Monsieur <HI>Catrier,</HI> then chief Minister to <HI>Ma∣dam.</HI>
<PB N="33" REF="23"/>
The King shew'd it me for the style of <HI>Madam de Rohan.</HI> An Apology full of prevarication, which <HI>Roquellaure</HI> hearing read, cry'd out, <HI>Mort dieu,</HI> They that wrote this, how much do they know of our busi∣ness? Some there are who accuse <HI>La Ruffie,</HI> in regard that after a discourse concerning the humor of the King, which was to punish good Services, and recompence Crimes, he said to them that complained of his Majesty, you ought to blame your selves not him. For since you understand his humor, if you expect rewards, you should do well to me∣rit them by works worthy of recompence. After that, he speaks of those who have the honour to be a kin to his Majesty; and those he renders worse us'd, then the mea∣ner Servants; which makes me suspect <HI>La Ruffie</HI> to be the Author of this writing, wherein he calls himself one of the King's kinsmen. Witness the speech that his de∣ceas'd Mother made to <HI>Madam</HI> at <HI>Bergerac, I recommend, said she, to your care that poor knave,</HI> La Ruffie. You have more reason to love him, then any other; <HI>For the same rea∣son that I have known the King your Father.</HI> So have many others besides you, reply'd <HI>Madam.</HI> To which the <HI>Perigordine</HI> made answer, <HI>so vostra gratia prou intendi so l'honordi die garde &amp; de la Compania, Carnaument.</HI>
<PB N="34" REF="24"/>
Afterwards <HI>La Ruffie</HI> was honor'd with the Office of a Spie at <HI>Chastellerault,</HI> where he did a deserving act, for he stole certain pa∣pers, and was made Counsellor of State, and Cuckold general under pay. He that desires to read more of this Story may read the Last Will and Testament of <HI>Salbeuf,</HI> a Gentleman of <HI>Gascognie,</HI> who though he were a good Catholic, accompany'd the K. in his flight from <HI>Paris</HI> untill the Siege, sold seven Horses which belong'd to his Train, making known to the King his daily losses. At length shame drave him away from the Court. But the desire he had to dye in his Prince's service, detain'd him in the Army, where he listed himself in one of the Com∣panies of the Guards, commanded by his younger Brother. It happen'd that when the Cannons had ruin'd the shops under the Gate <HI>St. Honorè,</HI> this very person de∣sir'd to be set the outmost Sentinel in the Ruins: whereupon, the King visiting his Guards, and his Approaches in the night-time, the Captain from the corner of a house, shew'd him his Eldest Brother. The King seeing himself touch'd so to the quick, went away without speaking one word. Some few days afterward, this poor Gentleman having again try'd the inclination of his Prince, at length o'recome with grief and
<PB N="35" REF="24"/>
labour of body dy'd; and though unlear∣ned, made his Will; wherein he first beg'd pardon of God and then of the King his Master, for having serv'd him in his Amours with <HI>Katharine de Luc d' Agen,</HI> and several others; some of whom were also themselves starv'd to death with the Children which they had by the King. There was also much about the same time another Will made by the younger Son of the Chancel∣lor of the Hospital, who having left his E∣state, betook himself to attend the King in all his afflictions, and to stick to the Faith and Religion of his party, who thinking to have found a Sanctuary for his Errors at <HI>Quillebeuf,</HI> which of a small Village was made a Garrison, was shamefully repuls'd and disgrac'd by the Sieur <HI>du Plessis.</HI> There∣upon pronouncing with his own mouth, the Sentence of his death, he call'd for Pa∣per, and made his Will, which contain'd much of the same subject: but more openly and plainly detecting the King's secrets: but his servants, violated the last commands of their Master, and surrender'd up the Copy, which as they say fully justifi'd my opinion concerning the Justification of Works.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="36" REF="25"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. VI. Of Miracles and Pilgrimages.</HEAD>
<P>THE Deceas'd Cardinal, of happy me∣mory, in regard of his birth, as be∣ing of the house of <HI>Lorrain,</HI> understand∣ing that the Marshal <HI>de Fervaques,</HI> of hap∣py memory also, had discover'd a young Girl, whom <HI>Belovet</HI> the Priest, otherwise call'd the holy man, had instructed how to counterfeit a <HI>Demoniac,</HI> or person possess'd with a Devil, on purpose to make out a Miracle the <HI>Easter</HI> following; this great Pre∣late pronounc'd <HI>Fervaques</HI> guilty of a high peice of Impiety, saying, That though Mi∣racles were false, they were useful to make out pious frauds: and certainly he did a very great kindness to the Country; for in a place uninhabited before, in three years there were built up above fourscore Houses, and fifty Inns, which nevertheless were not sufficient to entertain the Pilgrims that came from all parts, and some of them Personages of great Quality living in other Countries. Now, were there no other Miracle then that of the building of the
<PB N="37" REF="25"/>
Houses, the far spreading, and the long continuance of an opinion firmly and really believ'd without any foundation, me∣thinks there is no Schismatic, but should con∣fess it to be somewhat strange; and indeed this it is which madds the Heretics, to see the people enflam'd with zealous intenti∣ons. True it is, that I would fain ad∣monish the good Fathers that manage these things to carry their business a litle more prudently and closely. He that taught the Demoniac of <HI>Laon</HI> to bid us labour the ex∣tirpation of the Hereticks or <HI>Huguenots</HI> was a mere fool; for, as <HI>Postell</HI> observes, That would seem to intimate that the Devil is the commander of our happiness. There∣fore when Prelats design any such Inven∣tions, which are not well laid, or well disguiz'd, they ought to dress them up a∣gain, polish and put a value upon them, not by opposing them, as did the Bishop of <HI>Angers</HI> when two young religious Friers, full of <HI>zeal,</HI> brought him a young Lady, ex∣actly instructed in demonology, who play'd her part so well, that she play'd the Devil for God's sake. The Bishop caus'd the Demoniac to be brought before him, and made a most nice inquisition into the busi∣ness. He demanded which were the most violent signs by which they conjectur'd
<PB N="38" REF="26"/>
her to be so cramm'd with Devils. One of the <HI>Devil-masters</HI> made answer, That there were two things by which they knew the violence of her Torments; one was, if her skin were touch'd with any Cross, but e∣specially one that were made of the Wood of the true Cross; the other was, by her bounding, and leaping, and yelling, and roaring, when any Text of the Gospel was read to her. The Bishop had then about his neck one of those Crosses of which we shall speak in the Chapter of Relicques. For his Father, from whom I learnt the most secret passages of the deceas'd King's life, could not want Jewels that was so dex∣trous as he was, and so often entrusted with the King's Jewels. One of the <HI>Devil-teachers</HI> espying this Cross, pull'd up the Maid's Coats, almost as high as her Knee, as she lay upon the ground, and desir'd the Prelate to touch her skin gently with the Cross. Upon which this wicked Bishop pulls off his Cross indeed, but at the same time slily pulls out a Key out of his pocket, and touches the Girle's Leg; She, no sooner felt the cold of the Key, but she almost frighted the people out of their wits to see what Curvets and Capers she made. To make the second proof, the Bishop pull'd out of his pocket a <HI>Petronius
<PB N="39" REF="26"/>
Arbiter,</HI> instead of his <HI>Breviary,</HI> and began to read <HI>Matrona quaedam</HI> Ephesi: With that she fell a foaming at the mouth, and won∣der-working at a prodigious rate, but when the Bishop came to read <HI>placitone eti∣am pugnabis amore?</HI> The Devil, who ne∣ver lov'd in his life, grew so impatient, that the poor Creature not able to endure his twinges, sounded away upon the floor: upon that, the Bishop, like a demi-<HI>Luthe∣ran,</HI> said, he could not smother such an imposture: but he had not read an ancient Doctor, who says 'tis better to let people go on in their Superstition, then spoil their Devotion. The Bishop was well reprov'd for his rashness, so that he did not shew himself so much a misbeliever to the se∣cond Demoniac that was presented to him, whose name was <HI>Martha,</HI> and brought by an honest <HI>Capuchin.</HI> She had two Devils within her, the one was call'd <HI>Belzebub,</HI> and the other <HI>Astarot.</HI> The first was a chur∣lish, boystrous, hectoring Devil, a great E∣nemy to the <HI>Huguenots</HI>; he fought with all the World, and he had drubb'd Mon∣sieur <HI>Matros</HI> of <HI>Angiers</HI> himself, had he not taken a good Cudgel in his hand, cry∣ing out, Mr. Fly-catcher <HI>Belzebub,</HI> if thou playest thy tricks with me, I will swinge thee like a Devil indeed. <HI>Astarot</HI> was an
<PB N="40" REF="27"/>
honest Devil, young and gentle, who de∣sir'd that <HI>Martha</HI> should be well treated and handsomely clad; in which Equipage she was presented to the Clergy of <HI>Angiers.</HI> The Clergy desir'd that these two Devils of quality should be first examin'd by the Church. One of the Judges of the City said, that it concern'd their Honour, and upon the Examination of these two Spirits began to speak Latin, and then Greek; at that <HI>Belzebub</HI> began to be in wroth and told 'em, if they would, he would answer 'em as well in Greek as in Latin; but the Capuchin, to furnish the Devils with an excuse, reply'd, my friend <HI>Belzebub,</HI> you must know that here are Heretics in the Room, and therefore I advise ye not to speak at all. Then they went to posing of <HI>Astarot,</HI> but he excus'd himself by reason of his Youth. <HI>Belzebub</HI> made his excuse by saying he was a poor Devil. Upon that a∣rose a great dispute, whether the Devils were bound to go to School. The Lawyers maintain'd, that it was proper <HI>in quarto modo</HI> for Demoniacks to speak all Langua∣ges, as he did at <HI>Cartigni</HI> in <HI>Savoy,</HI> who was try'd in 16 Tongues: So that the Mi∣nisters at <HI>Geneva</HI> durst not attempt to exor∣cise him. They of <HI>Angiers</HI> were more hardy, who began thus, <HI>Commando tibi ut
<PB N="41" REF="27"/>
exeas</HI> Belzebub <HI>&amp;</HI> Astarot, <HI>aut ego augmen∣tabo vestras poenas et vobis dabo acriores.</HI> The second time he was more fierce, <HI>Jubeo ut exeatis super poenam Excommunicationis ma∣joris &amp; minoris.</HI> The third time in a pelt∣ing chafe, <HI>Nisi vos exeatis,</HI> said he, <HI>vos re∣lego &amp; confino in infernum centum annos plus quam Deus exordinavit.</HI> The Counsellours were about to laugh, and to have disco∣ver'd the fraud, but the people mutiny'd, and the Bishop to make his peace, alleg'd that he had suppress'd a Catholic Printer by Excommunication, who was about to print a book of <HI>Duplessis,</HI> and that if they pleas'd, he would excommunicate <HI>Haut∣tain</HI> of <HI>Rochel.</HI> That which is the great∣est blot to the Reputation of these incar∣nate <HI>mock-shews</HI> is, that the affront re∣dounds to our Lady of <HI>Ardilliers,</HI> there be∣ing a necessity for her Curate to cast out Devils by the power, and in the name of that good Lady, that scorn'd to stir at the name of God; which has mainly augment∣ed the devotion and number of her <HI>Pil∣grims.</HI> Some said, that this Miracle was reserv'd for precedencie's sake, to Frier <HI>Ange, Lugulis,</HI> Lievtenant to the grand Provost, and a great Adversary of these Fable-mongers, who would make us all turn Heretics; <HI>but if I believe 'em,</HI> quo
<PB N="42" REF="28"/>
he, <HI>would I were hang'd.</HI> When I reply'd, that he did not do well to speak so plain∣ly, he made answer; that there were two thousand Souls in Heaven, and as many upon Earth, that would answer for him, that he was no <HI>Huguenot</HI>: we laugh'd at him, and would not suffer him to raise the <HI>Huguenots</HI> blood, seeing so many lame, blind, deaf, leaprous in mind, as well as body, flocking to our Lady of <HI>Ardilliers,</HI> and the whole Level full of comers and goers, who if they are not cur'd, it is for want of Faith, as <HI>Belovet</HI> told his <HI>Pil∣grims.</HI> And therefore you are not to be scandaliz'd, to see the diseased return as they came; for the operation of the Miracle never appears, till after beleif. Upon which score that Preist persuaded some of the blind to say they did see, and some of the deaf to say they did hear when they did not. He had never a trick in his budget to help the crooked and lame, and therefore they had nothing to say, but only this, that they could not go at all be∣fore they were brought thither. Accord∣ing to that, <HI>Obedientiam expostulat Eccle∣sia.</HI> Or as <HI>Bernardus Ochinus</HI> says, <HI>That the Miracles of the Mass are invisible.</HI> He that knows not his Trade, must shut up his Shop. Could but the Heretics convert
<PB N="43" REF="28"/>
into Miracles, the Cures which are done at the Hot-baths, they would have a fine time on't, and therefore our people have dextrously canoniz'd the foundations of <HI>Pougnes,</HI> and every where else establish'd very passable natural Miracles. It behoves us to give a small sample of the Miracles of our good Lady, that shall endure to the Resurrection, by the notable story ensu∣ing; <HI>Madam de la Chastre,</HI> being become extraordinary jealous of her Husband, and of one of her Daughters, reconcil'd her self to the <HI>Sieur de Montigni,</HI> to whom she had bin an utter Enemy before the Wars. Neither was there any need of much invi∣tation to recal him to her friendship, in re∣gard he was very much a freind to <HI>La Marcoussi.</HI> The first office of Reconcilia∣tion was to kill <HI>La Berthelemy,</HI> the Disco∣verer of the Amours of the Father and the Daughter. And it was probable enough that the Murder would take effect, in re∣gard that she had in truth combin'd a∣gainst <HI>Montigni.</HI> After all satisfaction and content in the beleif of the execution, comes post to the House, riding a straddle, <HI>Madam Avoy de St. Lawrence of the waters,</HI> who after she had made the sign of the Cross, began the harangues of <HI>Nathan</HI> and <HI>David.</HI> Which being done, these two fair La∣dies
<PB N="44" REF="29"/>
resolve after Confession, to go and do Penance at <HI>Ardeliers.</HI> Madam <HI>Avoye</HI> cau∣ses a new habit to be got for her self; the habit of Madam <HI>La Castre</HI> was put on by <HI>Suardaine,</HI> and she put on the habit of Ma∣dam <HI>Avoye:</HI> The Mistress call'd her self <HI>Madamoiselle de St. Lawrens, La Sour∣daine</HI> went by the name of <HI>Celestine.</HI> Be∣ing come to <HI>Ardilliers,</HI> the Curate of the place heard the Confession of the Murder, with sighs and sobs: but at length it was concluded first by the Curate, and then by <HI>Celestine,</HI> that our Lady should repair this loss rather by a Resurrection, then by an Intercession. By which means it came to pass that the poor — — which was thought to have bin buried, was rais'd a∣gain through the merits of the Curate. A most delicate Vision, when after nine days, Madam <HI>Celestine</HI> lying prostrate before the Altar; her Mistress, <HI>Madamoiselle St. Lau∣rens,</HI> holding the Curate by the tail, that the <HI>Host</HI> (for there were no other Witnesses) should behold the plump <HI>La Berthelemie</HI> come from behind the Altar; who throw∣ing her winding sheet to the ground came forward to pardon her Mistress, then habited like a penitent Sister; who presently fell upon her knees before the naked Soul, which she took at first for an apparition,
<PB N="45" REF="29"/>
but finding her entire and every part safe and sound, Madam <HI>Avoye</HI> ran to embrace her, Madam <HI>La Chastre</HI> kiss'd her; after that they interkiss'd one another, and the Curate kiss'd 'em all four. The main trou∣ble was to cover the nakedness of the par∣ty risen, for the Pilgrims were out of pa∣tience to find the Doors of the Chappel so long shut: Thereupon Madam <HI>Avoye,</HI> and Madam <HI>La Chastre</HI> divided their own Vestments: Madam <HI>La Chastre</HI> gave her her▪ Petty-coat, and <HI>Celestine</HI> gave her her Cap, and so they carry'd her, crying out <HI>a Miracle, a Miracle,</HI> to the Curat's House, where <HI>Montigni</HI> lay conceal'd. He that would know the rest of the story, may see the Process in the Grand Council, which will not be cancell'd this Shrovetide, whatever it be the next. The Heretics commenting upon the Story, say, That it was a Sheep which <HI>Montigni</HI> murder'd, <HI>La Berthelemie</HI> her self had buri'd it in a Garret, and afterwards <HI>Madam de la Cha∣stre,</HI> when she had danc'd the Canaries a∣bout the blood, and sung an <HI>I am reveng'd, La Berthelemie</HI> return'd, and assisted to draw away the dead body, and so threw it into the house of Office. They say also, that it was <HI>Montigni</HI> who caus'd Madam <HI>Avoye</HI> to take Post, to scare that
<PB N="46" REF="30"/>
enrag'd Woman out of her house, to the end that while she was from home, they might the better send away <HI>La Berthelemy</HI> from <HI>Boyancy,</HI> and convey her to <HI>Sau∣mur,</HI> where she might be useful to her Be∣nefactor, after her Resurrection, in his <HI>A∣mours.</HI> They say, That the Curate of <HI>Ar∣dilliers</HI> was pay'd in good flesh, which <HI>La Berthelemy</HI> provided for him during the nine dayes; but that he found <HI>Madam de</HI> St. <HI>Lawrence</HI> and <HI>Celestine</HI> so lean, that he was satisfi'd with one meal. I could tell ye the whole Story, the Prisons broken, the Skirmishes between the Guards of <HI>Ma∣reschal de la Chastre,</HI> and the Ladies Pages, the Preparatives of <HI>Marcussi</HI> to poyson his Wife. But the Secretary of <HI>Molier</HI> of <HI>Poictou</HI> has wrote a Relation thereof to celebrate the Miracle, after which I was sa∣tisfi'd that it went somewhat beyond the limits of Theology. I will conclude this Chapter with the Epitaph made at <HI>Ardilli∣ers</HI> by Madam <HI>Avoye</HI> in the style of St. <HI>Innocent.</HI></P>
<Q><L>Here she lyes, yet lyeth not;</L>
<L>A Mutton in her place was put.</L>
<L>Nor did <HI>Montigni,</HI> as they cry,</L>
<L>Murder plump <HI>Barthelemie.</HI></L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="30"/>That she was kill'd is truely said,</L>
<L>Because she shew'd her self so busie</L>
<L>To pimp for Wife of young <HI>Marcussi;</HI></L>
<L>But the Preist of <HI>Ardilliers</HI></L>
<L>Rais'd her sweetly by his prayers,</L>
<L>When fifteen Months she had bin dead.</L></Q>
<P>If you find this Sepulcher in any other place, the treaty of Miracles requires it at your hands.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VII. Of the Relicques and Devotions of the deceas'd King.</HEAD>
<P>ONe of the things which mov'd me most of all to contemn the Church, was to read certain books, which are utterly suppress'd (heaven be prais'd) at this time, as the <HI>Book of the Merchands,</HI> the <HI>Christian Knight, Ransack and Fragments between the Pope and Christ.</HI> But above all, the In∣ventory of Relicques; with several others which I will not name, for fear of sending to read them Wits too curious of their Sal∣vation, and too much enclin'd to reject the
<PB N="48" REF="31"/>
works of authentic writers. One day I saw an <HI>Austin</HI> Frier, with a wallet on his back, crying out, Will ye buy any Para∣dise. A <HI>Huguenot</HI> saw me scandaliz'd at the passage, and took his time to shew me all those little books which I forbid all persons whatever for the repose of their Consciences to read, who intend to live at rest and quiet in the Catholic Religion. It is known that I have bin thirteen times an Embassadour, for which reason, as I have travel'd at another mans Cost, I have bin so ill adviz'd, as to justifie this inventory of Relicques, and another book entitl'd, <HI>Le Cose mara vigliose del alma Città di Roma The wonderful things of our Mother Church of</HI> Rome, printed at the same place, <HI>Anno</HI> 1545. with Licence of the Superiours, by <HI>Giovanni Osmarino Gigliolo.</HI> This book confirms the Inventory which <HI>Calvin</HI> made. This I found in my Travels, and the reading of such books taught me to contemn the Relicques of Saints, finding 15 or 16 Bodies of St. <HI>Peter,</HI> 18 of St. <HI>Paul,</HI> seaven or eight Bodies of every Saint, ten thousand Martyrs buri'd in the compass of a small Chest; the prints of the footsteps of our Lord, and the An∣gels; the prints of the Buttocks of St. <HI>Fi∣acre en Brie</HI> upon a stone. At <HI>Josse</HI> in <HI>Au∣vergne,</HI>
<PB N="49" REF="31"/>
in <HI>Catalogne</HI> and other places, a lin∣nen cloth of the Virgin's own fowling; when she might have made the same excuse that <HI>Rachel</HI> did. The feathers of the Angel <HI>Gabriel.</HI> The Hatchet of <HI>Joseph</HI> the Carpen∣ter. The stones of the Window where the Angel enter'd. The Virgin's Milk: At <HI>Maille∣rais, in una parva pursa satini Rubri,</HI> the pa∣rings of her nailes. Several heads of St. <HI>Denis</HI> and St. <HI>John</HI>; in sundry places some of his blood, which they say boils upon his Festival day; and the sneezings of the Holy Ghost. As I was a Heretic, I laught at these things, and wondred at such a dis∣sipation of the members of the Saints, e∣specially when we reproach the <HI>Huguenots</HI> for having so far disturb'd their repose, as they have done already▪ I am also to desire the pardon of Monsieur Confessour. For I must confess in good earnest in this Chap∣ter, That I have laught at the great blessings and benefits, which he caus'd to be print∣ed the last year, for the reasons which the Reader shall find by what follows. I have strange stories to tell, to prove the virtue of Reliques. For I protest, I had rather see the <HI>Huguenots</HI> laugh at the great power and efficacies of St. <HI>Goyaux,</HI> then publish such stories as these, were they not com∣mon to Lacquayes and Pages. For we
<PB N="50" REF="32"/>
ought to conceal the Vices of our Princes: but since they are discover'd, we must seek to defend them by the authority of the Sta∣tutes of the Holy See. St. <HI>Luke</HI> was the first that discover'd the Mystery. For he fled to <HI>Brouage,</HI> when <HI>La Sarbarante</HI> and the <HI>Angel,</HI> which he counterfeited, to ter∣rifie his Master and rescue his own Carcass, were discover'd by his companion, the Duke of <HI>Joyeuse. Rochefort</HI> was too blame, to make the Anagram of St. <HI>Luke, Cats in cul.</HI> He poor boy abominated that sort of Villany, and was absolutely forc'd to it the first time; the King causing him to take a book out of a Chest, the cover of which the grand <HI>Prior</HI> and <HI>Carmelle</HI> clapt down upon his Reines; and this they call'd pri∣vately among themselves, <HI>taking the Hare in a trap.</HI> So clear it is that this honest Gentleman was forc'd to the trade, and thereupon so terrifi'd his Master, that he had either sorely repented or dy'd for it, had not the Duke of <HI>Joyeuse</HI> discover'd the en∣terprize, to prevent the utter ruine of his fortune. I do not think I do ill, to disco∣ver the story of the <HI>Tapistry-maker</HI>; for the King seeing him at the top of his two lad∣ders wiping the dirt from the Candlestics, became so enamour'd of him, that he fell a weeping before he went forth, and call'd
<PB N="51" REF="32"/>
out for Monsieur <HI>Le Grand</HI> to be sent for to him, who to him himself discover'd the love of one ey'd <HI>Reveillon,</HI> Captain of the Guides, who was laid hold upon, through impatience of expecting a young guide which he had promis'd; and those Amours of the Duke, and of <HI>Espernon,</HI> and He, when upon the very day of the death of the deceas'd King, he fell upon his knees in the Chamber, between the deceas'd King and him that is now living, before two hundred Gentlemen, and which is worse, the greatest part of them <HI>Hugue∣nots,</HI> at what time he cryed out, with tears in his eyes, Cousin, pardon me, for the King forc'd me to it at first, and I have not taken your place, to do you any wrong. <HI>Espernon</HI> asham'd, but better adviz'd, re∣ply'd, you talk like a Woman, I know not what you mean. <HI>Siblot</HI> at a public au∣dience, the King having sent for him to make sport, and inform'd him touching Master — who to cause him to re∣store a Livery Horse, fail'd in his bargain, to tax him with so much violence concern∣ing his Governour, but because he does not well explain his meaning, I shall say no more of it. However <HI>Loignac</HI> went a∣way snobbing and crying all the way to <HI>Poictiers,</HI> where being visited by the chief
<PB N="52" REF="33"/>
of the Town, who thought him still in fa∣vour, he made them sad complaints of his Honour lost, and of his being turn'd out of Service and not paid, almost all at the same time. After came to light those of the Wife of <HI>Salettes,</HI> by means of a Let∣ter taken, among the Baggage of the Duke of <HI>Joyeuse</HI> at <HI>Coutras.</HI> St. <HI>Severine,</HI> for this very act afterwards call'd the <HI>wild Colt,</HI> having escap'd out of the King's Ca∣binet, by the overturning of <HI>Duhalde</HI> and <HI>Soupitre,</HI> who kept the doors of the two high Chambers, fled among the Guards to tell the Marshal <HI>d'Aumont,</HI> that the King had sent <HI>Montigni</HI> to find him out; and that he, joyful to be admitted into the Ca∣binet, made hast away thither, where the King demanding of him, Who that Mistres<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> was, for the sake of whose love he could never have his company, and he again re∣plying in brok'n <HI>French, that if he had <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Mistress of Gold, he would serve none but hi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Majesty,</HI> the King made answer, I find yo<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> take the Womens part, but yet you a<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> not ignorant of the sacred and philosoph<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cal Love, <HI>who I,</HI> said St. <HI>Severin,</HI> I am <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Souldier, and no Philosopher. Here th<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dispute ended. For at the same time th<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Master laid hold of his Codpeice, <HI>Montig<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> flew to his neck, and Monsieur <HI>d'O.</HI> to h<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>
<PB N="53" REF="33"/>
points. Now they run after the poor Gen∣tleman to appease the Guards, dissatisfi'd with his Hat and his Cloak. The worst was, that the old <HI>French-man</HI> had like to have kill'd him, after he had heard his tale, Swearing he'd be hang'd if this were true. More then that, he must to Prison. That imprisonment compleated the Trage∣dy. He was kept close for a Month, and some say longer. True it is, that after∣wards he surrender'd himself to the Duke of <HI>Mayen</HI>: but those of <HI>Paris</HI> not believing this story, took him for a <HI>Zopyras,</HI> and sent him to be kept in safe Custody at St. <HI>Germaines de Prez</HI>; and some few Months after that, he was slain, together with two or three hundred Gentlemen more, at∣tempting to regain the City. Stories like these, and many others were brought by the Courrier of the Duke of <HI>Longuevile,</HI> from whom the King demanded the other Pacquet, before he had seen that of <HI>Papier</HI>; after which he return'd with his post-boy to carry the news of their actions into <HI>Pi∣cardie.</HI> The Constable's Courrier made the same complaints as far as <HI>Languedoc,</HI> above all things complaining of the Count of <HI>Mauleurier</HI> who produc'd him. But his Master reprehended him for bogling at a small matter, and sent him back again with
<PB N="54" REF="34"/>
his pacquets. Is not this enough to satis∣fie the World, that these secrets were not divulg'd by me alone? Should I relate what the Prince of <HI>Conde</HI> privately told me, when they spent a whole night highly pleas'd in the Apprentiship of the Count of <HI>Avergne</HI> to his Navel. Or should I relate the banishment of young <HI>Rosny,</HI> for being ill supply'd: Or of <HI>Noailles</HI> for having writ∣ten over his bed these Verses,
<Q><L>No happiness, no good contents me,</L>
<L>That from my Deity absents me.</L></Q></P>
<P>To which the King of <HI>Navar</HI> added with his own hand.</P>
<Q><L>Ne're exalt my Aunt so high,</L>
<L>She loves too well Humanity.</L></Q>
<P>By that, a discovery was made, that he lov'd women, contrary to the Rules of the Holy Love, which caus'd him to be kick'd out of doors, like the Duke of <HI>Longuevile,</HI> for requesting his Colours of the King by a Letter written in guilt Paper. Should I relate the Espousals of <HI>Quelus,</HI> and that other Contract signed with the blood of— and Monsieur <HI>O.</HI> by which he espoused Monsieur <HI>Le Grand.</HI> Should I rehearse the
<PB N="55" REF="34"/>
words of that Prince, kneeling by the body of dead <HI>Maugiron,</HI> with his lips where they ought not to have been, I should displease the Count of <HI>Curavas,</HI> who having lent them his Chamber, spy'd them through a hole in his Cabinet. Should I discover the door which the Constable made at <HI>To∣lembray,</HI> for his private converse with <HI>Le Grand,</HI> Men would blame my too Satyri∣cal humor: should I relate what was told me by <HI>Le Pont,</HI> how he was taken by the Coller, at a time when <HI>Le Grand</HI> was impa∣tiently expected, who durst not pass by, for fear of the Duke of <HI>Espernon,</HI> who walk'd in his way, with his Hat pull'd down over Eye-brows, &amp; Sword his in his hand, swear∣ing like a Bell-founder, There was no pas∣sing that way to day. Did not the young Deputies of the Estates of <HI>Blois,</HI> make their complaints to the Provinces that sent them, That they were sent only to be abus'd in their Chastities, as the only means to cor∣rupt their Fidelity? But to draw advantage from these things thus divulg'd, I say, and I know (for my services gave me the con∣veniency of access) that the King having conciev'd a wonderful dread of these things in the time of <HI>Sarbatane,</HI> became so fearful, that he trembled at the least flash of Light∣ning, or at the least noise of Thunder. Mon∣sieur
<PB N="56" REF="35"/>
<HI>Roe,</HI> cur'd him of the greatest part of this fear, with an <HI>Agnus Dei</HI> blest by the hand of his Holiness. But after that, he chang'd his fancy from active into passive, and grew so timid, that he was afraid of the whistle∣ing of the very winds; and then the good Prince stood in need of more violent reme∣dies, and by the counsel of Father <HI>Ange,</HI> who griev'd for him, and shew'd him, how he had committed Masculine Incest, because he was Brother to the Duke of <HI>Joyeuse,</HI> they lay'd the foundations of the <HI>Capuchins, Je∣rosolimites</HI> and <HI>Fueillants,</HI> a sort of begging Fryers that wear brown habits; where you have seen the D. of <HI>Joyeuse</HI> in his Glory, and whither, as they say, he intends to re∣turn, when he finds himself fully glutted with the pleasures of this World. Not∣withstanding all which, the devout Prince, being not yet quit of his fears; several Fraternities of Penitents were erected, and other pious Orders which are to be seen up and down in <HI>France.</HI> But the exquisite artifices of the Voluptuous heighten'd these fears, when Monsieur Confessor lent his helping hand with more potent Amulets. He sent from <HI>Rome</HI> for Chaplets, and bless'd beads, which the King presented to the <HI>Fra∣ternity</HI> of the Cabinet, being adviz'd to pra∣ctise their pleasures athwart the said Chap∣lets;
<PB N="57" REF="35"/>
which was afterwards also practis'd in the public Stews of <HI>Paris</HI> to preserve them from the foul Disease. Monsieur <HI>Pi∣nars</HI> affirm'd to me, that a Jesuit confess'd that he approv'd of the remedy, and because some of the sacred band had been too se∣verely wounded in their Chamber-Wars, that the Mass was added, which an <HI>Almoner</HI> read upon a board which was lay'd upon the Bed of the Cabinet. A holy Mass no doubt, whose Ornaments were accommodated to the Sin: as the application of a Cross made of holy wood to the shoulders; Fomen∣tations of the Chine, and Clysters of Holy∣water, beads, which they call blessed, other wise profane trifles and fooleries. We have heard how about 20. years since the Convent of <HI>Franciscans</HI> was burnt at <HI>Paris,</HI> by fire from Heaven: but we never heard how that the King having found it out, that those <HI>Franciscans</HI> were dealers in Sacred Amours, and that the Reliques of St. <HI>Fran∣cis</HI> and Father <HI>Mace</HI> serv'd them in the same stead as we make use of Laurel against Thunder; thereupon the King made the Guardian his Confessor, upon condition that he should purloin those Relicques, which had not been long in the King's Ca∣binet, but the Convent was fir'd, <HI>juxta il∣lud</HI>
<PB N="58" REF="36"/>
12. <HI>tit.</HI> 7. <HI>Fulgura de sursum depellit.</HI> The same Guardian also taught him that that sin was no sin in the Habit of a <HI>Fran∣ciscan,</HI> and committed with a good inten∣tion to be conformable to St. <HI>Francis,</HI> and Father <HI>Macè,</HI> his <HI>Mignon.</HI> For which rea∣son they into whose hands the King's Pray∣er-Books fell, have shewed their familiar friends, the names of all those that are men∣tioned in this Chapter, and at the end of the said Prayer-books, the names of those he could not bring to his bow; among the rest <HI>Chastillon</HI> and <HI>Chambret,</HI> the first with his sleeves thrust back, to shew his plump white Arm, and his Motto, <HI>non pro amor, ma pro vendetta; Not for Love, but for Re∣venge.</HI> This is a kind of a secret, but not such a one as felt that fatal clap of Thunder, which in a clear day, at one of the Clock in the afternoon, in the view of five hundred Gentlemen, and as many <HI>Swisses,</HI> and with no more then one single clap, brake into the low Chamber of the Count of <HI>Soissons,</HI> where Monsieur <HI>Le Grand,</HI> and he were at their belov'd Recreation; and two others upon another bed; and parted company, killing two and leaving the third at the Window half dead; in this more memora∣ble, that the lightning enter'd the Criminal members, and issu'd forth behind. And here
<PB N="59" REF="36"/>
observe the advantage of adorning the hair like a person in Orders; for the two which escaped had both the Popes Chaplets upon their heads; but they that were kill'd had none. I suppose that the fifth, who lay like one half dead for two months to∣gether, had lost not above half his. Thus you see the Experience which authorizes Relicques, and take notice that you shall never see any of the Brethren of the Sacred Society without <HI>Agnus</HI>'s, Crosses, or Chap∣lets about their Arms. To the purpose of Relicques, that wicked Count of <HI>Ro∣chefoucaut,</HI> dining one day with the Queen's Maids of honour, who peck'd at him by express order, and ask'd him for some of the fine Relicques which he had plunder'd at <HI>Towrs</HI> in the first Wars, he reply'd, That he had made them all away, looking upon them as gewgaws and trifles. But they be∣ing importunate, at length he promis'd them, that upon condition they would all come and kiss him, he would give them one of S. <HI>Katherine</HI>'s Wast-coats, that should make their breasts as hard as when they were Maids. For my part if I do not make such a stir about Relicques, or do not wor∣ship them as others do, you must excuse me; for going one Evening to <HI>Bosnis,</HI> two Leagues from <HI>Orleans,</HI> which is the seat of
<PB N="60" REF="37"/>
the Masters of St. <HI>Lazarus</HI>; I was strange∣ly surpriz'd, to hear in the morning as I rose, so many little Bells about the House, as also to see the Banner, and the Cross, and a great number of the Canons of St. <HI>Agnan</HI> in <HI>Orleans,</HI> and not only so, but to see as many Banners and Crosses, as could possibly enter into a little Gallery leading to the House of Easment. The business was, a young Girl belonging to the Cheva∣lier <HI>Salviati,</HI> grand Prior of the Order, had found certain Chests, which in the time, of the Wars had been thrown into the Pri∣vy. As she was picking them open, to see what she could steal, in one of them she found a little box, upon the which was written <HI>R. d. Coti.</HI> The Commander being advertiz'd thereof, made hast to the place, together with his Secretary <HI>Valderio,</HI> who took the <HI>R.</HI> with the Print, for the Father of St. <HI>Katherine.</HI> Thereupon strict charge, was given not to touch the box upon great penalties, and the Master and the Man, went both to the Bishop of <HI>Orleans.</HI> The Doctors, and among the rest <HI>Picard,</HI> being call'd to consultation, the result was, That this box was to be open'd by the Sacred hands of the Bishop only, assisted with the Neighbouring processions. Thus they came one morning, and after a Mass of the Holy
<PB N="61" REF="37"/>
Ghost devoutly said, the Bishop washes his hands in holy-water, makes three steps to the Coffer upon his knees, opens it and there finds <HI>a Box of good Marmalade of</HI> Or∣leans; and thus as Prophesies are never understood till they are fulfil'd, they found that <HI>R.</HI> signifi'd the Remainder, and <HI>d. C.</HI> of the <HI>Cotignac.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VIII. Of Vows.</HEAD>
<P>MR. <HI>Peter Foncet,</HI> a Gentleman Prea∣cher, he that when Monsieur <HI>d'Esper∣non</HI> tax'd him for making people laugh, made answer, that he caus'd many more to weep. This honest man, one day preach∣ing among the <HI>Mathurins,</HI> made a long discourse upon the miseries of the <HI>Chartreux,</HI> that they fed upon nothing but fish, of o∣thers that fed upon nothing that ever had life, of the <HI>Capuchins</HI> that wear nothing up∣on their feet, of the <HI>Fueillans</HI> that are so poorly clad, <HI>&amp; vivunt in diem</HI>; of the <HI>Fri∣ers Ignorant</HI> of <HI>Italy,</HI> who dare not presume to know any thing; of St. <HI>Anthonies Por∣kers</HI>
<PB N="62" REF="38"/>
near <HI>Roanne,</HI> and the <HI>Penitents</HI> that whip themselves. This Preacher caus'd abundance of people to weep; and from all those Devotions, and austere Vows drew this argument, That if the Romish Reli∣gion were false, men would never keep Vows so difficult and uncomfortable. I in∣vited the said <HI>Foncet</HI> and <HI>Renardier</HI> of <HI>Bre∣taigne</HI> to dinner▪ where we brought all his reasons to the test; and that fool <HI>Renardier</HI> put the other into a great heat, telling him that those austeritics of Vows and manner of living, were rather marks of a false Re∣ligion, then of a true. Witness, said he, that the Sacrifices of men were forbid to the <HI>Israelites,</HI> and observ'd among the Gen∣tiles; and those mad Codsheads in <HI>Turky,</HI> the <HI>Caloyer,</HI> who all the year long wear no other covering for their nakedness, then Nets. Only they carry in their right hands a great Razor, with which they make a new stream of blood, when the first begins to close up▪ and as to their fasts and abstinen∣cies, that from Wine, which is enjoyn'd to all persons, is the most difficult to be ob∣serv'd. When they fast they neither eat nor drink. As to their Pilgrimages, where do we find so impetuous a devotion as that of the Pilgrims to <HI>Mecca,</HI> of whom there are many, who after the hardships of a tedi∣ous
<PB N="63" REF="38"/>
journey, and the sight of <HI>Mahomet</HI>'s Se∣pulcher, put out their Eyes, as unwilling to see any thing prophane, after the sight of a thing so holy? Afterwards he alleg'd the strange zeal of the <HI>Calignois,</HI> and how we might find in the Grand Temple of <HI>Mexico,</HI> the walls besmear'd with the blood of Infants offer'd to the Devil by their Fa∣thers and Mothers, and this blood above two fingers thick, through the whole in∣side building; which I have heard con∣firm'd by the <HI>Franciscans</HI> of <HI>Mexico,</HI> and o∣thers. <HI>Renardier</HI> concluded from thence, that all such inventions were very fanati∣cal, or rather diabolical, which inforce men to such hardships. Thereupon this good man Coxcomb fell upon Antiquity, and I cannot tell where he pick'd up his learning. Do you not know, quo he, that the <HI>French</HI> and <HI>English Druids</HI> sacrific'd upon certain days, and accompted those Sacrifices most acceptable, when they put men to the most cruel deaths? The <HI>Carthaginians</HI> took the Children of the most Noble Families, put them on Royal Apparel, and sacrific'd them; neither were their Parents permit∣ted to rescue one, so that being vanquish'd by <HI>Agathocles,</HI> out of an opinion which they had, that their Gods were angry at the discontinuance of such Sacrifices, they
<PB N="64" REF="39"/>
knock'd o'the head above 200 young Gen∣tlemen for the service of their Altars. The <HI>Rhodians</HI> and <HI>Cretans</HI> were wont to make their Victims drunk before they offer'd them up. In <HI>Chio</HI> and <HI>Salamine</HI> they tore men limb-meale to sacrifice them to <HI>Dio∣medes.</HI> The <HI>Arcadians</HI> whipt their Dam∣sels to death. The <HI>Spartans</HI> did the same to their Children upon the Altars of <HI>Diana</HI> and <HI>Mercury.</HI> Others made a great Pen of hurdles, and fill'd it up with men, of which <HI>Theopompus</HI> was one. The <HI>Thracians</HI> slew their Victims with Lances at the Altar of <HI>Tamelus.</HI> Some of the <HI>Germans</HI> and <HI>Bur∣gundians</HI> carous'd blood at their Sacrifices. The <HI>Persians, Greeks,</HI> and some of the <HI>Eng∣lish,</HI> buri'd their Sacrifices alive. I will not stand to repeat several other abominations practis'd upon Boys and Girls; and other follies committed by the <HI>Corinthians</HI> and <HI>Bretons.</HI> I say therefore that these austere and cruel Vows have been in all Ages a great part of the worship giv'n to the De∣vil. From thence <HI>Renardier</HI> betook him∣self to his <HI>Theology,</HI> quoting in the 16 chap. of St. <HI>Matthew,</HI> the words, <HI>My yoke is light,</HI> with several others, and told us withal, my Masters, quo he, the best Vow that we can make is to St. <NOTE N="*" PLACE="inter">The Mad∣mens Saint.</NOTE><HI>Mathurin,</HI> for I assure ye that
<PB N="65" REF="39"/>
the wisest among us is but a fool. All the World did not know <HI>Renardier</HI>; he was one that would speak the truth to the de∣ceas'd King, who desiring to have his char∣ges defray'd by his Marshals of the Camp, told him one day that he did more then God; for he said, <HI>by the labour of thy hands thou shalt live commodiously.</HI> But you, said he, let your Marshals of the Camp live more then commodiously, by that labour and cal∣ling, of which they understood nothing. At last <HI>Poncet</HI> was in a pelting chafe and re∣ply'd, that he discours'd like a <HI>Huguenot.</HI> The other went on smiling, and began to spend his rallery upon the <HI>Pythagorisms</HI> of the <HI>Chartreux,</HI> and other honest fellows, among the rest, he did not forget Mr.— Neither did he omit to tell us that Mr. <HI>de Bouchage,</HI> being weary of the King's scourge, and imprison'd between four screens, made his Confession to one of his companions of the buttock-trade, who having heard of the violences of the Cabinet, persuaded him to forsake the World, and urg'd it to him withal, that if he would undergo a <HI>Capu∣chin's</HI> life for some time, he doubted not but to see him Pope. This is that which the Cunning-man <HI>Raoul</HI> has confirm'd to him, and you shall see, said <HI>Renardier,</HI> that from hence in time he will return thither, mark a
<PB N="66" REF="40"/>
fool's Prophesie. <HI>Poncet</HI> and I laugh'd at him: which made the good man very an∣gry: well, said he, you are a couple of as naughty Companions as Marshal <HI>Biron</HI> who scoff'd at poor Frier <HI>Ange,</HI> when he went to act the Passion before the King at <HI>Char∣tres,</HI> causing himself to be whip'd and car∣rying a Cross, that would have weigh'd down <HI>Goliah.</HI> There, was Monsieur <HI>de Montpensier</HI> enquiring who was Master of the Ceremonies of this Mortality. Sure 'twas not he that flung away the spiggot of his <HI>Gascoigne</HI> Wine because that Monsieur <HI>Babelot</HI> told him it was fit to be the blood of a Martyr. 'Twas he that to get a good gobbet, went to hear Vespers among the <HI>Austin</HI> Friers. The Marshal thereupon drawing himself aside; this widgeon, said he I warrant ye fares well below the wast, though paradventure he may miss of Para∣dise. To whom the Duke return'd, by St. <HI>Slash-back,</HI> quo he, this fellow plays well, but that his Musick is a little too sharp. It was a Cantle of Earth, which he had rub'd off from an Oven as he drawl'd his Cross along for which the Baker was not forget∣ful with a good palt to make him sing <HI>La∣crimae.</HI> Such as you were those devout Bishops of <HI>Lyonnois,</HI> who called a Synod to reform the Custom of St. <HI>Anthony</HI> in that
<PB N="67" REF="40"/>
place. They are oblig'd to make eight meals to shew the frailty of Mankind. There were some Jesuits, Frier minors, and certain young Bishops, who made smooth and long Harangs, to shew that such Constitutions might be alter'd <HI>habita ratio∣ne temporum.</HI> And that what our Ancestors had formerly done with a good intention, was at this day ridiculous. But to all these reasons the <HI>sub Prior</HI> of St. <HI>Anthony,</HI> who was a great snoarer, made answer only with one grave and remarkable Sentence; Let us not intrude Innovations upon our Age. They began again a very fair speech against the scoffers of this Age, but the <HI>sub Prior</HI> with four Chins retorted, le, le, le, le, let us—<HI>Hickup</HI>—take care, &amp;c. But you'l say that under the umbrage of Devo∣tion many great follies are committed. By St. <HI>Anthony</HI> I know it well enough. But it is none of the Churches fault. Who has exclaim'd more then I against the King and his Minions; who had like to have told i'my Pulpit the following Story?</P>
<P>The King falling in love at <HI>Lyon</HI> with the Wife of the Sieur—The bargain be∣ing made with the woman by the Count of <HI>Maulevrier,</HI> the next thing was, how to cajole the Husband out of the way; so jea∣lous, that he refus'd an honourable Employ∣ment,
<PB N="68" REF="41"/>
and a profitable Commission, as to the Salt of <HI>Peccaise</HI> to boot. Thereupon he applies himself to a <HI>Franciscan,</HI> Confessor to the jealous Husband, declaring to him that the Chief men of <HI>Lyon</HI> had their Eye upon this poor man, as looking upon him to be a Heretic, because he was not of the Fraternity of the Penitents. To the point answer'd the <HI>Cordelier</HI>; Sir, I am no such fool to suspect you of Devotion. Speak to me in the Language of St. <HI>Francis,</HI> and you shall find that the <HI>Franciscans</HI> are good Companions. By all that's vertuous then, reply'd the Count, we have a private kind∣ness for his Wife, and there are thirty Crowns for thee. To which the <HI>Francis∣can,</HI> get ye gone, quo he, like Lords as ye are, and leave the business to me. Six days after that, you might have seen the poor Gentleman in the Vestry preparing to carry the Cross as the youngest Novice. In the mean time the King, the Count, and <HI>Clermont d'Entragues</HI> go to play their Game; and in a short while after they saw through the Window of the Chamber, the Proces∣sion and the Cross-bearer, who in the midst of his devotions could not choose but have strange Whimseys and Imaginations in his head, which so intoxicated his <HI>Pericranium,</HI> that he fell in a Swoon before his own door.
<PB N="69" REF="41"/>
Thereupon the Procession stop'd, to change the Cross-bearer. There was now a ne∣cessity to open the door, and to hide the three Adventurers in the best manner they could, in a small Compting-house, Where they had bin in great danger, but that the <HI>Franciscan</HI> and one of his Brethren over∣rul'd the devout Cuckold, that it was a re∣ligious duty incumbent upon him to carry back his habit to the Vestry. Who has ex∣claim'd more then I, against the deceas'd King, who carry'd the names of his Mini∣ons in his prayer books, illuminated with the light of St. <HI>Francis</HI>? Did I not know the Dutchess of <HI>Guize</HI> and <HI>Nevers,</HI> who carry'd <HI>Roquemont</HI> and the Baron of <HI>Fu∣mel,</HI> painted in the Crucifix both in their Prayer-books and Cabinets; and they their Mistresses also in the same manner like the Virgin <HI>Mary</HI>? But you other Heretics, you do ill to blame the Church for this. I broke the design of <HI>Poncet</HI> by saying, that the in∣vention of Habits and Prayer-books is no way guilty of ill Customs. But to reim∣burse ye both, for your unlucky tales, I will tell ye one spick and span new. What was the reason, think ye, that the Count <HI>de la Chapelle</HI> forsook the World? Whuh! said <HI>Renardier,</HI> that was, because the Car∣dinal of <HI>Florence</HI> fool'd him, and promis'd
<PB N="70" REF="42"/>
he should be Pope. With that I shook my head; Why no said <HI>Poncet</HI> as well as Pope— who was taken up at the door a poor boy, because the Cardinals she-monky fell in love with him? Some say she lov'd him for the number of Lice he had about him. However it were, being once well cleans'd and furbish'd up, he pleas'd his Master, was afterwards advanc'd, and call'd Cardinal <HI>della Simia,</HI> and last chos'n <HI>Holy-Father.</HI> At what time the College check'd him, that he had made a Beggar, and an ignorant Fellow, Cardinal, he re∣ply'd, 'tis but the same that ye found in me, and if he live to be old, 'tis that will make him Pope. The reason was this; His Mo∣ther being weary of him, partly because he was troubled with the falling sickness, and for that she found him a fool, but chiefly because his Maiden Brother began to grow ripe, she therefore sent him into <HI>Italy,</HI> and gave him Father <HI>Jeronimo</HI> for his Confes∣sour. He knew so well how to pick the worms out of the nose of this Calf, that he made him a Confession of such sins as I am asham'd to tell ye, for the expiation whereof, he made him believe there was no other way, but for him to forsake the World, and devote himself to the Church. I know, said <HI>Renardier,</HI> more then you
<PB N="71" REF="42"/>
dare say. I once heard at the Window of the Stable of St. <HI>Denis</HI> of one who impor∣tuning his Companion to tell him whether the Count <HI>de la Chapell</HI> were a coming? this answer was made, I know no more then I can divine, who had his Maiden-head; whether his Father or his Mother, his Uncle or his Sister But to the purpose; this Vow being as severe as the Penance for his offences, as that which <HI>Aretine</HI> describes in the person of Master— His Mother believing she should dye for grief of having born him, devoted him to be a Cardinal in humility. This is he upon whom <HI>Pasquin</HI> jokes; What has the Cardinal done, has he left his Eleemosynarie at the Hospital? At length Monsieur <HI>Poncet</HI> grew weary of the discourse and told us if you, and o∣ther sort of <HI>Huguenots,</HI> had not come a∣thwart us, we had tought the deceas'd King the value of Vestments, shavings and secret Vows. For we had put him in the great <HI>Chartreuse,</HI> being fortifi'd with good Bulwarks instead of Reasons. We had Habited him like the Ingles in his prayer-books. We had chang'd his Crown for a shav'd Circle, and to bid ye God-buy and end our discourses, we had answer'd his motto, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="inter"><HI>The last Crown in Heav'n.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Manet Ʋltima Caelo,</HI> with a Distic
<PB N="72" REF="43"/>
that was assix'd to the Dyal of the Pa∣lace.</P>
<Q><LG>
<L>Qui dedit ante duas, unam abstulit, altera nutat;</L>
<L>Tertia Tonsoris nunc facienda manu.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Once two Crowns were thee design'd,</L>
<L>But the Donor chang'd his mind.</L>
<L>One he retook, and this doth shake,</L>
<L>The next the Barber is to make.</L>
</LG></Q>
<P>Farewel Gentlemen, I am sorry to see ye make such ill use of pious works. Thus <HI>Poncet</HI> took his leave, but <HI>Renardier</HI> staid to make an end of his story. This is the reason said he, that the Bishop of <HI>Xantes</HI> is one of the best Companions in the world. There is also an Abbess in the Suburbs, whose Convent is more like a Court, then a Religious House. Where with <HI>Maubusson</HI>'s good leave, at the Seige of <HI>Pontoise,</HI> there lay no less then eight godly Virgins sick of the <HI>Crinkums,</HI> and five newly brought to Bed. Let it not of∣fend <HI>Longchamp</HI> nor <HI>Mont Martre,</HI> that this place was call'd the Magazine of the En∣gines of the Army. Nor let it offend the Trinity of <HI>Poictiers, Vilmur</HI> of <HI>Albi∣geois, Lys,</HI> the true Seminaries of Children in Red Coats; the Abby of the Holy
<PB N="73" REF="43"/>
Ghost, the Nunnnery whither <HI>Suresne</HI> brought <HI>Fervaques</HI> some few days ago, and told the Abbess, who is her Daughter, that she ought to shew the honour of her house to the new Duke and Peer; his design being only to debauch a young Religious Nun, which was the real cause of their journey. In half an hours time <HI>Suresne</HI> return'd and whisper'd her fellow-traveller in the Ear, Go fall on, <HI>Mortbieu,</HI> the Slut has put me to some trouble, but the business is done. Hast makes wast of the body, quoth <HI>Fervaques</HI>; for I have play'd two Acts with the Abbess. How? She's my Daughter: Then I am your Son in law, said the other. The Abbess of <HI>Xantes</HI> is inferiour to none of them all, for Gallantry, Courtship, and Mascarading. And in a word, there is nothing acted there, but what is acted at Court. Only sometimes the Bishop and the Abbess steal abroad to some remote and convenient pla∣ces; and then the Nuns fall to their Ori∣sons, in regard that <HI>Monsieur</HI> and <HI>Madam</HI> are gone to perform works of Charity. E∣very one was much concern'd what pious works those should be: But the Prior of <HI>Pont l'abbè</HI> having discover'd them one day, wrote to Monsieur <HI>de Potonville</HI> the fol∣lowing Lines.</P>
<Q><PB N="74" REF="44"/>
<L>The Bishop and Abbess of <HI>Xantes</HI></L>
<L>For their works of piety, Saints,</L>
<L>Are often in private together:</L>
<L>But a Nun more witty then either,</L>
<L>Made a hole in the Wall,</L>
<L>And there she spy'd all.</L>
<L>She was paid for her peeping,</L>
<L>For now she knew more</L>
<L>Of Piety-works then ever before.</L></Q>
<P>He concluded with the answer of <HI>Ver∣ville</HI> touching so many piles of building for the entertainment of Franciscans, Je∣suits, Capuchins, and the like; to pre∣vent the folly of men, that let fools put out their eyes.</P>
<Q><L>You <HI>Huguenots</HI> that so severely frown,</L>
<L>And all our Monasteries would pull down</L>
<L>Should Knaves and Fools change places tell us, you</L>
<L>Whether you would not think 'em then to few</L></Q>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="75" REF="44"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. IX. Of the several ways of Angling for Men.</HEAD>
<P>WHatever St. <HI>Peter</HI> did, his Successours have strangely alter'd the course of his Vessel. For all the while that the times of darkness continu'd, the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> has fish'd in the fire. They have not spar'd for Wood, by which means, they have consum'd the bodies of them, who were too apprehensive of the fire of Souls. The Converters of these times made it their business to convert the Soul by terrifying the Body, or else by converting the Body into Cinders. When day and light ap∣pear'd, and that fire began to be out of re∣quest, then they fell to fish in troubl'd wa∣ters; and this they do in all times of trou∣bles, and then several persons exil'd from their houses fell into the fishermens Nets. When the water ceases to be trou∣bled, they fish in the calm, and then they never spare for <HI>unguis odoratus,</HI> which the Druggists of <HI>Italy</HI> furnish them withal.
<PB N="76" REF="45"/>
With this bait were taken the more weigh∣ty sort of fish, such as were the Marshals of <HI>Montmorancy</HI> and <HI>de Cosse.</HI> After that, they lay their baits for the larger sort of fish, so was <HI>Antony</HI> King of <HI>Navarre</HI> caught by <HI>Ro∣vet,</HI> and <HI>Lovis</HI> of <HI>Bourbon</HI> by <HI>Limeul</HI>; but this latter being a strong fish, and feeling himself in the Net, brake the meshes, and so escap'd. Some there are, that are de∣stroy'd by following the Dolphins; such are the <HI>Dog-fish, Barbels, Macquerel</HI> and all the lesser frie that follow the Court, who following their Master, enter with him in∣to the belly of that profound and vast Whale, the Church of <HI>Rome.</HI> The little frie is caught with more labour, while they are put to force them out of their lurking holes by beating with their long Poles. By this means, there is ne're a small Parish in <HI>France,</HI> where the <HI>Huguenots,</HI> beaten out by good and holy intelligence, more then others, are not forc'd into St. <HI>Peter</HI>'s Nets. The Winters of affliction cause se∣veral to remove to the Springs of Honour and Greatness, as the Courts of <HI>Rome,</HI> the Emperour, <HI>France</HI> and <HI>Spain.</HI> By this means, we have caught in these later Sea∣sons several haughty minds, impatient of meanness and poverty, and among the rest <HI>La Morlas,</HI> who not being able to recon∣cile
<PB N="77" REF="45"/>
the lowness of his Birth, and the great∣ness of his Courage, remov'd to those Springs, when the <HI>Huguenots</HI> were in a low condition. And also to draw advantage from others, he made use of a new arti∣fice. In that somewhat resembling the na∣ture of the Dolphin, but only in the e∣vent. He carry'd his Believers to the di∣spute with Monsieur Confessour. He ad∣monish'd them first to take a care of him, as being a dangerous impostor, and ex∣horted them to stand firm; but afterwards suffer'd himself to be caught in their com∣pany. I saw him one day bring to the line of the Net the little Baron <HI>de Courte∣mer,</HI> to whom he gave his hand sidelong in the middle of the dispute, and cry'd, Cou∣rage, my little Baron; <HI>however we ought to consider what Monsieur</HI> Perron <HI>sayes.</HI> Thereupon with an artificial and sanctifi'd prevarication he suffer'd himself to be van∣quish'd after a dissembl'd resistance. I my self have several times bin disintangl'd out of the same Net. Monsieur <HI>de Chastillon</HI> was inform'd by his Father's old Servants, That the design to bring him to Court was, as well upon his Body, as his Conscience. Monsieur Confessour, one of the best Fish∣ermen that has belong'd to the Church, has more luckily then others observ'd in these
<PB N="78" REF="46"/>
Seasons, the way of fishing with the Line: For he has got a trick to put the worm so far on upon the hook, that the fish is caught before it has swallow'd the bait. Witness poor <HI>Desponde,</HI> whose bait was laid for a∣nother, and who having sacrific'd his Soul for the Church, has bin so wickedly gull'd, that before he dy'd, he saw his Children go a begging, his Wife in the Stews, and himself in the Hospital. Witness poor <HI>Cahier</HI> who gap'd after the Abbey promis'd him, but saw nothing but the Walls and the Steeple. The Holy men of former times fish'd with Preaching, and baited their hooks with Salvation. But now a days we suffer that sort of coin to grow rusty; for the fish is too much awake, and will not be caught by licking the mud. <HI>Dandelot</HI> cost little, for he was taken with the hand, and that was a riddle to the good Companions. I will say this more∣over in a word, for the prudence of Mon∣sieur Confessour, that he fishes best in still waters. Not such waters as <HI>Desponde</HI> caus'd to swell at M. <HI>de Guerres:</HI> but be∣cause he has an eye upon those whose Fa∣milies are going to rack; like a Pond that drains it self through its own Sluces and so becomes dry; as it happen'd in the case of the Baron of <HI>Salignac,</HI> when his Wife
<PB N="79" REF="46"/>
converted him. Some are caught by the foresight of such accidents, like my self, that I might fish on in still waters. Mon∣sieur Confessour has taken the pains to come and fish and preach at St. <HI>Merry,</HI> in the face of the people: there where they take Frogs sleeping, there he preaches like a Deacon to a Subdeacon; His Brother and some others of his Apostles have a seat la∣den with good Livres just before the Pul∣pit. They open the bags upon the quota∣tion of passages; they tie them up again as fast as they can to awaken attention. But this great Personage is so full of talk, that the greatest part of the auditory sleep three hours together, and get terrible Colds; and so the faculty of Theology becomes very profitable to the faculty of Physic.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. X. Of Transubstantiation.</HEAD>
<P>WE cannot say much upon the point of Transubstantiation; for it is more difficult to prove then pronounce, though the word be somewhat of the long∣est. But as Monsieur Confessour says,
<PB N="80" REF="47"/>
confessing that it was an absurd point, yet it ought to be debated for the honour of the Church. Though not to dive too far into the will of God, he forbid me to read the most part of the Ancients, especially St. <HI>Austin l. de agone Christiano, c.</HI> 25. <HI>De Praesentia Dei ad</HI> Dardanum. <HI>c.</HI> 17 <HI>in Psal.</HI> 33. <HI>&amp;</HI> 34. <HI>In Evangel. Johannis. tract.</HI> 27. <HI>ad Bonifac. Epist.</HI> 23. <HI>In Sermon. Infant. l.</HI> 3. <HI>de doctrina Christi. c.</HI> 9. <HI>&amp;</HI> 16. He also forbad me to read the rest not corre∣cted by the <HI>Index expurgatorius,</HI> and taught me to insist upon nothing in this dispute but Omnipotency. Now therefore hear the ar∣guments which I have pick'd out of my own invention. Wherefore cannot we change and alter the substances of all things in the name of God, seeing we do the same thing in the King's name, whereby we see such strange Transubstantiations and Metamorphoses perform'd every day? The sweat of a miserable Labourer into the fat of prosperous Partisan and Treasurer? The marrow of the fingers of a Vine-dresser of <HI>Gasconie</HI> rejoices the heart of every one, and fills the belly of a Parasite. The tears of the Widow ruin'd in <HI>Bretagne</HI> caus'd <HI>San∣tory</HI>'s Wife to grow fat. The blood of a Souldier slain, to chace <HI>Espernon</HI> out of <HI>Pro∣vence</HI> turns to Hypocriss. The <HI>Host</HI> of the
<PB N="81" REF="47"/>
Rose at <HI>Bloise</HI> we find now transubstanti∣ated in <HI>M. Bussy Guibert.</HI> The Imposts of <HI>France</HI> have transubstantiated the Plough-fields into Pasture, the Vinyards into wast land, and the Husbandmen into Beggars; The Souldiers into Thieves, with little or no Miracle; The Plough-joggers into Gen∣tlemen, the Lacqueys into Masters, the Ma∣sters into Lacqueys, the Horsemen into Hal∣berdeers. The Curtisans of Princes are transubstantiated into Women, and Wo∣men into Curtisans. Panders becom Marquises. <HI>Varenne</HI> has undergone such Transubstantiations would make your hair stand an end. Pardon <HI>Morlas,</HI> if he see∣mingly believe Transubstantiation; He who in his Cradle was chang'd from a Bastard of <HI>Sallette</HI> into the Son of a Botcher, and from that time bred up by the almes of the Churches of <HI>Pau</HI>; afterwards a Scho∣ler at the Queen's charge; from a Scholer he became a Minister and Spie upon the <HI>Huguenots</HI> of <HI>Paris,</HI> from a Spie a <HI>Gendar∣me,</HI> from a <HI>Gendarme</HI> a Disciple of <HI>Perron,</HI> thence a Pandar, so a Traytor, and last of all Proveditor General. Who can reck'n the notable Changes of <HI>Lansac Laverdin,</HI> the <HI>Marquis de Bell'ilse, Monluc</HI> and <HI>Bal∣gagny</HI>? The deceas'd Bishop of <HI>Valence,</HI> who believ'd nothing of Transubstantiati∣on,
<PB N="82" REF="48"/>
what would he have said to have seen his Son <HI>de Champis</HI> a Captain, from a Cap∣tain a Soveraign Prince, from a Prince a Poltron, from a Poltron an Exile, from an Exile a Marshal, from a Marshal a Cuc∣kold, just such another as Marshal <HI>Vulcan</HI>? But that which convinces me more of the truth of Transubstantiation is the Proverb, <HI>Know thy self.</HI> When I consider how many times I have bin my self transubstanti∣ated, from a Sholer to a Councellour, thence to an Ambassadour, thence to a Bankrupt, thence to a Coney-catcher, thence to an Excise-man, thence to a Col∣lonel, Captain, and Constable of Petty <HI>Chalons.</HI> It had bin also a fair argument to prove the wonderful Transubstantiation, had Prince <HI>Maurice</HI> bin as quick to contri∣bute the 400. M. Crowns, as they of <HI>Bearn</HI> and <HI>Geneva</HI> were the 10. M Crowns for the hire of my third Conversion: But let that pass, only let me tell ye, had I bin Earl of <HI>Burgundy</HI> I had paid my <HI>Swisses</HI> in salt. We have seen the lower Hall of the <HI>Loure</HI> chang'd into a Comic-Stage, from a Comic-Stage into a Tragic; from a Pa∣lace Royal, into a place of Execution, when President <HI>Brisson</HI> and his Companions were there hang'd. To which I will on∣ly add the example of the Duke of <HI>Merceur</HI>
<PB N="83" REF="48"/>
who from a petty Prince, became the King's Brother in Law; from thence Governour of <HI>Bretaigne,</HI> from a Governour a Tyrant, from a Tyrant a Duke, and in his own fan∣cy the Terrour of <HI>France,</HI> and the hope of <HI>Spain.</HI> And indeed he is so transubstan∣tiated, that the new Proverb of <HI>Spaniards</HI> calls him, The scorn of <HI>France,</HI> the shame of <HI>Lorrain,</HI> the disdain of <HI>Bretaigne.</HI> He is neither Duke, nor Tyrant, nor Gover∣nour, and he that had bin Victorious in Bat∣tel, has suffer'd that fair Fortune to go to Ruin, without the shot of one single Pi∣stol; only one Scape which he let the other day in cold blood, in the presence of the King.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="book">
<PB REF="49"/>
<PB N="85" REF="49"/>
<HEAD>THE CATHOLIC CONFESSION OF THE Sieur <HI>de SANCY.</HI> SECOND BOOK.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. I. A Dialogue between Madam <HI>Mathu∣rine,</HI> and young <HI>Peronne.</HI></HEAD>
<P>I Have lately receiv'd here, such an odd piece of Divinity, that methinks I can∣not but for shame stick it in among the rest, because it looks so all of a piece. 'Tis a very modest discourse, that truly conside∣ring the times, may very well pass muster. By the contents, you will find what a strange sort of Cattel our careful and pro∣vident Mother, the Church, employs to
<PB N="86" REF="50"/>
bring men back into the broad Road. <HI>Dame Mathurine,</HI> that <HI>Mad Girl,</HI> was co∣ming from Madam <HI>de Monlukes,</HI> where she had been tutoring <HI>Vignoles,</HI> and met with <HI>Perronne</HI> going thither to perform the same Office. He blush'd to see <HI>Mathurine,</HI> and stroking his bald Pate, thus accosted her. Well met, Madam; I hear you boast about the Town▪ how you have converted St. <HI>Mary du Mont.</HI></P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who told you this merry news, my good friend?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth, 'tis very probable— you are, indeed, a dainty She-Divine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis very true, where men are to be converted by Smock-learning. And now I think on't, don't you remember, that he engag'd to meet me this night? With that, I went to carry the joyful news to your Brother, and as good luck would have it; for 'twas somewhat early i'the morning, who should I meet but Madam <HI>de la Cour</HI> just tripping out of his Cham∣ber?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, my dear brisk Madam, hold a little; you do ill to bespatter so renown'd a Prelat and Father of the Church.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Sir,—such delights and innocent sports as those don't hinder the work of Conversion. Besides, <HI>La Chesnay</HI>
<PB N="87" REF="50"/>
is a witness; for he going to visit him, as I did, a little more early then ordinary, saw fairly in the Chamber the accoutre∣ments of a certain female among the sancti∣fi'd Garments of thy Brother in Or∣ders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray leave off these gigling stories; I shall be angry else at your impertinence. I don't say, but that Msr. <HI>de St. Mary</HI> gave you a promise; but the day before I had made a handsome progress i'my underta∣king: For the day before that, I had caus'd three whole Porters loads of Books to be sent in to the Lady Marquesses Lodgings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Think you that I am ignorant what game you were at instead of dispu∣ting? But I would have you to know too, that 'twas I that first tickl'd his humour; 'twas I that play'd the same Ledger-du∣main with him below the wast-band, as I did with you when we were first sweet to∣gether: I taught him to be a good marks∣man, and to swim without water▪ Thou didst not so much as speak with him till two months after that, at least, and then you were forc'd to wait wi'your gravity, when I was still sent for, and circumspectly usher'd in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly your Introductions were ve∣ry Ceremonious—but can any man ima∣gin,
<PB N="88" REF="51"/>
that with the air and levity of a Cur∣tizan, thou should'st be admitted to talk of such a difficult matter as Conversion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<P>And can you imagin, by that silly in∣vention of yours, of interpreting the familiar Epistles of <HI>Cic.</HI> to become familiar with him? I have heard <HI>La Brosse</HI> the Pedagogue say, that when he was Regent of the third Classis in <HI>Burgundy,</HI> he would have lash'd his boys, if they had not translated better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you think I have taught him nothing else? He was at first a meer No∣vice, and a block-head—I have taught him to cite the Fathers, without ever read∣ing them; to quote the Councils which he never saw. I have not only taught him to chop Logic like a <HI>Sorbonne</HI> Mountebank; but to talk of State affairs; to admire the great Kingdom of <HI>Spain,</HI> and to propose projects of Government according to the humour of the Church of <HI>Rome.</HI> Instead of naming the Pope, I have taught him to say his <HI>Holiness.</HI> Instead of calling the King, the <HI>King,</HI> I have taught him to say —<HI>His Majesty.</HI> Before he cry'd — plain <HI>Little Roche, Zamet, Varenne,</HI> as if they had been meer Dwarfs, Lackies, or Turn-spits. But I have taught him to say Monsieur <HI>Varenne,</HI> and to snarl out the <HI>r.</HI> with a grace. He began to laugh, when I
<PB N="89" REF="51"/>
told him that to speak otherwise was a piece of High-Treason. But I shew'd him how that unmannerliness only befitted morose Antiquity, and that to honour by halves the Darlings of a King was below the Polite∣ness of this Politic Age. I have taught him also with his right fore-finger and his left Thumb to thunder out Maxims of State, to disclose and complain of distem∣pers of Government, to nod his head and cry <HI>mark the End on't</HI>; to accept of a fair proffer, to mind his fortunes; and to sea∣son his discourses with the true terms of Art; as for example, <HI>To have a jealousie, to ambitionate, intregue, to take his mea∣sures,</HI> and the like,—the true Phrases whereby a man may be judg'd capable of business.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Coxcomb you mean — I con∣fess I have not taught him so many scrapps of State—Gibberish.—But I have taught him all his Clock-work Motions to a hair— to walk as upright as a Gentleman-Usher— to bow often—and not to laugh with∣out a serious cause—I gave him the Po∣stures of Monsieur <HI>Le Grand</HI>—I taught him to turn his heels inward—to walk in State like a Goose—to shrink up his shoulders—to give an admiration— start—to screw his head gently a one
<PB N="90" REF="52"/>
side upon dislike—all the quarter and half quarter Motions of the Al-a-mode scrape—to laugh a one side of his mouth— and grin like a Dog when we give him Garlick—to speak i'the Throat—to comb his Periwig—at least while his friend speaks— to cry by my faith—hay—instead of plain by my faith, I have taught him, and that quickly too, all the knick-knacks of Admiration—as Jesu! drawl'd out— <HI>But that you say it, I should never—well— He!—Ave-Maria!</HI>— When he meets any of the painted Ladys of the Court, to make a stop, and cry—how beautiful you appear to day; Madam! fair as the new blown Rose and then to discourse of the colours of her Ribands according to Art, and not to take notice how ill they become the Rotten Harlot. I have taught him to dis∣semble like the Court Marquesses, who are scarce worth groats a piece—I have taught him to pull his hat down upon his Periwig, though he wear his band without starch, as when high Collars were in fa∣shion. I gave him six of these bands the o∣ther day, that reach down half way his back, and as many pair of Cuffs, that turn up to his Elbows.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly you very much oblig'd him —For when he went the other day, to
<PB N="91" REF="52"/>
dine with the Marquess of <HI>Beuvron,</HI> after they had wash'd, the Marquess <HI>d'Arly,</HI> sneering at the strangeness of the Vision, took one of his Cuffs to wipe his hands in∣stead of a Towel. But I have taught him more serious Lessons; as to guess betimes at such as are creeping into favour; to cry, Monsieur, twenty times in forty words; to pretend modesty and respect, and to with∣draw into a Corner; to Complement the Servants of those that the Sun shines upon; and not only the Servants of Princes, but also of the Counsellors of the long Robe, as —<HI>D'Aubeville,</HI> and <HI>Caumartin,</HI> men lear∣ned in the modern laws; who know how to manage a Court Cause, and to take a Dinner at the Chancellor's by way of re∣turn.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you say, there is nothing in the motion of the hand, not to order the folds of the band, according to the mode? Are all the Mops and Mows of <HI>Fecan</HI> no∣thing? which caus'd the Marshal <HI>d'Ancre</HI> to call him the fair <HI>Egyptian,</HI> and the only Minion among the Beautiful—In short, I have enter'd him; for which he seems to be so much endebted to me, that he curls and turns up his hair like a very <HI>Narcissus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go—go—by St. <HI>Denis,</HI> you are a meer baud—In a word let them dare to
<PB N="92" REF="53"/>
say at <HI>Rome,</HI> that you have converted St. <HI>Mary.</HI> What will the <HI>Huguenots</HI> say?— They'l say, that to bring Whore-masters to the great Whore of <HI>Babylon,</HI> bauds are the only decoys.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>How long, dear Brother, have you been a despiser of the Trade? How did you get your Living, before your Bro∣ther came to be a Bishop? Have you for∣got your frolicks at the University with the Book-sellers, and Chandlers Wives? I could name ye twenty, that have hir'd ye for fifteen pence a time. But now since your Brother has set ye a Horse-back, and hung that furr'd Cloak upon your shoul∣ders, now all your attempts are upon Counsellors and Presidents Ladies—as if thou wer't aiming to be Pandar General to all the Courts of Parliament▪ and so by degrees to the Court it self. Why should your ambition seek the Ruin of Madam <HI>Tillet,</HI> and my self▪ by taking away our Trade? She brings forth only to get Cre∣dit; and I, that am a poor Maid, had need to make use of all my parts. A my word— if Madam <HI>du Tillet</HI> once give ye a blow o'the shins, there will a scar remain. I hear that the Queen has already said to the Marchioness of <HI>Guercheville, I understand this</HI> Perronne <HI>begins to delight in Ruffianry.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="93" REF="53"/>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>By St. <HI>Francis,</HI> thou art a foul mouth'd Baggage, I care not a fig either for <HI>du Tillet,</HI> or <HI>Tignaville</HI> either— How dar'st thou speak to me at this rate, thou that art a common Prostitute to the Foot-boys, Pages and <HI>Switzers</HI>? Thou that has't sent <HI>Le Pont de coulay</HI> and <HI>Engoulevent</HI> to the Surgeons already; and in short has hansell'd <HI>Vignoles</HI> also, under the pretence of conversion. Thou that hast got a Horse to thy green Velvet Gown, as a reward for the maiden-head of thy little— of∣fer'd up to Monsieur <HI>Le Grand?</HI> I name no body. Thy very skin is parch'd, thy head scorch'd with the flames of thy Lust: Thou art a meer Carcass above ground — Hence to the Devil— Thou turn'st my stomach to see thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Matth.</SPEAKER>
<P>How! ye stale Fornicatour! <HI>So∣domite</HI> both Active and Passive, Does your Chuch preferment make ye grow sawcy? Don't I know that thy Brother sold thee to the Lust of the Abbot <HI>Tyrone</HI>? Shall I publish to the World what I know of thee, and of thy Amorous God-father, and then reck'n up as many Sodomies, Bestialities, Witch-crafts, and Poysonings, as are men∣tion'd in two books call'd <HI>L'Abolition de la Fin,</HI> and in the Legend of St. <HI>Nicate</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mortbieu,</HI> Don't let me lay my hands
<PB N="94" REF="54"/>
on thee — If I do— I shall tye that tongue of yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do and ye dare—Tom Totty —there's <HI>Flamberge</HI> will pay ye off —don't venture upon me neither, you know I have been shot through the thigh already, and am a piece of a Soul∣dier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know thou hast bin a Souldier, as having march'd with the Regiment of <HI>Picardy.</HI> But why should we play the fool and upbray'd one another, that are both of a feather? Be satisfi'd, that I am the per∣son that has converted <HI>M.</HI> St. <HI>Mary.</HI> I did it by the Arguments of Visibility and per∣sonal Succession.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art a lyar—For he an∣swer'd thee, that If a Visible Head were needful in the Church, there would be re∣quir'd also a Visible Holy Spirit. And to thy argument of the personal Succession he re∣ply'd, Where should be then all the Bastards, seeing that the Priests were none of them marry'd? But I surpriz'd him—having lain two or three nights at St. <HI>Martin,</HI> to understand the arguments of <HI>Dr. de Cahier.</HI> I taught him, that <HI>Cain</HI> sung Mass, and of∣fer'd up the Sacrifice of the Altar, in the person of <HI>Abel</HI> his brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peron.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Murrain</HI> take him— there's a
<PB N="95" REF="54"/>
foolish argument indeed— does <HI>Cahier</HI> pay his Hostess with no better coin? Have not you bin playing the little man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I by my Virginity. He must sweat once more—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>I mean, have not you bin helping him to blow the soft fire under the Eggshel, with you know what in it, toge∣ther with the Crimson Silk, and the Magi∣cians choicest Dyet, the little Mandrake, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed he shew'd me in his Clo∣set, that which they call the work of the Creation, but stay till thy hair be grown, and then we'l speak more of that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou wilt do me an injury at one time or other in my Visits to the Princess's Palace. But as to thy argument; were it true, <HI>Judas,</HI> the Jews and the Murderers of Christ had bin the predecessours of our Priests. But I stop'd him and put him to a non-plus with an infallible argument. For quo I, do you believe the Pope to be Anti-Christ? — Yes— said he— Then said I, This Anti-Christ is to sit in the Temple of God, which is his Church: Therefore the place where the Pope sits is the Church; and the Church, that cannot err.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>I remember you did argue thus
<PB N="96" REF="55"/>
learnedly with him, and that he was mute; but at night he told me that it had very much perplex'd him, that there was no other way to prove the Church of Christ, but by the Kingdom of Anti-Christ. To which I answer'd him with another argument, invented by <HI>Bonniere,</HI> or else by <HI>Guedron,</HI> and <HI>Gouroy,</HI> who have converted him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh! I confess that might well be — for he chose rather to cry <HI>peccavi,</HI> then take upon him the superin∣tendency of <HI>Chartreux.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math,</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray give me leave to speak— The <HI>Huguenots</HI> say that the chief of the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> are Thieves, and such as prey upon the poor people. Now the Text says, <HI>My House is a House of Prayer, but you have made it a Den of Thieves.</HI> Our Church is a Den of Thieves, and therefore that House of Prayer of which the Text speaks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>By St. <HI>Dominic,</HI> I must needs tell thee thou art a quaint Slut— The rea∣son is profound and good; and of the same nature with that which is concluded upon these words, <HI>The Scribes and Pharisees sate in</HI> Mose<HI>'s Chair.</HI> Now our Works and Doctrine shew us to be both Scribes and Pharisees, and therefore we sit in <HI>Moses</HI>'s
<PB N="97" REF="55"/>
Chair. But to pay thee with thy own coin, I will tell the another argument which I keep a purpose for <HI>Vignoles.</HI> To prove that St. <HI>Peter</HI> was at <HI>Rome,</HI> we cite his Epistle, where he sends his Recommendations from those that were with him at <HI>Babylon.</HI> Now we cannot deny to the <HI>Huguenots,</HI> but that <HI>Rome</HI> was thus call'd, especially in the Revelations. Seeing then that <HI>Babylon</HI> is <HI>Rome,</HI> St. <HI>Peter</HI> of necessity wrote from <HI>Rome.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Reason may serve with the help of <HI>Monluke</HI>— Well— convert as many as you can— I'le do my endea∣vour— I hope to debauch some of your brother Apostles, as I have already done by the Trumpeters of his praises, <HI>La Bross</HI> and <HI>Beau Lieu</HI>— I will give them such vari∣ety of dishes, that they shall talk of my Conversions, as they have begun at the <HI>La∣dy Constables,</HI> at a Dinner, where they de∣clar'd, That I had more enclin'd St. <HI>Mary</HI> to be converted, then your brother, the Ma∣ster-worker of Conversions. Alas! men are tir'd with expectance. Thy brother was promoted by the Encomiums of <HI>Abbot Tyron</HI>; but no body is promoted by the Re∣commendations of your brother. So that they have very fairly told me, they will cry him up no more. Wherefore has not he
<PB N="98" REF="56"/>
satisfi'd them, since they were hir'd to cry him up?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>As for <HI>Duret,</HI> the Devil's in his tongue; He was so impudent one day at the Arsenal, as to say in my hearing, that he would never Dine where the Abbot and my Brother were, if the drinking Glasses were not mark'd, because the one was rot∣ten with the <HI>Neapolitan</HI> disease, and the other with the Leprosie. 'Tis a brave World, when such smell-feasts as He shall compare themselves with my brother. In my opinion they deserve the same sharp re∣buke, that the Count of <HI>Tonnerre</HI> gave to <HI>Beaulieu,</HI> who talking of a Masquarade, cry'd ever and anon; <HI>the Counts of Sois∣sons, Auvergne, and I.</HI> Whereupon the Count of <HI>Tounerre</HI> put him in mind of the Fable of the T—S. <HI>We Apples also swim.</HI> My Brother is none of their friend, nor will he ever assist them to unravel this yarn. They shall not swim together, be∣cause the Count has commanded the Cap∣tain of his Guards to cut off his hands, and cast him into the River. Thereupon he went to the King, and upon his knees besought him to give him a Grant to commit a mur∣der, which was to be done the same day the Grant was made. Was it not a cur∣sed peice of Impudence to report, and
<PB N="99" REF="56"/>
write in Rime doggerel, That the King and Monsieur <HI>Rosny,</HI> to save Charges, were a∣bout to dismiss the Comedians: Tho 'tis true indeed that the King, out of his particular inherent, wisdom, has bethought himself of a neat sham for the poor Players. For he has threaten'd to suppress them, unless they will admit him in without paying; which liberty he has also attain'd for Ma∣dam <HI>Marchioness.</HI> So that now they say they have a Play every Month which costs them nothing. But notwithstanding all this, this Varlet <HI>Duret</HI> (perhaps he aims to be Treasurer himself) still advises the King to put the Players down, telling him, That he has a compleat Company in his own House. That he had for a Captain <HI>Ʋpan∣ce Vitray,</HI> well pepper'd with the distem∣per; The Count of <HI>Soissons,</HI> who playes the Doctor, when he reads his military les∣sons like a School-master, at the door of his Closet. He says the King has provi∣ded among the rest, that the <HI>Italians</HI> shall act <HI>Gallows take thy due</HI>— being already like to starve; but there are Camp-masters and Captains in the lower Court, who are as able to act that part as they.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good faith, thy Brother would do well to shew 'em the way at a distance— He had little to do, to discontent <HI>Sallette,</HI> &amp;
<PB N="100" REF="57"/>
another of his Apostles, for that Strumpet <HI>Condel.</HI> But he cannot endure a companion, and therefore he cannot endure himself. And so you, because you have got a little Latin by surprise, cannot endure that I should share with yee, in the Conversion of St. <HI>Mary Mont.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>If there be any difference between us two, the younger ought to submit to the elder by right of Nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heed of establishing that max∣im, and advise your Brother likewise; for the <HI>Huguenots</HI> would make a wicked ad∣vantage of it. Don't you know very well▪ That all the Catholic Ceremonies of <HI>Cali∣cut,</HI> where the Church visibly adores the Devil, are like the Ceremonies of the <HI>Ro∣man</HI> Church, both in respect of their Monks and Nuns, their auricular Confessions and Fasts. Nay their chief Priest is likewise call'd <HI>Papa,</HI> having also a Papal Crown which has not one nail less then that <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Rome.</HI> The Jesuits excuse it, by saying that the Devil is God's Ape upon Earth But the <HI>Huguenots</HI> on the contrary main∣tain, That the Pope is the Devil's Ape, fo<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that very reason which you have alleg'd because the Devil is eldest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speak softly, the Devil's a fool. Se<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> yonder the Baron of <HI>Salignac.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="101" REF="57"/>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis all one, he's one of my choice Fathers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Proselytes thou meanest, dissem∣bling Hypocrite as thou art. So, — he is gone by; sometimes he curses himself for having bin converted, and at other times he never minds it: I would not for twen∣ty good Pistols, that he had overheard us; or any other. who was not well resolv'd in his mind. Thou hast call<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d me Pimp, and I have call'd thee Whore, which is the more honourable of the two? Who would think that such Doctors are fit persons to recall revolters from Heresie, or to save Souls that are in jeopardie of Perdition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>For thy part, Pimp-major, as thou art such a one, it is a thing without example. In reference to my self, it is not so, who as I am a good honest insinu∣ating Whore, may promise my self better success, for such a one was <HI>Rahab.</HI> There's a president for yee. <HI>Rahab</HI> the Harlot, thou knowst receiv'd and sav'd the Spies of <HI>Isra∣el.</HI> Thus have I done; I have sav'd <HI>M.</HI> St. <HI>Mary,</HI> who though he were no Spie of <HI>Israel,</HI> yet acted as one of the King's Spies among the <HI>Huguenot Israelites.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give me thy hand — I am thy humble Servant; and if ever I hear any body scandalize thee, and say, that
<PB N="102" REF="58"/>
thou hast giv'n St. <HI>Mary</HI> the foul disease, I will tell 'em, no, — thou hast it still i'thy own custody for them, if they please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Math.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go too, say thou hast found a Mistress of me— Good morrow— I'le go and repeat all our discourse to <HI>Gue∣dron.</HI></P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. II. Of the re-union of Religion.</HEAD>
<P>IT being a task of great difficulty to de∣stroy the opinion of the <HI>Huguenots</HI> by Disputes, we have design'd what is more probable, a re-union of Religions, by the discoveries and intelligencies of the gain'd Ministers: but of six that there were, there are five dead, and one banish'd. With∣out doubt there would be no great danger for them to quit several Theological Te∣nets, provided the authority of the Church and the Pope remain entire. The reason is plain, for that they having submitted to the authority of them, they might easily afterwards lose their arguments by virtue thereof. And when our Jesuits made op∣position to several Articles, which the other
<PB N="103" REF="58"/>
were willing to grant, they did not smell the design, in regard that some of them aim'd rather at a civil War then p<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace of Conscience. Now you shall see what we, of the other Club of honest good fellows would have had the <HI>Romish</HI> Church let go. First, That the obedience should rest in the <HI>French,</HI> provided they dismiss'd some of their Drolleries which caus'd the people to laugh, as the beginning the Mass with an <HI>&amp;c.</HI> and other absurdities, which are di∣stinctly and sutly discuss'd by <HI>Bernard O∣chinus</HI> in his Treatise <HI>della Natività della Messa.</HI> As to the Ceremonies, take away the most ridiculous, and for the rest, make answer to what <HI>Bernard Ochinus</HI> says, That it is the Lord's Supper disguis'd, and clog'd with Ceremonies to make it appear more holy. Next, that the Priests should be per∣mitted to marry, and to leave their Wives when they grow irksom. In all cases to make use of the holy Decree, and its liber∣ties, as you find it in the Canon, <HI>is qui non habet uxorem, loco illius,</HI> &amp;c. It is nota∣bly said in the Rubric of the Decree, <HI>Quod qui non habet uxorem, loco illius debet concu∣binam habere. Ita nefas Episcopum creari nisi saltem unius Concubinae dominum.</HI> Distinct. 34. qu. 9. per de var. stud Vol. l. 4. sect. 5. <HI>Villavinceni</HI> ibid c. 4. Were these privi∣leges
<PB N="104" REF="59"/>
rightly observ'd and establish'd, he were the son of a Whore that would not be of the Church of <HI>Rome.</HI> Then we would abolish all Fasts, unless it were to the poor, and the sick; dismiss the Terrour of ima∣ginary Purgatory, yet without any injury to the mediation of Saints, for fear of ruining the Church. I do not without reason ad∣vise the abolition of Purgatory. There is nothing has made so many Souls very curi∣ous of their Salvation at their latter end, as the story which follows. A Priest when he comforts a sick person, tells him, That the pangs of death are the entrance into the Gehenna's of Purgatory; A Minister teach∣es him, that they are as the pains of Child-bearing, that lead into eternal life, and builds his argument upon this Text, <HI>This day shalt thou be with me.</HI> I will boldly say, That the <HI>Index expurgatorius</HI> ought to take notice of this passage. Now the relish of these two differences of dying, has caus'd seve∣ral good Catholics to renounce Purgatory upon their death beds, where the hopes and fears of this world give way to those of the other. We would have allow'd them for their Markets, Wednesday and Sa∣turday, Lent and Vigils, but that Policy has otherwise order<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d it, and thus we had made a perfect peace with St. <HI>Paul</HI> in the 4.
<PB N="105" REF="59"/>
of the 1. to <HI>Timothy.</HI> This is also a forget∣fulness of the <HI>Index.</HI> Also we ought to withdraw these marks of the Faith, of a∣busers, of Preachers of lyes, Hypocrisie, and the Doctrine of Divels. <HI>Calvin</HI> could not have said more. That no person read St. <HI>Paul,</HI> till the agreement be made, and firmly sign'd, and the pensions of the con∣senting Ministers well assign'd. At the same time the other Church shall reassume their Pomp, their Music, their Dancings, great Feastings, and the vast Revenues of their Church. These Ministers I would they might keep their Coaches, Hounds and Haukes. We would have established a free Liberty, especially to expel that trou∣blesome Discipline that has lost us so ma∣ny good people. We would not have ac∣compted for sins, simple Fornication, nor Adultery for love, according to <HI>Cahier</HI> in his learned book, upon the re-establishment of <HI>Bourdeaux,</HI> and his admirable dispute upon the 7. Commandment. I say the seventh, because we have releas'd the se∣cond, which the Council of <HI>Trent</HI> would needs take away. For this 7. Command∣ment, which is, <HI>non moechaberis,</HI> forbids the sin only to the Children of <HI>Onan,</HI> in re∣gard that according to our modern Theo∣logy <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> is deriv'd <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> and
<PB N="106" REF="60"/>
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>quod est humidum fundere.</HI> It had bin a brave Religion, which had rejected what was irksom to either, and had establish'd what was plausible and agreeing to both. Every one had bin receiv'd and satisfi'd, no one excluded. I know the <HI>Aristarchians</HI> will oppose my good intentions; but a∣gainst them I say, First, that the Church ought to have its arms open to all sorts of people. Now the expulsion of vices or in∣coveniencies is no reception. The <HI>Hugue∣nots</HI> cry, That the Church is only of the e∣lect; but this is too severe. Secondly, I would fain ask these sowerlings, whether they would be wiser then the Apostles, who desir'd to enter Judaism with honour? You see in the Epistle to the <HI>Galatians,</HI> how M. St. <HI>Peter,</HI> conform'd and comply'd like a complaisant Gentleman to the humours and infirmities of the <HI>Jews.</HI> St. <HI>Paul</HI> re∣prehends him; but Frier <HI>Gilles</HI> said, he might better have held his tongue, then spo∣ken so many things that smelt of the Fag∣got. But let us also examin what our Ho∣ly Fathers said, when they went about to give <HI>Paganism</HI> a decent Funeral. They taught us to paint our Lady after the anci∣ent Model of <HI>Vesta,</HI> holding little <HI>Jupiter</HI> in her Lap: the Trinity, like <HI>Medius— Fidius.</HI> They have brought in the <HI>Cornival</HI>
<PB N="107" REF="60"/>
instead of the <HI>Saturnalia</HI>; Twelf-day in∣stead of the <HI>Lupercalia.</HI> The first of <HI>May</HI> belonging formerly to <HI>Cloris,</HI> they gave a∣way to St. <HI>Thais,</HI> canoniz'd for that pur∣pose. The <HI>Pervigiliae</HI> are solemnis'd at <HI>Beaucaire</HI> upon St. <HI>Magdalen</HI>'s day in com∣memoration of her first Life. The Cur∣tisans have a Mass particular to themselves, which after they have said, they betake themselves to their Callings. <HI>Candlemass,</HI> what is it but the <HI>Februaria</HI> of the Ancients, when they lighted their Candles. Their Feast of St. <HI>John</HI> answers to the <HI>Palilia</HI> in honour of <HI>Pales,</HI> goddess of Sheep— What the ancients call<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <HI>Supplications,</HI> are no more then our <HI>Processions,</HI> especially at <HI>Poictiers,</HI> where they go in Procession to re∣quest water from the <HI>Naiades</HI>; and at <HI>Paris La descendente de la Chaste de S. Geneviesve</HI> is the same thing. In imitation also of an∣tient <HI>Gentilism,</HI> instead of their <HI>Lustral</HI> we have our <HI>Holy water,</HI> and set Bread and Wine upon the Graves of the deceas'd: of all which things honest <HI>Benedict</HI> one day said, <HI>Ista Paganismum sentiunt.</HI> In the same manner the Institutors of our Cere∣monies, have not bin asham'd of the most ancient leudnesses of Antiquity, as having ador'd the Garden God <HI>Priapus</HI> in several parts of <HI>France.</HI> Witness St. <HI>Foutin de
<PB N="108" REF="61"/>
Varailles</HI> in <HI>Provence,</HI> to whom are conse∣crated the secret parts of both Sexes, form'd in wax. The Chappel is well furnish'd; so that when the wind blows a little brisk, it causes no— small disturbance in the devout thoughts of those that come to ho∣nour that Saint. When the <HI>Huguenots</HI> took <HI>Embrun,</HI> they found among the relicques of the chief Church a <HI>Priapus</HI> a <HI>l'antique,</HI> which had bin unseemingly colour'd with red Wine, with which it had bin often wash'd: of which Wine the Women after∣wards made a holy <HI>Vinegre,</HI> for uses alto∣gether as strange and absurd. When those of <HI>Orange</HI> ruin'd the Church dedicated to St. <HI>Eutropius,</HI> they found another of the same kind, much bigger and more natu∣rally set out; which was publicly burnt by the Heretics. There is another St. <HI>Foutin</HI> in the City of <HI>Auxerre</HI>; a third in <HI>Verdre</HI> upon the Confines of <HI>Bourbonnis</HI>; another in the Diocess of <HI>Viviers,</HI> in low <HI>Langue∣doe,</HI> call'd St. <HI>Foutin de Cives</HI>; another at <HI>Pontigni,</HI> to which the Women resort, when they are with Child, or desirous of Chil∣dren. Thus you see how our Doctours have made <HI>Paganism</HI> and Christianity ac∣cord. It became them either in the name of God, or of some body else, only to unsow, and not tear in peices like those
<PB N="109" REF="61"/>
hot-headed Ministers, who desire the pu∣rity of Christian worship. I find <HI>Riviere,</HI> the King's chief Physician of a better hu∣mour then these people. He is a good <HI>Ga∣lenist,</HI> and a very good <HI>Paracelsian.</HI> He says that <HI>Galen</HI>'s method is honourable, not contemptible in the cure of diseases, but exceeding profitable to the Shops. The other, provided you follow the true pre∣cepts of <HI>Paracelsus,</HI> is an excellent Method for truth, suttlety of knowlege, and thrift. Therefore he deals by his Soul, as by his Body: being a <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic for his Profit, and a <HI>Huguenot</HI> for his Salvati∣on. Monsieur <HI>Gervaise,</HI> Philosopher of <HI>Magne,</HI> goes higher: For he maintains that all our Wars proceed from want of Gram∣mar. For had we follow'd <HI>Grandem Ma∣trem,</HI> we had spoken well; speaking well, we should be understood, and consequent∣ly agree; for we never fall out about dis∣course, but because we do not understand one another. His first rule is, That we should make a great abatement of <HI>Financi∣ers,</HI> who are the participles of interjecti∣ons, to silence the exclamations of the Pul∣pit: as also of several <HI>Nouns</HI> and several <HI>Adverbs</HI>; as <HI>Corporally, Transubstantially, Carnally</HI> and the like. This brave Blade boasted that he knew more of the state of
<PB N="110" REF="62"/>
Religion, then <HI>Bisouze,</HI> or his Foot-man, or M. <HI>de Royan,</HI> Ambassadour at <HI>Canada.</HI> But yet to fortifie my design more strongly by example, <HI>Roquelaure</HI> said, That he who refus'd to put all differences to the deter∣mination of three throws of the Dice, as <HI>Bridoye,</HI> ought to shut up a dozen of Do∣ctors, and as many Ministers in a Room with Victuals for one day; but not to let them have any more, till they had let down by a Rope out at the Window their final determination legally and firmly sign'd. The Curate of <HI>Eschillets</HI> said, That that would be foul play, in regard the Ministers are accustom'd to live upon little or no∣thing. As for his part, because he would not concern himself in troubles, he set all things to right in his Parish; so that when they brought him a Child to baptize, he ask'd of what Religion the Father and Mo∣ther was of? If they cry'd, we are of the Religion of our Fathers, then he whisk'd to the Altar half drest, and began, <HI>Adju∣torium nostrum in nomine Dei.</HI> If they said, That they had the knowlege of God by his Grace, then placing himself at the back of a Chair, and laying his hands upon it. <HI>Our Saviour teaches us what our first begin∣ginning is</HI>; Poverty, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> If it be a Mar∣riage, after the same question demanded,
<PB N="111" REF="62"/>
he either falls to his old <HI>Adjutorium,</HI> &amp;c. or else— <HI>God the Father, after he had for∣med man.</HI> This was a man of a yielding temper, not such a passionate Son of Thun∣der as Frier <HI>John Bonhornme,</HI> who let a loud F— for very madness in his Pul∣pit, crying out upon the Conversion of the
King, Courage,— my Parishoners, the Heretics are confounded, they dare no more call us Papishes, nor eat flesh in Lent before all the World. They shall make holy-day upon holy-days; They hang their heads like Bulrushes, while you exalt your horns, and flourish like the Cedars of <HI>Lebanon.</HI> And thus you have my own sentiments touching the Union of the two Religi∣ons.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. III. Of the Causes that mov'd me to my second Reformation, which was my third Conversion.</HEAD>
<P><HI>DAniel,</HI> as he says in his own book, pray'd with his Windows open,
<PB N="112" REF="63"/>
with his face turn'd toward the East. Oh! how I saw Monsieur Confessour, triumph one day upon this Text. In truth, he's a wonderful man, when he finds a Text pro∣per for his purpose. Therefore, said he, as <HI>Daniel</HI> when he pray'd, turn'd his face toward the rising Sun, so it always behoves a man of Virtue to address his Devotions to the rising Sun, to growing greatness; and to turn his tail upon them that are sink∣ing into disgrace. I made little accompt of the King after the feast of the <HI>Barricado</HI>'s, but having made a quick judgement of his prosperity, I vear'd my Devotions toward the beams of that fair rising Sun, who ha∣ving dissipated all Clouds, got into his hands all the forces of the deceas'd King, and brought the League to lye at his feet. I return'd from <HI>Auvergne</HI> and the confines of <HI>Italy,</HI> where I understood that the com∣mon Themes of the publick Disputes at <HI>Rome</HI> were the Comparisons between the King of <HI>Spain</HI> and <HI>France.</HI> Those Figure-casters found by their art in <HI>Geomancy,</HI> by Prophesies, by the fatal name of <HI>Bourbon,</HI> that this Prince was born to change the Hi∣erarchy into an Empire, the Chair into a Throne, and the Keys into Swords, and that he was to dye Emperour of the Chri∣stians. The <HI>Venetians</HI> ador'd the rising Sun
<PB N="113" REF="63"/>
with so much devotion, that when a <HI>French</HI> Gentleman pass'd only through their City, they ran after him with the same ardency, as the Frantic Dotrels ran after <HI>Rablais</HI>'s Pope, crying out, <HI>have ye seen him.</HI> Up∣on the Gentleman's affirming he had, the best of their Painters presently drew his picture by imagination, and so soon as the first picture was finish'd, the Gentleman was publicly treated. And after their Grandsigniour-ships had stood staring upon it, with their Chaps four fingers asunder for a quarter of an hour together, the Pain∣ter was paid to his heart's content, and the Picture hung up as safe as St. <HI>Marks.</HI> The Court of the Emperour, and <HI>Poland</HI> rang with nothing else but public thanks for putting the Empire into such happy and victorious hands, and nothing but re-union of Religions, or a toleration of all, was in every mans mouth. Much talk there was of bringing <HI>Italy</HI> to this, that the King of the <HI>Romans</HI> should be really so, and not merely titular. And for the re∣duction of the Pope to his Bishopric, the Duke of <HI>Saxony</HI> caus'd several Sermons to be Preach'd before him, upon the simili∣tude between <HI>David</HI> and this King; ho∣nour'd and rewarded those that were more in favour with this, then the former King;
<PB N="114" REF="64"/>
and sent a chain of Gold as far as <HI>Zurick</HI> to the Author of <HI>Carolus Magnus Redivivus.</HI> This high luster of Reputation seconded with so many warlike exploits, what did they not promise from this Prince? had he made use of the divisions already created betweeen the <HI>Muscovites, Poles,</HI> and <HI>Swedes,</HI> the <HI>Transilvanians,</HI> and the Em∣perour; and well knowing the infirmities of the King of <HI>Scotland,</HI> the several de∣signs in <HI>England</HI> upon the old age of the Queen, the revolt of <HI>Ireland,</HI> the decrepit years of the King of <HI>Spain,</HI> the ambition and suttlety of his Daughter, the small re∣putation of his Son, the designs of the Princes of <HI>Italy</HI> to recover their liberty, up∣on the declining years and affairs of their Tyrant. The Court of the grand Duke open to the King; <HI>Caesar</HI> of <HI>Ferrara</HI> at∣tempting the succession in <HI>France,</HI> which he saw beginning to fail. The Duke of <HI>Savoy</HI> disputing about the accomplishing the Articles of his Marriage. <HI>La Bresse</HI> lost; the rest almost ruin'd by <HI>Les Diguie∣res,</HI> and ill succour'd by their own. Above all things, the preparations of the Turks, mainly distracted both the minds and for∣ces of Christendom. These Occurrences design'd the King for the supreme Head of Christendom, in regard that all people be∣leiving
<PB N="115" REF="64"/>
in their hearts, that this King was acceptable to God for the purity and sin∣cerity of his Religion, prepar'd themselves either to suffer or follow him. At the same time I also began to think of throw∣ing off the Popes yoak, and so bring all Benefices without Curates into the treasury at War, by changing the Order of Priest∣hood, into the Order of Knight-hood. This was to be done, by putting into the Princes hands four times <HI>le Peron,</HI> without the expence or hazard of Convoys. I came to Court big with overtures, full of advantages, to be a partaker of such great expectations, Master of such a Treasury, and a good Servant to my Conscience by the same means, which was the chief con∣sideration. Judg. now, Gentlemen, if this change of judgment were not main∣tainable. In truth I was not sufficiently verst in the Cabals of the World, the in∣firmities of Princes, and less in the grand interests of Councellers of State to uphold the <HI>Diana</HI> of <HI>Ephesus.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="116" REF="65"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. IV. An Apology for my long stay among the Heretics.</HEAD>
<P>MAnifold are the considerations by which I was allur'd to a Religion once already tasted and follow'd, whence I was thrown out by the miseries that atten∣ded it: which miseries seem'd to be per∣mitted to afflict a poor Church, which in∣stead of Militant, took the course to become Triumphant. Some light of Salvation al∣so entic'd me; and whoever has at any other time experienc'd such combats of the mind, will excuse me for having consider'd and paus'd a while before I resolv'd. But having withal seen at a distance, what a leap I was to take, I took a resolution to assist the Catholic Party, assisting my Ma∣ster to jump the first frisk, that the Ser∣vant might be the less asham'd to follow him. The question was, how to weaken the <HI>Huguenot</HI> Party; and to bring that to
<PB N="117" REF="65"/>
pass, nothing more conduc'd then to un∣dermine their two main Pillars; the first of which, was that distinction of condition, by which, under the Law of Truces they were separated from our Politic Regiment. The second was that difference of Religi∣ons, which it was requisite to render less, that it might be afterwards utterly an∣null'd. We had a touch at the first of these, when the <HI>Huguenots</HI> liv'd in full pro∣sperity, when very unhappily they conclu∣ded, That having a King and a Protector in one and the same person, these two qua∣lities were inseparable without the loss of the thing. Upon this point we dispatch'd away that M. Busie-body <HI>du Fay,</HI> deserved∣ly a deceiver, and as deservedly deceiv'd; as appears by his Will and Testament, wherein he confesses, That he had betray'd the people of God, to raise his own For∣tune. But we are forbid to speak of that Will. He having a smooth tongue in his mouth, &amp; impudence enough upon his Fore∣head, in a months time he sent the Mass where he pleas'd himself, put down all the Chambers of Justice, caus'd them to quit their Treasuries, taught their men of War to dispute concerning States, to acknow∣ledge none but the King, who having ob∣tain'd that point, soon after lay'd the Pro∣tectorship
<PB N="118" REF="66"/>
aside: for finding the name of Protector too weighty for his shoulders, he buried it near the King's, at the door of St. <HI>Denis</HI>'s Church. For the bringing about these fine preparations, to all those who demanded of <HI>Fay,</HI> his particular Commis∣sion, <HI>Du Fay</HI> for answer, shew'd the Key of Madam <HI>Martine's</HI> Love-letters, which he said, was the key of the Seals of Nature. Some malicious <HI>Huguenots</HI> endeavour'd to oppose this conspiracy; the other <HI>Huguenots,</HI> either out of simplicity, or being brought over, call the War the <HI>Horn-war,</HI> and ac∣cuse their Brethren to the King. So that now the whole power rests in one man's hands. Their Judicature and treasure fall into the hands of Madam <HI>Formality,</HI> by which means we withdrew from them in a little time, the strong holds of <HI>Clermont, Joynville, Chasteaudun</HI>; and in <HI>Lorain, Ste∣nay, Ville Franche, Dan</HI> and <HI>Beaumont, Cha∣vigni, Aubena,</HI> and several other places. Thus I may safely boast to have given the most considerable stroaks toward the un∣dermining the Rampart of this distinction. For the second, God rest the Soul of the deceas'd <HI>Morlas</HI>; For if he and his Com∣panions had acted their part as well for the business of Religion, as for <HI>du Fay</HI>'s Estate, there had been no <HI>Huguenots</HI> in <HI>France,</HI> but
<PB N="119" REF="66"/>
such as were good for nothing but to be burnt: for the <HI>Huguenots</HI> of State, or of the Sword, which you please, had made up their pack. Yet we endeavour'd, to asto∣nish the more Godly, to have gain'd the proudest and most stately Six of their Mini∣sters; who had sworn, that being chosen for the dispute, after they had boasted ve∣ry high, they would make use of a Holy prevarication. That it might not be so, my Master <HI>Rotan,</HI> whisper'd me in the Ear, as he was going to the dispute at <HI>Mantes,</HI> that he would do like <HI>Otho,</HI> when he kill'd himself, that is, he would quit all his particular Interests to save Christianity from utter Ruin; but he was taken with a fretting in the Guts which prevented him. His Second was not so honest as he; He had prevail'd with the <HI>Huguenots</HI> to choose him in all affairs, and he was gene∣rally president. He had propos'd the Que∣stion among the Synods, whether if the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> were not the Church of Christ <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or at least <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, we might not be assur'd of Salvation therein? And this was the loop-hole out of which, the King and many others crept. He caus'd the word <HI>Papists</HI> to be left out of their Prayers, when they mix'd them with In∣fidels, and taught the young Ministers to
<PB N="120" REF="67"/>
speak mildly. Judge now throughly, good brother Catholic, in the midst of these holy Exercises, whether I have been an unprofitable servant to our Religion. Had I been as Impatient as <HI>Cahier,</HI> or a solliciter of Assignations, like <HI>Serres,</HI> I had never procured in the name of the <HI>Hugue∣nots,</HI> the Election of the Chamber. I had not had the Credit to send away <HI>Choupes,</HI> before the Parliaments rejected him. For that old man had been invincible, had he not thought me very zealous. I know not who it was that went about to bespat∣ter the Dialogue of <HI>Rosny</HI> and <HI>Revel</HI>; I am sure I was ready to dye for fear, when I read my name there. For had I been dis∣cover'd by that Divine, as well as by <HI>Morlas,</HI> I had lost my credit for ever. It was my Invention, during the Assemblies of the <HI>Huguenots</HI> to dispatch ten men into their ten several Provinces to sow the Darnel, which has so advantagiously prosper'd there ever since. They had all their dis∣patches under my hand, and were the ra∣ther encourag'd to go upon that design, be∣lieving me to be of the same Religion with them; especially <HI>Sowrce,</HI> an ancient person; <HI>de la Cour,</HI> that has made so many excellent Sermons, and <HI>Marmet</HI> of <HI>Nerac.</HI> He, tho we had mortify'd him by a te∣dious
<PB N="121" REF="67"/>
Famine, protested he would neither have accepted my mony, nor taken my In∣structions, but out of his assurance of my piety at that time. I taught the sprucest of the <HI>Huguenots</HI> this Lesson. <HI>Tarda sunt quae in publicum postulantur, privatam gratiam cito mereare, cito accipies.</HI> Do thy own bu∣siness, and let the public alone. I do not speak of those Aphorisms of State which I taught little <HI>Bisouse,</HI> his little Lacquay, <HI>Lomeny, Mainville,</HI> and M. <HI>de Royan.</HI> So well it appears, that I did the worst I could; like them who are afraid in the Siege of a Town; before they leap over the Wall, they scare their Companions, what in them lyes; and when they are o∣ver, being carry'd before the Commander of the Siege, they speak the worst they can to save themselves from disgrace. More∣over there are no Catholics so zealous, or that do more mischief to the <HI>Huguenots,</HI> then your new Converts. For proof whereof, I will make an Apology for the Jesuits, who are accus'd for setting all the World together by the Ears; for thereby they shew themselves true followers of <HI>J.C.</HI> coming as he did, to raise War against Fa∣ther &amp; Son, and to set Father &amp; Son at variance; not to be the messengers of Peace, but to carry Swords. And these are those
<PB N="122" REF="68"/>
little weapons, which they slide out of their sleeves, when they find it convenient to rid the World of a Monarch that will not submit to their Maxims. 'Tis requi∣site that Proselytes should sign their zeal with the blood of their former Compa∣nions. And <HI>Fougasse,</HI> Tutor to the Prince of <HI>Conde,</HI> has promis'd me, that he will breed up his Pupil to be the most treache∣rous and bloody Enemy of those, who have followed his Grand-father and Father, up∣on all occasions, where he can kill them, without being kill'd himself.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. V. Of the Miseries of the <HI>Huguenots.</HI></HEAD>
<P>SEeing I have display'd so large a field to the Brothers, for the discovery of my Conversion, I am resolv'd to satisfie the more curious, to shew that I made a se∣rious conscience of what I did. Every one is inquisitive what induc'd <HI>Sancy</HI> to this re∣volt? I ask, what constrain'd the King to the same? If they answer, to save his Ba∣con; that's my answer too. Ay, but
<PB N="123" REF="68"/>
that's ignominious—Poverty is more— Then Poverty there is nothing more dif∣ficult to undergo—which makes men contemptible and ridiculous. Hastening to the Port design'd—but changing the voyage and the wind, let us philoso∣phize a little upon the Question. This is not to follow, but always to pursue the same end. My end has been the same without Alteration, Profit, Honour, Ease, and Security. So then I pursu'd my aim, but only I chang'd the means. Now for profit, what means has a poor <HI>Huguenot</HI> to advance himself in time of peace? if he be a Country-man, the Catholics are the As∣sessors and Receivers, the <HI>Huguenots</HI> only Collectors. If he be a Gentleman, and expect any thing from the King, we our selves have left him nothing to dispose of. If Monsieur <HI>Huguenot</HI> pretends a title to any Benefice, we have made all the Ecclesiastics take their Oaths, to strike out their names, and not to keep their words, according to an Article made by the Council of <HI>Con∣stance.</HI> Their Titles will serve them in as little stead as those of <HI>Cheradame.</HI> This was a <HI>Huguenot</HI> of the Antient simplicity. I ask'd him one day whether he did quiet∣ly enjoy the Benefice of <HI>Bandoville,</HI> which the King had giv'n him? Yes, said he,
<PB N="124" REF="69"/>
for it is one of the Benefices of which it is said, <HI>The blessed shall inherit the Earth.</HI> Well, said I, but what Title can you shew that it belongs to you? A very good one said he, The Earth belongs to the Lord. Have you no better Foundation then that, said I; for those words mention nothing of <HI>Bondaville.</HI> How can I have a better assu∣rance, said he, then from Holy Writ; <HI>Thou hast lay'd his Foundations in the Sea,</HI> now to shew you that those words are spoken of <HI>Bandoville,</HI> if you have ever been there, read what follows, he hath enrich'd it, and environ'd it with many waters. All the reasons which the <HI>Huguenots</HI> can bring to our Judges, will signifie no more then these of <HI>Cheradame.</HI> As for honour, what content can they have among people that dare not give them respect; if the Edict will permit them to come to Court? who if they be merry with their Neighbours, shall have a supervisor set over them, that shall stick as close to their skins as a scab. If it be in time of War, what can a man of my Estate expect in those affairs? can they cant after our fantastic formalities? Honour is not to be got among us, but by dint of hard blows; which I must con∣fess I never much car'd for in my life, though they made me a Colonel of <HI>Swi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>zes.</HI>
<PB N="125" REF="69"/>
As for the point of Ease, what ease can it be to be clasp'd up in a Cuirass, like a <HI>Tortoise</HI> in his shell. And for security, they have only God to trust to upon all occasions, in whom a man of my humour seldom puts more then a moderate confidence. But to handle this matter a little more gene∣rally, I saw in <HI>France</HI> that their resolu∣tions were agitated to the wish of their Enemies; That they sought their security other-where then one among another, or within themselves. That they fix'd their resolutions in their Enemie's Country and not at home, as the <HI>Switzers</HI> do; look up∣on the Peace as concluded, before the Trea∣ty was begun, and bereav'd themselves of their advantages, and distinctions before it was proclaim'd. Which is worse, we have gain'd three in four of their principles, which caus'd them to treat as already sow'd up in the Kings party; not in War, for they bore Arms for him; not in Peace, for that their necessity urg'd them to treat; not in Truce, because they had quitted their Distinctions, their Judicature, their Treasure, and their separate Forces. So that being neither in War, nor in Peace, nor in Truce, they fancy'd a fourth con∣dition, which never was, tossing up one leg i'the Air, which could be no steady
<PB N="126" REF="70"/>
march. Some there were that cry'd shame upon these proceedings; others would not seek to remedy these things, unless the Grandees, who were gain'd by the King, would return among them, to buoy up their party, now patch'd up of several pie∣ces, choosing rather to be fat, then healthy. They apprehended their own weakness, without considering the distinction of affairs of State. Hence they began to treat with respect, to conclude without se∣curity. They did enough to offend, but not to defend. Thus were these poor people condemn'd in their simple fidelity, to be the sport of the great ones, persuaded to have pity upon <HI>France,</HI> when <HI>France</HI> had no pity upon them; to preserve it, when they had no interest in it; to fortifie it, when they had expell'd themselvs out of it. But when men have their hands ty'd by the fear of God, and a bashful respect of their Prince, they should be advis'd of their first motion; for whatever Peace they make, can be no Peace, but a Contract of Servitude.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="127" REF="70"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. VI. An examination of some Books of these times.</HEAD>
<P>WHen Monsieur Confessour came to my Lodging, he sent in three Por∣ters Load of Books to enhance the Cere∣mony of my Conversion. Some Censu∣rers of these times have observ'd that we did not lash one of them, but that after Dinner we spent all the day in playing at <HI>Cent.</HI> But I will shew those that were so careful to spie what was done that day, that I have well employ'd others in mo∣dern Theology: to authorize my design, I have read the Answers to the book of <HI>Plessis Mornay.</HI> 'Tis very great pity he has not had leisure to follow his studies as he did some 18. years ago. But since, he has had so many affairs of State under his hands, so much authority to sustain, such a large Family to govern, nothing has ap∣pear'd lately from him. The Theologist of <HI>Xantes</HI> seeing all our Dogs upon that Bear, and that none bit him, or durst so
<PB N="128" REF="71"/>
much as take him by the Ear, gave a leap at him; I would every one would do as much. For though he answer'd little to the purpose, yet what one cannot do sing∣ly, many may. There is the same method to be us'd against this person, and matters must d<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> boldly asserted without coming to the point of close argument; for mischief might come of it. As for <HI>Richeome,</HI> the Heretics are constrain'd to confess, that the style is the genteelest of any that has lately become public, at least the Preface: and if they say 'tis none of his, yet it is his either by way of gift or purchase. If the body of the work be dull and flat, is it not a common Custom for the Youth of these times, to wear the fore part of their Dub∣lets of Satin, and the hinder part of Can∣vass? Does he not do well to bring three Battalions before the King to persuade him to admit the Jesuits? Though in truth, three Battalions of eight Thousand men a∣peice, and fifty great Guns, would be more persuasive, and prove better Ad∣vocates, then the book of truth defend∣ed. Now in pursuit of my design, I put on my Spectacles, as when I play at Ta∣bles, and viewing at hand these three Bat∣talions, in the first Rank I saw none but a Company of Whipper Snappers with <HI>Mor∣rions</HI>
<PB N="129" REF="71"/>
guilt with leaf Gold. But any thing for a Civil War. At the head of 'em rode a fair Argument to prove Miracles. Nature is able to perform this or that. Such and such things have bin produced con∣trary to the order of Nature, <HI>Ergo.</HI> The Miracles of <HI>Ardilliers</HI> are not false. The Colours were of good Taffata. He that carry'd the Collonel's colours, having a mind to play the Coxcomb, and flourish his Colours under Leg as they do at <HI>Paris,</HI> strain'd himself so hard, that he befowl'd himself. This is the Confession of de∣ceas'd <HI>Beza,</HI> who bequeaths all to his Wife, and the rest to the <HI>Franciscans,</HI> dyes a good <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic, and this is that which became of him. I am told, an old arch Heretic read this book with a great deal of pleasure. I would make a slight answer; but perhaps he will burst himself with laughing, which would be an argu∣ment to prove Miracles, which is the subject of the book. I know abundance of Ca∣tholics look upon the supposition of his death as a strange thing. But in a book that treats of wonders, can any discourse be thought Miraculous? For my part I affirm and maintain it to be as true as other Miracles, That <HI>Beza</HI> is dead. First, by the argument by which we prove Transubstan∣tiation,
<PB N="130" REF="72"/>
God may cause him to dye. <HI>Ergo</HI> he is dead. Then again, This book which is in the rank and number of Traditions ought to be sooner believ'd then the Bible, as the Curate of St. <HI>Gervaise</HI> but lately preach'd. Traditions, said he, are sooner to be believ'd then the Old &amp; New Testa∣ment, provided that they are authoriz'd by Traditions, and not Traditions by them. More then this, <HI>Beza</HI> is Civily dead, by Banishment, and Spiritually dead, by Ex∣communication. But grant he be not dead, this news has always serv'd, the news has bin still made use of like a Vul∣tur's-skin to the stomach of some weak Ca∣tholics, to advance the pious frauds of ho∣nest Mr. Cardinal, according to this book, and that of the deceased good Queen his Play-fellow. Think you that that same book of St. <HI>Clement,</HI> which <HI>Capil</HI> the <HI>Ve∣netian</HI> found in the Isle of <HI>Crete,</HI> has not mainly conduc'd to the establishing private Masses. For all the World has not such a quick understanding, when they see the let∣ter by which St. <HI>Clement</HI> advertiz'd St. <HI>James</HI> of St. <HI>Peter</HI>'s death, to know that St. <HI>James</HI> was dead seven years before the other. 'Tis a great benefit for an ingeni∣ous man to understand who tells truth, whether <HI>Anaclete,</HI> who stiles himself Suc∣cessour
<PB N="131" REF="72"/>
to <HI>Clement,</HI> or <HI>Ireneus</HI> and <HI>Eusebius,</HI> who say that <HI>Clement</HI> succeded <HI>Anaclete,</HI> who notwithstanding that, wrote a very compleat Letter to <HI>Clement</HI> after he was dead. He speaks of the Temple of St. <HI>Peter,</HI> but it was an hundred years before the Christians had any Church. I alleg'd these things in imitation of that pious Fa∣ther, who living three hundred years be∣fore <HI>Constantine,</HI> nevertheless is so prudent as to call <HI>Byzantium, Constantiople,</HI> to the end ye may not laugh at the letter which — wrote to the Virgin <HI>Mary,</HI> and that other which <HI>J. C.</HI> wrote to the three honest Catholics, under the Cross at <HI>Azè</HI> in <HI>Poictou,</HI> op'nly read by the Curates of the Pa∣rishes. But not to injure the Chapter of Miracles, and to shew you that I was not converted out of Ignorance, I have read almost all <HI>Bellarmin,</HI> and I took great care, being resolv'd upon my Conversion, not to meddle with <HI>Whitaker, Lambert,</HI> or <HI>Rey∣nolds.</HI> I have read the Declamations and Fictions of <HI>Campanus,</HI> where I saw so ma∣ny Martyrs of the new Catholic Church, 'Tis the best way to read that book with∣out examination. I did more, for I stop'd my Eares against a Heretic, that would have made me believe all those Martyrs to be lyes and fables, alleging that there were
<PB N="132" REF="73"/>
two Characters of Martyrdom, the one, that it must be purely for Religion, and the other, that it be at the Parties own choice, whether he will live or dye. I began to swear that the Queen of <HI>Scot</HI>'s was a true Martyr. Oh, said the Heretic, what a miserable Re∣ligion is yours, that hath no Martyr pu∣rer then a Homicide, nor any more chast, then a Strumpet. I could have found i'my heart to have bang'd him, but he was a man of the Sword. I have read the Amorous Sermons of M. S. <HI>Panigarole,</HI> but cannot find what the Heretics report of his <HI>Cata∣mit</HI>: As to his Mistress indeed ye say something, for whose sake he begins one of his Sermons thus, <HI>'Tis for you, fair one, that I dye.</HI> Nor can I find fault with his Complement, for presently after he added, <HI>said Christ to his Church.</HI> He was a bold Preacher, yet not so bold neither, but that I have read in some of his Sermons preach'd at <HI>Turin,</HI> that although the Saints were Ca∣noniz'd, he did not beleive them all to be in Paradise. A wary man, not to be a general voucher for every body. I have read the Thundring Sermons of the Bishop of <HI>Bizonte,</HI> which hard'nd my heart for the Massacre at hand. Whoever read a more substantial Clause then this, <HI>Che la crudelta loro era pietosa, That their Cruelty
<PB N="133" REF="73"/>
was Mercy.</HI> I have read the writings of <HI>Re∣boul,</HI> who has told tales out of School, be∣cause he had bin whip'd there. That book will serve excellently well for a Farce, af∣ter those Tragedies, which afflict the squea∣mish &amp; raw Conscience of a Convert newly gall'd with his Conversion. I have read Dr. <HI>Boulanger,</HI> who has written like a De∣vil, all <HI>ran dan</HI> and without premeditation; they that will not believe me, may beleive their own eyes. He is better skill'd in Lo∣gic now, then when he disputed at <HI>Miot,</HI> and had he now to do with that blind zea∣lot, he would conundrum him in another manner then he did. For he has answer'd the Preface of <HI>Duplessis,</HI> at least he gives him good words; being resolv'd like the chief Captains of the holy Party, to ob∣serve this maxim, <HI>That in great underta∣kings, 'tis enough to shew a good intention.</HI> In the same manner I could not forbear laughing, when I read the <HI>I'ambonicum</HI> of <HI>Michau</HI> against him. 'Tis well known that the <HI>Sorbon</HI> has forbid him to write upon a Letter of M. Confessour. But in the reply of <HI>Michau</HI> I blame him for say∣ing, That the <HI>Boulangers</HI> are of <HI>Troye</HI> in <HI>Champagne.</HI> He was ignorant that they came from <HI>Lyons,</HI> where they could not stay as being too near <HI>Provence,</HI> where they
<PB N="134" REF="74"/>
had seen M. <HI>Auguste</HI> upon the <HI>Scaffold</HI> or upon the Ladder. I read the beginning of <HI>Doxemel,</HI> but he put me out of humour: At first I was pleased with young <HI>Sponde</HI>'s manner of arguing: for we have a young <HI>Sponde,</HI> as well as a young <HI>Nostredamus.</HI> They say the Widow wrote it; which causes many to admire, because it was ve∣rily thought that she had made all public before. I have not spoken at all concerning the Treatises of the Husband; because the first disgrace the later; which do not seem to be made with so good a will nor in so good an humour as the first. Those are full of discourse enliv'nd only by pomp of words, the first moving, and persuasive <HI>ad fidem faciendam.</HI> But the young man treating of consecrated Church-yards, draws from the sum of his discourse this consequential Argument. The <HI>Jews</HI> were very curious in reference to their Se∣pulchers. The <HI>Turks</HI> account their Sepul∣chers Holy, and go in Pilgrimage to <HI>Mec∣ca</HI>; The <HI>Pagans</HI> erected lofty <HI>Pyramids,</HI> canoniz'd their dead, and ordain'd them Supplications. <HI>Ergo</HI>; The Christians ought to do the like, in imitation of the <HI>Jews Turks</HI> and <HI>Pagans.</HI> But not to bereave any person of the honour which is due to him, we are well assur'd that this was the off∣spring
<PB N="135" REF="74"/>
of M. <HI>Raymund</HI>'s brain, or rather of his Host, who is also reported to have made the preliminary Epistle to <HI>Richeome.</HI> Let it be as it will, both together have taught me very fine fancies. First, that it is a duty to carry the Pope upon our Shoul∣ders. Thus the <HI>Pagans</HI> exalted their <HI>Druids</HI> and <HI>Vestals.</HI> The <HI>Romans</HI> were carry'd by their Slaves in Litters. The <HI>Chineses</HI> in <HI>Tunquin</HI> carry their Religious Orders a <HI>Cock loft</HI> in the same manner, and the Country people in <HI>Xantoigne</HI> upon their wedding days, are hoisted after the same fashion, as it is also the Custom in <HI>Lorrain. Ergo</HI>; We are to carry the Pope, Cardinals and Bishops upon our Shoulders, to shew our selves <HI>Pagans</HI> like the <HI>Chineses,</HI> or Slaves, as among the <HI>Romans,</HI> or else in imitation of the Courtly fashion, of the Country <HI>Bump∣kins</HI> of <HI>Xantoigne</HI> and <HI>Lorrain.</HI> The same Author tells, That Madam <HI>Simonite,</HI> he meant <HI>Sunamite</HI> kiss'd <HI>Elisha</HI>'s feet, <HI>Ergo</HI>; all Kings, who are <HI>Simonites,</HI> ought to kiss the Pope's feet. This Monsieur <HI>Raymund</HI> and his Companions, speak very well to the <HI>Hu∣guenots</HI> and their printed Complaints, by declaring to them that they do not com∣plain without a cause. For as <HI>Raymund</HI> says to <HI>Rabesne,</HI> contentiously wrangling to make a <HI>Huguenot</HI> Lady lose the Guardi∣anship
<PB N="136" REF="75"/>
of her <HI>Children</HI>; The Laws are not to be observ'd according to humour, or to please proscrib'd persons: and afterwards solliciting to have a <HI>Huguenot</HI> put to death, for a Murder which a pious Catholic had committed, we need not make any scruple to destroy the Estates of those whose lives are under Condemnation; or to cut off par∣ticular Members where the Body is under the general attainder of the Church. I have also read a book, much after the same rate, and which I believe to be a chip of the same block, mainly endeavouring to extir∣pate the memory of <HI>Papes's Joan.</HI> And to shew you that I have studi'd, and that I keep a Correspondence with the Learned, I have sent him an Epigram upon this subject, which begins <HI>Foemina quod mentita virum,</HI> to which I expect his answer.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VII. Of the Arrogance of the <HI>Huguenots.</HI></HEAD>
<P>IF ever any Prince would raign so exact∣ly, That neither Justice nor the word of God should have any cause to blame his Government, it behoves him to extermi∣nate
<PB N="137" REF="75"/>
the <HI>Huguenots</HI>: For they are a sort of strange people, that when the Ho∣nour of God comes in competition, tram∣ple under their feet the Honour of men, yea even of Princes. But those of this Age are a little more respectful. 'Tis pub∣licly known what strange reports they rais'd against the Mother of the late Queen-Mother, taxing her with unseemly famili∣arity with the Cardinal of <HI>Lorrain,</HI> as if she, that she might take the care of men upon her, had despoil'd all other women of their Vices. They made verses upon the said Cardinal for a good turn procur'd him by the Prince of <HI>Portian.</HI> But St. <HI>Nicaise,</HI> the said Cardinal's natural Son, honourably poyson'd the said Prince. These Knaves impudently reported over all <HI>France</HI> the news of a certain Picture, where the Car∣dinal, the Queen of <HI>Scots,</HI> and several o∣ther persons were lovingly entertain'd with a strange peice of workman-ship. And all these Stories printed after the great contests and execution of St. <HI>Berthelemy.</HI> At the same time they were so Arrogant as to de∣mand peace at <HI>Millaud,</HI> and cause him to order a peace, when they had no more then four or five Holds, more advantagi∣ous for them, then the last peace which was granted them by the Court of Parliament.
<PB N="138" REF="76"/>
You would not beleive how little respect they gave the Queen and the Councellers of State that attended her. Monsieur <HI>de Pi∣brac</HI> had made use of two pair of <HI>Topics,</HI> to frame a petition, which he addressed to the Deputies of the <HI>Huguenots,</HI> in the pre∣sence of the Queen. He wip'd his eyes with his Hankercher, the Duke of <HI>Mont∣spensier</HI> snivell'd, <HI>Richelieu</HI> sigh'd, <HI>Gadagne</HI> shew'd nothing but the whites of his eyes. When he came to <HI>Dixi,</HI> the Queen ask'd them, well, Friends, what have you to say to this? Now you shall hear the answer of limping <HI>La Meausse.</HI> Ma∣dam, because Monsieur has made such a fair speech, must we therefore perish? The same person halting by the Chamber of the Maids of Honour, over-heard <HI>Altri</HI> saying, Must we be confin'd to this Cursed <HI>Gascony,</HI> only for the Deputies four rusty Swords? <HI>Madamoiselle,</HI> answer'd this same <HI>Vulcan,</HI> I confess they are not so well scour'd as your <HI>Engines.</HI> 'Tis incredible how these people have bearded the greatest of Princes; and made head against them with their smart and brisk replys; as for example, that of the Prince of <HI>Conde</HI> to the Queen Mother, who seeing a Troop of white Coats march by, reproach'd him, that his Souldiers were Millers. Yes Madam, reply'd the Prince,
<PB N="139" REF="76"/>
to handle your Asses. The same Prince, at another time, when the King ask'd him, why he did not acknowlege the Virgin <HI>Ma∣ry</HI> for the Queen of Heaven, made answer, Because 'twas pity, so fair a Kingdom should be govern'd by a Distaff. To give you fresher marks of their Boldness; The King, then King of <HI>Navar,</HI> having sent <HI>Aubigny</HI> to <HI>Hen.</HI> the 3d. to restore him the honour of his Alliance, before he did him∣self right, either for his Sister, or the inju∣ries which had bin done him; the King in a great fury reply'd, Let your Master, if you call him so, have a care what he does, if he knows me to be his King, I shall put such a weight upon his Arms, as would make the great <HI>Turk</HI> stoop. To which this impudent <HI>Huguenot</HI> made this answer, Sir, the King of <HI>Navar</HI> my Master, has to his great grief bin bred up under this Bur∣den. Without Threats, the homage of his Life and Fortunes is at your Majesties Devotion; But the homage of his honour he will yeild to ne're a Prince in the World, so long as he has a drop of blood in his Body, and a Sword by his side. But not to relate the sawciness of them, who make profession of it, what think ye of the poor Potter M. <HI>Bernard</HI>; to whom the King one day said these words, It is now five and
<PB N="140" REF="77"/>
forty years since you first serv'd the Queen, my Mother, and me, we have suffer'd you in the mid'st of Flames and Massacres, to enjoy the freedom of your Religion all this while; but now I am so perplex'd by those of <HI>Guis<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> and my people, that in spite of my teeth I must be forc'd to put those two poor Women and you in Prison, both they and you shall be burnt to morrow, if you change n<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t your opinion. Sir, answer'd <HI>Bernard,</HI> Yesterday the Count <HI>Mauleurier,</HI> came to proffer those two Sisters their Lives, if they would each of them permit you a nights lodging. They answer'd, They would be Martyrs as well for their Honour as for their Religion. You have told me also several times you would have pity upon me: But I take pity upon you, who have pronounc'd these words; I am constrain'd; you do not speak like a King. Those Virgins and I, who I hope have a share in the Kingdom of Heaven, will teach you this Royal expression, <HI>That nei∣ther the</HI> Guisarts, <HI>nor all your people, nor you your self, shall constrain a poor Potter to bend his Knee to Images.</HI> Did yee ever hear such an impudent Scoundrel? You'd swear, he were one of <HI>Seneca</HI>'s Disciples, <HI>qui mori scit, cogi nescit.</HI> He that knows how to dye, know's not what compulsion means.
<PB N="141" REF="77"/>
More malapartness then this appear'd in these people at the last Treaty of Peace, and at the Assemblies which continu'd four years, where these self-will'd moody Mules with∣stood not only the honestest Deputies which the King could pick out of his Council of State, but all the Grandee Lords of their own party. These forheads of Brass cry'd out, These Propositions do not answer the good opinion which we had conceiv'd of those which were sent to us. They were ask'd the meaning of these words, <HI>La Valiere</HI> stands up; the meaning, quo he! The meaning is, That ye go about to betray the Church of God. Monsieur <HI>Le Villeroy</HI> told me, that being sent once to parley with these <HI>Male-contents,</HI> while <HI>Calignon</HI> was en∣deavouring with a Sugercandy-speech, to soften their fury, that Lubber <HI>Chamier,</HI> ha∣ving lay'd his Cloke under his Buttocks, lean'd with his left Elbow i'the very mid∣dle of the Table, and in that posture fell a paring his nails, which were so long, that the Splinters flew in the Oratour's beard, one hit <HI>de Rosny</HI> in the eye; yet no body durst reprove him; for his very Counte∣nance shew'd how little it would be to the purpose. <HI>Choupes</HI> was so audacious as to car∣ry to the very Privy Council the refusal of all the Parliaments of <HI>France,</HI> and could
<PB N="142" REF="78"/>
hardly be hawl'd from the door by the ho∣nest <HI>Huguenots</HI> of the Court. <HI>Aubigne</HI> was so void of modesty, that when the King had given him a handsom reception at <HI>Senlis,</HI> and did but only ask him a civil question, what he thought of the wound that <HI>Chastel</HI> had given him i'the lip, this unmannerly Clown made answer, I say, Sir, said he, that that same God, whom as yet you have only deny'd with your lips, has only smitten your lips, but so soon as you shall renounce him with your heart, he will strike and peirce that heart. I could name another, that was an ancient Deputy, who sitting one day with the rest of his associates upon a Trunk in the Anti-Chamber, took notice that M. <HI>d'O.</HI> young <HI>Rosny,</HI> and some others of the Court Gal∣lants laught to see the Deputies in their old fashion'd Garments. These airy Courtiers having a mind to shew their Wit, says one to the other, I'le say he's a brave fellow that dare's but go and ask that old Curmud∣geon of a Heretic his name. <HI>D'O.</HI> to shew his valour approaches the old man, and full of high flown conceit, Sir, says he, these Gentlemen and I have an earnest desire to know your name. If I knew how to call you, said the other, I might perhaps give you an answer; I am a Gentleman, but not
<PB N="143" REF="78"/>
at your Conmand. Sir, said the Courtier my name is <HI>D'O.</HI> It may be so, reply'd the Deputy, had you bin in as many Battels as I, you needed not have ask'd the Question. As for <HI>O</HI> 'tis a Cipher better known in the Chamber of accompts, then where I have bin. The Brethren of the Cabinet fell a laughing, but the poor Messenger was more dash'd out of countenance, upon what the Deputy added. Go, friend, go, go kill some-body, that the King may bestow some favour upon yee, otherwise ye may chance to go without it. The Sieur <HI>Bellevre</HI> being sent by the King, to the King of <HI>Na∣var</HI> at <HI>Mont de Marsan,</HI> every morning, through the window of his Lodging, saw the <HI>Countess de la Guiche,</HI> then Miss in waiting, going every morning to Mass at∣tended by <HI>d'Espent,</HI> little <HI>Lambert,</HI> a <HI>Black,</HI> the <HI>Baboon Bertrand,</HI> an <HI>English</HI> Page, a shock Spaniel, and a Lacquey. Of all which the great Senatour took notice to a <HI>Huguenot</HI> in these terms. I have several times, said he, seen some Mistresses of our Kings, who are with them in such esteem, that the greatest Peers of the Nation think themselves happy, if they can but watch their coming out in a morning to pay their respects. But here I see a Lady of a no∣ble Family, who turns and winds the King
<PB N="144" REF="79"/>
as she pleases, walk to the Church in a morning, fitted for all purposes with a Monkey, a Shock, and a Buffoon. Oh Sir, the reason's plain, reply'd the <HI>Huguenot,</HI> for in this Court there is neither Ape, nor Shock, nor Buffoon, but what you see. The <HI>French</HI> Courtier was not a little non∣pluss'd at the reply; but much more when he knew the St. <HI>Maxants</HI> Curse upon the cheek of Madam <HI>Duras.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VIII. Of Martyrs after the <HI>Romish</HI> way.</HEAD>
<P>OF all the Books, which are enough to make a man a Heretic, or of which at least a <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic ought to be very careful: I find none, next to the Bible to be so dangerous as this great Volum of Martyrs. For 'tis a great matter to see five, six or seven thousand dead people, with all the Marks of real Martyrdom, as probi∣ty of Life, purity of Religion, and full freedom to choose either Life or Death. This has depriv'd us of abundance of peo∣ple that beheld those Preachers, who had no
<PB N="145" REF="79"/>
other Pulpits then the Scaffold, the Ladder or the flaming Faggot. These are the glo∣rious Nicks of time, when vain hopes are said to give place to Zeal and Vertue. They order their affairs now more prudently, both in <HI>Italy</HI> and <HI>Spain.</HI> There does not a Year go about, wherein they do not put to death some hundreds. But their con∣stancy has no other witnesses then Goalers and Hang-men, who are like the Cranes of <HI>Pyrrhus</HI> for keeping secrecy. 'Tis not above Thirty Years ago, that all the Pro∣cesses, of which this dangerous book is full, and which testifie the truth of it, were or∣der'd to be taken off the files of all the Courts of Parliament. But is their no way to stifle the memory of these things, and to cry down all these Stories for Fa∣bles, though the eye-witnesses are living? What shall we do? I am of opinion that the best way will be, to make Choice of some florid stile, like that of the Count <HI>de Permission,</HI> and to write a Book, of which the Title shall be, <HI>The Martyrs</HI> a la Roma∣na, <HI>or after the</HI> Romish <HI>manner</HI>; Wherein we will not have so much as one finger of a Martyr of the Primitive Church; in re∣gard there is some debate concerning them, between the other and us; as also for that, these blessed Reformers cry that the
<PB N="146" REF="80"/>
Church has bin as long reformed as it has bin persecuted, according to what Pope <HI>Silvester</HI> said, when <HI>Constantine</HI> freed him from the Rocks of <HI>Soracte,</HI> Farwel Po∣verty, Farwel Purity. Now then we must make it out, that we have Martyrs of this Age of as good Families as any of o∣thers. The Bel-weather of the Flock shall be the Curate of St. <HI>Medard</HI> in <HI>Paris,</HI> who was wounded in ringing the Alarum Bell. The Curate of St. <HI>Crespin</HI> in <HI>Tourain,</HI> who was hang'd in the Bel-rope performing the same Office: both taking pains to stir up the people to make another sort of Martyrs. From thence, to disguise the Story, we will take a frisk to <HI>Japan,</HI> where the Je∣suits say some of them have bin crucifi'd, and where they have done several Miracles, which could be done no where else but at <HI>Japan,</HI> because of the incredulity of the rest of the <HI>Indians.</HI> Moreover we will condemn all the <HI>Huguenots</HI> in <HI>France</HI> to go thither, to see if what they say be true. Our Fathers the Jesuits, foreseeing the necessity of this book, &amp; that there will be more Confessours then Martyrs; On the other side, the <HI>Hu∣guenots,</HI> instead of putting men to death for the Faith, busying themselves in praying to God for their Conversion: The sharp-witted Projectours have provided a reme∣dy
<PB N="147" REF="80"/>
for both; having set up at <HI>Rheimes</HI> and at <HI>Rome,</HI> two Colleges of young <HI>English,</HI> chosen out of a Melancholy adust humour, the most part Exiles, Thieves or defam'd persons, who when they are put into these Colleges, as <HI>Marius Navarrus</HI> writes in his 3. book of Councils, by an establish'd Pa∣pal constitution, are bound to swear, That after so many years they shall return into <HI>England</HI> to publish what they have learnt. And because it has bin observ'd that much good has come of it, witness Cardinal <HI>A∣lain,</HI> in his Apology for Seminaries, the Pope has redoubled their Pension. Here∣upon, I guess <HI>Baronius</HI> in his <HI>Roman</HI> Marty∣rology said these words, <HI>That the holy Priests, as innocent Lambs, fatted in the Sa∣cred Cloysters, by the holy society of</HI> Jesus, <HI>with divine instructions for Martyrdom, Sa∣crifices acceptable to God and the Sacred Col∣leges of</HI> Rome <HI>and</HI> Rheimes, <HI>have bin put to death, because they preach'd in</HI> England <HI>the Doctrine of the Holy</HI> Romish <HI>Church.</HI> I wish he had not said it, in regard they are Envoys of the Society of Jesuits: because they are accus'd to be liberal enough of o∣ther men's blood; and therefore though it be a commendable thing to meet Martyr∣dom, yet I would not have them guilty of sending people meerly upon that errand.
<PB N="148" REF="81"/>
Then to breed 'em up as Victims to God, that looks as if we Sacrific'd them our selves; and smels a little of <HI>Baal-peor.</HI> A∣gain, the word <HI>Cloyster</HI> sounds like a Pri∣son, as if we kept them in Sties to force them to keep their Oaths: and upon this the Heretics would be upon our bones, and say of the God to whom we sacrifice them; That it must be some God of this Age, or else some God of the Earth; for that the God of Heaven requires now no more Sacrifices at all, nor never did those of human blood. But that which spoils all is the word,— <HI>fatted</HI> or <HI>greas'd.</HI> I ask'd Archbishop <HI>Valgrand,</HI> what the meaning of it was; he sent me to the <HI>Saturnalia</HI> of <HI>Lipsius l.</HI> 1. <HI>c.</HI> 14. There I found that the Term was proper to the Gladiators who were pick'd out of the condemn'd persons or miserable Slaves, and afterwards main∣tain'd in their sacred or rather execrable Seminaries, to the end they might purchase their fat by their death; of whom <HI>Pro∣pertius.</HI></P>
<Q>Qui dabit immundae venalia fata saginae.</Q>
<P><HI>Bellarmin</HI> did very ill to put us in mind of the ninescore taken at <HI>Menerbè,</HI> who, e∣very one of them chose rather to be burnt,
<PB N="149" REF="81"/>
then to deny the least tittle of their Religi∣on. And <HI>Antonine</HI> did very ill to write, that they gave the Prisoners their choice, either to abjure their Religion and have their liberty, or dye; whereupon a hun∣dred and fourscore chose rather to be burnt. For which reason I would not have him that makes our book of Martyrs med∣dle with your ear-lulling <HI>Latin</HI>; which af∣fected persons, to shew their gift, make use of to our prejudice, and the discovery of our business. The <HI>Balderdash</HI> Latin which Monsieur Confessour uses, will be good enough for us. And in pursuit of our design we must gain in <HI>England</HI> some Ministers or other Officers, that when they hang our people there, may discourse to 'em some point of Religion, and not of Warlike preparations, Seditions, Petars, Guns, Mines and Poysons from the Pope's Apothecary. Then upon the Ladder they must have their choice either to turn, or turn off the Ladder. For those <HI>Heretics</HI> never account for Martyrs any but those, who have such a choice propos'd to them, and such as it appears by their Endite∣ments, that they dye for the sole point of their Religion. According to this Rule they never list for Martyrs, those that are arm'd for their defence, but only such as
<PB N="150" REF="82"/>
have no other Weapons but their Prayers. Such as were the 17000 <HI>Albigeois</HI> slaugh∣ter'd in one day, and the 30 or 40000 Souls sent upon St. <HI>Bartholomews</HI>-day to the furies of St. <HI>Bartholomew.</HI> But as for us, who have a better view of things, I am not of opinion, that we should be so nice, but let us muster, for default of o∣thers, in our Martyrology all those that are slain in Battails, Seiges, Skirmish∣es and Duels. Especially such as have fought against the Heretics; and all the <HI>Irish,</HI> their Wives and Children that are starv'd to death in the streets of our Ci∣ties. These are the Victims of that great Sacrificer <HI>Sanders,</HI> and other Doctors, who notwithstanding several pardons, caus'd them to make use of the <HI>Bull</HI> of the Holy Father <HI>Pius</HI> the V. as <HI>Bellarmin</HI> reports, by virtue whereof they made no scruple of violating their Allegiance to the Queen. And as for them, that lay sculking in the Niches of <HI>Pont Neuf,</HI> not then finish'd, and in the night time Rob'd all those that pass'd along, and then threw them into the River, if there be any scruple of cano∣nizing them, we must be careful what we do, lest we should injure them that did no harm but only to the <HI>Heretics.</HI> There are some who believe the Bishops ought to
<PB N="151" REF="82"/>
tain the poor; But my thoughts are, that they are for the generality very uncharita∣ble, out of a good intention to fill our Book with the sweet scented Sacrifices of their starv'd Bodys. Of which number were those poor people, whom the Bishop of <HI>Mayence</HI> caus'd to be burnt, out of a good intention, to save Corn. If the <HI>Hu∣guenots</HI> refuse these at the Muster, we will in spight of their teeths, pass them for Martyrs whom we allege to have dy'd in the Wars. We have a good Title to it: For the Fathers of the Society of <HI>Bourde∣aux</HI> have learnedly consulted about it, and wrote them down by parcels in the Trea∣tise of the Massacre at <HI>Coutras,</HI> of which Pamphlets <HI>Paris</HI> was full. All honest men believe, that the <HI>Huguenots</HI> being forc'd to the Battel, gain'd the Victory by Treache∣ry, in regard they had hid their Canon un∣der ground, and by that means made our people fly in the Air like so many Birds. By this Ladder we mount to Heaven much more noble Martyrs then the Heretics can do. St. <HI>Foy</HI> was made Bishop of <HI>Senlis,</HI> for having plac'd the last <HI>Charles</HI> among the Martyrs. If so, there is a Bishopric due to me, for having muster'd up such a scroll of Martyrs as I have done. But to return to my Text, the King, said that
<PB N="152" REF="83"/>
good Preacher, had so much trouble to mas∣sacre the <HI>Huguenots,</HI> that he dy'd for grief, because he could not finish his design, nay some say, that he dy'd blaspheming for madness. 'Tis a Gentile expression which some of our Doctours use, to some con∣cerning the Millers Bridg, I mean those Ca∣tholic <HI>Bigots,</HI> who beleive that God over∣whelm'd that Bridge, as being the Scaffold of the Butchery, and that it was a notable mark of Celestial Vengeance. But I say no, 'twas not for the Cruelties exercis'd, but because they exercis'd no more, by which default of theirs, I warrant ye, we lost above six or seven hundred fresh-water Martyrs. But may we not search for those who have dy'd in cold blood? Of that sort the most bright-shining Martyr is the Queen of <HI>Scots,</HI> who had blown up her Husband before, con∣stantly resolv'd so to do, notwithstanding all the kindness and amorous humility which he shew'd her. 'Tis true indeed, her heart taught her what belong'd to gun-powder. But 'tis all one, she shall be ca∣noniz'd, and in spight of the Heretics teeth, she shall be plac'd in the Almanack next to St. <HI>Mary</HI> the <HI>Egyptian,</HI> only for distinction sake, she shall be called St. <HI>Mary Morter∣peice.</HI> At her feet we well place <HI>Peter Ed∣mond,</HI> and— with their Company of a
<PB N="153" REF="83"/>
hundred and ten, according to the account of <HI>Baronius.</HI> The most part of these were brave Souldiers, excellent <HI>Petardeers</HI> of the Seminary of <HI>Maurevel,</HI> and the ancient <HI>de La Montagne,</HI> who for a small sum would have taken any man out of your way that offended ye, or obstructed your designs, ha∣ving always an intention against Heresie. The Souls of these we must believe to be sav'd, for they would fain have damn'd 'em themselves, but you know what is said of them that willingly lose their Souls. <HI>Maurevel</HI> was so zealous a Catholic, that in hatred of misbeleivers, for a small sum of money which the Queen had pro∣mis'd him, having fail'd at <HI>Moncontor</HI> to kill the Admiral, however he offer'd a bloody and sweet smelling Sacrifice to her Interests, by murdering <HI>Mosny,</HI> who for a long time had maintain'd him, and rais'd him. He was afterwards martyr'd by <HI>Mos∣ny</HI> the Son. As for old <HI>de la Montagne,</HI> he was a shrewd cunning Fellow, and as I may say, the Patriarch of the Jesuits. For by assuring his zealous Assassinates of his counterfeit Paradise, he sent them away o∣verjoy'd, to dye themselves, to murder the Heads of the Christians. This Para∣dise was the Model of a Chamber of Me∣ditation. For the more variety and orna∣ment
<PB N="154" REF="84"/>
of this our design we will bring in all the Crucifixes, Statues of Saints, both Male and Female, whether of Stone or Wood, in whose faces, as <HI>Baronius</HI> observes, the <HI>Huguenots</HI> have spit, or have any other way abus'd, by treading them under their feet, pulling out their eyes, or cutting off their ears or noses. To these we may add the bodies of dead Saints, which they have burnt, as that of St. <HI>Claude,</HI> together with the Abby, in the year 1654. 'Tis very true, that some pious Christian or other put in its place the Body of one that was hang'd at <HI>Dortaile.</HI> For new Martyrs we have <HI>Chesse, Bencharde,</HI> and that fair List of <HI>Plessis de Cone,</HI> and <HI>Fontenelle.</HI> Nor must we forget the Martyrs of <HI>Blois,</HI> the Father of whom was a canoniz'd Martyr at <HI>Rome,</HI> under the name of St. <HI>Francis</HI> the <HI>Pistoleer</HI> of <HI>Orleance.</HI> Their Posterity shall be also canoniz'd, that is to say, <HI>Henry</HI> of the <HI>Barricados,</HI> and St. <HI>Denis</HI> Captain, and Cardinal. On the other hand we will put M. St. <HI>Clement,</HI> and M. <HI>Sponde,</HI> one martyriz'd by the Procurator General, the other by his Wife. These two zealous Personages I have put together to spite the <HI>Huguenots,</HI> who mistrusting to what end they were canonis'd, one so soon after the other, marry'd them together in the follow∣ing <HI>Epigram.</HI></P>
<Q><PB N="155" REF="84"/>
<L>Qui modo Clementem voluisti jungere divis,</L>
<L>Et Spondam Divis annumerare potes.</L>
<L>In vitas Regum fuit insidiator uterque:</L>
<L>Ille animum Regis sustulit, hic animam.</L></Q>
<P>What shall become of St. <HI>Chastel,</HI> S. <HI>Bur∣goign,</HI> St. <HI>Guinan,</HI> St. <HI>Barriere,</HI> St. <HI>John Nilhet,</HI> and St. <HI>Garnet</HI>? We must also have room for the President <HI>Brisson,</HI> and the five Martyrs, and the St. <HI>Hangman</HI> who was executed with them. Among the rest must be admitted the twelve St. <HI>Francis∣cans</HI> of <HI>Chasteau Villain,</HI> whom the deceas'd Admiral caus'd to be lay'd hold on for mur∣dering the sick Souldiers of the Army, wherever they met with them. The great∣est grief to the rest was, that two of these poor Martyrs quarrell'd, who should have the Commission to perform the Execution. To decide this Ambitious debate, each of the two had a Rope given them, to try who was the most dextrous at the sport. Ne∣ver did two nimble Skip-jacks shew more dancing Bear tricks to avoid the Noose, then these two Rascals did; of which one at lenth was seiz'd, as he was giving a jump upwards. The Victor having securely strangled his <HI>Compagnen,</HI> hang'd all the rest. For the hangman and the persons executed
<PB N="156" REF="85"/>
were all of the same Livery. This shoot of St. <HI>Francis,</HI> so long as the War endur'd, ne∣ver chang'd either his employment or his habit; but knowing where there was a young Novice, who had escap'd out of the Covent, sent for him to be his journey∣man. After that they went on chearfully with their business, and were very useful to∣ward the Discipline of the Army, it being a common word of admonition, ware the <HI>Franciscan.</HI> Among the <HI>Neoterics</HI> are also Father <HI>Henry d'Anvers,</HI> and <HI>S — de Sau∣mur,</HI> who were burnt for being <HI>Roman</HI> Ca∣tholics, according to the Interpretation of the Count of <HI>Rochefort.</HI> They confess'd a very strange exercise of their piety, with∣out which confession the latter could not have bin burnt; For the Scholer and the Sergeant were only whipt for having de∣voutly attempted to murder <HI>du Plessis,</HI> that arch Heretic. Here M. S. <HI>Biron</HI> comes in for a share, who having all his life time liv'd in contempt of all Religion, all of a suddain grew so sottishly superstitious, that if he found in his way any little remaind∣er of a broken Cross, he stop'd and crawl'd upon his Knees fourscore or a hundred pa∣ces to kiss the dirty stone where it was fix'd; insomuch that near <HI>Bretigny</HI> in <HI>Bur∣gundy</HI> he kiss'd another between two T—
<PB N="157" REF="85"/>
He was one of the Churches great Gates: for he had renounc'd God, and sworn to kindle a War in <HI>France</HI> against the <HI>Hugue∣nots.</HI> He was the Devil of a man, but of a plausible behaviour. Don't you believe that he swore like a <HI>Huguenot,</HI> any more then <HI>Cotton,</HI> when he was run through the left Buttock. You have a notable Martyr of M. S. <HI>Bosnier,</HI> whose story the wicked <HI>Feneste</HI> stole from us. But he forgot the difference between his Wife and the Coun∣tess of <HI>Norton</HI> about the Gown and Petti∣cote which the She-Physician got by doing and not doing. For the Countess having declar'd to her Husband tha she had made a Vow for Chastity for four days in a week; her Husband made another, for the other three. The poor Lady dy'd for grief, and is now a Martyr <HI>Alamode.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. IX. The Corollary.</HEAD>
<P>ONE day, that it thundred, Monsieur Confessour came to visit me, and found me in a great confusion, shortly after
<PB N="162" REF="86"/>
my Conversion. I had not slept well the night before, and without lying, I could have wish'd my Conscience had lain by its self. That which troubl'd me in the E∣vening was the cursed company of idle stories that were brought me, how the <HI>Hu∣guenots</HI> began to enter into new Consulta∣tions concerning their affairs. That Cox∣comb <HI>Luat</HI> had open'd my eyes to see, how that after my Conversion, the King put no confidence in me; on the contrary, that <HI>Rosny</HI> who continu'd a firm Heretic got ground in the King's favour, and thereby great Authority in <HI>France.</HI> In the mid'st of these thoughts, I call'd to mind the mi∣serable ends of <HI>Sponde,</HI> discountenanc'd by the King after his Conversion; of <HI>Morlas,</HI> of <HI>Clairville,</HI> grieving at his death to have damn'd himself to gain something, and yet never to tast the pleasure of enjoyment; of <HI>du Fay</HI> who dy'd altogether slighted, and despairing to that height, that he publicly question'd, whether the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> were the Church of Christ. <HI>Barrilliere</HI> like him, was upon the same strain. <HI>Sallettes,</HI> who steer'd the same course, as having bin taught by his Wife, That he who greatly fears God, is also afraid of men; She that never fearing nor refusing the men of this World, was bold against God. The ends
<PB N="163" REF="86"/>
of these men pester'd my thoughts, with many others of the same sort. While I was in this Agony, I saw M. <HI>Cahier</HI> walk∣ing in the lower Court. To him I ran, and ask'd him what was become of the Mi∣nister <HI>Le Vaux?</HI> Sir, said he, that unfor∣tunate person, after the fair promises which he had made to <HI>Monsieur d'Evreux,</HI> and the money which he receiv'd from him for the performance thereof, a Rascally Feaver seiz'd him, and he is gone, into his own Country, tearing and raving that the cause of God was betray'd by him, and five of his Associates, whom he fairly character'd, without naming them. To this, he ad∣ded, that he hop'd God would pardon him, into whose hands he was going to surren∣der his Soul, so soon as he came to <HI>Millaud.</HI> He offer'd in the mean time to write to <HI>M. d'Evreux,</HI> in recommendation of some a∣ble person, and withal discover'd the pre∣varication of the dispute at <HI>Mantes,</HI> and the other preparatives of <HI>de Roan</HI> and <HI>Ser∣res,</HI> who you know, had offer'd their per∣fidious mediation at a lucky time. The <HI>Huguenots</HI> were so silly as to refuse the of∣fer, saying, That the Church of Christ was not establish'd upon tricks and fallacies. A little while after, added he, when he came to <HI>Millaud</HI> he continu'd his crys and la∣mentations
<PB N="160" REF="87"/>
especially upon the day that he dy'd; upon which day he walk'd out of the City with his freinds, supp'd well, but so soon as he was a-bed, he call'd his Wife, told her he should dye, repeated these Lines of the <HI>Psalmist.</HI></P>
<Q><L>A Soul with true Repentance fill'd,</L>
<L>Is thy most grateful Sacrifice;</L>
<L>A brok'n and a contrite heart</L>
<L>O God thou never wilt despise.</L></Q>
<P>And having so said, he expir'd. After I had mus'd a while, I took a little heart a-grace, and ask'd him, how it far'd with <HI>Rotan, Serres</HI> and others▪ Those two an∣swer'd <HI>Cahier,</HI> are forc'd to hide their heads, for they are both under ground: and I'le tell ye how: so soon as they had heard of <HI>Vaux</HI>'s confession, they encou∣rag'd one the other by Letters, got them∣selves chosen by the National Synod of <HI>Montpelier,</HI> with a resolution, like <HI>Caesar,</HI> to pass the <HI>Rubicon</HI>; but before they went, to try to gain something with the Confede∣rates. But such was their misfortue that they both dy'd before the sitting of the Sy∣nod. I am very sorry for the money which <HI>Serres</HI> carry'd to his Wife, for she dy'd the same day that he did, like <HI>Ananias</HI> and
<PB N="161" REF="87"/>
<HI>Saphira,</HI> so that that money might have bet∣ter have fallen into my hands— Sir, <HI>If you please to order me a sum, and take</HI>— I would not suffer him to go on, but kept the Begger who was very im∣portunate, at staves end, making hast to bed, though without hopes of repose. By break of day my Servants having inform'd Monsieur Confessour of my restlesness, and continual exclamations, he comes into my Chamber, takes a Chair, and began these honey-dropping words. Sir, I have bin in∣form'd by your Servants, this morning, and yesterday in the Evening, by M. <HI>Cahier,</HI> of the strange disturbancies of your mind; and something I find my self by the vehe∣ment motion of your pulse; but I desire ye to take a tast of my words, as assuaging Remedies for your exteriour Distempers; for no outward violence, no promise, hope or fear can change the inward distem∣per of Opinions. Reason alone, which moves and puts them into a ferment at first, is to them the proper application; seeing that her prevailing power produces either hopes or fears in a distracted mind. When I speak of hopes and fears, I mean, in re∣ference to the affairs of this World. For in truth, when the dispute extends its self to the World to come, then the hope of
<PB N="166" REF="88"/>
good, and the fear of evil, practise their force as well upon the one as the other. Do you not think your self happy in that you feel no other then the soft raigne, and natu∣ral power of your thoughts, and not the violence of necessity? Know then, that all men are reduc'd to this point, to be at an ill pass either with their Consciences, or with the affairs of the World. But because there is no perfect felicity, wise men find∣ing a persecution upon the liberty of their thoughts, they fly to the privacies of the heart; so that if your Conscience cannot reconcile it self to the temper of the times, fly to the secret retirements of the wise, reserving to your self, those things, of which you your self are Judg, and leaving to others those things which fall under the scan of Forraign judgment. Our external Actions may be censur'd by those who are in power, and for that they have the know∣lege thereof, you cannot prevent them from dealing in their own Element, or from pu∣nishing or rewarding as they deem most proper: but they cannot controul your thoughts, which they can by no means im∣peach. Sir, I speak these things as well in reference to my self, as you; beseeching ye, that the Combats of our Consciences may not vent themselves: or if the Con∣science
<PB N="167" REF="88"/>
struggle to get loose, at least to lull it asleep, if you cannot stifle it in the Cradle. <HI>Cahier</HI> informs me that you are very much surpriz'd at the suddain ends of our new Converts. The <HI>Baron of Salignac</HI> and my self are still alive. His Wife, and the Wives of <HI>Salette, Sponde, Morlas</HI> are also yet living. The reason is plain: They that are dead would not stifle their Consci∣ences; and they choak'd them. We must therefore kill our Consciences, as I can boast to have done by mine; or lay them fast asleep in the Bed of Stupidity, as the Ba∣ron and his Wife, and others, have done by a thousand little charming pastimes of Love. Come, I will give ye a few precepts, which I make use of my self. Many men render deservedly culpable themselves through their own ill conduct. Loyalty, though it be highly to be applauded, becomes liable to punishment, when it sustains them who are depress'd by Fortune. We ought to follow favour, honour those who are in prosperi∣ty; spurn at the miserable. For never wise man made choice of the unfortunate for his Friends. We ought to change as the times alter, and abandon that Party, from which we can hope for no support. There is as much difference between profit and right, as between Heaven and Earth, wa∣ter
<PB N="164" REF="89"/>
and fire. The greatest Families in the World would soon decay, should they make any account of Justice. A ty'd re∣spect to Honesty would overthrow Citys and Castles. The liberty of committing all sorts of Impiety, supports Kingdoms. Though it went against thy Nature to ob∣serve any measure in evil-doing, yet he that acts by appearance shall easily find im∣punity, when the fact is committed. Let him abstain from the Court, that will needs be pious. Truth and Grandeur are always at daggers drawing. He shall al∣ways be in fear. Why should a wise man be asham'd to follow the example of his King. Wickedness renders them equal who are equally contaminated. 'Tis not a thing that deserves a little praise to deceive a Prince. Honesty, not accompany'd with feli∣city, is always contemptible; and for poor Vertue, see how it is forc'd to suffer the scoffs of the Vulgar. Thus you see, Sir, how I have endeavour'd to employ your contemplation, not doubting but you will make your advantage of what I have said; as being the most proper Physic for your disease. I return'd my most humble thanks to Monsieur Confessour, and applauding his discourse, Sir, said I, what follows, I speak by way of Confession, in acknow∣ledgment
<PB N="165" REF="89"/>
of your kindness. I recommend my honour to your care. And to shew ye that your Doctrin is sow'd in a good ground, I am so far from contradicting your grave advice, that henceforward I intend to piss upon the friendship of the miserable. I have learnt from you, that the best way is to eat fowl when they are mortifi'd, and to make advantage of men when they are suppl'd by their misfortues. To this pur∣pose, I will tell you a brave Act which I did upon my second Conversion. We were at <HI>Orleans,</HI> the Abbot of— and I when the Massacre was committed. The Abbot advis'd me to go forth into the street with my Sword i'my hand and to do as the rest did, to save my own Life. Seeing that his Counsel succeded, and that for having my Sword in the guts of a poor Hat-maker, I was welcom among the Massacrer's, it put me in mind of a Gentleman, to whom I had bin beholding for four Months enter∣tainment. I went to the door with— and other Consorts. The good man was upon his knees in the Chamber preparing himself to dye. When he heard my voice he came running down, receiv'd me full of joy, crying out, with his eyes lifted up to Heaven; O God thou hast sent this man as an Angel to succour me in my affliction.
<PB N="170" REF="90"/>
That is, thought I, to put ye quite out of your misery, and thereupon I presently sheath'd my Sword in his heart to do him a freindly office. I sav'd his Wive's Life, of whom I and— and the rest of the company made some small use as the time would permit. Afterwards for grief of the Injury done her, she ran foolishly into the heat of the Massacre and was her self knockt o'the head. I miss'd killing a Varlet <HI>Huguenot,</HI> who would never do as I would have had him. So that for want of suffi∣cient help, I got no more than fourscore Crowns, and a green Camlet Suit. And this is that wherewith you have hear'd me openly tax— when they return'd with me to <HI>Paris.</HI> A noble Act, cry'd <HI>M.</HI> Confes∣sour, and I think it was almost in the same Coyn that you pay'd M. <HI>Gennes,</HI> though you did not cut his throat, when he impor∣tun'd ye to repay the 100000. Crowns. Such discourses as these chear'd me up for a time. So that I resolv'd to harden my heart; never think of what was past, but altogether mind the future. I have now only two little Fears that disturb me; the one in reference to my Estate, the other, my Religion. The first is, if the <HI>Hugue∣nots</HI> should mind their business as they might do, then would the greatest part of
<PB N="171" REF="90"/>
<HI>France</HI> fly to their embraces. But in that case, God be thanked, we know how to go, come and return again. Let me alone to counterfeit <HI>Eubolius,</HI> and to rowl my self in a Sack to the St. <HI>John</HI>'s Gate in <HI>Ro∣chel,</HI> with an humble Petition in my mouth, <HI>Christians tread me to dirt, who am but salt without savour.</HI> But the fear of my Con∣science is, least a burning Feaver should surprize, and deceive me, as it did <HI>Morlas.</HI> However, let the worst come to the worst, it may be God may pardon me; if he does but see me kick a woodd'n Saint <HI>topsy turvy</HI> in sign of Repentance.</P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

