<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A fannaticks mite cast into the Kings treasury being a sermon printed to the King because not preach'd before the King / by Henry Adis.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Adis, Henry.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A26412</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing A581</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R28080</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">10390272</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 10390272</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">44940</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A26412)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44940)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1372:8)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A fannaticks mite cast into the Kings treasury being a sermon printed to the King because not preach'd before the King / by Henry Adis.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Adis, Henry.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EDITIONSTMT><EDITION>The second edition, corrected and amended.</EDITION></EDITIONSTMT><EXTENT>[17], 59, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by S. Dover,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1660.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>"A declaration of a small society of baptized believers undergoing the name of free-willers about the city of London": p. 49-59.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM><TERM>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A26412">
<STC T="W">A581</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">10390272</BIBNO>
<VID>44940</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A Fannaticks Mite Cast into the Kings Treasury: BEING A SERMON Printed to the KING, Because not Preach'd before the KING.</P>
<P>The Second EDITION, Corrected and Amended.</P>
<P>By <HI>HENRY ADIS,</HI> a Baptized Believer, undergoing the Name of a Free-Willer; and also most ignomineously by the tongue of Infamy, called a <HI>Fannatick,</HI> or <HI>a mad man.</HI></P>
<P><Q><HI>Silver and Gold have I none, but such as I have give I Thee,</HI></Q> <BIBL>Acts 3. 6.</BIBL></P>
<P><Q>First Read, then Judge; and Judge nothing before the time, because the Wise Man saith, That to <HI>him that</HI> Iudgeth <HI>a matter before he heareth it, it is folly and shame,</HI></Q> <BIBL>Prov. 18. 13.</BIBL></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>S. Dover,</HI> for the Author, 1660.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="author's note">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<P>DElivered into the KINGS own-Hands by the Author, the <HI>26th.</HI> day of <HI>Chisleu,</HI> in Scripture so called, <HI>Zech.</HI> 7. 1. which is the <HI>9th.</HI> Month, and therefore vulgarly called <HI>No∣vember,</HI> 1660.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the king">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO CHARLES the II, OF <HI>England, Scotland, France</HI> and <HI>Ireland,</HI> KING.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>May it please Thee, O King,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Am come now to present Thee with that MITE, the Composing of which I have been very much pressed to in spirit, ever since Thou wast brought again into this Land of Thy Nativity, with that great Solemnity and Triumph; the noise of which hath rejoyced the hearts of forregn Princes, daunted the spirits of thy Domestick Enemies, made thy Friends merry, and the rude multitude mad, even to the sadning the hearts of the truly vertuous (and as I judge) not because thou art restored again, for the meerly Rational may plainly behold in it an high Act of Divine Providence: But the Moon-sick madness of the multitude, yet unrepen∣ted of, together with the revived and dayly continued Acts of abomination in <HI>Stage-playes, May-games,</HI> and <HI>Pastimes,</HI> with the many <HI>bitter</HI> and <HI>most horrid Oaths</HI> and <HI>Execrations,</HI> uttered almost in <HI>every corner,</HI> by <HI>Nine-Pinn, Nine-Hole,</HI> and <HI>Pigeon∣Hole-Players,</HI> and to the poysoning the youth of our Age, in that multitude of <HI>dammy and debauched Bawdy-houses,</HI> even the <HI>foul and detestible shame</HI> of a <HI>Christian Kingdom;</HI> is that they fear is gathering into a black thick Cloud over the Land, and in special over <HI>rude, revelling, ranting London;</HI> out of which it is to be feared (<HI>unless Nineve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s Repentance intervene</HI>) will be
<PB REF="4"/>
poured out one or more of those three heavy Judgments of God, <HI>Plague, Sword,</HI> or <HI>Famine.</HI></P>
<P>Therefore, O King, I have brought <HI>Thee</HI> an <HI>Antidote,</HI> both for <HI>Thee and Thine,</HI> the which haply may <HI>prove bit∣ter to the taste, and will hardly go down;</HI> yet let me assure thee upon the word of an honest man, there is nothing hurtful in it, there is not so much as an <HI>unwholsome Bud,</HI> nor a <HI>stinking Weed,</HI> but all <HI>precious Flowers</HI> and <HI>wholsom Herbs,</HI> newly ga∣thered out of the <HI>Garden of God</HI> by a <HI>faithful Hand,</HI> and tem∣pered together by a <HI>sincere heart;</HI> and is a <HI>Potion</HI> of that <HI>rare Vertue,</HI> that if it be <HI>willingly taken</HI> and <HI>well digested,</HI> it will <HI>take down</HI> the <HI>Tinpany</HI> of <HI>Pride,</HI> and <HI>utterly dry up</HI> the <HI>Dropsicall humours</HI> of all <HI>Abomnations; it will perfectly recover</HI> out of the <HI>Consumption of Vertues,</HI> and <HI>fortifie</HI> the <HI>heart</HI> against <HI>all vice whatsoever;</HI> it will <HI>strengthen</HI> the <HI>stomack,</HI> both to <HI>re∣ceive</HI> and <HI>retain wholsom</HI> and <HI>sound Doctrine,</HI> and <HI>perfectly purge out</HI> the <HI>Iniquity of all your Holy Things;</HI> it will <HI>purge the Brain</HI> from all <HI>fansical, formal frenzy,</HI> and cause it only <HI>to study</HI> the <HI>Great Things of Gods Law;</HI> it will <HI>perfectly purge out Me∣lancholy,</HI> and <HI>generate Joy unspeakable,</HI> and <HI>full of glory;</HI> it will <HI>dry up</HI> the <HI>overflowing Issues</HI> of <HI>Sin,</HI> and <HI>nourish</HI> up <HI>a Soul unto Eternal Life;</HI> it will <HI>Operate</HI> upon the <HI>inward Man so, as</HI> that there will be a <HI>sudden change in the outward;</HI> it will make the <HI>proud person, Humble;</HI> the <HI>Lofty, Lowly; the Careless Careful;</HI> the <HI>Rich in this World, Rich in Good Works; the Spotted</HI> and <HI>painted face, truly panitent:</HI> To be short, it will operate upon the <HI>Luxurious, Lascivious</HI> and <HI>Licentious;</HI> and indeed upon all, <HI>so</HI> as that it will take <HI>down</HI> the <HI>Inordinate beat</HI> of <HI>Lust,</HI> and make such a sweet <HI>Composure,</HI> as that it will set <HI>Love, Joy, Fear, Zeal, Pitty,</HI> and <HI>Piety</HI> upon their <HI>right Objects;</HI> it will <HI>perfectly purge out all Envy</HI> and <HI>Malice, Blood∣thirstiness, Hatred, with all uncharitableness,</HI> and <HI>Create in</HI> the room thereof, <HI>Love, Joy, Peace, Long-suffering, Gentle∣ness, Goodness,</HI> with <HI>Meekness</HI> and <HI>Temperance;</HI> it will <HI>operate</HI> upon all <HI>Complexions</HI> and <HI>Sexes,</HI> and upon <HI>all Ranks</HI> and <HI>Subor∣dinations</HI>
<PB REF="4"/>
of <HI>men of all ages;</HI> and as I said before, <HI>if willingly Received</HI> and <HI>well Digested,</HI> it will make the PRINCE <HI>Pittiful, Just</HI> and <HI>Pious,</HI> and the SUBJECT <HI>Loving, Faithful</HI> &amp; <HI>Loyal;</HI> it will make <HI>Great persons Noble,</HI> with that <HI>true Berean Nobili∣ty,</HI> and <HI>joyn Goodness</HI> to their <HI>Greatness, (a Rarity indeed) it</HI> will make the <HI>middle</HI> sort of men <HI>Moderate,</HI> and cause them to use the World as if they used it not; yea, it will make the <HI>very Beggers</HI> of the <HI>Blood Royal of Heaven,</HI> and <HI>Children of God,</HI> yea <HI>Kings</HI> and <HI>Priests</HI> to <HI>God,</HI> and to <HI>Christ; it will</HI> make the <HI>Sluggish</HI> and <HI>Slothful, watchfully Vigilant,</HI> and the <HI>Vitious, truly Vertuous;</HI> it will make the <HI>Child Dutiful,</HI> and the <HI>Parents Indulgent,</HI> the <HI>Servant Painful,</HI> and the <HI>Master Pit∣tiful;</HI> it will keep the <HI>Virgin Chaste,</HI> and <HI>breed Loyalty</HI> in the <HI>Married;</HI> it will make <HI>Youth Sage</HI> and <HI>Grave,</HI> and <HI>gray Hairs truly Honourable;</HI> it will make the <HI>Bond-man Free,</HI> and the <HI>Free-man</HI> a <HI>Fellow Citizen with the Saints,</HI> and of the <HI>House∣hold of God;</HI> it will make the <HI>Poor man, truly Rich,</HI> and the <HI>Rich</HI> by <HI>Poverty</HI> of <HI>Spirit blessedly Poor;</HI> it will <HI>Corroborate the Cow-hearted,</HI> and <HI>cause the Coward earnestly to contend for the Faith:</HI> In fine, it will <HI>so purge out the old Leaven,</HI> as that it will <HI>make a man become a new Lump;</HI> it will make a <HI>meer Natural man, truly Gratious,</HI> and cause him to <HI>put off that old man with all his deeds,</HI> and put on <HI>that new Man, which after God is crea∣ted in Righteousness,</HI> and <HI>true Hulyness:</HI> And <HI>thus</HI> when old things are passed away, ye may <HI>evidently behold all things to become new;</HI> for though a <HI>spiritual man</HI> be produced, yet he is <HI>not like a Spirit,</HI> So <HI>as to be invisible,</HI> but <HI>apparently</HI> you may behold his <HI>Dialect changed,</HI> and his <HI>Aspect altered;</HI> for that <HI>tongue</HI> that in the old man was <HI>an unruly member,</HI> and <HI>full</HI> of <HI>deadly Poyson, Oaths, Execrations, and debauched Abominations;</HI> is in the <HI>new Man,</HI> an <HI>Instrument to set forth the Praise of God,</HI> and to <HI>tell what God hath done for his Soul,</HI> to <HI>talk</HI> of the <HI>Ma∣jesty of Christs Kingdom,</HI> and to <HI>declare his Power.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Eye</HI> that was never better satisfied then <HI>when it was be∣holding vanity,</HI> is now <HI>looking within the vail, where</HI> the <HI>Fore∣runner.</HI>
<PB REF="5"/>
<HI>is entred,</HI> it is now <HI>beholding the goodness of the Lord,</HI> and <HI>enquiring in his Temple,</HI> and <HI>diligently seeking after that one thing necessary, that once Mary chose.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>feet</HI> which before were <HI>swiftly running to shed blood,</HI> are now <HI>in Zions Pathes, readily running</HI> the <HI>way of Gods Com∣mandements.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>hands</HI> which before were <HI>other wayes employed,</HI> are now <HI>handling of the Word of Life, which their Eyes have seen,</HI> and <HI>their ears have heard, the which their Tongues also are now ready to declare; that so others may partake</HI> of <HI>that Fellowship,</HI> which they have with the <HI>Father,</HI> and <HI>his Son Jesus Christ.</HI></P>
<P>To conclude, It is an <HI>Antidote</HI> of such a <HI>transcendent ver∣tue,</HI> that being <HI>rightly applyed, according to the ensueing Dire∣ction,</HI> it will <HI>translate</HI> a <HI>Creature out of the kingdom of darkeness, into the kingdom of Gods dear Son;</HI> and also <HI>cause</HI> him <HI>there</HI> with <HI>Enoch</HI> and <HI>Noah,</HI> to <HI>walk with God.</HI></P>
<P><HI>O King, Silver and Gold have I none, but such as I have give I thee;</HI> I <HI>give</HI> it thee <HI>freely, dispose</HI> of it <HI>at thy pleasure, for freely through mercy I received it,</HI> it cost me <HI>nothing that was worth the keeping, I parted not</HI> with so much as one <HI>Mite for it, but that</HI> which for some time was my <HI>daily insupportable bur∣then,</HI> which at length <HI>grew so ponderous,</HI> that <HI>it weighed me down,</HI> even to the <HI>very brink of Hell,</HI> the <HI>Horrour whereof, Da∣rius-like,</HI> caused me to <HI>forsake my meat,</HI> and also my <HI>sleep to pass from me,</HI> it being a <HI>Mountainous confused Lump</HI> of <HI>Ini∣quities, Transgressions and Sins,</HI> the <HI>fruits of my labours</HI> from my <HI>Cradle some forty years</HI> in the <HI>Devils slavery, in which</HI> I was <HI>led captive by him at his will; the parting with which</HI> was my <HI>great gaine,</HI> not only by <HI>lightning my burthen,</HI> but by an <HI>en∣lightning the eyes of my understanding,</HI> to the <HI>beholding</HI> and <HI>lay∣ing hold on him who is invisible.</HI> And <HI>thus</HI> O King, <HI>through Grace</HI> I became a <HI>Fannatick,</HI> or <HI>a mad man,</HI> as some call me.</P>
<P>And now let me <HI>beg thee, O King;</HI> First, <HI>Neither to slight the Gift for the meanness of the Giver,</HI> nor the <HI>Potion, because not compounded by the direction of a Colledge of Phisitians,</HI> that
<PB REF="5"/>
have read <HI>many Authors;</HI> but the rather <HI>esteem it,</HI> because it is an <HI>experienced Receipt,</HI> and because as the <HI>Physitians</HI> use to say, <HI>Probatum est,</HI> is <HI>engraven upon it.</HI></P>
<P>And secondly, let me beg thee, <HI>O King,</HI> to <HI>make use of it thy self;</HI> for, <HI>sure I am, thou hast need</HI> of such an <HI>Antidote;</HI> the whcih if thou dost, I am confident I need not then beg a <HI>third Boon</HI> of thee, to <HI>recommend</HI> it to thy <HI>great Family,</HI> viz. <HI>to those</HI> that are <HI>under thy charge;</HI> for that is one part of the <HI>excellent ver∣tue</HI> that <HI>Souls</HI> are <HI>made partakers of, that well digest it,</HI> viz. that <HI>when</HI> they are <HI>Converted,</HI> they will be <HI>provoked then,</HI> to <HI>strengthen their Brethren.</HI></P>
<P>And now, <HI>O King,</HI> I shall at <HI>present</HI> cease to ask more at thy Throne, but shall apply my self to the <HI>Throne of Grace,</HI> and there <HI>beg the Lord,</HI> to give thee <HI>as much true joy in Reading,</HI> as he <HI>in mercy gave me in writing it,</HI> and that as he hath begun <HI>this good Work, to put this Antidote into thy hand,</HI> so he would <HI>perfect the same,</HI> that he would <HI>sweeten it to thy taste,</HI> and <HI>help thy disgestion;</HI> and seeing he hath declared himself to be such an one that <HI>waiteth upon Souls, that he might be gracious unto them,</HI> that he would <HI>wait upon thee with the sweet incomings of his own Spirit;</HI> and in <HI>special, whilst thou art taking this Po∣tion,</HI> that he would <HI>visit thee with his loving kindness,</HI> So, as that it may <HI>effectually operate upon thee, to the bringing forth the fruits thereof in thy Life and Conversation, to the Honour</HI> and <HI>Glory of him,</HI> who hath already done such <HI>great Things for thee;</HI> into whose <HI>Care, Direction</HI> and <HI>Pro∣tection,</HI> he shall now commend thee, who is, and by <HI>his Assistance</HI> shall <HI>ever be,</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thy <HI>Loyal</HI> Subject to <HI>Pray,</HI> but <HI>neither to Swear, nor Fight for thee,</HI> yet <HI>Faithfully to Obey thee in all things,</HI> that <HI>God requires in his Scriptures of Truth;</HI> who <HI>never did fight against any of</HI> thy <HI>Predecessors, nor never shall re∣solve to fight against Thee, nor any of Thy Successors,</HI>
HENRY ADIS.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the king">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>An After-Writing TO THE KING.</HEAD>
<P>MArvel not, O King, at my single-hearted Conclusion, in that I said, I shall neither <HI>Swear</HI> nor <HI>Fight for Thee,</HI> nei∣ther conclude me <HI>peremptorily Peevish,</HI> nor <HI>factiously Rebel∣lious, because I am so plain:</HI> But by the way know, That in <HI>Conclusion,</HI> Thou wilt find him to be Thy <HI>truest Friend, that dealeth plainliest with Thee,</HI> for <HI>one Dram of down right honesty,</HI> is of more <HI>true worth,</HI> than a <HI>whole Pound of fawning flattery;</HI> for mine own part, although I am by Trade an <HI>Upholdster,</HI> yet know, O King, I come not to <HI>sow Pil∣lows under thy Elbows,</HI> I fear thou hast <HI>Artificial Work-men at that work already, and too many too, for thy future good;</HI> but what I have received of the Lord, in the singleness of my heart, and in plainess of speech, I declare unto Thee, Take it as Thou <HI>wilt,</HI> and do <HI>with me for it as Thou pleasest,</HI> the <HI>meaning</HI> of it <HI>I yet understand</HI> uot, but sure I am, I have <HI>more than a common impulse to the Work,</HI> however it will fare with me I matter not, I <HI>both Hope</HI> and <HI>Pray</HI> it may <HI>prove</HI> of good <HI>use to Thee:</HI> Therefore I shall beg Thee in Gods fear, to <HI>consider seriously</HI> what Thou <HI>dost,</HI> when Thou shalt <HI>force men to Swear;</HI> for he that will <HI>Fight</HI> for Thee, and he that will <HI>Swear</HI> for Thee, <HI>being thereto con∣strained,</HI> will be as ready, <HI>if it stand with his own interest,</HI> both to <HI>Swear</HI> and <HI>Fight against Thee;</HI> for men generally make <HI>little Conscience of keeping constrained Vowes.</HI></P>
<P>O King, Thou hast been Tutored by <HI>Experience,</HI> the <HI>best Master;</HI> and I need not tell Thee, that <HI>Coustraint</HI> and <HI>Restraint</HI> are two <HI>Ex∣streams,</HI> and therefore <HI>dangerous to deal withal.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Voluntarily</HI> some there are, but others <HI>being thereto forced,</HI> have <HI>already</HI> to <HI>their hearts trouble Sworn against Thee:</HI> And now, if thou shalt again <HI>compel them to Swear for thee,</HI> what is it less than to <HI>ravish their Consciences,</HI> and to <HI>force them most abominably to forswear them∣selves? A ready way to pull down Gods Judgements upon the Nation;</HI> for
<PB REF="6"/>
so saith the Prophet, <HI>Jer. 23. 10. For because of Swearing the Land mourneth:</HI> So also saith another Prophet, <HI>Hos. 10. 4. They have spoken Words, Swearing falsly, in making a Covenant: Thus</HI> Judgement spring∣eth up as Hemlock in the furrows of the Field.</P>
<P>And lest I be found guilty of such a <HI>heinous sin,</HI> I shall <HI>resolve</HI> to <HI>trust</HI> a man upon his <HI>bare word,</HI> rather than <HI>force</HI> him to <HI>Swear;</HI> for he that <HI>for his own Benefit</HI> will not regard <HI>the keeping</HI> his word passed <HI>be∣fore God to Man,</HI> will for his own <HI>advantage</HI> be as <HI>careless</HI> both <HI>of God</HI> and <HI>Man,</HI> in <HI>slighting</HI> his <HI>unwilling Vow.</HI></P>
<P>Therefore <HI>in this, O King,</HI> be perswaded to <HI>leave men to their Liberties;</HI> and know, that <HI>Englands Subjects</HI> will be <HI>sooner won</HI> by their <HI>Kings Kindness,</HI> than <HI>brought under by his cruelty:</HI> It is the <HI>Love of Christ that constrains his;</HI> So let thy <HI>Lenity allure thine.</HI></P>
<P>And be entreated to shake off all <HI>slavish carnal fear,</HI> and cast thy <HI>care</HI> and <HI>burthen upon him,</HI> who <HI>hath hitherto taken such care for thee, Render thou but to him according to his Benefits bestowed upon thee,</HI> and confi∣dent I am, that the Keeper of <HI>Israel,</HI> who <HI>neither slumbreth nor sleep∣eth,</HI> will <HI>watch thy Subjects hearts, So,</HI> as that they <HI>shall be kept close to thee; for when a mans wayes please the Lord, he will make his Enemies to at Peace with him.</HI> Prov. 16. 7.</P>
<P>And think not to make thy <HI>self strong,</HI> by <HI>forcing</HI> thy Subjects to <HI>for∣swear themseves,</HI> in <HI>sweariug for thee,</HI> l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st he that <HI>Swore by himself,</HI> when he could <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by no Greater, stretch out his Sin-revenging hand against thee;</HI> but <HI>rather</HI> say to thy <HI>Subjects,</HI> as <HI>the Lord Christ saith to his,</HI> Mat. 5. 34. <HI>Swear not at all: And I being one of his Subjects,</HI> this is <HI>one Reason, O King,</HI> why I told thee in plainness of speech, that I cannot <HI>Swear for thee;</HI> and because he farther <HI>requireth me,</HI> thar I should <HI>love my Enemies,</HI> and <HI>do good to them that hate me,</HI> and <HI>pray for them that daspitefully use me,</HI> Mat. 5. 44. This is <HI>another Reason, O King,</HI> why I <HI>cannot Fight for thee:</HI> And I being a <HI>Branch</HI> in that <HI>Vine,</HI> of which the <HI>Root and Off-spring of David</HI> is the <HI>Root,</HI> and from <HI>whom onely I dayly</HI> through mercy receive <HI>sap, vigour and fresh supplies of Grace,</HI> for the <HI>strengthening</HI> and <HI>supporting</HI> of my <HI>inward man, dare not</HI> have so much as a <HI>thought</HI> to <HI>Swear</HI> thee to be <HI>Supream of that Body</HI> of <HI>which Christ is the Head;</HI> and because the Lord by his Prophet, <HI>Jer.</HI> 18. 9. saith thus, <HI>At what instant I shall speak concerning</HI> a <HI>Nation, and con∣cerning a Kingdom,</HI> to <HI>Build and to Plant it;</HI> if it do <HI>evil</HI> in my sight, so that it <HI>obey not my voice, then will I repent of the good wherewith I said I would Benefit it:</HI> This is also another <HI>Reason, O King,</HI> why I can∣not <HI>Swear</HI> nor <HI>Fight for thee; for if thy Actings</HI> shall nor <HI>answer Gods End (if his Word be true)</HI> thou must then expect a <HI>removal,</HI> and a <HI>pul∣ling</HI>
<PB REF="7"/>
<HI>down;</HI> and if I <HI>shall Swear,</HI> or <HI>Fight, to support thee,</HI> when by thy <HI>Actings</HI> thou shalt <HI>cause God to pull thee down;</HI> What is it less than for me to he found <HI>fighti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>g against God?</HI> And besides, <HI>A Servant of the Lord must not strive, but be gentle to all,</HI> 2 Tim. 2. 24.</P>
<P>And by the way know, That <HI>these Resolves</HI> were not <HI>intended to thy self only,</HI> but <HI>also to those</HI> that were <HI>in Power after</HI> thy <HI>Father,</HI> and <HI>before thee,</HI> were these things manifested; as by my Declaration in the End of this Book, is evident.</P>
<P>Therefore, O King, if thou shalt seem to <HI>Counter-mand</HI> my <HI>Loyalty</HI> to <HI>him,</HI> who <HI>bought</HI> me at so <HI>dear a price,</HI> as the <HI>shedding of his own pre∣tious Blood,</HI> Acts 20. 28. I shall desire <HI>thee to Judge between me</HI> and <HI>my God,</HI> aud shall ask thee in the words of <HI>Peter</HI> and <HI>John,</HI> Acts 4. 19. <HI>Whether it be right in the sight of God, to hearken unto thee, more than un∣to my God? I shall desire thy self to be Judge.</HI></P>
<P>And thus, <HI>O King,</HI> having (I hope) given thee a <HI>Rational account,</HI> of my <HI>down</HI>-right <HI>and single-hearted Conclusion of my Epistle to thee De∣dicated;</HI> I shall now tell thee <HI>in the faithfulness of my Soul,</HI> that by the <HI>Law of the same Law-giver,</HI> I am bound not onely to <HI>pray for thee,</HI> 1 Tim. 2. 2. but also to <HI>obey thee in all Civil things, that are agreeable to the Mind of God, revealed in his Scriptures of Truth;</HI> and also to ren∣der <HI>Tribute, Custome, Fear</HI> and <HI>Honour,</HI> both to thee, as God hath set thee over us, <HI>and to all others sent by thee,</HI> Rom. 13. 7. 1 Pet. 2. 13. <HI>Whose Obedience upon the word of a Christian,</HI> without <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> or <HI>Fighting,</HI> either <HI>for</HI> or <HI>against thee</HI> (God assisting) he shall <HI>faithfully continue;</HI> who resolveth (unless <HI>for his i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nocent Judgement, thou either Deprive him of Life,</HI> or <HI>Banish him this Land of his Nativity) to remain till Death,</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thy Loyal Subject,
HENRY ADIS.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>A WORD to the READER.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>READER,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>THE Common Proverb goes, <HI>That every Little makes a Mickle;</HI> and the Kings TREASURIES being empty, whilst the <HI>Parliament</HI> and <HI>City</HI> are throwing in their Rich Gifts, I (with the Poor Widow in the Gospel, have cast in my MITE, let the King take it how he pleaseth, sure I am, he <HI>will take it amiss,</HI> if he <HI>take it not well;</HI> for God is my Witness, I intended it for good, and so it will <HI>Prove,</HI> if rightly <HI>improved;</HI> and is of that worth, that it may be said of <HI>it,</HI> as our Saviour said of the Widows Mite, <HI>It will Prove worth all;</HI> not for the <HI>Quantity,</HI> but for the <HI>Quality</HI> of it; not for the <HI>Beauty,</HI> but for the <HI>Blessedness;</HI> not for the <HI>Eloquence,</HI> but for the <HI>Excellency</HI> of it; theirs being <HI>Material,</HI> but this <HI>Superna∣tural;</HI> theirs <HI>Perishing,</HI> but this <HI>Permanent;</HI> theirs onely to <HI>Feed, Cloath</HI> and <HI>Pamper</HI> the Body, but this to <HI>Nourish, Streng∣then,</HI> and to <HI>Support the Soul.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Reader,</HI> I was neither bred <HI>a Scholar</HI> nor a <HI>Courtier;</HI> there∣fore thou must expect in it neither <HI>Complement</HI> nor <HI>Curiosity;</HI> neither was I ever out of this Land of my Nativity; there∣fore look not for any <HI>forreign Rarities,</HI> but such only as are to be <HI>found in the Garden of God.</HI></P>
<P>It is a Home-spun Piece, wherein there is little <HI>Eloquence,</HI> and less <HI>Flattery,</HI> but <HI>store</HI> of <HI>down right honesty,</HI> with <HI>abun∣dance</HI> of <HI>Fidelity;</HI> a <HI>Ponderous weight,</HI> of the <HI>truest Love,</HI> wrapt up in an <HI>homely Garment</HI> of the <HI>best Loyalty.</HI></P>
<P>To be short, it is that which I know, must undergo many <HI>Censures</HI> (if <HI>not my self severely Sentenced for it</HI>) both by the <HI>Critical Church-man,</HI> and the <HI>Carnal Church-member,</HI> the <HI>Flat∣tering Courtier,</HI> and the <HI>Flouting Citizen,</HI> the <HI>Learned Lawyer,</HI> and the <HI>Illiterate Rustick;</HI> but let them say what they will, and do with <HI>It</HI> and <HI>Me</HI> what they please, I much matter it not;
<PB REF="8"/>
for in my Composing of it, I had a <HI>good Conscience;</HI> which, sure I am, <HI>in the midst of the worst of Miseries,</HI> will be to me a <HI>Continual-Feast;</HI> for I look upon it, to be a part of my <HI>Gene∣ration work, to speak a word in season,</HI> to the <HI>Cherishing of Vertue,</HI> and the <HI>bearing my Testimony against Vice,</HI> as far as the Lord hath enabled me to the <HI>beating it down;</HI> and so, to be guilty of the blood of none, but to have a Conscience al∣wayes void of offence, both towards God, and towards Man, and to have no fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but to Reprove them.</P>
<P>Reader, In fine, it is a part of my <HI>Talent,</HI> the which <HI>I dare not hide</HI> in a <HI>Napkin;</HI> and seeing it cannot be permitted to be employed where <HI>it ought, at mine own peril I dare not but Mini∣ster it where I may:</HI> Therefore <HI>take</HI> and <HI>read</HI> it, after which, if thou <HI>find Benefit by it, bless God for it,</HI> and <HI>crave his assi∣stance,</HI> that thou mayest make a <HI>right use of it; for it is his,</HI> and <HI>mine no otherwise, than from him,</HI> through Mercy <HI>I have received it.</HI></P>
<P>Neither do I <HI>so highly praise</HI> it, for any thing that I have <HI>in∣fused into it;</HI> but for what through mercy I have been <HI>made partaker of by it; by Divine assistance,</HI> I have Composed it, and the Shearcher of all hearts knows, it is neither <HI>Pay,</HI> nor <HI>Praise</HI> I aim at, <HI>for my reward is with him:</HI> But if the <HI>Glory of God,</HI> the Well-<HI>being of his People,</HI> the <HI>Good of the King, or</HI> the <HI>Benefit but of one Soul be thereby produced,</HI> he hath his <HI>End;</HI> who desireth according to the <HI>Ability received,</HI> to remain,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Thy Faithful Friend in the Truths of Jesus,</HI>
HENRY ADIS.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="8"/>
<HEAD>An After-Word to the READER.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>READER,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I Knowing the <HI>temper</HI> of the <HI>spirits</HI> of the generality of the Sons and Daughters of men of this Nation, <HI>in this juncture of time,</HI> cannot but <HI>expect</HI> that thou shouldst be <HI>something unsatisfied</HI> with my <HI>plainness of speech;</HI> and my Terms of <HI>Thy, Thee, Thou,</HI> and <HI>O King,</HI> in my <HI>Discourse to the King;</HI> and also, in that I <HI>afford him not</HI> those <HI>Titles</HI> that some men are <HI>pleased to put upon him,</HI> and <HI>therein</HI> I am perswaded thou wilt be ready to <HI>judge me,</HI> as one that am either <HI>peremptorily slighting,</HI> or <HI>peevishly undervaluing</HI> the <HI>King,</HI> because I do not <HI>say</HI> and <HI>do, to</HI> and <HI>for</HI> him, as thou haply <HI>canst</HI> and <HI>dost.</HI></P>
<P>Or at the best, for the plainness of my speech, thou wilt conclude me to be one of those New-lighted men of our age; commonly distin∣guished by the name of <HI>Quakers,</HI> because that in their Speakings and Writings, they generally use the same Terms; and to say Truth, if they did not speak the Language, and wear the Cloathing of the Sheep of Christ, they could not (Wolf-like) so easily deceive as gene∣rally they do.</P>
<P>Therefore Reader, I do hereby assure thee, that I am not of that <HI>Synagogue;</HI> for through mercy I can groundedly, and upon a good account let thee know, that I walk by the direction of a more <HI>surer word of Prophesie,</HI> to which I shall endeavour by the assistance of the Eternal Spirit, to take good heed to; and from which I shall war∣rant the soundness aud manner of my Speech (though it be in such plainness and without flattery) to be of God.</P>
<P>And because <HI>these Notionists</HI> have some of <HI>Canaans Language</HI> in their <HI>mouths;</HI> I shall <HI>therefore</HI> no more <HI>forbear</HI> the using of it, than the <HI>Apostle Peter</HI> did the <HI>Confessing</HI> of <HI>Christ</HI> to be the <HI>Son of the living God,</HI> Mat. 16. 16. <HI>Because</HI> the Devil in so many words acknowledged the same, <HI>Mat.</HI> 8. 29. <HI>Mark</HI> 5. 7. <HI>Luke</HI> 8. 28.</P>
<P>Neither shall I resolve to <HI>alter my Habit,</HI> because these men <HI>being deceived,</HI> run up and down <HI>in the sheeps cloathing, deceiving;</HI> but shall patiently wait upon God for a Manifestation of <HI>them</HI> and <HI>all others,</HI> to be of the <HI>Synagogue of Satan,</HI> who say, they are <HI>Iewe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> and <HI>are not, but do lie.</HI></P>
<P>In the mean while Reader, in Christian love I shall further en∣deavour thy <HI>satisfaction,</HI> and in the singleness of my Soul, I shall let thee know, that <HI>I both do</HI> and <HI>shall Honour the King,</HI> with that <HI>honour</HI> and <HI>respect</HI> that the <HI>Lord requireth I should;</HI> as in this <HI>Discourse,</HI>
<PB REF="9"/>
<HI>compared</HI> with my <HI>Declaration</HI> in the end of this Book folded, is <HI>evi∣dent;</HI> although as thou haply mayest Judge in my <HI>so speaking, I rude∣ly behave my self.</HI></P>
<P>Therefore for thy farther <HI>satisfaction,</HI> know, That as I am a <HI>Servant</HI> to the <HI>Most High God,</HI> and a <HI>Member</HI> of a <HI>Church of Christ;</HI> So I look upon it to be my <HI>Duty,</HI> to <HI>Regulate</HI> my <HI>Conversation</HI> as <HI>becometh</HI> the <HI>Gospel</HI> of <HI>Christ,</HI> and to <HI>walk</HI> in the <HI>footsteps</HI> of the <HI>Flock</HI> of <HI>God gone before;</HI> who, though according to the <HI>Requirement</HI> of <HI>God,</HI> they were <HI>obedient</HI> to <HI>Kings, Rulers</HI> and <HI>Governours,</HI> yet they gave them <HI>no other Language</HI> than in <HI>this my Discourse I give to King CHARLES;</HI> witness that Discourse the Prophet <HI>Daniel</HI> had wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h that <HI>Head of Gold,</HI> that <HI>King of Kings, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> King</HI> of <HI>Babylon,</HI> Daniel 2. 29. who said, <HI>As for</HI> thee, <HI>O King, thy thoughts came into thy head; and thou, O King, sawest,</HI> &amp;c. And in ver. 31. <HI>And thou, O King, art King of Kings.</HI> Ver. 37. <HI>And thou art this Head of Gold.</HI> Verie 38. And in Dan. 4. 22. <HI>It is thou, O King, that art grown and become strong, and thy greatness is grown and reacheth unto Hea∣ven, and</HI> thy <HI>Dominion unto the ends of the Earth; yet they shall drive thée from men, and</HI> thy <HI>dwelling shall be with the Beasts of the Field; and they shall make thée to eat grass as Oxen; and they shall wet thée with the dew of Heaven; and seven times shall pass over thée, till thou know that the Most High Ruleth in the Kingdom of men,</HI> and giveth <HI>it to whom he will,</HI> V. 25. <HI>Wherefore; O King, let my Counsel be acceptable to thée, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d break off thy sins</HI> by Righteousness, and <HI>thine iniquity</HI> by <HI>shewing Mercy to the Poor, is it may be a lengthning out if thy Tranquility.</HI></P>
<P>But lest any man should say, that <HI>Nebuchadnezzar</HI> was a <HI>Heathen;</HI> and therefore the <HI>Prophet</HI> gave him neither <HI>the Titles,</HI> nor that <HI>due Respect</HI> that otherwise he would have done.</P>
<P>In Answer whereunto, I shall lay before thee the Prophet <HI>David,</HI> a King <HI>in Israel,</HI> and <HI>a man after Gods own heart;</HI> who, if it had been his <HI>due by Gods Appointment,</HI> could as well have become the <HI>Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>le</HI> of <HI>Sacred,</HI> and <HI>Most Sacred Majesty,</HI> as any <HI>He</HI> that I ever read or heard o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, either before or after him, to this very day; yet we read, that when the <HI>Prophe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> came to him in the case of <HI>Uriah</HI> the <HI>Hittite,</HI> he said no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, <HI>May it please your Sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>red Majesty;</HI> but <HI>Nathan said unto David,</HI> 2 Sam. 12. 7. <HI>Thou art the Man.</HI> And V. 9. <HI>Thou hast kil∣led Uriah th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Hittite with the Sword, and taken his Wife to be thy Wife; now the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fore the Sword shall not depart from thy House.</HI></P>
<P>Neither did <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>he Woman of <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>koah,</HI> in <HI>Absoloms</HI> case, come with a, <HI>May it please your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st Sacred Majesty,</HI> for we may plainly under∣stand what her Dialect was to King <HI>David,</HI> 2 Sam. 14. 5. Even, <HI>Help,</HI>
<PB REF="9"/>
<HI>O King.</HI> Then said she, V. 11. <HI>I pray thée, let the King Remember the Lord thy God, that thou wouldest not suffer the Revenger of blood to destroy. Many more</HI> Examples of this kind might be sufficiently mul∣tiplyed, if need<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ul.</P>
<P>But to come nearer, even to the dispensation we are now under; <HI>Peter</HI> said unto the <HI>Lord Christ,</HI> to <HI>Emanuel,</HI> even to <HI>God with us,</HI> Mat. 16. 16. <HI>Thou art Christ the Son of the living God.</HI> And the <HI>Apo∣stle Paul</HI> being a Prisoner, and coming to make his defence, <HI>Acts</HI> 26. 2, 3. he said, <HI>I think my self happy, King Agrippa, because I shall An∣swer for my self before thée, this day;</HI> for I know <HI>thée to be expert in all Customes and Questions among the Jews; wherefore I beseech thée (not your most Sacred Majesty) but I beseech</HI> thée <HI>to hear me patiently.</HI> And in V. 13. &amp; 14. <HI>At mid-day, O King, I saw a light from Heaven,—And a voyce speaking unto me; Whereupon,</HI> O <HI>King Agrippa,</HI> I was not disobedient to the heavenly voice, V. 19. And in V. 27. <HI>King Agrippa, Believest thou the Prophets? I know thou Beleevest.</HI> And <HI>Paul</HI> said, V. 29. <HI>I would to God that not onely thou, but all that hear me this day, were both almost and altogether such an one as I am, except these Bonds.</HI></P>
<P>Even so shall I say to thee, <HI>O Reader,</HI> I would to God that as to my Judgement, thou wert even such an one as my self, that so thou <HI>mightest give to Caesar, onely the things that are Caesars, and to God the things that are Gods.</HI></P>
<P>And, <HI>Reader,</HI> consider with thy self, that if the Lord Christ <HI>re∣proved</HI> him that said to him, <HI>good Master;</HI> saying, <HI>Why callest thou me good? There is none good but One, even God,</HI> Luke 18. 19. Even <HI>so</HI> do <HI>I say</HI> to <HI>my self;</HI> Why should I <HI>dare</HI> to <HI>call</HI> the <HI>greatest</HI> of <HI>Men, most Sacred?</HI> When it is an <HI>Attrib<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>te</HI> that <HI>properly</HI> and <HI>peculiarly be∣longs</HI> to <HI>God himself,</HI> and was <HI>never given to Man by God;</HI> and <HI>to me,</HI> it <HI>seems</HI> to be one of those <HI>names</HI> of <HI>Blasphemy</HI> upon the seven <HI>Heads of the Beast,</HI> Rev. 13. 2. and no <HI>better</HI> than a <HI>flattering Title.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>which</HI> with <HI>another</HI> of the <HI>Kings Titles,</HI> had I but the <HI>privi∣ledge</HI> of his <HI>Ear</HI> but one <HI>little pittance of time,</HI> I question not, but by <HI>Divine assistance,</HI> I should so <HI>discover</HI> the <HI>unlawfulness thereof,</HI> as that he <HI>would himself refuse to own them.</HI></P>
<P>And for me to <HI>flatter him,</HI> or <HI>any man else,</HI> I <HI>dare not for these Reasons:</HI></P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>First, <HI>Lest thereby I bring my self and mine, under the Sin-reveng∣ing-hand of God.</HI> And,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Secondly, <HI>Lest I thereby ensnare others.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>First, Least I <HI>endanger my self and mine; Because,</HI> if <HI>Jobs</HI> words
<PB REF="10"/>
be true, who saith, That <HI>he knoweth not to give flattering Titles;</HI> if I <HI>so do, my Maker</HI> (saith he) <HI>would soon take me away,</HI> Job 32. 21, 22. And should I <HI>be found so doing,</HI> God would <HI>no more excuse me, tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> him;</HI> for saith the <HI>Prophet David,</HI> Psa. 12. 3. <HI>The Lord will cut off</HI> all <HI>flat∣tering lips, and the tongue that speaketh proud things;</HI> and also saith that <HI>upright man Job, He that speaketh flattery to his Friend, even the eyes of his Children shall fail,</HI> Job 19. 5. So that as I <HI>tender the good of my self and mine, I dare not do it.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>And secondly, I dare not do it, lest <HI>I endanger others; for a man that flattereth his Neighbour, spreadeth a</HI> Net <HI>for his</HI> feet, saith the wisest of men, <HI>Prov▪</HI> 29. 5. for saith he, <HI>A flattering mouth worketh ruine,</HI> Prov. 26. 28.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>And this is that which was the destruction of <HI>King Herod,</HI> Act. 12. 21. for saith the Text, <HI>On a set day, Herod arrayed in Royal apparel, sate upon his Throne and made an Oration unto his Subjects;</HI> who upon the hearing thereof, began to flatter him; for saith the Text, <HI>The Peo∣ple gave a shout, saying, It is the voyce of a God, and not of a Man; and immediatly the Angel of the Lord smote him, because he gave not God the Glory; and he was eaten of Worms, and gave up the Ghost:</HI> had not his subjects <HI>given</HI> him that <HI>flattering Applause, he had not robbed God of his Glory,</HI> and so the <HI>Angel had not smitten him.</HI></P>
<P>So that <HI>in this</HI> I question not, but I shall <HI>evidence my love</HI> to the <HI>King more,</HI> than they that <HI>so</HI> flatter him.</P>
<P>Therefore this shall be my Resolution (the Lord assisting me) to continue treading in the <HI>footsteps</HI> of the <HI>Flock of God gone before,</HI> and shall conclude with my self, and say with that Queen, <HI>Hester</HI> 4. 16. And if <HI>therein I perish, I perish;</HI> for I had <HI>rather suffer by man in obedi∣ence to my God, than by the Sin-revenging hand of God, to be cut off in his displeasure.</HI></P>
<P>And thus, <HI>Reader,</HI> having given thee an account of my <HI>manner of Speech to the King,</HI> which is <HI>none other than what he Popple of God in former Ages used, both under</HI> the Law, and <HI>under this Gospel Dispensation:</HI> I shall take my leave, and desiring the Lord to <HI>set it home upon thy heart,</HI> and that it may be <HI>satisfactory to thee,</HI> that so thou <HI>mayest not have a prejudice in thy spirit against him,</HI> who <HI>desireth to do nothing,</HI> ei∣ther in <HI>word</HI> or <HI>Action,</HI> but what may tend to the <HI>Glory of God,</HI> the good of his <HI>own Soul,</HI> and the <HI>enlightning</HI> of those with whom he doth Converse; who shall be ready in Christian love, to give thee a Verbal satisfaction, to any thing that in this Discourse may be thy dissatisfaction,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>And to remain thy Friend therein, to serve thee,</HI>
HENRY ADIS.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="1" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>A Fannaticks Mite Cast into the KINGS TREASURY.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>2 Chron. 32. 25.</BIBL>
<Q><HI>But</HI> Hezekiah <HI>rendred not again according to the benefits bestowed upon him; but his heart was lifted up: Therefore there was wrath upon him, and upon</HI> Judah <HI>and</HI> Jerusalem.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>THESE Words themselves have a Dependancy upon the Story going before, and are no other but a <HI>Declaration,</HI> or <HI>Manifestation</HI> of the Kings <HI>unthankfuluess to God,</HI> for his <HI>Mercies bestowed,</HI> and of the <HI>sad Consequences thereof.</HI></P>
<P><HI>But</HI> Hezekiah <HI>rendred not again according to the Benefits bestowed upon him; but his heart was lifted up: Therefore there was wrath upon him▪ and upon</HI> Judah <HI>and</HI> Jerusalem.</P>
<P>Had this Discourse been spoken as it is now written to thee, O King, many <HI>distinctions</HI> might have been made, and <HI>several</HI> and <HI>re∣markable Observations hinted at,</HI> which might have been <HI>very useful (if diligently minded, and as effectually put into practise)</HI> some of which for brevity sake I shall here omit, and shall first run over the Story that <HI>occasioned the Spirit of God to lay down these</HI> words, and therein briefly hint at some things I shall judge <HI>useful;</HI> and then <HI>in the strength of the same Spirit,</HI> come to the handling of the wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ds themselves.</P>
<P><PB N="2" REF="11"/>Good <HI>Hezekiah</HI> after the death of his Father King <HI>Ahaz,</HI> began his Reign, as we may read, 2 <HI>Chron.</HI> 28. 27. who had set his Son <HI>so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a Copy,</HI> that in truth he could not write after it <HI>without blotting▪</HI> And therefore <HI>he leaves the steps of his Father,</HI> and walks in the <HI>pathes</HI> of <HI>Da∣vid, and some others of his Fore-fathers.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>Ahaz</HI> (his Father) <HI>Reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem, but he did not that which was Richt in the sight of the Lord, like David his Fa∣ther,</HI> Chap. 28. 1. for he <HI>walked in the wayes of the Kings of Israel</HI> (which were the wayes of <HI>Jeroboam</HI> the Son of <HI>Nebat, who made Israel to sin) And also,</HI> or over and above their abominations, <HI>he made molten Images to Balaam,</HI> v. 2. <HI>And burned Incense in the valley of the son of</HI> Hinnom, <HI>and burned his Children in the fire, after the manner of the Heathen,</HI> v. 3. <HI>He Sacrificed also <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> and burned Incense in the high Places, and under every green Tree,</HI> v. 4. For which mis-actings <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <HI>God delivered him into the hands of the Kings of</HI> Syriah<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>and into the hands of the Kings of</HI> Israel, <HI>who smote him with great slaughter,</HI> v. 5. Whence we may note, That when <HI>Kings, Rulers</HI> or <HI>Governours, Act con∣trary to the mind of God, God raiseth up Adversaries against them,</HI> as once he did against <HI>Solomon,</HI> 1 Kings 11. 14. And as <HI>Ahaz continues his mis-actings,</HI> so God <HI>encreaseth his Adversaries;</HI> for the <HI>Edomites also came and smote</HI> Judah, <HI>and carried away Captives,</HI> v. 17. Yet for all this, <HI>Ahaz returned not to bim that smote him; Therefore the</HI> Phi∣listines <HI>also had invaded the Cities of the Low-Countreyes, and had taken several Towns and Villages, and came and dwelt in his Land,</HI> vers. 18. Whereupon <HI>Ahaz</HI> sends out for help to suppress his Enemies, but all in vain, so long as he <HI>continues an Enemy to God by wicked works. For at that time</HI> Ahaz <HI>sent to the Kings of</HI> Assyria <HI>to help him,</HI> v. 16. <HI>To whom</HI> Ahaz <HI>gave gifts out of the Lords House, and out of the Princes Houses; but they helped him not,</HI> v. 21. <HI>but distressed him,</HI> v. 20. Whence we may further note, That whilst men <HI>continue wicked,</HI> their <HI>Blessings become Curses,</HI> and their <HI>hoped for helps, hindrances.</HI></P>
<P>And <HI>thus</HI> whilst <HI>Ahaz</HI> is under the sin-revenging hand of God, the saying of the Prophet <HI>Isaiah</HI> is in him made good, <HI>Isaiah</HI> 1. 5. <HI>Why should ye be smitten any more? ye will revolt yet more and more.</HI> For <HI>with our first Parents in the Garden,</HI> Gen. 3. 8. <HI>Ahaz runs surther from his God, and returneth not</HI> to <HI>him that smote him.</HI> And with the <HI>fierce dog earnestly snaps at the stone that is thrown at him, little considering</HI> the <HI>hand that threw it.</HI> And <HI>thus</HI> whilst men are <HI>quarrelling at second causes,</HI> they loose both the <HI>Benefit</HI> and the <HI>Blessing</HI> of <HI>Gods chastising hand;</HI> And therefore cannot with <HI>David</HI> (that man after Gods own heart) say, as once he did, <HI>Psal.</HI> 119. 67, 71. <HI>It was good for him</HI>
<PB N="3" REF="11"/>
<HI>that he was afflicted, for before he</HI> was <HI>afflicted he went astray; but now</HI> (saith he) <HI>I have kept thy word. Thus</HI> whilst <HI>David</HI> is making a <HI>Right improvement of Gods chastising hand upon him,</HI> he is made <HI>sensible of Gods faithfulness towards him;</HI> which causeth him thankfully to acknow∣ledge the same; and to say, v. 57. <HI>I know, O Lord, that thy Judge∣ments are right, and that thou in faithfulness hast afflicted me:</HI> He now sees the dealings of God herein towards him to be such, as that he makes that <HI>Sanctified use of it,</HI> as once <HI>Moses</HI> the servant of the Lord <HI>required of Israel,</HI> Deut. 8. 5. <HI>Thou shalt also consider in thine heart, that as a Father chasteneth his Son, so the Lord thy God chasteneth thee.</HI> And so saith our Apostle, <HI>Heb.</HI> 12. 5, &amp;c.—<HI>My son despise not thou the chastening of the Lord—For whom the Lord loveth he chasteneth, and scourgeth every Son whom he receiveth.</HI></P>
<P>Men lie under the <HI>Chastising hand of God, as Wax and Clay</HI> in the <HI>heat of the Sun,</HI> whose <HI>heat</HI> so <HI>Mollifieth</HI> the <HI>Wax,</HI> as that it becomes <HI>plyable</HI> and <HI>fit</HI> for the <HI>Impression</HI> of the <HI>Seal;</HI> Whilst the <HI>Clay</HI> (though before soft) yet is thereby <HI>hardened,</HI> made <HI>stiff,</HI> and so <HI>brittle,</HI> that it will <HI>rather break,</HI> than in the <HI>least conform</HI> to the <HI>Seal.</HI></P>
<P>And thus, it fares with King <HI>Ahaz,</HI> he grows <HI>worse</HI> and <HI>worse; for in the time of this distress, did he Trespass yet more and more,</HI> saith the Text, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 28. <HI>vers.</HI> 22. <HI>For he Sacrificed to the Gods of Damaskus, which smote him; and he said, Because the Gods of the Kings of Syriah helped them, Therefore will I Sacrifice to them, that they may help me, vers.</HI> 23. <HI>Thus whilst men forsake the true God, they trust on them which by nature are no Gods: And so</HI> become as <HI>senseless,</HI> and as <HI>sottish as they. For they that make them, are like unto them; And so are all they that put their trust in them, Psal.</HI> 115. 8.</P>
<P>And as if these <HI>mis-actings</HI> of his were not enough to make <HI>him,</HI> and his <HI>People sufficiently Miserable;</HI> he <HI>Crowns,</HI> as it were all his former Evlls, with this <HI>tripple Crown</HI> of <HI>Abominations;</HI> First, <HI>he cut in pieces the vessels of the Lords House.</HI> Secondly, <HI>he shut up the Doors of the Lords House.</HI> And Thirdly, <HI>he sets up a false worship in every Corner of Jerusalem, to burn incense unto other Gods, v.</HI> 24, 25.</P>
<P>Thus whilst men <HI>relinquish</HI> their <HI>knowledge of the true God,</HI> they are <HI>given up</HI> to <HI>blindness</HI> of <HI>Eyes,</HI> and <HI>hardness</HI> of <HI>Heart;</HI> To <HI>commit all Abominations</HI> with <HI>greediness;</HI> for so saith our Apostle, <HI>Rom.</HI> 1. 28, 29. <HI>And as they did not like to retain God in their knowledge, God gave them up to a reprobate mind, to do those things which were not convenient,</HI> being <HI>filled with all unrighteousness,</HI> &amp;c. And thus whilst <HI>Ahaz</HI> is <HI>com∣mitting sin</HI> with <HI>greedilness, Ahaz</HI> is made <HI>partaker</HI> of its <HI>wages;</HI> for the <HI>wages</HI> of <HI>sin</HI> is <HI>death, Rom.</HI> 6. 23. And seeing <HI>Ahaz</HI> will thus
<PB N="4" REF="12"/>
<HI>forget</HI> God in his life time, God at length will <HI>deprive</HI> him of a <HI>pos∣sibility</HI> of <HI>remembring</HI> him at all; for in <HI>death</HI> there is no <HI>remembring of thee; And who shall give thee Thanks in the Pit?</HI> Psal. 6. 5.</P>
<P><HI>Ahaz</HI> being thus deprived of life, <HI>Hezekiah</HI> now cometh to <HI>suc∣ceed</HI> his Father in the <HI>Crown</HI> and <HI>Government:</HI> And seeing the several <HI>mis-actings</HI> of his Father, and the sad <HI>Consequences</HI> that <HI>attended</HI> both <HI>him</HI> and his <HI>People thereupon,</HI> is not willing to heir his <HI>Fathers punish∣ments;</HI> And <HI>therefore wlll not act in his Fathers sins,</HI> but makes an <HI>evi∣dent Manifestation</HI> of his <HI>experimental knowledge of them;</HI> and also of his <HI>utter Detestation to them;</HI> together with a <HI>Publick Declaration</HI> of the <HI>intentions of his heart,</HI> for a <HI>thorow Reformation</HI> throughout his <HI>whole Realm;</HI> for <HI>he gathered the Priests and the Levites together into the East∣street,</HI> Chap. 29. v. 4. and said, v. 6. <HI>Our Fathers have trespassed and done that which was evil in the eyes of the Lord our God, and have forsaken him, and have turned away their faces from the Habitation of the Lord, and turned their backs,</HI> v. 7. <HI>Also they have shut up the Doors of the Portch, and put out the Lamps, and have not burnt Incense, nor of∣fered burnt-offerings in the Holy Place, unto the God of Israel: Where∣fore</HI> saith he, v. 8. <HI>The Wrath of the Lord was upon Judah and Jerusa∣lem, and he hath delivered them to trouble, to astonishment, and to hissing, as ye see with your eyes;</HI> for saith he, v. 9. <HI>Our Fathers have fallen by the Sword, and our Sons and our Daughters, and our Wives are in Captivity</HI> (<HI>for this</HI>) <HI>And now it is in mine heart to make a Covenant with the Lord God of Israel, that his fierce wrath may turn away from us,</HI> vers. 10. <HI>Therefore</HI> he calls upon the <HI>Levites</HI> and the Priests, to be active in the Work, <HI>and not to be negligent in the places God had set them in,</HI> verse 11.</P>
<P><HI>A glorious Reformation</HI> is likely to <HI>succeed,</HI> when a Prince, <HI>not out of Custome,</HI> but out of <HI>Conscience, shall begin the Work;</HI> and the more likely it is to <HI>prosper,</HI> when his <HI>zeal</HI> thereunto shall <HI>thus</HI> cause him to <HI>provoke them,</HI> who indeed <HI>should have first stirred him up to the Work.</HI></P>
<P>And in this Reformarion, the first work that he enters upon, is the <HI>opening and Repairing the Door of the Lords House, and to cause the Levites to sanctifie themselves, and to sanctifie the House of God, and to carry forth the filthiness out of the holy Place,</HI> v. 3, 4, 5. the <HI>direct way</HI> to a happy <HI>Reformation,</HI> and as ready a way to have with God a <HI>Re∣conciliation;</HI> for if the <HI>iniquity of our holy things be not done away,</HI> what will it avail us, though we thrive never so well in our secular affairs? for saith our Saviour, <HI>Mat. 16. 26. For what is a man profited, if he shall gain the whole world, and loose his own Soul? Or what shall a man give in exchange for his Soul?</HI></P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="12"/>In this Reformation, <HI>Hezekiah's speed equals</HI> his <HI>willingness;</HI> and like <HI>a pair of Heisers</HI> accustomed to the yoak, they <HI>draw both together; for</HI> as it was his <HI>first work,</HI> to have respect to the <HI>cleansing of his holy things;</HI> so it was his care to do it in the <HI>first year of his Reign;</HI> and not late in the year, but in <HI>the first month of that first year;</HI> for so saith the Text, 2 <HI>Chron.</HI> 29. 3. <HI>He in the first year of his Reign, in the first month, ope∣ned the Doors,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>And <HI>this</HI> is that which I am perswaded is well pleasing to God, when men <HI>sleep not upon good Resolutions, but puts them into present and effectu∣all practise;</HI> for no man can call to morrow his: Therefore the Coun∣sel of the Spirit of God is good, which he hath given by the Wise Man, <HI>Eccles.</HI> 9. 10. <HI>Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it wich thy might, for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom in the grave, whither thou goest.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Hezekiah began to Reign when he was five and twenty years old,</HI> Cha. 29. 1. <HI>And he did that which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all that David his Father had doue,</HI> v. 2. And as by Faith <HI>Moses, when he came to years, refused to be called</HI> the Son <HI>of Pharaoh's Daughter, choosing rather to suffer Afflictions with the People of God, than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season; esteeming the reproach of</HI> Christ, <HI>greater riches than the treasures of Egypt</HI> (<HI>because</HI>) <HI>he had respect to the recom∣pence of reward,</HI> Heb. 11. 24. So <HI>Hezekiah</HI> being <HI>five and twenty years old</HI> when he began to Reign, <HI>refused to walk in the wayes of sin,</HI> as <HI>Ahaz</HI> his Father had done, but <HI>begins with discretion</HI> to <HI>consider</HI> what was <HI>well-pleasing to God;</HI> and <HI>therefore he learns</HI> to <HI>write</HI> by a <HI>perfect Copy,</HI> he takes a <HI>Man after Gods own heart</HI> to be his <HI>Pattern, though</HI> they that <HI>hated</HI> him without a cause, were <HI>more than the hairs of his head, though</HI> his <HI>enemies</HI> were <HI>mighty,</HI> Psal. 69. 4. though he became a <HI>Proverb</HI> to many, <HI>verse</HI> 11. and though they that sate in the gates spake against him; and though he became a <HI>Song</HI> to the <HI>Drunkards,</HI> ver. 12. yet <HI>these</HI> and such <HI>reproaches</HI> as <HI>these,</HI> shall not <HI>frighten</HI> him, but <HI>Hezekiah</HI> will <HI>do</HI> according to all that <HI>David his Father had done; David</HI> we see was no <HI>Allower</HI> of <HI>Drunkenness;</HI> for the <HI>Drnnkards made Songs of him,</HI> as they do <HI>now in this our dayes upon those that desire to walk in the integrity</HI> of their <HI>hearts before the Lord,</HI> as <HI>David</HI> did; <HI>David opened not</HI> a Door to any manner of <HI>licencious∣ness; neither</HI> doth <HI>Hezekiah,</HI> when he comes to Reign, go to the house of <HI>laughter,</HI> but to the <HI>house of God;</HI> he runs not to <HI>Hawkings,</HI> nor <HI>Huntings, Revellings,</HI> nor <HI>Dancings, Riotings</HI> nor <HI>Banquetings,</HI> he sets not up, nor tollerates <HI>Stage-Playes, May-games,</HI> nor <HI>Pastimes;</HI> but comes to <HI>a serious consideration what the mind of God was,</HI> that so he might <HI>pleas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI>
<PB N="4" REF="13"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="5" REF="13"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="6" REF="14"/>
him, to the <HI>Eternal well-being,</HI> both <HI>of himself</HI> and <HI>those that were under his charge;</HI> therefere with <HI>spéed</HI> he <HI>opens</HI> the <HI>Doors of the Lords House, and begins to put away the iniquity of his holy things.</HI></P>
<P>Now know, O King, that <HI>Hezekiah</HI> was a <HI>good man,</HI> and went on in his <HI>Reformation in Gods way;</HI> let me therefore beg of thee, as thou tenderest thy Souls good to Eternity, <HI>take him for thy Pattern, begin thy Reign as he did his, look into thy holy things,</HI> see <HI>what there is amiss there, consider the Common-prayer, whence it came and whither it tendeth, weigh it with its appurtenances in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, try it by the Touch-stone of Gods Word,</HI> see <HI>whether it b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> not too <HI>light,</HI> of what God <HI>would have it</HI> to be; see also whether the <HI>Inventions</HI> of <HI>Men have</HI> not <HI>made it too heavy,</HI> thou canst not be <HI>too exact therein;</HI> for he that <HI>doth</HI> in his service to God, <HI>more than what God Commands, doth too much, and is no better than a Will-worshipper;</HI> he that doth <HI>less than God Commandeth him, doth too little.</HI></P>
<P>Consider also, <HI>which is the Door of Gods House,</HI> and <HI>open that,</HI> for Christ himself saith, <HI>That many false Prophets will arise, and shall deceive many; and therefore he requireth his</HI> Disciples, <HI>not to go out to them,</HI> Mat. 24. 24, 26. Therefore the opening of <HI>any Door will not serve the turn; Hezekiah opened the Door of the Lords House:</HI> Therefore for the Lords sake Consider what thou doest, take that Counsel from the Spirit of the Lord, which is Recorded in 1 <HI>Thes.</HI> 5. 21, 22. <HI>Prove all things, aud hold fast that which is good, and abstain from all appearance of evil.</HI></P>
<P>Take notice of the <HI>Dispensation thou art under,</HI> and do thy <HI>Genera∣tion work in Gods way;</HI> the <HI>Church</HI> of <HI>Christ</HI> under <HI>the Gospel, is not National,</HI> but <HI>Congregational; Hezekiah</HI> was of the <HI>Race</HI> of the <HI>Jews,</HI> and a <HI>King of Judah;</HI> it was <HI>Hezekiahs work</HI> to open the <HI>Doors</HI> of the <HI>Material Temple, scituate</HI> in <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> where God had under that dispensation <HI>promised</HI> his <HI>presence,</HI> 1 Kings 9. 3. So that if <HI>Heze∣kiah</HI> had <HI>opened any other Door,</HI> he had been a <HI>sinner</HI> as well as his Fa∣ther <HI>Ahaz,</HI> who opened another, when he <HI>shut those Material Doors,</HI> where the Jews had a Right to Worship, as they were in a <HI>National Church-Communion,</HI> upon the <HI>due administration</HI> of that fleshly Or∣dinance of <HI>Circumcision, peremtorily</HI> upon the eight day, <HI>Gen.</HI> 17. 12. Under which he that <HI>neglected</HI> to <HI>Circumcise</HI> his Male Infant upon the eighth day, did it <HI>too late,</HI> and <HI>after Gods time,</HI> and that <HI>Infant</HI> was to be <HI>cut off from the People,</HI> V. 14. and he that did it before the eighth day, did it too soon, and before Gods time, and so became a <HI>transgressor.</HI> We usually say in our common Proverb, that <HI>it is dangerous jesting with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ged tools;</HI> so may I safely say, it is a <HI>dangerous</HI> thing to <HI>cross</HI> the <HI>de∣sign</HI>
<PB N="7" REF="14"/>
<HI>of God;</HI> it is a <HI>desperate design</HI> to undertake to <HI>open</HI> that which God hath <HI>shut,</HI> or to <HI>shut</HI> that which God hath <HI>opened.</HI></P>
<P>God hath <HI>shut</HI> the <HI>Doors</HI> of a <HI>National Church,</HI> then let men <HI>fear</HI> to <HI>open it;</HI> and God hath <HI>opened</HI> the <HI>Door</HI> of a <HI>Congregational Church,</HI> let Souls <HI>tremble</HI> at the thought of <HI>shutting it;</HI> for so saith the Lord Christ, <HI>John</HI> 4. 21, 22, 23. <HI>Believe me</HI> (saith he) <HI>the hour cometh when ye shall neither in this Mountain,</HI> nor yet in <HI>Jerusalem Wor∣ship</HI> the <HI>Father; ye Worship ye know not what:</HI> We know what we Worship, <HI>for Salvation is of the Jewes;</HI> but <HI>the hour cometh, and</HI> now is, <HI>when the true Worshippers</HI> shall <HI>Worship the Father</HI> in <HI>Spirit</HI> and in <HI>Truth:</HI> And saith <HI>Peter, Now I perceive of a truth, that God is no Respecter of persons, but in every Nation he that feareth him, and worketh Righteousness, is accepted of him,</HI> Acts 10. 34, 35. <HI>So that Church∣fellowship</HI> and <HI>Son-ship with God,</HI> is <HI>entailed</HI> upon persons <HI>under the Gospel, not</HI> upon the <HI>account</HI> of the <HI>bare Subjection to the Ordinances,</HI> as it was <HI>under</HI> the <HI>Law, but</HI> upon the account of their <HI>Faith;</HI> for saith the Apostle, <HI>Ye</HI> (Members of the Church of <HI>Galatia) are all the Chil∣dren of God by Faith in Christ Jefus</HI> (which Faith working by love, hath evidenced it self to be true, by working you to obedience to Gods Ordinances) <HI>for so many of you as have been Baptized into Christ, have put on Christ.</HI></P>
<P>And as no <HI>uncircumcised</HI> person was to <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>at</HI> of the <HI>Passeover under the Law,</HI> Exod. 12. 48. <HI>So of Christ our Passeover, who is Sacrificed for us</HI> under this Gospel-dispensation, 1 <HI>Corinth.</HI> 5. 7. <HI>is no unbeliever to have Communion,</HI> 2 Corinthians 6. 14. to 17. And as under the Law it was charged upon the Jews as <HI>a sin</HI> to bring the <HI>Uncircumcised</HI> into the <HI>material▪ Temple,</HI> Ezek. 44. 7, 9. because Circumcision was the <HI>inducting Ordinance</HI> of Cod under that dispensation: So also under a Gospel-dispensation, we dare not administer that Inducting Ordi∣nance of Baptism, <HI>without Faith in God be firct begotten.</HI></P>
<P>So that if persons shall <HI>require</HI> from us the <HI>Administration</HI> of that <HI>Ordinance,</HI> we shall no more dare to do it than <HI>Philip,</HI> who <HI>first would have an account of the Eunuch's faith, before he Baptized him;</HI> for so saith the Text, <HI>Acts</HI> 8. 37. <HI>If thou Believest with all thy heart, thou mayest;</HI> who <HI>immediatly</HI> made a <HI>Confession</HI> of his <HI>Faith;</HI> and this is according to the <HI>Commission</HI> of Christ, <HI>Mark</HI> 16. vers. 15. which saith not, that he that is <HI>Baptized,</HI> but he that <HI>Believeth</HI> and is <HI>Baptized shall be saved;</HI> So that it is a <HI>dangerous thing to make the strait Gate that leads to life, wider than God hath made it.</HI></P>
<P>Therefore know O▪ King, that thou art under that dispensation, in which the <HI>Ax</HI> is <HI>laid to the root of the Tree,</HI> and wherein <HI>every tree</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="15"/>
that brings not forth <HI>good fruit,</HI> is to be <HI>hewen down</HI> and <HI>cast into the fire,</HI> Mat. 3. 10. Under which persous are <HI>forbidden to plead their Birth-Priviledges,</HI> V. 9. as that they are <HI>Children of Believing Parents,</HI> or <HI>Sons</HI> and <HI>Daughters</HI> to <HI>Abraham;</HI> but under that dispensation by which <HI>they are all the Children of God by faith in Christ Iesus</HI> (as afore∣said) <HI>who have actually manifested their faith by their obedience, in their putting on of Christ by Baptism,</HI> as that Church did, <HI>Gal.</HI> 3. 26, 27. <HI>Such as are chosen out of the world,</HI> John 15. 19. John 17. 6, 14. <HI>Separating themselves according to the requirements of God, from false and Baby∣lonish worship,</HI> Revel. 18. 4. 2 Cor. 6. 14, 17. <HI>Being begotten to the faith,</HI> Philemon 10. 1 Tim. 1. 2. 2 Tim. 1. 2. Titus 1. 4. <HI>By the Preaching of the Word,</HI> James 1. 18. 1 Cor. 4. 15. <HI>And quickned by the Spirit,</HI> John 6. 63. Rom. 8. 11. Eph. 2. 1, 5. Col. 2. 13. <HI>Being born again,</HI> 1 John 4. 7. 1 John 5. 1. 1 John 3. 9. <HI>Not of corruptible séed, but of incorrup<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ible,</HI> 1 Pet. 1. 23. <HI>Not of flesh nor blood, nor after the will of man, but of God,</HI> John 1. 13. <HI>Being born of water and the Spirit; without which,</HI> if we may believe our blessed Saviour himself, John 3. 5. <HI>no man can enter into the Kingdom of Heaven;</HI> the <HI>necessity whereof</HI> is <HI>fully laid down</HI> by the Apostle, 1 Pet. 3. 20. who speaking of the <HI>preservation</HI> that <HI>Noah had by the Ark</HI> from that <HI>deluge</HI> of water, <HI>Gen.</HI> 7. 17. <HI>The like figure whereunto even Baptism</HI> (saith he) doth <HI>now</HI> (under this Gospel-dispensation) <HI>save us;</HI> not <HI>by washing away of the filth of the flesh, but the answering a good Conscience towards God by the Resurrection of Jesus Christ;</HI> as if the Apostle should have said, it is not the <HI>washing</HI> the <HI>body in Water,</HI> that is of <HI>this saving nature,</HI> but <HI>it is</HI> the <HI>going into the Water</HI> in a <HI>Conscionable obedienee</HI> to the <HI>Command of God,</HI> to have our <HI>sins mystically washed away by Faith in the blood of Christ;</HI> and so also saith the Apostle, <HI>Acts</HI> 22. 16. <HI>And now why tarriest thou, arise and be Baptized,</HI> &amp; <HI>wash away thy sins, calling on the Name of the Lord▪</HI> and the same Apostle writing to <HI>Titus,</HI> makes a clear discovery by what means God on <HI>their parts saved them,</HI> Titus. 3. 5. <HI>Who hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> us</HI> (saith he) <HI>not by deeds</HI> of <HI>Righteousness that we have done, but by</HI> the <HI>washing of Regeneration,</HI> or (as the old Translation renders it) <HI>by</HI> the <HI>fountain of the new birth,</HI> and <HI>renewing of the Holy Ghost;</HI> by <HI>Water∣work,</HI> and <HI>Spirit-work;</HI> the <HI>Spirit operating upon,</HI> and <HI>working up a Soul conscionably</HI> to <HI>obey God in</HI> that <HI>holy</HI> (though amongst men that <HI>much despised</HI>) <HI>Ordinance of Water-baptism.</HI></P>
<P>And thus the Apostle tels us by what means <HI>Christ hath clenfed his Church;</HI> viz. <HI>with the washing of water,</HI> by (or according) to the <HI>Word,</HI> Eph. 5. 26. And <HI>thus</HI> some in the Church of the <HI>Corinthians,</HI> who formerly were unrighteous, even Fornicators, Idolaters, Adul∣terers,
<PB N="9" REF="15"/>
Effeminate, Abusers of themselves with man-kind, Thieves and Robbers; were by this <HI>Spirit</HI> and <HI>Water-work washed and clen∣sed:</HI> For so saith our Apostle, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 6. 11. <HI>And such were some of you;</HI> but ye are <HI>washed,</HI> but <HI>ye are Sanctified</HI> in <HI>the Name of the Lord Jesus,</HI> and by the <HI>Spirit of our God:</HI> So that a Church of Christ, or House of God under a Gospel-dispensation, is to be <HI>built up of lively stones,</HI> a <HI>spirituall House,</HI> an <HI>holy</HI> Priesthood, to offer up <HI>spiritual Sacrifices</HI> (that will be) <HI>acceptable to God by Jesus Christ,</HI> 1 Pet. 2. 5. <HI>Of which the building of the Material Temple was a Type;</HI> for, as the <HI>House</HI> which <HI>Solomon built,</HI> 1 Kings 6. 7. <HI>was built of stone made ready before it was brought thither;</HI> so <HI>that there was neither</HI> Hammer <HI>nor</HI> Ax, <HI>nor any tool of Iron heard in the House, when it was in building:</HI> So in the <HI>gathering</HI> or <HI>building</HI> a <HI>Gospel-Church, persons are to be fitted, hewen</HI> and <HI>squared, before</HI> they are laid <HI>into this Building;</HI> they are to <HI>repent</HI> from <HI>dead works,</HI> and to have <HI>Faith in God, before they be Baptized;</HI> that as <HI>that</HI> was a <HI>Material,</HI> so this a <HI>spiritual House;</HI> as those stoues were <HI>dead,</HI> these <HI>lively;</HI> as those stones so <HI>soon</HI> as they were laid <HI>into the building,</HI> and the <HI>work finished,</HI> they became a House fit to <HI>sacrifice in;</HI> so these <HI>lively stones</HI> being brought together, are fit <HI>presently, actually</HI> to <HI>offer up spiritual Sacrifices,</HI> such as God will <HI>accept;</HI> they <HI>being in Jesus Christ,</HI> first <HI>mystically</HI> by <HI>Faith;</HI> and secondly, <HI>actually</HI> by <HI>their Obedience;</HI> and <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Obedience</HI> being Gods <HI>Twins, we dare not in the least entertain so much as a thought to separate them.</HI></P>
<P>So that, O King, if thou with <HI>Hezekiah</HI> wilt open the <HI>Door of the Lords House,</HI> it is <HI>not a National,</HI> but a <HI>Congregational Door thou art to open,</HI> which is not to be <HI>compulsive,</HI> but <HI>perswasive;</HI> for so saith a <HI>true Gospel-Minister, Knowing therefore the terrour of the Lord, we perswade men,</HI> 2 Cor. 5. 11. <HI>Now then we are</HI> Ambassadors <HI>for Christ, as though God did</HI> beseech you by us; We pray you <HI>in Christs stead, be ye reconciled to God,</HI> v. 20. Whence we may note, that a <HI>Gospel Minister</HI> is not to be like the <HI>General</HI> of an <HI>Army,</HI> to <HI>frighten, beat</HI> or <HI>fight men into faith;</HI> but as an <HI>Ambassador</HI> to <HI>perswade</HI> and <HI>in∣vite,</HI> and <HI>gently</HI> to <HI>treat</HI> with, and to <HI>entreat into the way of God;</HI> the one being <HI>Diabolical,</HI> but the other <HI>Evangelical,</HI> and the way of <HI>Love</HI> being <HI>Gods Way;</HI> this is one of the <HI>distinguishing Characters of a true Gospel-Minister,</HI> whom the <HI>Love</HI> of <HI>Christ hath constrained,</HI> which causeth men to look upon them, to be <HI>Fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>naticks,</HI> or <HI>mad men;</HI> for so saith our Apostle, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 5. 13. <HI>For whether we be besides our selves, it is to God, or whether we be sober, it is for your Cause; for the Love of Christ constraineth us:</HI> And saith he, in Chap. 12. 14. <HI>I will not be bur∣thensom to you, for I seek not yours, but you;</HI> (and he gives this in as a
<PB N="10" REF="16"/>
Reason, for saith he) <HI>The Children ought not to lay up for the Parents, but the Parents for the Children; and I will very gladly spend</HI> and <HI>be spent for you, though the more abundantly I love, the less I am loved;</HI> And <HI>such are made Over-seers of the Flock of God by the Holy Ghost,</HI> Acts 20. 28. <HI>who feed it, and take the oversight thereof, not by constraint, but willingly; not of filthy lucre, but of a ready mind,</HI> 1 Pet. 5. 2. as good Stewards of the manifold grace of God, 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 4. 10. <HI>Such are good Shepherds, and not Hirelings, who will lay down their life for the sheep,</HI> John 10. 11. Whilst others being <HI>made Over∣seers by men,</HI> instead of <HI>feeding the Flock, feed upon the Flock;</HI> as those careless Shepherds, spoken of▪ <HI>Ezek.</HI> 34. 2, 3, 4. <HI>against whom a Woe is pronounced, Who feed themselves, who eat the fat, and cloath themselves with the Wool, and kill them that are fed, but feed not the Flock;</HI> who <HI>strengthen not the diseased,</HI> nor <HI>heal the sick,</HI> nor <HI>bind up the broken,</HI> nor <HI>bring again that which is driven away,</HI> nor <HI>séek that which is lost, but Rule them with cruelty;</HI> as the Prophet saith, <HI>Micah</HI> 3. 2, 3. <HI>Who hate the good, and love the evil;</HI> who <HI>pluck off their skins from off them,</HI> and <HI>their flesh from their bones; who eat the flesh of my People,</HI> and <HI>stay their skins from off them; who break their bones, and chop them in pieces as for the Pot, and as flesh for the Chaldron,</HI> v. 5. <HI>Who bite with their teeth, and cry, Peace;</HI> and he that <HI>putteth not into their mouths,</HI> they <HI>make War against him;</HI> who are <HI>Hirelings, and not true Shepherds;</HI> who <HI>formerly,</HI> if a <HI>fatter Bene∣fice came in the way, would not stay till the Wolf came,</HI> but hearkned to <HI>that</HI> Call, and left the Sheep, <HI>to secure themselves</HI> from the <HI>Wolves, if they would: But such are false Apostles,</HI> deceitful <HI>workers, transforming themselves into the Apostles of Christ: And no marvel, saith our Apostle,</HI> 2 Cor. 11. 13, 14. <HI>For Satan himself is transformed into an Angel of Light,</HI> ver. 15. <HI>Therefore it is no great thing, if his Ministers</HI> also <HI>be transformed into the Ministers</HI> of <HI>Righteousness; whose end shall be according to their works;</HI> whilst the true Apostle is as <HI>frée</HI> to <HI>give,</HI> as <HI>fréely</HI> he <HI>hath received, who is ready to Preach the Word,</HI> and <HI>to be instant in season</HI> and <HI>out of season,</HI> and <HI>to reprove, rebuke,</HI> and <HI>exhort, with all long-suffering</HI> and Doctrine, according to that good Advice, 2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 4. 2.</P>
<P>And thus, O King, having in some measure given thee the Character of a <HI>Gospel-Church,</HI> and <HI>Ministry;</HI> I shall now beg thee in Gods fear, that thou have a care thou open the <HI>right Door:</HI> open not the <HI>broad Gate that leads to destruction,</HI> instead of that <HI>narrow way that leads to life,</HI> Mat. 7. 13, 14. If <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hou incendest to do <HI>Gods Work,</HI> have a care thou doest it <HI>in Gods Way.</HI> And that I may the better perswade thee there unto, I shall briefly lay before thee two or three Examples, of
<PB N="11" REF="16"/>
Gods severity against those that have been careless therein: <HI>Moses</HI> and <HI>Aaron</HI> the Servants of the Lord, <HI>Numb.</HI> 20. who but for <HI>smiting</HI> the Rock, when they should have <HI>spoken to</HI> it, died in the Wilderness, and were not suffered to carry <HI>Israel</HI> into the Land of <HI>Canaan,</HI> as we may fully understand by comparing the eight verse with 11, 12, 23. to 29. with <HI>Numb.</HI> 27. 12. to 15. with <HI>Deut.</HI> 34. If <HI>Saul</HI> will save alive those which God will have destroyed, <HI>Saul</HI> must deeply suffer for it, 1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 15. but more of this anon: And if <HI>Akan</HI> will take of the ac∣cursed things, <HI>Akan</HI> must deeply suffer; for saith the Text, <HI>Joshua</HI> 7. 24, 25. And <HI>Joshua</HI> said, Why hast thou troubled us? The Lord shall trouble thee this day; and all <HI>Israel</HI> stoned him, his Sons and his Daughters, his Oxen and his Asses, and his Sheep, and burned them with fire: <HI>The Lord give thee,</HI> O King, <HI>an understanding heart, to con∣sider things aright.</HI></P>
<P>But to proceed, <HI>Hezekiah doth</HI> not onely stir up the <HI>Priests</HI> and <HI>Levites</HI> to the Work of <HI>Reformation,</HI> but <HI>also all</HI> Judah <HI>and</HI> Jerusalem, <HI>and wrote Letters,</HI> Chap. 30. 1. <HI>and made a Decree, and made Pro∣clamation, that they must come up to</HI> Jerusalem, <HI>to keep the Passeover unto the Lord; for they had not done it of a long time in such sort as it was written,</HI> ver. 5.</P>
<P>Whence we may note, That in <HI>Hezekiah's</HI> Reformation, he <HI>Re∣formed not</HI> according to what had been their <HI>custom of a long time,</HI> nor to what his <HI>Father before him did;</HI> but according <HI>as it was writ∣ten,</HI> according <HI>to the Law of God:</HI> And this is that which <HI>makes</HI> the Work to <HI>thrive</HI> in his <HI>hands;</HI> when he doth <HI>Gods Work in Gods Way.</HI> Therefore let me beg thee, <HI>O King, as thou tenderest thine own good,</HI> now thou art upon thy <HI>Reformation,</HI> to <HI>take Hezekiah</HI> for thy <HI>Pattern,</HI> have the <HI>Word of the Lord for thy Warrant,</HI> see thou do it according to the <HI>written Law of God; for such a Reformation onely will stand, and thou with it:</HI> But if thou do it according to the <HI>former customs,</HI> and what thy <HI>Father did before thee,</HI> thou sawest <HI>that fell, and him with it:</HI> for what is of man, will come to nothing, but if it be of God, it cannot be overthrown, <HI>Acts</HI> 5. 38, 39.</P>
<P>And know, <HI>O King,</HI> that <HI>much Knowledge</HI> and <HI>true Light</HI> hath bro∣ken forth within these twelve years, and <HI>what</HI> men might do in <HI>Igno∣rance,</HI> haply may be <HI>excusable, which now cannot;</HI> for so saith our Apo∣stle, <HI>Acts</HI> 17. 3. <HI>In the times of this Ignora<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce God winked at, but now he Commands all men every where to repent:</HI> And let no man despise my Speech, in saying, <HI>much knowledge</HI> and <HI>true Light</HI> is within these few years▪ <HI>broken out;</HI> if they shall, I must answer them after the manner of <HI>Peter,</HI> answering those scosfing Jewes, <HI>in that then so much</HI>
<PB N="12" REF="17"/>
<HI>admired-at giving out of the Spirit,</HI> Acts 2. 14, 15. We are not <HI>Fan∣naticks</HI> or <HI>mad men,</HI> as ye <HI>suppose</HI> in so saying; <HI>but this is that</HI> which was spoken of by the Prophets, <HI>Dan.</HI> 12. 4. <HI>Many shall run to and fro, and Knowledge shall encrease;</HI> for saith the Prophet, <HI>Haba.</HI> 2. 14. <HI>The Earth shall be filled with the Knowledge of the glory of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea:</HI> Therefore be sure, O King, thou have, <HI>Thus saith the Word of the Lord,</HI> for thy <HI>Warrant;</HI> for God is a jealous God, and will not be served with any thing, but <HI>what is of his own.</HI></P>
<P>And <HI>this did Hezekiah throughout all Jndah, and wrought that which was good,</HI> and <HI>right,</HI> and <HI>truth before the Lord his God; and in every work that he began in the service of the House of God, and in the Law, and in the Commandments, to seek his God, he did it</HI> with all his heart; and saith the Text, <HI>He prospered,</HI> Chap. 31. 20, 21.</P>
<P>Whence we may note, <HI>That whilst Hezekiahs heart was upright to God, God prospered him;</HI> and thus we find in Holy Writ, <HI>That whilst men with a perfect heart, have a careful eye in all their undertakings to please God, God hath a tender eye over them to prosper them:</HI> And thus whilst <HI>Joseph</HI> is answering his lustful Mistris, with a <HI>How can I do this great wickedness and sin against God?</HI> Gen. 39. 9. Though <HI>Joseph</HI> by her revengeful malice be cast into Prison, <HI>yet God is with him, v.</HI> 21. <HI>And God gives him favour in the eyes of the Prison-Keeper, insomuch that the Prison-keeper looked not after any thing that was under his hands;</HI> and the Reason is added, <HI>vers.</HI> 28. <HI>Because the Lord was with him; and that which he did,</HI> the Text saith, <HI>The Lord made it it prosper.</HI></P>
<P>And thus whilst <HI>Daniel</HI> in the Babylonish captivity, is <HI>resolved in his heart not to defile himself with a portion of the Kings Idolatrous Meat, nor of his wine,</HI> God <HI>bringeth Daniel iuto</HI> Favour <HI>and</HI> tender Love <HI>with the Prince of the Eunuches,</HI> Dan. 1. 3, 9. <HI>Insomuch that</HI> the Eunuch <HI>will venture his head to the King</HI> his Master, rather than <HI>Daniel</HI> shall <HI>want that food he desires,</HI> V. 10, 14.</P>
<P>A good encouragemant for the People of God in the very worst of times, even to take up a Resolution, to <HI>eye God in what he would have them to do in all things, and not</HI> at all to <HI>fear the faces of men, though never so great;</HI> for if <HI>Shadrach, Meshach</HI> and <HI>Abednego,</HI> will not bow to <HI>Nebuchadnezzars</HI> Image, but keep themselves <HI>close to their God,</HI> God will <HI>keep as close to them; and one like the Son of Man shall walk with them in that seven times hot fiery Furnace, to preserve them,</HI> Dan. 3. 16, 25. Will <HI>Daniel</HI> Petition <HI>no other but the true God, though against the Decree of the King? that God will send his Angel, to shut</HI>
<PB N="13" REF="17"/>
<HI>the mouths of the Lyons, that they shall not hurt him,</HI> Daniel 6. 10. 22.</P>
<P>Theresore suffer me to bespeak thee and thy People, O King, in the Language of <HI>Azariah</HI> the Son of <HI>Obed,</HI> which he once uttered to King <HI>Asa,</HI> 2 <HI>Chron.</HI> 15. 1. Hear thou me CHARLES, and all <HI>England, Scotland, Ireland,</HI> and in particular thou proud, voluptuous and vain-glorious City of <HI>London; the Lord is with you whilst you are with him; if</HI> ye <HI>seek him, he will be found of you; but if ye forsake him, he will forsake you.</HI></P>
<P>And let not the King be angry, if one that is counted a Fannatick speak once more to him, not in his own Language, but in the words of the Spirit of the Lord, in the Prophet <HI>David</HI> to his Son, 1 <HI>Chro.</HI> 28. 9. <HI>And thou Solomon my Son, know thou the God of thy Fathers, and serve him with a perfect heart, and with a willing mind; for the Lord searcheth all hearts, and understandeth all the imaginations of thy thoughts; if thou seek him, he will be found of thee, but if thou forsake him, he will cast thee off for ever.</HI> Thou knowest, O King, thou hast <HI>had a cast∣ing off,</HI> and that <HI>that</HI> casting off may not be for ever; be perswaded to turn to thy God <HI>with all thy heart.</HI></P>
<P>We usually say, That he that would <HI>move another to weep,</HI> must <HI>first cry</HI> himself, he must <HI>first begin the passion;</HI> thus God hath done, God hath <HI>begun a Work,</HI> God hath <HI>first troden a Path</HI> for thee, O King, to walk in, God hath made a <HI>Return</HI> to thee <HI>most miraculously,</HI> and far (I presume) beyond thine own <HI>Expectation,</HI> or the <HI>Imagination</HI> of <HI>many</HI> others; therefore, O King, <HI>Prepare to meet thy God,</HI> have a care thou walk not in any <HI>By-Path,</HI> but <HI>onely and alone in that Path of Returning,</HI> which God hath <HI>troden for thee;</HI> and as God hath been <HI>Miraculous</HI> in <HI>his Returning to thee,</HI> O be thou as <HI>Eminent in thy returniug to him; this</HI> is that which I am confident the <HI>Lord looketh for</HI> at thy hands; for so saith the Lip of Truth it self, <HI>Luke</HI> 12. 48. <HI>For unto whomsoever much is given, of him shall be much required;</HI> and the <HI>same voice</HI> hath the Spi∣rit of the Lord in my Text, <HI>But Hezekiah rendred not again according to the Benefits bestowed upon him; therefore wrath fell upon him, and upon Judah and Jerusalem.</HI></P>
<P>And that I may come to the handling the words themselves, I shall briefly shew what God did <HI>for Hezekiah,</HI> that caused him to look for so <HI>suitable a return from Hezekiah.</HI></P>
<P><HI>After these things, and the establishment thereof,</HI> Chap. 32. 1. That is, After the <HI>Reformation that Hezekiah</HI> had made, as I have in part laid down, and as in the three foregoing Chapters is more particular∣ly discovered; <HI>Aster these things, and the establishment thereof, Senna∣cherib,</HI>
<PB N="14" REF="18"/>
<HI>King of Assyria, came and entered into Judah, and Encamped against the fenced Cities, and thought to win them to himself.</HI></P>
<P>Whence we may note, That though men <HI>walk</HI> never so <HI>close with God,</HI> yet they cannot be <HI>exempted</HI> from the <HI>malicious endeavours of wicked men: David</HI> we know, is Recorded in holy Writ, to be a <HI>man after Gods own heart,</HI> who in the <HI>Confidence of his Soul,</HI> sometimes can say, The <HI>Lord is on his right hand,</HI> he <HI>shall not be moved,</HI> Psal. 16. 8. And <HI>anon</HI> in <HI>Psal.</HI> 17. 8. he begs of the Lord, to <HI>hide him under the shadow of his Wings,</HI> from the <HI>wicked that oppress him,</HI> and from his <HI>deadly Enemies: Now he will not fear what man can do unto him;</HI> And <HI>anon,</HI> he <HI>cryeth out, That one day he shall fall by the hand of Saul.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Good men are at an uncertainty of quietness,</HI> or <HI>tranquility, on this side the grave:</HI> If the Sons and Daughters of God had <HI>too much Happi∣ness and Peace in this life,</HI> they would <HI>then</HI> begin to <HI>settle upon the Lees,</HI> and <HI>satisfie</HI> themselves with that which <HI>cannot profit: God knows what is fitter for his, than they do themselves;</HI> and therefore it is that he <HI>suf∣fers</HI> his <HI>dearest Children</HI> to <HI>undergo great Tryals,</HI> and that for several Reasons.</P>
<P>First, for the Tryal of their Faith, according to that of <HI>Judg.</HI> 2. 21. <HI>I will not,</HI> saith the Lord, <HI>drive out any of the Nations which Joshua left when he died;</HI> and the Reason is added: That <HI>through them</HI> I may <HI>prove Israel, whether they will keep the Way of the Lord, to walk therein, as their Fathers did keep it:</HI> therefore saith the Text, <HI>The Lord left those Nations, without driving them out hastily, neither de∣livered he them into the hands of Joshua,</HI> V. 23. according to that of the Apostle, 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 1. 7. <HI>That the Tryal of your Faith being much more precious than of Gold that perisheth, though it be tryed with fire, may be found unto Praise, and Glory, and Honour, at the appearing of Jesus Christ.</HI></P>
<P>A second Reason may be, for the <HI>encrease of their Graces,</HI> according to that saying of the Apostle, <HI>James</HI> 1. 2, 3. <HI>Knowing that the Try∣al of our Faith worketh Patience;</HI> and therefore the Apostle <HI>Paul</HI> did <HI>glory in Tribulations, knowing that Tribulation worketh Patience, and Patience Experience, and Experience Hope; and Hope,</HI> saith he; <HI>maketh not ashamed,</HI> Rom. 5. 3, 4.</P>
<P>A third Reason may be, because <HI>Troubles</HI> and <HI>Afflictions</HI> being <HI>right∣ly improved,</HI> worketh good to a Soul to <HI>Eternity;</HI> and so saith our Apo∣stle, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 4. 17. <HI>For our light Affliction, which are but for a Mo∣ment, worketh for us a far more Exceeding and Eternal weight of Glory; whilst we look not at the things which are seen, but at the things which are</HI>
<PB N="15" REF="18"/>
<HI>not seen; for the things which are seen, are Temporal; but the things which are not seen, they are Eternal.</HI></P>
<P>And further, God by these Actings keeps a Soul <HI>close to himself,</HI> and thereby gives it opportunities continually, either <HI>to Pray,</HI> or <HI>to Praise him, for Deliverances.</HI></P>
<P>For this <HI>Invasion,</HI> together with the <HI>abominable Blasphemies</HI> of <HI>Sennacherib, drives Hezekiah to his God;</HI> and so saith the Text, <HI>For this cause, Hezekiah the King, and the Prophet Isaiah, Prayed</HI> and <HI>cryed to Heaven,</HI> vers. 20. <HI>Men that walk close with God in time of Prosperity, can with boldness go to God in time of Adversity, with an as∣sured confidence of a gracious Answer:</HI> Hezekiah <HI>and</HI> Isaiah <HI>no sooner Pray, but Speed;</HI> and <HI>another opportunity is now put into their hands, to return again with Praises in their mouths, to the Throne of Grace; for the Lord sent an Angel to cut off all the Mighty men of Ualour, and the Leaders and Captains in the Camp of the King of Assyria: So he re∣turned with shame of face to his own Land; and when he was come into the House of his god, they that came out of his own bowels, slew him there with the Sword,</HI> V. 21.</P>
<P>Whence we may note, <HI>That when Gods People cry to him, there is no staying the raising an</HI> Army <HI>or</HI> Money, <HI>or the Making or Providing Ammunion;</HI> but when they are in a <HI>Suffering condition,</HI> they <HI>dispatch</HI> a <HI>Messenger to Heaven</HI> in a <HI>moments time,</HI> to the <HI>Captain of their Sal∣vation,</HI> who <HI>himself was made perfect through Sufferings,</HI> Heb. 2. 10. And such a <HI>Messenger who can</HI> neither be stayed by the way, nor his <HI>Message intercepted,</HI> even the <HI>Spirit</HI> of <HI>Truth,</HI> who will tell the truth of <HI>their Cause,</HI> and help their <HI>Infirmities,</HI> and <HI>express</HI> their <HI>Con∣dition with groans that cannot be uttered;</HI> and he that searcheth <HI>the heart, knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit,</HI> Rom. 8. 26, 27. <HI>God is a free Agent, and cannot be limitted to any means, but acteth how, when, and which way he pleaseth.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>Hezekiah</HI> and <HI>Isaiah no sooner Pray, but an Angel is as soon dis∣patched into the Camp of Sennacherib;</HI> (<HI>for are they not all Ministring Spirits sent forth to Minister for those who shall be Heirs of Salvation,</HI> Heb. 1. 14.) And this Angel destroyes his Mighty men, Captains and men of Valour: <HI>Hezekiah</HI> we see spake truth, when he <HI>encouraged the People, saying, Be not dismayed at the King of Assyria; for there is more with us than with him; with him there is an Arm of flesh, but with us is the Lord</HI> our God, to help us and <HI>to fight our Battels,</HI> ver. 7. and 8.</P>
<P>Happy it is <HI>then</HI> with the People of God, <HI>when</HI> they can <HI>trust God for their Deliverance;</HI> and observe that Word of Command from the
<PB N="16" REF="19"/>
Captain of their Salvation, Mat. 24. 6. <HI>Then when they shall hear of Wars, and rumours of Wars, Nation against Nation, and Kingdom, against Kingdom, that then they be not troubled;</HI> but can take that <HI>good Advice</HI> that once <HI>Moses</HI> gave to <HI>Israel</HI> of old, <HI>Exod.</HI> 14. 13. Even <HI>to stand still</HI> and see <HI>the Salvation of God, which he will work for them.</HI></P>
<P>The Angel finisheth his work with <HI>speed,</HI> which causeth <HI>Sennacherib</HI> with <HI>shame</HI> &amp; <HI>Confusion of face,</HI> with speed to return into his own Land.</P>
<P>Whence we may note, That whilst men <HI>depend</HI> upon an <HI>Arm</HI> of <HI>flesh,</HI> upon every Defeat, their spirits are more or less <HI>dejected:</HI> whilst he that <HI>trusteth in the Lord, is not afraid</HI> of <HI>evil Tidings;</HI> for <HI>his heart</HI> is <HI>fixed,</HI> Psal. 112. 7. When <HI>Sennacheribs confidence</HI> in which he <HI>trust∣ed; viz.</HI> His <HI>Great men,</HI> his <HI>Captains,</HI> and his <HI>men</HI> of <HI>Valour</HI> were brought down, then <HI>Shame,</HI> as a Vail, begins to <HI>cover his face; whilst the Righteous are bold as a Lyon, and shall not be ashamed</HI> in <HI>the evil time,</HI> Psal. 37. 19. An Arm of flesh will fail; <HI>For all flesh is grass, and all the goodliness thereof as the Flower of the Field; the Grass withereth,</HI> and the <HI>Flower fadeth, because the Spirit of the Lord bloweth upon it: Surely, the People is grass,</HI> saith the Prophet, <HI>Isaiah</HI> 40. 6. and 7. Therefore the People of God trust in their God, because <HI>that in the Lord Jehovah is Everlasting strength, Isaiah</HI> 26. vers. 4.</P>
<P>The Text saith, That <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nnacherib,</HI> when he returned, he went in∣to the House of <HI>his god:</HI> Now, <HI>his god</HI> was one of the <HI>gods of the Hea∣thens,</HI> which had neither <HI>eyes</HI> to <HI>see,</HI> not <HI>ears</HI> to <HI>hear, hands</HI> to <HI>handle,</HI> nor <HI>feet</HI> to <HI>walk;</HI> and so uncapable of doing him good, as that he could not give <HI>good Advice,</HI> nor afford <HI>good Assistance,</HI> neither to <HI>him,</HI> nor to <HI>his People;</HI> yet such is his <HI>Zeal, notwithstanding his wickedness,</HI> as that he must into the <HI>House</HI> of this <HI>his god.</HI></P>
<P>Whence we may note, That the <HI>worst</HI> of <HI>men generally</HI> are <HI>under some Form of Worship,</HI> either to a <HI>false god,</HI> or to the true God <HI>after a false manner,</HI> in which usually they are <HI>very zealous,</HI> although in <HI>other things desperately wicked.</HI></P>
<P>Whence we may <HI>further note,</HI> That it is <HI>not Zeal under any Form,</HI> that <HI>makes that Form the true Form of Godliness;</HI> but it is the <HI>special Appointment of God in his Word of Truth, that is the onely and alone Way God will be worshipped in;</HI> in which he <HI>requireth men to be zealous:</HI> The Apostle <HI>Paul</HI> whilst he was in his <HI>unregenerate</HI> condition, his <HI>Zeal led</HI> the <HI>way,</HI> and <HI>marched</HI> in the <HI>Van,</HI> whilst his <HI>Knowledge lay behind in the Rear,</HI> which caused him so to make <HI>havock of the Church,</HI> as he him∣self confesseth, <HI>Phil.</HI> 3. 6. <HI>Gal.</HI> 1. 13. 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 15. 9. And saith he, <HI>Acts</HI> 26. 9. <HI>I verily thought with my self, that I ought to do many things, con∣trary to the Name of Jesus of Nazare<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h; which thing I did in</HI>
<PB N="17" REF="19"/>
<HI>Jerusalem, and many of the Saints did I shut up in Prison, having received Authority from the Chief Priests; and when they were put to death, I gave my voice against them,</HI> V. 10. <HI>And I punished them oft in every Syna∣gogue, and compelled them to Blaspheme; and being exceedingly mad against them, I persecuted them even unto strange Cities, v.</HI> 11. <HI>But</HI> this <HI>I did,</HI> saith he, <HI>Ignorantly</HI> in <HI>Unbelief,</HI> 1 Tim. 1. 13. And thus <HI>it</HI> fares often times with many in <HI>things about Religion,</HI> according to that <HI>Principle</HI> of the <HI>Church of Rome,</HI> that their <HI>Ignorance</HI> is the <HI>Mo∣ther of their Devotion.</HI> And is it not so in this our Day with thousands in this Land of our Nativity, that are of <HI>lewd, wicked,</HI> and <HI>debauched Conversations,</HI> yet are <HI>very zealous</HI> for their <HI>Common-Prayer?</HI> And though they will be <HI>Drunk</HI> many of them, and live in <HI>known abomina∣tions</HI> all the <HI>week long,</HI> yet such is their <HI>blind Zeal,</HI> that they must needs to their <HI>Common-Prayer</HI> on the <HI>Sunday,</HI> they think themselves undone else: This I know by <HI>Experience, it was so with my self for a long time together;</HI> but now through Mercy, I can say with the Apo∣stle <HI>Paul,</HI> 1 Cor. 15. 10. <HI>I thank God I am what I am; though some call me a Fannatick, or a mad man.</HI> I would not be mistaken, I do not here go to <HI>beat down Zeal; For it is good to be zealously affected alwayes in a good matter,</HI> Gal. 4. 18. But I would have <HI>Zeal <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oyned with Know∣ledge,</HI> and <HI>so set upon its proper and right Object;</HI> for the <HI>Jews,</HI> we know, <HI>had a Zeal to God, but not according to Knowledge,</HI> Rom. 10. 2. By which <HI>Zeal</HI> of theirs, they went about to establish a <HI>Righteousness of their own,</HI> and <HI>Contrary,</HI> or, in <HI>Opposition</HI> to <HI>Christ, who is made of God unto His, both Wisdom, Righteousness, Sanctification</HI> and <HI>Re∣demption,</HI> 1 Cor. 1. 30.</P>
<P>Thou, O King, as thou art now upon thy Work of Reformation, see thy <HI>Zeal run not before thy Knowledge,</HI> lest thou with the Apostle <HI>Paul, make havock of the Church of God, and waste it;</HI> (sure I am, thou wilt not want <HI>Perswaders thereunto:</HI>) But let me beg thee in Gods fear, first to <HI>Inform thy Judgement</HI> aright, Regulate that accord∣ing to the <HI>Rule of Gods Word;</HI> and then joyn Zeal to thy Knowledge, that so they may draw in one yoak together; and suffer me to bind this Pers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>vasion close to thy Conscience, for thy Eternal good, with that saying of the Apostle, <HI>James</HI> 4. 17. <HI>To him that knoweth to do well, and doth it not, to him it is sin.</HI></P>
<P>The next thing considerable in this one and twentie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h verse, is, <HI>That those that came out of his own Bowels, slew him with the Sword.</HI></P>
<P>Whence we may observe, That whilst men are acting against Gods People, out of a <HI>blind Zeal,</HI> to <HI>bring them at an under,</HI> and to <HI>root them out;</HI> God <HI>then appears</HI> for <HI>his People,</HI> and <HI>brings their enemies low,</HI> and
<PB N="18" REF="20"/>
many times maketh their nearest Relations to become their greatest Enemies: for it is in <HI>vain</HI> for men to <HI>fight against Christ;</HI> it is hard for them to <HI>kick against the pricks;</HI> yet <HI>thus inconsideratly do all those that fight against his People,</HI> and <HI>he looketh upon it as done to himself;</HI> for so saith the <HI>Lord from Heaven,</HI> Acts 9. 4. Saul, Saul, <HI>Why persecutest thou me?</HI> And he that <HI>receiveth you, receiveth me,</HI> Mat. 1. 40. And in as much as you did it not to one of <HI>the least of these, you did it not unto me,</HI> Mat. 25. 45.</P>
<P><HI>Thus</HI> in a most miraculous manner, &amp; <HI>without effusion</HI> of <HI>blood,</HI> God, on <HI>Hezekiah's</HI> part, <HI>delivered Hezekiah</HI> &amp; the Inhabitants of <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> and guided him on <HI>every side: And thus God hath done for thée, O King.</HI></P>
<P>And this was one <HI>great Cause why God expected</HI> an <HI>answerable Return</HI> from <HI>Hezekiah;</HI> and to me it seems as a Reason, <HI>Why thou, O King, shouldst render to the Lord according to his Benefits bestowed on thee;</HI> seeing God <HI>thus,</HI> or in such a <HI>miraculous manner,</HI> hath wrought such a <HI>Deliver∣ance</HI> for <HI>thée</HI> and <HI>thy Friends,</HI> without <HI>blood-shed.</HI></P>
<P>The next thing that God did for <HI>Hezekiah,</HI> was, He <HI>recovered</HI> him from a <HI>mortal distemper;</HI> for so saith the Text, <HI>ver.</HI> 24. <HI>In those dayes Hezekiah was sick to the death, and he prayed unto the Lord, and he spake unto him,</HI> and he gave him a Sign. This Text is but an abstract of what we have fully laid down to us, in 2 <HI>King.</HI> 20. 1, 2, 3. and <HI>Isa.</HI> 38. 1. The which Texts we must have some recourse to, if we intend to have a full discovery of what God did for <HI>Hezekiah,</HI> in 1 Kings 20. 1. The Text saith, <HI>In those dayes Hezekiah was sick unto death, and the Prophet Isaiah the son of Amos came to him and said unto him, Thus saith the Lord, Set thy House in order, for thou shalt dye, and not live;</HI> and <HI>Hezekiah turned his face towards the Wall, and prayed unto the Lord, and said, Remember now O Lord, I beseech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight; and Hezekiah wept sore. And it came to pass after Isaiah was gone out into the middle Court, that the Word of the Lord came unto him, saying, Turn again, and tell Hezekiah the Cap∣tain of my People; thus saith the Lord, the God of David thy Father, I have heard thy Prayers, I have séen thy Tears; Behold, I will heal thee, on the third day thou shalt go up to the House of the Lord.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Many things there are in this Passage worthy Consideration;</HI> and the first thing that I shall <HI>take notice of,</HI> is, <HI>That Hezekiah was sick unto Death, and he must</HI> set his House in order, for he <HI>must dye,</HI> and <HI>not live;</HI> yet <HI>Hezekiah prayed</HI> unto the Lord, and he <HI>healed him.</HI></P>
<P>Whence we may note, That <HI>many</HI> of the <HI>Resolves</HI> of God, con∣cerning the Sons and Daughters of men, are not <HI>absolutely peremptory,</HI>
<PB N="19" REF="20"/>
but many times <HI>conditional;</HI> for yet forty dayes, and <HI>Nineveh shall be destroyed;</HI> yet when <HI>Nineveh repents,</HI> God <HI>repents</HI> of the evil he in∣tended against them, <HI>Jonah</HI> 2. 4, 5, 10. And thus saith the Lord by his Prophet, <HI>Jer.</HI> 18. 7. <HI>At what instant I shall speak concerning a Nation, and concerning a Kingdom, to pluck up, and to pull down, and to destroy</HI> it; <HI>if that Nation against whom I have pronounced, turn from their evil; I will repent of the evil that I thought to do unto them.</HI> And <HI>at what instant I shall speak concerning a Nation, and concerning a Kingdom, to Build and to Plant it; if it do evil in my sight, that it obey not my voice, then will I repent of the Good wherewith I said I would Benefit them.</HI> So also saith the Lord to <HI>Ely</HI> (upon the misdemeanor of his Sons) by that man of God, 1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 2. 30. <HI>I said indeed, that thy House, and the House of thy Father should walk before me, for ever; but now the Lord saith, Be it far from me;</HI> for them that <HI>honour me, I will honour;</HI> and they that <HI>despise me,</HI> shall be <HI>lightly esteemed.</HI></P>
<P>Now know, O King, that God is about to <HI>Re-build</HI> and to <HI>Plant Thee and thy People again,</HI> and if thou and they shall <HI>answer God in acts of Obedience,</HI> and do that which is well-pleasing in his sight, he then will <HI>go on</HI> to perfect what he hath <HI>begun:</HI> but if Thou and thy People, and in especial this <HI>proud, Prodigal, vain-glorious,</HI> and <HI>most voluptuous City,</HI> that hath all this while sate as a Queen, and known no sorrow, shall not <HI>answer God in his Expectations;</HI> then be it known to <HI>thee</HI> and <HI>them,</HI> that God will <HI>repent</HI> him of the <HI>good</HI> he intended both to <HI>thée</HI> and <HI>them;</HI> and as he <HI>overturned</HI> thy <HI>Father,</HI> and <HI>those that overturned him,</HI> and hath been for some considerable time, <HI>overturning, overturning, over∣turning</HI> in this Land of thy Nativity; so know, O King, that he is as able to <HI>overturn thée</HI> as <HI>them,</HI> without thou and they make to him suitable Returns; <HI>for of a truth, God is no respecter of Persons, but in eve∣ry Nation,</HI> he <HI>that feareth him and worketh Righteousness,</HI> is <HI>accepted of him,</HI> Acts 10. 34, 35. Therefore in Gods fear consider thy Actings.</P>
<P>But to proceed, King <HI>Hezekiah</HI> prayes, and God heals: And thus whilst the <HI>Sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord, the Prayer of the upright is his delight,</HI> Prov. 15. 8. <HI>And Hezekiah turned his face to the Wall, and said, Remember I beseech thee, O Lord, how I have walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>He onely</HI> is likely to thrive at the Throne of Grace, <HI>who</HI> in his appeals to God can plead the uprightness of his heart, and the sincerity of his Soul; and whilst some are questioning, <HI>how God doth know, and whether there be Knowledge in the Most High?</HI> Psal. 73. 11. <HI>Hezekiah</HI> is earnestly begging the Searcher of all hearts, <HI>before whose eyes all things are naked and open,</HI> to remember the Actings of his former dayes. Happy it is
<PB N="20" REF="21"/>
with thy Soul, that in his <HI>sickness,</HI> can plead with God <HI>the good Actions of his health.</HI></P>
<P>Thus whilst <HI>Hezekiah</HI> is praying to the Lord, the Lord shews him∣self to be what in the Scriptures of Truth he is Recorded to be; even <HI>a God hearing Prayers,</HI> Psal. 65. 2. And <HI>Hezekiah</HI> must experience him to be such a one; <HI>For saith the Lord, Go, tell Hezekiah the Cap∣tain of my People, I have heard his Prayers, I have seen his Tears.</HI> God is a tender-hearted God, and when his People are moved to <HI>pas∣sion,</HI> upon a right account, he then shews himself a <HI>compassionate</HI> God to them, and this he did to <HI>Israel</HI> of old, when they were in <HI>Egypt</HI> under their hard Task-masters; for <HI>the Lord said, I have surely seen the affliction of my People which are in Egypt, and have heard their cry, by reason of their Task-masters; for I know their sorrows, and I am come down to deliver them,</HI> Exod. 3. 7, 8.</P>
<P>God is not onely said to <HI>hear the Prayers, and see the Tears of Heze∣kiah,</HI> but he is as ready to <HI>help;</HI> for so is his Promise, <HI>Psal.</HI> 50. 15. <HI>Call upon me</HI> in the day of trouble, <HI>I will deliver</HI> thee, <HI>and thou shalt glorifie me. A good refuge for all Gods People to flie to in time of distress.</HI></P>
<P>And here note, God doth not onely raise <HI>Hezekiah</HI> from his Bed of sickness, but he also promiseth to adde fifteen years to his dayes. <HI>Thus he giveth power to the faint, and to them that have no might, he encreaseth strength; even the youth shall faint and be weary, and young men shall utterly fail; but they that wait on the Lord, shall renew their strength; they shall mount up with wings of an Eagle; they shall run and not be weary; they shall walk and not be faint.</HI> Isai. 40. 31.</P>
<P>And seeing it is so then, O King, be perswaded to <HI>wait upon God,</HI> that so it may be a <HI>lengthening out</HI> of thy <HI>Tranquility;</HI> question with thine own Soul, <HI>whether God hath not added to thy dayes;</HI> remember with thankfulness <HI>the Hollow Oak, with all Gods Transactions towards thee in that juncture of time, when an Arm of flesh failed thee at</HI> Wor∣cester; not forgetting <HI>thy safe Passage in that little Vessel that Rides in thy constant view;</HI> and when thou lookest on that, suffer me to be thy Remembrancer, to perswade thee, that with <HI>thankfulness</HI> of <HI>heart,</HI> thou <HI>remember whence thy Deliverance came;</HI> and that thou give to God a suitable return, for that I am confident God expects from thee; and withall seriously to consider the <HI>sad Consequences of In∣gratitude:</HI> For <HI>Hezekiah</HI> rendred not again according to the Benefits bestowed upon him, but his heart was lifted up; <HI>therefore wrath was upon him, and upon Judah and Jerusalem.</HI></P>
<P>God doth not onely promise to <HI>heal Hezekiah,</HI> and <HI>to add fifteen years to his dayes;</HI> but further he <HI>giveth him</HI> (according to his own re∣quest)
<PB N="21" REF="21"/>
a <HI>Sign,</HI> and such an one, the like of which neither before nor since was known; for <HI>most miraculously</HI> he <HI>alters</HI> the <HI>course</HI> of the <HI>Hea∣vens,</HI> for the <HI>Sun who like a Bridegroom coming out of the Chamber, and rejoyceth as a strong man to run a Race,</HI> Psal. 19. 5. is by the great Power of God <HI>called back again</HI> fifteen Degrees.</P>
<P>Whence we may take notice of the <HI>great Condescention of the great God,</HI> for the <HI>satisfying</HI> his <HI>faithful ones.</HI> And this was his dealing with <HI>Gideon,</HI> Judges 6. who <HI>requires a Sign, that the Angel talked with him,</HI> v. 20. <HI>And the Angel put forth</HI> the end of his <HI>Staff that was in his hand,</HI> and touched the flesh, and the unleavened cakes that <HI>Gideon</HI> had provided, <HI>and there arose fire out of the Rock,</HI> and consumed them.</P>
<P>And again, when <HI>Gideon</HI> by Gods Appointment was to relieve <HI>Is∣rael</HI> from the hands of the <HI>Midianites, Amalekites,</HI> and the Children of the East, that were gathered together in the Valley of <HI>Jezrecl,</HI> Judges 6. 33. <HI>Gideon</HI> requires a <HI>Sign,</HI> if God would deliver <HI>Israel</HI> by his hands, ver. 36. And <HI>Gideon</HI> also propounds his own satisfaction; Behold, saith he, v. 37. <HI>I will put a Fleece of Wool in the Floor, and if the Dew be on the Fleece onely, and it be dry upon all the Earth besides, then shall I know that thou wilt save Israel by my hand, as thou hast said;</HI> and saith the Text, <HI>It was so,</HI> v. 38. <HI>For he rose up early in the morning, and thrust the Fleece together, and wringed out of the Fleece a Bowl full of water:</HI> Yet this will not fully satisfie <HI>Gideon,</HI> but he must come to the Lord, as once <HI>Abraham</HI> did, when he petiti∣oned for <HI>Sodom,</HI> Gen. 18. <HI>with an once more;</HI> for <HI>Gideon</HI> said unto God, Let not thine anger <HI>be hot against me, I will speak but this once; let me prove I pray thee but this once with the Fleece; let it now be dry one∣ly upon the Fléece, and upon all the ground let there be Dew; And God did so that night;</HI> for it was wet upon all the ground. <HI>It is good then for S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ls to be single-hearted to God, that God may be satisfactory to them.</HI></P>
<P>Thus having particularly discovered the manner of Gods <HI>merciful dealings</HI> towards <HI>Hezekiah;</HI> I shall now come to the words of my Text; wherein is briefly discovered <HI>Hezekiah's unthankful behaviour to God.</HI></P>
<P><HI>But Hezekiah rendred not again according to the Benefits bestowed upon him, but his heart was lifted up; therefore wrath was upon him, and upon Judah and Jerusalem.</HI></P>
<P>And because the main drift of the Spirit in the Text is, to discover <HI>Hezekiah's</HI> neglect, <HI>in not rendring</HI> to God, and the sad Consequences thereof; I shall therefore first consider what <HI>Rendring is,</HI> before I come to draw any teachable Conclusions from the Text.</P>
<P><HI>Rendring,</HI> then simply so considered, is none other, but a <HI>giving</HI>
<PB N="22" REF="22"/>
<HI>to God or Man that which is their due;</HI> for so saith the Spirit, 1 <HI>Chron.</HI> 16. 29. <HI>Give unto the Lord the Glory due unto his Name;</HI> and <HI>Rom.</HI> 13. 7. <HI>Render</HI> therefore to all men their <HI>dues, Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Custom to whom Custom, Fear to whom Fear, Honour to whom Honour;</HI> as if he should say, <HI>Give freely to God and Man that which be∣longeth to them,</HI> according to the saying of the Lord Christ himself, <HI>Mat.</HI> 22. 21. <HI>Give to Cesar the things that are Cesars, and to God the things that are Gods.</HI></P>
<P>There is also a <HI>Rendring</HI> spoken of in Scripture, <HI>by way</HI> of <HI>Requital, for some Benefit bestowed,</HI> or <HI>Injury done;</HI> and this is some∣times called <HI>Rendring,</HI> and sometimes <HI>Recompencing</HI> and <HI>Re∣quiting,</HI> as in that of <HI>Luke</HI> 14. 12, 14. <HI>When thou makest</HI> a <HI>Dinner, or a Supper, call not thy Friends, nor thy Brethren, nor thy Kins∣men, nor thy rich Neighbours, lest they also bid thee again, and a Recompence be made thee;</HI>—<HI>But call the Poor, the Maimed, the Blind, and the Halt, and thou shalt be blessed; for they cannot Recom∣pence or Requite thée;</HI> and in 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 5. 4. where Children and Ne∣phews are required to <HI>requite</HI> their Parents; and 1 <HI>Thes.</HI> 5. 15. where it is the Advice of the Spirit, that <HI>no man should render evil for evil to any man.</HI></P>
<P>So that there is a <HI>Rendring</HI> belongs to <HI>man from man,</HI> simply so con∣sidered, as they stand in <HI>such</HI> or <HI>such Relations;</HI> as <HI>Children</HI> to <HI>Parents, Servants</HI> to <HI>Masters, Wives</HI> to <HI>Husbands,</HI> or <HI>Subjects</HI> to <HI>Princes:</HI> And there is also a more <HI>Respective Rendring</HI> due to men, as they are <HI>Bene∣factors,</HI> or <HI>better than ordinary in those Relations;</HI> as <HI>from a Child</HI> to an <HI>indulgent Father, from</HI> a <HI>Servant</HI> to a <HI>very bountiful Master,</HI> from a <HI>Subject</HI> to his <HI>Priuce,</HI> as he is <HI>Wise</HI> and <HI>Prudentially careful, laying about him every way,</HI> for the <HI>better well-being</HI> of his Subjects; one that <HI>refuseth</HI> the <HI>way</HI> of <HI>Rehoboam</HI> the Son of <HI>Solomon,</HI> who <HI>threatned</HI> to make the <HI>burthens</HI> of his Subjects <HI>heavier</HI> and <HI>heavier,</HI> and to be <HI>worse</HI> to them than was his <HI>Father;</HI> 1 Kings 12. 11. But to such an one that will <HI>undo the heavy burthens,</HI> and <HI>let the oppressed go free,</HI> according to that of <HI>Isa.</HI> 51. 6<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> I say, to <HI>such</HI> a <HI>Father, Master</HI> and <HI>Prince,</HI> there is a more <HI>Tender, Respective, Affectionate Rendring due,</HI> and that by way of <HI>Requital,</HI> to <HI>answer the Love, Bounty</HI> and <HI>Care</HI> of such a <HI>Father, Macter</HI> or <HI>Prince.</HI></P>
<P>And this is that <HI>Rendring</HI> in my <HI>Text</HI> that God expecteth from <HI>Hezekiah,</HI> that as he had been a <HI>bountiful</HI> and a <HI>full-handed</HI> God to him; so he expected that <HI>Hezekiah, though a King,</HI> should have had his <HI>mouth filled with his Praises.</HI></P>
<P>For when the <HI>King of Babylon sent Ambassadors to him, to enquire of</HI>
<PB N="23" REF="22"/>
<HI>the Wonder that was done in his Land,</HI> 2 Chron. 32. 31. God <HI>expected</HI> that <HI>then</HI> he should have <HI>shewed</HI> the Ambassadours, how <HI>miraculous God had been in delivering him from his Enemies, and recovering</HI> him; and in <HI>satisfying</HI> his <HI>Request,</HI> in <HI>causing the Sun to run retrograde,</HI> in token of the <HI>certainty</HI> of his <HI>recovery,</HI> and of the fifteen years <HI>addition</HI> to his dayes; by which means God would have been <HI>glorified in the eyes of the Heathen;</HI> which is <HI>that</HI> that God <HI>requireth,</HI> That his Peo∣ple should <HI>sing forth the Honour of his Name, and make his Praise glorious,</HI> Psal. 66. 2. <HI>And also saith the Lord by the Prophet,</HI> Isai. 42. 12. <HI>Let them give glory unto the Lord, and declare his Praise in the Islands.</HI></P>
<P><HI>A good Lesson for thee to learn, O King, that when Ambassadours are sent from forreign Princes, to Congratulate thy condition, that then thou remember before them, to glorifie that God, and set forth his Praise, who hath been so miraculously bountiful unto thee.</HI></P>
<P>But <HI>Hezekiah</HI> rendred not again according to his Benefits bestowed upon him, but his heart was lifted up; therefore wrath fell upon him, and upon <HI>Judah</HI> and <HI>Jerusalem.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Quest.</HI> But here it may be demanded, when a person may be said, to <HI>render duely to God.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> To this I Answer, A person may <HI>then</HI> be said to <HI>make suitable Returns,</HI> or <HI>duely</HI> to <HI>render</HI> to God, when in the <HI>Relation</HI> he <HI>standeth in,</HI> he shall as much as in him lieth, <HI>Act faithfully both to God and man,</HI> according to the mind of God, whether they be Men or Women, as they stand in the Relations of <HI>Servants</HI> or <HI>Masters, Children</HI> or <HI>Pa∣rents, Wives</HI> or <HI>Husbands, Subjects</HI> or <HI>Princes:</HI> And because the sub∣ject matter of my Text is concerning <HI>Prince</HI> and <HI>People,</HI> I shall not stand to particularize the <HI>duty</HI> of the other <HI>Relations,</HI> but shall as briefly as I may, come to a discovery of what I know from the Scrip∣tures, to be the Mind of God in those Relations that concern my Text.</P>
<P>And first of the duty of a <HI>Subject</HI> to his <HI>Prince;</HI> a <HI>Subject</HI> may pro∣perly be said <HI>duely</HI> to <HI>render</HI> unto God, when according to the saying of the Lord Christ, Mat. 22. 20. <HI>He doth give</HI> to <HI>Cesar the things that are Cesars, and to God the things that are Gods;</HI> when he doth that in the <HI>Worship of God</HI> that is <HI>agreeable</HI> to the <HI>Mind of God,</HI> revealed in that <HI>plain Directory,</HI> the <HI>Holy Scriptures</HI> of <HI>Truth:</HI> And when accord∣ing to that Rule also he doth <HI>render</HI> to his <HI>Prince Tribute, Custom, Fear</HI> and <HI>Honour,</HI> according to the direction of the Spirit, <HI>Rom.</HI> 13. 7. A more full discovery hereof is laid down in my Declaration.</P>
<P>And secondly, A Prince may properly be said to <HI>render duely to</HI>
<PB N="24" REF="23"/>
<HI>God,</HI> when he doth also <HI>follow</HI> the <HI>direction</HI> of the <HI>same Spirit</HI> in the <HI>Directory;</HI> who saith, 2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 23. 3. <HI>He that Ruleth over men, must be just, Ruling in the fear of God.</HI> This <HI>fear of God,</HI> is that which made good <HI>Nehemiah,</HI> when he was <HI>appointed Governour over the Land</HI> of <HI>Judah, neither he nor his Brethren not to eat the Bread of the Go∣vernour,</HI> Nehamiah 5. 14. For saith he, v. 15. <HI>The former Governours that were before me, were chargeable to the People, and had taken of them Bread and Wine, besides forty shekels of Silver; yea, even their Ser∣vants bare rule over the People;</HI> But saith he, <HI>So did not I:</HI> And he <HI>addeth this as a Reason, Because of the fear of God:</HI> And this is that which the Wise man telleth us, is the sum or substance of all that is required from Man, in the twelfth Chapter of his <HI>Ecclesiastes,</HI> and the thirteenth verse. Let us hear the Conclusion of the whole matter, <HI>Fear God,</HI> and <HI>keep his commandments; for this</HI> (saith he) <HI>is the whole duty of Man:</HI> and so saith the Prophet, <HI>Micah</HI> 6. 8. <HI>He that shewed thee, O man, what is good. And what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do justly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</HI></P>
<P><HI>Pritnces, Rulers, Governors</HI> and <HI>Magistrates then,</HI> are required to do <HI>tha work</HI> for which they are set up, for they are Gods Vice-ge∣rents, set up by him for the <HI>due Administration of Justice,</HI> and <HI>not to be a terrour to good works, but to the evil; and are</HI> continually <HI>to attend upon that very thing,</HI> Rom. 13. 1, 3, 4, 6.</P>
<P>In that Antient History of the Succession o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the <HI>Saxon</HI> Monarchs, page 370. It is Recorded to the yet lasting fame of <HI>Edgar,</HI> some∣times a <HI>King</HI> of this Island, That he was so endowed with that <HI>Hea∣ven-bred,</HI> and <HI>most Heroick Principle of the due Administration of Ju∣stice;</HI> as in his Circuits he took so strick an account of the <HI>due Exe∣cution of his Laws,</HI> and of the <HI>Demeanour</HI> of his <HI>great Men,</HI> and <HI>espe∣cially</HI> of his <HI>Judges,</HI> as that he <HI>severely punished them,</HI> as often as he found the <HI>Execution of their Places ballanced either with bribery,</HI> or <HI>par∣tiality:</HI> So that (saith the Story) there was <HI>never less Robbery, Deceit</HI> nor <HI>Oppression,</HI> than in the Reign of this <HI>worthy</HI> King.</P>
<P>Therefore let me beg thee, O King, as thou tenderest thy own good, both here and hereafter, <HI>Rule with Diligence,</HI> and with <HI>King Edgar</HI> let After-ages know to thy lasting Praise, that thou <HI>hadst a delight to do thy Subjects good,</HI> in <HI>seeking Judgement,</HI> in <HI>Relieving</HI> the <HI>Oppressed,</HI> in <HI>Judging</HI> the <HI>Fatherless,</HI> and in <HI>Pleading</HI> for the <HI>Widow,</HI> in <HI>being a ter∣rour to Evil Works,</HI> and in shewing thy self a <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of them that do well. Measure thy Subjects Actions by a direct Rule:</HI> And as thou art a <HI>King</HI> over <HI>three Kingdoms,</HI> such as make much ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> about their
<PB N="25" REF="23"/>
<HI>Christianity,</HI> see that their Actions be <HI>Christ-like;</HI> for the assuming either the Title or Form of Christianity cannot do it; for <HI>from such as have not the Power of Godliness, there ought to he by the People of God a turning away,</HI> 2 Tim. 3. 5. For, <HI>every one that nameth the Name of Christ, is to depart from iniquity,</HI> 2 Tim. 2. 19. And it ought to be their <HI>onely</HI> care, to have their <HI>Conversation as becometh the Gospel of Christ,—striving together for the Faith of the Gospel,</HI> Phil. 1. 27 Not for the Promotion of <HI>Stage-Playes, Dancings, May-games,</HI> and <HI>Pastimes;</HI> for Christians are to <HI>abstain from all appearance of evil,</HI> 1 Thes. 5. 22. <HI>And as Pilgrims and Strangers they are to abstain from fleshly lusts, which war against the Soul,</HI> 1 Pet. 2. 11. <HI>And the lust of the flesh, the lust of the eye, and the pride of life, is not of the Fa∣ther, but of the World,</HI> and must <HI>perish with the World,</HI> 1 Joh. 2. 16.</P>
<P>Be <HI>careful</HI> therefore, I beseech thee, O King, of the <HI>Actions</HI> of thy <HI>Subjects,</HI> it stands thee in hand <HI>so to do;</HI> for a <HI>fruitful Land God turn∣eth into barrenness, for the wickedness of them that dwell therein,</HI> Psal. 107. 34. Yea, and thou maist fare the worse for it too; <HI>For</HI> the <HI>Transgression of a Land, many are the Princes thereof; But by a man of understanding and Knowledge, the state thereof shall be prolonged,</HI> saith the Wisest of the Sons of men, <HI>Prov.</HI> 28, 2. <HI>O then, in the fear of him that accepteth not the person of Princes, nor regardeth the rich more then the poor,</HI> Job 34. 19. <HI>In the fear of him that leadeth Princes away spoi∣led, and overthroweth the strength of the Mighty; that poureth contempt up∣on Princes, and weakneth the Mighty;</HI> that <HI>taketh away</HI> the <HI>heart</HI> of the <HI>Chief of the People</HI> of the <HI>Earth, aud causeth them to wander</HI> in <HI>a Wil∣derness, where there is no way,</HI> Job 12. 19, 21, 24. <HI>In the fear of him</HI> that bringeth <HI>Princes</HI> to <HI>nothing, and maketh the Judges of the Earth, as vanity,</HI> Isai. 40. 23. <HI>In the fear of that God, that hath done such great things for thee,</HI> be perswaded for thine own good, to render to him according to his Mercy bestowed, in seeing the <HI>due Administration of Justice without respect of persons;</HI> that so thou mayest <HI>Relieve</HI> the <HI>poor oppressed of thy People,</HI> that of a long <HI>time</HI> have <HI>groaned</HI> under the <HI>Ad∣ministration of Male-Justice.</HI></P>
<P>And know, O King, that as thou art to do <HI>justly;</HI> so thou art required to love <HI>Mercy,</HI> it is that which God accepteth before Sacrifice; for so saith the Prophet, <HI>Hos.</HI> 6. 6. For <HI>I desired Mercy, and not Sacrifice, and the knowledge of God more than Burnt-offerings;</HI> for by <HI>Mercy</HI> and <HI>Truth Iniquity is purged, and by the fear of God men depart from evil,</HI> Prov. 16. 6. For <HI>Mercy</HI> and <HI>Truth preseve the King, and his Throne is upholden by Mercy;</HI> For <HI>he that followeth after Righteousness and</HI>
<PB N="26" REF="24"/>
<HI>Mercy; findeth Life, Righteousness and Honour,</HI> Prov. 21. 21. <HI>A good man is Merciful and lendeth, and his Seed shall be blessed,</HI> Psal. 37. 26. Yea, <HI>Blessed are the Merciful, for they shall obtain Mercy,</HI> Mat. 5. 7. But <HI>he shall have Iudgement without Mercy, that hath shewed no Mercy; And Mercy</HI> rejoyceth <HI>against Judgement,</HI> James 2. 13. The neglect of <HI>shewing Mercy,</HI> is that which caused the wrath of God to burn hot against <HI>Israel</HI> of old, <HI>Zech.</HI> 7. 9. For <HI>thus spake the Lord of Hosts, saying, Execute true Judgement, and shew Mercy and Compassion</HI> every <HI>man to his Brother, and oppress not the Widow, nor the Fatherless, the stranger, nor the Poor; and let none of you imagine evil against his Brother in his heart: But they refused to hearken, and plucked away the shoulder, and stopped their ears that they should not hear,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>Therefore came a great wrath from the Lord of Hosts,</HI> V. 12.</P>
<P>Then be perswaded, O King, to <HI>shew Acts of Mercy,</HI> thou hast Objects <HI>enough to exercise it upon;</HI> and know, That <HI>pure Religion and undesiled before God and the Father, is this, To visit the Fatherless and Widows in their Affliction,</HI> James 1. 27. <HI>Not to make Fatherless and Widows, to bring them to Affliction.</HI> And in thy shewing Mercy, take the Advice of the Spirit of God, in <HI>Rom.</HI> 12. 8. <HI>To do it readily, and with Cheerfulness.</HI></P>
<P>Thou hast begun already to tread in this Way, in thy Act of Ob∣livion, let not the malicious endeavours of any, though never so great, pervert thy steps; for it is one of <HI>Zions</HI> Paths.</P>
<P>A third thing that is required of thee, O King, is, That as thou art <HI>to do Justly,</HI> and <HI>to love mercy;</HI> so <HI>also,</HI> to <HI>walk humbly with thy God.</HI></P>
<P>But here it may be demanded, when a person may be said to <HI>walk humbly with God?</HI></P>
<P>To this I Answer; A man may <HI>then</HI> be properly said, to <HI>walk hum∣bly with his God, when</HI> he goeth not <HI>before God,</HI> or <HI>without God</HI> in his Actions; but that in all his undertakings, he doth that which is <HI>required of him by God,</HI> in order to his <HI>humble obedience to God,</HI> whe∣ther it be in the <HI>Worship and Service of God,</HI> or in his <HI>Actings towards men:</HI> Thus <HI>Enoch walked with God three hundred years,</HI> Gen. 5. 22. And <HI>Enoch</HI> walking with God, God was so well pleased therewith, as that he <HI>exempted him from the Pangs of Death;</HI> for so saith the Text, V. 24. <HI>And</HI> Enoch <HI>walked with God, and was not; for God took him: Enoch</HI> walked with God <HI>faithfully; for without Faith it is Impossible to please God,</HI> Heb. II. 6. And we find him so <HI>Recorded</HI> in <HI>that Catalogue</HI> of <HI>faithful ones,</HI> Heb. II. 5. <HI>By faith Enoch was translated, that he should not see death, and was not found, because God had translated him; and</HI>
<PB N="27" REF="24"/>
<HI>before he was translated, he had this Testimony, That he pleased God.</HI></P>
<P>Thus <HI>Noah</HI> also <HI>walked with God,</HI> Gen. 6. 9. And when a <HI>World of wicked Men and Women,</HI> for their <HI>ungodliness must be drowned; the Lord said unto</HI> Noah, <HI>Come thou, and all thy House into the Ark; for thee have I seen Righteous before me in this Generation,</HI> Gen. 6. 1.</P>
<P>Thus also <HI>Zacharias</HI> and <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> the Father and Mother of <HI>John the Baptist,</HI> who walked with God, Luke 1. 5, 6. <HI>who were both righte∣ous before God, walking in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord, blameless.</HI></P>
<P>So that I say, To <HI>walk humbly with God,</HI> is to <HI>follow God fully</HI> in <HI>all</HI> his <HI>Laws, Statutes, Ordinances,</HI> and <HI>Appointments.</HI></P>
<P>And thus the <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>People of God,</HI> are required to be <HI>Followers of God, as dear Children,</HI> Eph. 5. 1. That as <HI>Children</HI> are to <HI>follow</HI> the <HI>Directions</HI> and <HI>Appointments</HI> of their <HI>Earthly Parents;</HI> so <HI>Gods People</HI> should <HI>follow</HI> the <HI>Directions</HI> and <HI>Appointments</HI> of their <HI>Heavenly Father;</HI> and should <HI>walk</HI> in the <HI>foot-steps</HI> of the <HI>Flock</HI> of God, <HI>gone before;</HI> who run <HI>neither before</HI> nor <HI>without God;</HI> but with the Prophet <HI>David, Psal.</HI> 119. 32. in the <HI>Laws, Statutes, Ordinances</HI> and <HI>Appointments</HI> of God: <HI>Thus they walked humbly with their God.</HI> So that this is that which I would willingly lay before thee, O King; and also beg and entreat thee for thine own good, seriously to consider of, That to <HI>walk humbly with God,</HI> is <HI>not to walk in any way,</HI> but in <HI>that which is well-pleasing to God; in that way which is</HI> by <HI>himself directed, for his to walk in;</HI> for persons <HI>cannot</HI> be said <HI>to be no more Forreigners</HI> and <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rangers, unless</HI> they <HI>become fellow Citizens with the Saints, and of the Houshold of God; being built upon the foundation of the Prophets and Apostles, Jesus Christ himself being the chief Corner stone,</HI> Eph. 2. 19, 20. By which means <HI>onely, they grow up an Holy Temple in the Lord, in whom they also are builded together for an Habitation of God, through the Spirit,</HI> ver. 21, 22.</P>
<P>Then consider thy standing, O King, and with <HI>Hezekiah</HI> purge out the filthiness of thy Holy Things, in order to thy walking <HI>humbly with thy God;</HI> in order to thy <HI>Rendring duely to God,</HI> for thy great Mer∣cies received, considering the <HI>danger</HI> of <HI>not Rendring.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>Hezekiah</HI> rendred not again according to the Benefit done un∣to him, for his heart was lifted up; <HI>therefore wrath was upon him, and upon Iudah and Ierusalem.</HI></P>
<P>Thus having shewed in some measure the Occasion of the words of my Text; I shall now come to the handling of the words themselves.</P>
<P>But <HI>Hezekiah</HI> rendred not again according to the Benefit done unto
<PB N="28" REF="25"/>
him, for his heart was lifted up; therefore there was wrath upon him, and upon <HI>Judah</HI> and <HI>Jerusalem.</HI></P>
<P>The words in themselves contain these four Particulars.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. Gods Benefits bestowed upon <HI>Hezekiah.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. <HI>Hezekiah's</HI> Unthankfulness to God.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. The Reason of <HI>Hezekiah's</HI> Unthankfulness.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. The sad Consequences of his Unthankfulness.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. Gods Benefits bestowed upon <HI>Hezekiah,</HI> in these words, <HI>Accord∣cording to the Benefit done unto him.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. <HI>Hezekiah's</HI> Unthankfulness to God, in these words, <HI>But Heze∣kiah rendred not again.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>3. The Reason of <HI>Hezekiah's</HI> not rendring, in these words, <HI>For his heart was lifted up.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>4. The sad Conseqnences of <HI>Hezekiah's</HI> not rendring. And they are two fold, and implyed in these words:</ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<ITEM>1. <HI>Therefore there was wrath upon him;</HI> And,</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. <HI>Upon Iudah</HI> and <HI>Ierusalem.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>But <HI>Hezekiah</HI> rendred not again according to the Benefit done unto him, for his heart was lifted up; therefore there was wrath upon him, and upon <HI>Judah</HI> and <HI>Jerusalem.</HI></P>
<P>Thus having laid down the <HI>Occasion</HI> of the <HI>words of the Text,</HI> and the <HI>Particulars contained in the Text;</HI> I shall now proceed to lay down, what <HI>teachable Conclusions may be drawn from the Text;</HI> which are these three:</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. <HI>That God requires suitable Returns for Benefits bestowed, though from the greatest of Men or Nations; upon the neglect whereof, God punish∣eth without respect of persons.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. <HI>That many times God punisheth a People, for the miscarriages of their Governours, whether in Church or State, or in a particular Family.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>3. <HI>That outward enjoyments many times do so affect the heart of man, as that they lift it up, even to the forgetting of God, and to their own ruine.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>To the first of these, <HI>That God requires suitable Returns for Benefits bestowed, though from the great est of Men or Nations; upon the neglect whereof, God punisheth without respect of persons.</HI></P>
<P>King <HI>David,</HI> I presume, was well acquainted with the Truth of this Assertion, which made him so earnestly enquire, what he should render to God, in <HI>Psal.</HI> 116. after a full Declaration of what God had particularly done for his Soul; he oryeth out, ver. 12. <HI>What shall I render to the Lord, for all his Benefits bestowed upon me?</HI> And in v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>13.
<PB N="29" REF="25"/>
and 14. he gives in his Resolution, <HI>I will,</HI> saith he, <HI>take the Cup of Salvation, and call upon the Name of the Lord; I will pay my Vowes unto the Lord now, in the presence of all his People;</HI> and in <HI>Psal.</HI> 58. 12. <HI>These Vowes are upon me, O God, I will render Praises unto thee.</HI></P>
<P>But for the proof of this point; consider, <HI>Nebuchadnezzar</HI> King of <HI>Babylon,</HI> who dreamed a Dream, which to him was very terrible; in∣somuch, that <HI>his spirit was troubled, and his sleep brake from him,</HI> Dan. 2. 1. Then the <HI>King commanded to call the</HI> Magicians, <HI>and the</HI> Astrologers, <HI>and the</HI> Sorcerers, <HI>and the</HI> Caldeans, <HI>to shew the King his Dream;</HI> to whom <HI>he promised great Rewards, if they could shew him the Dream, and the Interpretation,</HI> (for it was gone from the King) <HI>But if they could not, then he threatned death to them, and ruine to their Houses,</HI> vers. 6, 7, 8, 9. The which they could not do; and thereupon a <HI>Com∣mand went out from the King, to slay them:</HI> The Executioners of whose <HI>Will</HI> sought <HI>Daniel</HI> and his <HI>Fellows</HI> also to <HI>slay them.</HI> Then <HI>Daniel enquired of Arioch the Captain of the Kings Guard, the Reason of the hastiness of the Decree from the King, who telling him the matter; Daniel went in to the King, and desired time that he might shew the King both the Dream, and the Interpretation;</HI> the which being granted, he sudden∣ly after came and told it the King, V. 31. <HI>Thou, O King, sawest, and behold a great Image; this great Image, whose brightness was excellent, stood before thee, and his form was terrible.</HI></P>
<P><HI>This Images Head was of fine Gold, his Breast and his Armes of Silver, his Belly and his Thighs of Brass, his Leggs of Iron, his Feet part of Iron, and part of Clay; Thou sawest till that a Stone was cut out without hands, which smote the Image upon his Féet, that were part of Iron and part of Clay, and brake them to pieces.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Then was the Iron, the Clay, the Brass, the Silver, and the Gold broken to pieces together, and became then as the Chaff of the Summer Threshing-floors,</HI> and the <HI>wind carried them away, that no place was found for them; and the Stone that smote the Image, became a great Mountain, and filled the whole Earth. This is the Dream</HI> (said Daniel) <HI>and I will tell the Interpretation thereof before the King.</HI></P>
<P>THOU <HI>O King, art a King</HI> of <HI>Kings, for the God of Heaven hath given thee a Kingdom, Power, and Strength, and Glory; and wheresoever the Children of men dwell, the Beasts of the Field, and the Fowls of the Heaven hath he given into thine hand, and hath made thee Ruler over them all; Thou art this Head of Gold.</HI></P>
<P>By all which we see, that God had done very much for <HI>Nebuchad∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> and made him <HI>King</HI> of <HI>Kings,</HI> and <HI>higher than all the Kings of the Earth:</HI> Yet when <HI>Nebuchadnezzar rendreth not to God according</HI>
<PB N="30" REF="26"/>
<HI>to the Benefits bestowed,</HI> God takes him down from all his Pomp; when <HI>Nebuchadnezzar forgat God that made him so great,</HI> and begins to <HI>Sa∣crifice to his own Net, as he did,</HI> Dan. 4. 30. For said the King, <HI>Is not this Great Babylon, that</HI> I <HI>have builded for the House of my Kingdom, by the Might of my Power, and for the Honour of my Majesty?</HI> Thus whilst he was <HI>glorying himself,</HI> instead of <HI>glorifying God,</HI> God takes him down; for so saith the Text, V. 31. <HI>Whilst the word was in the Kings mouth, there fell a voice from Heaven, saying, O King Nebuchadnezzar, to thée it is spoken, the Kingdom is departed from thée, and they shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the Beasts of the Field; they shall make thee to eat grass as Oxen, and seven times shall pass over thee, until thou know that the Most High Ruleth in the Kingdom of men, and giveth it to whom he will;</HI> and saith the Text, V. 33. <HI>The same hour was the thing fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar.</HI> So that in him we see the <HI>Assertion</HI> made good, <HI>That God requires suitable returns for mercies bestowed, though from the greatest of Men or Nations.</HI> This man was <HI>so great,</HI> as that there was <HI>none greater;</HI> for he was <HI>over All;</HI> not a King over some <HI>few Countries,</HI> or an <HI>Emperour</HI> over <HI>seven Nations,</HI> but a <HI>Monarch,</HI> one that had an <HI>unlimited</HI> and an <HI>universal Power,</HI> V. 36. Yet when he comes to <HI>walk contrary to God, God walks contrary to him;</HI> when he refuseth <HI>to glorifie God,</HI> God will be glorified <HI>upon him.</HI></P>
<P>The like we may see in <HI>King Saul,</HI> 1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 15. The <HI>Prophet Samuel</HI> came to him, and appointed him his work from God; and in his so doing, he first layes before him <HI>what God had done for him;</HI> and giveth it in as a Reason, why <HI>Saul</HI> should perform the Will <HI>of God;</HI> for saith he, V. 1. <HI>The Lord sent me to Anoint thee to be King over his People, over</HI> Israel; <HI>Therefore hearken thou unto the voice of the Word of the Lord; Thus saith the Lord, I remember what Amalek did to Israel, how he laid wait for him in the way, as he came up out of the Land of Egypt; now go and smite Amalek, and utterly destroy All that they have, and spare them not, but utterly destroy both Man and Woman, Infant and Suckling, Ox and Shéep, Camel and Asse, Amalek</HI> lay in wait, to have <HI>destroyed Israel;</HI> now <HI>God takes Israels Cause in hand, and Amalek must be</HI> utterly <HI>cut off. It is good for the People of God, to let God alone with his own Work; for vengeance is mine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> and I will repay</HI> it, <HI>saith the Lord,</HI> Rom. 12. 19. And Gods <HI>time</HI> is the best <HI>time to revenge in;</HI> for <HI>so</HI> saith the Lord by his Prophet, <HI>Zephaniah</HI> 3. 8. <HI>Wait ye upon me, untill the day that, I rise up to the prey; for my determination is, to gather the Nations, that I may assemble the Kingdoms, to pour upon them mine Indignation, even all my fierce Anger;</HI> for, <HI>All the Earth shall be de∣voured</HI>
<PB N="31" REF="26"/>
<HI>with the fire of my Jealousie:</HI> for, saith the Prophet, <HI>It is the day of the Lords vengeance, and the year of Recompences, for the Controversie of Zion,</HI> Isai. 34. 8. And saith the Lord, <HI>I am jealous for Jerusalem and for Zion, with a great jealousie,</HI> Zach. 1. 14. <HI>For precious in the sight of the Lord, is the death of his Saints,</HI> Psal. 116. 15. and Psal. 9. 12. <HI>When he maketh Iniquision for blood, he remembreth them, and forgetteth not the Cry of the humble.</HI> Had <HI>Israel</HI> been the <HI>Revenge</HI> of his <HI>own quarrel,</HI> it had not made so much for <HI>Israels comfort,</HI> neither would <HI>Amalek</HI> have had his <HI>deserved due; Israel</HI> might have <HI>under-done the Work;</HI> for <HI>Israel</HI> knew not the <HI>bent</HI> of <HI>Amaleks spirit,</HI> so well as <HI>he</HI> that <HI>took</HI> the <HI>Work</HI> in <HI>hand;</HI> for God sees not as Man sees, Man onely knows the <HI>outward act,</HI> but God also the <HI>intention</HI> and <HI>thought of the heart;</HI> God without all Question knew that <HI>Amalek intended</HI> the <HI>utter ruine of Israel;</HI> and therefore <HI>Amalek</HI> must be <HI>utterly destroyed:</HI> For God is a Righteous God, and commonly deals with men by the <HI>Law of Retaliation; for Adoni-bezek</HI> said, <HI>Threescore and ten Kings having their Thumbs</HI> and <HI>their great Toes cut off, gathered their Meat under my Table; as I have done so God hath done to me,</HI> Judges 1. 7. And <HI>Nathan</HI> said unto <HI>David,</HI> 2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 12. 9. <HI>Thou hast done evil in the sight of the Lord, thou hast killed</HI> Uriah <HI>the</HI> Hittite <HI>with the Sword, and hast taken his Wife to be thy Wife; now therefore the Sword shall never depart from thine House,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>And I will take thy Wives before thine eyes, and give them to thy Neighbour, and he shall lye with them in the sight of the Sun; for thou didst this secretly, but I will do this before all Israel, and before the Sun.</HI> And the Prophet <HI>Samuel</HI> also said unto <HI>King Agag,</HI> 1 Sam. 15. 33. <HI>As thy Sword hath made Women Childless, so shall thy Mother be Childless among Women; and Samuel hewed Agag in pieces before the Lord.</HI></P>
<P>It is good for men <HI>then</HI> in all their undertakings, to do <HI>to others,</HI> as they <HI>would have others to do unto them:</HI> And this is that <HI>golden Rule,</HI> that the Lord Christ himself layes down, <HI>Mat.</HI> 7. 12. <HI>All things whatsoever ye would that men should do unto you, do ye even so unto them; for this is the Law and the Prophets:</HI> And that he might the better be∣speak his People to a strict Observation of this Lesson, he requires them in the first and second verses, <HI>Not to judge, lest they be judged,</HI> for saith he, <HI>with what judgement ye judge, ye shall be judged; and with what measure ye met, it shall be measured to you again:</HI> The perfect Law of Retaliation.</P>
<P>I am the willinger to say the more to this, though I am upon a <HI>di∣gression,</HI> because, if possible, I might keep others from <HI>transgression;</HI> for there are many in this our day, I know, that are ready and willing
<PB N="32" REF="27"/>
to <HI>run head-long</HI> to the <HI>ruine of the People of God</HI> here, though it be to the <HI>ruine of their own Souls hereafter, and that to Eternity;</HI> for so saith the Lord Christ himself, <HI>Mat. 25. 41. Then shall the King say to them on his left hand, Depart from me, ye cursed, into Everlasting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels; for when I was an Hungry, ye gave me no meat; I was Thirsty, and ye gave me no Drink; I was a Stranger, and ye took me not in; Naked, and ye cloathed me not; Sick, and in Prison, and ye visited me not; for, inasmuch as ye did it not to one of these little ones, v. 45. or the least of-these my brethren, ye did</HI> it <HI>not unto me,</HI> v. 40.</P>
<P>Whence I would have all <HI>persecuting spirits</HI> to take notice, That if <HI>Christ at that great day will be so strict upon men, for omitting the doing of that good, that they might have done to the People of God; that he will be far more stricter with them, for doing Acts of violence against them;</HI> for God is very tender of his People, however men esteem of them; and so saith the Prophet, <HI>Zach.</HI> 2. 8. <HI>He that toucheth you, toucheth the Apple of his eye.</HI> God hath been Eminent in his Judgements of late dayes: And therefore let all <HI>persecuting spirits, hear,</HI> and <HI>fear,</HI> and <HI>tremble,</HI> for the Lord will appear mightily for his People.</P>
<P>But to return to our matter: King <HI>Saul</HI> being fully Commissionated for this work of <HI>Amaleks</HI> destruction; and being perswaded to the faithful performance thereof by <HI>Samuel,</HI> upon the account of what Benefits God had done for him; <HI>yet Saul rendred not according to the Benefits bestowed upon him;</HI> and therefore he was looked upon as a <HI>Rebel astainst God,</HI> 1 Sam. 15. 23. in that he saved the best of the Sheep and Oxen, and King <HI>Agag</HI> alive; and this caused God to rend the King∣dom from him, v. 28. And this is that, together with his going to the Witch of <HI>Endor,</HI> that also cost him his life; for so saith the Text, 1 <HI>Chron. 10. 13. So Saul died for his transgression, which he committed against the Lord, even against the Word of the Lord, which he kept not; and also for asking Counsel of one that had a familiar spirit, to enquire of it:</HI> So that in <HI>Saul</HI> also we see the <HI>Assertion</HI> made good, That God re∣quires suitable returns for Benefits bestowed, though from the greatest of Men or Nations; upon the neglect whereof, God punisheth with∣out respect of Persons.</P>
<P>It is neither the <HI>Name, Dignity</HI> nor <HI>Power</HI> of the <HI>greatest of Kings,</HI> that can <HI>exempt</HI> them <HI>from the sin-revenging hand of God; for Tophet is ordained of old,</HI> saith the Prophet, <HI>Isaiah 30. 33. yea, for the King it is prepared, he hath made it deep and large; the pile thereof is fire and much wood; the Breath of the Lord like a stream of Brimstone doth kindle it.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="33" REF="27"/>Neither is it the <HI>greatness of a Nation</HI> or <HI>a People,</HI> that can excuse them, if they be found sinning against God; witness <HI>Israel of old, a Nation</HI> like the <HI>Sands of the Sea shore,</HI> or <HI>as the Stars in the Firmament for number;</HI> yea, the Lords <HI>Portion;</HI> for so saith the Text, <HI>Deut.</HI> 32. 9. The Lords <HI>People are his Portion, Jacob is the Lot of his Inheritance; the Vineyard that his own right hand hath planted,</HI> Psal. 80. 15. Such as in their day had the highest Priviledges of any Nations under the Hea∣vens; for so saith the Prophet <HI>David, Psal. 147. 19, 20. He shewed his Word unto Jacob, his Statutes and his Iudgements unto Israel, he hath not dealt so with any Nation:</HI> And <HI>as for his Iudgements, they have not known them;</HI> yet for all <HI>this,</HI> by reason of <HI>Gods sin-revenging hand upon them,</HI> the Apostle <HI>Paul</HI> takes up a great Lamentation, <HI>Rom.</HI> 9. the beginning, and tells us, <HI>That he could wish himself, that he were accursed from Christ, for his Brethrens sake, concerning the flesh; who,</HI> saith he, <HI>are</HI> Israelites, to whom <HI>pertaineth</HI> the <HI>Adoption,</HI> and the <HI>Glory,</HI> and the <HI>Covenants,</HI> and the <HI>giving of the Law,</HI> and the <HI>Ser∣vice of God,</HI> and the <HI>Promises;</HI> whose are the <HI>Fathers,</HI> and of whom <HI>concerning the flesh, Christ came.</HI></P>
<P>Yet notwithstanding all these high Priviledges, the Prophet is sent to them with a Message from the Lord, <HI>Isaiah 6. 9, 10. Go, saith the Lord, and tell this People, Hear ye indeed, but understand not; and see ye indeed, but perceive not; make the heart of this People fat, and make their ears heavy, and shut their eyes; lest they see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their hearts, and convert, and be healed.</HI></P>
<P>And what's the Cause of all this, may some say?</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> The Prophet that was sent on this Message, with other of the Prophets, will give a perfect answer, and tell you, <HI>That Israel did not render unto the Lord according to his Benefits bestowed; and there∣fore wrath was upon them from the Lord▪ for God had planted them a noble Vine, wholly a Righteous Seed;</HI> but they were turned into <HI>the degenerate Plant of a strange Vine unto him,</HI> saith the Prophet, <HI>Jeremiah</HI> 2. 21. And the Prophet <HI>Isaiah</HI> sings the same Song, <HI>Isaiah</HI> 5. 1, &amp;c. <HI>Now will I sing,</HI> saith he, <HI>to my well Beloved, a Song of my well Beloved touching his Uineyard. My well beloued hath a Uineyard</HI> in a <HI>very fruitful Hill, and he fenced it and gathered out the stones thereof, and planted it with the choisest Uine; and he Built a Tower, and set a Winepress there∣in, and he looked that it should bring forth Grapes,</HI> and it brought forth <HI>Wild Grapes.</HI> V. 7. The <HI>Vineyard</HI> of the Lord of Hosts, is the <HI>House of Israel, and the Men of Judah,</HI> his <HI>pleasant Plant; and he looked</HI>
<PB N="34" REF="28"/>
<HI>for Judgement, but behold, Oppression; for Righteousness, but behold,</HI> a Cry.</P>
<P>And therefore God calls themselves to Judge the Cause, v. 3. <HI>And now, O Inhabitants of Jerusalem,</HI> and men of Judah, <HI>Judge, I pray you, between me</HI> and <HI>my Vineyard, What could have been done more to my Vineyard, that I have not done in it? And now, saith he, Go to, I will tell you what I will do to my Vineyard, I will take away the Hedge thereof, and it shall be eaten up;</HI> and <HI>break down the Wall thereof, and it shall be troden down;</HI> and I will <HI>lay it waste, it shall not be pruned nor digged; but there shall come up Bryers</HI> and <HI>Thorns.</HI> And for these Mis-actings of theirs, the Lord by his Prophet, <HI>Isai.</HI> 1. 2. takes up a great com∣plaint, saying, <HI>Hear O Heavens, and give ear O Earth;</HI> for the Lord <HI>hath spoken, I have nourished and brought up Children, and they have rebelled against me; the Ox knoweth his Owner,</HI> and the <HI>Asse his Masters Crib; but Israel doth not know, my People do not consider: Ah! sinful Nation, a People laiden with Iniquity, a Seed of Evil-doers, Chil∣dren that are Corrupters; they have forsaken the Lord, they have provoked the Holy One of Israel to anger, they are gone away backward:</HI> By Rea∣son whereof, we see the Lord looks upon their <HI>Holy Duties as nothing, even as vanity;</HI> and their <HI>burning of Incense,</HI> an <HI>abomination unto him.</HI></P>
<P>Whence we may note, That though men be in the <HI>Perfect</HI> and <HI>Real Way of God,</HI> as to his <HI>Worship;</HI> yet, if they do <HI>not render to God,</HI> if <HI>their Conversation</HI> answer not <HI>their Profession,</HI> the <HI>best</HI> of their <HI>Wor∣ship</HI> is but <HI>vain</HI> and <HI>abominable in Gods sight;</HI> and such as God is <HI>weary</HI> to <HI>bear,</HI> Isai. 1. 14. And such persons are looked upon <HI>as Enemies to the Crosse of Christ, Phil.</HI> 3. 18. And God looked upon <HI>them to be so to him:</HI> and such as he will <HI>not long be burthened withal;</HI> for so saith the Prophet, <HI>Isaiah 1. 24. Thus saith the Lord of Hosts, the Mighty One if Israel, Ah! I will ease me of mine Anversaries, I will avenge me on mine E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>emies:</HI> And we find this <HI>threatning</HI> was <HI>made good upon them,</HI> Zach. 7. 13, 14. <HI>Therefore,</HI> saith the Prophet, <HI>it is come to pass, that as he cryed, and they would not hear; so they cryed, and I would not hear;</HI> but I <HI>scattered them with a Whirl-wind among all the Nations whom they knew not,</HI> &amp;c. and so they continue a scattered peo∣ple to this very day. So that we see the Assertion made good in them also, <HI>That God requires suitable▪ Returns for Mercies bestowed, though from the greatest of Men or Nations; upon the neglect whereof, God punisheth without respect of persons.</HI></P>
<P>So that we see the point fully proved upon <HI>Nebuchadnezzar</HI> and <HI>Saul,</HI> two <HI>Great</HI> and <HI>Potent Kings;</HI> and also ugon <HI>Israel,</HI> the <HI>greatest</HI>
<PB N="35" REF="28"/>
of <HI>Nations;</HI> and that not onely upon the account of <HI>multitude,</HI> but also the <HI>greatest Priviledged Nation under the Heavens.</HI></P>
<P>I shall not spend time to lay down the Reasons of the Point; but in a word shall say what the Lord Christ saith, <HI>Luke 12. 48. To whom much is given, of him shall be much required.</HI></P>
<P>And so I shall come to some Uses, that may be made of the Point.</P>
<P>For, as Practice is the very life of Profession, So the Uses of a Sermon, being well applyed, become words spoken in season; which the Wise Man saith, Are like Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver, <HI>Prov.</HI> 25. 11.</P>
<P>And seeing it is so, that God requires suitable Returns for Benefits bestowed; upon the neglect whereof, <HI>God punisheth,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>This then may serve for a Use to great ones; and first, to thy self, O King, to Exhort thee in the Name and Fear of Cod, seriously to consider particularly what God hath done for thee, how God hath preserved thee both abroad and in this Land of thy Nativity; and let me humbly beg thee once again; seriously to consider the <HI>Hollow Oak,</HI> and that little Vessel which rides in thy constant view, and those that were acting in and by them, for thy personal preservation (the which, if report be true, thou hast in a great measure already done, which is very commendable) But this is that, O King, that I am chiefly pleading for, that thou wouldst endeavour to look <HI>through and beyond them, even to the Finger and Power of that God that wrought in and by them;</HI> not only for thy Temporal, but also (if thou beest not wanting to thy self) for <HI>thy Eternal preservation,</HI> if thou dost make <HI>suitable Returns to him;</HI> that so <HI>wrath may not follow.</HI></P>
<P>To this purpose, consider <HI>every one of thy Thoughts</HI> and <HI>Intentions,</HI> and examine them <HI>before</HI> thou put them into <HI>action,</HI> see whether they tend to a <HI>suitable Returning to God,</HI> for such great Benefits <HI>received from God,</HI> or not.</P>
<P>And if <HI>this, O King,</HI> be the <HI>bent</HI> of thy <HI>Spirit,</HI> and <HI>thy continued practice,</HI> I can <HI>assure thee</HI> from the <HI>Word of the Lord,</HI> that it will be a <HI>lengthning out of thy Tranquillity;</HI> for so saith the <HI>wisest of men,</HI> by the <HI>assictance</HI> of the <HI>Eternal Spirit, Prov. 16. 7. When a mans wayes please the Lord, he will make even his Enemies to be at peace with him;</HI> and not <HI>onely so,</HI> but thou <HI>shalt also</HI> have a <HI>Benefit hereafter,</HI> and that to <HI>Eternity;</HI> for so saith the Lord by the <HI>mouth</HI> of a King, <HI>Psal. 50. 23. Whoso offereth praise, glorifieth me, and to him that ordereth his Conver∣sation aright, will I shew the Salvation of God.</HI></P>
<P>And secondly, O King, seeing <HI>many Great Ones</HI> in this Nation have
<PB N="36" REF="29"/>
had a great share in the Benefits God hath bestowed upon thee; this may serve for a Use of <HI>Exhortation</HI> also to them, to perswade them to consider seriously what God hath done for them in doing for thee; and further to examine what suitable Returns they have already made, and what Rendrings they intend to make to God for such great Benefits be∣stowed.</P>
<P>I desire to urge this the rather, because I see many of their Coaches standing daily, where I fear they cannot duly Render to God according to such Mercies bestowed; and therefore I shall desire to discharge my Conscience to them, in letting them know, That without Holiness no man shall see the Lord, <HI>Heb.</HI> 12. 14. and without Faith it is impossible to please God, <HI>Heb</HI> 11. 6. Which Faith comes by Hearing, and Hearing by the Word of God, <HI>Heb.</HI> 10. 17. and not by Hearing <HI>scurrility</HI> in <HI>Stage-playes, May-games</HI> and <HI>Pastimes:</HI> Consider O ye Great Ones, that are guilty of such actings; and know, that God requires other things from you; and make suitable Returns to God, lest God Return his Judgements with Indignation, and so the last be worse than the first: for we usually say, that Relapses are dangerous, and many times prove worse than the first Distemper.</P>
<P>Thirdly, Seeing God requires suitable Returns for Benefits bestowed, though from the greatest of Men or Nations; upon the neglect whereof, God punisheth without respect of Persons.</P>
<P>This then may also serve for a Use of <HI>Exhortation</HI> and <HI>Examination</HI> to this Nation, <HI>considered as a Nation:</HI> And as some have said, <HI>They</HI> (to wit) <HI>the Nation</HI> was a <HI>Body without a Head;</HI> meaning, they were with∣out <HI>a King;</HI> for the King is the Head, or Supream, 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2. 13, 14. ac∣cording to that of <HI>Samuel</HI> also to <HI>Saul,</HI> 1 Sam. 14. 17. And <HI>Samuel</HI> said to <HI>Saul,</HI> When thou wast <HI>little</HI> in thine <HI>own sight,</HI> wast thou not made the <HI>Head</HI> of the <HI>Tribes of Israel?</HI> And the Lord anointed thee <HI>King over Israel,</HI> &amp;c. So that now, O <HI>England,</HI> thou canst not so Complain, for by a <HI>miraculous hand</HI> thy <HI>Head</HI> is restored to thee again; examine thy self now what <HI>Benefit</HI> thou <HI>hast received;</HI> and also, how thou art <HI>bettered thereby:</HI> Dost thou render to God according to his Benefits bestowed? Art thou grown more Holy than thou wast? Or rather, art thou not grow <HI>openly prophane,</HI> out of a <HI>sense</HI> of Gods <HI>Great Love to thee?</HI> Dost thou rejoyce before the Lord with <HI>trembling?</HI> Or rather, is not thy re∣joycing such, as that it would and doth, even make a truly Regenerate Soul <HI>tremble to behold it?</HI> Art thou <HI>rendring</HI> to God, for bringing this great Design about without <HI>shedding of blood?</HI> Or rather, is not thy <HI>Be∣haviour</HI> such, as suddenly may cause God to open another <HI>vein</HI> to the
<PB N="37" REF="29"/>
Effusion of thy Bloud, even to the Confusion of thy face? Art thou <HI>rejoycing,</HI> that the <HI>Sword</HI> in all visible probability is now <HI>sheathing</HI> again? And is not that <HI>rejoycing</HI> such, that may justly cause God to Command it to run thorow thy <HI>Borders</HI> a second time?</P>
<P>Art thou <HI>humble</HI> before thy God, O <HI>England,</HI> out of a Considerati∣on of thine <HI>own unworthiness,</HI> and of Gods great <HI>love to thee</HI> in these things? Or rather, art thou not grown more <HI>haughty?</HI> And may not the Lord take up a <HI>Complaint</HI> against thee and thy Daughters, O <HI>England,</HI> as once he did against his People of old? <HI>Isa.</HI> 3. 16. and say to <HI>England,</HI> and in special to <HI>London, Because thy Daughters are haughty, and walk with stretched out Necks, and wanton Eyes, walking and mincing as they go, and making a tinkling with their feet; therefore the Lord will smite with a</HI> Scab <HI>the</HI> Crown <HI>of the</HI> Head <HI>of the</HI> Daughters of <HI>England; And the Lord will discover her secret parts in that day:</HI> Or when the Lord shall say so to <HI>England,</HI> Then will he take away the <HI>bravery</HI> of their <HI>tinkling Ornaments about their feet,</HI> and their <HI>Cauls,</HI> and their <HI>round Tiers like the Moon,</HI> and the <HI>Braslets,</HI> and the <HI>Mufflers,</HI> the <HI>Bonnets,</HI> and the <HI>Or∣naments of the Leggs,</HI> the <HI>changeable suits</HI> of fantastical Attire; and in∣stead of their <HI>sweet Powders, a stink;</HI> instead of a <HI>Girdle, a Rent;</HI> in∣stead of their <HI>crisped and well-set Hair, Baldness;</HI> and instead of a <HI>Sto∣macher, a girding of Sack-cloth;</HI> and <HI>Burning</HI> instead of <HI>Beauty;</HI> and cause a <HI>second time</HI> their <HI>Men to fall by the Sword,</HI> and their <HI>Mighty in War;</HI> for <HI>England</HI> is full of Distempers; so that God may justly say of her, as once he said of <HI>Israel,</HI> Isa. 1. 6. <HI>From the sole of the foot, even un∣to the head, there is no soundness in it, but mounds, and bruises; and pu∣trified sores; they have not been closed, neither bound up, nor mollified with Ointments;</HI> for the <HI>Judgements</HI> nor the <HI>Mercies</HI> of God, have nei∣ther <HI>allured</HI> nor <HI>restrained</HI> them from their Iniquities, but to this very day she hath her <HI>Tinpenny of Pride,</HI> being also full of the <HI>Dropsical Hu∣mours</HI> of all Abominations; and yet in a deep Consumption of all <HI>true Piety, Pitty, Penitency, Patience</HI> and <HI>Purity;</HI> by which means she is be∣come very <HI>Perverse, Peevish, Prophane</HI> and <HI>Pittiless.</HI></P>
<P>Therefore, O <HI>England,</HI> Consider what God after all his <HI>Judgements</HI> and <HI>Mercies</HI> requireth of thee; and for the time to come, meet thy God with suitable Returns, lest God meet thee again, in some or all his three fierce Judgements, <HI>Sword, Pestilence</HI> or <HI>Famine;</HI> either to thy speedy rooting out, or thy Consuming lingring Ruine. Consider what I say, and the Lord make thee wise.</P>
<P>And Secondly, Seeing it is so, That God requires suitable Returns for Benefits bestowed, though from the greatest of Men or Nations, &amp;c.</P>
<P><PB N="38" REF="30"/>This then may serve for a Use of <HI>Reproof</HI> to all, from the Highest to the Lowest, from him that <HI>sitteth upon the Throne,</HI> to him that <HI>grindeth at the Mill,</HI> even to the <HI>Hewer of Wood</HI> and <HI>Drawer of Water;</HI> to all that have <HI>received,</HI> and have not duly <HI>rendred,</HI> to such who like the Swine under the Acorn Tree, have greedily swallowed down all the Be∣nefits that comes <HI>from,</HI> God, never so much as once looking <HI>to</HI> God, nor to him that sends them; And to say truth, it fares generally with men as with those Leapers, <HI>Luk</HI> 17. 17. where ten were cured, &amp; but one found to return Praise: And indeed it is ten to one, whether men generally know it really to be their duty, or not; therefore I shall commend this Use to all that have not Rendred, and shall let them know in the words of <HI>Solomon</HI> the wise, <HI>That he is in the way of Life that keepeth knowledge; whilst he that refuseth reproof, erreth,</HI> Prov. 10. 17. <HI>For he that hateth reproof is brutish,</HI> Prov. 12. 1. <HI>And shame shall be to him that refuseth Instructi∣on; whilst he that regardeth reproof shall be honoured,</HI> Prov. 13. 18. And therefore I shall desire all, seriously to consider the danger of not Rendring.</P>
<P>For <HI>Hezekiah</HI> rendred not again according to the Benefits bestowed upon him, but his heart was lifted up; <HI>therefore wrath fell upon him, and upon</HI> Judah <HI>and</HI> Jerusalem.</P>
<P>And so I shall pass to the next Teachable Observation.</P>
<P N="2">2. That many times God <HI>punisheth a People</HI> for the <HI>misactings</HI> of their <HI>Governours,</HI> whether in <HI>Church, State,</HI> or <HI>particular Families.</HI></P>
<P>For the Proof of which Point, let us consider King <HI>David,</HI> who as to the integrity of his inward-man, was upright before God; therefore we have this Testimony of him, <HI>That he was a man after Gods own heart,</HI> 1 Sam. 13. 14. Yet this integrity of his was accompanied with some imperfections, which caused <HI>Gods wrath to burn hot against his People,</HI> as we may read, 2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 24. 1. For King <HI>David</HI> by the insti∣gation of that Enemy of mankind, was moved to <HI>number his People,</HI> by which means the <HI>wrath of God</HI> was kindled against <HI>Israel;</HI> for so saith the Text, 2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 24. 1. <HI>And again the Anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel;</HI> and <HI>He</HI> moved <HI>David</HI> against them to say, <HI>Go number</HI> Israel <HI>and</HI> Judah.</P>
<P><HI>Quest.</HI> But here it may be asked, How I prove this to be done by the perswasion of that Evil One, seeing the Text doth not in so many words say so?</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> To which I Answer; The Text in 2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 41. 1. nor in any other part of the Chapter, doth not in so many words prove it; but if according to the teaching of the Apostle <HI>Paul,</HI> 1 Cor. 2. 13. <HI>We compare</HI>
<PB N="39" REF="30"/>
<HI>Spiritual things with Spiritual;</HI> the Holy Ghost will make a clear Disco∣very; for compare this▪ 2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 24. 1. with, 1 <HI>Chron.</HI> 21. 1. we shall find this, He that moved <HI>David</HI> in this, 2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 24. 1. is that Enemy of man∣kind, that Evil One, or Satan; for so saith the text, 1 <HI>Chron,</HI> 21. 1. <HI>And Satan stood up against</HI> Israel, <HI>and provoked</HI> David <HI>to number</HI> Israel.</P>
<P><HI>Quest.</HI> But here it may be farther demanded, <HI>What was</HI> Israels <HI>sin? seeing</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, what had</HI> Israel <HI>done?</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> I Answer; <HI>Israel</HI> was not at this time (as we read of) acting in any gross or known sin; yet <HI>Isràel</HI> must be punished: Which proves our Assertion to be true, <HI>That God many times punisheth a People for the misactings of their Governours, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>Quest. <HI>What then was</HI> Davids <HI>sin, may some say?</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> I Answer; <HI>Davids</HI> sin lay in numbring the People; for so saith the text, 1 <HI>Chron.</HI> 21. 7. And God was displeased at this thing; therefore he smote <HI>Israel.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Quest.</HI> Was the numbring of the People then the only Cause, that moved God to slay with the Plague threescore and ten thousand? as we read, <HI>vers.</HI> 14.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Yea, so saith the text, <HI>v.</HI> 17. For <HI>David</HI> said unto God, <HI>Is it not I that Commanded the People to be numbred? Even I it is that have sinned and done evil▪ But as for these sheep, what have they done? Let thy hand, I pray thee, be on me and on my Fathers House, but not on thy People, that they should be punished.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Quest.</HI> Is it so dangerous a thing then to tell over, or number the People, may some say?</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> I Answer; That to tell over or number the People, simply so considered, is not sin; for then it were a sin for <HI>Joshua</HI> to number the People, <HI>Josh.</HI> 8. 10. Or to number the Eleven, <HI>Acts</HI> 1. 26. who were numbred; <HI>For they gave forth the Lots, and the Lot fell upon</HI> Matthias, <HI>and he was numbred with the Eleven.</HI></P>
<P>But to number the People, so as to put Confidence in an Arm of Flesh; to number the People so as to depart from the Lord, this is an accursed thing; for so saith the Prophet, <HI>Jer.</HI> 17. 5. <HI>Thus saith the Lord, Cursed be the man that trusteth in man, and maketh flesh his Arm; and whose heart departeth from the Lord:</HI> And <HI>this</HI> I humbly conceive might be <HI>Davids</HI> sin; for if we cast our eye but into 1 <HI>Chron.</HI> 20. we shall find <HI>Joab,</HI> the Captain of <HI>Davids</HI> Host, destroying the Country of the Chil∣dren of <HI>Ammon,</HI> and <HI>Rabbah,</HI> and slaying <HI>three Giants</HI> in three several Overthrows of the <HI>Philistines;</HI> and the Devil knoweth right well how to make his Advantages.</P>
<P><PB N="40" REF="31"/>He knew, that God was <HI>jealous</HI> of his <HI>Honour;</HI> and if he could but work up <HI>Danid</HI> to put <HI>confidence in an Arm of flesh,</HI> or to <HI>give glory to the multitude</HI> of his <HI>Armed men;</HI> this was an <HI>advantage good enough against Israel;</HI> this was that which <HI>would cause God</HI> to <HI>weaken</HI> his <HI>strength,</HI> by taking them away, and have a Controversie with them: And <HI>thus</HI> God doth in <HI>Mercy to his People,</HI> when they begin to <HI>put <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fidence,</HI> or set their <HI>hearts upon Creature-comforts,</HI> God is then <HI>rea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> take them away; and thus God is said, to hedge up their way with Thorns,</HI> Hos. 2. 6, 7. <HI>And to make a Wall that they shall not find their w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y; and they shall follow after their Lovers, but shall not overtake them, they shall seek af∣ter them, but not find them;</HI> for saith the Propher, <HI>Isai.</HI> 57. 13. <HI>The wind shall carry them away, vanity shall take them.</HI></P>
<P>We may see this Assertion farther proved in the <HI>Egyptians,</HI> in those <HI>ten Plagues</HI> that came upon them, for the <HI>hardness of the heart of Pha∣raoh their King;</HI> What <HI>misery</HI> did they <HI>endure in that weeks time of the waters of the Rivers being turned into Blood?</HI> Exod. 7. 20, 27. <HI>What did they endure by reason of the Plagues of Froggs, Lice and Flies?</HI> Exod. 8. 3, 17, 24. in those <HI>Plagues of Murrion</HI> and <HI>Hail?</HI> Exod. 9. 2, 10, 23. in those <HI>Plagues of Locusts,</HI> and <HI>Darkness?</HI> Exod. 10. 4, 22. and in the <HI>Death of all their first-born, both of Man and Beast?</HI> Exod. 12. 29.</P>
<P>The like we may see threatned against <HI>Israel</HI> of old, by reason of the <HI>misactings</HI> of their <HI>Princes, Judges, Priests,</HI> and <HI>Prophets,</HI> Micah 3. 9. <HI>Hear, I pray you</HI> (saith the Prophet) <HI>ye Heads of the House of Jacob,</HI> and <HI>Princes of the House of Israel, that abhor Judgement,</HI> and <HI>pervert all Equity,</HI> v. 10. <HI>That build up Zion with Blood,</HI> and <HI>Jerusalem with Iniquity,</HI> v. 11. The <HI>Heads thereof judge for Reward, and the Priests thereof teach for Hire, and the Prophets thereof Divine for Money;</HI> like the <HI>Priests</HI> and <HI>Prophets</HI> of <HI>England at this day;</HI> and they like∣wise, <HI>as those of old,</HI> will <HI>lean upon the Lord, and say, Is not the Lord among us, no evil can come upon us?</HI> But though they say thus; What saith the Prophet? <HI>Therefore shall Zion for your sake be plowed as a Field,</HI> and <HI>Jerusalem shall become heaps,</HI> and the <HI>Mountain of the Lords House, as the high places of the Forrest.</HI></P>
<P>So that we may see, That for the mis-actings of Church-men, that teach for Hire, and Divine for Money▪ <HI>Zion,</HI> or the Church, shall be <HI>punished, yea plowed as a Field, and laid waste, and the Mountain of the Lords House become as the high places of the Forrest;</HI> As well as for the perverting of Judgement and Equity by the Princes and Judges, <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> or the Kingdom, shall become heaps; for <HI>there will be a scat∣tering of the Sheep, for the negligence of the Shepherd;</HI> yea, so saith the Prophet, <HI>Isa.</HI> 10. 21. <HI>For the Pastors are become brutish, &amp; have not sought</HI>
<PB N="41" REF="31"/>
<HI>the Lord; therefore they shall not Prosper, and all their Flock shall be scat∣tered.</HI> And so saith the Lord Christ by <HI>John</HI> the Revelator, speaking to the Angel, or the Pastor of the Church of <HI>Ephesus,</HI> Revelation 2. 5. <HI>Remember</HI> (saith he) <HI>from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do thy first work, or else I will come unto thee quickly, and will remove thy Candle∣stick o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t of his place, except thou Repent.</HI></P>
<P>As if he should say, Thou art the Light of the Church, and the Feeder of the Flock; the Church or People, are the Candlestick that upholds thee, and the Flock that employes thee, and unless thou re∣pent of thy <HI>deadness,</HI> thy <HI>dulness,</HI> thy <HI>drowsiness,</HI> thy <HI>coldness,</HI> thy <HI>care∣lesness,</HI> and thy <HI>carnality; I will suddenly remove thy Candlestick, I will soon disperse the flock;</HI> And then, what will become of thee? <HI>who wilt thou feed? who wilt thou light?</HI> Thy <HI>Talent</HI> will <HI>then be under a Bushel, and not on a Candlestick, to give light to those that are in the House.</HI></P>
<P>This <HI>Assertion</HI> we may also see made good in or upon <HI>private Fa∣milies.</HI></P>
<P><HI>That God many times punisheth a People for the misactings of their Go∣vernours, whether in Church, State,</HI> or <HI>particular Families.</HI></P>
<P>When <HI>Abraham</HI> was journying <HI>into Egypt</HI> with his Wife <HI>Sarah,</HI> be∣ing driven thither by a Famine, <HI>Gen.</HI> 12. he said unto <HI>Sarah</HI> his Wife, v. 11, &amp;c. <HI>Behold now, I know that thou art a fair Woman to look upon; therefore it shall come to pass when the Egyptians shall see thee, that they shall say, This is his Wife, and they shall kill me, but they will save thee alive; say I pray thee, thou art my Sister, that it may be well with me for thy sake, that my Soul may live because of thee.</HI></P>
<P>Whence by the way we may note; First, That <HI>Famine</HI> and <HI>outward distresses</HI> possibly may <HI>attend the dearest of Gods Children;</HI> for we see <HI>Abraham that friend of God,</HI> was driven into <HI>Egypt</HI> by reason that the <HI>Famine was grievous in the Land,</HI> v. 10.</P>
<P>And secondly, That <HI>the fear of the loss of life, may stand with the nature of true Faith; for Abraham</HI> the <HI>Father of the Faithful,</HI> said, When the <HI>Egyptians</HI> shall see thee, they will say, this is his Wife, <HI>and they will kill me;</HI> therefore say, thou art my Sister.: And <HI>Paul</HI> the Apostle, a faithful Soul, whose life being laid wait for, <HI>was let down by the Wall in a Basket,</HI> Acts 9. 25. Yea, the <HI>Lord Christ him∣self refused to walk in Jury, but walked in Galilee, because the Jews sought to kill him,</HI> John 7. 1.</P>
<P>But to our Matter, upon <HI>Abrahams</HI> saying, that <HI>Sarah</HI> was his Sister, vers. 19. and upon the Commendations of <HI>Sarah</HI> to <HI>Pharaoh</HI> by his
<PB N="42" REF="32"/>
Princes, <HI>Sarah</HI> was taken into <HI>Pharaohs</HI> House, and <HI>Abraham</HI> was well entreated by <HI>Pharaoh</HI> for <HI>Sarahs</HI> sake, v. 15, 16.</P>
<P><HI>Yet the Lord Plagued Pharaoh and his house with great Plagues, be∣cause of Sarah, Abrahams Wife,</HI> v. 17. <HI>Pharaoh</HI> sins, and that igno∣rantly too, in taking <HI>Abrahams</HI> Wife into his House; for so saith the Text, v. 18. For <HI>Pharaoh</HI> called <HI>Abraham,</HI> and said, What is this that <HI>thou hast done</HI> unto me? <HI>Why didst thou not tell me she was thy Wife? Why saidst thou she is my Sister? So I might have taken her to me to Wife.</HI></P>
<P>Though <HI>Pharaoh sins,</HI> I say, and <HI>that ignorantly too,</HI> as it is clear he did; yet <HI>his House must be plagued with great Plagues.</HI></P>
<P>Whence by the way, I would have all to take notice, That <HI>it is not ignorance that will excuse or shroud, neither the meanest nor the greatest of men, from the sin-revenging hand of God.</HI></P>
<P>And secondly, That God takes special care for his faithful ones, so as that <HI>he will not respect persons when they evilly entreat them;</HI> for so saith the Prophet, <HI>Psal.</HI> 115. 14, 15. <HI>He suffered no man to do them wrong; yea, he reproved Kings. for their sake;</HI> saying, <HI>Touch not mine Anointed, and do my Prophets no harm.</HI></P>
<P>And thus as <HI>Abraham</HI> was travelling towards the South Countrey, whilst he so journed in <HI>Gerar,</HI> the Lord reproved <HI>Abimelech</HI> also, King of <HI>Gerar,</HI> for his sake, <HI>Gen.</HI> 20. For <HI>Abraham</HI> (again) said of <HI>Sarah</HI> his Wife, she is my Sister; and <HI>Abimelech</HI> King of <HI>Gerar</HI> sent and took <HI>Sarah,</HI> v. 2. <HI>But God came to Abimelech in a Dreame by night, and said unto him, Thou art but a dead man,</HI> (a sharp Reproof indeed) And he gives him a Reason for his so saying, <HI>For the Woman</HI> (saith he) <HI>which thon hast taken is a mans Wife,</HI> v. 3. Yet saith the Text, <HI>Abime∣lech had not come near her,</HI> v. 4. <HI>And Abimelech said, Lord, wilt thou stay also a Righteous Nation? Said he not, she is my Sister? and she, even she her self said, He is my Brother; in the integrity of my heart, and innocency of my hands have I done this,</HI> v. 5. <HI>And God said unto him in a Dream, yea I know that thou didst this in the integrity of thy heart, for I also withheld thee from sinning against me; therefore suffered I thee not to touch her,</HI> v. 6.</P>
<P>Whence I would note also by the way; First, That he who is the Searcher of the heart, and Tryer of the reins, takes a <HI>perfect account</HI> of the <HI>bent of the spirits of the Sons and Daughters of Men.</HI></P>
<P>And secondly; That <HI>accordingly he either restrains Souls from sinning against him,</HI> or else <HI>gives persons up to commit sin with greediness;</HI> for so saith the Text, And as they did not like to retain God in their know∣ledge; therefore God gave them up to a reprobate mind, <HI>Rom.</HI> 1. 28.
<PB N="43" REF="32"/>
But this is that in the seventh verse, that makes the Assertion good; <HI>Now therefore</HI> (saith the Lord) <HI>restore the Man his Wife, for he is a Pro∣phet, and he shall pray for thee, and thou shalt live; and if thou re∣store her not, know thou, that thou shalt surely die, thou and all that thou hast.</HI></P>
<P>The like we may see made good in <HI>Achans</HI> Family, <HI>Josh.</HI> 7. That when <HI>Achan</HI> had taken of the accursed things, that goodly Babylonish Garment, the Silver, and the Wedge of Gold; the Judgement ex∣tended not onely to the punishment of himself, but also to his whole Family, and all that was his; for so saith the Text, <HI>Josh.</HI> 7. 24. <HI>And Joshua and all Israel with him, took Achan</HI> the Son of <HI>Zerah, and the Silver, and the Garment, and the Wedge of Gold, and his Sons,</HI> and his <HI>Daughters,</HI> and his <HI>Oxen,</HI> and his <HI>Asses,</HI> and his <HI>Sheep,</HI> and his <HI>Tent,</HI> and <HI>all that he had:</HI> And v. 25. <HI>They burned them with fire, after they had stoned them with stones.</HI></P>
<P>Now the Lord Christ saith, <HI>Mat.</HI> 18. 16. That in the mouth of two or three witnesses every Truth shall be established; and I having proved each Particular in the Assertion by two witnesses at the least; That God many times punisheth a People for the misactings of their Governours, whether in <HI>Church, State,</HI> or <HI>particular Families.</HI></P>
<P>And now, lest I make my lines too numerous, I shall forbear to lay down any Reasons of the Point; but shall proceed to some Uses that may be for our present benefit.</P>
<P>And seeing it is so, That God many times punisheth a People for the misactings of their Governours, whether in Church, State, or par∣ticular Families:</P>
<P>This then may serve for a Use of Exhortation to thee, O King, to thee, and to all Kings, Princes, and Governours of Nations, Pastors, and Elders of Congregations, and Masters of Families, as they ten∣der their own good, and the good of those that are under them, that they walk before the Lord, and go in and out before their People in singleness of heart, and in the sincerity of their Souls, as in the sight of God, having a single-eye to the Glory of God, and the good of the Souls that are under their charge, carefully watching over all their thoughts, words and actions, so as that they bring not the Judgements of God upon their people by their misactings; and to be often with the Lord in Prayer, that so they may have his Direction and Protecti∣on in all their Enterprises and Undertakings, to the comfort of their own Souls, and the Peace, Benefit and Well-being of those that are under them.</P>
<P>And secondly, This may also serve for a U<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of Exhortation to all
<PB N="44" REF="33"/>
Subjects, though they be Pastors, or Elders of Congregations, and Ma∣sters of Families, as well as Members of Churches, or Children, or Ser∣vants in particular Families, that they be often at the Throne of Grace in the behalf of their Kings, Princes and Governours; and in special, that <HI>Englands</HI> Subjects be often with the Lord in the behalf of their KING, who from his long Exile and Restraint, is brought again into this Land of his Nativity, which is so full of <HI>Licentiousnes, Luxury</HI> and <HI>Lasciviousness, Revilings, Rendings</HI> and <HI>Tearings, Roarings, Rantings</HI> and <HI>Swearings,</HI> with those <HI>Abominations</HI> of <HI>Stage-Playes, May-games</HI> and <HI>Pastimes, Pride</HI> and <HI>Prodigality,</HI> that God in Mercy would be pleased to direct his Heart so, as that he be not won <HI>either to own,</HI> or <HI>allow of them;</HI> but to <HI>disown, diswade</HI> and <HI>discountenance them:</HI> And that God would farther <HI>strengthen</HI> both his Heart and Hand, to <HI>prosecute</HI> that <HI>lovely, laudable, prudent, pious, Conscientious</HI> and <HI>Christian,</HI> that <HI>truly Noble</HI> and <HI>most Heroick Princely PROCLAMATION,</HI> by Him issued forth at his first coming amongst us again, and fince by him seconded by another; that so <HI>England,</HI> though <HI>now even a sink of Abominations,</HI> may by the good hand of God upon us, by his <HI>industry, become</HI> as it shall be once said of <HI>Jerusalem, to be a Praise of the whole Earth.</HI></P>
<P>And that God would direct him so to consider of his Holy Things, as that he present nothing to God, but what is Commanded by God, that so God may not only <HI>Crown</HI> him with a Crown of Gold here, but also with that Crown of Glory, which shall never fade away.</P>
<P>And that he be <HI>thus</HI> found Rendring to the Lord, considering the dan∣ger of the neglect thereof.</P>
<P>For <HI>Hezekiah</HI> rendered not again according to the Benefits bestowed upon him, but his heart was lifted up; <HI>therefore</HI> wrath was upon him, and upon <HI>Judah</HI> and <HI>Jerusalem.</HI></P>
<P>And Thirdly, This may serve for a Use of Exhortation, to Mem∣bers of Congregations, and Children, and Servants of particular Fami∣lies; that they be also constant in this Duty of Prayer, in the behalf of their respective Pastors, Elders, Fathers or Masters, that they may be so directed by divine Assistance, <HI>that as under their Prince,</HI> so likewise un∣der <HI>them,</HI> they may lead a peaceable, a quiet, and a godly life, in all godliness and honesty.</P>
<P>And so I shall passe to my Third and last Teachable Conclusion, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, <HI>That outward Enjoyments do many times so affect the Heart of man, as that they lift them up, even to the forgetting of God, to their own ruine.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="45" REF="33"/>The great <HI>Jehovah</HI> knowing right well the <HI>nature of things,</HI> as he was the <HI>Maker of thom;</HI> and the <HI>temper of Mans Heart,</HI> as he was the <HI>Former of it;</HI> when he caused <HI>Moses</HI> to let <HI>Israel</HI> know the particular Priviledges they should enjoy in the Land of <HI>Canaan,</HI> Deut. 8. he giveth them this Caution, <HI>v.</HI> 12, 13, 14. <HI>That when they had eaten and were full, and had built goodly Houses, and dwelt therein, when their Heards</HI> and <HI>Flocks,</HI> their <HI>Silver</HI> and their <HI>Gold</HI> was <HI>encreased,</HI> that then their <HI>heart should not be listed up.</HI></P>
<P>But the truth of this Assertion we may see verified in <HI>Belshazzar</HI> King of <HI>Babylon;</HI> for when <HI>Daniel</HI> was sent for to <HI>Read</HI> and <HI>Interpret</HI> the <HI>Haud-writing</HI> on the <HI>Wall, to Belshazzar,</HI> Dan. 5. 18. he said, <HI>O King, the Most High God gave unto thy Father a Kingdom, and Majesty, and Glory, and Power; and for the Majesty he gave him, all People, Na∣tions and Languages trembled and feared before him: whom he would he slew, and whom he would he kept alive; whom he would he set up, and whom he would he put down;</HI> as thou dost now, O King: <HI>But when his heart was lifted up, and his mind hardned in Pride, he was deposed from his Kingly Throne, and they took his glory from him, and he was driven from the Sons of Men, and his heart was made like the Beasts, and his dwelling was with the wild Asses, they fed him with grass like Oxen, and his body was wet with the Dew of Heaven, till he knew that the Most High Ruleth in the Kingdom of men, and that he appointeth over it whomsoever he will.</HI></P>
<P>Whence we may note, That as his heart was lifted up, and his mind hardned in Pride, so it was upon the account of his <HI>high en∣joyments,</HI> to the forgetting of God, who dispensed them to him; which we see was the Cause of his casting down.</P>
<P>The like we may see in <HI>Uzziah,</HI> 2 Chron. 26. 1. who after the death of <HI>Amaziah</HI> his Father, was made King of <HI>Judah, And he Reigned in Jerusalem fifty and two years, and he did that which was right in the fight of the Lord:</HI> And V. 5. <HI>He fought God in the dayes of Zecha∣riah, who had understanding in the Visions of God,</HI> and as long as he sought the Lord, God made him to prosper; <HI>And he went forth and warred against the Philistines, and brake down the Wall of Gath, and the Wall of Jabneh, and the Wall of Ashdod; and God helped him against the</HI> Philistines, and <HI>against the</HI> Arabians; <HI>and the Ammonites gave gifts to him, and his Name spread abroad, even to the entring in of Egypt; for he strengthened himself exceedingly, and he built Towers, both in Jerusalem and in the Desert; and digged many Wells, for he had much Cattel, both in the law Countrey, and in the Plains; Husbandmen also,</HI> and <HI>Vine-dressers: Moreover, he had an Host of fighting men, that went out to War in Bands;</HI>
<PB N="46" REF="34"/>
<HI>his chief men or Captains of War, were two thousand and six hundred:</HI> And vers. 15. <HI>He made in Jerusalem Engins of War, made by cunning Work-men, to be on the Towers, and on the Bulwarks, to shoot Arrowes and great Stones withal; and his Name spread far abroad, for he was marvel∣lously helped, till he was strong: But when he was strong,</HI> V. 16. <HI>his heart was lifted up to his destruction; for he transgressed against the Lord his God, and went into the Temple of the Lord; and burned Incense upon the Altar of Incense.</HI> And he was struck with Leprosie, and died with∣out cure.</P>
<P><HI>Thus whilst Uzzia sought the Lord,</HI> V. 5. <HI>God made him to prosper: But when his heart was lifted up, aud he forgat God,</HI> God left him, and <HI>punished</HI> his sin with a <HI>Disease, that to him proved mortal.</HI></P>
<P>Whence we note, That when <HI>Uzziah</HI> separates himself from his God, hy forgetting him; God by that Leprosie separated him from the Priviledges of his House, and the Society of men, and <HI>from all things that were the Cause of his hearts lifting up;</HI> for so saith the Text, ver. 21. <HI>And Uzzia the King was a Leper until the day of his death, and dwelt in a several house, being a Leper; for he was cut off from the House of the Lord:</HI> And <HI>Jotham</HI> his Son was over the Kings House, Judging the People of the Land.</P>
<P>And thus we see the Lord had a Controversie with the Prince of <HI>Tyrus,</HI> against whom he gave out a Commission to the Prophet, <HI>Ezek.</HI> 28. 2. saying, <HI>Son of Man, say unto the Prince of Tyrus, Thus saith the Lord, Because thine heart is lifted up, and thou hast said, I am a god, I sit in the Seat of God, in the midst of the Seas; yet thou art a Man, and not God, though thou set thine heart as the heart of God.</HI> And the reason of the lifting up of his heart is rendred in the fourth and fifth verses, which proves our Assertion fully; for saith vers. 4. <HI>With thy Wisdom and with thy Understanding thou hast gotten thee riches, and hast gotten Gold and Silver into thy Treasuries.</HI> And v. 5. <HI>By thy great Wisdom, and by thy Traffick hast thou encreased thy riches, and thy heart is lifted up, because of thy riches.</HI> V. 7. <HI>Behold, therefore I will bring strangers upon thee, the terrible of the Nations; and they shall draw their Sword against the beauty of thy Wisdom, and they shall defile thy brightness.</HI> And v. 8. <HI>They shall bring thee down to the</HI> Pit, <HI>and thou shalt die the deaths of them that are slain in the midst of the Seas.</HI> And vers. 10. <HI>Thou shalt die the death of the Uncircumcised, by the hand of Strangers; for I have spoken it saith the Lord.</HI></P>
<P>Thus whilst mens hearts are lifted up, and they forget God in the Enjoyment of outward things; and with the rich Man in the Gospel, <HI>Luke</HI> 12. 19. begin to live to themselves, and to sing a <HI>Requium</HI> to
<PB N="47" REF="34"/>
their Souls; the Lord we see brings them down with a, <HI>Thou Fool, this night shall they require thy Soul from thee.</HI></P>
<P>So that we see the Point also fully proved. <HI>viz.</HI> That outward En∣joyments, many times do so affect the heart of man, as that they lift it up even to the forgetting of God, to their own ruine.</P>
<P>Several Uses might be made hereof, the which for brevity sake I shall here omit. And shall onely this say,</P>
<P>That we see by common Experience, That they that are hunger∣bit, when they come to their full of Diet, they run upon it with greedi∣ness, like <HI>Israel</HI> of old, 1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 14. 32. <HI>Who flew upon the Spoil, and took Sheep and Oxen, and Calves, and slew them on the ground, and the People did eat them with the Blood:</HI> Which was contrary to the Law of God, and which <HI>became their sin.</HI> Even so hunger-bit Souls many times eat with that eagerness, that they do not onely sin in their <HI>Ex∣cess,</HI> but also <HI>Surfeit</HI> themselves to the loss of their lives.</P>
<P>This then may serve for a Use of Caution to thee, O King, that of a long time hast been a Stranger to this Land of thy Nativity, and hast been forced to wander from one Kingdom to another Nation, from one Language to another People, in <HI>penury</HI> and <HI>want;</HI> and now being come to three Kingdoms of thine own, flowing with Milk and Honey, and yet abounding in all manner of Excess of Riot; let me Caution thee in the fear of the Lord, that thou <HI>surfeit not</HI> thy self upon the <HI>profits</HI> nor <HI>pleasures</HI> thereof; nor, let thy Men of Valour, neither Domestick nor Forreign, that are lately come over to thy assi∣stance, cause thee to put thy confidence in an Arm of flesh; <HI>lest thy heart be lifted up,</HI> and <HI>so thou forget thy God to thine own ruine: Neither surfeit thy self with too much blood-shed, lest</HI> thou make thy self <HI>Blood-guilty,</HI> and <HI>so</HI> God <HI>begin a new Inquisition;</HI> but rather shew <HI>Pitty</HI> and <HI>Compassion, Love</HI> and <HI>Lenity,</HI> and rather <HI>Lament</HI> than <HI>Launce;</HI> and rather Triumph over the <HI>killing thy Corruptions</HI> than thy <HI>Subjects;</HI> and resolve to refer thy will to the Lord, who saith, <HI>Uengeance is mine, and I will repay it,</HI> Rom. 12. 19. I would here be understood in a good sence; for I do not desire the <HI>Obstruction of the due Administration of Justice,</HI> but that it may be so admini∣stred, that <HI>Mercy</HI> may be <HI>intermixed therewith;</HI> and also that <HI>Relent∣ing</HI> and <HI>Sobriety,</HI> and not <HI>Exaltation</HI> and <HI>Inhumanity, be in the</HI> Exe∣cution.</P>
<P>For I know, That it is an Ordinance of God; <HI>For Magistrates are set up for the punishment of Evil doers,</HI> Rom. 13. 3, 4. For the Law is not made <HI>for the</HI> Righteous man, but for the <HI>Lawless</HI> and <HI>Disobedi∣ent,</HI> for the <HI>Ungodly</HI> and for <HI>Sinners,</HI> for <HI>Unholy</HI> and <HI>Prophane,</HI> for
<PB N="48" REF="35"/>
<HI>Murtherers</HI> of <HI>Fathers,</HI> and <HI>Murtherers</HI> of <HI>Mothers,</HI> for <HI>Man-slayers,</HI> for <HI>Whoremongers,</HI> and for them that <HI>defile themselves with man-kind,</HI> for <HI>Man-stealers,</HI> for <HI>Lyars</HI> and <HI>perj<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>red persons,</HI> or any <HI>thing else</HI> that <HI>is contrary to sound Doctrine,</HI> 1 Tim. 1. 9, 10.</P>
<P>And seeing the Apostle saith, <HI>That in many things we offend all,</HI> James 3. 2. <HI>For if we say we have no sin, we deceive our selves, and the truth is not in us,</HI> 1 Joh. 1. 8.</P>
<P>O then, be perswaded to bring thy self to the <HI>Bar of Gods Justice,</HI> and there <HI>Arraign, Judge, and condemn thy self;</HI> for, saith our Apostle, 1 Cor. 13. 31. <HI>If we would Judge our selves, we should not be Judged; but when we are Judged,</HI> we are <HI>chastened of the Lord, that we should not be condemned with the World.</HI></P>
<P>And this, O King, is the <HI>readiest way I know of, to render duely to God, and to keep thy heart from being lifted up, that so wrath fall not upon thee and thy Kingdoms.</HI></P>
<P>I beseech thee then in the fear of the Great Jehovah, <HI>consider what I say;</HI> and the Lord in <HI>Mercy make thee Wise;</HI> that as thou art an Heir to <HI>a Crown of gold here,</HI> so thou mayest he made partaker of <HI>that Crown of Righteousness which never fadeth away;</HI> which, saith the Apostle, <HI>The Lord the Righteous Judge shall give to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at that day, and not to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> onely, but unto all them also that love his appearan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e,</HI> 2 Tim. 3. 8. And so, O King, let thy <HI>Soul</HI> in the <HI>singleness, thereof Eccho</HI> with mine, and say, <HI>Even so, come Lord Iesus, come quickly.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="49" REF="35"/>
<HEAD>A DECLARATION Of a small Society of BAPTIZED BELIEVERS, undergoing the Name of FREE-WILLERS, about the CITY of LONDON.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>E well knowing, that we are and have been mis-represented to the People of this and other Nations, as well by particular Letters from friend to friend, as by publick Intelligence in Pamphlets and News-Books, by which means we have been rendred odious in the eyes almost of all, and, as it were, made a by-word, and a hissing to all; were notwithstanding willing, according to the requirement of our Saviour, <HI>Luke</HI> 21. 19. <HI>In our patience to possesse our Souls,</HI> and silently to wait upon our God, for a clearing of our innocen∣cy, and the cleannesse of our hands in his eye-sight: But lately having had a view of a Declaration, dated the 12th, of <HI>December</HI> last, made by some Persons of the particular Judgment, in which some others of another perswasion have joyned, to the which in severall particulars we cannot in the least assent; We therefore thought it our bounden Duty for the vindication of that Truth, which we are in present profession and practice of, as also fearing lest they having declared to publick view, we by our silence should be looked upon, either to be of the same Judgment with them in what they have declared, or else guilty of all or some of those five Particulars they in that Declaration say the Baptists in general are charged withall; have therefore set pen to paper, and shall first give a particular of the said five Charges, and then, as in the presence of God, lay down our real Judgments, and Perswasions, grounded upon Scripture record, to those Charges; by which it will be apparent that we are not guilty of them at all, and that we differ from
<PB N="50" REF="36"/>
the said Declarers in point of Judgment; and if we shall in any thing therein derogate from the minde of God, we shall desire in the Spirit of love to be rectified by better Judgments, from the word of truth, and shall think our selves happy gainers in such a Christian reproof. Say they, we being mis-represented to the Nation;</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. <HI>As such as are opposite to Magistracy.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. <HI>That we would destroy the Publick Ministry of the Nation, who differ from us in some things about Religion,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>3. <HI>That we do countenance the People called</HI> Quakers, <HI>in their irregular practice.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>4. <HI>That we do endeavour a toleration of all miscarriages, in things Ecclesiastical and Civil, under pretence of Liberty of Conscience.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>5. <HI>That we desire to murther and destroy those that differ from us in matters of Religion.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>To the first, we positively say, that we are so far from opposing Magistracy, as that it would be to us matter of great rejoycing to know who were our Magistrates: But farr greater to see such set up who are men fearing God, and hating covetousness, that so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> might be duly executed without respect of persons, and Judgment <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> down like water, and righteousness like a mighty stream; that so there might be no more leading into captivity, &amp; that complaining in our streets might have an end: But for our parts to take a carnal weapon in our hands or use the least violence either to support or pull down the worst▪ or to set up or maintain the best of men, we look not upon it to be our duty in the least; much lesse to have a thought of endeavouring to set up our selves, either directly or indirectly; for were we abilitated and furnished with such endowments as might render us capable of being Rulers, yet could we not allow our selves to act as Magistrates, because we are a People <HI>chosen out of the world,</HI> John 15. 19. and look upon ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> selves as <HI>Pilgrims and Strangers in the earth,</HI> Heb. 11. 13. 1 Pet. 2. 11. But this we know to be the mind of God, from <HI>Rom.</HI> 13. the beginning, 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2. 13. <HI>Tit.</HI> 3. 2. that we are to be <HI>subject to, and not to resist the Powers,</HI> because they be <HI>ordained of God;</HI> and as God sets them up, so he requires his Sons and Daughters to render to them <HI>Tri∣bute, Custom, Fear and Honour, Romans</HI> 13. 7. And we further declare, That it is our bounden duty i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>obedience to our God, to <HI>pray for Kings, and all that are in Authority,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>Tim.</HI> 2. 22. So that we are so far from opposing them, as that we say it is our duty to obey them, in all civil things that are agreeable to the mind of God; and if they shall require any thing from us that is contrary to his mind and will, revealed in his Holy Scriptures of truth, we say we are not to resist them; but if in
<PB N="51" REF="36"/>
conscience we cannot obey them, then we are patiently to suffer under them, whatever they shall inflict upon us for our non-obedience to their requirements: And to this we yet further declare, that it is our real Judgment, as to things Spiritual, not to own them as our Law-givers in the least, <HI>for there is one Law-giver which is able to save, and to destroy,</HI> Jam. 4. 12. which is the Lord, <HI>Isa.</HI> 33. 22. And therefore, if they shall at any time impose upon us Laws in point of worship, that is, either to worship a False God, or the true God after a false manner, we by Gods assistance shall tell them with <HI>Shadrach, Meshach,</HI> and <HI>Abednego,</HI> Dan. 3. 16. That we are not carefull to answer them in that matter, yet shall not violently resist, but with them patiently suffer under them, as aforesaid.</P>
<P>To the second, <HI>That we would destroy the publick Ministry of the Nation, that differ from us in some things about Religion;</HI> We do declare, that if there be a destruction intended between us, we must leave it at their doors, and desire them to Judge between the all-seeing God, the searcher of all hearts, and their own consciences, what they have intended by their so often pressing <HI>Parliament</HI> men, from time to time, for a suppression of all that are not of their Judgment in matters of Religion: and upon search made, if they find themselves guilty of a desire of any such destruction to us, we shall beg them in Gods fear, to break off that evil by timely Repentance, and make their Peace with God; as for our parts, we are so far from desiring any revenge against them, or any other that shal desire or endeavour our ruine, as that in the presence of God, we shall rather pitty than envy them, and according to the requirement of our Law-giver, <HI>Mat.</HI> 5. 44. <HI>pray for them,</HI> and their conversion, not at all in the least desiring or, endeavouring their confusion. That there are many things wherein the publick Ministry of the Nation and we differ, in matters of Religion, both in Doctrine and Discipline, is very clear; and that we designe or so much as desire the destruction of them, or any other persons whatsoever, for such differences, or any other matters concerning our selves, we hope in our further answer to this, and to the fourth and fifth Particulars, we shall manifest to be as clear; and also therein discover our selves to be the <HI>peaceable Lambs of Christ▪</HI> John 21. 15. <HI>the great Shepherd and Bishop of our souls,</HI> 1 Pet. 2. 25. 1 Pet. 5 4. Heb. 10. 20. Who doth require us to <HI>learn of him, for he is lowly and meek,</HI> Matth. 11. 29. Yet notwithstanding, we do declare, when or wherever some of us shall conveniently meet with any of them, either in private or in publick, we shall resolve (God assisting▪ us) to <HI>contend earnestly with them, for the Faith once delivered to the Saints,</HI> according to that Exhortation of the Spirit of God by his
<PB REF="37"/>
Apostle, <HI>Jude</HI> 3. and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them, and all oppositions, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> whatsoever, as good <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of Jes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Chri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> 2 Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>. 2, 3. <HI>fight the good fight of Faith,</HI> 1 Tim. 6. 12. In which combate we are confident, we neither shall hazard life, nor draw blood; for through mercy we can say, with our Apostle, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 10. 3, 4. <HI>That though we live in the flesh, yet w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> war not after the flesh, for the weapons of our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> not carnal.</HI></P>
<P>To the third, <HI>That we <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Peopl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> called</HI> Quakers <HI>in their irregular practice.</HI> To this we answer, and God is o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> witness, we lie not, that we are so far from countenancing the <HI>Quakers,</HI> or our selves in any irregular practice, as that if we our selves be found i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> any such actings, we shall not violen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ly oppose, but patiently subject to such penalties as the breach of such Lawes calls for: it would have been well, if the Afsertors had declared wherein this Irregular practice doth consist, that so we might have given a more particular answer; yet we hope by what hath and shall be declared, it will be easily judged, that w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> for our parts are no such people as the Baptists generally are reported, and some <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hew themselves to be.</P>
<P>To the fourth, <HI>That we endeavo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r a tolleration of all misc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>riages in things Ecclesiastical and Civil, under <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of Liber<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y of Conscience▪</HI> If by endeavouring a tolleration of all miscarriages in things Ecclesiastical, the Assertors intend amongst our selves in our own Assembles: we shall answer them, as in the presence of God, the searcher of all hearts; That we are so far from any such Toleration, as that we at this very day go under a reproach by that people we formerly walked withal, because in the reallity of our souls, and the integrity of our hearts, we cannot allow of some things, that we judge to be of that nature amongst them; we well knowing, that the Lord Christ requires a perfect observation of, and a universal obedience to all things whatsoever he commanded, <HI>Mat.</HI> 28. 20. And that as well to what hath been laid down by his Apostles, given in by the incomes of that Spirit that was to lead them into all truth, and to shew them things to come, <HI>Iohn</HI> 16. 13. which are also the commands of Christ, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 14. 37. as to those that were laid down by himself, <HI>Iohn</HI> 18. 12, 15. So that we positively say, that if we shall allow of any miscarriages either in Doctrine or Discipline amongst our selves, to 'thwart the mind of Christ revealed in his Scriptures of truth, we can expect no better answer from him, than a Proclamation of our Worship to be a vain Worship, as once he declared against the Jews, <HI>Matth.</HI> 15. 9. And therefore if miscarriages rise amongst us, we are to bring such miscarriages to the the touch-stone of Gods word, and so weigh them in the ballance of the Sanctuary, and finding them either too heavy or too light, that is, either adding or diminishing from or to the mind of Christ,
<PB N="53" REF="37"/>
we are the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> to repair to those wholsome Lawes left us in Scripture record, for the regulating of such miscarriages, according to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of them, as they are private or publick, or more or less in their several agravations; and as they are committed by persons standing in such o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> such relations: We say the more of this, because most persons think, and many do not stick to say, that we live and act in things Ecclesiastical, as Libertines, and without Church-Government, because we withdraw our selves from the publick Assemblies; But did such persons rightly consider, what the Discipline of the Ministry of the Nation is, in their Parochial Assemblies, who professe themselves to be the true Spouse and Church of Christ, and compare it with the mind of Christ revealed in the Scriptures of Truth, who gives Law<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> to his Church, which is that body of which he himself is the head, <HI>Ephes.</HI> 4. 15. 21. 22. <HI>Col.</HI> 1. 18. 2. 19. They would then finde themselves to be the Libertines, and not we; and therefore we shall earnestly desire all that are unacquainted with the true Discipline of the Church of Christ, well to weigh, and seri∣ously to consider these Statute Laws of Christ, in that case provided, 2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 3. 16. 2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 4. 1, 2. <HI>Ephes.</HI> 5. 11. <HI>Matth.</HI> 18. 15. 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 5. 12, 19, 20. 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 6. 5. 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 1. 20. <HI>Tit.</HI> 3. 10. 2 <HI>Thes.</HI> 2. 15. 2 <HI>Thes.</HI> 3. 10. 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 5. 4, 9, 11. The which, as we will answer the contrary at the great Day of account, we dare not in the least wilfully violate or neglect. But if by miscarriage<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> in things Ecclesiastical, they mean that we endea∣vour a Tolleration of all miscarriages amongst them in their Assemblies, we shall in the presence of God clear our selves and say, we have nothing at all to do with them, in such matters; for we say, they are without as to us, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 5. 12, 13. And so we look upon our selves to be as to them: And if any one shall seem to be troubled at this term Without, and object and say, that we are all the Creation of God, and what need these expressions of, <HI>Stand at a distance, I am more holy than you;</HI> To such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e shall answer in the Spirit of Love and Meeknesse, and God is our Witnesse without OSTENTATION, that it is true, all the Sons and Daughters of <HI>Adam</HI> are the Sons and Daughters of God by Creation, but few by Regeneration and Adoption, for <HI>Many are called, but few are chosen,</HI> Matth, 20. 16. for not the <HI>hear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rs of the Law, but the doors shall be justified,</HI> Rom. 2. 13. And not every one that saith, <HI>Lord, Lord, shall enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, but he that doth the will of the Father,</HI> Matth. 7. 21. We well know, that many will say, these are hard sayings, and cannot well bear them; But to such we shall give a direction in our Post-s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ript, where from one of us they may expect, and we hope also find good satisfaction as to the tearm Without.</P>
<P><PB N="54" REF="38"/>That we own Liberty of Conscience we confesse; but under that or any other pretence; to endeavour a Toleration of any Miscarriages, either in things Ecclesiastical, or Civil, we have given (we hope) full satisfaction; for seeing it is the will of our Master, to have the Tares and the Wheat grow together till the Harvest, <HI>Matth.</HI> 13. 30. And that our Heavenly Father doth exercise his long-suffering to the whole bulk of man-kind, <HI>not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to Repentance,</HI> 2 Pet. 3. 9. We look upon it to be our Duty to follow God, as <HI>Dear Children,</HI> and thus to <HI>walk in love,</HI> Ephes. 5. 1, 2. and therefore are <HI>like-minded,</HI> having the same love, <HI>Phil.</HI> 2. 2. And therefore do further declare, that we are as free, that all others should enjoy their Liberties, as we our selves, of what Judgment soever they be; we well knowing, that some are called at the eleve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th hour, as well as at the first and third, <HI>Matth.</HI> 20. 1, 6. And had the Apostle <HI>Paul▪</HI> been plucked up whilst he was a Tare, a Persecutor, a Blasphemer, 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 1. 13. and the chief of sin∣ners, <HI>v.</HI> 15 he had never been such choyce Wheat, to Satisfie, Refresh, Enable, Enliven, Inlighten, Encourage, build up, and Instruct, Correct, and Reprove the Building of God; 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 3. 9. the House of God, <HI>Heb▪</HI> 3. 6. the Houshold of God, <HI>Ephes.</HI> 2. 19. the Sons and Daughters of God, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 6. 18. Nor that body of which Christ is the head, <HI>Col.</HI> 1. 18. and therefore we cannot but say again, that we are as free that all others should enjoy their Liberties in the things of God, as we our selves; We well knowing, that every one must give an account of himself to God, <HI>Rom. 14. 12. for every one shall receive the things done in the body, according to what they have done, whether it be good or bad,</HI> 2 Cor. 5. 10. Matth. 25. 34, 41. But either to procure or maintain our own or others Liberties by force of Armes, or the least violence, we can find no warrant from the Scriptures of truth in the least, which is that only and alone Rule that we walk by, for all the remedy that we find there recorded is, that if they <HI>persecute us in one City, we may flee into another;</HI> and this we see acted by our Saviour himself, <HI>John</HI> 7. 1. and by his Parents, <HI>Matth.</HI> 2. 14. and the Apostle <HI>Peter, Acts</HI> 12. 17. and Saint <HI>Paul, Acts</HI> 9. 25, 26. 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 11. 33. And to follow our Master, and to tread in the footsteps of the Flock of God gone before us, we judge it very safe; but to resist by force of Armes, or use the least violence, we judge unwarrantable.</P>
<P>To the fift and last particular, <HI>That we would murther and destroy those that differ from us in Matters of Religion.</HI></P>
<P>To this we cannot but answer, that so to do we judge were not so much as common Humanity, much less Religion or Christianity; but our Religion is, <HI>pure and undefiled before God and our Father,</HI> which is,
<PB N="55" REF="38"/>
to <HI>visit the Fatherless and widdows,</HI> not to make fatherless &amp; widdows; and to visit them in their afflictions, not to murther and destroy their Relations, to bring them under Afflictions: But to this we further answer, that this and the 4th Particular we judg seem to contradict one another, for murthering and destroying for difference in matters of Religion, and Liberty of Conscience cannot stand together, nor in the eye of Reason can they be charged against one and the same persons; for murthering and destroying for difference in matters of Religion, destroyes Liberty of Conscience; and Liberty of Conscience swallows up and drowns murthering, and destroying for difference in matters of Religion; so that it argues, that the Assertors of these things are yet in Babylon, and Confusion, with those our Apostle writ of, in 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 1. 7. not <HI>knowing well what they say, nor whereof they do affirm;</HI> yet notwithstanding seeing we are therewith charged, in order to the discharging our selves of this confused burthen, we shall in the singleness of our souls yet farther discover our real judgments, as to the main intent of the Charge, which is murthering and destroying; and add this further, that we read of a threefold Sword in Scripture.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. The Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God, <HI>Ephes.</HI> 6. 17.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. The Sword of Justice, which is the Magistrates Sword, <HI>Rom.</HI> 13. 4</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. The Sword of Steel, usually so called, which is the Sword of slaughter, <HI>Isa.</HI> 1. 20. <HI>Ezek.</HI> 9. 1, 2.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>The first of these we are required to take to us, and <HI>put on,</HI> Ephes. 6. 11, 13, 17. and <HI>thus</HI> to be <HI>strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might,</HI> whose might was evidenced once, again and again, by using this Sword skilfully, <HI>Matth.</HI> 4. 4, 7, 9. <HI>For it is mighty through God, to the pulling down of strong holds, casting down imaginations, and every high thing, that exalteth it self against the knowledg of God, and bringing into captivity,</HI> &amp;c. and having in a readiness to <HI>revenge</HI> all <HI>disobedience,</HI> 2 Cor. 10. 4, 5, 6. and is <HI>profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Instruction in Righteousness, that the man of God may be perfect, thorowly furnished unto all good works,</HI> 2 Tim. 3. 16, 17. <HI>for we wrastle not with flesh and blood, but against principalities, powers, the Rulers of the d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>kness of this world,</HI> Ephess. 6. 12. not for nor against the Magistrates, Parliaments, nor Armies of the world, the best of whose strength is flesh and not spirit, who shall be destroyed together, <HI>Isa.</HI> 31. 1, 2, 3. <HI>Mat.</HI> 26. 52.</P>
<P>As for the Sword of Justice, or the Magistrates Sword, we are to be subject to it, as we have fully declared, and not to resist it, which Sword
<PB N="56" REF="39"/>
takes revenge on no man before he be apprehended, charged, heard, and by good evidence convicted, and sentence according to the fact proved, given, and then an immediate Commission given to an Executioner, according to the Fact and Sentence, for the putting this Sword in execution.</P>
<P>But the Sword of slaughter, without examination or due consideration, is many times put in execution to the slaying and destroying of friends as well as enemies; witness those slaughters, and woundings in this City, in the late Insurrection.</P>
<P>And for our acting in this Sword, we can find no warrant from Scriptures in the least, for that sword being once procured by <HI>Peter,</HI> and another of the Disciples, and that by an immediate Commission from Christ, the work being finished for which it was intended, we find an immediate and peremptory command for the sheathing it again; and this reason rendred from the lip of truth it self, <HI>for all they that take the sword shall perish with the sword,</HI> Matth. 26. 52. <HI>for whosoever will save his life shall lose it,</HI> Matth. 16. 25. and we find no tolleration in Holy Writ to the people of God for the drawing it again in the least, neither by Precept or Example.</P>
<P>But lest this countermand should not be looked upon to be a sufficient warrant for its continuance in its place, by the People of God for the time to come, the Lord Christ, amongst several other weighty things, sent to the seven Churches in <HI>As<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>a,</HI> and in them to us, by <HI>John</HI> the Revelator, is not backward to remind them, and us in them of it again, as a matter of no small concernment; and (as we judg) lest it should not be taken so much notice of by us in this our day, as he would have it, he bringeth it in, in the midst of a Discourse, not long before the rise of the Man of Sin, when one of the heads of the Beast is wounded, as it were to death, and that deadly wound was healed, <HI>Rev.</HI> 13. 3. intimating thus much, as we apprehend, That as Kingly power hath had a wound in these Nations, even as it were unto death, so we know, that the design of God shall be brought about, and the Scriptures must be fulfilled, for that deadly wound shall be healed, <HI>Rev.</HI> 13. 3. and we finding the spirits of the generality of the People of the three Nations very high in this juncture of time, in the behalf of Kingly Government, like <HI>Israel</HI> of old, 1 <HI>Sam:</HI> 8, so that by the face of things, as they appear to us in this last change, we do discern, as through a glasse darkly, that the deadly wound is now going to be healed, although we do really judge, that several that are in present eminent power, intend no such thing, no more then the Jews in the crucifying of Christ, intended the bringing the great design, and fore-appointment of God about, <HI>Acts</HI> 2.
<PB N="57" REF="39"/>
23. By all which we judge, that Caution was intended chiefly to us <HI>upon whom the ends of the world is come;</HI> and lest we should not be so mindful of our Duties as he would have us, he makes as it were a Procla∣mation, to bespeak our better attention to what he intendeth, &amp; saith, <HI>Rev.</HI> 13. 9, 10. <HI>He that hath an ear to hear let him hear; he that leadeth into captivity, shall go into captivity; he that killeth with the sword, shall be killed with the sword.</HI> Here is the Faith and Patience of the Saints, that whilest others are leading into Captivity, and killing with the Sword, to pull down, or set up this or that Power, Man, or Government; to give a deadly Wound to Kingly Power, or to heal that deadly Wound again, that then the People of God should in their <HI>Patience possess their souls,</HI> and in the midst of these Revolutions, exercise their Faith, as once that Prophet did, <HI>Hab.</HI> 3. 17. and faithfully to depend upon God for his Preservation and Protection, keeping themselves pure and undefiled from leading into Captivity, or killing with the Sword, lest they themselves be led into captivity, &amp; killed by the sword; thereby evidencing themselves to be the <HI>peaceable Flock of Christ, chosen out of the world,</HI> Joh. 15. 19. and following their <HI>Master the Lord and Prince of Peace,</HI> Isa. 9. 6. 2 <HI>Thes.</HI> 3. 16. being regulated by his requirements in the <HI>Gospel of Peace, Romans</HI> 10. 15. <HI>Ephesians</HI> 6. 5. having received from the <HI>God of Peace,</HI> Rom. 15. 33. Rom. 16. 20. 2 Cor. 13. 11. that <HI>Spirit,</HI> whose <HI>fruits</HI> is <HI>Love, Joy, Peace, long-Suffering, Gentleness, Goodness, Faith, Meckness and Temperance, against which there is no Law;</HI> that as they are Christs, so they should evidence that they have <HI>crucified the flesh with the affections and iusts,</HI> Gal. 5. 22, 23, 24. But lust being not crucified, it breaks forth into wars and fightings; for when <HI>men lust and have not,</HI> then they <HI>kill and desire to have,</HI> James 4. 1, 2. and when the People of God shall act thus, the Spirit of God brands them with those Ignominious Names of Adulterers, and Adulteresses, informing them, that what they are fighting for, is enmity against God; and that if they obtain it, they are enemies to God, <HI>James</HI> 4. 4. and we well knowing, that whilest we are Friends to the world, we are Enemies to God; dare not in the least have to do in the world, so as to set up our selves, or to side with any, either in setting up, or pulling down; And how can a mans love to the world be evidenced more, than in venturing his life for it? according to that saying of our Sa∣viour, <HI>John</HI> 15. 13.</P>
<P>And we further Declare, That as we are to be <HI>a peaceable People</HI> up∣on the account of Action, so we look upon it to be our Duty, to keep our selves from Oaths, Engagements, and Covenants, either <HI>For</HI> or <HI>Against</HI> this or that Person, Government, or Persons whatsoever: <HI>For because</HI>
<PB N="58" REF="40"/>
<HI>of SWEAPING the Land mourneth,</HI> Jerem. 23. 10. <HI>For the Lord hath a Controversie with the Inhabitants of the Land, because there is no Truth, nor Mercy, nor Knowledge of God in the Land; for by</HI> SWEARING, <HI>and Lying, and Killing, and Stealling, and committing Adultery, they break forth, and bloud toucheth bloud,</HI> saith the Prophet, <HI>Hos.</HI> 4. 1, 2, 3. And saith the same Prophet, <HI>Hos.</HI> 10. 3, 4. <HI>They have spoken words,</HI> SWEARING <HI>falsly, in making a Covenant;</HI> THUS <HI>Judgement springeth up as Hemlock in the furrows of the field;</HI> and we not knowing what the Cabinet Counsel of God is in this our day, upon the account of Government, dare not in the least have so much as a thought to Engage in any such thing, <HI>lest we be found Fighters against God;</HI> according to the saying of <HI>Gamaliel,</HI> though in a∣nother case, <HI>Acts.</HI> 5. 39.</P>
<P>And therefore do Declare our Resolution herein, That we shall not (God assisting us) enter into any Engagement whatsoever, upon any such account; Yet shall this say again, That we shall not violently re∣sist the Imposers of any such Engagements, but shall patiently suffer the penalty of our non-obedience, as aforesaid.</P>
<P>And we further Declare, as in the presence of God, who is the searcher of all hearts, That as it hath been some of our great trouble for a long time, to see some of those that are in the same Faith and Order with us, so acting; so it is now become even an overwhelming burthen upon our Souls, to see them generally running such a precipitant course; by which actings of theirs, the mouths almost of all men are opened against them, and that Truth they profess, most ignominiously branded and reproached.</P>
<P>And therefore we further Declare, That in the sight of God, Angels, and Men, that we bear our Testimony against them in their present act∣ings, and cannot stand by them, nor have Communion with them therein, nor with those that strengthen their hands in standing by them; and must tell them in the words of our Savior, <HI>Luke</HI> 9. 55. <HI>That they know not what Spirit they are of;</HI> for, <HI>the Son of Man</HI> (their Master) <HI>came not to destroy mens lives, but to save them.</HI> The Premises considered, we shall Appeal to the Judgement of all Rational men, whether we are guilty of what we are Charged withal, or not; Yet if they shall still go on notwithstanding to use us Reproachfully, for the Name of Christ, we shall be so far from Endeavouring or Desiring a Revenge, as that in the words of Christ, we shall in our Requests at the Throne of Grace, cry out and say, <HI>Father, Forgive them, they know not what they do.</HI></P>
<DIV2 TYPE="postscript">
<PB N="59" REF="40"/>
<HEAD>POST-SCRIPT.</HEAD>
<P>FOrasmuch, as the said Declarers, in their Answer to the First Particu∣lar in their Declaration, do call the <HI>Independants</HI> and <HI>Presbyterians</HI> their Christian Friends; the which, however it is they so complement with them, yet in reality (we judge) they cannot own them as such upon a Scripture account; as also, because one Mr. <HI>William Alleyn,</HI> in a Book lately by him Published, Intituled, <HI>A Retractation to Separation:</HI> In which Book, in the whole currant of it, all the Scriptures that he brings which were written by the immediate directions and Incomes of the Ho∣ly Spirit of God, to the Churches, as they were in the Faith and Order of the Gospel, he applyeth to, and also for, and in the behalf of <HI>Episcopals, Independants,</HI> and <HI>Presbyterians,</HI> who are opposite both to the Doctrine and Discipline of those Churches, he intending thereby to perswade us, if possible, to a Belief, That they are the true and visible Members of that Body, of which Christ is the Head; the which Book, by Gods assistance, is intended suddenly to be Answered by one of our Society, who Resol∣veth to entitle it, <HI>The Retractators Work, Scaned; Or, the Conceptions and Supposals of Mr.</HI> W. Alleyn, <HI>regulated by Scripture Record:</HI> in which, with other things, a Gospel-Believer, or a true Church of Christ, upon a Gospel account, is intended to be stated; the which is hoped will be so plain, that it may prove Instrumental to the Undeceiving of some that are under a Deceipt, by means of that, and such deceitful Discourses as that is; In which Answer it is farther hoped, That those that are un∣satisfied with our tearm <HI>Without,</HI> in our Answer in our Declaration to the Fourth Particular, may receive also good satisfaction; and in the mean time we desire all to take notice; That though we thus speak, yet we have good thoughts of those Friends that go under those Denominations, and do own them, and all others, of all other Opinions whatsoever, in Union, so far as they own God, Christ, and their Truths; but to own the best of men to be Members of that Body, of which Christ is the Head, and so to have Communion with them, either to make them our mouth in Prayer to God for us, or Gods mouth in speaking forth his Truths to us, or in Breaking of Bread at the Table of the Lord, we cannot own them in the least; Our Reasons, we hope, will be fully laid down in the Answer to the said Book.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Henry Adis. Richard Pilgrim.
Abel Hutchins. William Cox.
In behalf of themselves, and those that walk with them.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<PB REF="41"/>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI></P>
<P>Re-printed by <HI>S. Dover,</HI> in <HI>Christophers Alley,</HI> in <HI>Martins</HI> near <HI>Aldersgate,</HI> 1660. And formerly Printed the 12th Day of the 11th Month, Heathenishly called in Honour to their god <HI>Janus, January,</HI> 1659.</P>
<PB REF="41"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

