<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The glorious kingdom of Christ, described and clearly vindicated against the bold asserters of a future calling and reign of the Jews, and 1000 years before the conflagration and the asserters of the 1000 years kingdom after the conflagration : opening the promise of the new heaven and earth and the everlastingness of Christ's kingdom against their debasing it, who confine it to 1000 years ... : answering Mr. Tho. Beverley ... in his twelve principles and catechisms, &amp;c. / by Richard Baxter ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A26934</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing B1277</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R5007</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12318058</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12318058</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">59413</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A26934)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59413)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 201:3)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The glorious kingdom of Christ, described and clearly vindicated against the bold asserters of a future calling and reign of the Jews, and 1000 years before the conflagration and the asserters of the 1000 years kingdom after the conflagration : opening the promise of the new heaven and earth and the everlastingness of Christ's kingdom against their debasing it, who confine it to 1000 years ... : answering Mr. Tho. Beverley ... in his twelve principles and catechisms, &amp;c. / by Richard Baxter ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[6], 73, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by T. Snowden, for Thomas Parkhurst ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1691.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Dedication: To Mr. Increase Mather, the learned and pious rector of the New-England college (now in London).</NOTE><NOTE>Advertisement: p. 73 and p. [1] at end.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in British Library.</NOTE><NOTE>Marginal notes.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Beverley, Thomas. --  Catechism of the kingdom of our Lord Jesus Christ, in the thousand years.</TERM><TERM>Eschatology --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Millennium.</TERM><TERM>Jews --  Restoration.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A26934">
<STC T="W">B1277</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12318058</BIBNO>
<VID>59413</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>The Glorious
<HI>Kingdom of Christ, Described</HI> and clearly <HI>Vindicated,</HI></P>
<P>Against the bold Asserters of a Future Calling and Reign
of the Jews, and 1000 years before the Conflagration.</P>
<P>And the Asserters of the 1000 years Kingdom after the
Conflagration.</P>
<P>Opening the Promise of the New Heaven and Earth, and
the Everlastingness of Christ's Kingdom, against their
debasing it, who confine it to 1000 years, which with
the Lord is but as One day.</P>
<P>Answering Mr. <HI>Tho. Beverley,</HI> who imposed this Task,
by his oft and earnest Challenges of all the Doctors
and Pastors, and his Censure of Dissenters as <HI>Semi-Sadduces
of the Apostasie,</HI> in his Twelve Principles
and Catechisms, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>By <HI>RICHARD BAXTER,</HI> whose Comfort is
only the Hope of that Kingdom.</P>
<BIBL>2 Peter 3. 13.</BIBL>
<Q>We according to his Promise look for New Hea∣vens
and a New Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteousness. <HI>(Af∣ter
the Conflagration.)</HI></Q>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by <HI>T. Snowden,</HI> for <HI>Thomas Parkhurst</HI> at the <HI>Bible</HI> and
<HI>Three Crowns,</HI> the lower end of <HI>Cheapside.</HI> 1691.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To Mr. Increase Mather, the Learned and Pious Rector
of the New-England Colledge (now in London.)</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Worthy Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>WHen it befalleth me to differ from men more judicious, it
is not because I have a greater esteem of my Intellect
than of theirs, but because that which to me seemeth
Evidence constraineth me. And when I publish that
seeming Evidence, it is not in expectation that any receive it, save
those that by impartial deliberate thoughts, discerning it, are con∣vinced
by it. I therefore craved your censure of these Papers, because
I found that you had long and laboriously studied the Controversie,
and were confident of much of that which I write against: I have
read no man that hath handled it with so much Learning and Mo∣deration
as you have done: And therefore I knew no man fitter, if
I err, to detect my Errours. And as your Candour is rather for my
publishing, than suppressing these Papers; so truly I am so far from
disliking a true Confutation of this (or any Errour that I shall pub∣lish)
that I therefore direct these lines to you, to intreat you, to
write (whether I be alive or dead) your Reasons against any mo∣mentous
or dangerous Errour which you shall here find: That as we
thus friendly consent to such a Collision, or rather Communication,
as may kindle some further sparks of light, the Readers may be helpt
by comparing all, the better to find out the truth.</P>
<P>Seeing the chief Writers for the <HI>Millennium</HI> are Conformists,
(and men of greatest Learning and Piety among them) as <HI>Jos.
Mede,</HI> Dr. <HI>More,</HI> Dr. <HI>Twisse,</HI> (then conformable) Dr. <HI>Cressoner,</HI>
Mr. <HI>Beverley,</HI> Mr. <HI>J. M.</HI> &amp;c. I hope they will not take it for scan∣dalous
in you and me herein to differ.</P>
<P>You have partly relieved me against some Accusations of Singu∣larity,
when you tell your Readers (in the Preface to your English
<HI>Mystery)</HI> that so many think the Thousand years past already, <HI>viz.</HI>
<Q>That <HI>Aretius, Bilney, Wickleffe, Walter Brute, Benno
Cardin,</HI> &amp;c. thought that the time began at the Birth of Christ.</Q></P>
<P><Q>That <HI>Viegas, Pererius, Augustine, Primasius, Beda, An∣dreas,</HI>
thought it began at the Passion of Christ: That <HI>Junius,
Pareus, Dent, Broughton, Bibliander, Usher,</HI> thought it be∣gan
at the Destruction of the Jewish State: And that even
<HI>Brightman, Majer, Forbes, Willet, Gerhard, Guild, Cart∣wright,</HI>
as well as <HI>Alcaser Castiglius,</HI> begin it at <HI>Constantines</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
Inthronization;</Q> which is as the same with <HI>John Fox</HI> (Acts and
Mon. Vol. 1. p. 111.) <HI>Grotius, Hamond,</HI> and many others that
begin it at the Fall of <HI>Maxentius,</HI> or <HI>Licinius,</HI> or at <HI>Constan∣tines</HI>
Edict for Christians, from whence to the <HI>Ottoman</HI> Empire
say they was just a Thousand years: <Q>And that the Conversion of
the Jews will not be till the present state of this World be near its
end, you hold with <HI>Beda, Estius, Acosta, Stella, Zanchy, Per∣kins,
Vossius, Finnus.</HI></Q></P>
<P><Q>And page 20. you believe that the 1290 years in <HI>Dan.</HI> are past
long ago, as you say, <HI>Arnold. de Villa nova,</HI> The Author
of the Problem Mr. <HI>Stevens, Mede, Alsted, Lud. Capellus,</HI>
Dr. <HI>Twisse</HI></Q> (to whom I may add many more.)</P>
<P><Q>Though you are plain, that the Thousand years are not before
the Conflagration, and that Antichrist shall not be finally destroy∣ed
till then (though <HI>Rome</HI> shall) and that a Thousand years will
be but a part, a morning of the last great day, in which the Just
only shall rise, and that the evening will be the time of the rising of
the unjust to destruction, and the space that is till Christ give up the
Kingdom, <HI>&amp;c.]</HI></Q> Yet because oft-times you joyn the Jews earthly
Monarchy so obscurely with the Resurrection, without mentioning
the intervening Conflagration, I intreat you in your next to make
your self therein more intelligible: And give some proof that the
wicked shall not be raised nor judged till after the Thousand years,
(neither those dead before, nor those found alive at the Conflagra∣tion:
seeing many words of Christ and <HI>Paul</HI> seem plainly to assert a
common Judgment, of Sheep and Goats, just and unjust, at the same
time of Christs coming.</P>
<P>As to my Opinion, that Pagan <HI>Rome</HI> was <HI>Babylon,</HI> I have so
much to say for it, as must not here be repeated: If that cast away
my reputation with any or many, let it go: He is unworthy of reputa∣tion
that cannot give it up for Truth. The Revelation hath much
plain and easie to them that read it without prejudice (who I doubt
are few.) I only fix on so much, and leave the rest to wiser men, with∣out
dishonouring of their Judgments, so be it they give not up our
Cause to the Papists, by laying it upon things doubtful or untrue,
while we have sure and plain proof enough against them.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your unworthy Fellow-servant, RICH. BAXTER.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>London, <DATE>Decemb. 19. 1690.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="table of contents">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE
CONTENTS.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Chap. I.</HI> THE Kingdom of Christ as described in the
Scripture.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Chap. II.</HI> An Answer to Mr. <HI>Tho. Beverleys</HI> Twelve Prin∣ciples,
and much of his Catechism of the <HI>Millennium,</HI>
necessitated by his many provocations, and challenge to all
the Doctors and Pastors of the Church, and his censure of
Dissenters as Semi-Sadduces of the Apostasie.</ITEM>
<ITEM>His first Principle examined. Of delivering up the King∣dom
to the Father. Christs Kingdom began before the
(disputed) Thousand years, proved. His Enemies much
subdued before.</ITEM>
<ITEM>What is meant by Giving up the Kingdom? The longer
continuance of Christs Kingdom, proved. Of Christs be∣ing
subject to the Father. And God All in All.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Whether it be true that Christ was eternally a Man, having
an eternal Kingdom as Man; but not as the Son of Man
after the <HI>Millennium?</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Whether out Union with God and Christ, <HI>Joh.</HI> 17. be that Then
God shall be All in All as before the World began? Whe∣ther
we were in God before the World began, and how?
The tendency of this Doctrine. Of Mr. <HI>T. B</HI>'s ambi∣guous
Language.</ITEM>
<ITEM>His 2d, 3d, 4th, 5th and 6th Principles.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The 7th Principle. That those found on Earth shall be pre∣sently
caught up at the Lords Coming, and not stay a
Thousand years after; proved fully: And the limitation
of a Thousand years confuted.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="4"/>
The 8th Principle. The Thousand years further confuted.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The 9th Principle more of the Giving up the Kingdom.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The 10th, 11th and 12th Principles. Of the Fifth Monar∣chy,
<HI>&amp;c.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>More of Mr. <HI>B</HI>'s. Ambiguities.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Chap. III.</HI> Of those <HI>Millenaries</HI> that place the Thousand
years Reign before the Conflagration.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Chap. IV.</HI> That the Ten Tribes will never be found and
called, if they never were so heretofore.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Chap. V.</HI> The Ten Tribes were not lost nor extinct, proved.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Chap. VI.</HI> What Conversion the Twelve Tribes have alrea∣dy
had?</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Chap. VII.</HI> Whether there be any <HI>Jerusalem</HI> Monarchy of
Jews, or any further Conversion of them, more than of
other men promised by God? The pretended proofs ex∣amined.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Chap. VIII.</HI> Reasons for the Negative humbly offered to
Tryal. And some Objections answered.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Chap. IX.</HI> Of the New Earth; what is certain, and what
uncertain?</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Chap. I. The Kingdom of Christ, as described by the
S. Scriptures.</HEAD>
<P>BEing by Mr. <HI>T. Beverleys</HI> importunate requests and
challenges, and his heavy Accusation of Dissenters
from him as <HI>Semi-Sadduces of the Apostasie,</HI> urged to
give an account of the Reasons of my dissent from Him
and others of the Millenary Judgment, it is meet that I first
tell him what I take for the true Scripture Doctrine of the
Kingdom of Christ, which I am to defend. Premising my
desire to the Reader, that he will first read as presupposed
Truth, the Judicious Treatise of my dear Brother Mr. <HI>John
Corbet,</HI> of <HI>The Kingdom of God with Men:</HI> And <HI>Cluverus</HI> his
Arguments against the <HI>Millennium.</HI></P>
<P>I. GOD made Man in his own Image (Natural,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 1. 26, 27. &amp; 9. 6.</NOTE> Mo∣ral,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 11. 7.</NOTE>
and of Supereminence) in Wisdom, Righteousness, and
true Holiness;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Col. 3. 10.</NOTE> to know, love, and obey his Creator: There∣fore
they err that say, <HI>Adam</HI> had no Spiritual Holiness,
and did no Act of Holiness and Obedience before his Fall:
For else he had lived in great and constant sin: For it could
be no better for him, not to esteem God to be the chief
Good, and amiable Object; or not to Love him whom he
knew to be the best; or not to serve and obey him whom
he knew to be his Creator.</P>
<P>In this state God was to Govern him as a <HI>righteous Sub∣ject,</HI>
by the Law which obliged him to <HI>Personal, Perfect, Per∣petual
Obedience;</HI> revealed partly by the Creation, and partly
by express prohibitions and commands.</P>
<P>II. Upon Mans Fall and Forfeiture,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 3. 13, 14, 15, 16.</NOTE> GOD first pro∣nouncing
part of the penalty which he would inflict,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccles. 7. 29.</NOTE> decla∣red
his Decree so far to forgive the rest of the penalty,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hos. 13. 9.</NOTE> as
to reprieve and yet continue his faln Creature;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 34. 7.</NOTE> and to give
them a Redeemer that should overcome the Serpent that
had overcome Man,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 86. 5.</NOTE> and to make him the Captain of Salva∣tion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 28. 19.</NOTE>
and to put faln Man, and all things, and power into
his hand, for the accomplishing of this Recovering work,
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
for the glorifying of his Love and Mercy thereby. The
eternal <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the Second Person in the Trinity, being de∣signed
to this great undertaking.</P>
<P>III. Whether this Eternal Word,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 29. 29.</NOTE> did first unite it self to
the Prime Being of the Creation?<NOTE PLACE="marg">Joh. 3. 5 6, 7.</NOTE> And whe∣ther
that Prime Being was the Universal Soul
of the World,<NOTE PLACE="marg">This is written with relation to the Writings of Mr. <HI>Sterry,</HI> Dr. <HI>More.</HI> Mr. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Tur∣ner,</HI> Mr. <HI>Beverley, &amp;c.</HI> which I would not be too peremptory in my opposing.</NOTE> or there were any such Uni∣versal
Soul,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 11. 33.</NOTE> save God that is more than a Soul,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Jo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 5. 9. &amp; 40 &amp; 41. &amp; 42.</NOTE>
or it be not universal, but yet of the highest
Created Species,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of the World.</NOTE> and had any causality in the
creation or production of the rest of the
World? and whether it (and the World, as
<HI>Aristotle</HI> thought) was (except revolutions and
alterations) an eternal Effect of an eternal
first Cause, and many such cases about the Original of Souls,
are questions that God having not clearly decided by Natu∣ral
or Scripture Light, I cannot peremptorily decide, but am
lost in difficulties when I attempt it.</P>
<P>IV. Till the Incarnation of Christ,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 34. 6, 7, 8.</NOTE> the World was Go∣verned
by God, as the God of Mercy and Redemption; by
a Regiment of Grace;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 3. 15.</NOTE> which may be called the Kingdom
of Christ,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 1. &amp; 3. &amp; 8.</NOTE> as Christ was the undertaker of future Redemp∣tion:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 2. 4, 7.</NOTE>
And the World being all under a pardoning Law of
Grace,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Heb. 11. 26.</NOTE> that alloweth Repentance on hope of Mercy; God
dealt with none upon the meer terms of the Law of Perfe∣ction
or Innocence; which ceased <HI>cessante capacitate subdito∣rum:
Be innocent and live, or sin and die,</HI> is not the Law that
any are judged by.</P>
<P>V. God that first made this Law of Grace to Faln Man∣kind
in <HI>Adam</HI> and <HI>Eve,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 9.</NOTE> renewed it to all in <HI>Noah.</HI></P>
<P>VI. <HI>Abraham</HI> pleasing God above others by Faith and full
Obedience,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 22. 15. &amp; 26. 5, 24.</NOTE> God chose him to be the Father of a Peculiar
People,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 4. 3, 9.</NOTE> promising him that his Seed should be multiplied
into an eminent Policy,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gal. 3. 8, 24.</NOTE> and that the Saviour Incarnate should
be of his Seed,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Heb. 11. 8, 17.</NOTE> in whom all the Nations of the Earth should
be blessed:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Jam. 2. 23.</NOTE> Not ending the Law of Grace to the rest of
the World, but priviledging <HI>Abrahams</HI> Seed with the state of
peculiarity.</P>
<P>VI. By <HI>Moses</HI> God brought <HI>Abrahams</HI> Seed into the pro∣mised
Political State, and gave them a Law to be a Rule to
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
their Political Governours,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Moses,</HI> the Pro¦phets and Christ <HI>Mat. 5.</HI> attest all this.</NOTE> when to punish, and in what
sort and degree: And God being their Absolute Soveraign,
and their Government a Theocracy, he reserved to him∣self
the Power of Legislation in all the necessary parts, and
the choice of their Chief Rulers under him. And what the
Magistrate failed to punish according to his Law, he would
punish himself. This Law was but the Rule of their Obe∣dience,
supposing them Believers of the Promise to <HI>Abraham,</HI>
justified by Faith: But the carnal Jews were so taken up
with the outward Ceremonies and Works, that they lost the
understanding of that Justifying Promise, and the very use of
all the Types and Ceremonies, and thought to be Justified
by the bare Works or doing of what the Law required of
them as their duty. And because God had not done so by
any other Nation, they were proud of their Law, and yet
only outwardly obeyed it.</P>
<P>VIII. In the fulness of Time the Messiah came Incarnate
(after 4000 years) And then that which before was only
in Decree,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 3. 15. &amp; 5. 17.</NOTE> became a Law of Mediation or Redemption,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gal. 4. 4, 5.</NOTE> or
a Covenant between the Father and the Son in Flesh;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Heb. 4. 15. &amp; 9. 14.</NOTE> Christ
being obliged in Habit,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Pet. 1. 19.</NOTE> Act and Suffering, to do all imposed
for the Recovery of Man,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Phil. 2. 7, 8, 9, 10.</NOTE> and for this was to be King and
Lord of all, and having finished his undertaken work, to
reign for ever as God-Man with the Glorified recovered So∣ciety
as his reward in Heaven for ever.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 28. 19.</NOTE> And all power to
this End was given to him,<NOTE PLACE="marg">John 17. 3, 4.</NOTE> and all Judgment or Govern∣ment
committed to him,<NOTE PLACE="marg">John 5. 22, 23, 26, 27.</NOTE> to be exercised on lapsed Man for
Recovery, the Father judging no man, as meer Creator of
Innocent Man, till this work is done.</P>
<P>IX. When Christ Incarnate came the King came from
Heaven,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 19. 34.</NOTE> and therefore <HI>John</HI> Preached that the Kingdom of
Heaven was at hand,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Jo. 18. 37.</NOTE> and Christ first preached that it was
come and was among them;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 17. 14.</NOTE> that is,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Jo. 1. 49.</NOTE> The King promised
from Heaven to Rule the World for their Salvation.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Col. 1. 13.</NOTE> And
when he had first wrought Miracles enough to prove it,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 12. 28. &amp; 21. 43.</NOTE> that
Faith might not be precarious,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mar. 1. 15.</NOTE> and built upon his bare affir∣mation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 7. 28. &amp; 9. 27. &amp; 10. 9. &amp; 11. 20. &amp; 13. 18, 19, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> &amp; 17. 20, 21. &amp; 21. 31. 22. 16, 18.</NOTE>
he openly claimed first the Kingdom of <HI>Judea,</HI> as
of the Line of <HI>David,</HI> and caused the people to applaud him
with <HI>Hosanna</HI>'s.</P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="6"/>
But being to Redeem us as a Sacrifice by his Blood, and
to Conquer Death, and confirm his Gospel, by Dying and
Rising again, he oft foretold all this to his Disciples, and
the rejecting of him by the Jews,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 14. 17, 18.</NOTE> and their Nations, Cities
and Temples ruin for it, and his purpose to cease the Mo∣saical
Politie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 12. 10.</NOTE> and to make his Church more Great and
Catholick by the Calling of the Gentiles;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 10. 7.</NOTE> especially the
<HI>Roman</HI> Empire.</P>
<P>X. At his Resurrection he took more solemn possession
of his Kingly Government.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 28. 19.</NOTE> And first Commissioned the
Twelve Apostles whom he had before made Preachers to
the Jews,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mark 16. 16, 17.</NOTE> to continue their Ministry to them (in a num∣ber
related to the Twelve Tribes) till Persecution should
expel them,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 23. 37.</NOTE> and then to do their best to make all Nations
(as such) his Disciples,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 11. 20, 23, 24, 25, 26.</NOTE> Baptizing them (as the Entrance
into his Kingdom) into the Name of the Father,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 11. 15.</NOTE> the Son,
and the Holy Ghost, and there teaching them to observe all
his Commands delivered to those Apostles, and promising
to be with them to the End of the World.</P>
<P>XI. By this and more it appeareth that a great triumphant
Kingdom on Earth,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 11. 17. &amp; 19. 6.</NOTE> and National Churches, which are no∣thing
but Christian Kingdoms, was at first in Christs Inten∣tion,
though the Embrio and Infancy anteceding, it was
to be first in Execution: For he commanded the Discipling
of Nations, and would have gathered <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> and not
cut them off, nor taken the Kingdom of God from them,
but for their unbelief.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts 1. 25.</NOTE> And the number of Twelve was by
<HI>Matthias</HI> to be made up,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mar. 28. 20.</NOTE> to shew their relation to the Jews
National Church State, till Persecution drove them to the
Gentiles, and then <HI>Paul</HI> and <HI>Barnabas</HI> were added.</P>
<P>The Apostles have Successors in all the parts of their
Office, which is to be continued to the End, but not in the
parts that were extraordinary, peculiar and temporary.</P>
<P>XII. Christ by the Holy Ghost (which he promised to
send to be his powerful Agent) propagated a holy Genera∣tion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">John 14. 16, 26. &amp; 15. 26. &amp; 16. 17.</NOTE>
and by his Messengers Preaching (his Resurrection
and Kingdom especially) and the Miracles which they
wrought,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts 2. 37, 38. &amp; 21. 20.</NOTE> he confirmed his Gospel;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 7.</NOTE> And Converted quick∣ly
many Myriads of the Jews, and after far greater numbers
of the Gentiles: Thus preparing materials or subjects for his
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
more visible Kingdom of Power on Earth; Himself reign∣ing
over all in Heaven.</P>
<P>XIII. That his Subjects might know the Nature and
Terms of his Covenant and Government (which was to
bring them to a Heavenly Kingdom) he not only requi∣red
their Covenant-Consent to forsake the Flesh and this
World,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 14.</NOTE> and the Devil,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 8. 29.</NOTE> for that Eternal Life which he had
promised them,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 8. 17.</NOTE> but he was pleased to put them on the actu∣al
exercise of this agreement,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Thes. 2. 5. &amp; 2 Thes. 1. 6. 11.</NOTE> and to try their sincerity,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Tim. 2. 12. &amp; 3. 12.</NOTE> by
putting them often upon Sufferings and Martyrdom:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 2. 10.</NOTE> And
therein he exercised his Heavenly Power, in strengthening
them, and making them more than Conquerors, while they
went as Sheep to the slaughter; to the honour of their Lord
and Faith, and the confusion of their Persecutors.</P>
<P>XIV. Yet did he so over-power the Spirits of the Pagan
Persecutors, that of Forty Emperors, there were at most but
ten that persecuted them; so that in this Captivity and Wil∣derness
state by their liberty their numbers so increased
that they became a considerable party in their Dominions
and Armies.</P>
<P>XV. Of all these Persecutors,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The <HI>Roman</HI> History is the full proof of this.</NOTE> the Cruellest were <HI>Nero,
Domitian, Maximinus</HI> and <HI>Decius,</HI> but far above all, the last,
who were seven together <HI>(Dioclesian, Max. Herculius, Max.
Galerius, Max. Daya, Severus, Licinius, Maxentius,</HI> (and
<HI>Constantius</HI> not wholly innocent) The cruelty of their Tor∣mentors,
and the great numbers Tormented and Martyred,
is frightful even to read: By all which Christ shewed his
Heavenly Power, in the terrible punishment of all their Per∣secutors:
First in the dreadful destruction of the cursed part
of the Jews; who were by <HI>Vespasian</HI> and <HI>Titus</HI> so destroy∣ed
that 110000 of them were killed, and about 700000 Cap∣tivated:
And their State, City and Temple overthrown,
and saith <HI>Origen</HI> and <HI>Chrysostom,</HI> it is certain that they shall
never (that is, the Infidels) return to that Land.</P>
<P>And afterwards by <HI>Trajan</HI> and <HI>Adrian,</HI> in revenge of the
Murders of <HI>Barcocheba</HI> an Antichrist, near as many more
were killed; which must needs leave the Infidels few in so
small a Land, when <HI>London</HI> is supposed not to have near one
Million of Inhabitants.</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="7"/>
And as to the great Pagan Empire,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The <HI>Revelati∣on</HI> and the <HI>Roman</HI> Histo∣ry compared, prove this, and expound each other.</NOTE> (the greatest that
ever the World had) Christ rode on the White Horse a∣gainst
them Conquering, and executed on them all the
Plagues gradually numbered in the <HI>Apocalypse,</HI> the Seals, the
Trumpets, the Vials, till he had utterly overcome them
and all their Confederates: He dealt so severely with them,
that of Forty Emperors there were scarce ten or seven that
died without Murder a natural death: But they were still
in Bloody Wars with other Nations, and with one ano∣ther,
so that <HI>[The Beast that was, and Is not, and yet Is,]</HI>
became a fit description of their State: As notably suited
to <HI>Domitian</HI> at first, and to <HI>Dioclesian, Herculius,</HI> and their
Fellows at last, so all along to the ordinary Succession:
<HI>To day</HI> there was an Emperor; the next day he was kill'd,
and there was <HI>None;</HI> And yet another presently succeeded
him, and so there is one again; The Soldiers selling the
Empire to him that would give most for it, or was likest
to advance them. How dreadful a destruction did Christ
by one <HI>Constantine</HI> bring on the seven Heads and ten Horns
at last, in a very little time. So that Heaven and Earth
triumphed with Joyful Praise that <HI>Babylon</HI> was fallen, and
the Kingdoms of the World were become the Kingdoms
of the Lord and of his Christ, and he had taken to himself
his great Power and had reigned, and was setting up the
New <HI>Jerusalem</HI> (as a Fifth Monarchy) the Embrio of the
Coelestial <HI>Jerusalem</HI> in its visible Reigning Power. I am
none of those that will secure Papal <HI>Rome</HI> from an answer∣able
Name, and Guilt, and Fate: But he that will con∣vince
me that Pagan <HI>Rome</HI> was not the <HI>Babylon</HI> there meant,
or that it is not fallen, must first convince me that he is of
more credible Authority than the <HI>Apocalypse.</HI></P>
<P>XVI. O how great a change was it for poor Christi∣ans
throughout all the Empire,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Read <HI>Eusibius Eccl. Hist. L.</HI> 8. &amp; <HI>Rev.</HI> 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, &amp; 19. And the Prophets that proclaim it a great de∣liverance to the <HI>Israelites,</HI> to have their Mountains again Inhabited, and their Cities Built.</NOTE> to be brought from Scorn
and Torments, and the Martyrdom of many Thousands,
after 294 years Captivity, to be suddenly made Freemen,
to celebrate Christs Worship in the most Solemn Assem∣blies,
and to be made Lords of their <HI>Persecuting, Captivating,</HI>
Idolatrous Enemies, lately so great that no Nations could
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
stand before them. Who did the Godly desire should be in
Power, rather their Bishops that came newly out of the
Furnace of Tryal? O what a change! O what a joyful
day! And shall the success of the Devil, that quickly sow∣ed
the Tares of Covetousness, Pride and Contention among
the Clergy and Laity, tempt us to undervalue Gods great
mercy to his Church which Angels and Saints gave him so
much praise for. Emperours also had their odious Crimes;
even <HI>Constantine</HI> killed his Eldest Son <HI>Crispus,</HI> and after his
Step-mother for accusing him, and banished <HI>Athanasius:</HI>
Shall we therefore be unthankful for a Christian Empire,
which was Christs own Visible Kingdom?</P>
<P><HI>Theodosius</HI> killed the <HI>Thessalonians: Arcadius</HI> banished holy
<HI>Chrysostom-Theodosius</HI> the second, a Saint, was called an Eu∣tychian,
and so of others. <HI>David</HI> committed Murder and
Adultery: <HI>Solomon</HI> was a Monster of Lust and Voluptuous∣ness,
and at last of Revolt to favour Idols; yet were they the
peculiar Kings of Gods peculiar People; and few better
followed them.</P>
<P>All this sheweth that Christ all this while Reigned, and
left it not wholly to the Resurrection, to make his Enemies
his footstool.</P>
<P>XVII. It is not unlikely that this delivered,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mr. <HI>Potter,</HI> and many Protestant expositors <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Rev.</HI> 20. 21, 22. to speak of the Church on Earth.</NOTE> exalted state
of the Church (though after corrupted by Temptation to
Pride) was the New <HI>Jerusalem</HI> in the <HI>Embrio,</HI> of which <HI>Con∣stantinople</HI>
was the Capital Seat, as the Porch or Infancy of
the heavenly City of God, and that one as the Infant Heir,
and the other as the Possessor of the Inheritance, is described
in <HI>Rev.</HI> 20. 21. 22. But of this more fully elsewhere.</P>
<P>XVIII. The Dragon being bound up a Thousand years
from the Churches deliverance (from <HI>Constantines</HI> Edict to
the <HI>Ottoman</HI> Empire) the Church after grew corrupted:
And Papal <HI>Rome</HI> imitated Pagan <HI>Rome,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 20. 5, 6, 7, 9.</NOTE> though under more
plausible names and pretences, and exceeded them in Cruelty.
And <HI>Mahomet</HI> the Eastern Antichrist, compassed and con∣quered
<HI>Constantinople</HI> the holy City; and Christs revenge on
<HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog,</HI> the Turk and Tartarian (with the rest of the
Infidel World) are yet to come, and therefore dark.</P>
<P>XIX. At the end of this World,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Pet. 3. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</NOTE> which shall be burnt
with fire, God will make a New Heaven and Earth; in
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
which shall dwell righteousness without sin. And all things
shall be restored,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 8. 19, 20, 21.</NOTE> and the Creature delivered from the bon∣dage
of corruption, into the glorious liberty of the Sons of
God. How God will people this New Earth, he hath not
told us; whether by Creation, as by <HI>Adam,</HI> or by Transmi∣gration:
Nor yet how long it shall continue, unless for
ever as part of the endless Kingdom.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Fully proved after, <HI>Mat.</HI> 25.</NOTE> Scripture giveth us
no confinement of it to a Thousand years, but the con∣trary.</P>
<P>XX. Christs Glorious Appearance and Judgment, will be
both the triumphant concluding parts of the Kingdom of Re∣demption,
and Grace, which he will deliver up when his
Recovering work is done: And the beginning of the King∣dom
of Glory: In which, as his Reward, he will for ever
in Humane Nature be glorified, as the Mediator of <HI>Fruition,</HI>
as he was of Acquisition; and that in the Heavens. His
coming in the Air is not there to Reign a Thousand years,
but presently to Judge the World, as in <HI>Matth.</HI> 25. he de∣scribeth
it: And to confine his Kingdom in Humane Na∣ture,
and ours with him to a Thousand years, and confine it
to the Air, and the survivers on Earth, is a fiction full of
contradictions, dishonourable to Christ and his Kingdom,
uncomfortable to his Church.</P>
<P>XXI. There is but one Thousand years mentioned in
Scripture, from whence they can fetch the least shew for
their limitation; and that is only in <HI>Rev.</HI> 20. But it is most
evident that the Thousand years there mentioned was to
be before the Conflagration, and New Earth, and the Re∣surrection:
For it was to be before Satan was loosed,
and before <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog,</HI> and their numberless Armies as∣saulted
the Holy City; and before the fire from God came
on them. And the Paradise restored State of the New Earth,
in which dwelleth Righteousness, is not consistent with so
much wickedness of the Inhabitants, and Satans Power over
the Nations: Nor with a <HI>Laodicean</HI> Lukewarmness, and
danger of being spued out. They therefore that well ex∣pect
a Thousand years Reign before the Resurrection, have
no pretence to expect another <HI>Millennium</HI> after.</P>
<P>XXII. To expect a Thousand years, and that after the Fall
of Papal <HI>Rome,</HI> before the Resurrection, is a supposition
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
that this World will endure a far longer time than Chri∣stians
have hitherto believed: And that the great Sabba∣tism
is to be before the New Earth: And what a Sab∣batism
that will be, the description of <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog,</HI> and
of their <HI>Laodicea,</HI> may tell you: Far unlike a Paradise
state, when all things shall be restored, and the groaning
Creation be delivered from the bondage of Corruption,
into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God.</P>
<P>XXIII. They that assign this Thousand years on this
side the Conflagration and Resurrection, for the setting up
a Fifth Monarchy of the Converted Jews at <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> are
the grossest feigners of all the rest. Well did <HI>Jerom</HI> say,
That the Millenaries fetch their Errour from the Jews, and
would set up Judaism by it. (He that dwelt so long at
<HI>Bethlehem</HI> knew the Jews Opinions.) For (to pass by what
else is after to be said) Their very Fiction is a contra∣diction.
Were our Jews converted, they would in less
than a Hundred years be no longer a Jewish Nation: For
their state of peculiarity with the Mosaical Policy is abo∣lished
by Christ, and must never be restored: And they
must and would marry with Gentile Christians, and fall
into the Catholick Church as Rivers into the Sea, and
lose the name of Jews: So did their converted Prede∣cessors.</P>
<P>XXIV. And seeing it is not like that our now Infidel
Jews are one to a hundred of the Posterity of the first be∣lieving
Jews that have been propagated these sixteen hun∣dred
years, why should a glorious Monarchy be set up of
this self-cursed Remnant, excluding all the first-fruits, both
the sealed, <HI>Rev.</HI> 7. and all since? But if the Posterity of
all those old holy Jews were now sought for, to be sent to
<HI>Jerusalem,</HI> not one man of them would be found and
known; (of which more after.)</P>
<P>XXV. It is a marvel that the great disagreement of the
Millenaries among themselves, yet hindereth not their seem∣ing
Concord, while they can but cry up the Thousand years
Reign, though most of them know not what the words
mean. Some of them say, The Thousand years are on
Earth; and some say, They are only of the Souls of the
Martyrs and Confessors in Heaven: Some say, They are
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
both in Heaven, or in the Air, and on Earth at once.
Some say, That they shall be a Jewish Monarchy at <HI>Jeru∣salem;</HI>
and some, That it shall be of the Godly all over
the World. Some say, Christ will Reign there visibly in
his Humane Nature: Others, That he will only some∣time
appear, as he did after his Resurrection: And some,
That he will Rule there only by Reforming Christian
Princes. Some hold but one Thousand years, and some
two, (one being after the other.) Some hold two New
<HI>Jerusalems,</HI> and some but one. Some say, That the Day
of Judgment is the Thousand years (and yet that Scrip∣ture
hath not told us how long Christ will be Judging
us.) And some, That it is only the Beginning and the End
of the Thousand years, that the Judgment will take up,
and the rest will be in other Government. Some think
that Execution on Men and Devils will be but that Thou∣sand
years; which some decry. Some think that the first
Resurrection, is from an Aereal Vehicle or Body into an
Ethereal; and others that it is from earthly dust to a hea∣venly
body by transmutation of Elements: And others that
it is to be a Paradise body, like <HI>Adams</HI> before he sinned.
Other differences seem almost reconciled to some, by the
bare name of a Thousand years Reign.</P>
<P>XXVI. It is a far more glorious Christian Monarchy
which Christ by <HI>Constantine</HI> set up, than most of the Mil∣lenaries
give any probability of. 1. It was a Deliverance
from the cruellest Persecution. 2. And from the Dragons
most potent Empire. 3. A Deliverance of all Christians as
well as of Jews. 4. Without confinement to the narrow
Land of <HI>Israel.</HI> 5. A setting up of a National-Provincial
Church in <HI>Judea.</HI> 6. With the great Charges of promoting
it, by New Churches, Monasteries, Bibles, Bishops! What
could he do more? The knowledge of what hath been done
long ago, would have prevented many mens expectation of
the same.</P>
<P>XXVII. If it prove that their Millennial Doctrine, and
the Calling of the Jews, prove a meer mistake, it will not
be so small as should suspend our detection of it. Because
it is an adding to Gods Word, and fathering on him many
untruths, and so a taking of his name in vain; and a cor∣rupting
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
of his Worship while we preach, write and pray for
that which we ought not (further than we must pray for
the Conversion of all sorts of men) and a turning of mens
Zeal to promote untruths, and corrupt mens minds.</P>
<P>XXVIII. We find it so easie to possess men with a fer∣vent
Zeal for the Millenary Opinion, and so hard to make
them zealous in holy Love to God and Man, and in a hea∣venly
conversation, as may make us suspicious that both sorts
of Zeal have not the same original: I am not willing to
name some tremendous Instances of men nearly known to me,
hereabout.</P>
<P>XXIX. Our worthy Brother that hath more Learnedly
opened that Cause than any else that ever I read, by mode∣ration
hath brought the difference into so narrow a com∣pass
(in his <HI>Diatriba de signo filii hominis)</HI> that except, 1. The
Calling of the Jews, 2. And the Extending of the Day of
Judgment to a Thousand years, and that the general Resur∣rection
and Judgment of the wicked, shall begin after the
Thousand years are expired, there remaineth to great and
weighty disagreement of such with the Judgment of the
Churches.</P>
<P>XXX. Seeing we ascribe to Christs Kingdom so much
more than they that we oppose, why should they be thought
to extol his Kingdom more than we? 1. Is not Eternity
longer than a Thousand years? 2. And Heaven a more
glorious state than the Air? 3. And a New Earth inhabi∣ted
only by the righteous, better than one that is Laodicean,
or that hath such Enemies of Saints as <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog?</HI>
4. And this New Earth either everlasting, or of undeter∣mined
time, better than one but of a Thousand years du∣ration,
which is but with the Lord as One day, and about
a sixth part as durable as this corrupted World, that is un∣der
sin and curse? Is this Doctrine, or the other, more ho∣nourable
to Christ, and more comfortable to Believers, and
more evident in the Word of God?</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>Chap. II. An unwilling Answer to Mr. Tho. Beverleys
Twelve Principles, and his Catechism of the Millen∣nium;
necessitated by his many provocations of many
Ministers, and me by name, and his Challenge of all the
Doctors and Pastors of the Church, and his Censure of
the Denyers of that Millenary Reign, as SEMI∣SADDUCES
OF THE APOSTASIE.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. Reverend and truly beloved Brother,</P>
<P>I Take it for no wonder that great and many disagree∣ments
in matters of Religion are among us, while in
Professions of less Mystery (Law, Policy, Physicks, Medi∣cine,
<HI>&amp;c.)</HI> there are so many; that [so many men, so ma∣ny
minds] hath so long been a Proverb: And in such to∣lerable
cases as much endanger not <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>Souls,</HI> few
men are more for mutual forbearance and charitable con∣struction
than I am: Therefore the Millennial Opinion I
have never been a censorious opposer of, while men kept
up Peace and Charity with it.</P>
<P>But the case lately is altered, and is made a matter of
necessary Zeal, as part of the Creed and the Lords Prayer,
if not essential to the Gospel and Christianity: And very
many of the Antinomian, and Separating Opinion, that least
understand it, lay much of their Religion on it: And the
just honour of many Conformists, of the most peaceable
Principles otherwise promoteth it; such as Mr. <HI>Jos. Mede.</HI>
Dr. <HI>H. More,</HI> Dr. <HI>Cressoner,</HI> your self, Mr. <HI>M.</HI> Author of the
<HI>Midnight Cry,</HI> Mr.<HI>R. M.</HI> the Publisher (most pious men
both) and many others. And we must not now be suffered
to be silent, but must answer your provocations, or be grosly
guilty of the evil that will follow your success.</P>
<P>§ 2. The Millenary Opinion was indeed early received
by some followers of <HI>Papias:</HI> But the universal opposition
of the Christian Church that hath exploded it ever since,
tells us that it was a singular Opinion: And is he a humble
man that now calleth the Christian Church for sixteen hun∣dred
years, and all those Learned and Holy Divines of
<HI>England,</HI> and other Reformed Churches, that differ from
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
your conceit, by the name of <HI>[SEMI-SADDVCES OF THE
APOSTASIE.]</HI> Bear with my freedom. Is it humility
that so loudly challengeth all the Pastors and Doctors of the
Churches to answer you? Have you answered all them?
or so much as one <HI>Cluverus</HI> alone, or <HI>James Calvert</HI> whom
you promised me to answer? Was it humility that <HI>cast</HI> a
<HI>Glove</HI> for an Answer to two or three trifling Fallacies about
the Pagan <HI>Babylon,</HI> when I had given you an Answer to them
long before, and you modestly sent it back without a Con∣futation?</P>
<P>I have had long by me, as a Learner, some humble Queries
to you, and no Bookseller will Print them, because they say
men look on you as diseased with prophesying Self conceit,
and will not read a Confutation.</P>
<P>Your Leader Dr. <HI>More</HI> saith, That the Papists not an∣swering
my Books against them, is, because they despise
them, as unworthy of an answer. May not your case be
much the same? Men have greater matters to mind, than
to trouble themselves with you and me, or answering our
Challenges.</P>
<P>§ 3. But I come to your <HI>Chain of Principles:</HI> And 1. It's
a half and fallacious description of Christs Kingdom, to say
it is his <HI>As the Son of Man.</HI> There be millions of <HI>Sons of
Men</HI> that have no such Kingdom. It is his Kingdom as
God-man, the Redeemer and Recovering Mediator.</P>
<P>This Kingdom is to him as the Eternal Word, and the
Son of Man in one person of a Redeemer.</P>
<P>And because you confessed to me, that if you err, the
misunderstanding of <HI>The Delivering up the Kingdom to the
Father, that God may be All in All]</HI> is your <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,
I will first prove that you grosly err in this your foun∣dation.</P>
<P>§ 4. 2. You say oft, that Christs Kingdom begins at
the <HI>Millennium,</HI> as if he had none before: And you di∣stinguish
not the several Gradations of his Kingdom, as
from the Conception and <HI>Embryo</HI> to its maturity: As it
began in the Promise to <HI>Adam,</HI> and renewed to <HI>Noah,</HI>
and proceeded to the Covenant of Peculiarity, made to
<HI>Abraham</HI> and his Seed, settled in a Common-wealth by
<HI>Moses,</HI> renewed to <HI>David:</HI> And as it came from Heaven
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="14" REF="12"/>
in the Person of the Incarnate <HI>Messiah,</HI> shewing his Kingly
Power by his Miracles and Doctrines, and in his Transfi∣guration,
and acknowledged by <HI>Hosanna</HI>'s, and owned to
the death before the <HI>Roman</HI> Judge. Nor his entrance on
the more open exercise of it, by his Resurrection, Ascen∣sion,
and sending down his Paraclete the Holy Spirit, and
by it in his commissioned Apostles and Witnesses, con∣vincing
and converting the World. You take little notice
of his going forth conquering on the White Horse, as
King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, and calling all the Fowls
of the Air to eat the flesh of Kings and Captains, and his
utter subversion of Pagan <HI>Babylon,</HI> taking to himself his
great Power and Reigning, when Heaven and Earth tri∣umphed,
with joy, that the Kingdoms of the World were
made the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Christ, and
Christ set up Christian Princes as his Officers representing
him to Rule as in his name (as his Ministers do in Preach∣ing
in his name.)</P>
<P>If you say that these things were not done, your unthank∣ful
slander of Providence and the Revelation, is confuted
by the whole stream of the Roman and Church History:
What more will be done hereafter is a further question.
The fulness of the Gentiles then came in. And is all this
no Kingdom and Reign of Christ?</P>
<P><HI>§ 5. Compare Christs words of his Kingdom and yours,</HI>
Matth. 12. 28. The Kingdom of God is come unto you. <HI>Matth.
21.</HI> 43. The Kingdom of God shall be taken from you, and given
to a Nation that will bring forth the fruit thereof. <HI>Luk.</HI> 11. 20.
No doubt the Kingdom of God is come upon you. <HI>Luk.</HI> 9. 27.
There are some here that shall not taste of death, till they see the
Kingdom of God come in power. <HI>Luk.</HI> 17. 21. The Kingdom of
God is among you <HI>(or within you.)</HI> Matth. 13. <HI>Likeneth the
Kingdom of Heaven to a Sower, to a grain of Mustard-seed,
to a Treasure hid, to rich Pearls sought, to a little Leaven,
to a Fishers Net, to a field of Corn and Tares,</HI> Luk. 19. 12, 15.
<HI>When Christ ascended, he then received for himself a
Kingdom, before he came to Judgment,</HI> Joh. 5. 22. The
Father judgeth no man, but hath committed all Judgment to the
Son. <HI>Matth.</HI> 28. 19. All power in Heaven and Earth is given
me. <HI>Joh.</HI> 17. 2, 3. All things are delivered to him. <HI>Luk.</HI> 23. 42.
<PB N="15" REF="12"/>
<HI>He that prayed Christ to remember him when he came in
his Kingdom, was told that he should be in Paradise with
him that day.</HI></P>
<P>§ 6. <HI>Abraham, Isaac</HI> and <HI>Jacob,</HI> are now in the King∣dom
of God, and others shall sit down there with them.
God is not the God of the dead, but of the living. <HI>Laza∣rus</HI>
was in <HI>Abraham</HI>'s bosom: <HI>Moses</HI> and <HI>Elias</HI> appeared
with Christ on the Mount of Glory: And <HI>Enoch</HI> was
translated. Christ is not in Heaven alone without any com∣pany
but Angels: And if <HI>Moses</HI> and <HI>Elias</HI> be there, more
are there, to make the superiour part of his Kingdom. He
hath there a nobler Reign now, than is exercised in this
dark, distracted World, that is drowned in wickedness, and
torn by mutual Enmity and Malice. It would not else have
been better for <HI>Paul</HI> to be dissolved and to be with Christ.
Those that follow him, shall be where he is, <HI>Joh. 12. 26.
We live, because he liveth,</HI> as branches in him the Vine.</P>
<P>§ 7. Either this World is Governed now by God, or
not: If not, he is not a God to it; or Kings are more
to it than God: If yea, it is by Christ that he governeth
it. Are there any Divine Laws, or not? If there be, they
are Christs Laws, and the Execution is Christs Execution of
them. And sure the exercise of Legislation, Judgment,
Protection, Rewards and Punishments, are the exercise of
Kingly Government.</P>
<P>You deny Christ, if you deny him to be King: Will you
not obey him as King, till the Trumpet sound, and he come
to the final Judgment?</P>
<P><HI>§ 8. But where is the present Kingdom of Christ, more
gloriously described than in the Prophecies which you call
your self the</HI> Humble Reader of? <HI>and especially in the Apoca∣lypse
(if it be not you only that understand it?) It would
swell this writing to name all the Texts that expresly assert
it.</HI> Isa. 9. 6, 7. To us a Child is born, to us a Son is given, and
the Government shall be upon his Shoulder, and his Name shall be
called Wonderful, Counsellor, the mighty God, the everlasting
Father, the Prince of Peace; of the increase of his Government
and Peace there shall be no End; upon the Throne of <HI>David,</HI> and
upon his Kingdom, to order it, and to stablish it with Judgment
and with Justice, from henceforth even for ever. <HI>Is this only at
the Millennium.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="16" REF="13"/>
<HI>He is a Prince and a Saviour to give repentance and remission
of sin.</HI> God hath made him Lord and Christ, <HI>Acts</HI> 2. 16.
To be Lord is to be King: To deny this is to say that we
owe him no obedience, and is Apostacy indeed.</P>
<P>How could he make us Kings and Priests to God, if he
were not King himself? even a Priest after the order of
<HI>Melchizedeck,</HI> and a Prophet raised up like <HI>Moses</HI> that was
King in <HI>Jeshurun.</HI> But enough of this to real Christians.</P>
<P><HI>§. 9. But what is all this to you? Do you deny it? 1. If
you do not, it is not</HI> Christs Kingdom, <HI>but the</HI> Consummation
of his Kingdom, <HI>and his Glorious appearing in it that is to be∣gin
at Judgment after the Conflagration. 2. But it is your
words and not your thoughts that are published in Print, and
if you have written contrary to your Heart, recant it, and
pity them that you deceived. In your Catechism of the
Millennium you say, pag</HI> 5. <Q><HI>Q.</HI> When doth Christs King∣dom
begin? <HI>Ans.</HI> It begins at the Coming and Appearance of
Christ, and at the Resurrection of his Saints at his Coming and
Appearance.] <HI>And page</HI> 6. The Apostle without any other
mention of his Kingdom saith, He must reign till he hath put
all his Enemies under his feet. Now when did this reign begin
but at his Coming? Or where did the Apostle give any intima∣tion
of his reigning but at his Coming? And when he comes and
descends, and no longer sits at the Right Hand of God, then
God first maketh his Enemies his Footstool: Not when he sits,
but when he comes: And then he begins to reign.—His
Kingdom and the Resurrection of his Saints begin together.]</Q></P>
<P>§ 10. I confess this Doctrine well agreeth with Doctor
<HI>More</HI>'s Life of Tryal in the Air, and Mr. <HI>Mede</HI>'s Conclusion
that our Salvation is not ascertained to us till the Resurre∣ction:
Indeed it maketh all our Preaching, and Religion
in this life of little moment, in comparison of that which is
after both Death and Resurrection: For if Christ Reign
not till then, he maketh no Laws till then; He bindeth us
to no obedience to him till then; He punisheth no sin till
then; He setteth up no Magistrates till then, to be Go∣verning
Officers in his Kingdom: He executeth no Disci∣pline
in the Churches as King▪ O how have Independents
and Presbyterians been deceived then, who have lamented
the neglect or suppression of Christs Kingly Government in
<PB N="17" REF="13"/>
the Church! It is then under his Thousand years Govern∣ment
that men must obey to secure their Salvation.</P>
<P>§ 11. But the contrary is fully evident by the Effects.
1. What new Laws he will make in the Air, you must
prove: But we can prove that he made Laws for Govern∣ment
on Earth: 2. Else the World hath had no King or
Government of God: 3. Nor no authorized Prince or Pa∣stor.
4. All Saints can say that he giveth Rewards on Earth
to Believers. 5. And he is the Protector of his Church.
6. He here is known by the Judgments which he executeth,
and maketh his Enemies his footstool, though their final
Fall be at the last. Did he not in that Kingly glory de∣scribed
by <HI>John,</HI> execute all those Plagues on Pagan <HI>Rome,</HI>
and its Beast, which are gradually described in the Seals,
the Trumpets and the Vials till it fell? If you say that all
this is meant of Papal <HI>Rome,</HI> sure I am, it was done first on
Pagan <HI>Rome:</HI> And you that tell us how shortly Turk and
Pope shall fall, sure take it to be before the Resurrection!
And doth not Christ then make his Enemies his footstool by
his Kingly Power?</P>
<P>12. What it is for Christ to subdue his Enemies, must be
known by his Office and Undertaking, which is to overcome
Satan, and to save his People from their sins. And did he
not conquer Satan as a Tempter, and triumph even on the
Cross? And doth he not conquer the Dominion of sin in
all his Members? Is he not mortifying them in us day by day?
And is not this treading down his Enemies? And is he not
taking off the Curse, the fruit of sin? These are Christs Ene∣mies,
because they are ours; even the diseases which he came
to cure?</P>
<P>§ 13. Is it not unreconcileable self-contradiction, for
you to extol the Doctrine of Dr. <HI>Crisp,</HI> who saith, That we
are so fully saved by Christ, even before Conversion, that
we have <HI>no sin,</HI> it being none of ours, but his; nor can any
sin hurt us (much less other mens) nor any penalty befal us,
nor any place left for any duty to do us the least good; and
yet that Christ our Saviour, subdueth not his Enemies be∣fore
the Resurrection?</P>
<P>Yea your self assert, that we are Righteous by Gods Es∣sential
Righteousness, and that as our only Justification and
<PB N="18" REF="14"/>
Holiness: And yet doth not Christ tread down his Enemies?
Hath he trod down in you, no Pride, no Lust, no Errour,
no Injustice? Doth he not tread down greater Enemies
than Turkish Swords, or Papal Inquisitions in every Soul
that he converteth? When we fight not against flesh and
blood, but against Principalities and Powers, and spiritual
wickedness in high places? And when we are but killed,
and counted as Sheep to the slaughter, in all this we are more
than Conquerours, and need not fear them that kill the body.</P>
<P>§ 14. Rev. 5. 12, 13. <HI>The numberless Host of Heaven
cry,</HI> <Q>Worthy is the Lamb that was slain, to receive power and
riches, and wisdom and strength, and honour and glory, and
blessing, <HI>(and is not that a Kingdom? and is it not till the
Resurrection?)</HI> And every creature which is in Heaven, and
on the Earth, and under the Earth, and such as are in the
Sea, and all that are in them, heard I saying, Blessing, and ho∣nour,
and glory, and power be to him that sitteth on the Throne,
and to the Lamb for ever and ever.]</Q> <HI>This is before the Re∣surrection.</HI></P>
<P>§ 15. Rev. 12. 7. <HI>If</HI> Michael <HI>be not Christ, he is Christs
Servant.</HI> <Q>And there was War in Heaven, and <HI>Michael</HI> and
his Angels fought against the Dragon, and the Dragon fought
and his Angels, and prevailed not; neither was there place
found any more in Heaven. And the great Dragon was cast
out, that old Serpent called, the Devil and Satan, who deceiveth
the whole World: He was cast out into the Earth, and his
Angels were cast out with him. And I heard a voice saying
in Heaven, Now is come salvation and strength, and the King∣dom
of our God, and the Power of his Christ, for the accuser
of our Brethren is cast down, who accused them before our God
day and night: And they overcame him by the Blood of the
Lamb, and by the Word of their Testimony, and they loved
not their lives unto the Death: Therefore rejoice ye Heavens,
and ye that dwell in them: Woe to the Inhabitants of the Earth
and of the Sea; For the Devil is come down to you, having great
wrath, because he knoweth that he hath but a short time.]</Q></P>
<P>He may make his own Faith, that will affirm, that this
describeth no Kingdom of Christ, or no Conquest of his
Enemies; or that all this is after the Resurrection, or yet to
come, and none of it yet fulfilled.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="14"/>
§ 16. <HI>Rev. 14. 7, 8. Fear God, and give Glory to him, for
the hour of his Judgment is come.</HI>—Babylon <HI>is faln, is faln,]</HI>
This is a Judgment and a treading down Enemies before the
final Judgment: And so is the Reaping and the Wine-press
mentioned, <HI>ver.</HI> 13. to the end.</P>
<P>§ 17. Were all the seven Vials poured out after the Re∣surrection?
<HI>c.</HI> 16. Or were there no treading down of the
Enemies of King Jesus?</P>
<P>Ch. 17. 12, 14. <HI>The Beast and his ten Kings</HI> make war with
the Lamb, and the Lamb shall overcome them; for he is Lord of
Lords, and King of Kings, and they that are with him are called,
and chosen, and faithful.] <HI>This is a Conquest before the
Resurrection.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ch.</HI> 18. Is yet more full herein, about all the Fall and
Plagues of <HI>Babylon:</HI> Over whom Heaven and Earth are cal∣led
to rejoyce.</P>
<P>And it was certainly before the Resurrection, that the
Kingdoms of the World are said to become the Kingdoms
of Christ.</P>
<P>And the three last Chapters describing the Glory of the
delivered Church on Earth, as representing the heavenly
Glory, is yet the fullest proof of all.</P>
<P>§ 18. By all this it is evident, that you call that <HI>Christs
Kingdom</HI> as <HI>begun,</HI> which is but his Kingdom in triumph and
maturity, as if a man were no man till he is at full Age. But
it is your not distinguishing the <HI>Kingdom</HI> of <HI>Mediatorial Re∣demption,
recovery</HI> and <HI>acquisition,</HI> from the Kingdom of <HI>Me∣diatorial
Glory</HI> and <HI>Fruition,</HI> that is, the Errour that corrupt∣eth
all your confident discourses. The Office of our Re∣deemer
is to Recover sinful man to God, and restore him
to purity, from sin, and all the curse or punishment for sin;
yea and to advance him to a more perfect and confirmed state.
And Christs Reward for this, is the everlasting Joy that was
set before him, in the fruition of the Divine Complacency,
and in the perfect and glorious Headship to his perfected glo∣rified
Church for ever. Let us consider, 1. Which of these
is Given up to the Father; And 2. What Giving up to the
Father is; And 3. When it is done.</P>
<P>§ 19. 1. The first all grant is to be Given up: <HI>The King∣dom
of Recovery;</HI> but not the Kingdom of <HI>Fruition:</HI> That of
<HI>Grace,</HI> not that of <HI>Glory.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="20" REF="15"/>
As a Prince commissioned to be General for the redu∣ction
of Revolted Rebels, brings them down by degrees,
and having slain some, and reduced the rest, he giveth up
his Commission, and is General no more; for his work is
done. But he hath after the promised Reward and Honour,
and may under the King, rule them as recovered.</P>
<P>Or as a Physician that hath an Hospital or infected City
to cure, giveth up that work when it is perfectly finished:
So Christ giveth up the Kingdom of Redemption when he
hath done that work. 2. But this <HI>Giving</HI> up is no deposing
of Christ, nor is he less, but more gloriously King than be∣fore.
Nor is God the Father any more King than before.
It's no diminution to Christs Royalty, nor any addition to
the Fathers. I shall prove this before I go further.</P>
<P>§ 20. 1. By comparing this Text with <HI>Joh. 5. 22. The
Father judgeth no man, but hath committed all Judgment to the
Son:]</HI> And yet the Father Governeth no less than he did be∣fore,
and is not deposed by giving up all Government to the
Son: Only the quality of the Subject, and the terms of his
Government are altered. Creation is in Scripture eminent∣ly
ascribed to the Father, and Redemption to the Son. The
Father as Creator Governed Man in his Integrity, to pre∣serve
and perfect him: Man being faln into sin and misery,
the Son as Redeemer Governeth Man as a Physician his Pa∣tients,
in order to his cure. The Father now judgeth no
Man as sinless according to the Law of Innocency, but hath
committed the Government of all to the Son as his Admi∣nistrator
and Physician, in order to their cure. This is but
altering the way of Government. And it is the Subjects
of the Kingdom that are called <HI>The Kingdom,</HI> who are now
restored, and delivered up to the Father, without blemish,
spot or wrinkle, that he may henceforth Govern them as a
perfectly healed People, according to the Law of Per∣fection.</P>
<P>The Father now judgeth no less by the Son, than before
in another way.</P>
<P>§ 21. 2. I prove the continuance of the Kingdom of the
Son, in the way of Fruition and Glory, by the Promise here∣of
made to him by the Father. The Covenant of Media∣tion,
hath Obligations laid on the Son, and Promises of a
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
glorious Kingdom, as merited by his performance of his
part. And doth his performance dispossess him of his pro∣mised
Reward, when it was the condition of his Title to it?
It's tedious to cite all Texts that prove it.</P>
<P>§ 22. 3. The Promises are made to Christ, that his King∣dom
shall be an everlasting Kingdom, and have no end:
And therefore ceaseth not by the delivery mentioned. And
though the Hebrew word commonly translated <HI>[for ever]</HI>
oft signifie but a long time, or many Generations; yet in
the Texts intimated, there is no reason for such a limitation.
If God say, that of his Kingdom there shall be no end, let
the deniers prove their denial.</P>
<P>§ 23. 4. Christ hath promised to make them that over∣come,
Pillars in his Temple, and they shall go out no more;
which he could not perform if he go out himself, or lose his
Kingly Power.</P>
<P>And he saith, That the Children of God and the Resur∣rection
are equal to the Angels, and die no more: And
sure he can make their state no more durable than his own.
And it is called <HI>Life Eternal</HI> which we shall possess: And
shall Christ have less than we?</P>
<P>§ 24. 5. Christs Humane Nature will be perpetuated,
and therefore so will his glorious Kingdom. No Text speak∣eth
of his ceasing to be Man; but many contrary. And
who should then presume to assert it? I know <HI>Smeckfeldius</HI>
held, that Christ ceased to be Man as soon as he entred
Heaven: But the Church called it a Heresie. As on Earth
he was to be Man like us in flesh, so in Heaven where flesh
and blood cannot enter; yet he will make our vile bodies
like to his glorious body.</P>
<P><HI>§ 25. 6. The state of Reward is an Advancement, and
not a Diminution, as to us, so to Christ,</HI> Phil. 2. 9, 10. Wherefore
God also hath highly exalted him, and given him a name which is
above every name, that at the name of Jesus every knee shall bow,
of things in Heaven, and things on Earth, and things under the
Earth, and that every Tongue should confess that Jesus is Lord,
to the glory of God the Father.</P>
<P>§ 26. 7. Christ hath promised us that we shall be with
him where he is, and prayed that we may there behold his
glory; which is plainly to say, that when he hath been the
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
Mediator of Redemption, he will be the Mediator of <HI>Frui∣tion;</HI>
that is, that we shall see Gods Glory as shining to us
in the glorified Humanity of Christ: For as we shall have
Bodies in Heaven as well as Souls; so our Bodies will have
a suitable Medium of Communion with God.</P>
<P>§ 27. 8. If Christs Humane Nature should cease its Glo∣ry,
<HI>ours</HI> by the same reason would do so too. But that is
contrary to the hopes of Faith.</P>
<P>§ 28. 9. Angels Glory and Being is perpetuated: And
therefore Christs Humane Kingdom and Glory, who is above
them, will not cease.</P>
<P>§ 29. 10. There is Executive Government by Christ to
be exercised after the supposed Thousand years: Therefore
he shall Reign after to perform it.</P>
<P>The Redeemed Believers must be Rewarded to Eternity,
and he must save to the utmost all that come to God by
him: He must continue and perpetuate their Reward and
Happiness: For they must live as his Members, because he
liveth: And I doubt not but if you are for ending Christs
Kingdom after a Thousand years, you will be for the ending
of ours.</P>
<P>And he hath his Enemies to punish longer than a Thou∣sand
years, <HI>Luk.</HI> 19. 27. And I believe that you are for end∣ing
their punishment then, if you would end Christs King∣dom
then, <HI>Rev.</HI> 6. 16. It is the Wrath of the Lamb that is
to be executed on the Enemies of the Lamb: It was against
him and his Grace that they sinned; and it is he that com∣eth
in flaming fire to execute Judgment on all that know
not God, and obey not the Gospel. And doth punishment
end with your Thousand years? The very nature of the
glory of the Glorified Body of Christ, is to live as Branches
in him the Vine: Our Life is hid with Christ in God:
And if his Kingdom be given up, all our life and security is
also given up. The same cause must continue that began,
the Reward of Believers (in whom Christ will be admired
more than a Thousand years) and the punishment of Unbe∣lievers.
The Kingdom of Glory therefore continueth when
the Restoring Kingdom hath done its work.</P>
<P>§ 30. 11. The Devil hath reigned by Gods penal per∣mission,
over this sinful World as to the far greatest part,
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
about 6000 years within 314, And shall Christ reign but one
thousand? Prove it before you affirm it.</P>
<P>§ 31. 12. How frivolous is your reason from <HI>Gods being
All in All?</HI> What do you think those words do mean? It's
neither any Addition to God, nor any Exclusion of Christ:
But Gods Governing Mankind as fully recovered according
to the Law of his perfect Nature, and without any more
Medicinal recovering Grace; and his filling them with the
Grace and Joy of his inhabiting Complacence.</P>
<P>1. It cannot mean that God in Essence is nearer the Crea∣ture
than before. For in him we Live and Move, and Be.
He is <HI>All in All</HI> now as the God of Nature.</P>
<P>2. It cannot mean that God will be more the Cause of
Grace or Glory, for Christs ceasing to be a Cause. For
God is no less a Cause when he useth second Causes, than if
he used none.</P>
<P>3. It can no more be an Exclusion of Christ from being
a Cause of our heavenly Communion with God, than an
Exclusion of all second Causes from their Office: And if all
second Causes be excluded, and there be no Cause but God,
there will be no Being but God, and this is but to reduce
the World into God or Nothing; which you must not
feign unproved.</P>
<P>§ 32. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> being plural cannot mean that God
will <HI>End all things,</HI> and so be <HI>Nothing in any thing,</HI> but Him∣self:
<HI>All things in All</HI> signifieth the Existence of those All
things. And shall not Christ and his Kingdom then Exist?
Not in its Paradise or Heavenly State?</P>
<P>§ 33. Can it possibly mean any more than <HI>Of Him,</HI> and
<HI>Through Him,</HI> and <HI>To Him are All Things?</HI> And so they are
now, <HI>Rom.</HI> 11. 36. Or that he is Above All, and through
All, and in us All: And so he is now, <HI>Eph.</HI> 4. 6. And that
he <HI>worketh All in All:</HI> And so he doth still, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 12. 6. And
that he <HI>filleth All in All:</HI> And so he doth still, <HI>Eph.</HI> 1. 23.
Even Christ is said to Be <HI>All in All, Col.</HI> 3. 11. And shall
he cease to be so. He is appointed Heir of All things, he
upholdeth All things by the Word of his Power. For whom
are All things, and by whom are All things? <HI>Heb.</HI> 1. 1, 3.
&amp; 2. 10. And why must he be deposed? By him are <HI>all</HI> things,
1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 8. 6. God gathereth All things in One in Christ, <HI>Eph.
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
1.</HI> 10. Who filleth All things, <HI>Eph.</HI> 4. 10. till we come to
the Unity of the Faith, and of the Knowledge of the Son of
God, unto a perfect Man, to the measure of the Stature of
the fulness of Christ, <HI>ver.</HI> 13. We are growing toward this
before the Resurrection. And if then we attain it, must it
endure but a Thousand years? The perfection of the Church
of Christ, is not like that of Fleshly Bodies, that when they
are at the top of Age, go downwards again; Nor Apples
and Pears, that when they are mellow soon rot.</P>
<P>§ 34. Obj. <HI>But Christ must then be subject to the Father.
Ans.</HI> And was he not always subject to him (in his Huma∣nity?)
He tells us oft that he doth not his own will, but the
will of him that sent him. The <HI>Father worketh,</HI> and he work∣eth.
He were not the true Christ if, as Man, he were not
subject to God: But <HI>Paul</HI> saith not that <HI>Then he begins to be
subject to the Father:</HI> But that he shall still be so. When his
War is over, and he hath done his work as General, or
Conquering Redeemer, he shall be still as Man, a Subject to
God, and Glorified as the Reward of his Redemption, and
be the Glorified Head and King of his Glorified redeemed
Kingdom.</P>
<P><HI>§ 35. I suppose you will say that</HI> Christ and his Saints
shall not die, nor be deposed, but have such a Glory in which God
shall be All in All.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Very good; who denyeth that God is or will be All
in All? But the doubt is, whether Christ shall be ever the
less Christ, or King? Or the Church ever the less his King∣dom
at the End of a Thousand years? I forget not your di∣stinction
of Christ as <HI>Man,</HI> and as the <HI>Son of Man.</HI> You con∣fess
that Christ shall be Man <HI>for ever,</HI> but not as the <HI>Son</HI> of
Man: That is, as Dr. <HI>More,</HI> and you, and <HI>John Turner</HI> say,
<HI>He is an Eternal Man, or Life, and hath</HI> say you, and Dr. <HI>M.
an Eternal Body, Flesh and Blood, from whence you plead for
Transubstantiation.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> You could scarce speak to a Man that hath been more
tempted to follow you in such intimations, as embolden
Reason to be too presumptuous; and I confess that the insi∣nuated
Opinions of <HI>Peter Sterry,</HI> Dr. <HI>More,</HI> and <HI>J. Turner,</HI>
and you, do strongly flatter emboldened Reason: But I take
<PB N="25" REF="17"/>
it but for a Temptation, while Scripture is against it, as well
as the judgment of the Universal Church.</P>
<P>When <HI>Paul</HI> tells us that Flesh and Blood <HI>cannot inherit</HI> the
Kingdom of God, I must in Charity suppose that by <HI>Flesh and
Blood Eternal,</HI> Dr. <HI>More</HI> and others, mean (not properly
but Catachristically) the <HI>Natura Mentalis,</HI> or the Intellectual
Nature, which they suppose to be the same in Christ, An∣gels
and Men.</P>
<P>It is not improbable that the highest of Creatures, is in
order of Nature, a prior effect of the Divine production be∣fore
the lower.</P>
<P>Whether this shall be called an Emanation or a Creation
you are not agreed. Nor whether this prime Created Na∣ture,
be <HI>Vniversal Life,</HI> and <HI>Vniversal Matter,</HI> and so be the
<HI>Soul and Body</HI> of the World, considered as before modal
Mutations; or whether it be only some nobler sort of <HI>Spirit</HI>
and <HI>Matter</HI> that is made before the more ignoble, and per∣haps
maketh the rest.</P>
<P>But it is concluded that Christ is the <HI>Life or Spirit</HI> and <HI>se∣cond
Person in the</HI> Trinity, and the <HI>Holy</HI> Ghost the Matter,
and so the <HI>third Person:</HI> And that Christ, the Soul, and the
Holy Ghost the Matter, are one; which some call A <HI>Crea∣ture,</HI>
and some call God, and some both. <HI>Peter Sterry</HI>'s is
the plainest way, that the Divine Nature first produceth and
uniteth it self to the Universal Intellectual Nature, which is
Christ the first Creature, including the Holy Ghost: And
that this first Intellectual Nature, uniteth it self at the Incar∣nation
to the Humane Nature: And so that Christ hath three
Natures. 1. Divine. 2. Superangelical Created. 3. Hu∣mane.</P>
<P>But still it is unresolved whether the prime Created Na∣ture,
be a Soul to the Incarnate Body, or Christ took both
<HI>Soul</HI> and Body of Man, besides the first Mental Nature.
<HI>Apollinarius</HI> was for the Godhead being instead of a Soul.</P>
<P><HI>Now you come and tell us that</HI></P>
<Q><P>[The Eternal Word in
Humane Nature hath a Kingdom throughout Eternity, but not
as the Son of Man, but as the Eternal Word: The Glory in
which Christ is seen with his Saints, being the Glory which he
had with the Father before the World began: Of the same Na∣ture
wherein he is now at the right Hand of God till he appears:
<PB N="26" REF="18"/>
And the Union in that Eternal State is by God to God, by the
Word to the Father; so the Son as Man is subject, and God All
in All. <HI>Catech. p.</HI> 21.</P>
<P>It seems by the high expressions of God, who is purest Spirit,
being All in All, and by the Lake of the Second Death, and
even the New Heaven and New Earth after the Thousand
years flying away, there is no bodily or material nature con∣tinued,
no not of the Sons glorious body, who is then subject,
nor of the Saints. <HI>Ans.</HI> Scripture having declared no such thing,
no such thing can be supposed, but that Christ and his Saints shall
be in bodies.</P>
<P>So high expressions can fit no state but of God All in All;
even as he was before the foundation of the World All in All,
and to which state our Lords words so much refer, <HI>Joh.</HI> 17.
When all the Saints are thus One with God in Christ, then he
is thus All in All, as before the World began.</P>
<P>Though this Kingdom of Christ be so holy, so heavenly, so
pure, so much of God in it—yet because it is the Kingdom
of the Man Christ Jesus, and of his Saints in a Visible Crea∣ted
Glory, and not the highest Union to God All in All, Christ
gives this last declaration of the Name, that is, of the Nature
and Glory of God; He freely delivereth up this his Kingdom,
and the Son as in Humane Nature suffers most willingly that
Glory of himself, and of his Saints, to be swallowed up by God
All in All, and unites them with himself to the Father, as he
is the Eternal Word, and so they are with him for ever, behold∣ing
the Glory which he had with the Father before the World
was, which is the highest instance of Self-denial of all Created
Glory, and giving up all to God All in All that could be given,
<HI>Joh.</HI> 17. 5.</P></Q>
<P>§ 36. Here you do but confound mens minds with ma∣ny
things at the best unproved. 1. That Christ was an Eter∣nal
Man; (of which your Transubstantiation-Book hath
more.) 2. That his Eternal Manhood is so distinct from his
being the <HI>Son</HI> of <HI>Man,</HI> that he hath a twofold Manhood;
one from Eternity, and one at his Incarnation. 3. That
Christs Kingdom as the Son of Man, that is, in his Manhood
which he had by Incarnation, endureth but a Thousand years.</P>
<P>4. That the Manhood of his Saints which they had by Ge∣neration,
also ceaseth after the Thousand years. 5. Yet Christ
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
and they shall have material <HI>Bodies</HI> after, even in Christs
eternal Body. 6. That this giving up of the Kingdom after
a Thousand years, is the greatest Self-denial in the World,
as if it were a loss or diminution of the Glory of Christ and
Saints. 7. That when all the Saints are thus One in Christ
with God, then God is All in All, as before the <HI>foundation of
the World.</HI> 8. That this is the Unity meant in <HI>Joh.</HI> 17. 24.
9. That this is glorifying Christ with the Glory he had be∣fore
the World began, <HI>Joh.</HI> 17. 5. And not that God would
glorifie him as the Son of Man, by advancing his Humane
Nature, to its participation in the Glory which the Divine
Nature had from Eternity. 10. Yet you tell me by word
of mouth, that you believe the Individuation of the Saints in
this united state. The Metaphor of <HI>[swallowing up in God]</HI>
you may make true or false as you shall expound it, which
till then signifieth nothing.</P>
<P>§ 37. Short-sighted men may reverence this the more,
by how much the less they understand it: But they that
will make sense of it must see, that it is to lead us to Hea∣then
Philosophy as a higher Light than Christ and Scripture,
and to introduce the Pythagorean Opinion of the Transmi∣gration
of Souls, and the Platonists and Stoicks Revolution,
and <HI>Averrhois</HI> his Universal Soul, and to make God or Christ
Divisible, and with <HI>Origen,</HI> to make the future Rewards
and Punishments temporary.</P>
<P>§ 38. 1. If Christ as a <HI>Man, or Life, or Spirit,</HI> was <HI>Eternal,</HI>
it was as <HI>God,</HI> or <HI>as</HI> a <HI>Creature.</HI> As God he was not Man,
nor Body. If you say that he was the second <HI>Hypostasis</HI> as
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, and the Holy Ghost the third as <HI>Matter,</HI> (as Dr. <HI>More</HI>
and <HI>J. Turner)</HI> then either you mean <HI>Vniversal,</HI> or <HI>Particular
Life</HI> and <HI>Matter:</HI> If Universal, you make the World to be
God, and make him Divisible: If Particular, you make God
a part of the World: And so you do if you make him but
the <HI>Soul</HI> of the World.</P>
<P>§ 39. 2. If the Saints were in God before the World be∣gan,
accordingly all things were eternally in God; and that
will bring in <HI>Aristotles</HI> Eternity of the World, which indeed
meer Reason might take for probable.</P>
<P>§ 40. Either you mean that we were in God only as in
<HI>Potentia Creatoris,</HI> and that is <HI>not to be in him,</HI> but only to say
<PB N="28" REF="19"/>
that he was <HI>able</HI> to make us: For <HI>existere est esse extra Cau∣sas
Efficientes.</HI> Or else that we did actually <HI>exist:</HI> (which
those hold that are for Souls <HI>Prae existence,</HI> or worse.) And
we did exist in God, either as being <HI>God himself,</HI> or <HI>Creatures,</HI>
or <HI>Effects</HI> of God. If we were God from Eternity, we are
God still: If as <HI>Effects</HI> or <HI>Creatures,</HI> then either as <HI>Parts of
one common Soul</HI> and body of the World (or of the Humane
Species,) or as so many Individuals. If it be said that we were
but <HI>Parts</HI> of one <HI>Soul</HI> or Body, it will infer that we are so
still, and that these parts are as the Rivers and Springs from
the Sea in continual Revolution: Or if we are fixed Indi∣viduals,
God kept us not <HI>idle</HI> from Eternity (or prae-existent.)
None can think that God from all Eternity (or since) kept
all the Souls that are to be embodied to the end of the
World, in a sleepy state till Bodies were generated for them.</P>
<P>If you say that they lived in God as pure Spirits without
Bodies, what then did the Prime Matter, which some of you
call the third Hypostasis in the Trinity? We see that God
put Souls into Bodies in this World: And can you prove
that he never did so before from all Eternity?</P>
<P>And when you have said, that Christ and Saints shall be
swallowed up in God, and have no more Kingdom as Sons
of men, but be in God as before the World began, do you
mean that they shall continue so to all Eternity, and never
revolve into Bodies more? When God hath shewed us that
he hath delighted in embodied Souls these five thousand six
hundred ninety years, will you feign that he never did so
before, nor ever will do so again?</P>
<P>§ 41. I conclude, 1. That there is no rational issue of
your Doctrine to be expected, but a Pythagorean, or Plato∣nick
Revolution or Transmigration of Souls, from one Uni∣versal
Soul into many particulars, as the Sea floweth into
Springs, and they into Rivers, and they into the Sea again,
and so round: Or as one Sun illuminating the Air, lighteth
many Candles, (by a burning-glass or by flames,) being indi∣viduated
only by the oily matter, but not divided from the
common Element of Fire.</P>
<P>2. And that all this is but to confound men partly with
falshoods, and partly with uncertainties; when the plain
Doctrine of Christ is a more quieting way. God hath kept
<PB N="29" REF="19"/>
us so dark about the <HI>Beginning</HI> or <HI>Prae-existence,</HI> and the
<HI>manner</HI> of his <HI>producing Souls,</HI> yea and of the manner of their
operation in their separated state, that to be confident beyond
his Scripture-Revelation, is but to be ignorant of our Igno∣rance,
and to venture to take Gods name in vain.</P>
<P>But we know that God breathed into Man that breath of
Life, and so made him a Living Soul, and said, <HI>Increase and
multiply;</HI> and that the Spirit goeth to God that gave it, and
we shall be with Christ in Paradise, and that he will receive
our departing Spirits, and that it's best to be with him.</P>
<P>§ 42. And now I see not what you can make of Gods
being <HI>All-in-All,</HI> more that at this day he is, and more than
that he shall Govern Man again as sinless and fully restored,
without any further Redemption or Recovering Govern∣ment;
but that you pervert the Text to countenance your
pretended abbreviation of Christs Reign to a Thousand
years.</P>
<P><HI>All things are now in him, and of him, and to him.</HI> Nothing
can be added to All. But I am not able to discern why you
speak so much in Equivocals and Generals, that cannot pos∣sibly
afford the Reader a determined sense. If you are un∣willing
to be understood, your Opinions are not of the Light.
If you understand not your own words, how should others
understand them?</P>
<P>No man can tell whether you infer from Gods being <HI>All
in All,</HI> the <HI>Deification</HI> of <HI>All things,</HI> or their <HI>Annihilation,</HI> or
the dissolving of all Bodies compound, and the Deifying on∣ly
of the spiritual part.</P>
<P><HI>You say</HI> Catech. p. 14. <Q>[It is the ultimate end, and last
result of All things. And (Creatures below being capable of
this Vnion, as All which have no understanding are annihilated.
And Creatures of understanding, Angels and Men, can be no
other than miserable in the loss of this Vnion.]</Q> <HI>But are
Christ the Son of Man and his Saints miserable till the end of
the Thousand years?</HI></P>
<P><HI>So p.</HI> 15. <Q>[In order to the Vnion of All Created Beings of
Vnderstanding, <HI>to God all in all.</HI>]</Q> <HI>(What, Devils and all
Damned Men!)</HI> <Q>The Eternal Word far above Angels became
lower than Angels by becoming Man, and so comprehended the
whole Created Intellectual nature, that he might be the Head
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
of the whole in their Vnion to God: And that in Him they
might All be reconciled to God with the whole inferiour Crea∣tion:
Which having served the Glory of the Creator by Jesus
Christ, they fly back into their former State of NOTHING in
themselves, but indeed are returned into the Divine Immensity,
and Angels and Men be Vnited to God for ever. Eph. 1. 10.
Col. 1. 20.</Q></P>
<P>Here we have <HI>Anihilation</HI> and <HI>Nothingness in themselves,</HI>
and yet <HI>[indeed are returned into the Divine Immensity.</HI> And so
that which is <HI>Nothing in it self</HI> hath a <HI>Being</HI> in God! What
can this mean but that the Creatures were once <HI>all God</HI> him∣self,
till he gave them a Self-being, which he taketh away,
and then they are God again, not only their Individuation,
but their Creature-Being ceasing. All things are still in God,
and his Immensity: But if they have no Being in them∣selves
there will be Nothing but God: But will they so con∣tinue?
And will God from Eternity to Eternity have no
Created Being save for Seven Thousand years (or days?)</P>
<P>And indeed is the whole understanding (and inferiour)
Nature, Devils and Men, thus reconciled?</P>
<P>And is God <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> when there is no <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> nothing
but Himself in Unity: Is he In that which is not?</P>
<P>I have been so long on your first Proposition as being your
Foundation: There is a Kingdom of Recovering Grace of
Christ Incarnate, and Glorified, delivered up when he hath
done that work, which the Kingdom of Glory succeedeth,
where God as All in All shall be Glorified in the perfection
of Christ <HI>God-Man</HI> and his Glorified Saints. This is agreed
and granted you.</P>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle II. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. No Text of Scripture saith that the Kingdom of
Grace or Redemption begins at Christs Coming to Judgment:
But that then it Endeth in the Triumph of the Redeemer,
and his Entering upon his Kingdom of Fruition in the full
Glorified Church, 2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 4. 1. saith no more: His Appear∣ing
there is for Judgment, which presupposeth Mans final
keeping or breaking of Christs precedent Ruling Laws. It
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
is his Triumphant ending of the Kingdom which he had,
and the Entrance of that of Glory.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle III. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. No doubt but Christ will reign with and in his
Saints.</P>
<P><HI>§ 2. But that the</HI> full number shall be made up <HI>then is your
own word. At his Coming you hold the number will not be
full: For you say Catech. pag.</HI> 4. <Q>They shall propagate a holy
Seed in such abundance, as to recompence with a much more to
the Glory of the second <HI>Adam,</HI> Rom. 5. for the few that are
saved within the World of the first <HI>Adam.</HI>]</Q> <HI>And all these
were not in Being at Christs Coming.</HI></P>
<P>Nor can you prove that the New Earth, and all Genera∣tion
shall end with a Thousand years.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle IV. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. Your supposition that they are not presently caught
up (yea till the end of a Thousand years) is your Forgery.</P>
<P>2. <HI>The Equality of Christs Love and Grace to All his Saints]</HI>
is also your own Doctrine, not Christs. For tho <HI>ex parte Dei</HI>
who operateth <HI>per essentiam,</HI> there is no inequality or differ∣ence,
yet in the <HI>Effects</HI> and the Relative <HI>extrinsick Denomina∣tions
of</HI> God from those Effects, there is great difference. All
have not equal Grace, nor equally improve their Talents,
nor are Rulers of ten Cities, nor as the Apostles sit on Twelve
Thrones judging the Twelve Tribes of <HI>Israel.</HI> Though you
say Catech. p. 3. <Q>[<HI>None of the Saints can be perfected, the
one without the other.</HI>]</Q> If that be true, either those on
Earth that you liken to <HI>Adam</HI> in Paradise are as perfect as
those in the New Heaven, or those in Heaven as imperfect
as those on Earth. (And no wonder, when you place them
but <HI>in the Air where evil Spirits dwell now,</HI> Catech. p. 12.) But
Christ saith the Children of the Resurrection neither Marry
nor are given in Marriage, but are like the Angels; And
you say on Earth they shall be getting Children abundantly
<PB N="32" REF="21"/>
a Thousand years; if you take that for no note of imperfecti∣on,
it seems Christ did.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle V. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. What could you have said more strongly against your
self? Death is subdued or swallowed up in Victory when
the Redeemed die no more. None of them die after Christs
first day of Judgment at his appearing? Are they dying all
the Thousand years? I cannot imagine what reasonable an∣swer
you can give to this Text and Argument!</P>
<P>If you say that there are Devils and wicked Men to be put
to death all the Thousand years, can you prove that they
were the Redeemed that Christ came to deliver from death?
or yet that some of them are damned in the beginning, and
some not till the end of the Thousand years? Or if their
death shall endure no longer than the Thousand years?</P>
<P>If you say that the Saints on Earth, have Natures Mortal,
though they shall not die; I answer, you have written that
they are in the Kingdom of Glory, and equal in Love and
Grace, and perfect, as those above. And if death be not
subdued when Men are secured from it by Christ and the
possession of promised Immortality, its a doubt whether it be
overcome at all: For none are above a <HI>posse mori</HI> but God,
because the Being of all Creatures dependeth meerly on his
will: The suspension of his support would end all Created
Being: In which sense it is that <HI>Arnobius cont. Gentes</HI> asserteth
the Souls Mortality. If Christ must be the Conqueror of
Death, when will he Conquer, if not when Men die no
more? Is it after he hath given up his Power and King∣dom?</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle VI. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. This is but your further owning your own full Con∣futation.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="principle">
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
<HEAD>Principle VII. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. This poor shift is answered above: Do you not say,
Those alive are in the same Glorious Kingdom? and that
none are perfect till all are perfect? And have those in the
Air any more assurance that they shall not die, than Gods
Love, and Will, and Promise, and their Union in Christ?</P>
<P>2. But why is not at least the Heavenly, or Airy Kingdom
given up at first?</P>
<P>3. Was not death Conquered to the Person of Christ,
after his Resurrection, though he was at his Ascension to be
taken up? And is not death Conquered to those on Earth
that have the foresaid security to ascend and never to
die?</P>
<P>This shifting is meer violence to the Text.</P>
<P>4. But I will prove that the Apostle tells us that the
<HI>Catching up</HI> will be presently; And your words of <HI>[Christ
first, and then those that sleep in him]</HI> have no more strength
than this Inference [If <HI>Paul</HI> telling us of the difference in
Order of time between Christs Resurrection and the End of
the World, be signified by that word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, after, then we
may suppose that <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> signifieth no sudden change of the
living at the Coming of Christ.] <HI>Ans.</HI> I deny the Conse∣quence:
The matter of fact tells us of a sixteen hundred years
distance in one, and the Text proveth a suddenness in the o∣ther.
The distance between Christs Rising and his Coming
to Judgment are so notoriously revealed, that <HI>Paul</HI> need not
say, It will not be the same moment. But here (if you
believe not your self instead of Gods Word) the contrary
is so plain as confuteth all your devised frame.</P>
<P><HI>§ 2. I. (Supposing that I need not confute to you the
two false readings reproved by</HI> Jerom, Augustine, <HI>&amp;c.)</HI>
1 Cor. 15. 51. <HI>saith,</HI> [We shall all be changed [<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>]
<HI>what could be spoken plainer?
At the Change joyned with the Resurrection, it will be</HI>
in a moment, in the twinkling of an Eye, <HI>and (which is unanswer∣able)</HI>
at the last Trumpet. <HI>That the said Trumpets sound is
at Christs Coming is evident,</HI> Matth. 24. 30, 31. <Q>They shall
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
see the Son of Man Coming in the Clouds of Heaven, with
Power and great Glory: And he shall send his Angels, with a
great sound of a Trumpet, and they shall gather together his
Elect, from the four winds, from one end of Heaven to the
other.</Q></P>
<P><HI>And</HI> 1 Thes. 4. 16. <Q>The Lord himself shall descend from
Heaven with a shout, with the voice of the Archangel, and with
the Trump of God, <HI>&amp;c.]</HI></Q></P>
<P>If you will feign <HI>two Trumps,</HI> one at the <HI>beginning</HI> and the
other at the <HI>end</HI> of the Thousand years, you will do it by so
gross an addition and contradiction of Gods Word, as that I
hope few will believe you: Nor yet if you feign that the
Trumpet will not sound till the end of the Thousand years:
For the Trumpet soundeth at the same time that Christ Com∣eth
with his Angels, and that the dead are raised, and the Elect
gathered. At this sound will be the change in a moment.</P>
<P>§ 3. II. The Text saith expresly that <HI>we shall be caught up
together with them.]</HI> And that none may feign it to speak but
of a <HI>simultas</HI> of Company and not of <HI>Time,</HI> the words are
placed so as to confute it. [<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>] we
shall <HI>with them be caught up:</HI> Not a Thousand years after
them.</P>
<P>§ 4. III. The Verb <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>] <HI>rapiemur, suddenly
caught up</HI> as by force, seemeth purposely put to signifie the
<HI>simultaneous</HI> speed.</P>
<P>§ 5. IV. The end of this <HI>Rapture</HI> is, not at a Thousand
years end to go dwell in the Air, or with the Lord, but to
<HI>meet the Lord in the Air,</HI> which is supposed to be at his Com∣ing,
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. The whole context, 1 <HI>Thes.</HI> 4.
and 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 15. implyeth this <HI>meeting him to be at his Com∣ing.</HI></P>
<P>§ 6. V. It is said to be to <HI>meet him in the Air.</HI> But no
Bible but yours doth say that Christ shall <HI>dwell a Thousand years
in the Air.</HI> And you your self say that at the end of the
Thousand years he shall give up his <HI>Airy Humane Kingdom:</HI>
And when he hath removed his dwelling the Inhabitants of
the Earthly Paradise will come too late.</P>
<P>§ 7. VI. It is said that when we meet him we shall <HI>for
ever be with the Lord:</HI> That is, <HI>The same Lord, that we meet,</HI>
which is Christ <HI>God and Man,</HI> and in the <HI>State and Kingdom
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
where we meet him;</HI> and not only come to him at a Thousand
years end, when he hath changed his Humanity, Kingdom
and Place.</P>
<P>§ 8. VII. <HI>Ver.</HI> 15. The <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>
we are left as reserved to the Coming of the Lord]
plainly imply that we are kept for <HI>that time to meet him at his
Coming,</HI> and not only a Thousand years after.</P>
<P>§ 9. VIII. 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 15. 52. Again expresly joineth the
sound of the Trumpet, the Resurrection, and our Change to∣gether,
<HI>[For the Trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be
raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed,</HI> that is, when the
Trumpet soundeth, and the dead are raised.</P>
<P>§ 10. IX. <HI>Matth</HI> 24. Christ tells us that <HI>He will gather
his Elect from the four Winds,</HI> when he cometh with his An∣gels,
and the Trumpet soundeth: But those found alive on
Earth, cannot be excluded from the number of the Elect
that are at or under the four Winds: Therefore they shall
then be gathered to him.</P>
<P>§ 11. X. The living shall be caught up when <HI>Death</HI> the
last <HI>Enemy is subdued:</HI> But that will be at Christs Trium∣phant
Coming, and the Resurrection: For after that there
will be no more death as an <HI>Enemy.</HI> If you would deny this
(as aforesaid) because in the New Earth the Blessed are
Mortal in possibility of Nature, I answer, that Paradise pos∣sibility
(were it true) is none of the Curse for Sin, and
therefore not the Enemy to be subdued.</P>
<P>§ 12. XI. The Saints shall be caught up when the day
and work of Judgment Cometh: But that will be at Christs
Coming, and the Resurrection: As he himself and many a
plain Text of Scripture tell us, (too much to cite.) And
whereas you feign a Judgment day of a Thousand years,
taking <HI>Judgment</HI> for <HI>Government,</HI> Christ otherwise expound∣eth
himself, and tells how the Judgment will proceed by
Exploration and Sentence, <HI>Mat. 25. &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>And Government in general containeth Legislation, Judg∣ment
and Execution: You tell us not a word what Legisla∣tion
will be in the Air the Thousand years. And for Judg∣ment
in special, will Christ be a Thousand years in <HI>Explora∣tion</HI>
and <HI>Sentence?</HI> Will the wicked so long be untryed and
uncondemned, or the Faithful so long unjustified, or by Sen∣tence
<PB N="36" REF="23"/>
judged to Salvation? Doth not Christ <HI>Mat.</HI> 25. con∣tradict
this? VViil their case be so long undecided?</P>
<P>If you mean that <HI>Execution</HI> will be that Thousand years,
can you prove that the Damned shall suffer no longer? Nor
the Blessed any longer reign with Christ? O make not a New
Gospel, Heaven and Hell!</P>
<P>§ 13. XII. The Saints will be taken up when the <HI>King∣dom
is delivered up to the Father, and God is All In All:</HI> But
that will be at Christ Triumphant Coming and Judgment at
the Resurrection. For it signifieth no more but that Sin
and Curse shall all be cast out, and all that rebelled against
God be Conquered, and all Christs Recovering work per∣formed,
and God again Rule Man as Innocent according to
the Law of his perfect Nature: This will be then fi∣nished.</P>
<P>You say that those on Earth shall be in a Paradise State,
and those in the Air will not be worse: And then Christs
Coming in Triumph delivereth up the Kingdom to the Fa∣ther,
that his and Christs Kingdom of Glory and Fruition
may succeed.</P>
<P>§ 14. XIII. When <HI>Paul</HI> was opening to them the Myste∣ry
of Christs Kingdom, if he had talkt thus of being caught
up in a moment of time, at the last Trump to meet the Lord,
and never told them a word of a Thousand years between
the Trumpet and being caught up, it must be because he
<HI>knew it not,</HI> or was not <HI>willing that we should know it:</HI> But <HI>nei∣ther</HI>
of these could be true in a matter of so great moment,
when it was that Coming of Christ that he was satisfying
them about. And I will learn from you, nothing that <HI>Paul</HI>
knew not.</P>
<P>§ 15. XIV. I have proved before how copiously Christ
openeth the nature of his own Kingdom in many Parables;
and how he maketh his Enemies his Footstool, Conquering
Satan, Sin and Enemies, and how the Revelation openeth
his Conquest of the <HI>Roman</HI> Empire: And he shall destroy the
Man of Sin with the Breath of his Mouth, and the Brightness
of his Coming. Therefore he hath not left this to be done
the Thousand years after his Coming.</P>
<P>§ 16. <HI>XV.</HI> Peter <HI>tells us that</HI> [the day of the Lord will
come as a Thief in the night: in which the Heavens shall pass a∣way
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
with a great noise, and the Elements melt with fervent heat.]
<HI>But a Thousand years is not such a sudden surprize: Nor
will Heaven and Earth be a Thousand years burning.</HI></P>
<P>§ 17. XVI. <HI>The Earth and the Works therein shall be burnt
up;</HI> and all these <HI>things be dissolved. 2 Pet.</HI> 3. 10, 11, 12.
Therefore the Bodies of those then alive would be <HI>burnt
and dissolved</HI> were they not first taken up. To say as you do,
that God would keep them in the Fire unburnt as he did the
three, <HI>Dan.</HI> 3. is to make and obtrude on us a Gospel of
your own.</P>
<P>§ 18. XVII. You think <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog</HI> shall live after
the Conflagration, who shall cover the Earth: And shall all
their Bodies too be unburnt in the Fire, that dissolveth all
these things on Earth? Is this any Word of God?</P>
<P>§ 19. XVIII. You that think Men live each one the
whole Thousand years, and <HI>generate so abundantly as to recom∣pense
with a much more for the few that were saved under the
first</HI> Adam, can by no reasonable imagination find room on
Earth, for the numberless Off-spring of a Thousand years,
to dwell all at once here: And the numberless followers of
<HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog</HI> also to dwell with them. They must not be
so unrighteous as to dispossess the wicked of their dwellings;
And for one year after all is burnt up, they may be in
want.</P>
<P>§ 20. XIX. It is incredible that your description of
Earth for the Thousand years can leave <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog</HI> in their
Hostility unconvinced: For to see Men live a Thousand
years in the sight of Christ and all the Saints in the Air,
one would think should convince them: Or if Men are chan∣ged
before at the common Age of Men, to see so many Mil∣lions
caught up to Heaven without Death or Burial, sure
would make them afraid of fighting against such.</P>
<P>§ 21. XX. There is not one word of God that confineth
Christs Kingdom to a Thousand years; and what are you
that you should presume to do it?</P>
<P>It hath continued much above a Thousand years already.
If you alledge 2 <HI>Pet. 3. One day with the Lord is as a Thousand
years, and a Thousand as one day,</HI> which speaketh only a∣gainst
doubting, because of the delay of Christs Coming, as
if this told us how <HI>long</HI> he should <HI>reign</HI> when he is Come,
<PB N="38" REF="24"/>
this would but confirm us that your Doctrine is meerly of
your self. The Thousand years in <HI>Rev.</HI> 20. is the same with
that of the Womans being in the Wilderness, and the Dra∣gons
being bound, which is plainly on this side the Confla∣gration.
And indeed is presently after the fall of Pagan
<HI>Rome.</HI> For that Pagan <HI>Rome</HI> was not <HI>Babylon,</HI> or that it is
not faln, I will not believe though you should swear it, or
cast the Glove in Challenge to dispute it.</P>
<P>§ 22. XXI. <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog,</HI> and all their Hosts are to
be in the end of the Thousand years: But they are to be be∣fore
the Conflagration and Coming of Christ: Therefore the
Conflagration and Coming of Christ is to be after the Thou∣sand
years. In the New Earth will dwell Righteousness,
that is, only Righteousness, and in a Paradise state: But
that is inconsistent with a numberless power of malignant E∣nemies
that shall compass the Holy City.</P>
<P>§ 23. XXII. You make a strange Exposition of <HI>John,</HI>
as if he wrote to five of the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches as in one World,
and to <HI>Laodicea</HI> the seventh in another when this is burnt up
and Christ come.</P>
<P>§ 24. XXIII. When you have almost equalled the New
Earth with Heaven, you debase it by making it a <HI>Laodicean</HI>
Church, which for Lukewarmness God threatneth to spew
out, and to take away their Candlestick? Is this the Paradise
World of Righteousness?</P>
<P>§ 25. XXIV. You make two New <HI>Jerusalem</HI>'s when
Scripture speaketh but of one after Christs Coming: One
you take to be in the Air, and the other on Earth: Though
one Society may be in both, one <HI>Vrbs</HI> or material City can∣not;
such as is described <HI>Rev.</HI> 21. and 22.</P>
<P>§ 26. XXV. You feign two Conflagrations: One to
Burn the World, and another after to Burn <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog</HI>
and their Followers over the Earth.</P>
<P>§ 27. XXVI. You groundlesly dishonour the Kingdom
of Christ by confining it to a Thousand years, which God
hath promised shall have no End.</P>
<P>§ 28. XXVII. You dishonour Christ and his Kingdom
by bringing him from his Fathers Right Hand in Heaven, and
placing him and his Saints a Thousand years in the Air,
where you say <HI>wicked Spirits now dwell,</HI> and where Dr. <HI>H.
<PB N="39" REF="24"/>
More</HI> saith, Good and Bad dwell in an Aerial Vehicle till
they are advanced to an Etherial: Yea where you say De∣vils
and Damned Men now dwell with Christ; And where
Christ must exercise the greatest self-denial in leaving that
lower Station.</P>
<P>§ 29. XXVIII. You make Christs Kingdom to be a
humbling loss to the Saints above, while you take them down
into the Air for a Thousand years, from the Heavenly state
where you say they were in God, where Christ is at his
Right Hand, as they shall be at last; or else you will make
that Everlasting Union their loss.</P>
<P>§ 30. XXIX. Either you also bring down the Angels
from their Glory to dwell in the Air, or else you separate them
from Christ and the Saints in the Air with him.</P>
<P>§ 31. XXX. When God hath already continued the old
sinful World under the Curse almost six Thousand years, you
by Fiction confine the New purified World wherein dwell∣eth
Righteousness to a Thousand years, and call this the Sab∣batism.
As if our Rest must be so much shorter than Sin
and Labour? When yet there will be no Sin to provoke
God to destroy the New World.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle VIII. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. How frivolous is your arguing from the name of a
Monarchy: God is ever the absolute Monarch: But if you
mean a Humane Visible Monarchy, and suppose he must so vi∣sibly
Rule the Earth, you do but beg the question. A Monarch
of all the World, none ever was, and therefore four such
never were. But if by a Monarchy you meant, the greatest
Visible Empire on Earth, so the Fifth Monarchy was set up
by <HI>Constantinople,</HI> which differs far more from the Pagan
<HI>Ro∣man</HI>
Monarchy, than that did from the Grecian or Assyrian:
And it was Christs Visible Monarchy Reigning by his Vice-Roys,
the Kingdoms being now said to be his Kingdoms.
This was the true Visible Fifth Monarchy: And the Turks
are the Sixth Monarchy, the renewed Reign of the captiva∣ted
Dragon, let loose after a Thousand years.</P>
<P><PB N="40" REF="25"/>
§ 2. But your fiction that the Scripture assigns a Thou∣sand
years to Christs Reign after the Resurrection is worse
than frivolous; a meer forgery; I answered it before. If
<HI>Peter</HI> quiet mens over-hasty expectation of Christs coming,
by telling them that a Thousand years time is as nothing to
the Eternal Infinite God; shall a man pretend skill in Pro∣phecy,
and tell us, that he meaneth that Christs Reign after
the Resurrection is measured and meant by this Thousand
years, and is as nothing to the Eternal God.</P>
<P>And I have proved to you that the Thousand years in the
<HI>Revelation,</HI> speaketh of no such thing, but of what is done
before the Resurrection.</P>
<P>For 1. Those Thousand years are most likely to signifie
an undetermined time, and mean no more than a Long time;
as Mr. <HI>Durham</HI> and <HI>Cluverus</HI> most incline to think (and ma∣ny
others.)</P>
<P>But 2. Granting the contrary, it plainly speaketh of a time
presently following the feasting of the Fowls of Heaven with
the flesh of Kings and Captains, and the Fall of the Pagan
<HI>Babylon.</HI> And not only <HI>Grotius,</HI> but <HI>John Fox</HI> and many others
tell us, that it is the just time between the Fall of Pagan
<HI>Rome,</HI> and the beginning of the <HI>Ottoman</HI> Empire; which was
about 1300 years.</P>
<P>3. And this Thousand years is before the suppression of
wickedness in the World, while <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog</HI> are in the
four quarters of the Earth, in number as the Sand of the
Sea; that shall go upon the breadth of the Earth, and com∣pass
the Camp of the Saints, the beloved City: And before
the fire that cometh down to devour them. And most cer∣tainly
all this is not in the New Earth, wherein dwelleth
Righteousness: So that this Thousand years seemeth to sig∣nifie
but 1. That Apostles and Martyrs go to Heaven, 2. And
leave their Names and Doctrine honourable on Earth; 3. And
that the surviving Confessors shall rise from their persecuted
state, to triumph with Christ in their deliverance and supe∣riority
on Earth; 4. And that this sudden Exaltation is a fit
representation of the Glory that they shall have perpetually
in Heaven.</P>
<P>Let any sober man judge whether this one only mention
of a Thousand years in a hard Prophecy, <HI>Rev.</HI> 20. under the
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
expository circumstances now named, will warrant a man
to Preach a new Gospel and Kingdom of Christ to the
World, without any proof from all the plain words of
Christ himself and his Apostles, and directly against them.</P>
<P>He that well considereth Prophetical Language, will think
that Articles of Faith should be founded on plainer words.
When we read in <HI>Ezekiel,</HI> that <HI>Egypt</HI> shall have no Inhabi∣tant
for forty years, that <HI>Tyrus</HI> shall be no more inhabited,
that <HI>Babylon,</HI> and the Land of <HI>Babylon</HI> shall be no more inha∣bited,
and abundance the like, we shall the better under∣stand
the <HI>Apocalypse,</HI> whose very words are much taken out
of the Prophets.</P>
<P>5. The Devil and the false Prophet are cast into the Lake
of fire after the destruction of <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog,</HI> and after the
Thousand years: But sure they are cast into the Lake at the
Resurrection: For if they stay uncondemned a Thousand
years after that, I know not what Christs coming to Judg∣ment
signifieth: Sure it is not the date of their Execution;
for they are to be tormented for ever and ever: And must
they be unsentenced a Thousand years?</P>
<P>6. And the Resurrection is described as coming after all
this: The Earth and Sea giving up their dead, and the dead
judged out of the Books, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>7. And <HI>Ch.</HI> 21. The New Heaven and New Earth com∣eth
after this Thousand years, and the destruction of the
Enemies; and the New <HI>Jerusalem</HI> coming down from God:
And there are yet Kings of the Earth that are to bring their
Glory into it: And there are Nations to be healed with
the Leaves of the Tree of Life; which made Mr. <HI>Potter</HI> and
many others conclude, that it is the glory of the Church on
Earth, that the 21, and 22 Chapters describe: Though it is
most probable that it is but as a representation of the hea∣venly
Glory: But the Thousand years is plainly ended before
the Resurrection.</P>
<P>8. The plain meaning that (Though the Old Serpent will
still be a Tempting Deceiver, both without the Church and
within, yet) as a Dragon or Babylonish Conqueror and
Captivater, he shall be bound up for a Thousand years after
the Churches delivery from the Pagan Captivity: And so
he was. And yet the Text tells us, that all that while the
<PB N="42" REF="26"/>
<HI>Earth</HI> had Nations of Enemies that at last were by that Dra∣gon
drawn to assault the Church again. Here is not a word
of a Thousand years New Earth in which dwelleth Righte∣ousness,
and that after the Conflagration and Resurrection.
The New Earth is mentioned with no such limitation: That's
all the device of presuming imagination.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle IX. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. The Recovering Victorious Gracious Kingdom, is
ended in the glorions triumph of his Appearing and Judg∣ment,
and his glorious Kingdom of Fruition then beginneth:
That all his Kingdom then beginneth, is a falshood largely
confuted by Christs own mouth. And as false is it that
the Kingdom of Recovery or Grace, is not given up till a
Thousand years after the Resurrection. That this is before
the Kingdom of Eternity, is false in any proper sense. If
you mean a Kingdom from Eternity without beginning, you
should prove that ever there was such: Your bare naming it
so is no proof. If there were no men from Eternity, then
there was no Kingdom of men. If you mean that which shall
endure to Eternity, so will Christs glorious Kingdom as
Man over Men. For many and many Scriptures tell us, it
hath no end, and is everlasting: And he that accuseth others
of <HI>Semi-Sadduceism of the Apostasie,</HI> should consider, whether
denying the Kingdom of Christ and his Saints in glorified
Humanity, as soon as a Thousand years (as one day) are
ended, be not liker Sadduceism and Apostasie, than our be∣lieving
the everlastingness of it.</P>
<P>§ 2. When your own presumption hath <HI>defined it to be a
Thousand years,</HI> you may as boldly assign its time and place.
But I have proved that the Scripture confuteth your time,
and that a <HI>moment,</HI> and the <HI>twinkling of an eye,</HI> and <HI>the last
Trump, sounding,</HI> is not a Thousand years: And therefore no
such space as the whole Kingdoms duration, between the Re∣surrection
and the living caught up.</P>
<P>§ 3. <HI>Paul</HI> saith, <HI>Phil.</HI> 3. 19, 20. that the Saviour that we
look for from Heaven, shall change our vile Bodies, and
make them like to his Glorious Body: He speaketh not as
<PB N="43" REF="26"/>
you of four Bodies and three Changes. 1. A Natural sin∣ful
Body turned into a Paradise Body. 2. And that (called
Vile) turned into a Glorious Body. 3. And that ceasing
left to a Divine Eternal Body.</P>
<P>3. I have oft told you that the Paradise Body or Morta∣lity,
is none of the Curse or Enemy to be subdued.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle X. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. We have better thoughts of the New Heaven and
Earth than you have; we expect both to be of longer conti∣nuance
than a Thousand years.</P>
<P>§ 2. That it is the Saints remaining that dwell on the
New Earth a Thousand years before they are caught up, is
your word, and not Gods, that I can find. God can reple∣nish
that New Earth as he did this, or how else he please.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="11" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle XI. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. Whatever they are <HI>Called</HI> you confess that the wick∣ed
Rise: And that they are not cast into the Lake of Fire
till <HI>the last</HI> of the Thousand years, is only your word. If they
have a Thousand years Life of further tryal, why may they
not repent and scape.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="12" TYPE="principle">
<HEAD>Principle XII. Answered.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. The Fifth Monarchy is Christs whole Kingdom,
1. As he preparatorily Governed by the <HI>Word, Miracles</HI> and
<HI>Spirit.</HI> 2. As he visibly Set up and Ruled by the Christian
Emperours and Kings. 3. As he at last entereth on the King∣dom
of Glory and Fruition. Your Fiction of another is but
your own word.</P>
<P>And now I have done what in the Enterance and Conclu∣sion
you provokingly Challenge all Persons believing the
Scriptures to do, and shew that while you say you <HI>Boast in
the Word of God,</HI> and not in your self, it is by giving us your
<PB N="44" REF="27"/>
own word, not only for Gods Word, but against it. The
Lord heal and forgive our weakness, and the ignorance of
our ignorance.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<P>It greatly hindereth the Edification of your Readers, that
you so much use terms General and Equivocal, that unexplain∣ed
signifie nothing: And so every Book needeth another to
Expound it, and that may as much need another. Some
think this is because you would not be understood, your Do∣ctrine
being not able to bear the Light. Others think it is
because you understand not your self, and therefore cannot
speak intelligibly, confused Notions having but confused Ex∣pressions.
The instances are more than I will recite. As
<HI>e. g.</HI> You place Christs Kingdom so often in his and his Saints
<HI>Appearance,</HI> as no Reader can discern, but you mean such <HI>Ap∣pearance</HI>
to Mans <HI>visive Faculty</HI> in these Fleshly Bodies, as if
now in Heaven Christ and Angels, and the Spirits of the Just
did not Appear to one another, because they <HI>appear</HI> not to us:
As if the Intuition of Spirits and Spiritual Bodies, were not
a more eminent discerning than our Eye-sight: Sure there is
a more noble sight, than that of Mortals.</P>
<P>So no Man can tell by your phrase of <HI>[swallowing up in God]</HI>
and that <HI>Christ</HI> was from Eternity, and shall be to Eternity,
the <HI>Word and Man imbodied,</HI> whether you mean that he was
an Individual Man distinct from any others, or the Univer∣sal
Soul of the World imbodied in Matter: And by your
talk of our being One in God, as we were before the World
began, none can tell whether you mean that we were Exis∣tent,
or only <HI>in Potentia Creatoris?</HI> And if Existent whether
we were God or parts of God, or individual Souls made from
Eternity for future Bodies, and kept till those Bodies were
made: And whether kept in Revolution from Body to Body?
Or how? And whether we shall have a future Revolu∣tion.</P>
<P>So your Doctrine of the Hell of the Devils and the Damn∣ed,
can tell no Man whether you think that after the Thou∣sand
years they shall not be as dead, under meer privation,
since you say, Catech. p. 5. and 22. <HI>It is a state of deprivation of
Glory, and casting into the Lake of Fire, signifieth, final and utter
<PB N="45" REF="27"/>
cessation of all action;</HI> And <HI>that they shall not appear</HI> but be un∣seen,
<HI>&amp;c.</HI> And if they have no Action, they have no sinful
Action, no Self-accusation, no Intellection, no Malice nor
Revenge, nor Hatred of God and Goodness.</P>
<P>So your Doctrine of the Kingdom of Christ; I cannot be∣lieve
you so notorious an Infidel, as to deny Christs Kingdom
in Heaven and Earth, till the Resurrection: And yet your
words expresly say, that his Kingdom then beginneth: and
that this Apostle mentioneth none till then.</P>
<P><HI>And in your</HI> Late Great Revolution, <HI>Epist. in the end, you
say,</HI> [His Monarchy shall then (1697) begin its Succession,
though the Glorious Investiture shall not be till Seventy five years
after.]</P>
<P>Can any but a Prophet that is inspired to Expound you, tell
what you mean by abundance such passages? What is the
difference between the <HI>Beginning</HI> of the <HI>Succession</HI> and the <HI>Glo∣rious
Investiture?</HI> What is the <HI>Succession?</HI> Doth it begin the
Thousand years or not? Doth the Succession begin Seventy
five years before the Investiture? Is not the <HI>Investiture</HI> Christs
Glorious Appearance?</P>
<P>Your Writings make it plain, that you are a good Man of
deep thoughts, faln into a fond esteem of your new unripe
Conceptions, and rapt up thereby into a diseased Conceited∣ness,
and how you will be able to bear it when providence
and experience have confuted you in 1697 I know not: But I
am the more bold to foretel your failing, by my perswasion
that your Exposition of the Revelation which you take for
granted, is a meer mistake from the Beginning almost to
the End.</P>
<P>And wonder not that no body writeth to confute you
For Men love not to trouble themselves with Convincing e∣very
single Man of his Errours. And the Reasons why I do
attempt it is because by the Seduction of some of my Friends,
and the general Inclination of the Antinomian, Anabaptist
and Separating Party, to this conceit of the Thousand years
Kingdom, and by the <HI>Midnight Cry</HI> published by Mr. <HI>R. M.</HI>
and preached by Mr. <HI>J. M.</HI> Men of very great Piety, whom
I highly value as any Conformists I know, I understand that
your Opinion that formerly was tolerable as confined to a few
conceited good Men, is now becoming a great Article of
<PB N="46" REF="28"/>
their Faith and Religion: Especially since I see that in all your
professed extraordinary Humility, you brand all that dissent
from you as Semi-Sadducees of the <HI>Apostacy,</HI> and earnestly
Challenge and provoke all Pastors and Doctors to answer you;
and maintain (though you Conform) that Gods Word
knoweth not a <HI>Clergy.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Chap. III. Of the other Sect of the Millenaries that place
the Thousand years Reign before the Conflagration.</HEAD>
<P>§. 1. THis was the Elder Sect: But Dr. <HI>More,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Be∣verley,</HI>
and Dr. <HI>Cressoner,</HI> and other late Writers,
being more searching, did perceive that this way would not
hold, nor by it could they countenance their Doctrine from
<HI>Rev.</HI> 20. the only Text that mentioneth a Thousand years
Reign (misunderstood.)</P>
<P>§ 2. They agree that, 1. There will be a Thousand years
Reign on Earth: 2. That the Jews shall be called, and make
a glorious part of this Kingdom: 3. That the Ten Tribes
now lost, shall be found, and be part of the Kingdom: 4. That
Turk and Pope shall fall before this: 5. That at last <HI>Gog</HI> and
<HI>Magog</HI> shall gather in War against this New <HI>Jerusalem:</HI> 6. That
fire from Heaven shall consume these Enemies.</P>
<P>§ 3. But they agree not, 1. Of the state of the Church
with Christ above all this time. 2. Nor whether there be one
or two New <HI>Jerusalems</HI> (one above, and one below.) 3. Nor
whether Christ shall Reign on Earth visibly in his Humane
Nature, or only by a holy Magistracy and Ministry? 4. Nor
whether all or most of the Jews shall go dwell at the Old
<HI>Jerusalem,</HI> or <HI>Judea,</HI> or stay in the several Countries where
they live? 5. Nor how far the Princes and Nations among
whom they live shall be converted with them? 6. Nor by
what means the Jews shall be converted? 7. Nor how long
it will be in doing? 8. Nor how the Princes under whom
they live will dismiss or use them? 9. Nor how they shall af∣ter
all become a <HI>Laodicea,</HI> and fuel fit for the Conflagration?
10. Nor whether that fire that burneth the Earth and Heaven,
and that which burneth <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog,</HI> make one or two
<PB N="47" REF="28"/>
Conflagrations? 11. Nor how far Christs Kingdom ceaseth
at the end of the Thousand years?</P>
<P>§ 4. As to both Sects, I know no more that I have further
to do for their full confutation, but I. To give a better Pa∣raphrase
of the Revelation than their feigned suppositions con∣tain:
And that I have done in a Book not yet Printed.</P>
<P>II. To prove that the Ten Tribes were but part of them
carried away by <HI>Salmanasser,</HI> and that they were in <HI>Cyrus</HI> Do∣minions,
and had leave as well as the Two Tribes to return
if they were willing: And that <HI>Galilee</HI> and other parts of
<HI>Israel</HI> as much owned Christ as the Two Tribes, at least: And
the Twelve Tribes made up the Converts that were the Ru∣diments
of the Christian Churches: And that it was to the
Twelve that <HI>James, Peter,</HI> and <HI>Paul</HI> to the <HI>Hebrews</HI> wrote:
And it was the Twelve that the 144000 <HI>Rev.</HI> 7. were sealed
out of, so expresly distinguished from the innumerable Gen∣tile
Christians, as may confute the Expositors, that make them
to signifie the Gentile Ministry.</P>
<P>III. To prove that at the Fall of the Pagan Empire, the
Fulness of the Gentiles came in, as meant <HI>Rom.</HI> 11. and all
<HI>Israel</HI> saved: That near three Millions of the Jews that were
cursed Infidels, being killed and ruined by <HI>Titus, Trajan</HI> and
<HI>Adrian</HI> (out of a Countrey not so big as half <HI>England)</HI> and
the Christians escaping, the Christian part remained the main
Body of the Nation: And marrying with Gentile Christians,
and forsaking <HI>Moses</HI> Law, lost the name of Jews, which re∣mained
only with the Off-spring of the scattered Infidels.
That <HI>Constantine</HI> made <HI>Judea</HI> one of the most famous Na∣tional-Provincial
Churches in the World, for Honours,
Temples, Monasteries and Bishops, no Jews being forbidden
there to dwell. And that God hath promised no further Con∣version
of the cursed remnant of the Infidel Jews, than of
any other Infidel Nations: And therefore all Christians
should not in ignorance of all this, corrupt their Prayers, and
Sermons, and Religion, with fathering on God such Promi∣ses
of the Jews Conversion as he never made, lest they be
found guilty of adding to his Word, and taking his Name in
vain, and scandalous depraving the Christian Faith. Nor
should they by ignorance unthankfully deny the performance
of Gods Promises, of the Fall of the Pagan Empire and <HI>Ba∣bylon,</HI>
<PB N="48" REF="29"/>
and so much of the Fifth Monarchy, and New <HI>Jerusa∣lem,</HI>
and Conversion of the Jews, as certain History puts us
past doubt is already past.</P>
<P>The performance of this, to avoid prolixity, I shall but
briefly give you as followeth.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Chap. IV. That the Ten Tribes of Israel, will never be
found and called, if they never were so heretofore.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. THose that are for a Jewish Monarchy, or their ge∣neral
Conversion, commonly hold that the Ten
Tribes carried away by <HI>Salmanasser,</HI> are lost, and never yet
restored. Whether this be true, we shall see anon. But if
it were true, it would follow, that they never will be found
and called, and consequently that they will be no part of the
Converted Jews.</P>
<P>§ 2. The proof is evident: Because the Accident suppo∣seth
a Subject: That which <HI>is not,</HI> hath no Accident. There
<HI>are</HI> no such Ten Tribes unknown and uncalled existent in
the World. None will say that any such are known: And
that's enough to prove them unknown, and if unknown, not
in being.</P>
<P>For 1. If the Infidel part of the Two Tribes be as many
as such think, how much more numerous must all the Poste∣rity
of the Ten Tribes be?</P>
<P>2. And Navigations, Travelling, and Merchandize, and
Embassies, have acquainted Men with so much of the Earth,
as tells us that they are not known in any known part of the
World: And were they Existent they could not be un∣known.</P>
<P><HI>Benjamin</HI>'s Itinerary that feigneth a discovery of them,
proveth it self fabulous, and is so accounted commonly by
sober learned Men. And dreaming that they are in <HI>America</HI>
is no proof.</P>
<P>§ 3. Learned Mr. <HI>Sam. Lee,</HI> well describeth many of the
places to which they were transplanted, and very learnedly
stretcheth his Wit to conjecture that they are in <HI>Tartary:</HI>
But 1. There is not any probability given us by him that
<PB N="49" REF="29"/>
ever they were thither removed, [at least any notable num∣ber.]
2. And though <HI>Tartary</HI> be large, and not all fully
known to us, yet so much is discovered by Historians and Tra∣vellers,
as may acquaint us that there is extant no Society of
known and professed Jews; they being all Heathens and Ma∣hometans,
save an inconsiderable sprinkling of Christians:
And <HI>Scythia</HI> hath been so anciently peopled, that even to the
Potent <HI>Roman</HI> Empire, they were the most Invincible Ene∣mies;
And the Wars of <HI>Tamerlane</HI> made them known to
much of the World. And if they were there, and Marrying
with <HI>Scythians</HI> have lost the Name of Jews, they are unreco∣verably
Extinct. And so cannot be called as Jews, being
now no Jews. It is become a Natural Impossiblity.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Chap. V. That the Ten Tribes were not lost, or Ex∣tinct.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. 1. THis is so clear by abundance of Prophesies in
<HI>Isaiah, Jeremiah,</HI> and <HI>Ezekiel, Hosea,</HI> that it
would be tedious to recite them; <HI>viz.</HI> That <HI>Judah</HI> and <HI>Israel</HI>
were to be again made one Kingdom, as two Sticks made
one Stick, and <HI>David</HI> their King to reign over them: If this
was not fulfilled, the Prophesie would fail, which must not
be imagined: For (as is aforesaid) if it be not fulfilled, they
being now extinct, and not existent, it never can be ful∣filled.</P>
<P>§ 2. 2. There is no probability (as Mr. <HI>Mather</HI> hath well
noted in his <HI>Diatriba)</HI> that all or most of the common people
were transplanted; but only the Rulers, and Rich, and Mi∣litary
and Leading Men. For 1. Considering how many
Millions that small Land maintained, it is improbable that
so great a multitude could be so far Ruled by an Army, or
that they should soon find vacant Habitations, and Victuals
for them. 2. And it is more unlikely that <HI>Salmanasser</HI> should
find so many of his Subjects to send into their places, and that
all those should be willing of a removal into so small a Land.
3. And it is known that no such thing hath been done by
Conquerours in any other Land. <HI>Nebuchadnezzar</HI> took from
<PB N="50" REF="30"/>
<HI>Jerusalem</HI> none but the Princes, Nobles, Priests, Rich Men,
Souldiers, and Men fit for his Militia, and Smiths, and Car∣penters,
<HI>&amp;c.</HI> But he left the common people to Manure the
Land: Otherwise they would lose all their Tribute, and the
Fruit of the Ground.</P>
<P>In all the Conquests made by the Persians, the Greeks, the
Romans, the Egyptians, the Saracens, the Turks, the Tar∣tarians
by <HI>Tamerlane,</HI> there hath no such thing been done, as
the transplanting of the most of the common Inhabitants.</P>
<P>Indeed the beggarly Goths, and Vandals, Ostrogaths and
<HI>Hemli, &amp;c.</HI> came with their Wives and Children sometimes,
resolving to possess or die: But what was a hundred thou∣sand
of such to all <HI>Italy</HI> when they possest it; or to all <HI>Spain,</HI>
or all <HI>France,</HI> or <HI>Africk,</HI> in comparison of the Inhabitants
whom they subdued and mastered?</P>
<P>In <HI>England</HI> how few were the Romans, yea or the Saxons,
or the Danes, or the Normans, in comparison of the <HI>Britains</HI>
that were brought in subjection unto them? It was but the
Great men, and Rich, and Military, and some fearful people
that fled from their Armies, that fled into <HI>Wales.</HI> As Mr. <HI>Tho.
Jones</HI> in his <HI>Hearts Soveraignty</HI> hath truly proved, the main
Body of this Nation called English, is of the Brittish Bllod
(it's like many hundred to one) though the Language fol∣lowed
the ruling part.</P>
<P>§ 3. 3. It is evident that All the Twelve Tribes were
in the Dominion of <HI>Cyrus,</HI> when he sent the Jews to repair
the Temple and City: The Two Tribes at <HI>Babylon</HI> where he
made <HI>Darius</HI> King, and the Ten in his Hereditary Dominions
and his Conquests, as Mr. <HI>Calvet</HI> in his <HI>Naphthali</HI> hath shew∣ed;
and as will appear by the Topography of the places
named in Scripture, to which they were carried, Learnedly
opened by Mr. <HI>Lee,</HI> abating his conceit of <HI>Tartary.</HI> And it is
evident that <HI>Cyrus</HI> meant not to confine the grant of his free
return to the Two Tribes: But those that were not willing
to return he did not compel: And most had possession by
that time of wider and fatter Habitations. <HI>Ezra 1. Cyrus</HI>
made no question of their liberty to dwell in <HI>Judea:</HI> But it
was Gods House at <HI>Jerusalem</HI> that God charged him to Build,
for which end he saith, <HI>ver. 3. [Who is among you of all his
people, his God be with him, and let him go up to</HI> Jerusalem <HI>which
<PB N="51" REF="30"/>
is in</HI> Judah, <HI>and Build the House of the Lord God of</HI> Israel <HI>(he
is the God) which is at</HI> Jerusalem. <HI>And whosoever remaineth in
any place where he Sojourneth, let the Men of his place lift him up
with Silver, and with Gold, and with Goods, and with Beasts,</HI> &amp;c.
Were the Ten Tribes none of <HI>the people of the God of</HI> Israel?
I must not swell this Book too big: Let the Reader that is
willing to understand, peruse <HI>Ezra, Nehemiah, Esther,</HI> and
<HI>Daniel,</HI> with <HI>Haggai,</HI> and <HI>Zechariah,</HI> and consider the Grants
of <HI>Darius,</HI> and <HI>Artaxerxes,</HI> and the vast number of Jews still
remaining abroad in the persecution of <HI>Haman,</HI> and he will
find that it was not for want of Liberty to return that so ma∣ny
stayed behind, but because the avoided returning as a
Suffering: And multitudes that had a Zeal for <HI>Jerusalem,</HI>
settled in <HI>Egypt</HI> at <HI>Alexandria,</HI> that thence they might three
times a year come to the Temple, without too much loss and
cost.</P>
<P>§ 4. 4. In Christs time the Habitations of the Ten Tribes
was of the same Religion with those at <HI>Jerusalem:</HI> And went
thither to the Feasts; and submitted to their Priests and
Ceremonies; Christ lived from his Childhood still in <HI>Galilee:</HI>
At <HI>Nazareth</HI> and <HI>Capernaum,</HI> where <HI>Peter, Andrew, James</HI> and
<HI>John</HI> lived: That is, close by the Ford of <HI>Jordan,</HI> by which
is the passage to <HI>Egypt:</HI> There he had far more Followers
than about <HI>Jerusalem:</HI> Thence went his supposed Father, and
Brethren ordinarily to the Feasts at <HI>Jerusalem: Zechary</HI> and
<HI>Elizabeth,</HI> many Levites, Scribes and Pharisees dwell in the
Countrey of the Ten Tribes: Though <HI>Samaria</HI> about the
place of Worship, by Customs kept up some Animosity a∣gainst
<HI>Jerusalem,</HI> yet the Woman, <HI>John</HI> 4. could say, <HI>When
the Messiah cometh he will tell us all things: And is not this the
Christ:</HI> And what place so generally received the Gospel
when <HI>Philip</HI> preached to them? It was not for nothing that
the Christians were so long called Galileans. But this and
more shall next be proved.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="6" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="52" REF="31"/>
<HEAD>Chap. VI. What Conversion the Twelve Tribes have al∣ready
had?</HEAD>
<P>§ 2. 1. AS is aforesaid, The Saviour himself (and his
Apostles) chose his abode on Earth among
them; and calleth them the lost Sheep of the house of <HI>Israel;</HI>
and the Children whose Bread must not be given to Dogs:
They were the Circumcision to whom he was a Minister:
He ordinarily Preached in their Synagogues, and there
wrought most of his Miracles: It was they that cryed him
as King with <HI>Hosanna</HI>'s: It was they that followed him to
the Cross; and it was in <HI>Galilee</HI> where on a Mountain he
appointed them to meet him after his Resurrection.</P>
<P>§ 2. 2. He appointed (not two, but) Twelve Apostles,
and 70 Disciples, as suited to the Twelve Tribes and their
Sanedrim, to shew what Form of Government he assigned
them, and for whom, and he sent his Apostles to the
Twelve Tribes of <HI>Israel.</HI></P>
<P>§ 3. 3. The chief success of their Preaching was on the
Samaritans and others of the Ten Tribes; and such of them
as came up to the Feasts.</P>
<P>§ 4. 4. There were three thousand at once converted of
the Jews; after made five thousand; and soon after many
Myriads of Jews believed (at least many thousands.)</P>
<P>§ 5. 5. These became the Mother-Church, and the Law
went out of <HI>Zion,</HI> and so all Nations were blest in <HI>Abrahams</HI>
Seed, and Christ became a Light to the Gentiles, and the
Glory of his People <HI>Israel:</HI> The scattered Jews of the
Twelve Tribes through much of the Empire, were the <HI>Sta∣mina</HI>
or Rudiments of the Gentile Churches: The Apostles
first Preached in their Synagogues, and the converted Gen∣tiles
were added to their Converts.</P>
<P>§ 6. 6. The Epistle to the <HI>Hebr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> was written to all
the Hebrew Christians, and not to Two Tribes only; and
implieth the great success of the Gospel on them.</P>
<P>§ 7. 7. <HI>Peter</HI> directeth his Epistle to all the Strangers
scattered through <HI>Pontus, Asia, Galatia, Phrygia,</HI> &amp;c. and
magnifieth their Grace.</P>
<P><PB N="53" REF="31"/>
§ 8. 8. <HI>James</HI> directeth his Epistle to <HI>the Twelve Tribes,
that are scatter'd abroad:</HI> And it is evident that he writeth to
them as Christians.</P>
<P>§ 9. 9. The seventh Chapter of the <HI>Revelations</HI> expresly
nameth the Twelve Tribes, of which One Hundred and
Forty four Thousand were Sealed, Twelve Thousand of
each Tribe (meaning a great number) that were to be
preserved from the Destruction that was to be executed
on their Enemies. The boldness of those Expositors
who give us their own Revelation instead of Christs, is
palpable: who tell us that by these One Hundred and For∣ty
four Thousand is meant all the Reformed that are saved
from the destruction to be executed on the Papists? What
words can we desire God to use more plain, that Men may
not pervert? 1. God speaketh of Jews, and they say he
meaneth Gentiles. 2. God nameth the Tribes, and they
exclude them. 3. They are called <HI>[The First Fruits]</HI> of the
Church:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 14. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> And they say, It meaneth the last. 4. The <HI>num∣berless</HI>
Gentile Christians that with them partaked of the pre∣servation,
are by way of distinction mentioned in the next
words: Yet these Commentators say, That the Gentiles are
meant by the Twelve Tribes. 5. The Prophesie is put in
the beginning before the Trumpets or Vials, even before all
the Judgments that were to come on Infidel Jews and <HI>Ro∣mans;</HI>
yet do they bring it down towards the end of the
World, or after the Fall of Pagan <HI>Rome.</HI></P>
<P>§ 10. 10. It was some considerable time before the Jew∣ish
Christians could be satisfied to let go their Priviledge of
Peculiarity and Mosaick Policy, and to Embody on equal
Terms with the Gentiles in the Catholick Church, and to
Marry with Gentile Christians: And all that time Dr. <HI>Ham∣mond,</HI>
and <HI>Grotius,</HI> and others say, They had in the great
Cities one Church of Jews and one of Gentiles; which also
difference of Language would require; and so had two Bi∣shops
in a City: And <HI>Peter</HI> for the Circumcision, and <HI>Paul</HI>
for the Uncircumcision, were the Roots of the Jewish and
Gentile Miracle-working Ministry, which I suppose were the
Two Witnesses mentioned in the <HI>Revelation;</HI> For whoever
they were they may be known by the Promise, <HI>Mark 16.
17,</HI> 18. <Q>In my Name shall they cast out Devils, they shall
<PB N="52" REF="32"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="53" REF="32"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="52" REF="33"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="53" REF="33"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="54" REF="34"/>
speak with new Tongues, they shall take up Serpents, and
if they drink any deadly thing it shall not hurt them, they
shall lay Hands on the sick, and they shall recover.]</Q> Our
Reformers pretended not to Miracles.</P>
<P>§ 11. 11. At the Wars of <HI>Vespasian</HI> and <HI>Titus</HI> against the
Jews, One Million and One Hundred Thousand were kill'd,
and Seven Hundred Thousand carried into Captivity; and
the Christians fore-warned by Christ, got out of the City
and escaped. And in <HI>Trajan</HI>'s days a Madness seized on the
Infidel Jews, and they rose up and Murdered many score
Thousands of the <HI>Roman</HI> Subjects: And after <HI>Barchocheba</HI>
proclaimed himself the Messiah, Murdered so many more as
amounted to an Hundred Thousands: VVhereupon <HI>Trajan</HI>
and <HI>Adrian</HI> in Revenge kill'd between One and Two Milli∣ons
of these Rebel Jews, still sparing the Christians. After
all this, the Infidel Jews could have but a small number left:
All <HI>London</HI> hath not near a Million. By which it appeareth
that the main Body of the Jews preserved, were the Christi∣ans,
to whom the Cursed part were few.</P>
<P>§ 12. 12. The Converted Jews fell into the Catholick
Church, and Married with Gentile Christians, and so ere
long lost the name of Jews, and became unknown.</P>
<P>So that the scattered Relicks now called Jews are but the
Off-spring of the Self-cursed Rabble that were scattered after
the aforesaid slaughter of them.</P>
<P>§ 13. 13. In <HI>Constantine</HI>'s Reign the Jews had as much
Liberty and Invitation to be Christians as any others: And
<HI>Judea</HI> was not only made a National-Provincial Church, but
was more honoured for Christs sake than any Nation no
greater, save the Imperial Seat. There were more Churches
Built, and more Monasteries, and more Bishops, than else∣where,
in so small a compass: No Jew was forbidden there
to live. No Countrey so honoured: The Devout People
from <HI>Rome</HI> and many Countreys went thither, some on Pil∣grimage,
and some to dwell: Thence they fetcht what Re∣licks
they could get in remembrance of Christ. There at
<HI>Bethlehem Jerom</HI> lived while he wrote and studied much of his
Works.</P>
<P>§ 14. 14. Since then in all Ages some of the Infidel Re∣licks
have been converted: Whether the History of the dis∣pute
<PB N="55" REF="34"/>
between <HI>Gregentius</HI> and <HI>Herbanus,</HI> and the miraculous
Conversion of them by Christs Appearance be true or no,
(which few judicious Men believe) in all Ages many Jews
have been Baptized, and some proved excellent Divines.</P>
<P>§ 15. 15. When all the Ten Kingdoms that had been
Tributary or Subject to the Pagan Empire, so quickly fol∣lowed
the success of <HI>Constantine</HI> and the Christian Arms, and
turned against the Pagan Idolatry, it is utterly incredible that
multitudes of the Infidel Jews did not the same. No one
Nation turned all at once: And no one National Church
under Heaven were all (that I say not the most) sincerely
holy Christians: The visible Church still consisted mostly of
temporizing Men, that came in to Christianity for worldly
Interest, over-awed by Christian Power: Till it came to
this, the Christians were a persecuted party, and no National
Church. And the unbelieving Jews were not like to be so
free from the Love of the Flesh and VVorld, as not to do
as others did. Christ Riding victoriously on the VVhite
Horse, and Conquering his Enemies, brought the Nations
to Submission, after he had by the Word and Martyrdom
purified to himself a holy Generation. As all the <HI>Revelation</HI>
fully telleth us. Therefore if <HI>Judea</HI> was not made a Na∣tional
Church, no other Nation was made such.</P>
<P><HI>Zonaras</HI> saith that many hired by Money turned Christians,
Two Hundred Thousand turned Christians for fear in their
Troubles at <HI>Toledo</HI> in <HI>Spain</HI> (whither they were long before
sent.) And Forty Fryars were sent to instruct them. Af∣ter
that <HI>Ferrerius</HI> converted many. Read but the Chrono∣logical
Tables of my worthy Friend Mr. <HI>Fr. Tallents,</HI> and you
shall find, how they were hated, hunted and destroyed, in
<HI>Spain, France,</HI> and almost all Christians Nations, except
<HI>Rome,</HI> and how many turned seeming Christians for fear.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="7" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="56" REF="36"/>
<HEAD>Chap, VII. Whether there be any Jerusalem Monarchy of
Jews, or any further Conversion of them, more than of
other Men, promised by God?</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. I know of no such Promise in Gods Word, but I
find it in many Books of Men, and I hear of it in
the Prayers and Sermons of many Men, so good, and of so
good repute, that divers of my Friends disswade me from
so much as giving my Reasons against it, lest I lose my Re∣putation
with such Men, and lest I occasion a Division by
contradicting them. And is it come to that? Must our Con∣cord
be held on such humane, loose and unsound terms? Is
this savouring the things of God, or of Men? If it be proved
an Errour, taking Gods Name in vain, polluting Sacred
Worship, and adding to the Word of God, must we by si∣lence
promote a Concord in it? I only humbly propose the
Reasons of my dissent to the tryal of wiser Men.</P>
<P>§ 2. 1. It belongeth to the Affirmers to produce their
proofs: But I can find no Text cited by them, that to a so∣ber
search hath any such proof.</P>
<P>1. As to the many Texts of the Prophets of the uniting of
<HI>Judah</HI> and <HI>Israel</HI> under <HI>David</HI> their King, and the Jews re∣possessing
their own Land, and the Subjection of their Ene∣mies,
and the Neighbour Nations to them, and the great
Slaughters of <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog</HI> in their Land, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> 1. Let the
Grandeur of Prophetical stile he allowed for, and this com∣pared
with the Prophecies against <HI>Babylon, Tyre, Sion, Moab,
Edom,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>2. Read the whole Text, and you will find most express
passages, that cannot be applyed to any such time and use as
this in question, but plainly speak of their return from Cap∣tivity,
and their following state. It would too much swell
my Book to try and vindicate all the particular Texts
Mr. <HI>James Calvert,</HI> having already done it in his <HI>Naphthali,</HI>
yet unanswered.</P>
<P>3. Confound not the Immediate Sense of the Prophesie,
with the remote, and set not one against the other, the se∣veral
<PB N="57" REF="36"/>
parts and degrees that make up the whole. Many Pro∣phesies
in the Psalms are spoken immediately of <HI>David,</HI> but
as he was a Type of Christ, in whom they were though re∣motely
yet chiefly fulfilled.</P>
<P>The Prophesies of the honour of the Jews, and their Re∣storation,
had divers degrees of fulfilling. 1. They were
primarily fulfilled in the return from Captivity, and the
Power that followed under <HI>Zorubbabel</HI> and the <HI>Maccabees.</HI>
2. They were further fulfilled by the Coming of the Messiah,
of the Seed of <HI>Abraham</HI> and <HI>David,</HI> in whom all the Nations
of the Earth are blessed. 3. They were further fulfilled at
Christs Resurrection, Ascension, and Effusion of the Holy
Ghost, and the many Thousands of them Converted; And
their spreading the Gospel over the Gentile World. 4. It
was yet more fulfilled when Dominion was given to Christi∣ans,
and the fulness of the Gentiles brought in all <HI>Israel,</HI> and
settled a National Church in <HI>Judea,</HI> and put all their Ene∣mies
in subjection to the Catholick Church of Jewish and
Gentile Christians, reconciled in one Body, the partition
Wall being broken down 5. It will be yet more fulfilled
in the New Heaven and Earth; under the Gospel there is
neither Circumcision not Uncircumcision, but Christ is All
and in All: How much more in the New World?</P>
<P>He that would promise to redeem Christians from Turk∣ish
Captivity, and restore them to their own Land, and pros∣per
and honour them there if they will obey him, must not
be thought to confound the several benefits and degrees of
this Promise: He that will lead you into an upper Chamber,
includeth every step of the Stairs that you ascend; and the
promise of helping you up the first step, includeth not the
last, but tendeth to it, and if you obey will lead you fur∣ther.</P>
<P>4. Read the Book of the <HI>Maccabees,</HI> and other History,
that you may not be ignorant of what is already done: For
instance, How the great Ruine of <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog</HI> (so Hy∣perbolically
set out) was fulfilled on the <HI>Syrian</HI> and <HI>Grae∣cian</HI>
Armies, (of which see the Assembly Mens Annota∣tions.)</P>
<P>§ 3. II. Their next seeming proof is from <HI>Rom.</HI> 11. of
which I have proved how much is fulfilled already; besides
<PB N="58" REF="35"/>
which I find no more there promised, than to all the Church
in the New World.</P>
<P>1. God cast not away the <HI>fore-known Elect, v.</HI> 1, 2, to 11.</P>
<P>2. Through their Fall and Infidelity, persecuting the Chri∣stians
from among them, the Gospel came to the Gentiles,
<HI>v.</HI> 12.</P>
<P>3. It was but <HI>some</HI> of the Branches that were broken off,
<HI>v.</HI> 17.</P>
<P>4. As the casting away of them was the converting and re∣conciling
of the Pagan World; so their receiving was as a
Resurrection of life from the dead, <HI>v.</HI> 15.</P>
<P>5. The Converted Gentiles were but grafted in among
them, and partakers with them, (and not without them) of
the fatness of the Olive, <HI>v.</HI> 17.</P>
<P>6. Not the Root, but the some Branches that were broken
off, was that we might be grafted in, <HI>v.</HI> 19. It was chiefly
the Priests, and Rulers, and the self-cursed Rabble that fol∣lowed
them, and yet some Priests and Pharisees were con∣verted.</P>
<P>7. If they continue not in Gods Goodness, the Gentiles al∣so
shall be broken off, <HI>v.</HI> 22. So much of conditionality is in
the Promise: And yet there is more Scripture to expect that
the Gentiles shall not be broken off, than that there shall be
any more National Conversion of the Jews.</P>
<P>8. The promise of restoring the broken Branches is, If
they continue not in unbelief, <HI>v.</HI> 23.</P>
<P>9. Yet here is a Prophecy that the Jews shall be eminently
replanted, <HI>v.</HI> 24. and not for ever left in general unbelief.</P>
<P>10. It was but blindness in part that happened to those
some, till the fulness of the Gentiles came in: Which must
either mean, till the Empire of the Roman World fell into
the Christians hands: Or else till all the Gentiles were con∣verted
that ever shall be: This last cannot be the meaning,
for then it would not be till the end of the World; there∣fore
it must be the former, which is long fulfilled, <HI>v.</HI> 25.</P>
<P>11. So all <HI>Israel</HI> were saved, that is, 1. All the <HI>Israel</HI> of
God, the believing Children of <HI>Abraham (for all are not</HI> Israel
<HI>that are of</HI> Israel,) gathered into one Catholick Body. 2. And
so many of Natural <HI>Israel</HI> as to make not only one of the two
Witnesses and Olive Trees, but also a formed National ho∣noured
Church-Society.</P>
<P><PB N="59" REF="35"/>
12. When to drive away the Gospel to the Gentiles some
were left in unbelief: The Elect part were they that were
beloved for their Father <HI>Abrahams</HI> sake, (much more for
Christs sake,) <HI>v.</HI> 28.</P>
<P>13. As it was from them that the Gentiles had the Gospel;
so it was from the Gentiles mercy that the restored Body of
the Jews obtained mercy, being by the Christian Emperors
and Princes restored and honoured, <HI>v.</HI> 29, 30.</P>
<P>14. God left the Rulers and many others in unbelief, that
he might recover (not each single person, but) a Political
Body and Power to the Nation as he did, <HI>v.</HI> 32. As <HI>Alexan∣der
Severus</HI> gave the Infidel Jews power to chuse them a Go∣vernour
of their own (under him) the Christian Emperors
did for the Christian Jews much more.</P>
<P>15. Thus is Gods Goodness and Severity glorified: And
what word in that Chapter proper to the Jews is not ful∣filled?</P>
<P>§ 4. As to the Texts that mention the <HI>Restitution of all
things,</HI> the Creatures groaning to be delivered from the bon∣dage
of corruption, drinking the fruit of the Vine new, and
such like; what word is in all this that respecteth the Jews
more than the Gentiles, or that may not be performed in
the New World, unlimited to Jews, or to a Thousand
years?</P>
<P>§ 5. The same I say of the Lords Prayer, <HI>Let thy King∣dom
come, &amp;c.</HI> which long made me hope for better days
on this same Earth: But this saith nothing more of the
Jews than of the Heathens. And who can here find any
limitation of this Kingdom to a Thousand years? All the
Word that tells us what to pray for, doth not tell us what
in this World we shall obtain. I doubt not but we may pray
for Jews and all men, but that proveth not all shall be con∣verted
and saved: We may have hope of many Individual
Jews, when we have no promise of a National further Resti∣tution
of the many more than of any others.</P>
<PB N="58" REF="37"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="59" REF="37"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="8" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="60" REF="38"/>
<HEAD>Chap. VIII. Reasons for the Negative humbly offered
to Tryal.</HEAD>
<P>§ 1. I. THat which is done already according to Promise,
we must not take for undone, or expect to be
done again. But the Calling of the Jews is done already ac∣cording
to Promise: <HI>Ergo, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>I hinted this oft before; I will not shun repetition where
the cause requireth it.</P>
<P>1. It is granted that the Catholick Church is called <HI>The
New Jerusalem,</HI> so far as it is short of the other World: But
the Catholick Church, and therein the Jewish Nation, was
more gloriously set up by the Christian Empire, than the Mil∣lenaries,
can reasonably expect or plead for: 1. What are
a few Rabble Jews, such as are among us, to the great, rich,
victorious Roman Empire, the greatest that ever was on
Earth, which turned Christian in the Regent part, and shortly
in the commonest Profession? What an Empire would the
Jews of <HI>England, Spain, Portugal, Turky, &amp;c.</HI> make?</P>
<P>2. <HI>Constantinople</HI> was then called not only <HI>New-Rome,</HI> but
<HI>New-Sion:</HI> And how greatly did it excel <HI>Jerusalem</HI> in spa∣ciousness,
riches, power and glory?</P>
<P>3. How small and barren a spot was <HI>Judea,</HI> (like our
<HI>Wales)</HI> in comparison of the Roman Christian Empire, in <HI>Eu∣rope,
Asia,</HI> and <HI>Africa?</HI> Like the <HI>Isle of Man</HI> to <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>4. How great a Protection had the Jews under <HI>Constantine,</HI>
and following Emperours, above what they had even after
their Restoration from Captivity, from <HI>Zorobabel</HI> and the
<HI>Maccabees</HI> to the end of their Policy.</P>
<P>5. What could they now desire for their return more than
they then had? What greater liberty, or encouragement, or
help? An excess of Honour was put on their Countrey, and
on all that would come into the Christian Church.</P>
<P>6. What better Plantation of Religion can be expected in
<HI>Judea,</HI> than was when the Emperours built them Temples,
and devout people travelled thither, and dwelt there, and
bought them Bibles, and built them Religious Houses, and
set over them Pastors, and Bishops, and A. Bishops, and a Pa∣triarch,
<PB N="61" REF="38"/>
one of the five in the Empire? And their National
Church honourably united to the Catholick? What outward
honour can they expect more? All Protestants note it as the
wicked Superstition of the Popes, that they were so set on the
honouring of <HI>Jerusalem</HI> and <HI>Judea,</HI> called <HI>The Holy Land,</HI> that
they forced Emperours, and Kings (of <HI>France</HI> and <HI>England, &amp;c.)</HI>
at vast charges to go fight for it, to the loss of 100000 men.</P>
<P><HI>§ 2. Obj.</HI> But <HI>Judea</HI> was not all planted with Jews, but with
a mixt people.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> 1. And must all that now possess it be robbed of their
Habitations and Estates, to make room for our Jews? 2. There
were no Jews restrained from going thither that desired it:
And would you have them forced, or sent thither with a
Pass? 3. Those that would not go thither had better en∣couragement
where they dwelt.</P>
<P><HI>§ 3. Obj.</HI> But it was not the main Body of the Nation
that was converted and restored.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> 1. I have given great probability that it was the far
greatest part, so many of the Rebels had been before de∣stroyed.
2. There was no Heathen Nation where the grea∣ter
number presently turned Christians, till Power and In∣terest
prevailed with them: Even till the days of <HI>Alari∣cus</HI>
and <HI>Theodorick</HI> thousands were Heathens in Christian <HI>Rome.</HI>
And holy <HI>Chrysostom</HI> in his days in the glory of <HI>Constanti∣nople,</HI>
reckoned but of a hundred thousand Christians, besides
Separatists and Hereticks, the rest being Heathens and Jews;
shall we therefore say that such were no National Churches,
that is, Christian Kingdoms?</P>
<P><HI>§ 4. Obj.</HI> But while their Governours were set over them
by others, and not chosen by themselves, they could not be called
Jewish National Churches.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> 1. Their Pastors were chosen by themselves, what∣ever
the Souldiers and Magistrates were. The Inhabitant
Christians Jews and Gentiles chose them. 2. Their submis∣sion
and consent might make them Churches of Jews. 3. But
I confess they were not, nor ever must be, Churches of Jews
separate from the Gentiles, or otherwise than as parts of the
Catholick United Church. It seems you take not the Jews
for converted, till they become separated from the Catho∣lick
Church, and claim their old peculiarity. Of which more
anon.</P>
<P><PB N="62" REF="39"/>
§ 5. II. The Doctrine of the Jews Conversion as in∣ferring
a Policy or Monarchy of Jews as such, is a con∣tradiction,
and therefore impossible.</P>
<P>Is there any room then for any further dispute of it?</P>
<P>When there are no Jews, there cannot possibly be any
Kingdom or Common-wealth of Jews: But were the self-cursed
Progeny converted, they would be no Jews imme∣diately
in a Religious sense, nor within sixty or eighty years
in a natural sense.</P>
<P>1. A Converted Jew joyneth himself to the Catholick
Church, and knoweth that this is his advancement,
above the old separate state of Peculiarity, and knoweth
that <HI>Moses</HI> Law and Policy is ended; and that if he turn
to that Law, he falls from Grace, and if he be (Jewishly)
Circumcised, Christ shall profit him nothing: Therefore he
is no more a Jew in Religion.</P>
<P>2. And being a Catholick Christian, he will marry with
Gentile Catholicks, and not confine Marriage to those of
his own Nation, to keep up the separation. And so with∣in
a short time there would be no Natural Jews. For instance;
If <HI>A</HI> marry <HI>B,</HI> a Gentile Christian, their Children will be
but half Jews: If their Children marry Gentile Christians,
their Children will be but a quarter Jews: And if those
marry Gentile Christians, their Children will be but an
eighth part of Jewish Race; that is, no Jews at all: Thus it
is faln out with the Progeny of all their converted Ance∣stors.
I have since I was twenty four years Old, lived in the
house with the Mother of the Grandmother of the Grand∣father
of some now living. And if I have seen between
24 and 76 so many Generations, in how short a time would
Converted Jews be no Jews?</P>
<P>§ 6. III. And the desire of such a Jewish Conversion,
State and Kingdom, or Church, as should continue them in
a Jewish Line and Peculiarity, distinct from the Catholick
mixed Church, is a <HI>wickedness,</HI> and contrary to the very na∣ture
of Christianity, and the Kingdom and Design of Christ:
For Christ came to take down the Partition Wall, Middle
Wall, and make of two one new man, even both one, (no
longer two:) Here is neither Greek nor Jew, Circumcision
nor Uncircumcision, Barbarian, Scythian, Bond or Free, but
<PB N="63" REF="39"/>
Christ is All, and in All, of whom the whole Family in Hea∣ven
and Earth is named, and will have all to grow up to one
perfect man, <HI>Eph.</HI> 2. &amp; 3. &amp; 4. <HI>Col.</HI> 3. Will Christ now turn
against his own uniting Design and Kingdom, and set up
<HI>Moses</HI> again and his Policy?</P>
<P><HI>§ 7. Obj.</HI> But we do not hold that he shall set up <HI>Moses</HI> Ce∣remonial
Law, or Worship.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Nor if you are Christians, should you say, that
he will turn again the one United Body into two, and by
restoring the carnal Peculiarity, to set up again the Wall
of Separation?</P>
<P><HI>§ 8. Obj.</HI> But if English, French, Spaniards, &amp;c. may be still
distinct, why may not Jews and Gentiles?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Because <HI>One</HI> is but accidentally and mutably, from
the difference of Countreys and Habitation, and of Lan∣guage,
and Trading, and Government, which Christ came
not to unite: But the other is on pretence of a Religious
Trust on a Divine Gift of Peculiarity, setting them up above
the rest of the Church, which Christ came to take down,
and tendeth to Church Divisions.</P>
<P>§ 9. IV. So hardly were the first Converted Jews taken
off their conceit of Peculiarity, and acknowledging Catholick
Equality of the Gentiles, and such doleful Heresies and
Breaches were made by this Pride, that it is not safe tempt∣ing
them to it again.</P>
<P>§ 10. V. It seemeth a Carnal Imputation of the most
Holy God; as if he made under the Gospel so great an ac∣count
of one sort of People by their peculiar Birth-priviledge,
above all the rest of the World. When <HI>Paul</HI> tells us that
All Believers are <HI>Abrahams</HI> Children, and that he is not a
Jew that is one outwardly, nor that Circumcision which is
of the flesh. And the Jews are so far from being of any
better nature or desert than other men, that the Infidel part
have ever since their self-cursing and obdurateness in unbe∣lief,
been found in all Nations to be the most covetous,
treacherous, and sottish sort of People: Much unprepared
for so great a change.</P>
<P>§ 11. VI. Either All the Off-spring of the Jews shall be
partakers of this pretended Priviledge and Monarchy, or only
the Off-spring of those that continued Infidels till the change.
<PB N="62" REF="40"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="63" REF="40"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/></P>
<P><PB N="64" REF="41"/>
But neither of these can be true. 1. The Off-spring of all
that have been converted for fourteen hundred years after
Christ, cannot possibly now be made any parts of a Jewish
Monarchy or State: Because they are all unknown, and are
now no Jews: And so that it is impossible.</P>
<P>2. And to advance only the present profligate Generation,
to a separate Monarchy, excluding all the Off-spring of the
Converts of all former Ages, looks so strangely, that the affir∣mers
had need to bring good proof of it, considering the diffe∣rence
of quality and number, that the least and worst part
shall be chiefly advanced.</P>
<P>§ 12. VII. Either in this Jewish advancement, all the
rest of the Godly through the World shall be as much ad∣vanced,
or the Jews alone. If all the Godly, they being I
hope a Thousand to one Jew, why should it be called a Jew∣ish
<HI>Jerusalem</HI> or Monarchy? Then sure, this New <HI>Jerusalem</HI>
must be setled in all Kingdoms, where the Godly dwell:
And shall they every where be Lords? If it be only for the
Jews, can any but a Jew believe it? That the Off-spring of
the scattered, cursed, sottish Enemies of Christ, shall be so
much preferred before all the Godly through the World?</P>
<P>§ 13. VIII. Either all the Nations of Heathens, Maho∣metans,
Papists, and Ungodly-Ones, shall be Converted,
with the Jews, or not: If yea, it will be a New and Hap∣py
World indeed: A Blessed Change will be made on Kings,
and Parliaments, and Lords, and Rich Men, and Poor:
And there will be as many Miracles as Men, when all those
shall be made wise and holy, that we cannot now with twen∣ty
years preaching prevail with to be Men, and to cease ma∣lignity,
and bestial Lusts: Sure God will not Burn such a
Blessed World, and bury so many Millions of Miracles in
the Flames.</P>
<P>But if it be only the Jews, that are miraculously Conver∣ted,
it must be a Miracle that must cause the malignant
Princes and People, Heathens, Mahometans, Greeks, Pa∣pists
and Carnal Protestants, either to become Subjects to
these poor Jews where they dwell, or to help or permit
their Transportation to <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> and then to be subject to
them there: If this must be their Fate, why do we not ac∣quaint
our selves with those few cursed Enemies of Christ,
<PB N="65" REF="41"/>
that live in <HI>London,</HI> in <HI>Wapping,</HI> or elsewhere near us, and
honour them, and beg their favour against the time of their
Reign. <HI>Oliver Cromwell</HI> appointed a Solemn dispute before
him, whether the Jews (for Money) should have a Tole∣ration,
and when that good Man Dr. <HI>Tho. Goodwin,</HI> and some
other godly Independents had spoken much for it, <HI>Matthew
Newcomen</HI> (that holy Man) so opened the wickedness of
turning loose a Cursed Generation to tempt a Nation to In∣fidelity,
that is already too much inclined thereto, as turned
the Scales, and put an end to that deliberation.</P>
<P>§14. IX. Either the feigned Conversion of these Jews
will be before the burning of the World, or after: But nei∣ther
before nor after: Therefore not at all.</P>
<P>1. If it be Before, either it will be the Thousand years
Reign, or some part of the Thousand years Reign, or be∣ffore
it all.</P>
<P>If it be the Thousand years Reign, then 1. The World
must last yet a Thousand year after the Jews Conversion:
Which few believe. 2. And then there will be no Thou∣sand
years Reign after the Conflagration, which our chief
Millenaries will not endure: For there is but One Thousand
years Reign looked for by them. 3. And then the New <HI>Je∣rusalem</HI>
state shall have the numberless Enemies of the Ar∣mies
of <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog:</HI> And shall fall to a Laodicean Luke∣warmness: What! After so many Millions of Mira∣cles?</P>
<P>2. But if they say it will be After the burning of the
World, that is before disproved: For the Thousand years are
past before that Conflagration. <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog,</HI> and the
numberless Enemies will not survive the Burning, nor live
in the New Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteousness.</P>
<P>3. And if they say that it will be but some part of the
Thousand years, or a short time before the Conflagration.
1. The Thousand years will not be divided, part before the
Burning, and part in the next World. 2. And so short a
Reign of the Jews, as shall end before the Thousand years,
and Burning, will not answer the glorious preparation of so
many Millions of Miracles, nor the Doctrine of their so
speedy Apostasie after, as to prepare for the <HI>Incendium.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="66" REF="42"/>
§15. X. The Miracles must be so many and great, that
must go to the feigned Conversion and Exaltation of these
Jews, that it will be a great and heinous crime to impose
them on God by presumptuous Fiction, if the Truth of
them be not proved; 1. As to the number of Converts.
2. Their present unfitness. 3. Their scattered distance.
4. Their Servitude in all Nations. 5. The feigned way of
their Conversion. 6. The state of their feigned Exalta∣tion.
All these must be so full of Miracles, that will a
thousand-fold exceed all the Miracles that ever Christ did on
Earth, or his Apostles after him. And God keepeth so con∣stant
a tenor in his Established Order of working by means
and subordinate Causes, as that we must have good proof
before we say that he will do all this. Tell us not <HI>what God
can do,</HI> when our Question is, <HI>what he will do.</HI> God can en∣lighten
the World without the Sun, or make all the frame
of Heaven and Earth to change their course: God can con∣vert
Turk and Pope, and all the Heathens in the World,
and all the bloody Princes and Souldiers, to morrow. But do
not therefore say that He will do it. When the Devil
tempted Christ to shew his power by a Miracle, he saith,
<HI>It is written, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</HI></P>
<P>God hath appointed a quite contrary way for mens Con∣version,
<HI>Rom. 10. How shall they believe on him of whom they
have not heard? and how shall they hear without a Preacher? and
how shall they Preach unless they be sent? Christ ascended on
high to give gifts and offices to men, for this end,</HI> Apostles, Pro∣phets,
Teachers, <HI>to gather and edifie his Church.</HI> Christ tells
us of no way but the Lord of the Harvest to send forth La∣bourers,
and the Messengers to go into the high-ways and
hedges, and compel them to come in: And the Sowers to
go forth to sow that Word, which is the regenerating
Seed.</P>
<P>Though Christ would speak to <HI>Paul</HI> from Heaven, it was
to send him to <HI>Ananias.</HI> And though an Angel appear to <HI>Cor∣nelius,</HI>
it is to send him to <HI>Peter</HI> to be taught. Though Mi∣racles
affright the Jailor, <HI>Act.</HI> 16. it is to ask <HI>Paul</HI> and <HI>Silas,
what he must do to be saved.</HI> And by what warrant shall we
say that Christ will for millions quite change this his ap∣pointed
way?</P>
<P><PB N="67" REF="42"/>
§ 16. 1. As to the number, it must be ten thousands of
Miracles that a number so great should be thus changed all
at once, or near it, throughout the World: And yet that
a number so small in comparison of all others, should become
a Monarchy, and <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog</HI> be so friendly to them, as
to permit and help them, as <HI>Cyrus</HI> did the Jews, in their re∣moval,
and afterward be subject to them.</P>
<P>§ 17. 2. They are now a more sottish Generation, full
of Malice against Christ, and Cruelty to Christians where
they dare shew it; sordidly worldly and covetous: They
live among Christians, and all our endeavours, converse and
examples scarce converteth in this Kingdom, three in an
Age. Bear with me you that talk so zealously for the
Jews Conversion and Kingdom, while I ask you, How
many in <HI>London</HI> have you converted in your lives? Yea▪
How many have you laboured with by Instruction and Ar∣gument
to convert them, while you have prayed for their
Conversion, and censoriously disputed against us that doubted
of your Opinion?</P>
<P>§ 18. 3. They are scattered over the most of the Earth,
being every where a hated and despised people. And
shall Preachers be sent to them in all Lands at once?
Shall Preachers so quickly be made, when no Countrey
have enough for their needful work at home? And shall
they quickly learn and speak all the Languages of the
Countreys where the Jews are? (For Hebrew alone will
not do the work.) And shall all Jews on Earth, get toge∣ther
to <HI>Jerusalem?</HI> Will they be Rich enough to bear the
charge of their Transplantation? Or enough cured of the
love of Riches, to leave their Trades and Wealth behind
them?</P>
<P><HI>§ 19. Obj.</HI> We hold not that they shall all be converted
or dignified, but enough to possess <HI>Jerusalem</HI> and Reign there:
<HI>Say some,</HI> The Tartarians may do it.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> It seems then it is but the Popes old Zeal, to re∣cover
the <HI>Holy Land:</HI> But what's this to the Conversion of
the Jews? Were they converted when <HI>Godfrey</HI> and others
recovered it? The Tartarians taking <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> will not
prove the Conversion of one Jew, that now is taken for a
Tartarian.</P>
<P><PB N="68" REF="43"/>
§ 20▪ 4. They are in such servitude in all Nations, and
so contemned a People among them, as must prove it a Mi∣racle
for them to remove so far, to power.</P>
<P>§ 21. 5. The feigned means of their Conversion is mil∣lions
of Miracles.</P>
<P>1. The New Opinion is, that Christ shall do it by ap∣pearing
in the Air as he did to <HI>Saul.</HI> O take heed what
you impose on Christ! That appearance of Christ was seen
but by a very few in one place: And the words heard by
none but <HI>Saul</HI> himself. Shall Christ in the Air be seen at
once in <HI>Persia, Greece, Rome, Portugal,</HI> and all Nations
where there be Jews? (And yet these good men are against
the <HI>Lutheran Vbiquitarians!)</HI></P>
<P>And shall Christ Preach to them in the Air, and his voice
be heard throughout the World, a thousand times further
than the Thunder?</P>
<P>And how will they know that it is Christ? when on
Earth they would not know him; but imputed his Miracles
to <HI>Beelzebub?</HI></P>
<P>And will the bare sight of Christ, make millions of ig∣norant
sots presently understand all the Essentials of Reli∣gion,
yea and become eminently wise and holy, when we
can scarce teach an ignorant one now to understand the Ca∣techism
or Creed in many years? I doubt many Mille∣naries
have some such Servants and Children in their own
houses.</P>
<P>2. Some say that <HI>Elias</HI> shall come and Convert them? A
Jewish Dream: And how will they know that he is <HI>Elias?</HI>
As they knew <HI>John Baptist</HI> to be <HI>Elias!</HI> If you say, as <HI>Peter</HI>
did on the Mount, I say, that was by Inspiration, or by
Christs telling him that it was <HI>Elias.</HI> Shall they have either
of these?</P>
<P>And where shall <HI>Elias</HI> preach to them? Is he also ubiqui∣tary?
If he preach in <HI>Spain,</HI> shall they hear him in <HI>Portugal?</HI>
Or if in <HI>Holland,</HI> or Rome, shall they hear him in <HI>England?</HI>
If he preach at <HI>Stepney,</HI> shall they bear him at <HI>Westminster,</HI>
at <HI>Tarmouth,</HI> at <HI>Norwich,</HI> and all over the Land, and over all
the World at once? Or must he stay long enough to go over
all the Earth? If one Man can do so much why have ma∣ny
thousands done so little on the Jews to this day?</P>
<P><PB N="69" REF="43"/>
3. If you say, God will raise up and send forth Ministers
enough, that will be yet a greater Miracle: To give so ma∣ny
Skill, VVill and Zeal? To cause them to speak with all
the Languages of the Nations? When the Jesuits at <HI>Japan,
Congo,</HI> and <HI>China,</HI> after many years Learning their Tongues,
do but set the Nations in a Laughter, to hear their mispro∣nunciation,
as <HI>Maffeius, Varenlus,</HI> and others tell us.</P>
<P>And who will furnish so many Thousand new inspired
Preachers, with Money to carry them through all the
VVorld? And procure them free passage through Enemies
Lands?</P>
<P>4. But the last answer I expect is, that nothing is difficult
where God will work, and Grace shall make one sight of
Christ, to Convert them all. I answer, If you lay all on
the Miraculous Inspirations of God, that can do it without
seeing Christ, and without preaching; As God made the
World with a Word: He can so make every Infant a
Doctor, that they not stay as Christ, to encrease in Stature
and Wisdom. But if you feign him to purpose or promise
this, take heed lest he will not hold you guiltless for taking
his Name in vain. This Creating Inspiration of sudden Wis∣dom,
Faith and Holiness, into so many Thousands over
the World at once, will be a greater Miracle, yea Milli∣ons
of Miracles, than ever Christ did: And is quite contrary
to the Word of God.</P>
<P>§ 22. 6. The feigned Exaltation of them by a <HI>Jerusalem</HI>
Monarchy is also a devised Miracle: That these scattered
people by such means, should get to <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> and become
a Grand Monarchy, and that in a place so uncapable, and that
never was such, no not in <HI>David</HI>'s days.</P>
<P>§ 23. XI. Another reason against this Jewish Monar∣chy
at <HI>Jerusalem</HI> is, that instead of an Exaltation, it would
be a Banishment to the Jews. <HI>Judea</HI> being like our <HI>Wales,</HI>
or not so big as half <HI>England,</HI> and a Countrey (though
flowing with Milk and Honey in comparison of the <HI>Arabian</HI>
Wilderness, yet) very full of Mountains, Rocks, and De∣serts,
and oft infested with Famines. So that could they
bear their charges thither, I believe that the Jews in <HI>Portu∣gal,
Constantinople, Rome,</HI> and <HI>Thessalonica</HI> alone, would take
it for as sad a Banishment to be sent to <HI>Judea,</HI> as all <HI>England</HI>
<PB N="68" REF="44"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="69" REF="44"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="68" REF="45"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="69" REF="45"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="70" REF="46"/>
would do to be sent to <HI>Jamaica,</HI> yea or <HI>Barbadoes.</HI></P>
<P>If you say that God can feed them by Manna, or by An∣gels,
or Ravens, or make all the Neighbours Countreys,
<HI>(Egypt, Mesopotamia,</HI> &amp;c.) feed them; take heed of impo∣sing
upon God.</P>
<P>§ 24. XII. God in Scripture hath given us another de∣scription
of the Two New <HI>Jerusalems,</HI> the Infantile and the
Perfect, that on Earth, and that on Heaven, more Glorious
and Desireable than the Jewish feigned one: Therefore we
should not obscure the Glory of them by such a Fiction. As
Satan fighteth against the Spirit by a false Spirit, and against
the Church by a false Church, and against the Ministry
by a false Ministry, and against Unity by false Unity, so
doth he against the Kingdom of Christ, and the New <HI>Jeru∣salem</HI>
by a Counterfeit.</P>
<P>1. As the <HI>Assyrian, Persian, Grecian,</HI> and <HI>Roman</HI> Mo∣narchies
were the four mentioned in <HI>Daniel;</HI> so there have
been since a fifth and a sixth. By a Monarchy now is
meant only the Greatest on Earth known to the Church.
The fifth was the Christian Empire, whose Chief Seat was
<HI>Constantinople,</HI> called <HI>New Rome,</HI> and <HI>New Sion.</HI> I am not
ignorant what is said against this by <HI>Heddeggerus</HI> and many
others: That is not to be disputed in this narrow Room.
The sixth Monarchy visibly is the Turks, with the Tar∣tarian
Unity, <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog.</HI> The seventh, the Sabba∣tical
and Perfect Monarchy is that of Christ in the New
Heaven, and New Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteousness,
after the Burning of this World: By debasing Fiction con∣fined
to a Thousand years, and Christs own Kingdom also
so confined, whereas this wicked World hath already lasted
Six Thousand years within Three Hundred and Ten. This
vilifying of Christs Glorious Kingdom is by blind Zeal
now made the exalting of it, by many deceived and de∣ceiving
Men.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="9" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="71" REF="46"/>
<HEAD>Chap. IX. Of the New Earth.</HEAD>
<P>§ 25. COncerning the New Earth we must content our
selves with what God hath revealed, and not
search into the unrevealed things.</P>
<P>1. It is revealed that it will be the Restitution of all
things; that in it shall dwell Righteousness; that the whole
Creation groaneth to be delivered from the Bondage of
Corruption into the Glorious Liberty of the Sons of God;
that it will be a Paradise State; that Christ shall Reign
over it; that no Glorified Saints shall lose any of their
part in Heaven by it; that there will be no death, nor mi∣sery:
Therefore there will be no <HI>Gog</HI> and <HI>Magog,</HI> and num∣berless
Armies of the wicked: For there entereth nothing
that is defiled: It will be a State of Communion with Hea∣ven.
Angels and Men will have familiar Converse: Christ
shall be joyfully known among them as their Saviour and
King: Neither Christ nor the Saints will lay by the Hu∣mane
Nature or Body, but their Bodies will be so far re∣fined
as shall be suitable to the condition of the New refined
World: This much is certain.</P>
<P>But these things following are uncertain. 1. How much
of the Old Earth God will use in the constitution of the
New. Whether only the Surface of the Earth shall be
Burnt, and the Things and Works thereon, or also the
Interiour parts dissolved into a Chaos: As it is uncertain
to us whether the Chaos at the present Earths Creation,
was the Relicks of a former World: We are not certain
whether there was any former World; Though to con∣jecturing
Reason it seems improbable that God who de∣lighteth
in his Works, and will continue a VVorld to Eter∣nity,
should from all Eternity have nothing but Himself,
till Six days ago (Six Thousand years.) But this will in∣fer
<HI>Aristotle</HI>'s Eternity of the Universe (except mutations
of alterable compositions) that the VVorld is an Eternal
Effect of an Eternal Cause; and <HI>Gassendus</HI> his Indefiniteness
(he meaneth Infiniteness) of the VVorld, and the old
<PB N="72" REF="47"/>
Opinion that God and the VVorld are but One, as Soul
and Body: By which they resolve the Grand difficulties
that God is not <HI>Pars Entitatis,</HI> which were to be Imperfect
and so no God, the Entity of the <HI>World and God</HI> being more
than of either alone, if the VVorld have any real En∣tity.</P>
<P>2. It is uncertain how God will people this New Earth:
Some think as he did this Earth by <HI>Adam</HI> and <HI>Eve.</HI> Some
think, by a Creation of many at once. Some think by a
Transplantation from some other Orb: Some think as Dr. <HI>H.
More,</HI> that except a few rare Saints or Martyrs, all go hence
but into an Aerial Vehicle, and may thence without loss
be made Inhabitants of the New Earth. And some think
that those that are found alive, shall live in the Fire and
after, and some that they shall be caught up from the Fire,
and Judg'd, and sent hither again.</P>
<P>3. It is uncertain whether there shall be any Generation
on the New Earth: Mr. <HI>Beverley</HI> saith, They shall multiply
so as to compensate with a <HI>[much more]</HI> for the <HI>Jewness
of the saved▪ under the first</HI> Adam] and each shall live the
Thousand years: But Christ saith that the Children of the
Resurrection neither Marry nor are given in Marriage, but
are like the Angels, and die no more. The doubt is then,
whether he call only those in <HI>Heaven,</HI> and not those on the
New Earth, <HI>the Children of the Resurrection.</HI></P>
<P>4. It is uncertain whether there shall be any stated visi∣ble
presence of Christ here, or that only he shall appear as
in Heaven, as the Sun doth by its Light; or only some∣times
be seen as he was after his Resurrection. And so of
the Angels.</P>
<P>5. It<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s uncertain whether the New Earth shall have any
End or Change, or shall be Everlasting. It's certain that
the Thousand years <HI>Rev.</HI> 20. are before it in this Life, but
of its Duration God hath said nothing to us.</P>
<P>6. It's uncertain how much of the Old Heaven shall be
Burnt: Though it's likely it will be only so much as was
Cursed for Sin.</P>
<P>7. It's uncertain whether there will be any removal to
a higher VVorld, and each Person live his Thousand years,
and then as <HI>Henoch</HI> and <HI>Elias</HI> be translated, and so on to
<PB N="73" REF="47"/>
following Generations; or each Person continue here for
ever.</P>
<P>8. It's uncertain whether Devils shall be permitted here
to be Tempters, or all Temptations be cast out.</P>
<P>§ 26. It will be no disparagement to Christ to Rule the
Restored Earth as well as Heaven. Nor to Saints or Angels
to be Governours under him. VVere the Sun Intellectual it
would be no grief to it to be a Benefactor by its Influence
to Earth: For it is no dishonour to God Himself, to Com∣municate
all to the Creature that it hath. There may be
here such Subjects as God promised Apostles and Saints that
they shall Judge.</P>
<P>If by Faith in Christ God dwell in us by Love, and we in
Him, and we have in us that Kingdom of Grace, we shall
have our Part in the future Kingdom, though we understand
not many difficulties about it. For Christ is the Author of
Eternal Salvation to all them that obey him.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE>Decemb. 10. 1690.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<HEAD>A Catalogue of Books Printed for, and Sold by Tho. Parkburst, at
the Bible and Three Crowns in Cheapside, near Mercers
Chapel.</HEAD>
<P>CAtholick Theology. <HI>Folio.</HI></P>
<P>The Saints Everlasting Rest; or a Treatise of the Bles∣sed
State of the Saints in their Enjoyment of God in Glory <HI>4to.</HI></P>
<P>The English Nonconformity, as under King <HI>Charles</HI> II. and
King James II. Truly Stated and Argued. <HI>4to.</HI></P>
<P>The Life of Faith in every State. <HI>4to.</HI></P>
<P>Alderman <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Funeral Sermon. <HI>4to.</HI></P>
<P>A Key for Catholicks to open the Juglings of the Jesuits.
The first part of answering all their common Sophisms: The
second against the Soveraignty and necessity of General Coun∣cils.
<HI>4to.</HI></P>
<P>Naked Popery: Answering Mr. <HI>Hutchinson. 4to.</HI></P>
<P>Which is the True Church▪ A full Answer to his Reply;
proving that the General Councils and the Popes Primacy
were but in one Empire. <HI>4to.</HI></P>
<P><PB REF="48"/>
The History of Bishops and their Councils abridged, and of
the Popes. <HI>4to.</HI></P>
<P>A full Treatise of Episcopacy, shewing what Episcopacy we
own and what is in the English Diocesan frame, for which
we dare not swear never to endeavour any alteration of it, in
our places. <HI>4to.</HI></P>
<P>A Search for the English Schismatick; comparing the Ca∣noneers
and Nonconformists. <HI>4to</HI></P>
<P>An Answer to Mr. <HI>Dodwell</HI> and Dr. <HI>Sherlock,</HI> consisting an
<HI>Vniversal-Humane Church</HI> Soveraignty, Aristocratical and Mo∣narchical,
as Church-Tyranny and Popery; and defending
Dr. <HI>Iz. Barrows</HI> excellent Treatise. <HI>4to.</HI></P>
<P>Catholick Communion defended against both Extremes.</P>
<P>Moral Prognostications, what shall befal the Church till
their Concord, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>Full and easie satisfaction, which is the True Religion:
Transubstantiation shamed. <HI>8vo.</HI> All <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by Mr. <HI>R. Baxter.</HI></P>
<P>A Hundred Select Sermons on several Texts, of Fifty on
the Old Testament, and Fifty on the New. <HI>Folio.</HI></P>
<P>The True Prophecies and Prognostications of <HI>Michael No∣strodamus,</HI>
Physician to <HI>Henry</HI> the Second, <HI>Francis</HI> the Second,
and <HI>Charles</HI> the Ninth, Kings of <HI>France,</HI> and one of the Best
Astronomers that ever were. <HI>Folio.</HI></P>
<P>Sixty one Sermons, Preached mostly on publick occasions,
whereof five formerly Printed by <HI>Adam Littleton,</HI> D. D.
Rector of <HI>Chelsea</HI> in <HI>Middlesex, Folio.</HI></P>
<P>A Discourse of the Saving Grace of God by the late Reve∣rend
and Learned <HI>David Clarkson,</HI> Minister of the Gospel. <HI>8vo.</HI></P>
<P>The Vision of the Wheels seen by the Prophet <HI>Ezekiel;</HI>
Opened and Applied: Partly at the Merchants Lecture in
<HI>Broadstreet,</HI> and partly at <HI>Stepney,</HI> on <HI>January</HI> 31. 1689 being
the Day of Solemn Thanksgiving to God for the great Deli∣verance
of this Kingdom from Popery and Slavery, by his
then Highness the most Illustrious Prince of <HI>Orange:</HI> Whom
God raised up to be the glorious Instrument thereof. By
<HI>Matth. Mead</HI> Pastor of a Church of Christ at <HI>Stepney. 8vo.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="48"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

