<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A remonstrance of some fallacies and mistakes, whereof the informers who have hitherto attempted against the House of the Stillyard, suppressing the truth, and by false suggestions deceiving at one those who do not heed, and those who are ignorant of the matter, or at least those who are too credulous, have made use of With particular answers to all, and a conclusion and petition on every point.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Boekell, Martin.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A28542</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing B3427B</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R214124</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99826338</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99826338</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">30739</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A28542)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30739)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1826:3)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A remonstrance of some fallacies and mistakes, whereof the informers who have hitherto attempted against the House of the Stillyard, suppressing the truth, and by false suggestions deceiving at one those who do not heed, and those who are ignorant of the matter, or at least those who are too credulous, have made use of With particular answers to all, and a conclusion and petition on every point.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Boekell, Martin.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>15, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>printed by Tho. Newcomb,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1659.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Signed at end: Martin Boekell.</NOTE><NOTE>Defends the right of the Hanseatic League to maintain their enclave at the Steelyard in London. Also an argument for continued trade between England and the League.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Guildhall Library, London.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Hanseatic League --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Merchants, Foreign --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Staple system --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ali Jakobson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ali Jakobson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A28542">
<STC T="W">B3427B</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99826338</BIBNO>
<VID>30739</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A
REMONSTRANCE
OF SOME
Fallacies and Mistakes,
Whereof the
INFORMERS
Who have hitherto attempted against
THE
HOUSE
OF THE
STILLYARD,
Suppressing the Truth, and by False Sug∣gestions
deceiving at once those who do not heed, and
those who are ignorant of the Matter, or at least those
who are too credulous, have made use of.</P>
<P>WITH
Particular ANSWERS to all, and a
Conclusion and Petition on every Point.</P>
<P>LONDON:
Printed by <HI>Tho. Newcomb.</HI> 1659.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A
REMONSTRANCE
OF SOME
Fallacies and Mistakes,
Whereof the Informers who have hitherto at∣tempted
against the House of the Stillyard, suppressing the Truth,
and by false Suggestions deceiving at once those who do not
heed, and those who are ignorant of the Matter, or
at least those who are too credulous,
have made use of.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">With particular ANSWERS to all, and a Con∣clusion
and Petition on every Point.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="fallacy">
<HEAD>The First Fallacy.</HEAD>
<P>THey oftentimes pretend, and almost every where lay
it for a ground, That the Right and Priviledges of
the <HI>Stillyard</HI> have no other foundation but the meer
Grace of the Kings in former Ages, not so well re∣garding
the Interest of the People; and therefore
at any time easily revocable.</P>
<P>But this is a mistake, As if the <HI>Hanse-Towns</HI> had obtained these
Rights through the meer Grace of the Kings; for they pro∣fess
to have merited the same,</P>
<P>1 By Supplies and Aids at their great Expences, in former
Ages administred to <HI>England,</HI> against the French and
other Enemies.</P>
<P>2 By many valiant Conflicts for the <HI>English,</HI> and suppres∣sing
of their Enemies.</P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="3"/>
3 In lieu of Damages unjustly in former times sustained by
the <HI>English.</HI></P>
<P>Of and for all which <HI>England</HI> having in those times confessed it
self unable to make Payment and Reparation, these Rights obtain∣ed
the place of a Debt.</P>
<P>And this is most evident, and in express words from the Agree∣ments
and Conventions of <HI>Henry</HI> the Third, the Treaty of
<HI>Utrecht</HI> with <HI>Edward</HI> the Fourth, and many other Publick
Writings, the Originals whereof are kept amongst the
Records of the <HI>Hanses</HI> in their Chamber of <HI>Lubeck.</HI></P>
<P>Hence it followeth,</P>
<P>1 That it is not true, That (as the <HI>Informers</HI> ever and anon assert)
any of these Rights come to the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> to the prejudice
and against the benefit of the people of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>2 But on the contrary it is most true, That these Rights and Agree∣ments
are Obligatory on both sides.</P>
<P>3 And that indeed for ever; for as much as the Causes thereof are
mutual, and oblige reciprocally.</P>
<P>4 And therefore cannot be revoked at the pleasure, or for the ad∣vantage
of the one party, the other not consenting, without
breach of that Law which is between Nation and Nation; no
more then Goods once sold and delivered, can be recovered or
claimed back by the Seller.</P>
<P>5 And although even the said Cities should consent to such Revo∣cation,
yet unless first Restitution and Reparation were made
unto them of and for those Expences and Services, by which
Ancient Merits they obtained these Rights, and of the Damages
by them sustained, it were not just to deprive them thereof.
And then they ought to be refunded,</P>
<P>1 Of those Auxiliary and Warlike Charges expended for the
benefit of <HI>England,</HI> together with the Interest of Four
hundred years.</P>
<P>2 Satisfaction ought to be given for the Services they did in
those times of War.</P>
<P>3 The Damages ought to be repaired which were sustained by
the <HI>Hanses</HI> so long since, with Interest for so long time past.</P>
<P>Which Damages alone, even as they then were con∣fessed
and calculated by the Parliament now above
Two hundred years past, did exceed the sum of
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
200000 l <HI>Sterling.</HI> From which it may be easily ap∣prehended
to what vast sum of Debt the whole would
amount, if all three, together with the accruing Inter∣est,
were to these times exactly computed.</P>
<P>6 And therefore they having for so many Ages past borne the Ad∣venture
of so high an Obligation, and the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> still not
esteeming the same so much as they do the Amity and Mutual
Correspondence of <HI>England;</HI> they think it equal that they
should be so much the more reciprocally favored, and their Pri∣viledges
cherished, maintained, and by all good means aug∣mented.</P>
<P>7 Much less beseeming would it be for no Default or Crime on
their part, without recompence for so many Services and Ex∣pences,
and that also upon false and frivolous Suggestions
against the Laws of Amity, to cast them out either of their
Possession, or those Liberties, Exemption from Taxes, and other
their Rights by them obtained in perpetuity; as some <HI>Informers</HI>
do endeavor to despoil them.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="fallacy">
<HEAD>The Second Fallacy.</HEAD>
<P>AS often as these Men discourse of the first Rise, Title, and Au∣thority,
by which the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> possess the <HI>Stillyard;</HI> they
speak as if they had obtained the same without the knowledge, and
against the consent of the people; and therefore they mention only
the Kings Grants, but omit those of the Parliaments: And this to
no other end, but to traduce and render the more odious their
whole Right before the people, and those of the generality and all
others, who are unversed in and ignorant of the Verity of their
Case. Whereas indeed,</P>
<P>1 The Kings alone in their Private were not the sole Authors
of these their Rights, but the same were also publickly seen,
considered, approved, solemnly ratified and confirmed by the
Parliaments: Of which Ratifications, the several Originals,
together with the Kings Letters Patents, are to be found
among the Records of the said <HI>Hanses.</HI></P>
<P>2 As moreover in the same are Extant in Authentick Form,
some Solemn Acts of the City of <HI>London,</HI> acknowledging and
accepting the same Rights and Priviledges.</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="4"/>
From hence it followeth,</P>
<P>1 That it is not true which the <HI>Informers</HI> feign, as if our Right did
depend upon the sole authority and grant of the Kings.</P>
<P>2 But it is much less true, That the same were obtained without
consent of the People; being the People is, and always will
be representatively in the Parliaments.</P>
<P>3 That it is most untrue (as sometimes it is suggested) as if the
same had been obtained by any sordid or unlawful means; yea
the Opposers of our Rights (when at any time there have
been such) by abusing the lenitie of the Kings, have indeed
rather prevailed in whatsoever they obtained against us in for∣mer
times, by sinister diversions of their grace and favor▪
And therefore the same having been detected, they have failed
in their attempts, and hitherto our right hath remained entire.</P>
<P>4 Hence it appeareth, That our Right by the accession of the au∣thority
of Parliament is altogether become irrevocable: For
as the People can never die, but that the People is alwaies
judged to be the same, so also Parliaments meeting in the
place of the People, do always represent the same and one Par∣liament.
Wherefore however a lawful Parliament may abro∣gate
the Acts of Kings, yet nevertheless it cannot revoke the
Acts of a Parliament alike equally lawful; Forasmuch as <HI>Par in
parem non habeat imperium;</HI> And it is to be believed they will
not, as neither being consistent with the Commonweal, nor
that one Parliament will easily do that to their predecessors,
which it would not have done to it self by their successors.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="fallacy">
<HEAD>The Third Fallacy.</HEAD>
<P>BUt it is said, That all their Rights were granted under certain
conditions and for some certain end, amongst which princi∣pally
was the Exportation of English Clothes in such abundance,
as the whole Nation should be sensible of the benefit thereof.</P>
<P>But that now no Clothes are any more exported by the <HI>Hanses,</HI>
but that this Trade is reduced to the Merchants-Adventurers, and
that they oftentimes in one year have exported more then double
the number which the <HI>Hanses</HI> formerly exported in two or three
years; And therefore the Condition and End ceasing, those Rights
also ought to cease.</P>
<P><PB N="7" REF="4"/>
But, 1 As to what concerns <HI>England,</HI> the benefit of the Trade of
Clothing was not the sole condition or cause of the <HI>Hances</HI>
Right, but rather alone that the Nation of <HI>England</HI> should
be discharged of a vast Debt wherein it was obliged to the
<HI>Hanses;</HI> And at that time it was to them a great advantage,
that the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> would in satisfaction of this Debt
rather accept some Rights and Priviledges for so great a
Sum of money, which otherwise <HI>England</HI> was obliged to
pay them.</P>
<P>2 So as there was not only regard had to the benefits which
in future times <HI>England</HI> might reap by these Priviledges,
but this principally was intended, that the <HI>Hanses</HI> in the
the coemption and exportation of Clothes should for ever
enjoy a prerogative above other Nations, and that for
their known merits and the damages by them sustained.</P>
<P>3 But moreover to clear this point, to what end or on what
condition this was contracted, if it were so, it ought to
have been expressed in the Convention it self, being other∣wise
there might be many accessory Ends assigned of one
and the same thing; Neither can every Condition have
the force of a Resolutive Agreement, but that alone which
is so especially inserted in the Contract, that the same
ceasing, the Contract may be understood dissolved, or such
as was the sole and only cause of the Contract.</P>
<P>4 And this is worthy to be observed, That it is not to be im∣puted
to the <HI>Hanses,</HI> that they have not hitherto continued
in the Exportation of Clothes. And no man, without it
be by his own default, ought to be punished.</P>
<P>Hence it followeth,</P>
<P>1 Being the <HI>Hanses</HI> have obtained their Right by a very hard and
chargeable Title, the same ought to remain unto them for ever
and irrevocable.</P>
<P>2 Nor can the same be revoked or altered by a Condition however
extrinsick and necessary.</P>
<P>3 As likewise neither one other accessory End ceasing.</P>
<P>4 Much less for any cause of private benefit.</P>
<P>5 Being it is neither lawful naturally, to recede from such a Con∣tract
on one party in respect of his own advantage against the
consent of the other party, who especially is so much damnified.</P>
<P><PB N="8" REF="5"/>
6 And therefore these <HI>Informers</HI> go to work frivolously, whilst
by such fallacies they seek to mislead the improvident and
heedless.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="fallacy">
<HEAD>The Fourth Fallacy—</HEAD>
<P>IS almost of the same stuff as the former. They would have it be
believed, that all the Right of the <HI>Hanses,</HI> and so their Right to
the House of the <HI>Stillyard</HI> are become void, because forsooth the
Corporation it self, (that is) the Body and Subject upon which
that Right was conferred, is no more a Corporation: And so the
Commerce of the said House ceasing, being intended for the Ad∣vantage
of <HI>England,</HI> the Right it self should withal cease.</P>
<P>But,
1 It is before shewn, that the <HI>Hanses</HI> did not obtain the possession
of the <HI>Stillyard,</HI> for this cause of Advantage to <HI>England</HI> only.</P>
<P>2 Neither that as it may be advantagious or profitable to one
Party, a Contract can be presently rescinded or dissolved.</P>
<P>3 The objection it self, if it relate to the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> themselves,
is manifestly false: For who can be ignorant, that the Confede∣ration
of the <HI>Hanses</HI> between these principal Cities, viz. <HI>Lubeck,
Breme, Hamburgh, Brunswick, Colen, Munster, &amp;c.</HI> doth not
continue to this day? nor ever to have been extinguished?
although of seventy two Cities (of which antiently they con∣sisted)
many, because of their decaied and weak estate, have
withdrawn themselves, and others through their own default
have been excluded the Society? There is nothing more cer∣tain
then that hitherto they observe their Conventions, and
jointly send forth their Ambassadors; and that in the publick
Constitutions of <HI>Germany,</HI> as well antient as modern, they
have an honorable place; and in <HI>France, Spain, Sweden, Den∣mark,
Mosco, Poland,</HI> and the <HI>Netherlands,</HI> they both are ac∣knowledged
under their common Denomination, and also
enjoy their Rights as a Body Confederate. But if this reflect
on the Merchants residing in the House of the <HI>Stillyard,</HI> How
can it be that their paucitie, and any act of theirs, can be any
argument that the House it self should be taken from the
<HI>Hanse-Cities?</HI></P>
<P>Being,
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>
1 That those Merchants are not the Proprietors of the said
House, but the said Cities.</P>
<P>2 Nor if they were, have we hitherto ever heard it proved,
that as yet they have committed or done any thing wor∣thy
to deprive them of this Right in Law.</P>
<P>3 And although they had committed any thing against the
Law, yet, <HI>Paena suos tenere debet Autores.</HI></P>
<P>4 And for their small Number, this also hath not come to
pass through their own fault; For the truth is, that they
have by little and little been so discouraged by the <HI>Eng∣lish,</HI>
that the rest have given place.</P>
<P>5 The <HI>Informers</HI> themselves use this for one principal Argu∣ment;
<HI>Strangers are to be restrained of the English Comerce.</HI>
But these are contraries, both to require and plainly to
intend the exterminating of Foreign Merchants, and
yet at the same time to punish ours by taking away their
Rights for this cause, that being reduced to such a pau∣citie,
they do not exercise Trade here in greater number.
This certainly is against all reason of Natural Justice,
that he who for the benefit of another hath relinquished
part of his Right, should be deprived of all the rest for
this onely cause, That he hath relinquished a part.</P>
<P>6 And lastly it is a Rule in Natural Reason, That a Col∣ledge
or Corporation which had its beginning in many,
may yet be conserved in three or two persons.</P>
<P>Hence it followeth,</P>
<P>1 That it is plainly false and contrary to the most evident truth of
the matter which is suggested, either of the taking away or
of the ceasing of this Corporation.</P>
<P>2 That it is not the question, What profit at this day the House
of the <HI>Stillyard</HI> contributeth either publickly or privately to
<HI>England,</HI> (for before the invalidity of this Argument is de∣monstrated)
but whether the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> for their own bene∣fit
will, and yet may enjoy the same to their own commodity.</P>
<P>3 That even three or two, yea one Merchant in the name of the
<HI>Hanse-Society,</HI> doth conserve the right of the <HI>Hanses.</HI></P>
<P>4 That the Delinquencies of any single person (if any such can be
proved) do not prejudice the <HI>Hanses,</HI> but reacheth alone
the Authors.</P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="6"/>
5 That the Actions of single persons are to be distinguished from
the Cause of an whole Society.</P>
<P>6 And therefore these <HI>Informers</HI> both deceive themselves, and also
would impose on the Parliament and people of <HI>England,</HI> so
often as they make use of this argument to impeach the Rights
of the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> in the House of the <HI>Stillyard.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="fallacy">
<HEAD>The Fifth Fallacy—</HEAD>
<P>IS the common benefit to this Commonwealth of <HI>England</HI> and
the people, whilst they say the Revenue would be augmented
yearly Two thousand pounds sterling, if the House of the <HI>Stillyard</HI>
were seised: By which specious insinuation they not only deceive
the incautelous, but seek to set the mouth of the people on water
and to excite them against the <HI>Hanses.</HI></P>
<P>But,
1 It is before made appear, that between those who are equal in
right, no Right can be taken away from the one party for any
consideration of the commodity or profit of the other party.</P>
<P>2 And what Reason did ever justifie this for a Law, That it should
be lawful for me to take away that from another, which he
possesseth by a Right obtained in perpetuity?</P>
<P>3 Also what profit can accrue by that which not only is repugnant
to the Rules of Honesty, but also would be prejudicial to the
glory and renown of the English Nation?</P>
<P>4 But yet this also by which they plainly insinuate the Publick
Revenue to be impaired through the House of the <HI>Stillyard,</HI>
and from which they make up the accompt of Two thousand
pounds sterl. <HI>per annum,</HI> hath never hitherto been proved, and
is of it self evidently false.</P>
<P>5 It is to be believed, that whatever profit from hence may be
gained, is rather aimed at by some private Persons, to their
own Lucre, then for any intent to advance the Publick good.</P>
<P>6 If any publick benefit ought to be in this case aimed at, the
most Renowned Parliament in their great wsdome, will rather
judge and discern this point, Whether it were better for so
small and indeed unjust and inconsiderable a gain (for such a
sum would no more add to the increase of the Treasury of <HI>Eng∣land,</HI>
then the smallest drop of water would to the British
<PB N="11" REF="6"/>
Ocean) by meer Power to take away the Rights of the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI>
with the hazard of the antient Amity and neighbouring
<HI>German</HI> Comerce, (for all the Maratine Comerce of <HI>Germany</HI>
is for the most part in those Cities) or rather not to preserve
intire the Amity, and the Rights and intercourse of Trade of
above 400 years, not to say, to augment the same, which yet
might be done to the great and mutual benefit of both parties.</P>
<P>Hence it followeth,</P>
<P>1 That it is a deceit and a meer empty pretect, whatever is in this
Argument speciously insinuated, concerning publick profit.</P>
<P>2 That on the other side it is more expedient, and for the Interest
of <HI>England,</HI> that the Right of the <HI>Hanses</HI> should be preserved,
yea augmented.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="fallacy">
<HEAD>The Sixth Fallacy—</HEAD>
<P>IS, that some deceased Kings have before this taken possession of
the House of the <HI>Stillyard,</HI> and that therefore the present possession
of the <HI>Hanse-Cities,</HI> as afterwards obtained by force and intrusion,
is unlawfull and unjust.</P>
<P>But,
1 Here is manifest false dealing, whilst the Publick Acts are neither
<HI>bona fide,</HI> nor fully alleadged, for they set forth the beginning
of the Fact, but the defences and issue of the matter they wholly
omit. They by peeces suggest that which one or other King, up∣on
importune Petitions perhaps, before the Cause was fully exa∣mined,
did resolve to doe; They smother and take no notice of
what followed thereupon, what resolutions after hearing of
the Cause and discovery of the Injustice of those Petitions
finally issued, and how this Cause suppressing all process at the
Common Law, was alwaies remitted to special Conventions,
Conferences and Amicable Treaties.</P>
<P>2 But yet it never came to that point, that in the time of any King
or Queen, the <HI>Hanses</HI> were ever ejected out of their possession.</P>
<P>3 For that the Queen did attempt to possess the House of the
<HI>Stillyard,</HI> it was not long; for still and nevertheless the Cities
did remain in continual and perpetual, as well Natural as Civil
possession, which the Fact it self proveth, and is known to the
whole World.</P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="7"/>
Hence it followeth,</P>
<P>1 It is false'y and absurdly asserted, That the <HI>Stillyard</HI> having been
formerly seised by the Kings, is devolved to the Demeans of
this Commonwealth, and at this day so remains.</P>
<P>2 It is also a fable, that the <HI>Hanses</HI> Repossession is by force and In∣trusion.</P>
<P>3 For how probable is it, that a few Merchants of the <HI>Stillyard</HI>
could repossess themselves by force and intrusion of any Estate
in the face of Kings against their will, and particularly in op∣position
to Queen <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> or against the Parliaments, the
City of <HI>London</HI> looking on and being Spectators? What
force, what Intrusion could defend them against these Kings,
Queen and Parliaments?</P>
<P>4 The <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> therefore have remained alwaies, and are at this
day in lawful, perpetual and continued possession of this House:
Lawful, because obtained from the beginning upon more then
valuable consideration, and a most chargeable Title; per∣petual,
because continued; continued, because never interrupted.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="fallacy">
<HEAD>The Seventh Fallacy.</HEAD>
<P>THat this Cause is the Cause of the Revenue and Demean of the
Commonwealth of <HI>England;</HI> that therefore of such Causes the
Barons of the <HI>Exchequer</HI> are competent Judges.</P>
<P>But,
1 Every cause whereby every Possession and Right is pretended
to be in the Demean of the Commonwealth, doth not apper∣tain
to those Judges, but only in Cases where the Action lies
against either the Subjects of <HI>England,</HI> or any private Stranger
usurping against the Right of the Commonwealth: For these,
because they are subject to the Courts and Ordinary Judica∣tures
of this Commonwealth, are rightly there convented;
but this is not the Case of the <HI>Hanse-Society,</HI> which being as
to Comerce absolutely free and at its own arbitrement, what∣soever
is contracted is transacted as with a free Foreign people;
so that the Confederacies, Pactions and Conventions made
with them, and all Rights thereby obtained, cannot be brought
before the ordinary Judicatories of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="7"/>
2 Otherwise it would follow from this Principle, That the Alli∣ances
and Contracts of all Kings and Republicks with this
Commonwealth might be questioned in the same, and that all
Foreign Nations hitherto have been bound to submit them∣selves
unto these Judicatories; which can with no more Equity
be done against Foreign Nations, then the People of <HI>England</HI>
would think it just that the same were done to them abroad.</P>
<P>3 But moreover, these which are called the <HI>Hanse-</HI> Priviledges, are
meer Contracts between this Commonwealth and those Cities;
and therefore if any difference do arise about the same, the
Controversie ought to be determined, not by the Private Judi∣catory
of any one Party, but by Commissioners of both Na∣tions.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="fallacy">
<HEAD>The Eighth Fallacy.</HEAD>
<P>LAstly, They conceive that the House of the <HI>Stillyard</HI> may be
with good reason taken away, because the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> have
planted other Residences of their Comerce, in <HI>Norway, Moscovia,
&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>But it is grounded upon no Reason; For when their Ancestors
obtained these Priviledges of <HI>England,</HI> they were not limited for
their Comerce to <HI>England</HI> alone, nor by any other condition were
prohibited to Traffick any where else; yea, never any King or
Parliament ever required, that they should not Traffick in any other
place but <HI>England:</HI> And to say no more, These objections can no
better be confuted, then by the notorietie of the fact, by which it
is evident, That for above Three hundred years past, the <HI>Hanses</HI>
have constantly exercised their Comerce in the said Countreys,
and yet nevertheless, in the mean time enjoyed their Trade in
<HI>England,</HI> with all Rights depending thereupon.</P>
<P>From all which, it is concluded,</P>
<P>1 That the pretences of the <HI>Informers</HI> are unjust against the <HI>Still∣yard,</HI>
by which they seek to invade without just cause, a Right
due to another, against that most general Law of all others,
<HI>Quae tibi non vis fieri, alteri ne feceris;</HI> contrary to Christian Cha∣rity,
and repugnant even to the Laws of <HI>England,</HI> which never
deviate from the Laws of God and Nature.</P>
<P><PB N="14" REF="8"/>
2 And therefore their Arguments ought not to be heard, but re∣jected.</P>
<P>3 Yea to be esteemed as prejudicial and derogatory to the Honor
of the English Nation; whilest they are so bold under the false
Representation of a small lucre of Two thousand pounds <HI>per an.</HI>
to violate an Amity of Four Ages, the entercourse of the
Commerce of all <HI>Germany</HI> almost, and especially the Faith and
Constancy of so many Treaties and Agreements: Not at all
observing (to omit many other) how much benefit the people
of <HI>England</HI> have thence reaped within few years past, in their
great necessitie, by the supply alone of all manner of Corn; and
how much <HI>Hamburgh</HI> to this day, and <HI>Lubeck</HI> now lately have
accommodated this Nation, by permitting them liberty to pass
their Commodities and Merchandises by their Ports.</P>
<P>4 And on the other side, That the <HI>Hanse-Cities</HI> ought without any
violation be left peaceably in their Possession and Right.</P>
<P>5 And that no Man ought to be permitted to make any attempts
in prejudice thereof.</P>
<P>6 Which if the Affair be rightly esteemed, will be both glorious
to the <HI>English</HI> Nation, and also as to the Publick of very great
advantage and benefit.</P>
<P>And therefore I do in the name of the said Cities, and the
whole Society of the Confederate <HI>Hanses</HI> pray,</P>
<P>1 THat such Informations, and the like attempts against the
manifest and known Rights of the <HI>Stillyard,</HI> may be al∣together
rejected and suppressed.</P>
<P>2 That if any Question do arise touching the said House, or the
Rights thereof, the same may according to the Custom of
Nations, and as hitherto hath been observed between <HI>Eng∣land</HI>
and the said <HI>Hanse-Cities,</HI> be reserved and referred to
amicable Treaty between this Commonwealth and the said
Cities.</P>
<P>3 That all things in the interim may remain intire and inviolate,
and in particular, That the Exemption from Taxes, both
Real and Personal, which the Inhabitants of the <HI>Stillyard</HI>
have hitherto enjoyed, may be preserved unto them without
any breach, according to the Antient Priviledges.</P>
<P><PB N="15" REF="8"/>
4 And lastly, That the Freedom of Trade throughout the
Dominions of <HI>England,</HI> as hitherto, so also for the future,
without any Restriction, may peaceably be permitted to the
said <HI>Hanse-</HI> Merchants, as well for the preservation as aug∣mentation
of mutual Commerce between the People of
<HI>England</HI> and <HI>Germany.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>LONDON,
<DATE>3 August,
1659.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Martin Boekell
Counsellor to the Commonwealth
of <HI>Lubeck,</HI> and Special Envoy of
the Society of the <HI>Hanse-Cities.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

