<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached in St. Maries Church in Dover, June the first, 1694 before the right honourable Henry Earl of Romney, being the day in which he entered upon the office of constable of Dover-Castle and Lord Warden of Cinque-ports / by James Brome ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Brome, James, d. 1719.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A29630</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing B4860</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R34383</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">14395377</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 14395377</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">102277</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A29630)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102277)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1565:18)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached in St. Maries Church in Dover, June the first, 1694 before the right honourable Henry Earl of Romney, being the day in which he entered upon the office of constable of Dover-Castle and Lord Warden of Cinque-ports / by James Brome ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Brome, James, d. 1719.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 23 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Eben Tracy ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>MDCXCIV [1694]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A29630">
<STC T="W">B4860</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">14395377</BIBNO>
<VID>102277</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A
SERMON
Preached in
St. <HI>MARIES</HI> Church
IN
DOVER,
<HI>June the First,</HI> 1694. BEFORE
The Right Honourable
<HI>HENRY</HI> Earl of <HI>Romney,</HI>
BEING
The Day in which he Enter'd upon the Office
of Constable of <HI>DOVER-CASTLE,</HI> and
Lord Warden of the <HI>CINQUE-PORTS.</HI></P>
<P>By <HI>JAMES BROME,</HI> A. M. Rector of
<HI>Cheriton</HI> in <HI>Kent,</HI> and Chaplain to His
Lordship in the <HI>Cinque-Ports.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed for <HI>Eben Tracy</HI> at the <HI>Three Bibles</HI> on <HI>London-Bridge,</HI>
MDCXCIV.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="half title">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<P>Mr. <HI>BROME</HI>'s
SERMON
Preached before
The Right Honourable
<HI>HENRY</HI> Earl of <HI>Romney,</HI>
IN
St. <HI>Maries</HI> Church in <HI>DOVER,
June</HI> 1<HI>st.</HI> 1694.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="imprimatur">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD><DATE>June 1. 1694.</DATE></HEAD>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Dover ss.</NOTE>ORdered by the Mayors, Bayliffs, and
Jurates of the <HI>Cinque-Ports,</HI> Two An∣tient
Towns, and their Members, that the
Thanks of this Assembly be given unto Mr.
<HI>James Brome</HI> Chaplain to The Right Ho∣nourable
Our <HI>Lord Warden</HI> for his Sermon
this day Preached before his Lordship and
this Assembly, and the said Mr. <HI>Brome</HI> is
desired to Print his Sermon.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Sandwich, <HI>Speaker.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
<CLOSER>Imprimatur, <SIGNED>Ra. Barker.</SIGNED> <DATELINE><DATE>July 9th.
1694.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
<PB REF="3"/>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="4"/>
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A
SERMON
Preached before the
Earl of Romney.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Proverbs xxix. v. 2.</BIBL>
<Q>When the righteous are in authority the peo∣ple
rejoyce, but when the wicked beareth
rule, the people mourne.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>IN all Nations Two things are Causes of
a Common Prosperity, good Government,
and Good Obedience; a good Magistrate
over a Perverse People is a Sound Head, as
hath been well observed, on a surfeited Body,
a good Commonwealth and a bad Ruler is a
healthful Body with a Head Aching; A good
Governour is a skilful Ship-Master, that takes
the safest and the shortest Course, and conti∣nually
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
so steers as the Rocks and Shelves, which
might Ship-wrack the State, be avoided, and
the Voyage ever made with the greatest speed,
best profit, and most ease; but a wicked Ma∣gistrate
is a Wolf made Leader of a Fold, that
both satiates his Cruelty, and betrays his Flock
to danger.</P>
<P>Upon which account no doubt it was, that
we find <HI>Solomon</HI> so frequently advising all in
Authority to the constant practice of Vertue
and Goodness, as knowing full well that no∣thing
would prove more Instrumental to pro∣mote
any Nations happyness, then Men of
such Sober and Excellent Principles: For 'tis
too visible in the World, that when the
Wicked get up into Power, and such as take
no care to oppose the growth of wickedness,
and to keep every Man within the bounds of
his Duty, are in Places of Trust and Authori∣ty,
as they open a Sluce to all manner of Im∣piety,
so such as are Vertuous must of necessi∣ty
groan under the intolerable weight of their
grievous Oppressions; but when Just and
Merciful Governours make Vertuous Men by
their Example become more numerous, then
doth a Kingdom begin to Thrive and grow
Happy; then appears a Publick Joy and Satis∣faction
throughout all the Community, then do
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
all Fears cease, all Jealousies are laid aside, all
dreadful apprehensions of the Peoples Insecu∣rity
do perfectly vanish, the Face of Publick
Affairs appears Fair and Serene, and nothing
move's eccentrically, but in a Just and Regular
Order, which seems to be the full Sense and
Meaning of the Wise-man's Aphorisme, <HI>When
the Righteous are in Authority the People rejoyce, but
when the Wicked beareth Rule, the People mourn.</HI></P>
<P>From which words,</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="I"/> I shall consider first, That there is always
great Joy when Righteous and Good Men bear
Publick Rule and Authority.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="II"/><HI>Secondly,</HI> I shall endeavour to shew you, that
there is very great reason for such Publick Joy
and Exultation, because as God is on their side,
so the whole Kingdom feels the Blessed Effects
of it:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 28. 12.</NOTE> For as <HI>Dionysius Carthusianus</HI> observes well
upon <HI>Prov.</HI> 28. 12. <HI>Ex hoc bonum Commune, &amp;c.</HI>
From hence the Common Good and Safety of
the People, and the Glory of God are procu∣red,
preserved, and promoted: And St. <HI>Austin,</HI>
whom he there quotes, agrees with him in his
Notion concerning this matter, <HI>Illi qui vera pie∣tate
praediti, &amp;c.</HI> They who being endued,
saith he, with true Principles of Piety, live
Good and Vertuous Lives, if withal they have
but attained to any Skill and Knowledge of
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
governing the People, must needs render that
Community extreamly happy, where God is so
propitious to confer upon them Authority:
<HI>But when the Wicked beareth Rule, the People mourn,
gemet populus,</HI> saith the same <HI>Dionysius</HI> upon the
place, <HI>timens exactionari, gravari, &amp; opprimi, &amp;c.</HI>
dreadfully fearing the great Exactions, Grie∣vances,
and Oppressions, that will most cer∣tainly
ensue.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="III"/> And lastly, I shall apply all to our selves by
some necessary and seasonable Inferences.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="I"/><HI>First,</HI> I shall consider that there is ever great
Joy, when Good Men are in Rule and Autho∣rity;
for if as St. <HI>Bernard</HI> observes, <HI>Rebus rari∣tas
pretium facit,</HI> the rarity of any thing adds a
Price and Value to it; then if Vertue in a Go∣vernour
appear more Orient than ordinary,
the uncommonness of the thing usually creates
a greater Respect and Veneration for the
Person.</P>
<P>For Vertue hath an Innate Beauty and Com∣liness
which is very taking, whereever it is
visible, and if in a private Sphere, its Charms
are very great; Virtue and Goodness, when
in Men of Birth and Power, like a Curious
Picture inchased with Gold and Diamonds is
set off with a far greater Lustre.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="6"/>
Men have naturally a great Opinion, Value,
and Veneration for true Goodness, and what∣ever
others may think of it, Vice can never so
far change its own Nature, or so fairly coun∣terfeit
Vertue as by the most Alluring Charms
or Features to gain the same esteem.</P>
<P>And although Virtue and Vice are reputed
by some Persons only to be Arbitrary things,
founded either in Mens Imaginations, or in
the Customs and Constitutions of the World,
and not in the Nature of the things themselves,
and so there is no Good and Evil, but what the
Supreme Authority of a Nation declares to be
so, yet it will most certainly appear, that there
is a vast difference betwixt Good and Evil, a
Natural Comeliness in Virtue, and a Natural
Deformity in Vice by the Universal Agree∣ment
of Mankind about it, and by the ge∣neral
Verdict of Humane Nature concerning
it.</P>
<P>And to make this a little more Intelligible by
some particular instances to this purpose; Will
Violence and Injustice, will Perjury and Perfi∣diousness,
will Unrighteousness and Ingrati∣tude,
and such like horrid Crimes pass off
with as great Esteem, Honour and Reputation,
as the contrary Virtues are wont to do? Sup∣pose
then the Reverse of all that which we now
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
call Virtue were solemnly Enacted, and the
Practice of Fraud and Rapine, Perjury, and
Falseness to a Mans Word, and all manner of
Vice and Wickedness were Established by a
Law; I ask now in the words of a very great
and Learned Divine, <HI>If the case betwixt Vertue and
Vice was thus alter'd, would that which we now call
Vice in process of time gain the reputation of Vertue,
and that which we call Vertue grow odious and contemp∣tible
to Humane Nature?</HI> Is it possible a Man,
that by all unjust and indirect means imagina∣ble
takes away from his Neighbour, that which
is really his own, and daily builds his Fortunes
upon the Ruines of other Men, shall either
have the same credit while he lives, which he
hath, that deals fairly and honestly with all
the World, or when he dies, shall leave the
same Monument of lasting Honour and Repu∣tation
behind him, which Truth and Fidelity
perpetuate to Mankind?</P>
<P>Nay is it not common with some even of
those, who are of the vitious part of the World,
to revile and speak against, and pretend to de∣test
and abhor those who have been more noto∣rious
than themselves for their Crimes and
Villanies?</P>
<P>Not but that wicked Persons may be some∣times
honoured by such as do not know them
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
to be wicked, and on the other side those that
are good may by others be esteemed and used as
the Rubbish and Off-scowring of all things, but
this is to be ascribed to their mistake and igno∣rance
of them; but the generality of Mankind
have heretofore, and still do pay the greatest
Reverence and Respect to any Persons, whom
they believe to be Innocent and Vertuous,
whereas Shame, Scorn, and Disgrace is com∣monly
the Lot and Portion of wicked Men,
which is plain from that of <HI>Solomon, Prov.</HI> 13.
5. <HI>A wicked man is loathsome and cometh to shame;</HI>
which word <HI>loathsome</HI> denotes all such kind
of Persons to be as nauseous and offensive to
the judgment of others, as the most loathsome
and unsavoury things are to their Taste and
Smell.</P>
<P>On the contrary the Wise Man speaking of
Religion saith, <HI>It shall be an ornament of grace to thy
head, and as a chain about thy neck; exalt her and she
shall promote thee, she shall bring thee to honour, when
thou dost embrace her</HI><NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Prov. 4. 8.</NOTE>: By which we may see
that nothing will sooner raise Mens Esteem,
and make them Great in the World than a
Righteous Conversation, for this will render
them illustrious both in the sight of God and
Man; <HI>For</HI><NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Ps. 84. 11.</NOTE> <HI>the Lord will give grace and glory, and
no good thing will he withhold from them that walk up∣rightly;</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
and to this purpose may the words
of the <HI>Psalmist</HI> not improperly be understood,
<HI>Psal.</HI> 97. 11. <HI>Light is sown for the righteous, and
gladness for the upright in heart:</HI> Besides the inward
satisfaction, which all good Men doe natural∣ly
reap by Vertuous Actions, the Publick Ac∣clamations
that do daily likewise Accompany
them from those that have received the Com∣mon
Benefit of them, are a Publick Testimony
how grateful and endearing they are in gene∣ral
to Mankind.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="II"/> But I proceed to the second thing, to shew,
<HI>That there is great reason to rejoyce when righteous men
are in authority,</HI> because as God is on their side,
so the whole Kingdom feels the Blessed Effects
of it.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="I"/><HI>First,</HI> God is on their side, and takes the part
of such as are Righteous Governours, and
therefore the People have great reason to re∣joyce
under such a Government: Nothing doth
more endear Men to God, and render them
Gratious and Acceptable in his sight than an
Holy and Vertuous Conversation: Now it is
Natural to take care of, and preserve such
things as are of the highest Value and Estima∣tion,
and by consequence good Rulers being
God's more special Favourites, hence hath
he a more peculiar regard for them, esteeming
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
them as the very apple of his Eye, and profes∣sing
it as possible for the Sons of Violence to
come near and touch that, as to do them any
Injury by their malitious Machinations.</P>
<P>Nay still further, as God claims a peculiar
propriety in them, so he sets the highest Marks
and Signatures of his Favour and Affection
upon them; <HI>For they shall be mine, saith the Lord
of Hosts, in that day when I make up my jewels, and
I will spare them as a man spareth his own Son that
serveth him.</HI><NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Mal. 3. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE></P>
<P>When the Wicked shall arise up in Tumults
against them, when they encompass them like
Bees, flaming with Rage and Fury, as if they
would presently consume them, then saith
God, Mine Hand shall hold them fast, and
mine Arm shall strengthen them, the Enemy
shall not be able to do them violence, the Son
of wickedness shall not hurt them, I shall smite
down their Foes before their Face, and plague
them that hate them; nay, he will certainly de∣fend
them under his wings, his Faithfulness
and Truth shall be their Shield and Buckler.</P>
<P>And what should be the reason of all this
kind Care and Regard, of this favourable Pa∣tronage
and Protection, which God affords
them, but because those Persons indeavour to
imitate God in those his excellent perfections
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
of Justice and Truth? God as he is the Sove∣reign
of the Universe, and the Great Gover∣nour
of the World performs his promises and
impartially distributes his Justice to Mankind,
and those who are his Vice-Gerents and Dele∣gates
here on Earth cannot more ingratiate
themselves in his favour, then when Judgment
runs down like Water, and Righteousness like
a Mighty Stream; <HI>For to do Justice and Judgment
is more acceptable to the Lord than any Sacrifice.</HI><NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Prov. 21. 3.</NOTE></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="II"/><HI>Secondly,</HI> As God doth constantly Patronize
all such Righteous Officers, so the whole King∣dom
feels the Blessed Effects of it, and this is
a further reason for the Peoples Joy and Exul∣tation:
Now we cannot better know the well∣come
Fruits of a Righteous Government, then
by the Joyful Experience of it, for from hence
it is, that true Religion is incouraged, and
kept up, maugre all opposition in its true Lu∣stre
and Glory, whilest all Prophaneness and
Impiety is utterly discountenanc'd and sup∣press'd
as the very Bane and Pest of all Hu∣mane
Society; whereas under Evil Gover∣nours
Vice grows Daring and Couragious, it
throws off all the Vizors and Masks of blushing
Modesty, and becomes Brazen-fac'd, Ventu∣rous
and highly Impudent, and by being open∣ly
countenanc'd by such as are in Authority,
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
it gains too great Reputation and Authority to
it self.</P>
<P>Again. When good Men sit at the Helm of
Government, Oaths are not reputed Withs,
nor Laws as Cob-webbs, which every vile Ma∣lefactor
may be allowed to break through, the
Princes Rights are inviolably secured, and the
Peoples Properties as safely hedged about;
Oppression and Violence dare not in the least
peep abroad, nor Perjury and Detraction ap∣pear
bare-fac'd at Noon-day as Advocates for
Truth; Fraud and Treachery sculk about in
the dark, and can hardly escape undiscovered
from their watchful Eye. Their Diligence and
Integrity is very signal and remarkable, and
all the Wheels of Government being kept up
and preserved in a very regular motion, the
good and wellfare of the whole Community is
most entirely promoted by their prudent Con∣duct
and Management of Affairs, by seasona∣ble
Debates, and sober Counsels, by serious
Advice and proper Resolutions, and God doth
many times by his secret Providence so concur
with their Endeavours, so strengthen their
Counsels, so prosper their Debates, and Crown
with Success all their Projects and Designs,
that they enjoy such measures of Temporal
Felicity, as neither the Plots of Foreign Ene∣mies,
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
nor the Machinations of Domestick In∣cendiaries
can ever be able to undermine.</P>
<P>Nay God is many times pleased to enrich a
Nation with Peace and Plenty, with Ease and
Liberty, and with all the outward Blessings
both of the upper and neather Springs for the
sake of good Men, they in their respective Sta∣tions
being very instrumental likewise towards
the procuring such things; whereas wicked
Men carry a Curse with them, wherever they
come, and like the dreadful <HI>Basilisk,</HI> dart out
nothing but Ruine and Destruction before
them; so that no People are safe where such
Persons are in Authority, because all their Po∣licies
and Projects prove commonly Fruitless
and Abortive.</P>
<P>And if under all Governments Wickedness
hath been the main Obstruction to all the brave
Designs and most Glorious Exploits, that have
been set on foot, then Vertue and Holyness is
the most prevailing Interest in the World, be∣cause
God is ever sure to be on that side; I
confess indeed Policy and Courage are the two
great Pillars of any Government, but unless
Vertue be the Basis to support those very Pil∣lars,
they will prove like the Earthen Legs of
<HI>Nebuchadnezzar</HI>'s Image, which will at last grow
feeble and impotent, and fall away to nothing:
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
It is therefore both a wise and a true observa∣tion
of <HI>Solomon,</HI> which hath been sufficiently
experienc'd in all Ages, <HI>Righteousness exalteth a
Nation, but sin is a reproach to any people. Prov.</HI> 14.
34. That is, Religion and Vertue are the great
causes of all Publick Happyness, for they raise
a Nation to the highest degree of Temporal
Felicity and Glory, and make both Officers and
People to flourish in the greatest Reputation
and Renown.</P>
<P>This it were easie to enlarge upon from the
Records of Time and Annals of History: The
<HI>Jewish</HI> Commonwealth is a very signal instance
of this Nature, for whil'st both Rulers and
People made it the chief of their business to do
Justice and love Mercy, and walk humbly with
their God; How did the <HI>Jewish</HI> Church tri∣umph,
and the State prosper, and nothing in∣terven'd
to Eclipse their Glory?</P>
<P>And thus again, whil'st <HI>Greece</HI> flourished,
<HI>Reges Philosophabantur, &amp; Philosphi regebant,</HI> those
Common-wealths being more numerous than
their Neighbours in nothing but in the sincere
Exercise of their Reason: And we find though
<HI>Lycurgus</HI> in <HI>Lacedemon, Aristides</HI> in <HI>Athens,</HI> and
<HI>Epaminondas</HI> at <HI>Thebes</HI> were not born to Com∣mand,
their Vertue bestowed on them what
their Birth deny'd: And when Tyranny and
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
Pride had by wasting these Common-wealths
made place for the <HI>Roman</HI> Glory, nothing did
so enlarge the Conquest of that Renowned
State (whose Center, as one speaks, was Ver∣tue,
and Circumference Fame) as their Hero∣ick
Actions: Upon which account <HI>Attalus</HI> King
of <HI>Pergamus</HI> did by Legacy leave them his
Kingdom, as to those whose Vertues deserv'd
it as a Reward, which occasion'd St. <HI>Austin</HI> to
fall into that Eloquent Expression, <HI>Because God</HI>
(saith he) <HI>would not bestow Heaven on the</HI> Romans,
<HI>they being Pagans, he bestowed the Empire of the
World upon them, because they were Vertuous.</HI></P>
<P>And though <HI>Nobis non licet esse tam beatis,</HI> tho'
we cannot at present be as great as other Na∣tions,
and such Conquests and Enlargements
of our Dominions are not in this Age as yet
the Fate and Portion allotted to us; and more
the pity, that under so Great and Puissant a
Prince, who by his Matchless Courage and
Conduct would make us as Renown'd and For∣midable
as ever, our own Vices should clip
the Wings of His Triumphant Victories; Yet
would we once be perswaded to become Con∣querours
over our selves, and over all our Ir∣regular
Passions and Appetites, we might then
at least have this assurance, that we shall ne∣ver
be Conquered, and triumph'd over by
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
those, who now apparently watch for our Ru∣ine
and Destruction.</P>
<P>And if we are not so happy now as we de∣sire
to be, 'tis because we are not so Vertuous
and Honest as is necessary for such happyness,
for till our Vices lessen, our Success will never
be great, nor can we hope to retrieve the Re∣nown
and Honour of our Illustrious Ancestors,
till we resolve to fetch back amongst us their
Ancient Manners and Heroick Gallantry: And
indeed if we could but recover the good <HI>English</HI>
plainness of Heart and Habit and Integrity of
Spirit, for which our Progenitors were so wor∣thily
Renown'd, we should then quickly find
the Tide turn upon us with an over-flowing
Torrent of Glory and Prosperity.</P>
<P>But whil'st there is so much Artifice and
Guile, so much Treachery and Selfishness a∣mongst
us, while like prophane <HI>Esau</HI> we can be
willing to sell all our <HI>English</HI> Birth-rights and
Properties only for a Mess of * Pottage;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 25. 33, 34.</NOTE> and
under the Mask of True <HI>English</HI> Patriots do our
Enemies Work to their hands, what can we
expect indeed at this rate, but to become a mi∣serable
and forlorn People, a Scorn to others,
and a Reproach to our selves? Nay what can
we expect, but to be made, as a just punishment
for such impardonable perfidiousness, Tributa∣ry
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
Vassals at last without another Miracle of
Providence to the most Domineering Monarch
in the Universe?</P>
<P>Since then Prosperity and good Success doth
usually attend Righteousness, and such Honest
Governours as are the Patrons of it, since Pro∣vidence
resists Vice, and Vices do not only
make Enemies to themselves, but by a Civil
War as a Just Judgment upon them destroy one
another, happy must that People needs be,
where God is pleased to bestow upon them so
Unvaluable a Blessing, and there cannot be
occasion of greater Joy, than when such Men
are advanc'd into Power and Authority by rea∣son
of that mighty influence, which both their
Actions and Examples have commonly upon
all Inferiour Persons who are under their Go∣vernment.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="III"/> What remains then but in the third place to
apply all to our selves by some seasonable Infe∣rences,
and so to draw to a Conclusion.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="I"/> And first, If Righteous Men in Authority
occasion great Joy, then the Choice of such
Governours appears from hence to be a thing
of the greatest moment and consequence: For
when the Lot of Government falls into the Lap
of good Men, Oh, how happy are the conse∣quences
in the investitures of such Persons?
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
and what Advantages do accrue both to the
City and Countrey from the Wisdom of their
Counsels and Excellent Administrations? The
Voice of Oppression then utterly ceaseth, and
there are no Complaints to be heard in the
Streets, when Justice is Administred, it is done
without partiality, and the Poor and Destitute
receive Comfort and Relief, the Widow and
the Fatherless find Patronage and Protection,
and their Souls are redeemed from Deceit and
Violence, the Rights of the Injured are with
great Equity asserted, and all things are settled
upon the most durable Foundations of Truth
and Righteousness.</P>
<P>For the True Statesman is inviolably con∣stant
to his most Excellent Principles of Virtue,
and Religious Prudence, his Ends are Noble,
and the Means he useth Innocent, he hath a
single Eye on the Publick Good, and meets it
in its several Pressures with sutable Reliefs.
Nay if the Ship of the State miscarry, he had
rather perish in the Wreck, then preserve him∣self
upon the Plank of an Inglorious Subterfu∣ge;
his Worth had led him to the Helm, the
Rudder he useth is an Honest and Vigorous
Wisdom, the Star he looks to for Direction is
in Heaven, and the Port he aims at is the
joynt-well-fare both of Prince and People.</P>
<P><PB N="18" REF="13"/>
So that when such places of Trust are thus
carefully disposed of, and such Noble Ensigns
of Honour conferr'd upon Worthy Patriots,
the greatest happyness doth then most certain∣ly
accrue to that Community, which they are
deputed to govern, that their hearts can possi∣bly
wish or desire.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="II"/><HI>Secondly,</HI> If the Power of good Men admini∣ster
great Joy, then Self-Interest as well as the
general good of that Community to which they
belong should make all Men in Authority ve∣ry
Active in all such Religious Performances,
and Righteous Practices: Nothing sure can be
a more powerful Encouragement to goodness,
than to consider what an Universal Satisfaction
it generally creates in the Minds of Men,
for the very Old Men in the Gates will rise
up and pay it a just Deference and Veneration,
and the Children cannot but warble forth its
Praise in the most Melodious Acclamations;
for every one looks upon a Righteous Ruler as
a Tutelar Guardian to the People, and the
greatest Blessing to his Countrey, whereas
they who are Wicked are the greatest Traitors
to their Nation as well as their God, and they
frequently betray both Prince and People into
the most Dismal Calamities by the Crying Sins
of Unrighteousness and Injustice.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="13"/>
So that no Man that is a well-wisher either
to himself or Country, but will resolve upon
such Virtuous and Upright Courses; for is
it not much better to be instrumental towards
a Blessing than a Curse, the first of which is
only attainable by Vertuous Actions? Is it
not a greater satisfaction to be capable to pro∣mote
the Prosperity of a People, than to hasten
their Ruine and procure their Destruction?
Is it not more grateful to the Ear to receive
the joyful applauses of Worthy Atchievements,
than to be harass'd even to Death with the bit∣ter
Taunts and Execrations of a flouting Mul∣titude
for the Vilest Misdemeanours! and to
be in the midst of the Congratulations and
happy Wishes of the People, whose Hearts
and Affections they entirely possess, then to
have only the Command of their Bodies, and
not the least of Charming Empire over their
Souls, which is the more Noble part of Domi∣nion?
If Men then in Authority would but
consult their own Interest, they cannot do bet∣ter
for themselves, they cannot do better for
the People, than by an inviolable Observation
of the Laws of Equity and Justice, which some
Unfortunate Politicians having neglected to
do, have too often made a woful Shipwrack
both of their Honour and Happiness.</P>
<P><PB N="20" REF="14"/>
Which brings me to the third and last thing,
That whenever God affords us such Publick
Blessings by such Righteous Rulers, we ought
to give him all the Praise and the Glory of it:
And this is <HI>Dionysius Carthusianus</HI> his Gloss again,
<HI>In exaltatione justorum multa gloria est, exultant enim
in Deo:</HI> There is great cause of rejoycing in
God, when he sends just Governours amongst
a People, for by that means they glorifie God,
who confers on them that happyness.</P>
<P>And since perhaps to the very Envy of our
Adversaries this is our Case at this time, Let
us not any longer affect to be the most Natu∣ral
Pictures of such horrible Ingratitude
and Ill-Nature, as our <HI>English</HI> Climate is not
usually acquainted with, nor by a down-look't
Male-Contentedness, and Unreasonable Mur∣murs,
by our repining against Providence,
and Carping at the Government provoke God
to deprive us of so great a happiness.</P>
<P>I confess if Ignorance and Blind Devotion,
if Superstition and Idolatry, if Subjection to
His Holiness, and a Tame Condescension to
his Unjust Usurpations be things in themselves
so desirable and to be admired, if it be a thing
<PB N="21" REF="14"/>
so Meritorious to advance the Interest of <HI>Rome,</HI>
and make this Kingdom again part of St.
<HI>Peter</HI>'s Patrimony, and so to introduce <HI>French
Dragoons</HI> and <HI>Popish Janezaries</HI> to be our constant
Guests and Companions; if such a new Re∣volution
will prove so Comfortable a <HI>Jubilee,</HI>
and changing the present Scenes after such a
fashion will become so Advantageous to us,
there is reason enough indeed for our vehement
striving and impatient struggling for it.</P>
<P>But if there is a Train of Blessings clear of
another Nature, which doth manifestly attend
us, if we are now under such an Heroick King,
who is as Tender of our Religious as Civil
Rights, under such Wise Councillors, who will
neither flatter their Prince to His Ruine, nor
dispense with his Laws to the prejudice of his
People, if under such Worthy Governours,
which though Loyal to the Crown will never∣theless
not forget the True Interest of the Sub∣ject;
then where is any room left for Murmurs
or Complaints? Or what reason is there for
any one to Rail or Revile, to bespatter or Re∣pine
against such a Government, whose Yoke
compared with others round about us is easie,
and whose Burden is Light?</P>
<P><PB N="22" REF="15"/>
Nay if these be such Mercies as would cer∣tainly
be esteemed so by all but a few Unthank∣ful
peevish Spirits of our own Nation, who do
not deserve the Benefit of what they so basely
Despise, let us who have learned better things,
think of nothing else but what we shall render
unto the Lord for such benefits as these which
he hath bestowed upon us.</P>
<P>Any Nation but we would never think they
could thank God enough for them, let us then
not be worse than other People, but let us by
our outward Testimonies of Joy declare our
inward satisfaction for the present Govern∣ment,
and let us turn all our Fears and Jealou∣sies
into Prayers and Supplications for the pre∣servation
of it; let us constantly pray for the
Well-fare and Prosperity of such as are in Au∣thority,
that we may lead quiet and peaceable
Lives in all Godliness and Honesty; and let
us have no reserve in our Prayers against any
of them, and hope to come off at last with
some such like trimming Apology as that of
<HI>Naaman,</HI> the Old <HI>Syrian</HI> Courtier, <HI>In this thing
the Lord pardon me</HI><NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">2 Kings 5. 18.</NOTE>, for this is but in plain
terms to equivocate with God Almighty, and
to pray backward, as Conjurers, they say, are
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>
wont to do when they raise up their Familiars,
or as Bells are wont to ring at General Confla∣grations.</P>
<P>To Conclude all, let us zealously endeavour
to promote in earnest what we so fervently
pray for, not by Calumnies and Reproaches,
not by be-spattering Their Majesties, or any
of Their Ministers of State, and blackning and
defaming the Established Government, not by
rendring every thing both in Church and State
odious and abominable in the sight of all the
People by Forgery and Detraction; but by an
unfeigned integrity to God in the first place,
by a ready submission to all our Superiours in
the next, by a generous Condescension to our
Inferiours, and by a meek and quiet and
peaceable Deportment amongst our Equals, let
us make our Kingdom Glorious, and our selves
entirely happy. <HI>Which God of his Infinite Mercy
grant we may be for the sake of Christ Jesus our Sa∣viour,
To whom with the Father,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<PB REF="16"/>
<HEAD>Books Printed for and Sold by Eben Tracy
at the Three Bibles on London-Bridge.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>THE Elements of the Mathematical Art,
commonly called <HI>Algebra,</HI> expounded in
four Books, by <HI>John Kerzey.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Lloyd</HI>'s Dictionary.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sanderson</HI>'s Sermons.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mariners Magazine.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Reynold</HI>'s of Murther.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Royal Practical Chymistry, by <HI>Oswaldus
Crollus,</HI> and <HI>John Hartman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>All Dr. <HI>Salmon</HI>'s Books.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Markham</HI>'s Master-piece.</ITEM>
<ITEM>De Grey's <HI>Horseman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Norwood</HI>'s Doctrine of Triangles.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The famous History of the destruction of
<HI>Troy.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Valentine <HI>and</HI> Orson.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Montelion</HI> Knight of the Oracle.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The Seaman's Glass.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The Boatswain's Art.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The Compleat Modelist.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Waple</HI>'s Shipwright.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Schamozzy</HI>'s Architecture.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Palladio</HI>'s Architecture.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Safeguard for Sailers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pilot's Sea-Mirror.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Newhouse</HI>'s Art of Navigation.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<PB REF="16"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

