<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Physick lies a bleeding, or, The apothecary turned doctor a comedy, acted every day in most apothecaries shops in London : and more especially to be seen by those who are willing to be cheated, the first of April, every year : absolutely necessary for all persons that are sick, or may be sick / by Tho. Brown.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Brown, Thomas, 1663-1704.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A29785</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing B5068</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R36385</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">15685297</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 15685297</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">104358</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A29785)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104358)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1180:10)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Physick lies a bleeding, or, The apothecary turned doctor a comedy, acted every day in most apothecaries shops in London : and more especially to be seen by those who are willing to be cheated, the first of April, every year : absolutely necessary for all persons that are sick, or may be sick / by Tho. Brown.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Brown, Thomas, 1663-1704.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 9-36 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for E. Whitlock ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1697.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A29785">
<STC T="W">B5068</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">15685297</BIBNO>
<VID>104358</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P><HI>Physick lies a Bleeding,</HI>
OR THE
APOTHECARY turned DOCTOR.
A
COMEDY,
Acted every Day in most Apothecaries Shops
in <HI>LONDON.</HI></P>
<P>And more especially to be seen, by <HI>Those who
are willing to be cheated,</HI> the <HI>First of</HI> April,
every Year.</P>
<P>Absolutely necessary for all Persons that are Sick, or
may be Sick.</P>
<Q><L>—Vmbricius Artibus, inquit, Honestis</L>
<L>Nullus in urbe locus, nulla emolumenta laborum</L>
<L>—Vbi Pharmacopola est.</L>
<L>Grammaticus, Rhetor, Geometres, Pictor, Aliptes,</L>
<L>Augur, Schenobates, Medicus, Magus:—</L><BIBL>Juv. Sat. 3.</BIBL></Q>
<P><HI>By</HI> THO. BROWN.</P>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed for <HI>E. Whitlock,</HI> near <HI>Stationers-Hall,</HI> 1697</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Names of the Principal Actors.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><LABEL>Iohn Galen.</LABEL> Dr. of Physick, and Fellow of the
Royal College of Physicians
<HI>London.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Tom Gallypot.</LABEL>
An Apothecary by Trade, but
practises Physick, as a Doctor,
near—<HI>Garden.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Lancet Pestle.</LABEL>
An Apothecary by Profession, but
boldly undertakes to be a Phy∣sician,
and Surgeon also, to all
his Patients that want the
Assistance of either; living in
—<HI>Market.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Retorto Spatula d' Vlceroso.</LABEL>
An Apothecary in—<HI>Lane,</HI> but
pretends to be a great Doctor,
Surgeon, and Chymist, valu∣ing
himself much upon his Fo∣reign
Birth, and Education.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Iack Comprehensive.</LABEL>
An Apothecary living in—<HI>street</HI>
who professes himself only to
be a Doctor, Surgeon, Chymist,
Druggist, Distiller, Confecti∣oner,
and (on occasion) Corn∣cutter,
<HI>&amp;c.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Trueman.</LABEL>
A Gentleman of honest Principles,
endeavouring to shew each Per∣son
their Faults, and perswa∣ding
them to act in their own
Sphere only.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Messengers, Glyster-Pipes, Mortars, Saws, Forceps's, Boxes,
Bolt-Heads, Crucibles, &amp;c. and other Attendants.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>The SCENE Apothecaries Hall.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Epistle Dedicatory, to that Worthy and
Ingenious Gentleman Dr. J. B.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Doctor,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I Am heartily glad that a Person of your Learning
and Parts has taken up the Cudgels against the whole
College of Physicians; and notwithstanding your
great Modesty have <HI>set your Face</HI> against so Learned and
Ingenious a Society. I must confess, I have a prety
good stock of Confidence my self, and perhaps dare at∣tack
any single Person whatever, nay even Mr. <HI>Bays</HI> him∣self,
but to attack such a Body of Men of Learning and
Sense, I must yield is a Task only fit for your Manage∣ment,
who I dare boldly say can rail as bluntly as any
Oyster-Wench at <HI>Billingsgate.</HI> Therefore as you have
began to make 'um appear a parcel of Sots, and perjured
Villains (as your witty Queries seem to import) I beg
the Favour of you to go on <HI>without any Consideration</HI> (as you
have done already) and perhaps in time you may prove
'um all Whores, and Rogues, Vagabonds, Persons that
had neither Fathers, or Mothers, and what not? For if
any can prove it, I believe it must be you, no Body else
daring to attempt to prove Matters of so great Conse∣quence,
because they want your Learning and Knowledg
to go through with it. Take only this Caution, <HI>Dear
Doctor,</HI> in the Management of your Affairs: Let not the
Multitude of Business distract your Regular Thoughts
(your Head being a little out of order sometime) lest
you grow apt to forget what you have said of 'um be∣fore,
<PB REF="3"/>
and as you have in the Lump call'd 'um a parcel of
Perjur'd Villians, so don't publickly talk and <HI>say that the're
about 10, or 12 Honest Fellows amongst 'um.</HI> This w'ont do
my Friend; to say they are <HI>all Rogues,</HI> and some of that
<HI>All</HI> are honest Men, is a little Illogical, neither doth it sa∣vour
much of an University Education, thô it may suit
well enough perhaps with Yours. The Irish Evidence
that ignorantly swore a Person of Quality into the Popish
Plot, thought he could make no juster Retaliation to him
than by swearing of him out again. Now if you intend
to follow the steps of this worthy Evidence, and as you
have stigmatized the Fellows of the College with abun∣dance
of hard Names, so to make 'um amends you will
endeavour to give 'um as good Characters as Moral Ho∣nesty
and Christianity obliges you to do; I think you
propose a fair method of Reconciliation, and perhaps even
against their own Inclinations, out of meer Compassion,
and not respect to your Merit, they may vouchsafe to ad∣mit
you into their Society. This Advice, my Friend, I
think is very seasonable, and were I a Member of the
Colledge I would endeavour all I could to procure your
Admittance upon your Submission: but if you will still
continue in an obstinate and perverse Humour of railing,
I think you will justly forfeit that good Opinion which
Indifferent Judges have of the Hardship of your Case (if
any such there were) and be fit only to be bray'd in that
necessary Instrument of your former Profession, a Mortar.
These are the real Sentiments of,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Loving friend <HI>T. B.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB N="9" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Physick lies a Bleeding,
OR
The Apothecary turn'd Doctor, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>ACT I. SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Dr. <HI>Galen</HI> and <HI>Trueman.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trueman.</SPEAKER>
<P>DOctor, Good Morrow, What News do you
hear about the Plot? who are taken up? who
are Evidences? are there any Persons of Qua∣lity
concern'd in it, d'ye hear?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Dr.</HI> Galen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I mind no Plots not I, but a Plot to get good store
of Patients, if I can, but I think they never were so Healthy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, what? you seem to speak a little concern'd, and look
as if something had vexed you, what's the Matter Doctor?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Dr.</HI> Matter?</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me tell you, Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> I have been a
Physician in <HI>London</HI> almost Forty Years, and I never knew so
little Business to do in all my Life-Time. 'Tis a <HI>Damnable
Healthy</HI> Town grown since I knew it first. I have known the
Time when I could go out and pick up 10 or 12 <HI>l.</HI> in a Morning,
come Home to Dinner and empty'd, so out again after to Reple∣nish.
<PB N="10" REF="4"/>
But I am sure the Times now are so hard that if my
good Father had not conveniently step'd aside, I could no more
have brag'd of living by my Wit, as some Men do, than the
D—s of <HI>N</HI>—can of her Chastity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray Doctor, not too severe. Why Damnable Healthy?
Do you wish the Nation a Plague, or an Epidemick Sickness,
purely to promote your own private Interest? Such Expressions,
methinks, become not Men of your Education, nor indeed sa∣vour
much of Religion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What do you talk of that to a Physician? I thought you
had known the World better than so. Is not every Body for
their own Interest, be Religion what it will? Do's not the
greatest Pretenders to Holiness cheat with <HI>Yea,</HI> and <HI>Nay,</HI> as oft
(if not oftner) as he that says <HI>Dam me it cost me so much,</HI>
when he knows that he Lies at the same time he Swears? and
all this to promote a Trade. All the Excuse being, <HI>a Man must
live,</HI> Customers always expect some Abatement of what we ask.
Nay I have known an Apothecary set down 4 <HI>s. 6 d.</HI> for a Spe∣cifick
Bolus, when it has been about a Farthing-worth of
Crabs-Eyes in a little <HI>London</HI>-Treacle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay, Doctor, that may be. That's 4 <HI>s.</HI> for the Word Spe∣cifick,
and 6 <HI>d.</HI> for the Bolus. Pretty cheap on my Word. But
this is not to the purpose to explain what you mean by Dam∣nable
Healthy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, Sir, are you always teazing me to explain my
meaning? Then if you will have it, I'll tell you. You know
that every Body wishes well to themselves; now Health is the
greatest Enemy to our Interest and Profit that can be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>But ye take care sometimes to subdue that Enemy of
yours, I believe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Mr. <HI>Trueman</HI> don't make Reflections upon our
Profession, when the Apothecaries after a long Siege have bat∣ter'd
down the Walls, then the World says we destroy'd the
Town; what reason is there in this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="11" REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth very little, I confess, if it be so; but however I
hope, Doctor, you won't be angry at a Jest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no. But to go on. I call that Damnable Health
(thô I know it bears another Sense) when the Sickness is not
great enough to require the skill of a Physician, but every igno∣rant
Apothecary assumes the Cure, and pretends to know more
than the learned'st Physician of us all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then, you would not have the Apothecaries reco∣ver
Peoples Health? Would you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, but I would, by all means, only let 'um do their part
in their own Sphere, and within their own Limits or Bounds.
For when Men have no lawful Authority to Act, that Action
may be call'd Damnable, that is, such an Action as may justly
be condemned by all Wise-men. Now 'tis plain that the A∣pothecaries
have no lawful Commission to do what they do of∣ten,
and consequently they may be justly condemn'd for doing
such an Action. So that if the Patient dies under such an one's
Hands, the Law judges him a bold Empyrick; and all Men
of Reason, the Patient a Fool, especially if he were able to pay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, Doctor, now you are grown Grave. We will let
this Nicety of examining Words alone; I see you are angry
with the Apothecaries for invading your Province. However,
you have one Comfort left that your Good Father Broke, and
left you an Estate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Broke, Sir? how d'ye mean?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>How; why did not you say just now, had not your Good
Father step'd aside. What's that but broke? And so compoun∣ded
his Debts to support you with the Cheat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly Mr. <HI>Trueman</HI> you run a little too fast now. When
I said my Father step'd Aside, I meant, into his Grave, and left
me some Estate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, I beg your Pardon, I thought you had meant
otherwise, because I hear all your whole Estate is mortgag'd
to pay the old Knights Heir some Thousand's o' Pounds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="12" REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What he has on my Estate, I'll not tell you; but I can
tell you that he has no more on it than what I am able to pay,
thô perhaps more than I am willing at the rate of such unrea∣sonable
Demands. Come let's talk no more of that, we had
Rogues and Knaves for our Ancestors, who brought us in Debt,
that's all can be said. You know the old Proverb, <HI>Happy is that
Family that has no Whores or Rogues belonging to it.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>[<HI>Tom Gallypot</HI> peeps in, with a Glyster-Pipe in one Hand,
and a Cordial Bolus in t'other.]</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come in, Come in, we were no sooner talking of
Rogues but enters an Apothecary: Prethee, <HI>Tom,</HI> where hast
been that thou com'st with the Accoutrements of thy Pro∣fession
thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom G.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly, Sir, I have been at your House; your Lady
was not very well to Day, and she sent for me to—to—to—
Canonade her Posteriors: You know by my Instrument what I
have been doing. And now I have done that, I have prescri∣bed
a Specifick Bolus for her to take after it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Pox of your Specifick Bolus, and You. My Wife is
never well but when she's taking Physick, I think. Prithee,
Mr. <HI>Gallypot,</HI> what will be the Charges of this Morning's work?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, but little, you never stand upon that I am sure
for your Ladies good; she must also have a Pearl Julep, and an
<HI>Anodyne</HI> Draught: and then I hope she'll be very speedily well
again.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Pox had you with your cramp Names. Tell me what
all this will cost? I am sure I left her well not above an Hour
ago.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>[<HI>Starts back.</HI>] Good Sir, be not so unreasonably Pas∣sionate,
and I'll tell you. Sir, The Pearl Julep will be Six
Shillings Eight Pence; Pearls being dear since our Clipt Mo∣ney
was current. The Specifick Bolus 4 <HI>s.</HI> and 6 <HI>d.</HI> I never
reckon less; my Master in <HI>Leadenhall-street</HI> never set down
less, be it what it would. The <HI>Antihysterick</HI> Glyster, 3 <HI>s.</HI>
<PB N="13" REF="5"/>
and 6 <HI>d.</HI> (a Common One is but 2 <HI>s. 6 d.</HI>) and the <HI>Anodyne</HI>
Draught 3 <HI>s. 4 d.</HI> That's all, Sir, a small matter and please
you, Sir, for your Lady. My Fee is what you please Sir.
All the Bill is but Eighteen Shillings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very fine, I'faith, d'ye make a <HI>But</HI> at it? I do suppose
to be Genteel, I must give you a Crown.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>If your Worship please; I take it to be a fair, and
an honest Bill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you so indeed? But I wish you had call'd a Doctor,
perhaps he would have advised her to have forbore taking any
thing, as yet at least, so I had saved 13 <HI>s.</HI> in my Pocket.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Sir, call a Doctor; we never do that, at least very,
rarely till we have done all we can with the Patients: And
when we can't tell what to do with 'um, then we oblige a
Doctor and call him in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very fairly confessed, Mr. <HI>Gallypot,</HI> I believe you never
spoke a truer Thing in your Life. I am glad to hear your Con∣fession
to Mr. <HI>Trueman;</HI> and am very sorry the State do's not
think fit to handle you a little for your unreasonable Practices.
I see you have Impudence enough to demand a Fee too, but do
wonder you should do it before my Face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly, Doctor, I did not mind you. However, I
hope, I may take what Gentlemen please to give me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pleased to give you? Faith, I am ashamed to see
Gentlemen so imposed upon by ye Mrs. Doctors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth, Doctor, that was a Lucky Thought of yours,
we are but Mrs. thô they commonly call us Doctors. And
now you put me in mind of it, ha'nt you seen my Paper, set out
<HI>March 2, 1695?</HI> wherein I make above half the College of
Physicians Masters, thô they are call'd Doctors among them∣selves?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>How! Mr. <HI>Gallypot;</HI> How do you do that? That's a
Trick and an half, pray let's know it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord, Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> can't you guess how? If the
Doctor pleases, I'll tell you immediately.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="14" REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my Heart, if you make it out, I believe you
will be a Man of admirable Sagacity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith so you will, for I can't readily guess, thô I am
sometime as good at guessing as another, if you can prove that
they are no Doctors, who have taken Degrees in the
Universities, then you'll certainly be in the right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prove? I can infallibly prove more than that if I
once undertake it. You must know that I own none to be
Doctors but those who have regularly done their Exercises for
Physick in one of our Universities; that's plain. But hold a lit∣tle,
here's my Brother <HI>Pestle</HI> of <HI>King-street</HI> coming in, he can
be a Witness of the whole. I Gad, I have so ferreted and
humbled 'um, that I'll spoil their Association against the Apo∣thecaries;
for they have Associated by the Names of Doctors,
and I'll prove above half of 'um to be but Masters at best.</P>
<STAGE>[Enter <HI>Lancet Pestle,</HI> with a Plaister-Box in his Hand.]</STAGE>
<P>Brother <HI>Pestle,</HI> I am glad you are come in, in this nick of
time; I was just a telling Mr. <HI>Trueman</HI> how I have humbled
the College of Physicians, has'nt thee read my Paper of Queries
I put out <HI>March 2, 1695?</HI> Do'st not see how smartly and finely
I jerk 'um? Hey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay Brother, I must needs say you have done your part
very handsomely, thô I don't hear any Body took much Notice
of what you said.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, that may be. And do'sn't that show their
want of Understanding the more? None but a Block-head
would slight such smart Reflections. O that I could think
of a short Saying in the Classicks relating to this Matter. I
vow 'twas a smart one, I remember it in English.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What was it Mr. <HI>Gallypot?</HI> can't I help you out? what
did it relate too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a Saying in Latin, all which I have now almost
forgot, except Physick-Latin; I remember 'twas a piece of a
Verse out of <HI>Tacitus,</HI> or <HI>Suetonius,</HI> I can't tell which.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="15" REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, Mr. <HI>Gallypot,</HI> let your two Poets alone,
perhaps you may think of <HI>Ovid,</HI> or <HI>Horace.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay really so 'twas, but 'tis a long while ago, so I had
forgot their Names on a sudden.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>What! perhaps it was.</HI> Pudet haec opprobria nobis, &amp; dici
potuisse, &amp; non potuisse refelli.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I troth that's the very Saying. I thank you that you
have help'd me out. Now is that not plain to the purpose?
<HI>Horace</HI> was a fine Fellow, I vow he was Mr. <HI>Trueman.</HI> Thô
I don't well know whether <HI>Ovid,</HI> or he said it; yet they were
both fine Fellows.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay so they were, I believe, Brother. But I am in
haste, and must go to blood an Eminent Citizen in <HI>Tower∣street.</HI>
So, I am in haste.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold a little, Mr. <HI>Pestle,</HI> one Word with you before you
go. Blood, Mr. <HI>Pestle!</HI> I thought you had been an Appren∣tice
to an Apothecary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I was, Sir, but I thank God, and my own Indu∣stry,
I have by my Diligence perfectly acquired the whole
Knowledg of Surgery. I Phlebotomize as well as the best Sur∣geon
in <HI>London,</HI> thô I say it that should not say it. I'll tell
you how I came to be so dextrous in performing that Opera∣tion
in particular.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well now am I fairly hope up, between two of ye, one
endeavouring to prove all his Doctors to be Masters, and
t'other showing his dexterity in Phlebotomizing, as he calls it.
What a Pox, were not both of ye bred Apothecaries?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp. <HI>and</HI> Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, pray be not so passionate. Yes we
were both of us bred Apothecaries. But Knowledg—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is Dr. <HI>Pestle</HI> here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes he is. What d'ye come from Sir <HI>Thomas</HI> in <HI>Tow∣er-street?</HI>
What do's he want to be let blood immediately?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, Sir, he do's, and stays for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="16" REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Lad, Well, I'll come presently. [<HI>Exit. Messeng.</HI>]
Now I know he will be blooded by no Body else; I have per∣swaded
him that all the Surgeons are Blunderers, as to Bleeding.
Sir <HI>Thomas</HI> is a Good-natur'd Gentleman. He believes that
no Body understands the curing a Disease, or an Ulcer, or in∣deed
any Thing, but an Apothecary. Faith he is one of the
honestest Gentlemen in <HI>England.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You make him a fine Gentleman indeed. Honest! For
no other reason as I see but because he suffers himself to be
made a Fool of by such as you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>But, Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> assure your self, he's a Man of very
good Sense: All the Apothecaries in Town say so, and then I
am sure it must be true. He pays well, and takes Physick free∣ly;
besides I particularly know his Constitution: after Bleed∣ing
he must take a Purge or two, then some Cordial Powders,
Dulcifiers of the Blood, and two or three odd Things more,
But as I was saying, this Sir <HI>Thomas</HI> has a Vein as fine, and as
small as the finest Silk you can imagine: I'll tell you what I did
to learn to let him Blood, I took a fine, nay super-fine Cobweb,
and pick'd out of it one of the smallest Filaments, or Threads I
could find: This Filament or Thread of the Cobweb, as I told
you, I lay upon a convenient place, as I remember upon a
piece of white Paper, then I took my Lancet, and without the
least Hesitation, divided it soquickly, all the whole length, to
the great Admiration of the Standers by, that—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>This was very admirable indeed, and almost like the
Virtuoso's learning first to swim on a Table in order to swim in
the Water. But suppose this true, do's this make you a com∣pleat
Surgeon, so as to undertake the Cure of any Ulcer, or
Wound?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh! Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> I tell you 'tis an easy thing for
a Man of Parts to be a Surgeon; do but buy a Lancet, For∣ceps,
Saw; talk a little of Contusions, Fractures, Compress and
Bandage: You'll presently, by most people, be thought an
<PB N="17" REF="7"/>
Excellent Surgeon. Especially—d'ye mind me—Lord,
you Nod, methinks, as if you were Sleepy:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, I hear you: But I sate up late last Night, and
am a little Drowsy. But I heard you say you were a Man of
Parts, I think, and that you had two Familiar Acquaintance
Compress and Bandage: I grant it, Sir, (<HI>rubbing his Eyes</HI>) but
still how do's this make you a Surgeon? You may as well say
my keeping Company with a Bishop may make me a good
Divine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas! poor Gentleman, I find you did not sleep well
last Night. Hah! Hah! I can't but laugh at your Mistake.
My two Acquaintance! Hah! Hah! Hah! a pretty Mistake!—
but true enough: For a Man must be acquainted with his Bu∣siness
indeed; now Compress and Bandage being a part of it,
you may term them my Familiar Acquaintance, if you please,
Mr. <HI>Trueman.</HI>—Lord, I think the Devil's in you for Drow∣siness,
and Gaping.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray, Mr. <HI>Pestle,</HI> pray say something then that may di∣vert
me and keep me awake, for I protest to hear you talk of
skill in Surgery will never do; for my part I am for employ∣ing
every Man in his own way, the Doctor for Advice, the
Apothecary for Medicines, and the Surgeon for Wounds, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, how you are mistaken again, don't you think
that one Man, being an Apothecary, may understand perfect∣ly
and thorowly all three parts?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, being an Apothecary indeed he may understand ve∣ry
much, as you say, especially if he be a Man of great Learning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Learning? That signifies but little in this Age, nor
(I thank our kind Stars) had ever less Encouragement; if you
but profess your self an Apothecary, and then undertake any
thing whatever, (as we dare do) no body questions but that
you are an Able Doctor, and a Good Surgeon, at any time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very fine, on my Word; and do you think the World
so blind as to believe it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="18" REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> they generally are. I my self
have turn'd out several Doctors out of Families, because they
would not prescribe Physick <HI>plentifully,</HI> and in large Quantities.
I have perswaded my Patients, that they did not well under∣stand
their Distemper; so have brought in another who has
<HI>swingingly dos'd 'um.</HI> I could tell you of a Sir <HI>Harry</HI> that paid
an 100 <HI>l.</HI> for Physick in six Weeks, and I accepted it, being a
Friend, without requiring one Penny for my own Fees.—You
don't know the Mystery of Trade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>In plain English, I know not what you call Mystery,
but I now know the Roguery of that Doctor and you too.
What an 100 <HI>l.</HI> in 6 Weeks? Bless me, what did she take?
I believe she swallow'd Guinea's made into Bullets for the
Gripes, so discharg'd 'um again for the Gold-finders. For I
hear Guineas are grown so cheap that Ladies begin to think
that they can take them cheaper than Apothecaries Do∣ses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Abominable! Do'st hear Brother <HI>Gallypot?</HI> I pro∣test,
Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> you scan Peoples Actions too narrowly.
Wou'dn't you have us live?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same Question may be as well ask'd by an High∣way-man,
or a Pick-pocket. Live upon honest Gains, come do,
and then it will <HI>wear</HI> well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, Sir, I go to Sir <HI>Thomas,</HI> and wait on you again
presently.</P>
<STAGE>[Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, if you must be gone, e'en let's all go for the pre∣sent,
and discourse the rest over to Morrow.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>[Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act and scene">
<PB N="19" REF="8"/>
<HEAD>ACT II. SCENE II.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Being the Representation of several Apothecaries, weighing
Rich Mens Brains in their Scales, by Scruples.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Dr. <HI>J. Galen</HI> and <HI>Trueman.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>MR. <HI>Trueman,</HI> methinks 'twas a pretty Diversion ye∣sterday,
to hear the Apothecary brag of his Skill in
Surgery and Physick; I could not imagine what he had to set
up with, but a large stock of Impudence: I know all his Me∣dicines
in his Shop did not cost above Fifty Pound, and in Six
Weeks Time has he made an hundred Pound of one part of it?
Such Reflections as these wou'd make a Man burn his Books,
and curse the Gentility of his Education. It seems indeed
wonder to me, that so many Gentlemen who serve in Parlia∣ment,
and have oft-times many Younger Sons to provide for,
do not find out a way to suppress these griping Empyricks, and
Quacks, that their Children may be the better able to support
themselves in a Genteel Profession, answerable to the Expence
they have been at in their Education. In troth 'tis a thing
worthy Consideration.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly, Doctor, I am of your Opinion, but in such
Points our English Gentlemen of what Sect soever are generally
of the same Temper with those they call Church of <HI>England</HI>-Men,
that is, <HI>lazy and slow in prosecuting a Publick Interest, but
active enough to promote their own private Advantage.</HI> And this,
to give you but one Instance, is evident enough in the Choice
of a Parliament-Man, where the active Dissenter generally gets
the Day, because the lazy Church-Man won't stir to manage a
<PB N="20" REF="9"/>
Publick Cause and choose honest Representatives, tho' his own
private Interest may be often promoted by the assistance of such
a Publick Friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>We have an English Saying that do's a great deal of
Mischief, which is this, <HI>That which is every Bodies Business is no
Bodies Business.</HI> Therefore I wonder that the College of Phy∣sicians
don't petition the Parliament for a Remedy in this Case,
and make it their particular Business.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Tom Gally pot <HI>hastily.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>College of Physicians! What of them? by
your leave, Doctor, I think the Company of Apothecaries
very Substantial Men, and are able to buy twice your College.
They are Monyed-Men; and have an Interest almost every
where. College of Physicians! they are Learn'd Men they
say, but what's that to Money? Hah! Hah! Hah!.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Look you, Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> I suppose you know this Gen∣tleman
is an Apothecary by his Carriage, and rude Beha∣viour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know him, Doctor? Ay very well, but I suppose he has
been taking a <HI>large Whet</HI> this Morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, Sir, but I ha'n't, I understand the regulating my
Health better than so; I that have practis'd Physick now near
30 Years know better things than <HI>Whets,</HI> as you call 'um.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, <HI>Tom,</HI> if thee wou'lt have no Excuse made for thy
Uncivility, I have done. Then for ought I know Impudence
is as necessary an Ingredient to an Apothecary, as Sugar of
Pearl for your Pearl Cordials, with a Pox.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you are my Patient, so you may say what you
please. But saving the Doctor's Presence, I hope you remem∣ber
what I said yesterday about my Paper that I put out <HI>March</HI>
2, 1695. wherein I cut out half the College from being
Doctors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have no Patience to hear this Fellow's prating.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="21" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, but prethee Doctor, stay a little longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beg your Excuse, I'll wait on you to Morrow.</P>
<STAGE>[Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ho! I know he wou'd'nt stay to hear my Reasons a∣gainst
their worthy Society.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor indeed do I desire it. But if I must of necessity hear
them, prethee put me out of Pain as soon as you can.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I'll tell you now. Some of them took their
Degrees at <HI>Leyden,</HI> some at <HI>Padua,</HI> some at <HI>Vtrecht,</HI> some in
<HI>Scotland,</HI> others incorporated at <HI>Cambridg,</HI> or Commenced
Doctors, as an Honour conferred on them, being in the Retinue
of some Great Person, as Ambassador, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Now all these
<HI>in reality</HI> are <HI>no Doctors;</HI> and consequently every Member of
the College that is such cannot rightly be called Doctor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why not, good Mr. <HI>Gallypot,</HI> is not a Doctor of Physick
bred in Foreign Universities as much a Doctor as one bred at
our Universities? As to their Titles I see no Difference.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I hope you will allow it to be more Honourable
to be educated regularly in one of our own Universities, and so
Commence Doctor in One's Turn.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Suppose that were so, yet I hope they are Doctors still?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But, Sir, I say they are not properly Doctors. For
then an Apothecary, or Farrier may go to <HI>Leyden</HI> a Year or
two, come afterwards to that <HI>free and unquestioning</HI> University
of <HI>Cambridg</HI> to be dubb'd Doctor, and straightway be admitted
into the College of Physicians.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I suppose you mean by <HI>properly Doctors,</HI> such Qualifica∣tions
as you require, they want. Else I should (as in other
Cases) think they were properly so. For a Church is properly
a Church, so and so Built, and Consecrated. And a Logger-head
arguing very silly is properly a Logger-head. Besides I
doubt such Remarks come Home upon your Self.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, Sir, then let's bar Reflections, e'en let it be
so as you say. Come, I hate arguing. But let me tell you un∣der
the Rose, I can write a Prescription as well as any of 'um all,
<PB N="22" REF="10"/>
I learn'd that the first thing I did, by reading Doctors Bills in
my Shop.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, I am glad I have brought you to a good Temper:
And I do believe you had better been an Apothecary still. For
to speak properly, as you call it, you are a Mr. Doctor, or
Dr, Master, which you please. But enough, hold, who is
that coming hither so gravely? what's his Name?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Retorto Spatula d' Ulceroso.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can't call him readily to my mind, but I know him
very well by Sight. I use to meet him at Apothecaries-Hall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, your Humble Servant. Pray, don't you belong to
the Spanish Ambassador?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retorto.</SPEAKER>
<P>[<HI>Stroaking his Whiskers</HI>] No, Sir, but I am an Ita∣lian
born, my Name is <HI>Retorto Spatula d' Vlceroso;</HI> I was bred
in <HI>Italy</HI> what you call an Apothecary, by which I attained to
the Knowledg of Physick, both the Theoretick and Practick part:
I also exercise the Art of Chyrurgery, as Scarrifying, Cupping,
Stupes, Rollers, and Bandage, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Besides, I can by Chymi∣stry
extract the Quintessence of the Four Elements, and tame
the Red Dragon: and in fine, I can make up a Cordial, Bolus,
or Pills, <HI>according to the best mode in Foreign Countries,</HI> as you
may see in my Shop in—<HI>lane.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, Sir, not too fast; after all with your hard Names,
I believe you are bred an Outlandish Apothecary; and they,
forsooth, make up things far better than our English Apotheca∣ries
do theirs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, infinitely better, in my Shop I should be
ashamed if <HI>my Pills</HI> look'd not like true Gold; tho' but gilt, <HI>my
Bolus</HI>'s are put up all in gilt Paper, cut in fine Shapes and Figures:
a Quire costs me 5 <HI>s.</HI> the cutting; besides the Paper is pure
<HI>Venice</HI>-Paper: My Cordials are all put into <HI>Venice</HI>-Vials, <HI>&amp;c.</HI>
and all this <HI>Alamodo d' Italiano,</HI> to make the Physick <HI>taste</HI> the
better, <HI>work</HI> the better, and <HI>look</HI> the better. O fine Italians!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="23" REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now you say something, <HI>look the better;</HI> but to taste the
better, or work the better, I don't well understand. Will a
Vomit work the better for being in a fine <HI>Venice</HI>-Glass? I think
a little Nastiness for a Vomit makes it work the better. I
knew a Doctor that used to stir it with his Finger, before he
gave it, to make it nauseate the more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, that be very unhandsome. No English-man
can do so finely as I can.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I must beg your Pardon, I believe they can all do
as well as you pretend; but I should look on it as a needless piece
of Foppery if they all should do as you do. And I am sure the
Patient must pay more Sawce for his Medicines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, that's very true; a good Cook will be well
pay'd for his Sawce, you know Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Pox, but this is paying Sawce for the use of Dishes,
like a young <HI>Oxford</HI>-Scholar's Treat, if he spends Five Pound in
Meat, 'tis odds but he pays 3 or 4 <HI>l.</HI> for the use of Dishes and
Linen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, notwithstanding all this, I never reckon for a
little Bolus above 11 or 12 <HI>s.</HI> made of very good <HI>Diascordium,</HI>
very good <HI>Gascoin</HI>-Powder, and a little Pearl.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, on my Word that's mighty kind, to take not above
12 <HI>s.</HI> for all your fine Dressing, and a Groats-worth of Medi∣cines.
And do you take any Apprentices?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retorto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, Sir, I do, for about 100 <HI>l.</HI> a Lad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, and very well worth it too, and a great deal of
Money saved, if you teach him all your Trades; for the De∣vils
in't if one don't hit. For the Education of a Son to be a
regular Doctor is reputed 1000 <HI>l.</HI> Charge at long run. Any
Surgeon of Note will have 120 <HI>l.</HI> or more, an Apothecary 50 <HI>l.</HI>
or more; a Chymist perhaps as mnch. Now if you will teach
my Son all these Arts and Sciences, I think I have a very good
Bargain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll certainly do it Sir, never doubt it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, agreed: I'll send my Eldest Son to you, and when
he is out of his Time, I'll bind all his Younger Brothers to him,
so each will have 4 Trades or Callings, won't they Mr. <HI>Retorto?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ye doubt it? I thought you had known an Apo∣thecary
better than to disbelieve him in his own Calling. Nay,
Sir, to be free with you, I'll teach you how to multiply Medi∣cines
so fast upon a Patient, that in a Weeks time he shall get ten
Pound in some Cases, when the Doctor shan't get above 20<HI>s.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's a rare Art indeed, then I suppose you must at∣tack
your Patient with a Quadripartite Army of Medicines
drawn from all Quarters of your four Sciences.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can do it, and will; and if you don't think this
enough, here's my Brother <HI>Comprehensive</HI> a coming.</P>
<STAGE>[Enter <HI>Comprehensive.</HI>]</STAGE>
<P>He can besides this teach him to make all sorts of Sweet-Meats,
buy and sell Drugs, distil all sorts of Strong-Waters; nay cut
Corns for a need to Persons of Quality.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, then he is a Corn-cutter only to Persons of
Quality.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, not unless he pleases.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor any thing else, unless he pleases. However, I am
content my Son shall only learn your four Arts, or Sciences, as
you call them. I think that's enough for One, especially if he
learn throughly the last, that is, to multiply Medicines so as
to get Ten Pounds to the Doctor's Twenty Shillings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>That, assure your Self, I'll teach him perfectly: For
all the Apothecaries in Town now understand it pretty well;
and, I think, I understand it <HI>exceeding</HI> well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, Sir, I thank you for your Kindness; but I'll see
ye all at the Devil first, to learn how to swallow <HI>Assafoetida,</HI>
before ye shall have the Education of my Son. I think, if it
be possible, ye have less Honesty than a Lawyer that has but
one Cause in a Year to keep him, and his Family, out of—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="25" REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, by your leave, this is not fit Language for a
Gentleman Apothecary to bear: He's a Brother of the Quill,
and an honest Man, I'll justify it. He was Master of the Com∣pany
not long ago.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>That may be, and never the honester Man, if he teaches
his Apprentices that Cheat. But, by your leave, I suppose you
are an Apothecary too by your Talk. Pray, what may I call
your Name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Name, Sir, is <HI>Iack Comprehensive,</HI> originally
a North Country-man, and Brother Apothecary to this Worthy
Gentleman, Mr. <HI>Retorto Spatula d' Vlceroso,</HI> Apothecary, Sur∣geon,
Chymist and Doctor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay, Sir, his Titles I knew before; and pray, Sir, how
many have you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I am, in short, generally call'd Doctor only,
but I also profess my self a Surgeon: An Apothecary, I should
have said first, then Surgeon, Chymist, Druggist, Confectio∣ner,
Distiller, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> And, to Persons of Quality, Corn-Cutter.
And—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, Sir, pray a little, 'till—I'll take out my Table-Book,
lest I should miscal you, and not give you your right
Title.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, no matter, Sir, to give your Self that
Trouble; I answer to any one of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I am glad you do, for fear of giving Offence.
Then pray, Mr. <HI>Corn Cutter</HI> of Quality (that was the last
Title I heard) tell me, since you have so many Trades, which
of all these were you bound to first? Or were you bound to 'um
all at once?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Corn-Cutter of Quality! What, could you pick
out none but that? I told you I was usually call'd Doctor, and
nothing else. I won't tell you what Trade I was bound to.
One would think you had Sense enough to guess I was an
Apothecary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="26" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Sir, pray don't be so angry. How should I guess
so many Trades to center in one Man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I see you don't know the Town. I thought
you had told me you had been in Town above 30 Years.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly so I have, and have known Apothecaries call'd
Doctors, which is but two Names; but you are Apothecary,
Doctor, Chymist, Distiller.—Hold, Call my Man to give me
my Pocket-Book out of—O! I have it by me in my Pocket.
Faith, you must excuse me, I can't remember all your Titles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis no matter, Sir, remember but Doctor, that's
enough, I'll answer to that, if you please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Comprehensive the Apothecary</HI>'s a better Name, in my
mind; it do's not please me to call you Doctor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then call me what you please; I am sure some
of the Greatest Men of the Nation honour us with that Title,
and value our Skill above a Physician's often.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sorry they do; and do think it a great Fault in our
Government that Men of Liberal and Ingenious Education—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Dr. Galen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr. Galen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, let me go on. I heard what you were up∣on:—I
think you were saying the Government wou'd do well
to suppress such Cheats, Quacks, and Empyricks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, Doctor, they were not my Words. But I was
saying that I thought it a Fault in a Government that Men of
Liberal and Ingenious Education should not have the Counte∣nance
of that Government under which they live, so far as to
have a Power granted them to punish Men who act out of their
Sphere, and Invade the Rights and Privileges of their
Neighbours: This is what I was about to say, but you inter∣rupted
me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beg your Pardon. When I hear these Apothecaries
talk of their Practice, their Skill in Diseases, and Medicines,
their taking of Fees, and Pretension to even the most difficult
<PB N="27" REF="12"/>
Diseases, it puts me into a Passion, then I am apt to call 'um
Cheats, and Quacks.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>[Pestle and Gallypot peep in.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold a little, Doctor, yonder are the other two a com∣ing;
if you talk at this Rate, they'l bait you to Death: I ad∣vise
you to retire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, Doctor, you highly value your self for your
Title; Brethren come hither, come in.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>[Beckoning to <HI>Pestle</HI>
and <HI>Gallypot.</HI> The Doctor hastily runs off.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. and G.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the matter ye look so angry?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Comp. and Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Angry! why the Doctor has most abomi∣nably
abused all Apothecaries; he calls us Quacks, and Cheats:
as if an Apothecary could be a Cheat, or Knave.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. and G.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did he so? wou'd we had come time enough;
we wou'd a rounded his Doctorship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, Gentlemen, I see ye are all four together, I'll
leave ye a little, and go see if I can reduce this Doctor to a
better Temper.—Your Servant.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>[Retires only behind
the Hangings.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, Gentlemen, now we are got by our Selves,
let's talk a little about Trade: How stand Affairs? Is there
any Business stirring? We ought to have a meeting every now
and then, to settle what ought to be the Prizes of our Medi∣cines.
Pray how do ye at your end of the Town prize a Dose
of Common Purging Pills?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, Brother, about Eighteen Pence, sometime
Two Shillings, with an <HI>Haustus</HI> after them of Three and Six
Pence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>And can you live so? I believe all the Things cost
you at least a Shilling out of Pocket.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, God forbid! How could I live then? indeed
they cost me about Six Pence, and I take but Five Shillings and
Six Pence, sometime less, and I think that's honest Gains.
Hey Brother!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="28" REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>I. Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>O very honest! very fair! There's nothing can
be fairer in the World! Shall I tell ye Gentlemen? I not long
ago had a Patient, who accidentally had a Robust heavy Fel∣low
tread on a Corn that grew on his left Toe, which put him
into some pain. I perswaded him he was a little Feverish, so
blooded him, and apply'd a Caustick to his Toe (as I told him)
to eat out the Corn: But unluckily eat to the very Bone, and
made a pretty handsome Ulcer. Then I Blister'd him, and
distilled some <HI>Antifebrifuge</HI> Drops, Specificks for him only, and
good for no body else besides. In short, he lay Ill of this but
Eleven Weeks, and what do'st think he wou'd have paid me
for the Cure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, I can't tell, perhaps 40 <HI>l.</HI> But why did'st
not call in a Surgeon at last for a dead Lift?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Pox Man! I saw I cou'd do it my self, tho'
but slowly. But Faith, I thank my Stars, I have learn'd now
to use them like the Doctors, never call in either, but when
I can't tell what to do my self.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, so have I, but what had'st at last?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>What do'st talk of Forty Pound! Indeed as an
Apothecary not above Thirty Pound a Month, or so, was e∣nough;
but as Doctor (and saving thereby many Fees) and
Surgeon also, I ask'd him but 132 <HI>l. 12 s.</HI> 8<HI>d.</HI> And he
scrupl'd to give it me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>[<HI>Peeps in from behind the Hangings.</HI>] And, Faith, if he
had paid you the odd 12 <HI>s.</HI> and 8 <HI>d.</HI> I think he had paid you too
much: A Parcel of Canary-Birds, now your Rogueries and
Cheats come out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee who was that peep'd in and talk'd so, was
it not Mr. <HI>Trueman?</HI> Well, I like that Man's Company very
well, were he not too Censorious upon a Man for getting an
honest Livelyhood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay, He is well enough but he has that disobliging
Humour in him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="29" REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a Pox, if I tell ye that ye are Knaves and Cheats,
when ye are so, this ye call a disobliging Humour: Leave of
Cheating then, and practise fair in your own Sphere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cheats, and Rogues, and Knaves! That will bear
an Action I am sure. Let's at him at Law, and maull him:
Have none of ye a Lawyer Clapt, or (to speak more modestly)
has the High Scurvy; let us employ him: As we take his Mo∣ney,
let him take ours: I warrant ye we'll out-do him in ma∣king
a Bill of Costs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>That, Brother, I don't question: Besides you
know if a Man be a Knave 'tis an hard Matter to prove him so.
Let's put him upon the proof of any one Apothecary in Town.
If he should at last prove it, why 'tis but one Maungy-Hound
in a whole Pack.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft and fair Brother. For suppose he should prove
you, or me, Brother, to be that very Knave ye talk'd of. Don't
venture Proofs. Come let's threaten him with it, and he'll
hold his Tongue a course.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gad, I won't venture it, not I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I neither. Come let's talk of something else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay; Prethee, Brother <HI>Comprehensive,</HI> tell me, did'st
abate him any thing of the Bill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, Faith, I did; being an old Customer, I a∣bated
the odd 32 <HI>l. 8 s.</HI> and 4 <HI>d.</HI> and took a Goldsmith's Note
for the other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Retort.</SPEAKER>
<P>On my Word pretty well paid too. I suppose he had
a good Estate, and was a Knight at least. But prethee deal in∣geniously
with me, What did it cost thee out of Pocket?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some body will hear me, or else I would: I
cast it up to a Penny to satisfie my self what really I gain'd by
my Medicines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, No, Here are none but Friends, prethee
tell us, I know you deal with Lords, Ladies, and Knights;
who sometimes pay, and sometimes not: But when they do
pay, besure you mount'um.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="30" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>I. Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>To tell you the Truth they cost—Hold look if
no Body be near us—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>No; I'll look my self (<HI>Looks</HI>) there's no Body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then, to be plain, the prime Cost was Six Pound
<HI>17s. 6d.</HI> Farthing, or near that: So I got in the 11 Weeks
clear Gains not above 93 <HI>l.</HI> of one Patient. That's all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wou'd I had half a Score such: I cannot for the
Life of me make above Sixteen Pound in Twenty clear Gains;
I mean not reckoning in my By-Fees of Ten Shillings, and Five
Shillings, or so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Compreh.</SPEAKER>
<P>No! Come that's pretty well too, considering
you are only Doctor, and Apothecary. But I am Surgeon, and
Chymist, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> you know.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Trueman</HI> from behind the Curtain.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the Doctor here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, Yes, and all run to him to know what's the
matter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hey! I find ye are all Doctors. O, <HI>Tom Gallypot,</HI> go
call Dr. <HI>Galen,</HI> and bid him go to my Wife, she's fall'n Ill
again.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, He'ant at Home; Can't I do it? Sir, 'twill
save you Fees.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>How d'ye know he'ant at Home? Go I say, I send for
him because I would save Money. I know last time how I
saved Money by you indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, if you will have the Doctor, I'll wait on
him to your Lady.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>[Offers to go out.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay a little; now ye are all here together I must tell
you, with the rest, before you go, that there was some body
behind the Curtain, when the Medicines cost but Six Pound
Seventeen Shillings and Six Pence; and an Hundred Pound
was paid for them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>O the Devil! What are we Betray'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="31" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Betray'd, d'ye call it? No; but ye have told your
Rogueries, and Cheats, in Private, and I'll publish 'um to
the World, with my own Sentiments about the Practice of
Physick.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay pray do, so you don't reflect on us; you use
to do things very fair sometimes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, <HI>Tom,</HI> my Advice to a Patient is as soon as he is
Ill, to send for some Doctor of the Lower Rank, of whose
Learning and Skill in Physick he has an Opinion; and in case
he grow worse, to send for one of greater Fame, Reputation,
and Vogue in the World to joyn in Consult: For the Diligence
of the one, who has less Fame, and Vogue in the World (tho'
perhaps equal in Learning and Skill really, tho' not thought so
in the Eye of the World) may, and oft do's make amends for the
supposed greater Skill of the other Physitian, by which means
the Patient may more reasonably, and upon juster grounds ex∣pect
a Cure. Besides the Hurry, and Multitude of Business
that distracts the Heads of Men in great Practice, and makes
'um either forget what they did formerly in the like Cases, or
at least write but cursorily, and as they say, iust for their Fee,
would by this means be a little tempered; and by the constant
Attendance and Observation of the Diligent Physician, the
supposed Great Man may be put in mind of using some
more proper Medicines for the Patient, which perhaps he
would otherwise forget. These, Gentlemen, are my real
Sentiments.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, Master, I like your Discourse very well,
seeing you make no Remarks on Apothecaries. Besides perhaps
it may open Peoples Eyes to employ me the sooner, for tho' I
am an Old Apothecary, I am but a Young Doctor. For I visit
in either Capacity, either as an Old Apothecary, which is as
good as a Young Doctor, or as a Young Doctor, and that's as
good as t'other again.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I thought you had left off Shop, and stuck only to
your Doctorship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="32" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I do <HI>openly,</HI> but <HI>privately I keep a Shop, and</HI>
side in all Things with the Apothecaries against the Doctors;
I am, and will be to such Families, as yours, an Apothecary
still, that pay well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay, <HI>Tom, 16 l.</HI> in 20 <HI>l.</HI> is good Gains. Your Apothe∣caryship,
I believe, out do's your Doctorship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Gallyp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What. Sir, I believe you heard me jest a little
among the rest. But pray no more Reflections, I beseech
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I'll say nothing to you about your Degree, for to
me you are an Apothecary still, and no other; to you as such,
and to ye all I direct my Speech, 'tis my Opinion that ye all
ought to be forced to take moderate Prizes, and be content
with honest Gains.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>So we are: What wou'd you propose?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>In Troth, Mr. <HI>Pestle,</HI> my Proposal will signify but
little I know; but were I to advise the Law-makers, they
should make a Law that no Apothecaries Bills should be
paid till first Taxed by Two or more Doctors, appointed
in every District, or Division, in and about the City of
<HI>London.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's very fine indeed: How is that Practica∣ble?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why not? as well as the Attorney's Bills by the Pro∣thonotories.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's only when the Client thinks himself over∣rated.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>So should this be, when the Patient thinks himself
over-rated in Medicines. This would prevent the extra∣vagant
Cheats put upon the Patient oft, and be decided
without the unnecessary Suits of Law. I am well assured
that very oft 'tis cheaper to see a Doctor and pay you for
Medicines, than employ one of ye as Doctor and Apothe∣cary
too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="33" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very fine again: You, and your Politicks, You
wou'd make the Doctors our Governours, wou'd you? Good
Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> we beg you Excuse, we are His Majesty's
Free-born Subjects. And after all, pray, Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> How
do the Doctors understand to make Medicines? How do
they understand the Prices of Drugs? Puh! you talk you
know not what. Come, let's leave him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Pestle,</HI> by your leave a little. How did all the
Apothecaries learn to make Medicines at first? 'Tis very
probable that Men of Learning, Study and Industry (such
which the World has call'd Physicians) first found out the
use of Herbs, Minerals, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Out of these, proportionably
mixed, formed Compound Medicines; and their Prescrip∣tions
taught the Apothecaries the general use of these Me∣dicines:
Which made the Apothecaries use <HI>these Weapons
first formed against all Diseases</HI> (as I beg leave to call 'um)
<HI>peculiarly against the First Inventor,</HI> to destroy him Root
and Branch if possible. Like the <HI>Spaniards</HI> in the <HI>West-Indies,</HI>
who thought it good Policy (tho 'twas neither Ho∣nesty
nor Christianity) to destroy the Natives wholly; to
make the Possession of their Countrey more quiet and se∣cure.
The Gentility of their Profession, I confess, has
been a great hindrance to them in reaping those Advantages
as they might (and with more Honesty than any of ye) other∣wise
have done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>E'en let 'um be Genteel still. I don't think 'um
indeed such Fools, as that they cannot make Medicines if they
will; but why can't they keep their Learning and Genti∣lity
to themselves, and let us alone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, Sir, I am glad you allow 'um to be capable of
learning to make Medicines if they please. Now, Mr. <HI>Pestle,</HI>
to tell you the plain Truth, I hear they have actually made se∣veral
good Medicines at the College, and continue so to
do; neither do I think it so very difficult to understand
<PB N="36" REF="16"/>
making Compound Medicines, and prizing of them: For
if I know the Price of every Simple, sure 'tis very easy
for me to guess what the whole Mass cost, and so consequent∣ly
by a farther Calculation tell you what an Ounce, half
an Ounce, or a Dram of that Mass may be sold for: Thus I
have made it plain that they can make Medicines, and prize
'um too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>How can they tell tho' when a Medicine is good?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very easy, Mr. <HI>Pestle,</HI> they have taste, and sight to
judge by as well as ye, by which they discern the Good∣ness
of Simples that make every Compound, and the Goodness
also of that Compound. Besides, if ever they have bought
good out of your Shops, (and yours is always right prime
good, ye know) or have made good, they may, and I
believe can make the like again.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Suppose all this true, tho' I am resolved I won't
believe it true; who after all shall give Attendance to ob∣serve
the Operations of Medicines?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who shou'd but the Doctors themselves? They are
paid for attending their Patients.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hah! Hah! Hah! Attending? I mean admini∣tring
Physick; how I should laugh to see a Doctor giving
a Glyster, and the Bladder break and bespatter all his Velvet
Jacket: Hah! Hah! Hah!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I find you wou'd be merry at such a Mischance as that;
but that's but Idle to object, because every Nurse do's that
Office acourse, and all that ye pretend to about sick Persons,
or else are but sorrowful Nurses. As for Bleeding, the Surgeon
ought to be employ'd. As for Chymical Medicines, the Chy∣mist
is at hand; and so for all others.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Methinks your Head is full of Projects, can't you
find out one to serve them in?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I don't pretend to be a Projector; but I think the
College would do very well to make all sorts of Medi∣cines
<PB N="33" REF="16"/>
themselves, and sell them out at easy Rates. What
they design by forming a Fund by Subscription, I pro∣fess
I at present know not, but one of 'um told me t'other
day that they design to make that a Fund for buying in
Drugs, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> and making of all sorts of Compound Medi∣cines
necessary for the Sick, selling them out again for
small profit, sufficient only to pay about a dozen Servants, and
the Prime Cost of the Medicines, with a Penny in the Shil∣ling
Over-plus to the College. By which means the
Doctors will be sure to have such good Medicines, and so
well prepared as to rely on them, not to be sophisticated;
or, for want of any one prescribed, to be supply'd by a∣nother
in the room of it, as you Apothecaries oft do: If
you han't one Thing, you in your mighty Wisdom will
put in another in the room of it; so that the Physician
may prescribe till Dooms-day, and the Patient will be
never the better, if ye substitute what Medicines ye please,
and after that put what Prices ye please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prices Sir? I sell as cheap as any Apothecary in
Town; I never have above 6 <HI>s.</HI> and 8 <HI>d.</HI> for a Pint of Pearl Cor∣dial
in my Life, an you go to that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so passionate, Good Mr. <HI>Pestle,</HI> I believe you sell
as cheap as your Brethren, but all damn'd dear, and much
to the Oppression of the Poor. To remedy which they
propose to sell a Pint of good Pearl Cordial for Eighteen
Pence, or thereabouts. A Cordial Bolus for a Groat, which
ye reckon sometimes 1 <HI>s. 6 d.</HI> and sometimes 2 <HI>s.</HI> A Quart
of Bitter Drink for 1 <HI>s.</HI> for which I my self have pay'd 5 <HI>s.</HI>
and 8 <HI>d.</HI> And so proportionable for all other Medicines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh! What if they do? our Old Customers won't
leave us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What if they do? Why then the Poorer sort of
People will buy of them, because they are sure of good
and cheap Medicines. The better sort will think it Pru∣dence
<PB N="36" REF="17"/>
to save 5 <HI>s.</HI> in 6 <HI>s.</HI> and 8 <HI>d.</HI> if they can, to help pay
Taxes, and not have a Bill after a great Sickness brought
in, enough to renew their Sickness again. Even the Rich∣est
of all will be apt to be influenced by their Physicians,
when they tell 'um that there are the only Medicines pre∣pared
which they can rely on. In short, every Body will
be willing in their Illness to go to such a Place, where they
can with great probability be assured of Good and Cheap
Medicines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pestle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Mr. <HI>Trueman,</HI> you may e'en prate about <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣ling
the Practice of Physick till you are weary, I warrant
ye, let 'um do what they can, we'll easily perswade Peo∣ple
that we are all very Honest Men.—We always said
you were always a prying, busie, Inquisitive Man, pre∣tending
to understand things, I am sure you don't under∣stand;
you have a mighty Opinion of your Self. Come let
us leave him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay come, come let's leave him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>[Exit. 4 Apothecaries
Whistling in Glyster-Pipes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis an Old Saying, <HI>Si Populus vult decipi, decipiatur,</HI>
if People will be cheated e'en let 'um be so.—I have done
what lies in my Power to open their Eyes; and by telling the
Truth have gain'd other Men's Hatred, but</P>
<L>I ne'er to Flatt'ry was, or will b' a Slave,</L>
<L>He that loves Truth is Generous and Brave,</L>
<L>And scorns the Wealthy and the Thriving Knave.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

