<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached before the King and Queen at White-Hall on the 19th day of October, 1690, being the day of thanksgiving for His Majesties preservation and success in Ireland by the Right Reverend Father in God, Gilbert Lord Bishop of Sarum.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A30435</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing B5893</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R4094</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13677451</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13677451</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">101261</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A30435)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101261)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 839:12)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached before the King and Queen at White-Hall on the 19th day of October, 1690, being the day of thanksgiving for His Majesties preservation and success in Ireland by the Right Reverend Father in God, Gilbert Lord Bishop of Sarum.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 36 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1690.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Half title: The Bishop of Salisbury's thanksgiving-sermon for the King's preservation in Ireland.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Sermons.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A30435">
<STC T="W">B5893</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13677451</BIBNO>
<VID>101261</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A
SERMON
Preached before the
KING and QUEEN,
AT
<HI>WHITE-HALL,</HI>
On the 19<SUP>th</SUP> Day of <HI>OCTOBER,</HI> 1690.
BEING THE
Day of Thanksgiving,
FOR
His MAJESTIES PRESERVATION and
SUCCESS in <HI>IRELAND.</HI></P>
<P>By the Right Reverend Father in God, <HI>GILBERT</HI>
Lord Bishop of <HI>SARVM.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI>
Printed for <HI>Ric. Chiswell,</HI> at the <HI>Rose</HI> and <HI>Crown</HI> in
St. <HI>Paul</HI>'s Church-Yard. MDCXC.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="half title">
<PB REF="2"/>
<P>THE
Bishop of <HI>SALISBVRY</HI>'s
Thanksgiving-Sermon
FOR
The KING'S PRESERVATION
IN
IRELAND.</P>
<PB REF="3"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB REF="4"/>
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>PSALM CXLIV. 10, 11.</BIBL>
<Q><P>It is He that giveth salvation unto Kings, who
delivereth <HI>David</HI> his servant from the hurt∣ful
sword.</P>
<P>Rid me and deliver me from the hand of strange
children, whose mouth speaketh vanity, and
their right hand is a right hand of falshood.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>HIS Place as well as this Day
is dedicated to the Honour of
the great God, to the Celebra∣ting
of his Praise, and the Glory
of the Deliverance and Victory
that he hath given us. Those
whom he has made the Blessed Instruments of
procuring it to us, do so entirely offer up the
Acknowledgments due for it to that Provi∣dence
which they signally Adore, that as they
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ould not endure so sacrilegious a thought, as
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he putting the Honour that belongs to Them in
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he least degree of Competition with the Praises
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat are to be offered up to the Great KING of
KINGS; so by a Modesty which gives a pecu∣liar
Grace to all they do, they cannot bear even
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
that which is just, and in some sort necessary
upon such occasions. In other Places and Courts,
Invention and Fancy are put to the rack to find
out the highest Figures, and the noblest Expres∣sions
to raise the Glory of Princes, even when
their Successes do more eminently belong to some
secret Design of Providence, since no share of
them can be ascribed either to their Courage or
Conduct. But here we are so confined by Or∣ders
which one knows as little how to obey, as
how to disobey, that how large soever the Field,
and how rich soever the Prospect is, it must ei∣ther
be quite overlookt, or if it be suffered to
be shewed, it must be by Reversing the Tele∣scope
in Little and contracted. Princes, whose
Actions are their own Panegyricks, cannot bear
that others should make any for them; for what
they themselves do, exceeds all that can be said
by others: Whereas the want of real Merit must
be hid or supplied by the false appearances of it▪
The Sun and Stars must be brought down, and
in every comparison be humbled in the Prefer∣ence
that is to be given to the Flatter'd Prince▪
How many a Reproach must the Sun have endu∣red
in some Courts, if when the day is at it
longest, the Prince had for some hours prevent∣ed
his Rising, and continued his watchful Fatigue
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
till after he was Set; and that a Wound which
made so wide a breach upon him by the certain∣est
Instrument of Death, could scarce interrupt
his Motion. Here had been a copious Theme
for Hungry and Mercenary Flattery: The Sun
would have been for ever after that, despised as
a diminution to their Prince's Glory, when com∣pared
to him. Impious Attempts which were
once began, would have been pursued, of <HI>calling
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>im the King of Glory, who is strong and mighty in bat∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>l.</HI>
One King was signally struck from Hea∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en,
for admitting Divine Honours that were
offered up to him: That Jealous God who will
not suffer his Glory to be given to another,
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nows what are the properest Times and Me∣thods
for Punishing all the Blasphemy that is in
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Courts of Princes who encourage and en∣gage
their Subjects, or rather their Slaves, to fly
to such an extravagant pitch. But to us, who ac∣knowledg
that Most <HI>High</HI> God, that <HI>rules in the
Kingdom</HI> of <HI>men,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Dan, 4. 25.</NOTE> and giveth it to whosoever he
will, and that he sets up and pulls down accord∣ing
to the hidden Designs of his Wise Providence;
As all that approaches to such irreligious Excesses,
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> matter of Horror; so the Princes we serve,
make this an easie Duty to us, they being as
deeply possessed with the Belief of Providence,
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
as they are free from all those swellings which
must be fed with gross and exorbitant Flat∣tery.</P>
<P>And therefore I am not afraid to make this
the Subject of my present Discourse: <HI>It ts God
that giveth Salvation to Kings, that delivereth</HI> Da∣vid
<HI>his servent from the hurtful sword.</HI> If any
considers the scituation of these words, between
those that go before, and those that come after,
they will see, that the Sentence is cut by this as
an abrupt Meditation, which probably was to
be sung by the Chorus; whereas what is be∣fore
and after, was, as is most likely, sung by
single Voices in the person of <HI>David.</HI> The
first part of this Verse contains a general Posi∣tion,
That the Advancement of Kings, and the
Progress of Empires, the Victories obtained by
them, their Escapes and Deliverances, is of
God, and is the effect of signal Providences,
that watch over them. The words that follow
relate more particulary to <HI>David</HI> himself.
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> shall not determine whether the word <HI>hurtful</HI>
or <HI>evil sword</HI> is only a Poetical Epithete, to
swell up and beautifie the Period; or if it re∣lates
to poisonous Swords, that gave a certain
Death with every wound.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="6"/>
In the second Verse that I have read, there
is a Prayer for a complete Deliverance; that
which is here celebrated being yet imperfect:
therefore the Psalmist, returning to his former
Thread, says, <HI>Rid me and deliver me from the
hand,</HI> that is, from the power, <HI>of strange children,</HI>
or the children of the <HI>strange God,</HI> that is, Ido∣laters.
Idols in the Scripture phrase are called
<HI>strange Gods;</HI> and as the People of <HI>Israel</HI> are cal∣led
the Children of God, so Idolaters are called
the Children of the <HI>Stranger,</HI> or of the Idol.
There follows a description of Idolaters by their
Words, and by their Actions: <HI>Their mouth speak∣eth
vanity;</HI> that is, either <HI>falshood,</HI> in which
sense <HI>vanity</HI> frequently stands in Scripture; or
words of arrogance and insolent scorn. <HI>Right-hand,</HI>
in the phrase of the Old Testament, is to
be understood, either of Oaths made by the
Ceremony of lifting up the right-hand to Hea∣ven,
or of Compacts and Agreements confirm∣ed
by the joyning mens right-hands; from
which came the phrase of the <HI>right-hand of fellow∣ship.
Their right-hand,</HI> that is, either their Oaths
or their Covenants, is a <HI>right-hand of falshood,</HI> or
<HI>of a lie,</HI> according to that in <HI>Isaiah 44. 20. A lie
is in their right-hand.</HI> Since in all these they were
double and false. The Characters here given
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
them, may either be thus understood; They
are false both in their Words and Oaths: or
thus; There is much haughtiness and pride in
their Discourses, and as much falshood in all
their Treaties and Engagements.</P>
<P>To return to the first words in my Text.</P>
<P>There appear often Eminent Characters of
God's Providence, in the raising up and pre∣serving
of Kingdoms, and in the Victories and
Salvation given to Kings. If there is a Provi∣dence
that watches over any part of this lower
World, then certainly the most eminent parts
of it, upon which the rest does so much depend,
are its chief care: This has been so universally
confessed, that those among the Philosophers
who thought it below the Infinite Greatness of
the Divine Being, that it should take care of the
most inconsiderable parts of the Creation, did
yet believe that the greater and more important
Transactions were conducted by it: Tho' this
slowed from the low and narrow Conceptions
which they had of God, as if an Universal Pro∣vidence
had been too great a distraction, and
too mean a care for a Being infinitely Perfect.
But there is such a Chain in all things, the most
Important Matters taking oft their rise or turn
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
from very inconsiderable Circumstances, that it
is certain that either there is no Providence at all,
or that it has no limits, and takes all things
within its care. Yet God having put the whole
Frame of Nature under certain Rules and Laws,
the greatest part of Providence is only the Sup∣porting
and Directing of those Beings that do
still act according to their own Natures; and
in these, tho' Providence is less discernable, yet
it is still the Spring of the whole Machine, which,
tho' covered and unseen, gives motion to all
the parts of it. There are other more solemn
Occasions, in which some second causes are
raised above their own pitch, and are animated
beyond the ordinary rate; and others are at the
same time as far depressed below themselves, the
Spirits of the One abating, as much as those of
the Other are elevated. This has never appear∣ed
with more eminent Characters than in the
Revolutions of States and Empires, in which
both the course of Natural Agents, the Winds
and Seasons, and the tempers of mens minds,
seem to have been managed by such a directi∣on,
that not only every thing, but every cir∣cumstance
has co-operated to carry on Great
Designs in such a Conjunction, that those who
observe them with due attention, are forced on
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
many occasions to cry out, <HI>This is the finger of
God! this is the Lord's doing!</HI> And we may the
more certainly conclude, that such a Systeme of
things is the effect of a special and directing
Providence, when the tendency of it is to ad∣vance
some Design in which the Honour of
God is more particularly concerned.</P>
<P><HI>Cyrus,</HI> in whom the second Great Monarchy
began, and by whom God's Judgments against
<HI>Babylon,</HI> and the bringing back the Captivity of
the <HI>Iews,</HI> were to be executed, according to
what <HI>Isaiah</HI> had prophesied above 150 years be∣fore
he was born; <HI>Cyrus,</HI> I say, a small Prince, and
doom'd to an early Death by a superstitious
Grandfather, scaped that severe Fate, and was
bred up in obscurity: He first dethroned <HI>Astya∣ges,</HI>
his Grandfather; and after that, he extended
his Conquests into <HI>Lydia</HI> and <HI>Asia</HI> the less: Du∣ring
all the progress of his Glory, the <HI>Babylonians,</HI>
instead of putting a timous stop to his Victories,
thought only of fortifying their Capital City;
which when they had done to a degree that al∣most
passes belief, he, by diverting the Course
of the River, made himself Master both of City
and Empire; and sent the <HI>Iews</HI> back to rebuild
their Temple, retaining still his Authority over
them.</P>
<P><PB N="9" REF="8"/>
When the final Period of this Monarchy came,
then one of the smallest Powers in <HI>Greece</HI> did
effect it. The Kingdom of <HI>Macedon</HI> had been
one of the most inconsiderable of all that Body,
tho it was become more Powerful in <HI>Philip</HI>'s
time. The <HI>Greeks</HI> had been twice attacked by
the <HI>Persians,</HI> and vast numbers had fallen before
handfuls of them; upon this, as had been pro∣phesied
by <HI>Daniel, Alexander,</HI> a Haughty, a Vain,
and a Dissolute Prince, with an Army of 37000
men, invaded the <HI>Persian</HI> Empire, and after
Three great Battels, in the First of which 200000
came against him; 600000 in the Second, and
a Million in the Third, he carried his Conquests
on to the <HI>Ganges</HI> with such a Rapidity of Victo∣ry
and Success, that nothing could stand in his
way: Among the conquered Provinces, <HI>Tudea</HI>
was one which came under his Protection, and
continued for 146 years under that Branch of
his Empire that reigned in <HI>Syria.</HI></P>
<P>But to give another instance of this, that has
a greater relation to the People of God, after the
<HI>Iews</HI> had been long under the <HI>Syrian</HI> Yoke; <HI>An∣tiochus
Epiphanes,</HI> not content with the Subjection
that they had paid his Ancestors, set himself to∣tally
to destroy both their Religion and their
Nation; upon which <HI>Mattathias,</HI> the Father of
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
<HI>Iudas,</HI> and his Brethren, a Priest full of Zeal for
God and for his Countrey, was raised up to re∣sist
that Fury; he only began the opposition,
but dying soon after, he left the conduct of the
Deliverance of his Countrey from Persecution
and Tyranny, to his Son <HI>Iudas Maccabeus,</HI> from
whom it passed to his Brethren, and to their Po∣sterity.
A total Subversion of their Religion
and Policy, was begun, and that according to
the sense of all mankind, has ever been esteemed
a Dissolution of Government; and <HI>Mattathias</HI> and
his children their venturing on so dangerous an
Undertaking, is reckoned up in the Epistle to the
<HI>Hebrews,</HI> among the Heroical Attempts of Faith;
it is reserved to the last place, and enlarged on in
a variety of lofty Expressions, to shew that it
was one of the greatest Performances of Faith:
And it was so indeed, for it seemed to be a de∣sperate
Attempt, in which the best Success that,
reasonably speaking, they could have expected,
was a speedy and a glorious Death; they had
nothing to trust to, but Miracles of Providence;
they were few in number, destitute of every
thing, and the Kings of <HI>Syria</HI> were Masters of all
the Strong Places in <HI>Iudea,</HI> and poured in at se∣veral
times, Seven or Eight great Armies upon
them: But that Deliverance which began in a
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
Cloud that was no bigger than a hand-breadth,
made such a Progress under several Heads who
conducted the <HI>Iews</HI> with equal degrees of Pru∣dence
and Courage, that tho they were unpro∣vided
of all things, but what were afforded them
from the Spoils of their Enemies; they, after a
War of Twenty-four years Continuance, and a
Series of constant and amazing Successes, be∣came
at last a free People, both with relation to
their Religion and Government.</P>
<P>Shall I give you another Instance of him, du∣ring
whose peaceful Reign, the Saviour of the
World was born? <HI>Augustus</HI> was the Son of a <HI>Ro∣man</HI>
Knight, and was but Eighteen years old
when his Uncle <HI>Iulius Caesar</HI> was killed, whose
Usurpation upon his Countrey had rendred him
and his Family the Objects of the Hatred of
<HI>Rome;</HI> yet he not only scaped the first Rages of
that Popular Fury, but was very soon at the Head
of their Armies; he entred into the <HI>Triumvirate,</HI>
and was in a few years rid of the other two;
and after that first scene of Artifice and Cruelty
was over, he became the Wisest, the Moderatest,
and was the Happiest Prince, and the longest
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of any in History, having had a course of
Glory of Fifty-six years Continuance.</P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="10"/>
But not to weary you with a dry Recital of
too much History, I shall conclude with one
whose Circumstances were as remarkable in
themselves, as in the Effects that followed on
them: When <HI>Dioclesian</HI> and <HI>Maximian</HI> had, chiefly
by the Instigation of <HI>Galerius,</HI> begun the last Per∣secution
of the Christians, the Design seemed
so well laid, and was managed with so much
Fury, that by all the appearances of things, it
could not miscarry, when Successors were pre∣pared
to carry it on steddily; <HI>Galerius,</HI> that had
been the most violent of all the Persecutors, ha∣ving
chosen <HI>Maximinus Daia,</HI> that had been an or∣dinary
Grazier, for his Successor, who had not
any one quality to recommend him to that Ele∣vation,
but his Fury against the Christians: It
is true there was a part of the Empire that fell
not under the common Calamity; it was in∣deed
that part in which there were the fewest
Christians. <HI>Constantius Chlarus</HI> had for Sixteen
Years govern'd the <HI>West,</HI> first as <HI>Caesar,</HI> then as
<HI>Emperor,</HI> in which time he had kept both <HI>Gaul</HI>
and <HI>Spain</HI> in perfect quiet; he had reduced all
<HI>Britain,</HI> and had frequently beat the <HI>Germains,</HI>
and driven them beyond the <HI>Rhine:</HI> These Suc∣cesses
made him so formidable, that tho he was
favourable to the Christians, and would not per∣secute
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
them in his share of the Empire, yet <HI>Ga∣lerius</HI>
durst not plainly fall upon him, but he
had got his Son <HI>Constantine</HI> into his hands, and
kept him about him at his Court in <HI>Nicomedia:</HI>
His Father began to languish, and upon that
sent for him, but <HI>Galerius</HI> put him off by de∣lays;
and tho he did not flatly refuse to let him
go, yet he plainly saw that he had no mind to
grant it. But <HI>Galerius</HI> happening as he often
did, to get drunk, he obtained then his leave to
be gone, and got his Seal for it. Upon this he
went away immediately, and crossed the Sea,
near to the place where <HI>Constantinople</HI> was after∣wards
built by him; and because he apprehended
that <HI>Galerius</HI> when he came to himself would
send after him, he took up all the Horses that
were in every Stage, and at the end of it disabled
them; so he passed quite through to <HI>Italy,</HI> and
it was impossible for those whom <HI>Galerius</HI> sent
after him, ever to overtake him: He came to
his Father at <HI>York,</HI> whom he found just expiring:
He immediately declared him his Successor;
which he was not willing to accept of, till the
Soldiery in some sort forced him to it, and made
him take the <HI>Purple.</HI> He went over after that
into <HI>Gaul,</HI> where his Father-in-law <HI>Maximian,</HI>
who had <HI>abdicated</HI> the Empire, came to him, and
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
intending to return to it again, he pretended
kindness to his Son-in-law, the more effectually
to betray him: He was practising upon his Ar∣my,
when he had advised himself to go on an
Expedition with a small part of it; but <HI>Constan∣tine</HI>
was inform'd of this in time, and came back
so quick upon him, that he being both afraid
and ashamed, fled to <HI>Marseilles: Constantine</HI> pur∣sued
him, and those within refusing to stand by
him, he delivered himself into his hands, who
for two years after that, used him in all respects
as became a Great Prince, and his Father-in-law.
Yet nothing being able to overcome his restless
Ambition, he solicited his Daughter to let him
into her Bed-Chamber, while <HI>Constantine</HI> was in
Bed; she thought her ties to a good Husband
were stronger than to a bad Father, and there∣fore
discovered all to him; so an Eunuch was
laid in the bed, and a door being left open by
the Empress, <HI>Maximian</HI> came in and killed the
Eunuch; <HI>Constantine</HI> was in the next room, and
rushed in with some of his Guards about him,
and <HI>Maximian</HI> being so fully convicted of the
Crime, all the Grace that <HI>Constantine</HI> thought fit
then to shew him, was to leave the manner of
his Death to his own choice; he chose the worst,
for he hanged himself. Another signal Instance
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
of God's care of <HI>Constantine,</HI> was, that when he
advanced towards <HI>Rome</HI> to possess himself of the
Seat of the Empire, <HI>Maxentius,</HI> that was <HI>Maximi∣an</HI>'s
Son, who had assumed the Power there, came
out to fight him: But he had taken care the
night before, to cut the Timbers and Beams of
the Wooden Bridg over the <HI>Tyber,</HI> so that they must
have cracked, if any great weight had been up∣on
them; and he reckoned according to the di∣sposition
of the Battel, that <HI>Constantine</HI> should be
forced to take that Bridg, and so perish with its
fall; but the issue of the Battel was such, that
he himself was forced to pass over the Bridg,
which crackt under him, and he was drowned
in the <HI>Tyber.</HI> Through this tract of wonderful
circumstances, was <HI>Constantiue</HI> brought to the
Possession of the Empire, by whom not only the
Persecution of the Christians was put to an end,
but in pursuance of the Dream he had the night
before, he defeated <HI>Maxentius,</HI> that represent∣ed
to him the Figure of the <HI>Cross,</HI> as that under
which he was to conquer, he himself both turn∣ed
Christian, and made it the Religion of the
Empire.</P>
<P>Such have been the Methods by which God
has raised up Kings and Empires for the advan∣cing
the Glory of his great Name, for the punish∣ing
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
and humbling persecuting Tyrants, and for
giving Salvation and Protection to his People.</P>
<P>But we need not weary our selves in seeking
instances of this in past times, when in our own
days, we have seen a Prince, born indeed to have
a rank among Sovereigns, but with no intrinsick
Power to support any great Undertaking; born
an Orphan and an Abortive both, and, as to all
appearance, crushed under a double misfortune:
A Royal Family to which he was allied, was be∣come
an encumbrance to him, and his own was
under a vast and a seemingly insuperable depres∣sion;
his Country ty'd up by Oaths to exclude
Him; and those from whom in Justice and Gra∣titude
he ought afterwards to have promised
himself a mighty Protection, leaving him to his
own Strength and Conduct: yet, by a series of
steps which need not be reckoned up, Him we
have seen raised from a Plant that seemed to
rise out of a dry ground, to be a Great Tree,
under whose Shade all the Beasts of the Field
come for shelter, and in whose Boughs all the
Fowls of the Air come now to lodge. It is this
very day two full years since he first set to Sea,
to calm our Storms. The beginning was rough
and inauspicious; yet even that seemed to be
intended only to those about Him a Lesson
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
which He had long before well learnt, of obser∣ving
Providence, and depending upon it. Since
that time, fair Winds, good Seasons, prosperous
Undertakings, happy Discoveries, Success and
Victory, seem to have been chained to Him,
and bound to follow Him; and now He has not
only the Necks of His Enemies, but the Hearts
of all His People, as well as the Hopes of all
<HI>Europe</HI> fastned on him. He triumphs over His
Enemies, as well by His Mercy in pardoning,
as by His Courage in conquering; and, which
is more, He triumphs over all the Accidents of
Life by such an unshaken Equality of Mind, that
His most glorious days and His less-prosperous
hours do not create in Him any varieties of tem∣per
and behaviour. And what can we now think,
but that a Life which has been a sequel of Won∣ders,
will be carried on and concluded as it hath
been hitherto advanced; and that if there is a <HI>Ne∣buchadnezzar,</HI>
or an <HI>Antiochus Epiphanius,</HI> a <HI>Gale∣rius,</HI>
or a <HI>Maximinian</HI> now in being, that God is by
This Hand to deliver his Church from them?
<HI>For it is God that giveth Salvation to Kings;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 2. 9.</NOTE> he puts
down one, and setteth up another.</HI> He raiseth up
Kings <HI>to break his Enemies with a rod of iron,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ps. 5. 12.</NOTE> and to
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sh them in pieces like a Potters vessel; for the op∣pression
of the poor, and for the sighing of the needy,
God will at last arise, and set him in safety from him
that puffeth at him.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="18" REF="13"/>
The second part of this Verse will also afford
us matter of useful speculation, which is, the
bringing the general Observation to a particular
Head in the Instance of <HI>David,</HI> who was preser∣ved
from many Dangers, the Accidents of War,
as well as the Attempts of <HI>Saul;</HI> He was raised up
from being the youngest of many Brethren, and
from looking after his Father's Flock, to be the
Shepherd of <HI>Israel.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ps. 78. 71.</NOTE> God girded him with strength,
and taught his hands to war, and his fingers to fight,
and gave him the shield of his Salvation; he delivered
him from the Lion and the Bear,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ps. 18. 35.</NOTE> and from the Phili∣stine
that defied the Armes of the living God;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ver. 43.</NOTE> he de∣livered
him also from the strivings of the people, and
made him the Head of all the Nations round about him.</HI>
Therefore it was that He, who had seen so ma∣ny
Essays of the goodness of God to him, be∣sides
his active Zeal when settled on the Throne
for advancing God's Glory, and the beauty and
solemnity of his Worship, he employ'd many of
his thoughts and hours in composing this Book
of Psalms, as the highest return he could make to
God, that by the Elegance and Variety of those
inspired Hymns, not only that Age and Nation,
but all succeeding ones, might be furnished with
a stock of the most elevating Devotions possible,
which might give wings to their minds, and raise<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
them up towards God. So much of the <HI>David in
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
my Text,</HI> which leads me to say somewhat of
the <HI>David of the Day.</HI></P>
<P>Is it nothing to you all, that see and hear
the signal steps of Providence, that have
so gloriously watched over, and conducted
this our <HI>David?</HI> I reckon not among the greatest
of these, his being raised up to a Throne
of such high Dignity among the Kingdoms
of the Earth, by a Title, that, let ungrateful
men say what they will, has more both from God
and man in it, than any the World has seen for
many Ages. But Kingdoms and Crowns are so
distributed in the World according to the secret
Designs of Providence, that this singly is but an
ordinary Blessing, and given in common to him
with other Crowned Heads. To be a Deliverer
of Mankind, a Preserver of Religion, a Fence a∣gainst
Tyranny and Cruelty; to have for his first
Essay saved his own Countrey from utter ruine,
when it seemed to be in its last Agonies; and to
have not only resisted, but beat back a mighty
Torrent that swept every thing before it; to have
stopt the blackest Designs that were formed a∣gainst
Religion and Liberty both there and here;
for the preserving the United Provinces, and
their Religion and Government, was at that time
likewise the saving this Church and Nation; so
soon did he begin to be a Deliverer to us: this,
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
perhaps, was not then known to every one; but
we do now all know, that we were to have been
the second Sacrifice); All this, I say, one should
think was Greatness and Glory enough to have
fallen to any one mans share. But that a reserve of
Blessings should yet be kept in store for the same
Person, is a peculiar Favour of Heaven; and
shews us, That <HI>this is the man whom God delights to
honour, and whom he has made strong for himself.</HI> That
the day of our Extremity being come, when we
saw the Net spread over us, and that a little time
was only wanting, to model the Army, and to
make a Parliament, that just then the conjuncture
of Affairs over all <HI>Europe,</HI> and the disposition of
all mens minds in the <HI>Netherlands,</HI> the Errors and
Follies of our Enemies, both within and without
this Kingdom, with the zealous assistance of our
Friends and Allies; but above all, That the In∣sensible
Creation, the Seas, the Winds, and the
Seasons, should all have joined together to pro∣mote
that great Undertaking, shewed the care
and tenderness of that wise Conduct that watched
over us. Every one of these Particulars is extraor∣dinary
in it self; but the conjunction of them
all together is such a scene of Wonders, that no
man who knows the contexture of all the parts
of this Deliverance, can look upon them, without
seeing such a prospect of Providence as raises his
<PB N="21" REF="14"/>
Mind into all the heights of Joy and Wonder. But
to view next the second Scene of God's raising his
Glory on this Stage, when our Sins had for a while
retarded the progress and the finishing of our Hap∣piness,
when many among our selves were wishing
to be again in <HI>Egypt,</HI> and were saying, <HI>We will not
have this Man to rule over us;</HI> when many of those
who had formerly aggravated our Dangers, as much
as any, were changing their Stile, and fancying
that a Power thrust upon us from <HI>France,</HI> and sup∣ported
and guarded from thence, was, or would be
a tame and harmless thing, and seemed to forget all
the Affections that Nature gives for our Country,
and that Religion gives for the Church of God, so
that a new and perhaps a greater Crisis than the for∣mer
had returned upon us; then it was that our
<HI>David</HI> resolved to be no longer a Spectator and a
Director of his Forces, and to make War by Proxy,
but again to venture that sacred Life, in which, if
in a Day of rejoicing we may mix any Complaints
with our Jubilee, we must venture to say, that by
a Courage which is too prodigal of that in which
we have all so great a share, even while he preserves
us by his happy <HI>Genius,</HI> yet he exposes us too much
by the repeated Dangers to which that Life is expo∣sed,
by which as we all live, so all <HI>Europe</HI> is kept united
against the great Destroyer and Enemy of Mankind.</P>
<P>Here again; the Winds and Seasons, the Cou∣rage
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
and Fidelity of all about him, the feeble Coun∣sels
and Conduct of the Enemy, conspired of his
his side; but above all, the Watchfulness of Provi∣dence
shewed it self in Instances that Posterity will
be tempted to think the Contrivances of a happy I∣magination
to beautify our History. But Inventi∣on
could hardly be so bold or so fruitful, as to re∣present
a Prince just in the Eve of a Day, upon
which not only the Security of his Throne, but that
which to a Mind like his is much more valuable, the
Preservation and Happiness of his People depended,
receiving a Wound by that, which of all the Inven∣tions
of giving Death, is the most infallible, and
yet so slight a Wound, that it seemed sent upon no
other Intent, but that the firmness of his Mind, upon
so extraordinary an Accident, and the care of Heaven
in so critical a minute, might be shewed in the pro∣perest
time, and in the sight of all his Army, both
for animating and assuring them, that there was an
invisible Guard watching about the Person of him,
under whose Standards they were to triumph next
day. This prov'd so inconsiderable, that it neither hin∣dred
the continuance of a Fatigue of nineteen hours
that day, nor a return to one of sixteen the next, in
which his Presence was every where so necessary,
that the slightest Wound which had disabled him
from that, might have proved a mortal one to us all.
The Glories of that Day, that was neither stained
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>
with a great effusion of Blood, nor with any of that sort
that might have lessened the beauty of the Victory,
the entireness of the Defeat, the Consequences that
followed upon it, the Quiet that it secured to us
here as well as that it procured there; the unhappy
State out of which it delivered us, when we were
beginning to languish by a Misfortune which I un∣willingly
mention, because nothing that is melan∣choly
ought to be mixed with the Joys of this Day.
All these things carry in them such matter of reflecti∣on,
that tho I must now croud them together, yet
they are capable of affording great variety of thoughts.
Our Spirits here were as much depressed, as those
of some unnatural English-men were exalted
in the prospect they had of the approaching Ruin
of their Country. Some were not ashamed to say,
that we needed fear nothing from the <HI>French,</HI> they
would not hurt us: and thus the terriblest of all the
Calamities that can befal our Nation, was set forth
by some as an innocent, or rather as a desirable thing,
that would prove a Deliverance and not an Invasi∣on.
While this Fermentation was working, even
in the very moment in which we wanted so mighty
a Support, came the happy News which put a new
face upon our Affairs. Some feared that in the ab∣sence
of our Sun we should have only had a faint
Moon-light to guide us, and that the gentle Hand
which then held the Rudder should have proved too
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
feeble for such rough Work, especially when the
first Essay was in a Storm, and that there was an E∣nemy
so powerful triumphing in view, and on our
Coasts, and so many ill Instruments at work within.
But to our Admiration, and to the eternal Praise of
Divine Providence, we found we had another Sun
in our Firmament, and that Spirit which till then
Gentleness and Modesty had shut in, now finding
that the Conjuncture required it, shewed it self
with so much firmness and so bright a lustre, that
we began to doubt whether one Soul did not ani∣mate
both, and give its Influences equally in both.
So much Skill in Government, tempered with so
much Softness, such a dexterity in Management,
such a constancy of Devotion, and so unwearied an
application to Business, are things so much out of all
common Roads, that we must look up to Heaven,
and acknowledge that this was of God, that has rai∣sed
up and conducted these our Deliverers and Pre∣servers.
He has also literally preserved our <HI>David</HI>
from the <HI>hurtful</HI> or the <HI>evil Sword,</HI> since we know
that the chief of our Enemies in the secret Correspon∣cies,
encouraged themselves, when the prospect of
their Affairs seemed melancholy and desperate, with
a reserve of Hope from the Negotiation of an Assas∣sinate
whom they had employed: but God has de∣livered
his Servant even from this <HI>evil Sword;</HI> and
to crown all the Blessings of this Year, he has now
<PB N="25" REF="16"/>
given Him the Hearts of his People, in so eminent
a manner, that the Q. <HI>Elizabeth</HI>'s Days seem to return
again upon us, in which the Purses of the Subject
were that happy Queen's never-failing Treasure,
who reckoned that their Money was never more
their own, and never better placed, nor better im∣ployed,
than when it was in the Queen's Hands.
She twice discharged the Subjects of the Taxes
they had given her for a War, when a Treaty of
Peace put an end to her Warlike Preparations. Such
a Justice to her self, and to her People, gave her so
sure a Title to their Wealth, that she was indeed the
Mistress of it all, and knew that she could call for
as much of it as the Publick Occasions required.
When we see the same Confidence in the Crown
returning in the Nation, which has been so long
and so fatally interrupted, we may then reckon that
our Kings are become truly great, and the Masters
of the whole Property of <HI>England,</HI> not by the strain∣ed
and false Pretensions of a devouring Preroga∣tive,
but by the surest and best-grounded Domini∣on,
which they have over the Hearts of their Peo∣ple,
which must infallibly draw every thing else
after it: For a Nation can deny nothing that it can
give, when it is both asked and laid out for their
own Defence and Preservation.</P>
<P>And now, DREAD SOVERAIGNS, suffer me, in the
<PB N="26" REF="17"/>
Name of God, to turn my self to You. It cannot
seem a small thing in your Eyes, that he has not on∣ly
raised you up to so sublime a Dignity, and set a
Crown of pure Gold on your Heads, but that he
has watched over your Persons, and blessed your
Councils, that you both do now shine with the Lu∣stre
becoming each Sex, the one with the Glory of
a Conqueror of Enemies, and the other with the
softer Rays of a Preserver of your People; that this
has given you the Hearts of your Subjects, and
made you the Terror and Dread of your Enemies,
of which they have made an ample confession, in
those barbarous Jollities upon the supposed Death
of You, <HI>Great Sir,</HI> every extravagant Demonstra∣tion
of that inhumane Joy, being a loud discovery
of what they apprehended from You. God has
drawn the Eyes of all the World upon You, who
hope that by You that tempestuous Sea, whose
Inundations have destroy'd so many Countries,
shall be shut up within Bounds, and that You shall
set Bars and Doors to it; and that by You God shall
say to it, <HI>Hitherto shalt thou come, and no further▪
and here shall thy proud Waves be staid.</HI> It is from
You that <HI>Europe</HI> expects Liberty and Peace, and the
Reformation a Recovery and a new lustre. By You
exiled Princes hope to be restored to their Rights,
and exiled Subjects to their Houses, Churches, and
Edicts. It is from Your Influence that our Elder
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
Brethren, the first begotten of the Reformation, or
rather the last Remnant of True and Primitive Chri∣stianity,
hope to be confirmed in the Settlement that
their Prince hath granted them. It is from Your
Counsels and Arms, that both Your Subjects and
Your Allies expect a happy and a secure Peace.
What more could have been hitherto done for the
gradual raising of your Glory than has been done?
You are now advanced to be as true Representatives
of God, as Mortals can be made, since from your
Power, your Justice, your Wisdom, and your
Goodness, so great a part of the World waits for
happy Influences, for great Undertakings, and for
glorious Successes, that shall be the Joy of the pre∣sent
Age, and the Wonder of the next.</P>
<P>But remember, O ye Kings, that to whom much is
given, of them much shall be required; and if You
expect from those that You imloy, degrees of Fide∣lity,
Zeal, and Application, proportioned to the Fa∣vours
and Trusts You bestow upon them; think a
little, I know You do a great deal, what Examples of
Piety and Vertue You ought to set your People,
and how much You ought to imploy your Autho∣rity
in promoting his Glory, who has covered You
with so much of his own Image. Ordinary degrees
of Zeal may be accepted from those of a lower
Form, but the highest pitch of it is the least Sacri∣fice
that You can offer. The discountenancing
<PB N="28" REF="18"/>
and driving from You all that prophane scorn of
Religion and Vertue, which has so deeply infected
the Nation, that strong Remedies must be used
before we are purged from it. The disgracing and
punishing such as are not ashamed of the most open
and crying Vices, the encouraging Vertue by all the
distinguishing Marks of your Favour to those who
pursue it. The Reforming your Court and your
People, and particularly that Body which of all o∣thers
should need your Care least, but I am afraid
does it but too much, I mean those who Minister
in Holy Things: these are the Returns that God ex∣pects
from you. I know all cannot be done at
once, and the leisure as well as the calm of Peace
will be necessary to bring this about. But as your
resolving on it inwardly before God, will be ac∣cepted
by him who knows the sincerity of your
Hearts, and does not oblige you to endanger the
Publick too much, by a violent and precipitated
Cure: So when it is once understood that You are
settled in these Noble Purposes, this will make the
execution of them easy to You. And to conclude,
I must crave leave to add one thing more; Your
Royal Grandfather, who had great Vertues in him∣self,
was perhaps too easy to Vice in others, and from
hence sprang in a great measure the ruin of his Af∣fairs;
for dissolute and depraved Men will be al∣ways
truer to their Vices, than to their Masters. I
<PB N="29" REF="18"/>
am not afraid of Your displeasure for this freedom,
it becomes the Place I am in, and the Station You
have raised me to; and I am sure the other parts of
this Discourse, which the Occasion has made ne∣cessary,
have been much more uneasy to You than
this is.</P>
<P>But <HI>David</HI>'s Joy was not so entire, when he com∣posed
this Psalm, that there was no need of pray∣ing
for a further and a more compleat Deliverance;
therefore he adds to this joyful Note a mournful
One; <HI>Rid me, and deliver me;</HI> he was yet encom∣passed
with Idolaters, and not only common Idola∣ters,
but Men whose Morals were as defiled as their
Worship; who were Treacherous and Insolent, to
whose Oaths and Treaties no regard was due, who
in the time that they made up their Treaties, were
intending to break them, which is imported in this,
that a <HI>Lie was in their right Hand;</HI> and whose Mouths
were full of Insolence, daring Pride, and haughty
Scorn: who how much soever they depressed their
God by their Idolatry, yet were swelled up in them∣selves
to all the Caresses of lofty Arrogance; they
perhaps loved to be celebrated by Statues, Titles, and
Inscriptions, which might render their Names
Immortal, tho they could not make their Persons
so: They might delight in all the Contrivances of
servile Flattery, to set them above all other Mortals,
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
and by hearing that oft said, they might fancy
themselves to be really so; they might suffer all the
Topicks of Flattery to be exhausted, and all the Me∣thods
of it to be imployed in adoring them with that
Tinsel. It might be understood that it was the surest
way of raising ones Fortune much more infallible
than any Merit whatsoever, to find out some new
Strains of Commendation; and when that once
appear'd, then Minds made for nobler Purposes
when pressed with a lowness of Fortune, would
stoop to the abjectest Things of Humane Nature
by turning their Wits to every Artifice that might
give a false Light and Lustre to counterfeit Ware.</P>
<P>But to compleat the Character of <HI>David</HI>'s Ene∣mies,
we are to consider them as breaking through
the sacredest Bonds, and protesting that they would
maintain them in the midst of the most publick Vio∣lations
of them, as if they had been equally voi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
both of Truth and Shame, giving and breaking
their Faith as oft as either their Interests or their Va∣nity
required it, violating the Ties of Nature, as wel
as breaking the bonds of humane Society, robbin<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
all their Neighbours, invading Orphans trusted t<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
their Care, and ruining whole Provinces after the<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
had purchased their Protection at the most extrava∣gant
Rates, sparing neither Age nor Sex, but destroy∣ing
both Cities and Countries, and hoping to com∣pensate
<PB N="31" REF="19"/>
for all the Crimes to which their Ambition
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd Fury could lead them, by a pretence of Zeal for
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eir Idol, and that way of Idolatry which best plea∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d
them; and yet sometimes with the basest sort
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Idolaters, who beat and whip their Idols when
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ey think they are not favourable enough to them,
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ey might even rob their own Idol, and profane eve∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> thing
that had relation to it, when they them∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lves
were not made the chief Idol, and served with
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> deepest Veneration: Such were many of the Ido∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ers
of the Heathen Nations. Perhaps the Cha∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ters
I have set them out in, may not all frequent∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
meet in the same Persons: yet tho many In∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ances
of every part of this Description might soon
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> found out, I will not interrupt the Chearfulness
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this Day, by setting before you Objects that
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>st give horrour: Nor will I seek for any of these
the present Scene of the World, nor examine any
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> our <HI>David</HI>'s Enemies, and see how well these
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>haracters may fit them. We serve Princes who
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e as little to hear their Enemies reproached, as
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>emselves commended; but it will be no hard
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ing, upon a general Survey of the present State
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Europe,</HI> to pronounce who seem to be born to
the Blessings, and who the Curses and Plagues
the Age.</P>
<P><PB N="32" REF="20"/>
But what or whosoever our Enemies may be,
both Kings and Subjects ought to join in their most
earnest Prayers to God, that we may be delivered
from all the Children of the strange God, who may
think that the offering up those that are of a diffe∣rent
Worship to that of their <HI>Baal,</HI> is a Sacrifice that
will atone for all the Rapine and Bloodshed, and
every others Immorality of which they may be guil∣ty.
It was no wonder that <HI>David</HI> by repeated Pray∣ers
desired to be delivered from such Enemies; for
we find this Petition, and this Character of them is
twice in this short Psalm, with this addition in the
<HI>7th</HI> verse, that imports their Strength and Num∣bers;
<HI>Send thy Hand from above, rid me and deliver
me out of great Waters, from the Hand of strange Chil∣dren.</HI>
We who are now the happiest Nation under
Heaven, want nothing to make us the most mise∣rable,
but to fall under the Power of those who
have no remnants either of Truth or Goodness
left in them.</P>
<P>But while our Kings are consulting, and our Par∣liaments
are assisting, while our Fleets and Ar∣mies
are a preparing, and our Allies are uniting;
while the joint Endeavours of so many within
and without the Kingdom, are all at work to pro∣cure
us an entire riddance and deliverance from the
Hands, the rough and Iron Hands of these our
<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
Enemies; There is one thing I am afraid is too ge∣nerally
neglected or forgotten, and that is, our pray∣ing
to God earnestly to rid and deliver us from those
false and cruel Men. We have been this last Sum∣mer
frequently brought together to fast and pray
for Success and Victory; God has heard our Pray∣ers,
and in that has given us all possible encourage∣ment
to continue our praying to him. We are
now, as to outward appearance, following the Me∣thod
that he has prescribed;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 50. 12.</NOTE> <HI>Call upon me in the day
of Trouble; I will hear thee, and thou shalt glorify me.</HI>
We have <HI>called,</HI> God has <HI>heard,</HI> and we are now
<HI>glorifying</HI> his Name, and rejoicing in the great Sal∣vation
that he hath wrought for us: And if we
desire a return of such happy Occasions, we must
in the mean while continue our most earnest Pray∣ers
to God; and when we are called on to it, we must
return to our monthly Fasts and Humiliations. It
did not derogate neither from <HI>David</HI>'s Courage nor
Conduct, that he acknowledged <HI>God was his For∣tress,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ver. 2.</NOTE>
his high Tower, his Shield and Deliverer, in whom
he trusted;</HI> who subdued his People under him;
and being full of the sense of his Glory, he reflect∣ed
on himself, and on all his People as nothing;
<HI>Lord, what is Man, that thou takest knowledg of him,
or the Son of Man, that thou makest account of him?
Man is like Vanity, his days are like a Shadow that pas∣seth
<PB N="34" REF="21"/>
away:</HI> Therefore it is that he prays earnestly,
<HI>Bow the Heavens, O Lord, and come down.</HI></P>
<P>Here is a Noble Pattern to excite and encourage
our Devotion, and we have all reason to conclude,
that the Blessings we now Celebrate, are in a great
measure owing to the Prayers of those happy Souls
that have been the Intercessors for the Nation, of
which it is not to be doubted but we have a great
many among us, for it is certain that we have never
seen a more solemn Observation, as to all outward
appearance, of such Days as was on those month∣ly
Returns; and tho many were very bare-faced in
their neglect of them, and others that should have
animated the Publick Zeal, were extream cold in
the observance of them, yet much earnestness and
fervour shewed it self in many places. We see
God has heard the Prayers of those who cried
mightily to him; and we have all reason to hope,
that he who has deliver'd us from so great a Cala∣mity
as then threatned us, will still hear and deli∣ver
us, if we continue still to call upon him.</P>
<P>But let the Murmurers and the Troublers of our
<HI>Israel</HI> say what they will, God hath wrought in the
midst of us a mighty Deliverance, and he will
perfect and stablish that which he hath wrought for
us, if we do not, by our Ingratitude and Rebel∣lions,
stop that course of Blessings that seems ready
<PB N="35" REF="21"/>
to flow in upon us, as soon as we are <HI>delivered from
our Enemies, and from the Hands of all that hate us.</HI>
Then we may hope to have the True Religion, and
the best Church in the World established among
us, and the Reformation by our Means secured
and maintained elsewhere: We may hope to see
this Nation become the Center of the Union and
Peace of <HI>Europe,</HI> that shall assert and warrant it a∣gainst
every bold or perfidious Invader: We may
hope to see this vvhole Island become one Church
and one Body, as it has one Head; and the
neighbouring Island set upon a Foundation liable to
no more Shakings nor Convulsions. We may
hope to see Law and Justice become the constant
and certain Measures of our Government; Chari∣ty
and mutual Forbearance, become the Strength
as vvell as the Ornament of our Church, and our
Church become the Pattern, as vvell as the Glory,
of the vvhole Reformation. And in conclusion,
vve may hope to see our Princes Heads still co∣vered
with fresh Lawrels, ever triumphing over
their Enemies, and yet never making themselves
Enemies to any, but to the Invaders and Enemies
of Mankind; giving Security to all about them,
and in a length of Days, and a stability of Peace,
giving a fulness of Wealth and Happiness to all
that are under them; an encrease of Trade, an
<PB N="36" REF="22"/>
improvement of Soil, and such an advancement
of the Prosperity of the Nation, as is expressed in
the followed words of the Psalm, <HI>That our Garners
may be full, affording all manner of Store; that our
Sheep may bring forth thousands, and ten thousands in
our Streets: That our Oxen may be strong to labour; that
there be no breaking in, nor going out; and that there
be no complaining in our Streets. Happy</HI> are the Prin∣ces,
and <HI>happy is that People that is in such a Case; yea,
and happy</HI> are the Princes, and <HI>happy is that People whose
God is the Lord.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

