<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The idol of the clovvnes, or, Insurrection of Wat the Tyler with his priests Baal and Straw together with his fellow kings of the commons against the English church, the king, the laws, nobility and royal family and gentry, in the fourth year of K. Richard the 2d, an. 1381.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Cleveland, John, 1613-1658.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A33434</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing C4673</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R5215</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12499886</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12499886</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">62665</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A33434)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62665)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 310:3)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The idol of the clovvnes, or, Insurrection of Wat the Tyler with his priests Baal and Straw together with his fellow kings of the commons against the English church, the king, the laws, nobility and royal family and gentry, in the fourth year of K. Richard the 2d, an. 1381.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Cleveland, John, 1613-1658.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[12], 154 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>[s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1654.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Attributed to John Cleveland. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Richard --  II, --  King of England, 1367-1400.</TERM><TERM>Tyler, Wat, d. 1381.</TERM><TERM>Tyler's Insurrection, 1381.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A33434">
<STC T="W">C4673</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12499886</BIBNO>
<VID>62665</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE IDOL OF THE CLOVVNES, <HI>OR,</HI> INSURRECTION OF <HI>WAT</HI> the <HI>TYLER,</HI> With his PRIESTS <HI>BAAL</HI> and <HI>STRAW;</HI> Together with His fellow Kings of the Commons, against the English Church, the King, the Laws, Nobility, and Royal Family and Gentry, in the fourth year of K. <HI>Richard</HI> the 2d. <HI>An.</HI> 1381.</P>
<P><HI>In rebus humanis saecula ac personae inter<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>unt, causae &amp; eventa eadem recurr<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> Nulla tyrannis vel quieta est vel di<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/></HI></P>
<P><HI>London</HI> Printed in the Year <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="page cropped" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD><HI>Iohn</HI> of Lydgate, <HI>lib.</HI> 4.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>ANd semblably to put it at a prefe,</L>
<L>And execute it by clere experience,</L>
<L>One the most contrarious mischiefe</L>
<L>Found in this earth by notable evidence,</L>
<L>Is onely this by Fortunate violence</L>
<L>When that wretches thurlish of nature</L>
<L>The estate of Princes unwarey doth recure.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>A Crown of Gold is nothing according,</L>
<L>For to be set upon a knaves heed</L>
<L>A Foltish clerk for to weare a King,</L>
<L>Accordeth nat, who that can take hede,</L>
<L>And in this werld there is no greater drede</L>
<L>Then power give (if it be well sought)</L>
<L>Unto such one that first rose up of nought.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There is no manner just convenience</L>
<L>A royal Carbuncle, Ruby, or Garnet,</L>
<L>Nor a chast Emeraud of virtues exelence,</L>
<L>Nor Inde Saphirs in Copper to be set,</L>
<L>Their Kind'ly power in foule metal is let,</L>
<L>And so the State of politike puysance</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> ever lost where knaves have Governance▪</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="3"/>
<L>For a time they may well up ascend,</L>
<L>Like windy smokes their fumes sprede,</L>
<L>A crowned asse plainly to comprehend,</L>
<L>Uoyde of discretion is more for to drede</L>
<L>Then is a Lyon for that one indede;</L>
<L>Of his nature is mighty and royall,</L>
<L>Uoyde of discretion that other beastiall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The gentle nature of a strong Lyon,</L>
<L>To prostrate people of kynde is merciable,</L>
<L>For unto all that fall afore him doun,</L>
<L>His royall puisaunce cannot be vengeable:</L>
<L>But churlish Wolves by rigour untreatable,</L>
<L>And follyshe asses eke of bestialty</L>
<L>Fayling reason brayde ever on cruelty.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>None is so proude as he that can no good,</L>
<L>The lender heed the more presumption,</L>
<L>Most cruelte and bengeance in lowe blode</L>
<L>UUith malapertnesse and indiscretion:</L>
<L>Of Churle and Gentle make this division</L>
<L>Of outhor of them I dare right well report</L>
<L>Fro thens thei came, thereto the wyl resorte.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To the Reader.</HEAD>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>He beginnings of the Se∣cond</HI> Richard's <HI>reign are turmoiled with a Rebelli∣on, which shoke his Throne and Empire: A Rebelli∣on, not more against Reli∣gion and Order, than Nature and Humanity too; A Rebellion never to be believed, but in the Age it was acted in, and our owne, in which we finde how terrible the overflowes of the common people (ever delighted in the ca∣lamities of others) untyed, and hurryed on by their own wills, and beastly fury must prove; though</HI> Masanello <HI>is short of</HI> Tyler, <HI>yet if we compare that Fisherman with our Hinde, the Neapolitan Mechanicks and our Clownes, we shall not finde them much unlike, not in their sudden flourish and prosperity, not in the mischiefs they did, and the barbarous savage rudenesse in the doing them:</HI> Masanello <HI>made a shew of foolish unseasonable Piety to
<PB REF="4"/>
the Prince and Archbishop, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> not his part, which made him the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> im∣perfect Rebell, the worse Polititian; how∣ever, he might seem the better man; but these too might be but counterfeit reverences; this might be his disguise, and h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> might have come up to more, according to the new lights which we may imagine were breaking in. The continuance and mis-rule of these Wor∣thies were much of a length; in a few dayes the brands themselves had fired, broke upon their own heads, they were pluck'd up before their full growth, like airy flitting clouds, they were blown over ere they could pour down the storm they were big with. The colours of thes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> tumults were fair, and taking, such as their Architects</HI> B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l <HI>and</HI> Straw, <HI>the Priests had layd, such as the Masters of these School<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s have delivered in all ages. The Weal pub∣lick, the liberty of the free-born people (pil∣led, and fleyed by the Kings taxes, and the cruell oppression of the Gentry▪) Iustice, Re∣formation, or Regulation of Fundamentall Laws long subverted (considerable nam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s if we may believe them) set them on. The King, his Glory, his Honour, his Safety, The King and the Commons are cryed up. But the King was compassed with Traitours and Malignants, they will have it so, and it is
<PB REF="4"/>
their care to re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ove the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t and branch; they will fire the house to cleanse it; much other businesse they had, much was amisse, much to be reformed, but in the first sall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y all is not noysed; what was not handsome, what might give a fuller fright was lapped up in folds, to be discovered as they had thri∣ven, to be swallowed, but gilded with a Victory: We know crimes carried in a happy streams of luck, lose their names in it, are beautifull, and must be thought so: The Ordale of the Sword justified</HI> Caesar, <HI>and condemned</HI> Pompey, <HI>not his cause,</HI> Adversae res etiam bonos detractant <HI>(sayes</HI> Salust.) <HI>Good men, if they miscarry, doe not onely lose themselves but their integrity, their just∣nesse, their honesty, they are what the Conque∣rour pleases, and the silly multitude, which e∣ver admires the glitter of prosperity, will hate them. Providence preserved the English Nation from this blow. The Lawrel of suc∣cess crowned not the Rebels, they crumble to their first dust again, are ruined by their own weight and confusion. They had ris<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n lik<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> those Sons of the Dragons teeth, in tempests, without policy or advice. Their leaders were meerly fantastical, but goblins and shadows, men willing to embr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>yl, and daring, whose courage was better then their cause; and
<PB REF="5"/>
who to advance the design would not boggle at a peece of Honesty, an Oath, a Protestati∣on, on Covenant, a Verse of</HI> St. Paul, <HI>or</HI> St. Peter, <HI>a Case of Conscience in the way of brave, bold, manly spirits, yet without heads or wits to manage the great work, which in so vast a body suddainly composed like the spawns of</HI> Nile, <HI>of slime and dirt, of so diffe∣rent parts, so unequall members, was fatall to the whole.</HI> Tyler <HI>had no brains, he could not plot, not contrive; and those about him were as heavy, as very Asses as himself: He is said to be</HI> a crafty fellow, and of an excel∣lent wit, but wanting grace; <HI>yet crafty e∣nough he was not for the great and dangerous enterprise:</HI> a Marius <HI>(however impious (for such he must be)</HI> p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce pessimus, <HI>fitter to re∣move things, to overturn, overturns, than for peace (but as</HI> Plutarch <HI>of him) subtill, faith∣less<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, one who could overdo all men in dissem∣bling, in hypocrisie, practised in all the arts <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>f lying (and some of these good slights</HI> Tyler <HI>wanted not) one who had sense and judgement to carry things on as well as desperate confi∣dence to undertake had become this part in∣comparably, had gone through with it, how easily under such a Captain (if we look upon the weaknesse of the opposition, and the villai∣nous baseness of the Gentry) had the frame of
<PB REF="5"/>
the ancient building been rased, the Mod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> must have held.</HI> Richard <HI>(whose endeavours of defence or loyalty alone should have been killing) had not fallen by the sword of</HI> Lanca∣ster, <HI>he had found his grave on</HI> Tower-hill, <HI>or</HI> Smithfield, <HI>where the faithfull lieges of his Crown were torn in pieces by these Cani∣bals. The reverence due to the annointed heads of Kings began to fall away, and naked Majesty could not guard where Innocency could not: But</HI> Tyler <HI>blinded with his owne fatall pride, throws himself foolishly upon the Kings sword, and by his over-muoh hast pre∣serves him whom he had vowed to destroy. The Heathens make it a mark of the Divinity of of their Gods, that they bestowed benefits upon mortal men, and took nothing from them. The Clownes of the Idoll upon this rule were not very heavenly, they were the meeke ones of those times, the onely inheritours of right, the kingdom was made a prey by them, it was cantoned out to erect new Principalities for the Mock-kings of the Commons; so their Chiefs or Captains would be called. Here, though the title of the Rebellion spoke fair, was sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>wn somewhat of ambition, and no little of injust private interest, no little of self-seeking which the good of the people (in pretence onely) was to give way to, and no wonder for the good
<PB REF="6"/>
of the people properly, was meeraly to be in∣tended of themselvs: and no where but a∣mongst those was the Commonwealth. Had these Thistles, these Brambles flourished, the whole Wood of noble Trees had perished: If the violent casting other men out of their possessions, firing their houses, cutting off their Heads, violating of all Rights, be thought Gods blessing, any evidence of his owning the Cause, these Thieves and Murderers were well bles∣sed, and sufficiently owned. Such was then tho face of things, estates were dangerous, every Rich man was an enemy, mens lives were taken away without either offence or try∣all, their reign was but a continuation of hor∣rible injuries; the Lawes were not onely si∣lent, but dead: The Idolls fury was a Law, and Faith, and Loyaltie, and Obedience to law∣full power, were damnable: Servants had the rule over Princes,</HI> England <HI>was near a slave∣ry, the most unworthy of free and ingenious spirits of any.</HI></P>
<P><HI>What I relate here (to speak something of the Story) I collect out of Sir</HI> John Froissart, <HI>a French-man, living in the times of King</HI> EDVVARD <HI>the third, and his Grandchild, King</HI> RICHARD, <HI>who had seen</HI> England <HI>in both the reigns, was known and e∣steemed in the Court, and came last over after
<PB REF="6"/>
these Tumults were appeased: and out of</HI> Thomas <HI>of</HI> Walsingham, <HI>a</HI> Monk <HI>of St.</HI> Al∣banes <HI>in</HI> Henry <HI>the sixth</HI>'s <HI>dayes; who (sayes</HI> Bale <HI>in his centuries of him) writes many the most choice passages of affairs and actions, such as no other hath met with. In the main, and to the substance of things, I have made no ad∣ditions, no alterations, I have faithfully fol∣lowed my Authors, who are not so historically exact as I could wish, nor could I much better what did not please me in their order. No man (saies</HI> Walsingham) <HI>can recite fully the mischiefs, murders, sacriledge, and cruelty of</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Hypod. <HI>Neust.</HI></NOTE> <HI>these Actors; he excuses his digesting them upon the confusion of the combustions flaming in such varietie of places, and in the same time.</HI> Tyler, Litster, <HI>and those of</HI> Hartfordshire <HI>take up most part of the discourse;</HI> Westbrome <HI>is brought in by the halves; the lesser Snakes are onely named in the Chronicle: What had been more, had not been to any purpose: Those were but types of</HI> Tyler <HI>the Idoll, and acted nothing but according to the Original, accor∣ding to his great example, they were Wolves alike, and he that reads one knowes all.</HI> Tho∣mas <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Par. Wals. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI> &amp;c. <HI>Per</HI> Thomae Sanguiuem <HI>salva nos Breviar. fest. S.</HI> Tho. Cant. Ri∣shang Polyd. <HI>D'Avilla Iaques Clem.</HI> the Paricide of <HI>Hen.</HI> 3. of <HI>France</HI> was prayed for as a Saint.</NOTE> <HI>of</HI> Becket, Simon <HI>of</HI> Montfort; <HI>the
<PB REF="7"/>
English Cataline,</HI> Thomas <HI>of</HI> Lancaster, <HI>Re∣bels and Traitors of the former years are Ca∣nonised by the Monks (generally the enemies of their Kings) miracles make their Tombes illustrious, and their Memories sacred. The Idol and his Incendiaries are abho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed every where, every History detests them, while Faith, Civility, Honesty and Piety shall be left in the world, the enemies of all these must neither be beloved nor pitied.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="7"/>
<HEAD>THE IDOL OF THE CLOWNES.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>He Reigne of King <HI>Rich∣ard</HI> the second, was but a throw of State for so many yeares, a Feaver to whose distempers all pieces of the home Do∣minions contributed by fits (<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Guinue.</NOTE> the forrain part onely continuing faithfull) in the fourth yeare of his reigne, and fifteenth of his Age, the dregs and off scum of the Commons unite into bodies in severall parts of the Kingdome, and forme a Re∣bellion (called the Rebellion of the <HI>Clownes)</HI> which lead the rest, and shewed the way of disobedience first. Of which may truly be said (Though amongst o∣ther
<PB N="2" REF="8"/>
causes we may attribute it to the in∣disposition and unseasonablenesse of the age, that the fruits of it did not take) it was strongly begun, and had not Provi∣dence heldback the hand, the blow had fallen, the Government had broke into shivers then. The young King at this time had few besides <HI>Thomas</HI> of <HI>Woodstock</HI> his Unkle, Earle of <HI>Buckingham,</HI> and after Duke of <HI>Glocester,</HI> but the servants of his house in ordinary about him, the Lord <HI>Edmund</HI> of <HI>Langly</HI> Earle of <HI>Cambridge,</HI> after Duke of <HI>Yorke,</HI> with the Lords <HI>Beauchamp, Botereaux,</HI> Sir <HI>Matthew Gourny</HI> with others of the Nobility, and Gentry had set saile for <HI>Portugall,</HI> the Duke <HI>Iohn</HI> of <HI>Lancaster,</HI> another of his Unkles was in <HI>Scotland</HI> treating a peace, when this commotion brake out. Though no cause can be given for Seditions, those, who designe publick troubles, can never want pretences; <HI>Polidore</HI> (as much out in this story as any) gives this reason for this. The Polle money sayes he (imposed by <HI>Parliament)</HI> a groat sterling upon every head was intollerable. It was justly im∣posed, and so by some to whom Law and Custome of <HI>England</HI> were intollerable not to be indured, but we shall find in the ty∣ranny breaking in, not onely fifth and
<PB N="3" REF="8"/>
tentieth parts and loanes forced out of feare of plunder and death, but subsidies in Troops and Regiments, by fifties, (more than Sequeltrations and Compositions) not under foot, low sales, for what had these Rascalls to give, but downright Robbery and violent usurpation of Estates.</P>
<P>Thus would <HI>Polidore</HI> have it in defence of his Priests, who blew the fire, and thrust the silly rout into the midst of it. He takes it ill that <HI>Baal (valle</HI> he calls him) should be supposed by I know not what slaterers of the Nobles to have filled these sailes, to have let these windes out of their Caverns.</P>
<P>In the fourth yeare of this King (sayes the Monk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> there was a grievous Tax ex∣acted in <HI>Parllament,</HI> after cause of great trouble, every Religious paid half a Mark, every Secular Priest as much, every Lay∣man or Woman 12d. This might discon∣tent the people, but who prepared the Mutineers for such dangerous impressions? who fell in with them after and pushed them forward will be soon found. <HI>Frois<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> sart</HI> complaines of the servitude of the villanes or Bond-men, (now Names worne out) a miserable sort of drudges frequent∣lh knowne here in the <HI>Saxon</HI> times: exclu∣ded from any right of propriety, sold, and
<PB N="4" REF="9"/>
passed away with the Mannour or Lands to which they belonged, bound to til the Lords ground, cut downe, and carry in his Corne, cleanse his Ditches, cover his Halle, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> These <HI>Froissart</HI> make the first stirrers in the Insurrection, these he makes look back to the beginning of men and things to talk of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> freedome, of the liberties of the Creature, above Ordinances, that only Treason against the Lords could for∣feit L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>berty, which was the case of <HI>Lucifer,</HI> and could not be made theirs, who were neither Angels nor spirits, but men of the same shape, extraction, and Soules with those who proudly would be thought their Lords, which (say they) was an height too much, and deserved levelling, must not be endured hereafter, equality was the way of peace and love. But can clouds fire in thunder and lightning, can earth quakes teare the entrailes of expi∣ring Kingdomes, without a <HI>Muncer,</HI> or a <HI>Wiggington,</HI> a <HI>Garnet,</HI> or an <HI>Hall</HI> in the mine?</P>
<P>If the Church and Government must be blowne up, it is fit a sanctified hand should (cast the Balles) a man (according to the pure dialect) <HI>of immediate calling,</HI> who has had the <HI>Seale</HI> of it, of <HI>wonderfull zeale, of resolute dealings, the Lords Messeng<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>▪ ex∣traordinarily
<PB N="5" REF="9"/>
gifted and exercised,</HI> is onely fit to advance <HI>Gods matters,</HI> the <HI>Holy caus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> and action, and a Renegado from his or∣ders: an Apostate Church-man will best be∣come this person, a man with whom no∣thing else is sacred but his owne ambition, his innovation, and the propagation of his Schisme. One <HI>Baal</HI> the most sottish and most unworthy, but most facti∣ous of the Clergy is stirred up by the Devill (who, if rebellion be as the sinne of Witchcraft, is the Father of both) to be the Antichrist of this Reign, to blaspheme and cry down <HI>God</HI> and <HI>Cesar</HI> his anoynted, the Rights of <HI>God</HI> and <HI>Cesar;</HI> and who, if he knew any thing, was certainly the very Atheist of that age, <HI>Of these imaginations</HI> (so <HI>Froissert</HI> of those before) <HI>was a foolish Priest in the County of</HI> Kent <HI>called</HI> John Wall (for <HI>Baal)</HI> and to make it plain th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> he was the Father of the uproare, he had been (sayes this Knight) three times in the Archbishops prison <HI>(a persecuted Saint)</HI> for these Opinions, but delivered by him, his Conscience was scrupulous of procee∣ding farther, which this Historian con∣demnes him for: we shall hereafter see the Archbishop in <HI>Iohn</HI>'s hands, who shall come short of this mercy. <HI>Iohn</HI> had prea∣ched (if it be not impious to use the word
<PB N="6" REF="10"/>
here) twenty yeares, and more, ever bab∣ling those things which he fancied would be gracious to the multitude; He haunted by-places, the Cloysters of the Cathedrall; when the Church was shut against him, the Streetes and Fields were holy ground; There this excommunicated Apostate laid his Nets. His discourses to the people were partly invectives against Tithes (which he allowed not where the Parishioner was of better life and smaller estate than the Parson, whose estate at this rate must be small enough) against Bishops, and the Clergy, Nobility, and Gentry; Then he had his quarrells to the Government, his Doctrine struck at propriety, and order, the World was impaired with Diseases, which must be the more for their age, the crisis would be dangerous, and there could be no health, no soundnesse hoped for, till Names, Estates, and things were common. His advise was to let the King know the resolutions of the new Common-wealths∣men, to tell him where the <HI>Supreme power</HI> lies, whose Trustee he was, that another course must be taken, and if he would not joyne with them, other remedies thought of: the third time he was imprisoned, he had his Revelations, his <HI>Enlightnings,</HI> was <NOTE PLACE="marg">Froiss.</NOTE> full of divine raptures, he foretold his de∣liverance
<PB N="7" REF="10"/>
by 20000. men, which happened in the following tumults, when his Disci∣ples made so many Gaole-deliveries. This, knowing what numbers he had seduced and abused, he might presume upon pro∣bable conjecture. He was no sooner loose, but he incites and stirs up the unruly <HI>Clowns</HI> to all the mischiefs possible.</P>
<P>He tells them they were pious and ne∣cessary excesses, and that the Law of Na∣ture, which allowes all acts for our owne preservation, would justifie them: that a mad Father, who seeks to rob and destroy his off-spring, might be resisted, his thrusts might be put by, the Son might binde his hands, and if there were no other way to escape his furious violence kill him in his owne defence. The safety of the people is the Supreme law. If the Prince persisting (after faire warning) <HI>to make himselfe a shield and defence</HI> to wicked instruments of <HI>mischiefs, Malignants and enemies</HI> of the Commons, <HI>securing them from the justice of the Commons, endanger himself and his King∣dome,</HI> he may thank himselfe; <HI>We</HI> (sayes he) <HI>are willing to hazard our selves</HI> (good men) <HI>to preserve both; we will never give any impediment, or neglect any proper means of curing the distempers of the Kingdoms, and of closing the dangerous breaches</HI> (made
<PB N="8" REF="11"/>
by themselves) <HI>according to the trust which lies upon us.</HI> At <HI>Black<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>heath,</HI> where an as∣sembly of 200000 men made their Randez∣vouze, after some time sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt <HI>in seeking God,</HI> he baits in Rime,
<Q><L><HI>UUahn Adam dalf and Eve span,</HI></L>
<L><HI>UUho was than a Gentleman?</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Walsingh.</NOTE></L></Q>
Was his levelling lend Text: hence it was to be consequent, that as nature, and the Cr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tion made no distinction, no more ought Lawes to make or suffer any; that servitude is the daughter of unjust oppres∣sion, introduced by wicked men against Gods Will. That if it had pleased him to have created slaves, in the beginning he would have chosen, and marked out who should have been the Lord, who the Vas∣sall; he askes where the <HI>word</HI> allowes these sweet things called Lords, verily <HI>Knaves in Purple,</HI> Sons of <HI>Caine,</HI> of <HI>Nim∣rod,</HI> of <HI>Esau,</HI> of <HI>Ishmael,</HI> fat by the blood and sweat of the poore innnocent Plebei∣ans, honourable in nothing but the out∣side, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd noble onely in riots and adulte∣ries, as cruell, as ravenous, as killing (and as barbarously) as the Beares, the Lyons, the Tigers of their escutcheons, the Dragons of their bearing; he askes why <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>he limb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>
<PB N="9" REF="11"/>
Knights, and Franklins, who are onely better combed, can kisse the hand and lowt with more grace, must <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t the C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣pons, which the sturdy brave Commons must starve themselves to cramme: nothing could be good which was great, nothing but <HI>Independency</HI> was divine.</P>
<P>He bids them consider, now was the time appointed them by God to cast off the yoake, that if they would not be wan∣ting to themselves, they should assert their <NOTE PLACE="marg">Deposito scrvitu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>is jugo, liber∣tate, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> long looked for liberty, and like good Husbandmen, who love their field, pluck up the weedes which over run it (which <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals. more boni patris. samil. exce∣lentis agri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> suum.</NOTE> signified <HI>rooting out the wicked, and those who carried the mark of the Beast)</HI> He points them out the heads devoted, destined for slaughter. <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Regni Majores.</NOTE> The House of Lords, the Peers (a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> yet they speak no higher) whom he would have <HI>brought to Repentance.</HI> Then the Lawyers, Justices, Judges, Jury-men, <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Quoscun∣que nocivos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> communita∣ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> de terra sua tolle. reut.</NOTE> all the enemies of the commonalty were to be swept from the Earth, there could not else (so he concludes) be any peace or security for the future, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Si subla∣tis Majori∣bus aequa li∣bertas, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> lopping off the Heads of those which were too tall, which over-topped too much, equall Nobility, equall Liberty, Dignity and Power (this was his old Doctrine) were the onely an∣tidotes, without which the poysoned
<PB N="10" REF="12"/>
Common-wealth must perish. Whosoe∣ver loved not the <HI>Cause</HI> was a Reprobate, hatefull to God, and damned Body and Soule. <HI>Iohn</HI> concludes with an exhortati∣on, that <HI>in order to the security and preser∣vation of Religion and Liberty of the Subject, they will never consent to the laying downe of armes, so long as the evill Councellors and Prelates arming, or in open warre shall by force of armes be protected against the justice of the Commons.</HI> John <HI>addes, of long time there hath beene, and now is, a traiterous plo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> for the subversion</HI> of us and <HI>the liberty of the Subject.</HI></P>
<P>No wonder, when <HI>Peter</HI> the Hermits Goose was believed to be the Holy Ghost, <NOTE PLACE="marg">In the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for holy land.</NOTE> that <HI>Iohn,</HI> amongst as very Ninnyhammers, could strike up for a Prophet.</P>
<P>The base crew prick up their Eares, and wonder at the new truths, which their Pastor <HI>heldforth,</HI> they applaud him, he is <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Ut accla∣marer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> cum Archiepis∣copum.</NOTE> Archbishop elect, and Chancelour, the true Archb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>shop must be called a Traitour, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Commu∣nium &amp; regni pro∣ditorem.</NOTE> a Traitour of the Commons and the Realm, to make him roome, is voted so, to be ap∣prehended wheresoever he could be found in <HI>England,</HI> and his Head to be cut off. Here was a new Treason, and a new way of triall and sentence. But though <HI>Baal</HI> had more of the <HI>Spirit,</HI> there were other
<PB N="11" REF="12"/>
adventurers not to be robbed of their ho∣nours, other <HI>Worthies, precious men, called to doe the Worke of the Lord;</HI> Who put to their hands, and brought Trowels and Mor∣ter toward the raising this <HI>Babel. Iack-Straw,</HI> another Priest full of life and vigor, the Confessour, and Bosom-chap∣lein of <HI>Tyler,</HI> more inward with him, his speciall Councellour, acquainted with all his plots, in the contrivance of which he had a great part, bestowed his paines upon the <HI>Cause,</HI> and for action next <HI>Tyler</HI> the Idoll carryed the name, which may be one cause why <HI>Polydore</HI> kills him in <HI>Tylers</HI> stead, with the Mayors Sword, the most eminent sticklers of the Laity, of the pro∣phane stie, where <HI>Wat</HI> the <HI>Tyler,</HI> a <HI>Tyler</HI> by Trade, not by Name, his Name was <HI>Helier (an ungracious Patron,</HI> as <HI>Fro∣issart)</HI> was <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Wals.</HI> Rex ribal∣dorum, Ido∣lum rusti∣corum.</NOTE> <HI>King of the Ribauldes, the Idoll of the Kentish Clownes. Iohn Kirkby, Alan Treder, Thomas Scot,</HI> and <HI>Ralph Rugge,</HI> a <HI>Magnifico,</HI> who gave freely away amongst his fellow Scoundrels the spoiles of his Conquests, were princes of the separation of the Tribes in <HI>Kent</HI> and <HI>Essex. Robert Westbrome (Wraw</HI> his Chaplaine refusing to set <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> Crowne upon Crowne, and con∣tented to be the Arch priest of the Pro∣vince) was King of <HI>Suffolke,</HI> and the parts
<PB N="12" REF="13"/>
adjacent. St. <HI>Edmunds-bury,</HI> once the Pa∣lace of the East Angle Kings, and <HI>Milden∣halle,</HI> were the seats of his Soveraignty. <HI>Iohn Litster</HI> a Tanner usurps the Name and power of a King at <HI>Northwalsham</HI> in <HI>Norsolk;</HI> I may say the power and more, never was any English King so absolute, nor can any just and legall Principality be so large, and Arbitrary, <HI>Law of the Land</HI> with which the old Englishman was free enough, and contented, was here to be thrown out of dores. The Heptarchy of the <HI>Saxons</HI> seemed to revive againe, but prodigiously, the blaz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of these Comets must have been fatall to the Nation; to keep an order in the History of these Ruf∣fians, who abhorred it, I will give the Van to the Idoll of the <HI>Clowns,</HI> it is due to him, he is the first who lifts up his Head in the confusion among the <HI>Brethren,</HI> and de∣serves the first chaire, He was the Dragon, and no question in the Conclusion, had swallowed up or clipped the rest, <HI>Litster, Westbrome,</HI> and the others merited highly, but they must have been taken down <HI>some pins, Tyler</HI> must have elbow-roome, he must have been Lord Paramount, and one such Comet would have been more than e∣nough for one Horizon. Besides <HI>Kent</HI> and <HI>Essex,</HI> were the puddle, the <HI>Lerna</HI>
<PB N="13" REF="13"/>
which bred this <HI>Hydra</HI> with the many Heads which poysoned most of the Coun∣ties, and in the conjunction of these two Provinces, <HI>Tyler</HI> the Idoll swayed all: and here I must observe this, that however <HI>Walsingham</HI> hatches the cause in <HI>Essex,</HI> yet his owne relations of <HI>Baal</HI> and the Letters and Sermons of this seducing Prophe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> bring this into question, and by him i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>Kent</HI> be not the Mother, yet are the Trea∣sons of her and <HI>Essex,</HI> Sister-twint of the same birth, <HI>Essex</HI> onely started first.</P>
<P>The fire kindled from a small sparke, The <HI>Clownes</HI> of two Village<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> not named in the <HI>Chronicles</HI> contrive the Conspiracy there; They send Warrants to the smaller Townes about, and rather command than intreat, all men of what age soever with∣out any stay or deliberation to repaire to a Rendezvouze set downe. The conclusion was terrible; It threatned plundering of Goods, Burning, P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ucking downe Houses, and cutting off the heads of those who disobey the <HI>present Power.</HI></P>
<P>The summoned Villages are frighted into Obedience, which is <HI>to rebell;</HI> They leave their Ploughs, their Fields, their Wives and Farmes, and in their first rising no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>esse than 5000 of the sink of the peo∣ple meet ill armed, some with Staves, some
<PB N="14" REF="14"/>
with rusty Swords, some with Bowes and Featherlesse Arrowes, few knowing any cause of their assembling, gazing upon one another, and not finding any enemie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> their own peace and good but themselves. Not one of a thousand was provided like a Souldier, but their number supplyed all things, they were highly conceited of themselves, and believed they were in∣vincible, not to be resisted. To confirme their steps, <HI>Baal</HI> (watching to catch, who had long waited for such an opportunity of imbroiling) drives them head-long forward, he writes to them his Letters ex∣hortatory (where to consecrate the enter∣prise, Gods name is brought in; He is made to owne the <HI>Cause)</HI> composed of a jargon, a canting gibridge, sit for the de∣signe (to abuse and cheat the innocent peasant, who cannot pry into things, can∣not look farther than the bait) fuller of Ridles than sense, one of them found in the sleeve of one of these wretched men condemned, and under the Gallowes was this.</P>
<P>John Schep, <HI>sometimes St.</HI> Mary <HI>Priest in</HI> Yorkn, <HI>and now of</HI> Colchester <HI>greeteth well</HI> John <HI>namelesse, and</HI> John <HI>the Miller, and</HI> John Carter, <HI>and biddeth them that they beware of</HI> guile in Borough (which <HI>Stow</HI>
<PB N="15" REF="14"/>
by a notable mistake calls <HI>Gillinborough) and stand together in Gods Name, and bid∣deth</HI> Pierse <HI>Plowman goe to his w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rk, and chastice</HI> Hob <HI>the robber, and take with you</HI> John Trewman, <HI>and all his fellowes and no moe,</HI> John <HI>the Miller hath yground smal, smal, smal, The Kings Sonne of Heaven shall pay for all. Beware or ye be woe, Know your friend from your foe. Have ynough and say hoe. And doe well and better, and fle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> sinne and seek peace, and hold therein; And so biddeth</HI> John Trewman <HI>and all his fellows.</HI> A List of Sanctity does well in these Cases, but his <HI>seeking of Peace, chastising the Rob∣ber, and fleeing of Sinne,</HI> I must leave a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> mysticall. This shewes the industry, care∣fulnesse, and vigilancy of the Prophet in his preparations, and his willingnesse to hurt. He disperseth other Letters of this kinde, in one, <HI>he chargeth all men in the Name of the</HI> Trinity, &amp;c. <HI>to stand Man∣like together, and help</HI> Truth (now we have <HI>Truth</HI> to our peace) <HI>and</HI> Truth <HI>shall help them,</HI> in his ragges of Verses (for a <HI>Rimer</HI> he would be) he is as earnest for <HI>Truth.</HI> They begin,
<Q><PB N="16" REF="15"/>
<L>Iack Crewman doth you to understoud</L>
<L>That falsenes, &amp; guyle hath reigned too long,</L>
<L>And Truth hath been set under a Lock,</L>
<L>And falsenes reigneth in every Flock;</L>
<L>No Man may come truth to</L>
<L>But he must sing fi <HI>dedero.</HI></L></Q></P>
<P>Many <HI>Remonstrances</HI> and <HI>Declarations</HI> flew abroad from him. The <HI>Kentishmen,</HI> seasoned by this Priest or Prophet of the Idol, are easily tempted by the <HI>Essex∣ians</HI> to associate in the undertakings, and share in the honour of gaining <HI>Liberty, pretious Liberty</HI> for the people, and taking away the evill customes of the Kingdom; which is the glorious Title of the tumult. This was no more (sayes the Monke) than the <HI>Kentishmen</HI> had long wished for. They are quickly ready, and by the Arts used by those of <HI>Essex</HI> put all the Countrey into a combustion. That they may not appeare <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> with too much horror at the first sight, they would seem to pretend to an out-side Piety, <HI>they account</HI> (so they tell the <HI>King∣dome and the world) the professing of any thing in the sight of God, the strongest obliga∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ion that any Christian, and the most solemne publick faith, that any such state, as a</HI> Com∣mon-wealth
<PB N="17" REF="15"/>
<HI>can give, In all humility and reverence they contrive a sacred vow and Covenant.</HI></P>
<P>They fasten the knot of their <HI>holy League</HI> with <HI>National Covenants</HI> and <HI>Oaths,</HI> which themselves will first break (than which there can be no stronger tie, Religi∣on consists in Faith, he who loses hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Faith hath lost himselfe) Oaths contrary to their sworne Allegiance, and former Oathes, which is a most absurd impiety, here God must be called upon to help<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, and witnesse the perfidiousnesse, oathe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> use to end—<HI>so helpe me God</HI>—he who per∣formes not his oath, directly and plainly, renounces God, and all that is sacred and Divine, to sweare to day against what we were sworne to yesterday, must be strange amongst Christians, these impieties being once allowed, there can be neither peace, society, nor government amongst Men safe and unindangered. The wayes leading to <HI>Canterbury</HI> are beset, the Pilgrimes swarming thither (according to the su∣perstition of those Ages) are seized, and forced to sweare with these <HI>extraordinary Workers.</HI> To keep faith to King <HI>Richard (whose most faithfull Servants, most humble and loyall Subjects, they professe themselves to be)</HI> and the <HI>Commons according to their
<PB N="18" REF="16"/>
power and vocation.</HI> To accept no King called <HI>Iohn</HI> (a vanity throwne in for Duke <HI>Iohn</HI> of <HI>Lancasters</HI> sake the Kings Uncle, and neglected by the <HI>Norfolke</HI> reformers, who advanced King <HI>Iohn Litstere</HI> to the Soveraignty) To be ready upon summons to assist the <HI>Commons</HI> (the great wheele of the <HI>New State,</HI> for whom this Oath was given, and to be principally respected by it.) To induce their friends and allies to hold with them, and to allow no Tax but the fifteenth (which say they falsly was the onely Tax their forefathers ever heard of, or submitted, to.) How sacred in all the parts this <HI>Oath</HI> will be with them (which never was to be intended more than temporary) will soone be discovered, diversity of words cannot change the na∣ture of things. Their first march is to <HI>Can∣terbury,</HI> where they visit <HI>Thomas</HI> of <HI>Can∣terbury,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Froiss.</NOTE> who lived and dyed a Rebell to his Prince, and to use the words of <HI>Ro∣gerius</HI> a <HI>Norman,</HI> in <HI>Caesarius</HI> the Monke <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>esar Dial. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 8, c. 69.</NOTE> <HI>deserved death, and damnation for this Contumacy against his King (the Minister of God,</HI> a fit Saint for such votaries; Their kindnesse was not much, they spoile his Church, break up the Bishops Chamber, and make a prey of all they finde, protest the Bishop shall give them an account of
<PB N="19" REF="16"/>
the profits of his Chancery, and here they begin their audit.</P>
<P>Thus we see our <HI>New reformers</HI> are en∣tred, but Sacriledge ushers them in, they break ope the Prisons, and free the <HI>Saint in Bonds, Baal;</HI> when they had done what they came for, the Citizens, who had en∣tertained them, willingly leave their hou∣ses to keep them company; a Councell is called to resolve upon what ground the next storme should poure downe, <HI>London</HI> ever false to the Prince. The Wood, which no doubt would lodge the Wolves, is set by their Orders. <HI>Tyler</HI> the Idoll who knew his Reigne would last no longer than while these Men continued madde, thought this the onely place likely to keep them so; <HI>London</HI> too was the fairest mark; and besides, the <HI>Clownes</HI> were assured of a welcome upon a private invitation from some of the Citizens, whose Ancestors and Predecessours in all ages, in the tumults of the Confessor S. <HI>Edwards</HI> reigne, in all the Barons Warres since, have gained the re∣nowned to be lovers of Reformation, otherwise pure Rebellion, enemies to Courtiers and Malignants, enemies to the enemies of their deare Liberties, which yet sometimes they pursue with too much heat and blinde zeale, sometimes to their
<PB N="20" REF="17"/>
cost and repentance, mistäking every where both notions and things; the bridles which they without feare or wit, provide for their Kings being often thrust into their owne mouthes by the new riders, which themselves lift into the saddle, while they growne sober Mules, dare neither kick nor sting. <HI>Behold the common people</HI> (sayes the Knight) <HI>when they be up against their</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>roiss. Wals. Lond. quib. nun{que} deest furia, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Prince, and especially in</HI> England, <HI>among them there is no remedy, for they are the perillousest people of the World, and most out, rageous if they be up, and specially the Lon∣doners;</HI> sayes the Monk. The Londoners never want fury if they be not kept in, if license or insolence be permitted them. The Princess <HI>Dowager</HI> of the incomparable <HI>Edward</HI> the black Prince, Mother of the young King, then at <HI>Canterbury,</HI> hardly escapes these Savages, who rudely assault her Chaire, and put her and her Ladies in no small feare of Villany to be done to their persons.</P>
<P>This princess was so willing to be out of their reach, that notwithstanding she was very fat and unwieldie, she got to <HI>London</HI> in a day. <HI>Tyler,</HI> who had insinuated him∣selfe into the good grace of these Churles by appearing the most stirring and active of the Kennell, who began and ruled the
<PB N="21" REF="17"/>
cry, and was by I know not what Cere∣mony, perhaps like that Irish election by casting an old shoe over his head, declared Prince of the rabble, leades them to <HI>Ro∣chester,</HI> which will not come behinde <HI>Can∣terbury</HI> in kindenesse. The people of the Towne (sayes the Knight) were of the same sect, it seemes the Castle (once one of the strongest in the Kingdome,) was now neither fortified nor manned, the Governour Sir <HI>Iohn Moton</HI> yeelds himself into their hands, he was one of the Kings Family, of his House-hold, and must be thought awed, as he was into the ingage∣ment. Here the <HI>Commons</HI> might be thought ashamed of their owne choyce, they offer Sir <HI>Iohn</HI> the Generalls staffe; which had he accepted, he must have commanded ac∣cording to the motions of the <HI>Lieutenant Generall Tilers</HI> Spirit, and when this turne had been over, at the least stamp of his foot have vanished, sneaked off the stage.</P>
<P>They tell him Sir <HI>Iohn,</HI> you must be <NOTE PLACE="marg">Froiss.</NOTE> our Captaine, and (which shewes the po∣wer of his Commission) you shall do what we will have you. The Knight likes not their company, he tries his best wit &amp; lan∣guage to be rid of them, but could not pre∣vaile, they reply downright, Sir <HI>Iohn,</HI> if you
<PB N="22" REF="18"/>
will not doe what we will have you, you dye for it; we will not be denied, but at your perill. Enough was said, the Knight yeelds, but his charge of <HI>Captaine Gene∣rall</HI> is forgotten, we shall see hereafter what use they make of him, and in what manner he must be imployed. This exam∣ple is followed in the other Countries. The Gentry did not onely lose their Estates, and honour, but their courage and gallan∣try, their blouds were frozen, feare had stifled their Spirits. The <HI>Clownes</HI> (as th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Knight) had brought them into such o∣beysance, that they caused them to go with them, whether they would or not, they fawned on them, humbled themselves to them, like Dogs groveling at their feer. The Lord <HI>Molines,</HI> Sir <HI>Stephen Hales,</HI> Sir <HI>Thomas Guysighen,</HI> this Sir <HI>Iohn Moton,</HI> and others were Attendants and vassales to the <HI>Idoll.</HI> Every day new heaps of men <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Wals.</HI> qui censuram juris time∣bant propter mal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> slock to them, like <HI>Catilines</HI> Troops, all that were nec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ssitous at home, unthrifts, broken fellowes, such as for their misdeeds feared the Justice of the Lawes; who <HI>re∣sent the dangerous and distracted state of the Kingdome alike,</HI> and will no doubt ham∣mer out an excellent reformation, they will mend their owne condition which will be enough, we must expect no more,
<PB N="23" REF="18"/>
and now the confidence in their strength made them bold enough to throw off their ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke of Hypocrisie, they began to open the inside. They departed from <HI>Ro∣chester</HI> (sayes <HI>Froissart)</HI> and passed the River (he sayes the <HI>Thames</HI> at <HI>Kingstone)</HI> and came to <HI>Brentsord,</HI> (where I thinke he leads them out of their way) beating downe before them, and round about, the places and Houses of advocates, and pro∣curers, and striking off the heads of diverse persons. <HI>Walsingham</HI> tells us, who those advocates, and procurers were; All men (sayes he) were amused, some looked for good from the new Masters, others feared this insurrection would prove the destru∣ction of the Realme. The last were not deceived. All the Lawyers of the Land (so he goes on) as well the Apprentices, Counsellours, as old Justices, all the Jury∣men of the Countrey, (this was Priest <HI>Balls</HI> charge) they could gripe in their clutches had their heads chopped off.</P>
<P>It was a maxime of the <HI>Cabal,</HI> That there could be no liberty while any of these men were suffered to breathe. From little to great they fell upon things which they never thought of in their first overflow, which <HI>Guicciardine</HI> observes (in civill dis∣cords, where the Rebellion is fortunate
<PB N="24" REF="19"/>
and mens mindes are puft up with suc∣cesse) to be ordinary. The statue of <HI>Cu∣maan Apollo</HI> weeps for the destruction of <HI>Cumae,</HI> we shall here reade of men with∣out sense or apprehensions; both the stories will seem as incredible. The stupid Nobi∣lity, and Gentry sleep in their Houses, till they are roused by these bloud-hounds, that they might seem to deserve the cala∣mity tumbling upon their heads; They were becomming tenants at will, in Villei∣nage, to their vassalls, under their distresse, their Taske, and Taxes, more by the Sot∣tish basenesse of themselves, than any ver∣tue in these Rascals, Scorned and sleighted by every tatter'd Clunch; Their Lands continually upon any Vote or Informati∣on to be sold, or given away upon any information of loyalty or faithfulnesse: the antient vertues of the Gentleman, not to be found in that age, and serving onely for a pretence to ruine, no one could form an expectation of more than this, to be the last man borne, (what was <HI>Polyphemus</HI> his kindnesse to <HI>Ulisses)</HI> to be devoured last, all which they were contented to ha∣zard, and indure to preserve a shred, or jagge of an incertaine ragged Estate (for the health or mistresses sake) subject ever to the violence of the same lawlesse spoiling
<PB N="25" REF="19"/>
force which maimed, and rent it before. N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>xt (to returne to this riffraffe) their cruelty reaches to Parchment Deeds, Charters, Rolles of Courts, Evidences are cast by them into the fire, as if they meant to abolish all remembrance of things; this was to defeat their Lords in the Claims of any antient Rights; and to leave no man more title, than themselves had to their Sword and power.</P>
<P>The <HI>Kentish</HI> and <HI>Essexian</HI> rout, were <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> joyned (sayes the Monke, but he tells us not where) and approached neere <HI>London,</HI> at <HI>Black heath</HI> they made an halt, where they were neare 200000 strong.</P>
<P>Thither came two Knights sent by the <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> King to them, to inquire the cause of the Commotion, and why they had amassed such swarmes of the people. They answer, they met to conferre with the King con∣cerning businesse of weight, they tell the Messengers they ought to goe back to the King and shew him, that it behoves him to come to them, they would acquaint him with their desires (we shall quickly discover why his presence was required,) upon return of the Knights, it was debated in Councell by the Lords about the King, wher<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e he should goe or no, some of the Table more willing to venture the King
<PB N="26" REF="20"/>
than themselves, willing to throw him in∣to the gulph, or perhaps not senting the designe of the <HI>Clownes,</HI> perswade him to see them, Your Majesty (thus they) must make a tryall of these men, necessity now must be looked on above reason, if any thing can give the check to the up∣rores, it must be your presence, there can be no safety but in this venture, it is now as dangerous to seeme not to trust, as to be deceived; fate is too much feared, if it be imagined that this tree of your em∣pite, which has flourished so many ages, can fall in an houre.</P>
<P>The Archbishop of <HI>Canterbury, Simon Theobald</HI> of <HI>Sudbury,</HI> Lord Chancellour <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> of <HI>England,</HI> the most Eloquent, most Wise, and most pious Prelate of the Age, faithfull to his Prince, and therefore odi∣ous to those who conspired against his Majesty, and authority, likes not the ad∣vise; <NOTE PLACE="marg">Discaliga∣ios r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>baul∣dos.</NOTE> The King ought not (sayes he) to venture his person among such hoselesse ribaulds, but rather dispose things so as to cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>be their insolence: <HI>Sir,</HI> (sayes he) <HI>your sacred Majesty in this storme ought to shew how much of a King you can play; what you will goe for hereafter; by your pre∣sent carriage, you will either be feared for the future, or contemned; If you seriously con∣sider
<PB N="72" REF="20"/>
the nature of these rough hewne sava∣ges, you will finde the gentle wayes perniti∣ous, your tamenesse will undoe you, mercy will ever be in your power, but it is not to be named without the sword drawne; God and your right have placed you in your throne, but your courage and resolution must keep you there; your indignation will be justice, good men will thinke it so, and if they love you, you have enough, you cannot Capitulate, not treat with your rebells; without hazarding your honour, and perhaps your royall faith; if you yeild to the force of one sedition, your whole life and reigne will be nothing but a continuation of broyles, and tumults, if you assert your soveraigne authority betimes, not onely these doults, these sots, but all men else will reverence you; remember Sir, God by whom lawfull Princes reigne, whose vice∣gerent you are, would not forgive rebellion in Angels, you must not trust the face, Peti∣tions delivered you upon Swords points are fatall if you allow this custome you are rui∣ned, as yet Sir, you may be obeyed as much as you please.</HI> Of this opinion was Sir <HI>Robert Hales,</HI> Lord <HI>Prior</HI> of Saint <HI>Iohn</HI> of <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> newly Lord Treasurer of <HI>Eng∣land,</HI> a magnanimous and stout Knight, but not liked by the Commons. When this resolution was known to the <HI>Clownes,</HI> they
<PB N="28" REF="21"/>
grow starke mad, they bluster, they sweat to seek out the Kings Traitours, (for such now they must go for; No man was either good or honest, but he who pleased them) the Archbishop, and Lord <HI>Prior,</HI> &amp; to chop off their Heads, here they might be trusted, they were likely to keep their words.</P>
<P>Here upon, without more consideration they advance toward <HI>London,</HI> not forget∣ting to burne, and rase the Lawyers and Courtiers houses in the way, to the Kings honour no doubt, which they will be thought to Arme for, Sir <HI>Iohn Froissart,</HI> and others report this part thus, which probably might follow after this refusall.</P>
<P>The Rebells say they sent their Knight (* so they called him, yet was he the Kings Knight, for <HI>Tyler</HI> came not up to dubbing, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Graion.</NOTE> we finde no Sir <HI>Iohn,</HI> nor Sir <HI>Thomas</HI> of his making,) Sir <HI>Iohn Moton,</HI> to the King, who was then in the Tower with his Mother, his halfe brothers <HI>Thomas Hol∣land</HI> Earle of <HI>Kent,</HI> after Duke of <HI>Surry,</HI> and the Lord <HI>Holland,</HI> the Earles of <HI>Sa∣lisbury, Warwick,</HI> and <HI>Oxford,</HI> the Arch∣bishop, Lord <HI>Prior</HI> and others. The Knight casts himselfe downe at the Kings feet, be∣seeches him, not to looke upon him the worse as in this quality and imployment, to consider he is forced to doe what he
<PB N="29" REF="21"/>
does; He goes on, Sir the <HI>Commons</HI> of this Realme (those few in Armes compara∣tively to the rest would be taken for the whole) desire you by me to speake with them. Your Person will be safe, they re∣pute you still their <HI>King</HI> (this deserved thanks) but how long the kindnesse will hold we shall soone finde, they professe that all they had done or would doe was for your honour, <HI>For your glory, (your ho∣nour and security are their great care) they will make you a glorious King, fearfull to your enemies, and beloved of your Subjects, they promise you a plentifull and unparallell'd revenue, They will maint<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ine your power and authority in relation to the Lawes, with your royal person, according to the duty of their allegeance, their protestation, their vow, their solemne League, and Covenant, without diminishing your just power and greatnesse, and that they will all the dayes of their lives continue in this Covenant against all oppositi∣on;</HI> They assure you Sir, <HI>That they intend faithfully the good of your Majesty, and of the Kingdome, and that they will not be di∣verted from this end by any private or selfe∣respects whatsoever.</HI> But the Kingdome has been a long time ill governed by your Uncles, and the Clergy; especially by the Archbishop of <HI>Canterbury,</HI> of whom they
<PB N="30" REF="22"/>
would have an account. They have found out necessary Counsels for you, they would warne you of many things, which hitherto you have wanted good advise in.</P>
<P>The conclusion was sad on the Knights part, His Children were pledges for his returne, and if he faile in that, their lives were to answer it. Which moved with the the King; He allowes the excuse, sends him back with this answer, that he will speake with the <HI>Commons</HI> the next Mor∣ning; which it should seeme the report of the outrages done by the <HI>Clownes</HI> upon his refusall, &amp; this Message made him con∣sent to. At the time he takes his Barge &amp; is rowed downe to <HI>Redriffe,</HI> the place nearest the Rebells, ten thousand of them descend from the Hill to see, and treat with him, (with a resolution to yeild to nothing, to overcome by the Treaty; as they must have done, had not the Kings feare pre∣served him.) When the Barge drew nigh, the new C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uncell of state (sayes out <NOTE PLACE="marg">Fro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ss.</NOTE> Knight) howled, and shouted, as though all the Devills of Hell had been amongst them; Sir <HI>Iohn Moton</HI> was brought to∣ward the River guarded, they being de∣termined to have cut him in pieces, if the King had broke his promise.</P>
<P>All the desires of these good and faithfull
<PB N="31" REF="22"/>
Counsellours contracted suddenly into a narrow roome, they had now but one de∣mand. The King askes them what is the matter which made them so earnestly solli∣cit his Presence? They have no more to say, but to intreat him to land. Which was to betray himselfe to them, to give his Life and Soveraignty up to those fickle Beasts, to be held of them during their good pleasures; which the Lords will not agree to. The Earle of <HI>Salisbury,</HI> of the antient Nobility, and illustrious house of <HI>Montacute,</HI> tells them their equipage and order were not comely, and that the King ought not to adventure amongst their troopes. They are now more unsatisfied, and <HI>London,</HI> how true soever to the <HI>Cause,</HI> and faithlesse to the Prince, shall feele the effects of their fury, <HI>Southwark</HI> a friendly borough, is taken up for their first quarters. Here againe they throw downe the Ma∣lignants Houses, and as a grace of their entrance, breake up the Kings prisons, and let out all those they finde under restraint in them; not forgetting to ransack the Archbishops house at <HI>Lambeth,</HI> and spoyle all things there—plucking downe the Stews standing upon the Thames banke, and allowed in the former ages; It can∣not be thought but that the Idol loved A∣dultery
<PB N="32" REF="23"/>
well enough, but perhaps these publick bawdy-houses were too uncleane, and might stinke in his nostrils; we can∣not finde him any where quarelling with the Beares, those were no Malignants.</P>
<P>They knocked not long at the City∣gates, which (some say) were never shut <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> against them, or (as others) quickly opened▪ The Citizens fancyed themselves privy Counsellours borne, inspired from their shoppes for affaires of State, and would not suppose, the Reformation could be effected without them, they were rich by lyes, and all the most sordid wayes of falshood, and must be sage and knowing, pride the first sinne the Devill taught man tickles them. The Major Sir <HI>William Waleworth,</HI> whose memory (while truth and loyalty shall be thought virtues) must be honourable, and nine of the Aldermen held for King <HI>Richard,</HI> in vaine; a prospe∣rous wicked chief shall never want wicked instruments, Three Aldermen, and the greatest part of the people for the <HI>King</HI> of the <HI>Commons,</HI> the Idol, and his Priests. Those, the <HI>considers,</HI> and well affected to <HI>Tyler,</HI> forbid their Major to keep him out, owne his actions, as done for the go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d of the faithfull people of the Land, and the <HI>Common-Wealth,</HI> &amp; his followers for their
<PB N="33" REF="23"/>
Brethren and Companions of the <HI>holy Cause. They vow to live and dye with Tylar.</HI> Many of those who had no thoughts of doing mischiefe (yet being none of the wisest) were cheated into a good beliefe of them, because of their <HI>Protestation</HI> (which in their first entrance they made solemnly) that they had no intent, but this onely, to search and hunt out the Traitours of the Kingdome, the <HI>subverters of the fundamentall Laws, evill Counsellours, and Malignants,</HI> and that this done they would give over, they would disband, and returne home the same men they were, to their Farmes and Cottages, without in∣riching themselves, without any other harvest of their Labours, <HI>not doubting bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> that in the end, it should appeare to all the world, that their endeavours have been most hearty and sincere, for the maintenance of Re∣ligion, the Kings just Prerogatives, the Lawes and liberties of the Land; in which endeavours, by the Grace of God, they would persist, though they should perish in the work.</HI> Which was believed; what confirmed this Faith was, they made Theft Capitall (which yet was confined, all without the Fold of the godly were <HI>AEgyptians,</HI> and could not be robbed) and paid justly for what they had, but they paid not
<PB N="34" REF="24"/>
often, nor could their reckonings be great.</P>
<P>The Citizens were their purveiours, and made provision for them, every house was open to them, and tables continually fur∣nished. Their entry was on the 14 of <HI>Iune,</HI> 1385. on Wednesday (a little be∣fore Midsummer) the eve of <HI>Corpus Christi</HI> day; they spend the morning of the next day, being the festivall in ringes, discoursing of the Piety, Honesty, and fairenesse of their cause, of liberty and the courses to gaine it, of seising Traitours, <HI>Of bringing Incendendiaries, Malignants, and evill instruments to condigne punishment,</HI> of the Duke <HI>Iohn</HI> of <HI>Lancaster,</HI> who was above all men<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hated by them, but too far off for the scratches of their olawos, be∣ing imployed in <HI>Scotland</HI> to treate a peace there, whence these report him turned a traitour to the <HI>King,</HI> and become Scottish: about <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>noone, being warmed more by their cups, than with the Sun, for the richest Wines were drawne for them, and swallowed with that greedinesse, that they were got to the height of drunken∣nesse and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aved like mad men, They are for execution; The Savoy of the Duke of <HI>Lancaster</HI> a Princely building, the most stately fabrick of the Kingdome was fired
<PB N="35" REF="24"/>
by them, his Servants there murthered, his Plate and Jewells broke in pieces, a Coat of his of great value (called in that age a Jack) in contempt and scorne to this Prince, was stuck on the top of a Lance, made a marke for their Arrows, then cut and gashed to jagges with their hatch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s, one of them who had hid a piece of Plate, was throwne by the rest into the fire with it, crying out, <HI>We be zealous of Truth and</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Knighton</NOTE> <HI>Iustice, and not Theeves and Robbers.</HI> The <HI>Londoners</HI> were here no slow men, they knew themselves guilty of receiving, and that their condition could be no worse, they might thinke too, it would be their shame for ever to be overdone in mis∣chiefe, nor were they here exceeded.</P>
<P>The next fiery shower is discharged up. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> the Temple an Innes of Court, or College for Students of the Lawes of the Nobler sort, but belonging to the Knights of Saint <HI>Iohn</HI> of <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> to whom the possessions of the Knights Templars were given by this Kings Grandfather. Many men lost there the evidences of their e∣states, many their lives. From hence in malice to the Lord <HI>Prior,</HI> they hasten to <HI>Clerkenwell,</HI> where they leave nothing of that noble Palace of the Knights of S. <HI>Iohn</HI> of <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> but rubbidge, and ashes,
<PB N="36" REF="25"/>
their Church too was consumed in the same wicked flames. This house was seaven dayes burning downe. They breake open the Exchequer and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Westminster</HI> the same day. The Flemmings or Dutch strangers, who siace the <HI>Iewes</HI> were ba∣nished, suffer their part in every Sedition, are sought for all the streets through, all of them massacred, no sanctuary could save them, thirteen Flemmings were drawne out of the Church of the Friers Hermits of Saint <HI>Augustine,</HI> and beheaded in the streets, and seaventeen others pulled out of another parochiall Church dye in the same manner. They had a <HI>Shibboleth</HI> to discover them, he who pronounced <HI>Brot</HI> and <HI>Cawse,</HI> for <HI>Bread</HI> and <HI>Cheese</HI> had his head lopt off; It was their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> if they could catch any man, who had not sworne their <HI>Oath,</HI> was not of the side, or was hated by any of the <HI>Commons</HI> to snatch off his hood or Capuch (which w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s a part of the Cloak, or out∣ward garment worne then, and served to cover the head) with the accustomed cry, or yelling which they used in beheading and overthrowing Houses, then to rush in to the streets, and hack with their fellow Jobernolles, at his neck in Crowds, till the Head dropped down.</P>
<P>Our most famous <HI>Chaucer</HI> flourishing
<PB N="37" REF="25"/>
then, in his description of the terrible fright, and noyse, at the carrying away of <HI>Chanticlere</HI> the Cock by <HI>Reinold</HI> the Fox, reflects upon these cries, but in an Hyper∣bole of his Poeticall feined ones, and much undervaluing the horrour of the <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ntish</HI> throats, as he will have it.
<Q><L>They yellen as Fiends do in Hell, &amp;c.</L>
<L>So hideous was the noyse, <HI>Ah benedicie!</HI></L>
<L>Certes Iack-Straw ne his meyney</L>
<L>He made shouts halfe so shrill,</L>
<L>UUhen they would any Flemming kill.</L></Q></P>
<P>The <HI>Lombards</HI> scaped better, they were onely robbed of what they had, their skins were left them whole, <HI>Wat</HI> the Idol had long agon in <HI>France</HI> s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rved <HI>Richard Lyon</HI> a Merchant, and Lapidarie, formerly She∣riffe of <HI>London,</HI> one of the wealthyest of the City, who had given him blowes, it was not fit this inju<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y should be forgotten, nor was it; It was a score now, or never to be paid, he strikes off his old masters head, which in triumph is carryed before him on a Speare.</P>
<P>This night the King was counselled to fall upon these beasts, for the most part drunk, and cut their throats, easie to be de∣stroyed, if any man had had but the courage to overcome. It was the gallant Mayors advise, they lay on heaps without sense or motion, tired with the mischiefes of the
<PB N="38" REF="26"/>
day, drunk and asleep, without Guards or Watch; the E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e of <HI>Salisbury</HI> and the No∣bility, against whose L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ves, Honours and Fortunes thes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> beasts had conspired, desire the King to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y all faire and gentle wayes of appeasing them, which counsell he ap∣proves. Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y were not so kind to them∣se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ves; many lost their lives by the hands and swords of their companions; every petty discontent, or grudging, being enough to provoke them. Thirty two of them be∣ing drunk in a Cellar of the <HI>Savoy,</HI> were immured there, finding in the same place Death and th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Grave together. Some of them threw Barrels of Gunpowder (which was little known then) into the fire, and are blown up with part of the Palace.</P>
<P>Proclamations were formerly made in <HI>Tylers</HI> name, not in <HI>Strawes,</HI> (as <HI>Polydore</HI> would have it.) <HI>Straw</HI> was this while bu∣sied elsewhere. The Country about was by these Proclamations summoned to re∣paire to <HI>London</HI> with all speed, to spoyle this <HI>Babylon;</HI> The close menaces <HI>(lest they provoke Gods Iudgments)</HI> pluck them down upon their heads, which themselves ex∣plain, if ye faile, <HI>if ye and your Officers give not obedience freely to the Protector,</HI> we will send ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> 20000 men (20000 of our Lo∣custs) who shall burn the Towns of the
<PB N="39" REF="26"/>
children of disobedience; Those of S. <HI>Al∣banes</HI> and <HI>Barnet</HI> (whose famous deeds challenge a place in this story by them∣selves) struck with the thunder of this e∣dict, haste to <HI>London;</HI> in their journey thi∣ther, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ibury,</HI> a retiring house of the Lo: <HI>Prior</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> of S. <HI>Iohn</HI> neere <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> they finde 20000. or thereabouts casting downe the firmer parts of the house, which the fire could not consume.</P>
<P><HI>Iack Straw</HI> C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ptain of this herd, calls <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard.</NOTE> these new comers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o him, and forces them to sweare to adhere to King <HI>Richard,</HI> and the Commons. How long this <HI>Oath</HI> will b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> sworne to we shall see, and how much the safer the King will be for it.</P>
<P>We shall see too what is lost by this new Union of King and Commons, by the new fellowsh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>p, to observe the horrible irreli∣gious hypocr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sie of these <HI>Clownes</HI> who onely would be thought the <HI>Protectors</HI> of his Crown and Person. They alone had decreed his ruine, who sweare thus often to prevent it, to guard him from it; A <HI>Treason</HI> not to be believed by some then till it had taken. The Commons were then divided into three Bodies, this with <HI>Iack Straw,</HI> the second at <HI>Mile-end</HI> unde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the Essexian Princes, <HI>Kirkby, Treder, Scot,</HI> and <HI>Rugge,</HI> the third on Tower-hill,
<PB N="40" REF="27"/>
where the Idoll, and Priest <HI>Baal</HI> were in chiefe.</P>
<P>This last crue grew horribly rude, and haughty; the Commons there were not cont<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nted to be the Kings Tasters and no more, they snatch the Kings provision vi∣olently from the Purveyours, he is to be starved for his own good, and after. Har∣pies or Vultures, choose you whether, strike high, like brave birds of prey they will kill no more Flies, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s was the way to secure their smaller mischiefs. <HI>Polydores</HI> conceit that the Archbishop and Lord Prior of S. <HI>Iohn,</HI> were sent out by the King to allay their heat, is not probable.</P>
<P><HI>Walsingham</HI> relates it thus, That they de∣manded these two (with full cryes no doubt of <HI>Iustice, Iustice)</HI> with some others Traitours by their <HI>Law,</HI> (a <HI>Fundamentall,</HI> never to be found or heard of before) to be given up to them by the King with all the earnestnesse, and violence imagi∣nable.</P>
<P>They give him his choice, bid him consi∣der of it, they will either have the blood of these <HI>their Traitours</HI> or <HI>his;</HI> they ma∣king <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Wals.</HI> alias scire<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> semetipsum vita p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>v'd dum.</NOTE> all those <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>linquents, who attended on him, or executed his lawfull commands;</HI> whom say they, The King <HI>with an high and forcible hand protects,</HI> will not be appeased,
<PB N="41" REF="27"/>
unlesse they be delivered up; conjuring him to be wise in time, and <HI>dismisse his ex∣traordinary guards, his Cavaliers, and others of that quality, who seem to have little inte∣rest or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ffection to the publike good.</HI> Whether the Tower doores flew open at this fright, or the M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n-wolfes crowded in, at the King<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> going out to appease the party at <HI>Mil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>end,</HI> as Sir <HI>Iohn Froissart</HI> tells it, <HI>Wat</HI> the Id<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l with Priest <HI>Baal</HI> are now masters of the Tower, into which on Friday the 16 of <HI>Iune</HI> they entred, not many more than 400 of their company guarding them, where then were commanded six hundred of the Kings men of Armes, and six hun∣dred Archers, a <HI>Guard</HI> not so extraordina∣ry as was necessary then, all so faint-hear∣ted, so unmanned at the appatition at the sight of these Goblins, they stood like the stones of <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dusa,</HI> remembred not them∣selves, their honour, nor what they had been. The <HI>Clownes,</HI> the most abj<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ct of them, singly with their Clubs, or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in their hands, venture into all the rooms, into the <HI>Kings</HI> Bed-chamber, (which per∣haps had been his Scaffold had he been there) sit, lie, and tumble upon his Bed, they presse into his Mothers Chamber, where some of the merry wanton Devills offer to kisse her, others g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ve her blowes,
<PB N="42" REF="28"/>
break her head. She swowne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, and is car ryed privately to the Wardrobe by her servants; Some revile and threaten the no∣blest Knights of the Houshold some strok<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> their heards with their uncleane hands (which beyond the Romane patience in the same <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>udenesse from the <HI>Gauls</HI> is in∣dured) and this to claw, and sweeten, (they meant it so) they glose with smooth words, and bespeak a lasting friendship for the time to come, they must maintain the injuries done to themselves, must not di∣stu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>be the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of their Estates and Rights, must not shew any sense of gene∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sity, of faith, of honour, (it concerned <HI>Tyler</HI> that they should be the veryest fools and cowards breathing) if they stir make any Cla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mes, they shall be reputed sediti∣ous, tu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bulent, and breakers of the publick (otherwise and plainly) <HI>Tylers peace.</HI> It was never heard (sayes the Emperour <HI>Charl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s</HI> in <HI>Sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>idan)</HI> that it should be law∣fu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l to despoile any man of his estates and rights, and unlawfull to restore him: Our <HI>Tyler</HI> and his Anabaptists thought other∣wise.</P>
<P>As <HI>Walsingham,</HI> they went in and out like Lords, who were varlets of the lowest rank, and those who were no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Cowherds to Knights, but to <HI>Bores,</HI> value themselves
<PB N="43" REF="28"/>
beyond Kights. Here was a hotchpotch of the rabble, a mechanick sordid state composed as those under <HI>Kettes</HI> Oke of <HI>Reformation,</HI> after,
<Q><L><HI>Of Countrey gnooffes, Hob, Dick, and Hick,</HI></L>
<L><HI>with Clubs, and clouted shoon.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Nevilli kettus.</NOTE></L></Q></P>
<P>A medley or huddle of Botchers, Coblers, Tinkers, Draymen, of Apron men and Plough-joggers, domineering in the Kings Palace, and rooting up the plants and wholsome flowers of his Kingdome in it; This place was now a vile and nasty sty, no more a Kings Palace, who will value a stately pile of building, of honourable ti∣tle, or Antique memory, since <HI>Constantine,</HI> when it is intected with the plagu, haun∣ted by Goblins, or possessed by Theeves. The knights of the Court, were but knights of the Carpet or Hangings. No man seem∣ed discontented, all was husht and still. White-hall was then a Bishops Palace, the Tower was to be prepared for <HI>Tylers</HI> highnesse, and his Officers but the Cement of the Stratocratie of the Government by Sword, and Club-Law, could not be well tempered with vulgar blood, a servant of the Arch-bishops (who had trusted him∣selfe to these Guards and Walls) is forced
<PB N="44" REF="29"/>
to betray his Lord. He brings them into the Chappell, where the holy Prelat wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> at his prayers, where he had cel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>brated Masse th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t morning before the <HI>King,</HI> and <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Wals.</HI> Sa∣cram Com∣munionem.</NOTE> taken the sacred Communion, where he had spent the whole night in watching and devotion, as presaging what followed.</P>
<P>He was a valiant man and pious, and expected these Blood-hounds with great security, and calmnesse of mind; when their bellowing first struck his ears, He tels his servants that Death came now as a more particular blessing; where the com∣forts of life w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re taken away, that life was i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>kesome to him, (perhaps his pious feares for the Church and Monarchy, both alike indangered, and fatally tied to the same chain, might make him weary of the World) and that he cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d now die with more quiet of conscience than ever; a quiet wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ch these Patricides will not finde when they shall pay the score of this and their other crimes. However the flattery of successe may abuse, our death-bed re∣presents things in their owne shape, and as they are: after this the rout of Wolves enter p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ophane'y roaring, wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re is the <HI>Traitour</HI> where is the Robber of the <HI>Com∣mon-people?</HI> He answers, not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oubled at what he saw, or heard.</P>
<P><PB N="45" REF="29"/>
Yee are welcome my Sonnes. I am the <HI>Archbishop</HI> whom you seek, neither <HI>Trai∣tour</HI> nor <HI>Robber;</HI> Presently these <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the Devill griping him with their wicked clutches, teare him out of the Chappell, neither reverencing the <HI>Altar,</HI> nor <HI>Cruci∣fix,</HI> figured on the top of his Crosier, nor the <HI>Host,</HI> (these are the Monkes observati∣ons, for which he condemnes them in the highest impiety, and makes them worse than <HI>Divells,</HI> and as Religion went then, well he might condemne them so.) They dragge him by the Armes and hood to Tower hill without the Gates, there they howle hideously, which was the signe of a mischiefe to follow.</P>
<P>He askes them what it is they purpose, what is his offence, tells them he is their <HI>Archbishop</HI> (this makes him guilty, all his eloquence, his Wisdome are now of no use) he addes the murder of their Sove∣raigne <HI>Pastour</HI> will be severely punished, some notorious vengeance will suddenly <NOTE PLACE="marg">Qui pastor <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> follow it. These destroyers will not trou∣ble themselves with the idle formality of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mock-trial or Court of their own erecting, an abominable Ceremony, which had made their impiety more ugly, they proceed down tight, and plainly, which must be in∣stead of all things, He is commanded to
<PB N="46" REF="30"/>
lay his neck upon the block, as a false trai∣tour to the <HI>Commonalty</HI> and Realm: To deale roundly, his life was forfeited, and any particular charge, or defenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> would not be necessary, his enemies were his Ac∣cusers, and Judge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, (his enemies who had combined and sworne to abolish his order, the Church, and spoile the sacred patrimo∣ny) and what innocency, what defence could save? Without any reply farther, he forgives the Heads-man, and bowes his Body to the Axe.</P>
<P>After the firsthit, he touches the wound with his hand, and speakes thus, <HI>It is the</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ab, ab, ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Domini<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></NOTE> <HI>Hand of the Lord.</HI> The next stroke falls up∣on his hand, ere he could remove it, and cuts off the tops of his fingers, after which he fell, but died not till the eight blow, his body lay all that day unburied, and no wonder, all men were throughly scared, under the tyranny of these Monsters, all Humanity, all Piety, were most unsafe.</P>
<P>The Archbishop dyed a Martyr of loy∣alty to his <HI>King,</HI> and has his * miracles Re∣corded, an honour often bestowed by <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> Monkes (friends of <HI>Regicide,</HI> and <HI>Regi∣cides,)</HI> on Traitours, seldome given to honest men. In his <HI>Epitaph</HI> (his riming <HI>Epitaph,</HI> where is showne the pitti∣full ignorant rudenesse of those times)
<PB N="47" REF="30"/>
he goes for no lesse, he speakes thus:
<Q><L>Sudburiae natus <HI>Simon</HI> jacet hic tumulatus,</L>
<L>Martyrizatus n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce pro republica stratus.</L></Q>
<Q><L>Sudburies Simon <HI>here intombed lies,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Who for the</HI> Commonwealth <HI>a Martyr dies.</HI></L></Q></P>
<P>It is fit (sayes <HI>Plato)</HI> that he who would appeare a iust man, become naked, that his virtue be despoiled of all ornament, that he be taken for a wicked man by others (wicked indeed) that he be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ocked, and hanged. The wisest of men tell us. <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 15.</NOTE> There is a just man that per sheth in his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ghteous∣nesse, and there is a wicked man that pro∣longeth his life in his wickednesse. The Seas are often calme to Pirates, and the scourges of God, the executioners of his fury, the <HI>Gothes, Hunnes,</HI> and <HI>Vandalls</HI> here∣tofore, <HI>Tartars</HI> and <HI>Turkes</HI> now, how hap∣py are their Robberies, how doe all thing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> succeed with them beyond their wish<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>! Our Saviours Passion, the great mysterie of his Incarnation lost him to the J<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>wes his <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Grot.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> ab impi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> non ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> turmodo <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> tur.</NOTE> Murtherers. Whereupon <HI>Grotius</HI> notes, It is often permitted by God, that pious men be not onely vexed by wicked men, but murdered too—He gives ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mples in <HI>Abel, Isaiah,</HI> and others, the MESSIAH
<PB N="48" REF="31"/>
dyed for the sins of the world, <HI>Ethelbert</HI> and Saint <HI>Edmund</HI> the East-Angles, Saint <HI>Oswald</HI> the Northumbrian, Saint <HI>Edward</HI> the Monarch, &amp;c. Saxon Kings, are exam∣ples at home.</P>
<P><HI>Thucydides</HI> in his narration of the defeat and death of <HI>Nician</HI> the Athenian in <HI>Sycily,</HI> speaks thus: <HI>Being the man who of all the Grecians of my time had least deserved to be brought to so great a degree of misery.</HI> It is too frequent to proclaim Gods Judg∣ments in the misfortunes of others, as if we were of the Celestiall Councell, had seen all the Wheels, or Orbs, upon which Providence turns, and knew all the reasons and ends which direct and govern its mo∣tions: men love by a strange abstraction to separate Facts from their Crimes; where the fact is beneficiall, the advantage must canonize it, it must be of heavenly off∣spring, a way to justifie <HI>Cain, Abimelech, Phocas,</HI> our third <HI>Richard, Ravilliac,</HI> every lucky parricide whatsoever.</P>
<P><HI>Alexander Severus</HI> that most excellent Emperour assassinated by the Militia or Souldiery, by an ill fate of the <HI>Common-wealth</HI> (for <HI>Maximinus</HI> a Thracian or Goth. <HI>Lieutenant Generall</HI> of the Army, a cruell Savage tyrant, by force usurped the Empire after him) Replyed, to one who
<PB N="49" REF="31"/>
pretended to foretell his end; That it troubled him not, the most renowned per∣sons in all ages die violently. This gallant Prince condemned no death but a disho∣nest fearfull one. Heaven it selfe declared on the Archbishops side, and cleared his innocency. <HI>Starling</HI> of <HI>Essex</HI> who chal∣lenged to himselfe the glory of being Heads man, fell mad suddenly after, ran through the Villages with his Sword han∣ging naked upon his brest, and his Dagger naked behinde him, came up to <HI>London,</HI> confest freely the fact, and lost his head there; As most of those did, who had laid their hands upon th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s Archbishop com∣ming up severally out of their Countries to that City, and constantly accusing them∣selves for the Parricide of their spirituall Father. Nothing was now unlawfull, there could be no wickednesse after this; They make more examples of barbarous cruelty under the name of Justice.</P>
<P><HI>Robert</HI> Lord <HI>Prior</HI> of St. <HI>Iohn,</HI> and Lord Treasurer of <HI>England Iohn Leg,</HI> or <HI>Laige</HI> one of the Kings serjeants at Armes, a <HI>Franciscan,</HI> a Physitian belonging to the Duke of <HI>Lancaster</HI> (whom p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rhaps they hated because they had wro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ged his Ma∣ster) a Frier <HI>Carmelite,</HI> the Kings Confes∣sour were murdered there in this fury.
<PB N="50" REF="32"/>
Whose heads with the Archbishops, were borne before them through <HI>London</HI> streets, and advanced over the Bridge.</P>
<P>This while the <HI>King</HI> was softning the Rebells of <HI>Essex</HI> at <HI>Mile-end,</HI> with the Ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>les of <HI>Sal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bury, Warwick,</HI> and <HI>Oxford,</HI> and other Lords Thither by P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oclamati∣on he had summoned them, as presuming the <HI>Essexians</HI> to be the more civiliz'd, and by much the fairer enemies, as indeed they were. There he promises to grant them their d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sires, <HI>Liberty, pretious Liberty</HI> is the thing they aske, this is given them by the <HI>King,</HI> but on condition of good beha∣viour. They are to cease their burning, and destruction of Houses, to returne quiet∣ly to their homes, and offend no man in their way. Two of every Village were to stay as Agents behinde for the <HI>Kings</HI> Charters, which could not be got ready in time. Farther the <HI>King</HI> offers them his <HI>Banners.</HI></P>
<P>Some of the were simple, honest people, of no ill meaning, who knew not why the Garboils were begun; nor why they came thither. These were won, and win others; without more stir those of <HI>Essex</HI> returne whence they came. <HI>Tyler</HI> and <HI>Baal</HI> are of another spirit, they would not part so ea∣sily, Tyler the future <HI>Monarch,</HI> who had
<PB N="51" REF="32"/>
designed an <HI>Empire</HI> for himselfe, and was now, <HI>sceleribus suis ferox atque praeclarus</HI> famous for his villeinies and haughty, would not put up so, he and his K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ntish rabble tarry. The next day being Saturday the 17 of <HI>Iune,</HI> was spent as the other dayes of their tyranny, in Burning, Rui∣ning houses, Murthers, and Depopulati∣ons.</P>
<P>The night of this day the Idol and his Priest upon a new resolution; intended to have struck at the neck of the Nation, to have Murthered the <HI>King (the Achan of the Tribes,)</HI> probably by beheading, the death these parricides had used hitherto, the Lords, Gentlemen, the wealthiest and ho∣nestest part of the Citizens, then to have pillaged their Houses, and fired the City in foure parts, they intended this hast to avoid odious partnership in the exploit, and that those of <HI>Norfolke, Suffolke,</HI> and other parts might not share in the spoile. This Counsell of destruction was against all policy, more profit might have beene made of this City by <HI>Excise, Assessment,</HI> and <HI>Taxes</HI> upon the <HI>Trade, Tylor</HI> might soo∣ner have inriched himselfe, and have been as secure. Estate makes men lofty, fearo and poverty, if we may trust <HI>Machiavel,</HI> bend and supple, every man had been in
<PB N="52" REF="33"/>
danger, and obnoxious to him, one <HI>Clowne</HI> had awed a street. Near the Abby-Church at <HI>Westminster,</HI> was a Chappell with an image of the Virgin <HI>Mary,</HI> this Chappell was called the Chappell of our Lady, in the P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>w it stood near the Chappell of S. <HI>Steph.</HI> since turned from a Chappell to the Parliament house, here our Lady then (who would not believe it) did great miracles. <HI>Richards</HI> preservation at this time was no small one being in the hands of the multi∣tude, let loose, and inraged. There he makes his vowes of safety, after which he rides towards these Sonnet of perdition under the Idol <HI>Tyler.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Tyler,</HI> who meant to consume the day in Cavills, protests to those who were sent by the <HI>King</HI> to offer those of <HI>Kent</HI> the same peace, which the <HI>Essex Clownes</HI> had accepted, That he would willingly embrace a good and honest <HI>Peace,</HI> but the <HI>Proposi∣tions</HI> or <HI>Articles</HI> of it were only to be dic∣tated by himselfe. He is not satisfied with the <HI>Kings</HI> Charters, Three draughts are presented to him, no substance, no forme would please, he desires an <HI>accommodation,</HI> but he will have <HI>Peace,</HI> and <HI>truth</HI> together. H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> exclaims that the <HI>liberty</HI> there is deceit∣full, but an empty name, that while the <HI>King</HI> talkes of <HI>liberty,</HI> he is <HI>actually levying
<PB N="53" REF="33"/>
Warre, setting up his Standard</HI> against his <HI>Commons,</HI> that the good <HI>Commons</HI> are abu∣sed to their owne ruine, and to the mis∣carriage of the great undertaking, that they have with infinite paines and labour acquainted the <HI>King</HI> with their <HI>humble de∣sires,</HI> who refuses to joyn with them, mis∣led, and carried away by a few <HI>evill and rotten-hearted Lords and Delinquents,</HI> con∣trary to his <HI>Coronation Oath; by which he is obliged to passe all Lawes off<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>red him by the Commons (whose the Legislative power is) which deniall of his if it be not a forfeiture of his trust and office (both which are now uselesse) it comes neare it, and he is fairely dealt with; if he be not deposed, which too might be done without any want of modesty or duty,</HI> and with the good of the Com∣mon-wealth, <HI>The happinesse of the Nation not depending on him, or any of the Regall Branches.</HI> I will <HI>deliver the Nation from the Norman slavery, and the world</HI> (sayes he) <HI>of an old silly superstition, That Kings are onely the Tenants of Heaven, obnoxious to God a∣lone, cannot be condemned and punished by any power else,</HI> I will make: here he lied not, <HI>an wholsome President to the world for∣midable to all tyrannes,</HI> I declare, That <HI>Ri∣chard Plantagenet,</HI> or <HI>Richard</HI> of <HI>Bourde∣aux, at this time is not in a condition to
<PB N="54" REF="34"/>
governe, I will make no addresses no applica∣tions to him, nor receive any from him;</HI> though I am but a <HI>dry bone,</HI> too unworthy for this great <HI>calling,</HI> yet I will finish the <HI>work, I will settle the Government without the King and against him, and against all that take part with him▪</HI> which sufficiently justifies our Armes. <HI>God with Us,</HI> sayes he, ownt them, successe manifests the righteousnesse of our cause, this is (sayes he) the voyce of the people, by us <HI>their Representative, and our Counsell. After the Vote of no more Addres∣ses,</HI> which with all their other <HI>Vote of trea∣sons</HI> were to be styled <HI>the resolution of the whole Realm;</HI> and while he swells in this ruffle, Sir <HI>Iohn Newton</HI> a Knight of the Court, is sent to intreat rather than invite him to come to the <HI>King</HI> then in <HI>Smith∣field;</HI> where the Idols Regiments were drawn up, and treat with him, concerning the <HI>additionall Provisions</HI> he desired to be inserted into the Charter.</P>
<P>No observance was omitted which might be thought pleasing to his Pride (which pride was infinitely puffing.) Flat∣tery was sweet to him, and he had enough of it, that made him bow a little, when no∣thing else could doe it. We may judge at the unreasonablenesse of all his demands, and supplyes of new <HI>Articles out of his in∣strument,</HI>
<PB N="55" REF="34"/>
by one: He required of the <HI>King</HI> a Commission to impower himselfe and a Committee teame of his owne choosing, to cut off the heads of Lawyers and Es∣cheators, and of all those, who by reason of their knowledge, and place were any way imployed in the Law. He fancied i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> those who were learned in the Law, were knocked ith head, all things would be ordered by the common people, either there would be no law, or that which was should be declared by him and his, subject to their will, with which his expression the day before did well agree; Then, attri∣buting all things to God (the God of Warre) and his conquering Armes, and striking his Sword (which shewed the <HI>pre∣sent power)</HI> on <HI>London-stone.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Cyclops,</HI> or Centaur of <HI>Kent</HI> spake these words: From this day (or within <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</NOTE> four dayes) all Law (or all the Lawes of <HI>Engl.</HI> as others) shall fall from <HI>Wat Tylers</HI> mouth. The Kings indeed had bound them∣selves, and were bound by the Lawes. They were named in them. <HI>Tyler</HI> was more than a King, he was an Emperour, he was above the Lawes; nor was it fit the old overworn <HI>MagnaCharta</HI> should hold him. <HI>The supreme Authority and legislative power</HI> (no one knowes how derived)
<PB N="56" REF="35"/>
<HI>were to be, and reside in him, according to the new establishment, Tyler</HI> like <HI>Homers Mars,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> was a whirlewinde, he was * <HI>Egnatius in Paterculus</HI> rather a Fen∣cer, a Swash buckler than a Senatour; his right A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>me, his brutish force, not Justice, not reason must sway all things, <HI>Tyler</HI> will not rule in fetters, his will, his violence shall be called Law, and grievous slavery under that will. falsly peace. Had those, whom no government never so sweet, and gracious will please, unlesse the <HI>Supreame power</HI> be given the people, seen the confusi∣ons and dangers, the cruelty and tyranny of these few dayes, they would quickly have changed this opinion.</P>
<P>The Knight performes his Embassy, he urges the Idol with great earnestness to see the <HI>King</HI> and speedily. He answers, if thou beest so much for hast, get thee back to the <HI>King</HI> thy Master, I will come when I list, yet he followes the Knight on Horse-back, but slowly. In the way, he is met by a Citizen, who had brought sixty doublets for the Commons, <HI>upon the Publique Faith.</HI> This Citizen askes him for his mony, he promises payment before night, &amp; presses on so near the <HI>King</HI> that his horse touched the croupe of the <HI>Kings</HI> horse.</P>
<P><HI>Froissart</HI> reports his discourse to the
<PB N="57" REF="35"/>
<HI>King,</HI> Sir <HI>King</HI> (sayes the Idol) seest thou yonder people? The <HI>King</HI> answers yes, and askes him what he meanes by the question. He replyes, they are all at my command, have sworne to me Faith, and Truth, to doe what I will have them. He and they had broke their Faith and truth to their Prince, and he thinkes these men will be true to him. Here though it be a digression too much, I cannot omit a passage of the late Civill Warres of <HI>France,</HI> begun and continued by the <HI>Iesuited</HI> party to extir∣pate <NOTE PLACE="marg">D' Avila.</NOTE> the royall Family there.</P>
<P><HI>Villers,</HI> Governour of <HI>Roüen</HI> for the ho∣ly League, tells the Duke of <HI>Mayen</HI> Cap∣taine Generall of the Rebellion, That he would not obey him; they were both com∣panions and spoilers of the State together: The King being levelled, all men else ought to be equall.</P>
<P>The Idoll, as he that demanded (so the Knight) nothing but Riot, continues his discourse (thus) Believest thou <HI>King,</HI> that these people will depart without thy Let∣ters? The <HI>King</HI> tells him, He means fairly, that he will make good his word, his Letters are neare finished, and they shall have them. But the glory of the Idoll (which was merely the benefit of fortune) begin to fade, his principali<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y was too
<PB N="58" REF="36"/>
cruell, too violent to be lasting. Vengeance here hovered over his head, and he who had been the destruction of multitudes hastens, nay precipitates his own fate, and ruins himself by his own fury, he puts him∣self into the <HI>Kings</HI> power, who should in his first towring had hebeen wisely wicked, likea Vulture of the Game, have flown at his throat. * The judicious politique will not begin to give over; However, will never venture himself in the Princes hands whom he has justly offended by treasons against his government.</P>
<P>† <HI>Charles</HI> of <HI>Burgundy</HI> confesses this to be a great folly; his Grandfather <HI>Philip</HI> lost his life at <HI>Montereau</HI> upon the <HI>Yonne</HI> by it, and our Idoll shall not escape bet∣ter.</P>
<P>Sir <HI>Iohn Newton</HI> the Knight imployed to fetch him, delivered his message on horseback, which is now remembred, and taken for an high neglect; besides, it see∣meth the carriage and words of the Knight were not very pleasing. Every trifle in omission was treason to the Idols person, and <HI>new state.</HI> He railes foulely drawes his Dagger, and bellowing out, <HI>Traitor,</HI> mena∣ces to strike the Knight, who returnes him in exchange the lie; and not to be behinde in blowes, drawes his: This the Idol takes
<PB N="59" REF="36"/>
for an intolerable affront, but the King fearfull of his servant, cooles and asswages the heat; he commands the Knight to dis∣mount, and offer up his Dagger to the Idol, which (though unwillingly) was done.</P>
<P>This would not take off his edge: The Prince who yeilds once to a Rebell, shall finde heaps of requests, and must deny no∣thing. The <HI>King</HI> had given away his <HI>Knights</HI> Dagger: now nothing will content <HI>Tyler</HI> but the <HI>Kings</HI> Sword, with which the <HI>Militia</HI> or power of Armes impliedly was sought. This he askes, then againe rushes upon the <HI>Knight,</HI> vowing never to eat till he have his Head.</P>
<P>When the Nobility and Gentry of the Kingdome, whom neither necessity nor misery could animate, lie downe trampled on by these Villaines without Soule, or motion; In comes the Major of <HI>London,</HI> Sir <HI>William Walworth,</HI> the everlasting ho∣nour of the Nation, a man who over-did ages of the <HI>Roman Scaevolae,</HI> or <HI>Curtii</HI> in an hours action &amp; snatches the <HI>King</HI> &amp; King∣dome out of these flames. He tells the <HI>King</HI> it would be a shame to all posterity to suf∣fer more insolencies from this Hongman, this lump of bloud. This the rest of the Courtiers now wakened by their owne
<PB N="60" REF="37"/>
danger, (For he who destroyes one man contrary to Law or Justice, gives all men else reason to feare themselves and take heed) are echoes to. This puts daring into the young <HI>King;</HI> he resolves to hazard all upon this chance: This way he could not but die kingly, at least, like a Gentleman, with the Sword, which God (of whose great M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>jesty he was a beam) gave him in his hand. The onely way left to avoid a shamefull death, was to run the danger of a brave one, and a wise coward (I will not say an honourable one) considering the in∣certainty of things under that Iron socage Tenure would think so.</P>
<P>The <HI>King</HI> commands the Major to arrest the Butcher: This was charge enough, and rightly understood, indeed there was then no time for fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>me nor tryall, the suspen∣sion of the Courts was <HI>Tylers</HI> act, his crime, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d he ought not to look for any advan∣tag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> from it: an Historian sayes the Duke of <HI>Guyse</HI>'s power was so much, that the ordinary formes of Justice could not be observed; faire Law is handsome, but it is not to be given to Wolves and Tygers, <HI>Tyler</HI> was a traytour, a common ene∣my; and against such (sayes a Father long agone) every man is a Souldier; whosoe∣ver st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ck too, st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uch as much in his owne
<PB N="61" REF="37"/>
defence, in his owne preservation, as the Kings: and the safety of the King and People made this course necessary; besides, <HI>Tylers</HI> crimes were publick and notori∣ous.</P>
<P>The generous Lord Major obeyes the sentence, which was given by the same power, by which the Judges of Courts sate and acted, when Justice flowed down from the fountaine in the ordinary channell, and which the damme head being thus trou∣bled by this Wolfe, could flow no other∣wise, which was authority sufficient; by this power <HI>Richards</HI> Captaines must fight when he has them, and kill those whom the Courts of Justice cannot deal with: <HI>Tyler</HI> saints, and shrinkes to what he had beene, he was as cowardly as cruell, and could not seem a man in any thing but that he was a theef, and a rebell; he askes the brave Major <HI>in what he was offended by him;</HI> This was a strange question to an honest man, he finds it so. <HI>The Major</HI> (sayes <HI>Fra∣issart) calls him false stinking knave, and tells him he shall not speake such words in the presence of his naturall Lord the King.</HI> The Major answers in full upon the accursed Sacrilegious Head of the Idol with his Sword. He struck heartily, and like a faith∣full zealous subject. <HI>Dagon</HI> of the <HI>Clownes</HI>
<PB N="62" REF="38"/>
sinkes at his feete. The <HI>Kings</HI> followers in∣viron him round, <HI>Iohn Standish</HI> an Esquire of the Court, alights, and runs him into the belly, which thrust sent him into another World, to accompany him who taught Rebellion, and murder first. Event was then no signe of a good cause.</P>
<P>All History now brands him for a Trai∣tour, which by some will be attributed to his miscarriage: witho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> doubt had he prospered in the <HI>Works,</HI> he had had all the honours which goe along with prosperity. The <HI>King</HI> had beene the wrong doer, and his afflictions, if nothing in so much youth could have beene found out, had beene crimes; we must overpower those whom we would make guilty. <HI>Henry</HI> the great of <HI>France</HI> under the <HI>Popes</HI> interdict, is told by a Gentleman, Sir, if we be overcome, we shall dye condemned hereticks, if your Majesty conquer, the censures shall b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> revoked, they will fall of themselves. He who reads the mischiefes of his usurpa∣tion will thinke he perished too late.</P>
<P>Now I come to an Act of <HI>Richards,</HI> the most glorious of his History, which the <HI>Annals</HI> past can no where parallel, here his infancy excells his after man-hood. Here, and in the gallantry of his death he appeares a full Prince, and perhaps vies
<PB N="63" REF="38"/>
with all the bayes of his usurpers tri∣umphs.</P>
<P><HI>Alexander</HI> the Monarch of the world, (Not more wondered at for his victories, then for that suppressing the Sedition of his <HI>Macedons</HI> in <HI>Asia,</HI> tired, and unable to march, whither his ambition carried him on wings) leaps from his Throne of State, into the Battels of his <HI>Phalanges</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>raged, Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ses thirteene of the chiefe malecontents, and delivers them to the custody of his Guards. <HI>Curtius</HI> knowes not what he should impute this amazement of the Se∣ditious to, every man returning upon it to his old duty, and obedience, and ready to yeild himselfe up into the same hands: it might be (sayes he) The veneration of the Majesty of <HI>Kings,</HI> which the Nations sub∣mitted <NOTE PLACE="marg">Li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</NOTE> under, worship equally with the Gods, or of himselfe which laid the tem∣pest. That confidence too of the Duke <HI>Alessandro</HI> of <HI>Parma,</HI> in a mutiny of the <HI>German</HI> Reiters at <HI>Namures</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s memorable, who made his way with his Sword alone through the points of all their Lances, into the middest of their Troops, and brought thence by the coller one of the Muti∣neers, whom he commanded to be hang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d to the terrour of the rest. The youth of <HI>Richard</HI> begat rather contempt, than reve∣rence,
<PB N="64" REF="39"/>
of which too these <HI>Clownes</HI> breasts were never very full: When the fall of the Idol was known to the rout, they put themselves into a posture of defence, thun∣der out nothing but vengeance to the <HI>King</HI> and his, whom they now arraign of Murder and Tyranny: He is guilty of <HI>Innocent bloud;</HI> a <HI>Tyrant,</HI> a <HI>Traitour,</HI> an <HI>Homicide,</HI> the <HI>publique Enemy of the Common wealth.</HI> Richard Plantagin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t is indicted <HI>in the name of the people of England, of treason, and other heynous crimes.</HI> He is now become lesse than <HI>Tylers</HI> Ghost, a Traitour to the <HI>Free∣borne people.</HI></P>
<P>His treason was, he would not destroy himselfe, he would not open his body to <HI>Tylars</HI> full blow. They roare out, our <HI>Captaine Generall</HI> is slaine treacherously, let us stand to it, and revenge his precious bloud, or die with him: I cannot passe this place without some little wonder; had these Ruffians (with whom Kings hedged about by holy Scripture, and Lawes hu∣mane, are neither divine nor sacred) beene asked whether <HI>Tyler</HI> the Idol, of their own clay and hands, might have been tryed, touched or struck, according to their re∣senting this blow here: let his tyrannies, his exorbitances have beene what they would, they would have answer'd no doubt
<PB N="65" REF="39"/>
in the negative: Though <HI>Richard</HI> might have been struck thorough and thorough, <HI>Tyler</HI> who had usurped his power, must have been sacred, it must have been treason to touch him: <HI>Phocas</HI> must not be hurt: in <HI>Tylers</HI> case <HI>Straw</HI> would allow the old texts againe: The powers were to be obey∣ed. Their bowes were drawne when the <HI>King</HI> gallops up to them alone, and riding round the throng, asks them, What mad∣nesse it was that armed them thus against their own peace, and his life, whether they would have no end of things or demands.</P>
<P>He tells them if <HI>Liberty</HI> be their onely aim, as hitherto they have pretended, they may assure themselves of it, and that it is an extreme folly to seek to make that our owne with the breach of Faith, of Lawes, with impieties, violating God and Man, which we may come by fairely. But they trod not the path to <HI>Liberty,</HI> That where every man commands, no man can be free; the <HI>Liberty</HI> too they fancy cannot be had, the world cannot subsist without Order and Subjection, men cannot be freed from Lawes: If they were, there could be no society, no civility any where, Men must be shunned as much as Wolves or Beares, ra∣pine and bloud-shed would over-run the world, the spoyler must feare the next
<PB N="66" REF="40"/>
comer, like savage beasts, who hurt others, and know not it is ill to hurt them, men would devout men, the stronger Thiefe would swallow up the rest; no Relations would be sacred, where every man has the power of the Sword, the aged sire (could there be any such) must defend his silver haires from the unnaturall violence of his own Sons.</P>
<P>He addes, if there can be any just cause of Sedition, yet is the Sedition unjust which outlasts it, which continues, when the cause is yeilded to, and taken away; that if his Prerogative has beene sometimes grie∣vous, his tax's heavy, and any of those they call evill Counsellours faulty, they ought to remember, in their first risings, and all along in all their <HI>Oathes,</HI> and <HI>Co∣venants</HI> they swore continually not to <HI>in∣vade the Monarchy,</HI> nor <HI>touch the Rights of his free Crowne.</HI> You ought to remember your own Remonstrances; you once de∣clared, that you acknowledged the Maxime of the Law, <HI>The King can dos no wrong; If any ill be committed in matters of State, the Councellors; if in matters of Law, the Iudges must answer for it</HI>—My person was not to be violated. He expects they should deale with him, as the honest Husbandman does in overflowes of Waters, who cleares
<PB N="67" REF="40"/>
and draines his ground, repaires the bankes, but does not usurp upon the streame, does not inhance within the Channell. And farther that quarrels to his Government and Lawes are unreasonable from those, who out of ambition arme to overthrow both, that reformation is not the worke of Sedition, which ever disorders what is well setled. He conjures them to forsake these suries, who, sayes he, abuse their lightness meerely for their owne ends, whose com∣panions or masters they were lately, now are they but their G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>urds, and that if they refuse a subjection according to all Lawes Divine and humane to his Scepter, they must become slaves and tributaries to their Iron, to the Flailes and Pitchforkes of some Mushrome of their owne dirt, and that advancing their Mushrome, thus upon his power by the wayes of force, gives an example to the next tumults against them∣selves.</P>
<P>There can be no safety for any new <NOTE PLACE="marg">Non est diuturua possessio in quam gla∣dio indu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> mur. <HI>Gurt.</HI></NOTE> power raised upon this force, the obedi∣ence to that upon these Rules being limit∣ted, and annexed to the force, and success, and to yeild, and give way to the next power visible which shall overbeare it. A way to thrust a Nation into a state of War, continuall perjury and impiety to the
<PB N="68" REF="41"/>
Worlds end. This Realm (as he goes on) is my inheritance, which I tooke possession of after the death of my Grand-father be∣ing a child, and did I claime onely by your gift (which I shall never grant) yet are not you free, to make a new choice, you are bound to me by <HI>Oathes</HI> and <HI>Compacts,</HI> and no right of new compliance, or submission can be left you to transferre. He concludes, That despair was a dangerous sinne, which would drive them head-long to destructi∣on; That whatsoever their offences had been, they were not above his mer∣cy.</P>
<P>He bids them not trouble themselves for <HI>Tyler,</HI> a base fellow, who thrust them into dangers, and blew them into a storme to raise himselfe upon the billowes, upon the ruines of his Country. He promises to lead them, he will be their Captaine, if they will follow him he will please them in all their desires. This he spake, to draw them off farther into <HI>Smithfield,</HI> fearing they would againe fall to burning of houses. They now wanted their Devill, who possessed them, and being in doubt whether they should kill the <HI>King,</HI> or returne home with his Charters, there being no incendiary to command, follow the <HI>King</HI> in suspence; <HI>Baal</HI> and <HI>Straw</HI> about this time amazed at
<PB N="69" REF="41"/>
the Idols fall, lose courage and fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>p away. In the meane time the stout Major spurres to the City with one servant, where in a few words he acquaints the Citizens with the Kings perill and his owne, and requests their sudden assistance, if not for himselfe, for the King, who (sayes he) is in danger now to be murthered. Some loyall hearts, some good men of the Kings party arme, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals. Froiss.</NOTE> and joyn, to the number of one thousand, and range themselves in the street, expe∣cting some of the Cavaliers, of the Kings Knights to conduct them, resolved either to overcome, or not to feare the Conque∣rours.</P>
<P>Sir <HI>Robert Knowles,</HI> a renowned Com∣mander in the French Warres of the Kings Grandfather (called falsly <HI>Canol</HI> by <HI>Poly∣dor,</HI> and others) undertakes this charge. Sir <HI>Perducas D' Albret</HI> (called <HI>D' Albreth)</HI> a noble Gascoigne and a Commander too in those Warres, <HI>Nicholas Brembre</HI> the Kings Draper, and other Alderm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n, come in with their Levies, and march to the King in sight of the Rebels. There the King Knights the brave <HI>Wil: Walworth. Iohn Standish,</HI> one of his Esquires, <HI>Nicho∣las Brembre, Iohn Philpot,</HI> (a most gene∣rous Citizen, famous for his faithfull ser∣vice to his Prince in the times succeeding)
<PB N="70" REF="42"/>
and others. The N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bility about the King desire him to strike off an hundred or two of the Clowns heads, in revenge of the in∣juries and infamy they had received from them. Sir <HI>Robert Knowles</HI> would have him fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l on and cut them all to pieces. The King dislikes both these counsels; He sayes many of these unhappy men were awed to side, without either malice to his P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rson or Power; and that if the first advise were taken, the most innocent might be punish∣ed, and the guilty scape; If the second, the very Rebel and the Counterfeit (the for∣ced one) must be swallowed up together, which was high injustice. Yet were there many of these R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bels called to account, and their acts of bloud, rapine and burning cost them deare; but these acts of theirs done against Law, were punished legally, upon the finding of Juries, when the Tu∣mults were composed: Which was faire and handsome, and shewes the honoura∣ble justice of our King. All that was done against them that night was, to forbid the Citizens by Proclamation to entertain any of these men in the City, or communicate with them; and to command all men who had not dwelt there for one yeare before, to depart:</P>
<P>So farre was the young King from ap∣proving
<PB N="71" REF="42"/>
the cruelty of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> counsels, that in the next place, he causes the Char∣ters, which he had promised them to be delivered; yet some may suppose this but a pardon of shew, and the pardon-piece of the Charters, as well as the other part, ra∣ther a piece of policy than any thing else, the Countries being yet tumult<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ous, the Clownes were upon their good behaviour, that was a condition of their pardon, which they would not observe, they com∣mit new outrages, break the Kings Laws, &amp; pluck down the vengeance of Justice upon their heads afresh, they did not give over their mischiefs after their return sayes, <HI>Wals.</HI> By the King and his Counsell, the Charters, as extorted out of force, and necessity were recalled; and though the M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ynie generally were pardoned, the King (againe provoked) staid but for a fit time to take vengeance on the Ring-leaders, and punish particular offendors who could not be forgiven: It being necessary in so des∣perate a Revolt for the terrour of others, to make <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of some such maliciou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> disturbers of the peace, as would never have been reclaimed. The Kings Charters contained a Manumission of the Villains, and abolition of the memory of what was past for the rest. The tenor, sayes <HI>Walsing∣ham,</HI>
<PB N="72" REF="43"/>
of the Charters <HI>ixtorted from the King by force,</HI> was this, (he gives us onely that of <HI>Hartfordshire</HI> the Province of his Monastery.)</P>
<P>RIchard <HI>by the Grace of God King of</HI> England <HI>and of</HI> France, <HI>Lord of</HI> Ireland, <HI>to all his Bailies, and others his trusty, to whom these Letters shall come greeting. Know yee that we of our speciall grace have made free all our Lieges, and every of our subjects of</HI> Hartfordshire, <HI>and we free those, and every of them from all</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Ab omni bondagio.</NOTE> <HI>bondage, and quit them by these presents, and also we pardon the same our Lieges, and sub∣jects, for all Felonies, Treasons, Tres∣passes, and extortions by them, or any of them in any wise done, or committed, and also every Outlary, or Outlaries, if any against them, or any of them, are or shall be published, and our full peace to them or any of them, therefore we grant, in witnesse whereof these our Letters we have caused to be made Pa∣tents. Witnesse our selfe at</HI> London <HI>the</HI> 15. <HI>day of</HI> June, <HI>the</HI> 4th <HI>yeare of our Reigne.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="73" REF="43"/>
This Charter was granted about the time the <HI>Clownes</HI> of <HI>Essex</HI> disbanded, and received theirs, it was brought into <HI>Har∣fordshire</HI> to Saint <HI>Albanes</HI> by <HI>Wallingford</HI> one of the Towne; * Friday sayes <HI>Wal∣singham</HI> the day of tribulation, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Illucescen∣te die Venerls.</NOTE> <HI>&amp;c.</HI> (which was the 16 of <HI>Iune)</HI> the Towns. men of Saint <HI>Albanes</HI> being at the time of Matines acquainted by those of <HI>Barnet</HI> with the command of the Ordinance or Act for repairing to <HI>London</HI> presently with the Esquires of the Abbot set forth; So that I conceive the day of this Charter is mistaken in it by the Monke.</P>
<P>The <HI>Clownes</HI> throw down their Armes at the <HI>Kings</HI> feet, sue for mercy, and deli∣ver up their chiefs; the principall of which Priest <HI>Straw</HI> was after drawne from his hi∣ding holes, and laid hold of by the Kings Officers. What became of them we shall see below, in the visitation made by the <HI>King,</HI> and his Ministers, through the Pro∣vinces in uproare.</P>
<P>The Commons of <HI>Kent</HI> now scatter and dissolve, the heads of the Archbishop, Lord <HI>Prior,</HI> and the rest, are taken down from the bridge, and the Idols advanced there; That <HI>Baal</HI> should now be taken in an old house is an errour of the Knights; <HI>Baal</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Froiss. <HI>so.</HI></NOTE> must take his turn, but he shall have a long∣ger
<PB N="74" REF="44" MS="y"/>
runne for it. That the dagger should now be given in honour of Sir <HI>William Walworth</HI> as an addition to the City armes is Fabulous, this dagger is the Sword of St. <HI>Paul,</HI> and was borne by the City when <HI>Ty∣ler</HI> was living.</P>
<P>The <HI>King</HI> now rides to <HI>Westminster</HI> where he gives God thankes for his de∣liverance, and presents his offering to the Virgin <HI>Mary,</HI> in her Chappell of the Piew, next he visits the Princesse mother in the Tower Royall, called the Queenes War∣drobe, and bids her rejoyce, for (sayes he) this day I have recovered mine heritage, the Realme of <HI>England</HI> near lost, the Lords <NOTE PLACE="marg">Froiss.</NOTE> returne to their owne houses. The other Countries now in combustion, and upon their march to <HI>London,</HI> make halt, they were thunder-strucken at the disaster of the Idol, they hated the fortune not the wic∣kednesse of that monster, And tarry to poure out those plagues at home, if they be not checked, which before they intended to carry farther off. The example and suc∣cesse of the Idol had moved with many, but his invitation, and sollicitation by the Emissaries of this confederacy and spirit more. The S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ctaries, or ringleaders of the hurden rustick raggamuffins in the severall Provinces of the association (while <HI>Tyler</HI>
<PB N="75" REF="44"/>
was thus busied in the chiefe seat of his new Dominions) promote the cause, and pursue the instructions of the Prince of Di∣vells, they were all to tread his steps, as we shall finde in what followes.</P>
<P>I have before spoken of the Summons of <NOTE PLACE="marg">The lewd prankes of the Clowns at Saint <HI>Albanes.</HI></NOTE> the I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ol to fetch the bordering rogues in∣to the <HI>Line of Communication,</HI> who were to serve as Auxiliaries onely, to strengthen <HI>Tyler,</HI> rather than to inrich themselves, and likely to be casheered, and cast off when he had perfected his <HI>Worke:</HI> amongst these take hells were the Towns-men of Saint <HI>Albane</HI> with the <HI>Abbots</HI> servants shuffled in the throng of purpose to oversee and awe the <HI>Clownes</HI> from the new fangles of our fan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ticks; These as is related, were sworne to the <HI>Ingagement</HI> at <HI>Heibury,</HI> whence they come to <HI>London,</HI> whither they are no sooner got, but the Towns men se∣parate from the servants of the Monastery, and in St. <HI>Mary bow.</HI> Church does their profane Conventicle consult how to make advantage of the tumult.</P>
<P>And what pretences of revolt from their Lord <HI>Abbot</HI> would seem most faire, and taking. Here they make not the causes of their disobedience, they were hatched secretly amongst themselves, they delibe∣rate how to perfect things, how to come
<PB N="76" REF="45"/>
to effects. The inlarging the bounds of their common, free fishing, hunting in cer∣taine places, when they pleased, and Hand∣mills, that the Baily of the Liberty shall no more meddle within the Precincts of the Towne, the revocation of Charters preju∣diciall to the <HI>Free-borne</HI> Burgesses, cancel∣ling the Bonds of their Fore-fathers made to <HI>Abbot Richard,</HI> are the Propositions first voted.</P>
<P>One, who would be wiser than the rest, perswades them not to attempt things rashly, and giddily, without authority, he tells them that <HI>Wat Tyler, Protectour and Captaine Generall</HI> of the <HI>Clownes</HI> was near, that the <HI>Protectour,</HI> was a righter of wrongs raised, and inspired by providence to redeeme the faithfull <HI>Commons</HI> from <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals. Ducem ri∣baldorum, ut accepta ab co pote∣state, &amp;c.</NOTE> the thraldome of the wicked, <HI>At the suite of the godly party,</HI> sayes he, <HI>Tyler has accep∣ted the Government, he is to govern the two Nations; The Supreame executive Power resides in him,</HI> from him (sayes he) and from the keepers of the liberties let us seek for remedy.</P>
<P>Let us make our addresses to him, let us seeke to his <HI>Highnesse</HI> for power, and Comm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ssion; This he said (as <HI>Walsingham</HI> writes) supposing a greater than <HI>Tyler</HI> should not be seene in the Kingdome, that
<PB N="77" REF="45"/>
<HI>Tylers</HI> greatnesse, for the time to come would onely be eminent; That the Lawes <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> of the Land (the most ancient English, Saxon Lawes) would be of no force, of no validity, because the most of the Lawyers were already murthered, and the rest in their account not long lived, the Axes edge was turned towards them. He concludes, let us returne home, and in the puissance of <HI>Wat,</HI> and our selves, force the <HI>Abbot</HI> to reason; If he deny our requests, we will awe hm with burning and demolishing the Monastery, with killing the Monkes, we will threaten not to leave one stone up∣on another; Others conceive it more safe to petition the <HI>King</HI> (who might be spoken with by every man, and durst refuse no∣thing) for his Letters under the Privy Seale, commanding the <HI>Abbot,</HI> to restore to the Towns-men the rights, and Liberties which their ancestours injoyed in the time of King <HI>Henry</HI> the first, as if the English Church had beene lately indowed, the Mo∣nasteries founded, their Royalties, Liber∣ties, Priviledges granted by the <HI>Norman</HI> Princes, than which nothing could be more false. The most Christian Saxon Kings of blessed memory, twelve of which died Martyrs of the Faith, ten shine glorious Starres in the Calender of Saints, were all
<PB N="78" REF="46"/>
nursing Fathers of the Church, scarcely wat there one in the illustrious rolle, who gave not Lands and Possessions with Ex∣emptions, and Immunities to the Church, who erected not Bishopricks, or Monaste∣ries into which thirty of our crowned, heads, <HI>Kings,</HI> or <HI>Queenes</HI> entred, the su∣perstition of the ages then ought not to blemish their Piety: The <HI>Mercian</HI> King <HI>Offa,</HI> his Son <HI>Ecgfryd.</HI> King <HI>Ethelred,</HI> King <HI>Edward,</HI> are the founders and donours of St. <HI>Albanes</HI> what King <HI>Henry</HI> the first did for the Towne I cannot say, nor how am∣ple its Liberties were then, this is true, he confirmes the grants of the <HI>Saxon</HI> Princes, to the Monastery, and addes the Norman <NOTE PLACE="marg">All these grants end with horri∣ble curses against Sa∣criledge.</NOTE> seale to strengthen the <HI>Saxon</HI> Crosses, this is all, but truth is not necessary in such up∣roares, the credulity of a light headed mul∣titude is quickly abused, their duty and obedience easily corrupted without it.</P>
<P>To keepe our way; Both these Coun∣sels are approved. <HI>William Greyndcob</HI> an <NOTE PLACE="marg">Walsingh.</NOTE> Hinde, who had eaten the breade of the Monastery for the most part of his life, is elected with others, and sent on this er∣rand to the King, before whom he kneeles six times out of zeale to prevaile. This Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> too was made principall Prolocutor (sayes our Monk) or Speaker to the Idol: before <NOTE PLACE="marg">Walsingh.</NOTE>
<PB N="79" REF="46"/>
whose sordid Excellency and his unclean Councell he complaines of the grievous ty∣ranny of the Abbot and Prior, (some few Monks are thrust in to make up the num∣ber) of the oppressures of the Commons, of withholding the wages of poor Labou∣rers, the design was to rowz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the Wolfe.</P>
<P><HI>Tyler</HI> meant not to leave <HI>London,</HI> yet he promises, if need be, to send twenty thousand of the <HI>Saints,</HI> who shall not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>all to shave the beards of the Abbot and the rest, which signified (in plain English) cut∣ting off their heads.</P>
<P>The gracious <HI>Captaine Generall</HI> was yet more kind; he vowes, if it be convenient, to assist them in his owne person. He gives them directions and orders to governe themselves by, and makes their obedience here, a condition of his love. These Or∣ders were generally injoyned by our En∣glish <HI>Mahomet,</HI> through all the Provinces of his Conquest, and were framed accor∣ding to the Law of his bloody <HI>Alchoran.</HI> He sweares them to omit nothing either in his Commands or Doctrine. A servant of the Abbot, one of the spies upon the Towns∣men, rides in full career to S. <HI>Albanes,</HI> and gives intelligence to the Abbie of the ex∣ploits of the New Masters at <HI>London.</HI> He tells them in what manner that dist of a
<PB N="82" REF="47"/>
Captaine <HI>(Tyler)</HI> fullyed and polluted with the bloud of the Noblesse, had butchered the English Patriarch, and the Lord Trea∣surer. That <HI>London,</HI> the den of these rave∣nous beasts, falsly called <HI>The Chamber of her Kings,</HI> was likely now to become the Charnelhouse of <HI>Richard,</HI> and his Loyall vassals; That these Fiends, who would goe for <HI>Saints,</HI> and the onely good <HI>Patriots</HI> commit the acts of Theeves, and Murthe∣rers, neither reverencing Religion nor Lawes: And that the Conquering French, who makes faire war, nay the barbarous Scot, broke out of the fastnesse of his owne Desart, mortall enemies of the Nation, could not spoile not ruine with more cru∣elty and villanie. No Mercy, sayes he, (yeild who will upon mercy) no favour, no good∣nesse can be expected from this rout of Wolves. He bids those pointed at, and na∣med by <HI>Greyndcob</HI> to <HI>Tyler,</HI> shift for them∣selves, which they are not long in resolving of. The Prior, four Monks, and some of their servants, one part horsed, another on foot, fly for their lives, not assuring themselves till they got to <HI>Tynmouth,</HI> a Priory of this Monastery of Saint <HI>Albane</HI> in <HI>Northumber∣land, William Greyndcob,</HI> and <HI>William Ca∣dindon</HI> a Baker, on Friday had hastened to S. <HI>Albanes,</HI> that they might make the ho∣nour
<PB N="81" REF="47"/>
of the atchievement theirs by first ap∣pearing in the action; these brag aloud of the prosperity of affaires, that they were no more drudges and slaves, but Lords for the time to come; that they had brought about great and wonderfull feats against the Abbie; they propose, first to defie the <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals. a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣dum.</NOTE> Abbot, to renounce all amity and peace with him, then to breake downe his folds and gates in <HI>Fauconwood, Eywood,</HI> and his other words, and to pull down the Under∣bowsers <NOTE PLACE="marg">Sub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣rii.</NOTE> house, standing over against the Fish-market, and hindering the prospect of the Burgesses and Nobility of the Town, this is their owne style, a Nobility scarce to be parallel'd in the world disco∣vered, unlesse we fetch in the Man-eaters of <HI>Brasil,</HI> who have neither Letters nor Lawes, acknowledge neither God nor Prince.</P>
<P>This night the first Seene of the Trage∣die is acted; the next day, being Saturday, fatall to the Hangman <HI>Tyler;</HI> the upstart Nobility of Churls assemble and make Pro∣clamation, That no man able to serve his Country, presume to sleight the Lieutenants of the Idol, but that every man furnish himself with such Arms as he can provide, to attend them the Lieutenants in his own defence. The Crew summoned are com∣manded
<PB N="82" REF="48"/>
to presse the Gentry for the sur∣vice, and to cut off the heads of those who would not joyn with them, and sweare to be faithfull to them; beheading, burning houses, forfeiture of goods were menaced to all that would not assist the Forces rai∣sed by <HI>Tyler,</HI> and fight the <HI>Lords Battels,</HI> that is, for the <HI>Cause.</HI> This, sayes our Monke, was the charge of their Lord and Master <HI>Wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> this was his Rubrie of blood.</P>
<P>Next, with great pomp they march to <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>um megna pompa.</NOTE> <HI>Fauconwood;</HI> to levell the slips of their haste and night-worke, something they feared might be left whole, upon review when <HI>Root and Branoh</HI> were pared and torne up, they retire.</P>
<P>The other Growtnolls of the Neigh∣bourhood, subject to the distresse, or Sieg∣niory of Saint <HI>Albane,</HI> wait for them; these were cited upon the same threats to meet, and promised belly-fulls, care loads of <HI>Li∣berties.</HI> Now or never for the <HI>Liberty of the Subject,</HI> and the <HI>power of godlinesse.</HI> This supply swells them into huge hopes, it puffs them up. <HI>Greyndcob</HI> and <HI>Cadindon</HI> more haughty now than ever; Lead their Bat∣taliaes, blustering with surly pride and dis∣daine, to the Gates of the Monastery, which with the same loftinesse they com∣mand the Porter to set open. Some of the
<PB N="83" REF="48"/>
company, friends of the house, had given private intelligence to the Abbots of the contrivances against him, who had instru∣cted his servants how to carry themselves towards this tag and rag of Swaines, they observe them punctually.</P>
<P>That they may seeme pious in their en∣trance, they free the publique Malefactors out of the Abbots prison; but so that they shou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d owe faith hereafter, and grace of the benefit to the <HI>Commons</HI> (a name the most honourable, and which must swallow up all things else) and ins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>parably stick to them, One of the offenders, whom they suppose unworthy of <HI>Liberty</HI> or life, (growne Judges and Executioners by the same inspiration and spirit) they behead on the ground before the Gates, then fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> his head upon the Pillory, roaring with that divelish cry they had learnt at <HI>London.</HI> This was plaine murther by the Law what∣soever this mans crime was, those Rogue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> were guilty in a most high nature, so th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> besides the basenesse of their condition, they were incapable of any jurisdiction by the antient foundamentall Lawes of <HI>En∣gland,</HI> as being Traitours, and out of the Kings faith; but to wave all thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> by these ancient Lawes, every prisoner might de∣mand <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 114.</NOTE> <HI>Oyer,</HI> hearing of the Judges Com∣mission,
<PB N="84" REF="49"/>
these villains had neither authority nor Commission, but from <HI>Tylers</HI> Sword, which was but a derivative of his usurpati∣on. No act of which can be just, the foun∣dation of his tyranny this way, in being just, and illegall at the first.</P>
<P>From the Idols first entrance no act of confirmation or grant was done (could any such act be done and valid) to establish or make a right, by the power which had that right to bestow, he asked for a Commission of life, and death, but was refused; and his arbitrary acts were onely a continuance of his intrusion, and of the violence upon which he began.</P>
<P>To fill up their tattered Regiments, their fellow Leaguers or <HI>Covend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ters</HI> of <HI>Barnet, Luton, Watford,</HI> and the Townes round enter St. <HI>Albanes</HI> of the same Sacrilegious aff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ction to the Abby, in all these Conspi∣racies the Church was the maine marke ai∣med at, about the carcasses of the Cathe∣dralls and Abbies (they were now nothing else) did these vultures gather; in the same conjuncture of time enters <HI>Richard Wal∣lingford,</HI> head borough or Constable of the place, who tarried at <HI>London</HI> for the Kings Letters of Manumission and Pardon, (which <HI>Greyndcob</HI> had been so earnest for) bearing the Kings Banner or Pennon of
<PB N="85" REF="49"/>
the Arms of S. <HI>George,</HI> being the red Cross before him, according to the fashion of the <HI>Clownes</HI> of <HI>London.</HI> The <HI>Commons</HI> hea∣ting of his coming, poure themselves out in heaps to meet him. He alights, strikes the Penon into the Earth, and bids them keep close and incircle it like a Standard. He intreats them to continue about it, and expect his return, and the Lieutenants, who were resolved with all speed to treat with the Abbot, and would suddenly bring them an answer to their propositions. Which said, he and they enter the Church, and send for the Abbot to appeare before them, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd answer the <HI>Commons</HI> (onely sa∣cred then, and to whom all knees were to bow.) The Abbot was at first resolute to die for the liberty of his Church, (a pious gallantry which will be admirable) but overcome with the prayers of his Monkes, who told him, as things stood his death could advantage nothing, that these stink∣ing Knaves, these Hell-hounds were deter∣mined to murder the Monkes; and burne the Monastery if they had the repulse, and that there was no way of safety but to fall downe before these <HI>Baals,</HI> he yeilds. After he was come to the Church, and a short salutation past; <HI>Wallingford</HI> reaches out to him the Kings Letter or Writ (as <HI>Walsingham</HI>
<PB N="86" REF="50"/>
calls it) in these words, as I have rendred them out of the barbarous French of that age.</P>
<P><HI>BEloved in God, At the Petition of our loved Lieges of the Towne of St.</HI> Albane <HI>we will and command you, That certaine Charters being in your custody made by our Progenitour King</HI> Henry <HI>to the Burgesses and good Peo∣ple of the said Towne of commune of pasture and fishing, and of certain other commodities expressed in the said Charters, in what they say, you doe as Law, and Reason requires, So that they may not have any matter to complaine to us for that Cause. Given under our Signet at</HI> London <HI>the</HI> 15. <HI>day of</HI> June, <HI>the fourth yeare of our Reigne.</HI></P>
<P>Here certainly againe is a mistake of the day, for till Friday the 16. of <HI>Iune,</HI> the <HI>Clownes</HI> of Saint <HI>Albanes</HI> (as is observed) stirred not. Thus is the King forced to be the Author of other mens injustice, to con∣sent to those insolencies (and wrongs) which must undoe all those, those who are faithfull to him, to please a base rable,
<PB N="87" REF="50"/>
ingaged to turn in the end their destroying hands upon himselfe and his royall Family, The Abbot receives the Letter with due reverence, and reads it: then thinking to worke upon the consciences of these Hel∣hounds, he begins a discourse of Law, Rea∣son, Equity, and Justice, Law and Reason were the princely bounds betwixt which the <HI>Kings</HI> commands ran. He tells them whatsoever was demanded by them, had beene long agoe determined in the Courts of Justice, by the publick Judges, persons knowing, and honourable, sworn to do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> equill right.</P>
<P>That the Records were kept amongst the <HI>Kings</HI> Rolls at <HI>Westminster,</HI> whence he inferred, That according to the Lawes antiently in use, they had neither right nor claime left: he addes, the usurpation upon anothers propriety is tyranny in the ab∣stract; it is the greatest injustice: the very heathens will have it unnaturall to inrich our selves, to make our advantage from Spoyle and robbery, but force is odious to God and man, that aggravates the sinne; violence is a more heynous crime than theft. This was ridiculous wisdome, con∣sidering who they were the good Abbot spake to, he had forgot perhaps how <HI>An∣tigon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s</HI> armed to invade and seize the Ci∣ties,
<PB N="88" REF="51"/>
and Countries of other Princes, laughed at the serious grave folly of one; who presented him with a tractate of Justice. <HI>Wallingford</HI> with his hand upon his Sword takes him off pertinently, as reflecting upon the manners of men, whose treasons prosper, and practise of the times; In which new men did not advance them∣selves by Vertue, by Learning, by Justice, or Valour, but by Murder and Robbery.</P>
<P>My Lord (sayes he) every story is not true, because it is eloquently told, you in∣deavour here to inveigle and deceive us in a long discourse of equity, of Law, and Justice, we come not hither for words but things, we pretend not to refute your rea∣sons, (which are but injust defences of your oppression, but cunning subtilities, but colours to paint ore the wrongs you doe us, nor can we, the rudenesse of our education must disable us for this part, we have beene borne and bred under your Dominion, slaves, and Villens to you, un∣der a Dominion so unmanly cruell, you have alwayes kept us deprived, not onely of all meanes of learning or knowledge, but would willingly have taken away ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> very reason and common understanding; that we might grone under our miseries, with the feeling of beasts, but be Masters
<PB N="89" REF="51"/>
neither of sence nor language for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> com∣plaint.</P>
<P>It is time now that we of the <HI>Commo∣nalty</HI> as you call and range us, should take our turne of command, however of <HI>Li∣berty.</HI> Nor is this to be wondered at if you consider our strength, and the happi∣nesse of the new <HI>Modell,</HI> the eminency of the Commons is visible to every eye, theirs is the present, theirs is the <HI>Supreame Power,</HI> we are armed, and we will not thinke of the Lawes, not regard them, they onely submit to Lawes, who want power to helpe themselves. Besides these Lawes you tell us of, are but the will of our enemies in forme and rule, they were made by them, they favour them; And our Cap∣taine Generall <HI>Tyler,</HI> who has conquered <NOTE PLACE="marg">Per{que} ute∣rum sonlpe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> hic matris agendus.</NOTE> (a sad unhappy word, where it is used of one part of a Nation against another, and of <HI>Benjamin</HI> against <HI>Israel,</HI> by the worst and least against the better and greater) the makers of them, the Law-givers, was so become above the Lawes themselves; your reasons, when these Lawes were bac∣ked with force, when <HI>your King</HI> could protect you, before our successe, might have served well enough; Now we ex∣pected them not, nor will we accept them.</P>
<P><PB N="90" REF="52"/>
He concludes in perswasion, not to ex∣asperate the <HI>godly party,</HI> the righteous <HI>Com∣mons,</HI> who sayes he will not be appeased, will not give over, not lay downe Armes till they be Masters of their desires.</P>
<P>The Abbot, entring into a new speech, is againe stopped, and told, the thousand before the doores of his Monastery sent for him not to parly, but consent, which they looke he should be sudden in, if not we (sayes <HI>Wallingford)</HI> the Lieutenants, chosen by the <HI>Captaine representatives of the people, will deliver up and resigne the pow∣ers to him, which we received of him.</HI> We have <HI>voted,</HI> if you comply not, to send for the Captaine Generall <HI>Tyler,</HI> and twenty thousand of his <HI>Militia</HI> to the danger of this place, and of the Monkes heads.</P>
<P>The Abbot here recites his good deeds, how often in their necessities he had relie∣ved them, he had beene (he sayes) their spirituall Father thirty two yeares, in all which time, no man had beene grieved, or oppressed by him, this giving implyedly the lie to <HI>Wallingford,</HI> they grant, but will not be denied. The Obligations and Char∣ters, which they r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>quire, are delivered them, which they burne in the Market∣place, neare the Crosse; This did not con∣tent them, they aske for an antient Char∣ter
<PB N="91" REF="52"/>
concerning the Towne Liberties, the capitall Letters of which (say they) were one of Gold, another of Azure; <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">De azorio</NOTE> The Abbot prayes them to be satisfied for the time, he protests, they have all he has to give them, he knew of no more, yet he would make a search, and if any such deed could be found, it should faithfully be de∣livered to them; This too was the answer of the <HI>Covent,</HI> it was agreed that the Abbot should after dinner disclaime under his hand and seale in all things prejudiciall to their Liberty. In memory of an old suit betwixt Abbot <HI>Richard</HI> the first, and the Townsmen in the reignes of <HI>William</HI> the second, and <HI>Henry</HI> the first, wherein the Townsmen were overthrown, were laid Milstones before the doore of the <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Locutorii.</NOTE> Parler. These <HI>Iohn</HI> the Barber with others tooke away, as a token of victory over the Law; these they break into small pieces, and di∣stribute amongst the worthies, as the sacred Bread is given in the <HI>Eucharist.</HI></P>
<P>Who could forbeare <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eares (sayes <HI>Wal∣singham)</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> heavi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y bewailing thess changes, to see servants command their Lords, who know not how to rule, nor how to pity. To see <HI>London</HI> (once the noble head of our Cities) become a stie for uncleane Swine. Who would not tremble to heare
<PB N="92" REF="53"/>
that the Archbishop and the Lord Treasu∣rer should be offered victimes to wicked spirits, to the Kentish Idol, the Kentish <HI>Saturne</HI> or <HI>Moloch,</HI> and his Hob-goblings in the midst of the Kingdome. Nay (sayes he) whose heart would it not have woun∣ded through to have seene the King of <HI>En∣gland,</HI> who of right for Majesty and dig∣nity ought to precede all Kings in the World, out of feare of his head, observe the nods, and becks of these varlets, and the Nobility and Gentry, mortifi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d beasts, trampled on by these scullions, it slaved at their owne charge, lick up their dust.</P>
<P>After dinner, a sad dinner to the Monks, this merdaille, these stinka<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ds, throng be∣fore the gates, and demand the Charter of L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>berties, which the Abbot had promi∣sed them to seale, which was sent, and read to them in the thickest of the rout: If they please to accept it, (this was the Abbots Complement) he is ready to seale. They (resolved never to be pleased) with much scorne and pride answer by an Es∣quire of the Abbot. That the Abbot must appoint some Clerk of his to attend them with Ink and Parchment, Themselves would dictate, and after the Abbot and Covent should confirme what was done; when this humour was satisfied, The safety
<PB N="93" REF="53"/>
and peace of the Monastery and Monkes were as desperate as ever. The old Char∣ter, which they will everlastingly believe concealed, must be produced, else they will bury the Covent in the ruines of the Cloysters.</P>
<P>This Charter did certainly (as they will have it) conteine all their antient <HI>Liberties</HI> and priviledges, and if this was true, there was no great reason it should be in the Ab∣bots keeping.</P>
<P>Here the Abbot imployes the most ho∣nourable Esquires of the Countrey, as Me∣diatours to soften them, and offers (if they desire it) to say Masse before them next morning, and to sweare upon the Sacra∣ment <NOTE PLACE="marg">Super Sa∣cramentum.</NOTE> he should be about to take, with what Monkes they would name, that he kept from them no such Charter with his knowledge.</P>
<P>Make choice (sayes he) of what <HI>Liber∣ties</HI> you can, you shall have my Charters drawne, they shall be granted you by it; I will seale you a reall Charter instead of a fantasticall one, never seene by you, no where to be had. The Abbot struggles in vaine against these waves, this Charter of their fancies they will have: Nor shall any other price redeeme the Monastery, they intended the subversion of the house, and
<PB N="94" REF="54"/>
wrangle thus crossely, that they might seeme to have some pretences to doe it, but because they had much businesse to goe a∣bout, and could not be here and there too, a truce was taken for that day, and many of these <HI>pure brethren</HI> betake themselves to other parts; some of them would not be prevailed with, the Bread and Ale of the Monastery brought forth to them in huge Fats, would not worke upon them to lay their fury, they stayed onely for a leading hand. Here an honest Burgesse interposes, <HI>Ribaulds</HI> (sayes he) what is it you purpose? most of you here are forrainers of the Vil∣lages <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ribaldi.</NOTE> about, this is the most famous mis∣chiefe which can be acted in this Countrey, this Beacon must set all on fire, and it is fit we, who are Burgesses and Free-men of this Towne should give the on-set: by this finenesse they are gained to quit the gates, and joyne to the assistance of their fellow∣labourers. The rest of the day is spent by their united forces, in overthrowing of houses, clashing of vessells, and spoiling of goods according to the rule of <HI>Walter</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Quod di∣dicerant. à Waltero.</NOTE> the false founder of the order. At night the Lieutenants make Proclamation under the Kings Banner, commanding strong Guards to be set about the Towne, that they may be assured against surprizes, and
<PB N="95" REF="54"/>
about the river <HI>Werlam,</HI> and Saint <HI>Ger∣manes;</HI> making it losse of the head to any Monke, who should be found issuing from, or entring the Monastery that way, This was done to set a trap for the Prior; and those who fled with him. They proclaimed also that whosoever could challenge any debts due to him from the Monastery, might put in his claime (and little proofe should be needed) the next day, and the Burgesses of the Towne, would discharge as far as the goods of the Monastery would reach; Much more was Magisteri∣ally throwne in, to shew a cast of the <HI>pre∣sent power:</HI> which was no sooner done, but there appeares a Farmour of the Man∣nor of <HI>Kingsbury</HI> belonging to this Abbey, armed with his Sword and Buckler, this man was much in arreares for his Farme, and durst not peepe abroade from his lur∣king holes before these broyles, which hiding of himselfe he imputes now to the injustice, and cruelty of the Prior, this chuffe demands one hundred Marks dama∣ges for the losses he had sustained in his absence, and threatens to burne the grange of Saint <HI>Peter,</HI> and Mannor-house of <HI>Kingsbury</HI> neare the Abby, if he be not re∣paired; twenty pounds, he receives upon this demand, and goes away, swearing, he
<PB N="96" REF="55"/>
would freely give it back againe for the Priors head.</P>
<P>Saturday night passed with much per∣plexity to the Monkes, who were at their wits ends, and lifes too, (they could not hope better things) about the Charter, which was no where extant but in the ndodles of these cluster-fists. But day, and comfort broke out together upon them; Suddenly this overflow of pride, and arro∣gancy abated, their loftinesse fell, and their bristles were somewhat laid, very unplea∣sing rumours concerning the Army were spread, and the death of the Idol <HI>Tyrant Wat,</HI> of stinking memory was certainely <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals. foedae memoriae.</NOTE> knowne and divulged, and what was as stabbing, that the Citizens of <HI>London</HI> growne wise, and resolute, either out of loyalty (or which is the rather to be sup∣posed experience of their new master) be∣gan now to owne their Prince, their na∣turall Lord unanimously, and to side with him against all seditious opposers of his Majesty, and the <HI>just rights and liberties</HI> of his people, which they saw like to perish together. Farther a Knight of the Court, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Walsingh.</NOTE> seconds the report, and by proclamation in the Kings Name (now legall againe) commands this herd to keepe the Kings peace under forfeiture of life, and members from that houre.</P>
<P><PB N="97" REF="55"/>
The King now growne a <HI>Protectour</HI> a∣gaine of his Subjects, sends his Letters pro∣tectory to the Abbot in these words.</P>
<P>RIchard, <HI>&amp;c. To all our Lieges, and Commons of</HI> Hartford <HI>&amp;c. We pray, Charge, Command, streightly as we may, &amp;c. by the faith and lige∣ances which to us yee owe, that to our Beloved in God, the Abbot of St.</HI> Al∣bane, <HI>nor to our House and Monastery of the said place, of our Patronage, nor to none of the People, Monkes, nor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣thers, nor to none of the goods of the said Monastery, &amp;c, Yee suffer to be done, as much as in you lies any grie∣vance, dammage, &amp;c. Given under our Great Seale at our City of</HI> London, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>Though now these Carles were well coo∣led, yet ere the zeale was quite <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>akened, and the Clouds dispelled, which hovered weakely, and were likely to scatter with the next breath of winde, they conclude to perfect their building, which to the great nusance of this Monastery they ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>
<PB N="98" REF="56"/>
raised; B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sides, the Lieutenants, or Ma∣jor Generalls of <HI>Tyler,</HI> thought it a much unworthiuesse to droope too soon, before those whom they had summoned in to piece up their deformed insutrection with so much bravery, and insolence. They con∣tinue and pursue their requests to the Ab∣bot, but with lesse noise than formerly, the Abbot was advised by Letters from Sir <HI>Hugh Segrave,</HI> Lord Steward of the Hous∣hold, and Sir <HI>Thomas Percy</HI> created after Earle of <HI>Worcester,</HI> to grant all things, assu∣ring him these grants being thus forced from him would be voide in Law, and could not hurt his Monastery. The Abbots Chamber, the Chappell, all places are full of them, they give directions to the Ab∣bots Clerke for their Charter of Liberties, which now they were contented to accept, but will have a Bond of one thousand pounds sterling for the delivering up the Charter unknowne, before the annuncia∣tion <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er∣lingorum.</NOTE> of the blessed Virgin next, if it can be found, if not, that the Abbot with his twelfth hand (an antient Saxon manner of purging or clearing the offender, where the offence was secret) with twelve of his chiefe Monkes should sweare, that he nei∣ther has nor detains any such Charter with his knowledge.</P>
<P><PB N="99" REF="56"/>
The Abbot agrees, he and the Covent Seale; But oh the miracle (not to be be∣lieved, nor understood without another upon our faith, and understanding the Seale, in which the glorious <HI>Protomarty<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> was figured, three times together could not be pulled from the Wax, no sleight, no strength could doe it; To passe by the pi∣ous frauds, and dreames of Monkes; from thence the black-bands depart to the Mar∣ket place, there at the Crosse they publish their new Acquisitions, the Charters of the King, and Abbot, with the Kings protecti∣on of the Monastery, which was but a counterfeit of their love. On Munday and Tuesday following the villeins of the Pa∣trimony of our <HI>Protemartyr</HI> (as the others did in all places else imbroiled) exact of the Abbot deeds of manumission, and <HI>Li berty,</HI> according to the effect of the Royall Charter before, which Charter the Abbot recites, and confirmes.</P>
<P>From villeins these now conceive them∣selves Gentlemen of Welsh pedegree, des∣cended of Princes, nay as our Monk, noble beyond the line and race of Kings, they are meere free-holders, hold onely of God and the Sunne, rather of the Sun, and club, and will neither performe their customes, and services, nor pay Rent. The common
<PB N="100" REF="57"/>
people, who are neither swayed by Reli∣gion or Honesty, stop and check them∣selves, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> not that they were contented, but because they could not, nay they durst not goe on to more.</P>
<P>The plague of this distemper was not onely epidemicall, but kept its dayes, on the fatall Saturday, fifty thousand Clownes, out of <HI>Suffolke, Essex, Cambridgeshire,</HI> the Isle of <HI>Eli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> (places miserably harrassed ac∣cording to the former presidents) were incorporated by the jugling tricks of the Essexian impostors, sent out by the Fathers of disobedience, in the first conception of the ruffle to inveigle proselites to the <HI>Holy League.</HI> This was but an indigested Masse without shape or forme, <HI>Wraw</HI> not <HI>Straw</HI> (as sometimes he is called) a most leud <HI>Presbyter</HI> as <HI>Walsingham,</HI> or Priest, who came from <HI>London,</HI> the day before with Orders from <HI>Tyler</HI> (who according to <HI>his</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Sceleratiss. Presbyt.</NOTE> <HI>owne establishment had the executive power)</HI> was imployed into those parts to lick and fashion the Monster. He with <HI>Robert West∣brome</HI> King of this Congregation, lead the tatter'd reformers from Mildenhall to St. <HI>Edmunds bury,</HI> where then stood a most glorious Monastery, and where their fel∣low scoundrells expected them, <HI>Wraw</HI> findes these choperloches good disciples,
<PB N="101" REF="57"/>
willing to learne, and quick of apprehen∣sion, so capable they understood his least signes. The same frensies are againe acted by other Lunaticks, the Lawyers or Ap∣prentices of the Law (as the Monke) and their houses are the first objects of their spight, they doe not onely cut off them, but fire their nests. Lir <HI>Iohn Cavendish</HI> chiefe Justice of the Kings Bench, who had beene one of the most able Serjeants of this Kings Grand-fathers Reigne, and was made chiefe Justice by him, they intercept, and behead. <HI>Orpheus Tra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>it, Ner<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> the <HI>Romane, Belgabred</HI> the <HI>Brittaine,</HI> excel∣lent in the sweetnesse of a voyce and skill of Song, with <HI>Iohn</HI> of <HI>Cambridge</HI> Prior of Saint <HI>Edmunds</HI> lose their lives in the same manner, as they unluckily fell in to their hands.</P>
<P>The cause of the Priors death is made this; He was discreet, and managed the affaires of his Monastery faithfully, and diligently, he was taken neare <HI>Mildenhall,</HI> a Towne then belonging to Saint <HI>Edmund</HI> of the demaine of the Abby, the Vassalls, Hindes, Villeins, and bond-men of the house, sentenced him, murthered him by Vote; His body lay five dayes naked in the field unburied. In Saint <HI>Edmunds bury,</HI> these cut-throats compasse the Priors head
<PB N="102" REF="58"/>
round as in a procession, after they carry it upon a Lance to the pillory, where that and the chiefe Justices head, are advanced. Their next worke was the levelling a new house of the Priours. After they enter the Monastery, which they threaten to fire, unlesse <HI>Iohn Lakinhethe</HI> Gardian of the temporalities of the Barony in the vacan∣cy then were delivered to them, which the Towns-men mingled in the throng▪ put them upon: the Gardian stood amidst the croud unknown. This man out of piety to preserve the Monastery (it was piety then though it may be thought impiety now) discovers himselfe, he tells them he is the man they seeke, and askes what it is the <HI>Commons</HI> would have with him. They call him traitor (it was capitall to be called so, not to be so) drag him to the Market-place, and cut off his head, which is set upon the Pillory to keepe company with the Priors, and chiefe Justices.</P>
<P><HI>Walter</HI> of <HI>Todington</HI> a Monke was sought for, they wanted his head, but he hid himselfe, and escaped. Our hacksters errant, of the round Table Knights of in∣dustry, would be thought Generall redee∣mers, to take care of all m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nin distresse; For the Burgesses sake, they command the Monkes, (threatning them and their walls
<PB N="103" REF="58"/>
if they obey not) to deliver up all the ob∣ligations of the Towns-men for their good behaviour, all the antient Charters from the time of King <HI>Cnut</HI> the Founder any way concerning the liberties of the Town, besides they must grant and confirm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> by Charter the <HI>Liberties</HI> of the Towne, which▪ could not be done in the vacancy (for so it was) <HI>Edmund</HI> of <HI>Brumfield</HI> Abbot in name, by provision: of the <HI>Pope</HI> was a pri∣soner at <HI>Notingham,</HI> nor had any election beene since the death of Abbot <HI>Iohn Bri∣vole,</HI> and therefore the Jewels of the house are pawned to the Townsmen as a g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> that <HI>Edmund</HI> of <HI>Brumfield</HI> (whom they would suppose Abbot, and whom they in∣tended to set free) should Seals, which Jewels were a Crosse and Calice of Gold, with other things, exceeding in value one thousand pounds, these were restored a∣gaine in time of peace, but with much unwillingnesse. Upon the brute of the I∣dol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> mishap, and the suppression of his Legions at <HI>London,</HI> these Caterpillers dis∣solve of themselves, <HI>Wraw</HI> the Priest, <HI>West∣brome,</HI> &amp; the rest of the capitall villeins in the generall audit, or doomesday for these hurliburlies, shall be called to a reckoning for their outrages. Cambridge suffered not a little in these uproars, the Towns-men
<PB N="104" REF="59"/>
with the Country peasants about confede∣rated together, breake up the treasury of the Universi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y, tear and burn its Charters, they compell the Chancelour and Schollars under their common Seals to release to the Major and townsmen all rights and Liber∣ties, all actions, and to be bound in 3000<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, not to molest the Burgesses by s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>its of Law concerning these things for the time to come. The Mayor and Bailiffs were fetched up by writ to the next Parl. where the deeds were delivered up and Cancelled, the Liberties of the towne seized into the Kings hand, as forfeited; new ones granted by him to the University, all which they owe yet to the piety of this King, and his Parliament, a Court which the Idol never names: had he set up one of his owne b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣getting, it must have had nothing else but the name; it would have beene as destroy∣ing as the field.</P>
<P><HI>Norfolke</HI> the Mother of the <HI>Kets</HI> would not loyter this while, nor sit lazily, and sluggishly looking on. <HI>Iohn Litster</HI> a Dyer of <HI>Norwich</HI> King of the <HI>Commons</HI> there, infuses zeale and daring into his Country∣men; he had composed out of his owne Empire, and the borders, an Army of fifty thousand Men. This upstart Kingling would not wholly move by example, h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>
<PB N="105" REF="59"/>
makes presidents of his owne, and tram∣ples not like a dull beast the r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ad beaten by others. He had heard what was done by the <HI>London</HI> Congregations, he had a stock of traditions from the Elders there, which he was able to improve; and al∣though I know not how he could exceed the Idol with his councell, yet (so the Monk) exceede them he did, he presumed greater things.</P>
<P><HI>Tyler</HI> lost his life before things were ripe, was watched and undermined by the King and Nobility, he could not spread his full sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>les, else for his presumption he far out-goes <HI>Litster. Litster</HI> the <HI>Norfolke</HI> Devil begins with plunder and rapine (the onely way to fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sh a young Rebellion.) The <HI>Malignants</HI> of the Kings party (the rich and peaceable goe under that notion) are made a prey, no place was safe, or privi∣ledged. Plots were laid to get the Lord <HI>William</HI> of <HI>Ufford</HI> Earle of <HI>Suffolke,</HI> at his Mannor of <HI>Ufford</HI> neer <HI>Debenham</HI> in <HI>Suf∣folke,</HI> into the company, out of policy; That if the cause succeeded not, then the Rebels might cover themselves under the shadow of that Peere. The Earle warned of their intention, rises from Supper, and disguised as a Groom <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Garci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></NOTE> of Sir <HI>Roger</HI> of <HI>Bois,</HI> with a Port-mantue behind him, riding by-waies,
<PB N="106" REF="60"/>
and about, ever avoiding the routs, comes to St. <HI>Albanes,</HI> and from thence to the King.</P>
<P>The <HI>Commons</HI> Failing here; possesse them∣selves of the places, and houses of the Knights neare, and compell the owners to sweare what they list, and for greater wa∣riness to ride the Country over with them, which they durst not deny: among those inthralled by this compulsion were the Lords <HI>Scales,</HI> and <HI>Morley,</HI> Sir <HI>Iohn Brews,</HI> Sir <HI>Stephan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> of <HI>Hales,</HI> and Sir <HI>Robert</HI> of <HI>Sall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> which last was no Gentleman borne, but as full of honour and loyalty as any man, Knighted by the <HI>Kings</HI> Grand-fa∣ther for his valour, he was (sayes <HI>Froissart)</HI> one of the biggest Knights in <HI>England,</HI> a man not supple enough, who could not bend before the new Lords; He had not the solidity of judgement (as some more subtle than honest call it) to accommodate himselfe to the times. Like <HI>Messala</HI> he would be of the Justest side, let the fortune be what it would, he would not forsake Justice under colour of following pru∣dence, he thought it not in vaine to prop up the falling Government, perhaps his judgement may be blamed he stayed not for a fit time, had he not failed here, he had not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ought against heaven, against provi∣dence,
<PB N="107" REF="60"/>
whose counsells and decrees are hid from us, are in the clouds, not to be pier∣ced, our understanding is as weake, as foo∣lish, as providence is certein and wise. Our hopes and feares deceive us alike, we can∣not resolve our selves upon any assurance, to forsake our duty for the time to come, Gods designes are knowne onely to him∣selfe, It is despaire, not piety (despair too farre from that) to leave our Country in her dangerous diseases, in her publick ca∣lamities; the insolency of injust men is a prodigie of their tuine, and the incerteinty of thing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> humane may teach us, that those we esteeme most <HI>established</HI> most assured, are not seldome soonest overthrown<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, <HI>Plato</HI> would not have men refer all things to fate, there is somewhat in our selves (sayes he) not a little in fortune, Ours are but cockfights, the least remainder of force and life may strike a necking blow, and by an unlooked for victory raise what is falne, if death cannot be kept off, if our Country cannot be saved by our attempts, there is a comlinesse in dying handsomly, nor can any man be unhappy but he who out-lives it. We have heard of Women who cast themselves into the fiery pits where their dead husbands are consumed; of Vassals who stab themselves to follow
<PB N="108" REF="61"/>
their Prince into the next world; of <HI>Otho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> Praetorians, of the Saguntines burning in their Cities flames. What can be so honou∣rable as to dye for or with our Countrey, or Faith, our Religion, or Honesty, to die with that which gave us life, and liberty, and sense of these?</P>
<P><HI>Litsters</HI> Hog-herds vow to burne <HI>Nor∣wich,</HI> unlesse this Knight will come out to them, which he does well mounted, and forsakes his Horse to please them. They seem to honour him highly, and offer him a faire Canton of the new <HI>Common-wealth,</HI> if he will command their Forces.</P>
<P>The faithfull <HI>Cavalier</HI> abhorred the pro∣position, and could not dissemble his dis∣like; He tells them he will not to his eter∣nall dishonour renounce his Soveraigne, whom all good men obeyed, to ingage with the veryest perfidious Traitors living, in their villanies. He attempts to Horse himselfe againe, but failes; It was Treason to speak against the Government.</P>
<P>The <HI>Commons</HI> grow furious, they cry out Treason, against Treason and Rebellion: Thousands of hands are lifted up against him, as if they all moved by the same Nerves, and Sinews; They hew him down, but he crushes some of them with his ruine; Whosoever stood within his reach, lost ei∣ther
<PB N="109" REF="61"/>
Head, Legs or Armes; He kils twelve of them, at length avillein of his owne beats out his brains; Then doe the infernal Curs rush in with full mouthes, and man∣gla him to b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, who (sayes <HI>Walsingham)</HI> would have driven a thousand of them be∣fore him, had he had faire play. This amazes the rest of the Gentry, they strive for <HI>Vas∣salage,</HI> with the same emulation others doe for <HI>Liberty,</HI> they observe <HI>Litster,</HI> they re∣ceive his Commands upon their knees who in all things imitates the state and pomp of Kings; Sir <HI>Stephen</HI> of <HI>Hales</HI> a Knight of honour ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ves before him, and tastes his Meates, and Drinkes, the rest of the mise∣rable Courtiers are imployed in their seve∣rall offices. But when the same of the Kings good fortune began to grow strong, and of his preparations to assert his Right and Authority, <HI>Litster</HI> sends on Embassie (from <HI>NorthWalsham,</HI> the thorne of his tyranny) to <HI>London,</HI> the Lord <HI>Morley,</HI> and Sir <HI>Iohn Brewes,</HI> with three of the <HI>confi∣ding Commons,</HI> to obtaine Charters of ma∣numission, and pardon, with great summes of monies, (squeezed out of the Citizens or <HI>Norwich,</HI> under pretence of preserving the City from slaughter, fire and spoile, or as others raised by an ordinary tribute to <HI>Litster.)</HI> Which monies were sent for pre∣sents
<PB N="110" REF="62"/>
to the King, to win him to grant them Charters more ample and beneficial, than had been given to any others.</P>
<P>THese Messengers are met at <HI>Ichlingham</HI> neere <HI>New-market</HI> by <HI>Henry le Spenser,</HI> Lord Bishop of <HI>Norwich,</HI> of a noble Fami∣ly, stout and well armed; He had been at his Mannor of <HI>Burleigh</HI> neere <HI>Okeham,</HI> and there heard of the tumults in <HI>Norfolke</HI> and was now hasting thither to see how thing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> were carryed, with eight Lances onely i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> his company, and a few Archers. He char∣ges the Lord <HI>Morley,</HI> and Sir <HI>Iohn</HI> upon their Allegeance to tell him, whether any of the <HI>Commons</HI> (the Kings Traitors) we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> with them. They look upon the Bishop a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> a young rash man, and the awe of thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Masters was so prevalent, he could hardly wrest the secret from them. After many words they discover it; and the Bishop causes the heads of the Clowns to be struc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> off, and fixed on a publick place at New∣market. Then taking with him that Lord and Knight, he posts for <HI>Northwalsham;</HI> The Gentry hearing of the Bishops arri∣vall in his Coat of Male, with his Helmet upon his head, his Sword by his side, and his Lance upon his thigh, croud in to him, the Bishop quickly found himselfe in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> gallant equipage, and as quickly reach<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>
<PB N="111" REF="62"/>
<HI>Northwalsham,</HI> the sinke of the Rebel∣lion.</P>
<P><HI>Litster</HI> was intrenched, he had fortified his ditch with Pales, Stakes, and Dores, and shut himselfe in behinde with his Carts, and Carriages. The heroick Bishop like another <HI>Maccabeus,</HI> charges bravely through the ditch, into the midst of the Rebells (when all the Barons of <HI>England</HI> hid themselves,) so suddenly that the Ar∣chers could not let an arrow flie at him, and came to handy blowes. As the <HI>French</HI> Historian <HI>de Serres</HI> observes, in affaires of the World oftentimes he that is most <NOTE PLACE="marg">Rar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> si <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bonam for∣tunam cum bona me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e. <HI>Liv.</HI></NOTE> strong carries it, a good fortune, and a good minde seldome goe together.</P>
<P><HI>Otho</HI> tells his Souldiers oftentimes where the causes of things are good, yet if judge∣ment be wanting (I may put in) where the Counsels are unsound, the Agents faith∣lesse, where Money, Armes, and Men are wanting, the issue must be per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>icious; The goods and honours of this world which follow the Triumphers Chariots are com∣mon to the good and bad; Grace, Charity and Love, are the marks of a pious man, not Successe, to brag of which becomes ra∣ther a <HI>Spartacus</HI> or <HI>Mahomet,</HI> (who carry Faith and Law upon the Swords point) than a Christian: The God of the Christi∣ans
<PB N="112" REF="63"/>
is not the God of robbery, and bloud, but things here fell out as could be wished, the innocency of the side prevailed, and the righteout weake side overcame the strong injust; <HI>Litster</HI> touched with the conscience of his mischiefes, strugles to the utmost to avert his danger, at length gives ground, and attempts to shift for himselfe by leaping over his Carriages in the Rere. The Bishop pressed forward so fiercely, this course proved in vaine, most of the unhappy Clownes are laid along upon the place. <HI>Litster</HI> and the Captains of the Con∣spiracy are taken and condemned to be drawn, hanged and beheaded, which was done. Others of the chiefe Conspirators dispersed over the Country, are searched out and executed.</P>
<P>The Monke here tells us, It was appa∣rent <NOTE PLACE="marg">Nisi enim daemoni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s pleni fuis∣sent, nequa∣quam in de∣struct, sacr. Eccles. Chr. fidei &amp; re∣gni exter∣mini<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> con∣spirass.</NOTE> by the workes of these Demoniacks, by their fruits, that they had conspired (he speakes of the whole) not onely the de∣struction of the Church and Monarchy, but of the Christian faith too. Schoole∣masters were sworne by them never to teach Grammer more, and whosoever was taken with an Inkhorne about him, never saved his head.</P>
<P>Our Monke attributes these calamities to the remisnesse of the Bishops; to the
<PB N="113" REF="63"/>
conceits and fangles of Presbyter <HI>Wycliffe,</HI> which if they be truly registred by the Monkes, his mortall enemies, were pesti∣lentiall and damnable. Indeed Presbyter <HI>Wycliffe</HI> was then living, but is not named in these commotions, as one busie in them, by the Monk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, (though busie he might be, we shall finde Sir <HI>Iohn Old-castle,</HI> Lord <HI>Cobham,</HI> and others of <HI>Wycliffes</HI> disciples, rebells, and traitours, too too bufie in <HI>Henry</HI> the fists beginning) <HI>Baal,</HI> and <HI>Straw,</HI> and <HI>Wraw</HI> were Priests of the Idol, and his Lieutenants, and might serve the turne to i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>broyle without fetching more aide in: He attributes too these mischiefes to the licentious invectives of the Clownes against their Lords, generally to the sins of the Nation, inclusively taking in the Orders of Mendicants, or Begging Fryars, (like factious Lecturers) who had nothing of their owns, and were obliged to flatter the people, and make themselves popular) who sayes he forgetfull of their profession and vowes, greedy and covetous of mony, foster the people in their errors, call good evill, and evill good, seducing the great men with fawning, and the rabble with lyer. So that in those dayes (thus he pro∣ceeds) the Argument held in every mans mouth, <HI>This is a Fryar, therefore a Lyar,</HI> as strong as this, <HI>This is white, therfore coloured.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="114" REF="64"/>
Here againe is <HI>Walsingham</HI> at a stand, he complaines, That it is impossible to relate the villanie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of the Rustick Devils, done in all parts.</P>
<P>We will now return to see what the King does next, who was not asleep this while. After he had cleared the City (late∣ly <HI>Tylers</HI> good Town) of the Kentish frie, he commands the Nobility and Gentry (wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> durst now peep abroad) all the Kingdome over to repair to him at <HI>London</HI> well armed, and well horsed, as they loved him; and his royall honour. Their owne danger, and late feares, adde wings to their haste. Within a few dayes, forty thousand Horse meet at a Rendezvouz upon <HI>Black∣heath,</HI> whither the young King, who had taken <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>his Sequestration off, and restored himselfe to his Blood and Majesty, rides daily upon a Royall Courser, to view their Order, with his Imperiall Banner born be∣fore him: He delighted to be seen and ac∣knowledged for what he was amongst his own Homagers. Here he is informed, that the Kentishmen (a stirring people, but with what generous resolution will soone be found) are again in mutinie, (a mutinie however else contemptible) not to be fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ighted at that time. The King commands his Cavalrie (on fire, as much as himselfe)
<PB N="115" REF="64"/>
to march, and root out this persidious r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, of miscreants. Here the Nobility and Gen∣try of the County interpose, and become pledges for the Commons, which appeases, the King; who now disbands his Army, and resolves to take no other course of Ju∣stice, but such as was ordinary and usuall, by Judgements upon the known Lawes of the Land and by Juties of twelve men, the a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>clent Birth-right of the Englishmen. Lawes which could not have fitted <HI>Tylers</HI> Courts, nor Tryals, but which have beene ever the rule in all just and legal Tryalls, in all calme, and pious Ages. The Law Mar∣tiall being proper to an Army marching, to be exercised in it. If otherwise, all Senten∣ces by colour of it, are against the <HI>Magna Charta,</HI> &amp;c. and to the manifest subversion <NOTE PLACE="marg">Earle of <HI>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</HI> case?</NOTE> of the priviledges of Subjects.</P>
<P>Upon this faire, and Kingly conclusion of <HI>Richard,</HI> Commissions were given, and Justices of <HI>Oyer</HI> and <HI>Terminer</HI> to heare and determine the Treasons and Felonis com∣mitted in the late Insurrections, and prin∣cipally to inquire, who were the chief au∣thors, fomenters, and incendiaries of the broyles, are sent into <HI>Kent, Essex,</HI> and the rest of the Provinces in Rebellion.</P>
<P>The most honourable Mayor of <HI>London</HI> with others in Commission with him, sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>
<PB N="116" REF="65"/>
upon those of <HI>Kent, Essex, Norfolke,</HI> and <HI>Suffolke,</HI> &amp;c. who were apprehended in <HI>London. Straw</HI> taken in an old rotten house about <HI>London, Kirkby, Treder, Sterling</HI> are condemned, and beheaded, <HI>Strawes</HI> head being set upon <HI>London bridge</HI> with <HI>Tylers;</HI> but <HI>Iack Straw,</HI> who was privy to all the contrivances, and plots of the confederacy could give light into the mid-night dark∣nesse of <HI>Tylers</HI> steps, through all the close windings of his labyrinths of Treasons; is urged (the Major promising with some hon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st Citizens to be at the charge of M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sses for his soule, the good of which they desire him to consider) to declare his full knowledge of the Counsells, and votes passed, and to what end they had conjured up the wicked spirits of those Garboyles, <HI>Iohn</HI> was obstinate at the first, and would confesse nothing, but gained by these pro∣mises, and a little penitent (which was much to be believed of one possessed with Legions) he tells them, <HI>because I have hopes of help from your suffrages after my death, and because this discovery may be advantageous to the</HI> Common-wealth, <HI>I will confesse truly to you what we intended; when we met at</HI> B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ck-heath, <HI>and sent for the King by our Captaine Generalls Order, we purposed to have massacred all the Nobility and Gentry with
<PB N="117" REF="65"/>
him, then to have lead the King with us respected, and treated Kingly from place to place, to baite the vulgar by the authority of his presence into our League, whom they might so have taken for the head of our Com∣motion, he being by those meanes likely to have beene supposed by his owne party too to have trusted us, when by the confluence of all the Counties our companies had been full, and the supreame</HI> Executive power <HI>wholy ours, we meant to have</HI> purged <HI>the Nation, to have destroyed the Gentry, and, first the Knights of</HI> Saint Johns <HI>of</HI> Jerusalem, <HI>with all the ragges of royalty, which by this time had been but a ragge it selfe. Afterwards to have kil∣led the</HI> King, <HI>whose Name could then have been of no use to us.</HI></P>
<P>Their Oath to preserve him could not last longer then their conveniency and opi∣nions, which had then changed. We meant so once, but we meane otherwise now, had beene a satisfactory excuse. They had often sworne and Covenanted that <HI>they neither meant nor had power to hurt the Kings Prerogative, that they intended to maintaine the Kings authority in his royall dignity, the free course of Iustice, and the Lawes of the Land,</HI> with infinite expressi∣ons and protestations of this kind. They might answer, The time was when all this
<PB N="118" REF="66"/>
was reall, when they would not have sub∣verted the government, not have destroyed the antient family; <HI>to which</HI> sayes a Statute (which we hope it can be no treason to <HI>Tylers</HI> Ghost to recite) the <HI>dominions,</HI> and <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>See</HI> Mag. Chart <HI>&amp;c. See</HI> 25 H. 8. 1 Eliz. 1 Jac.</NOTE> <HI>rights of the realme of England,</HI> &amp;c. Ought <HI>by inhaerent birth-right and lawfull and un∣doubted succession descend and come.</HI> This <HI>we being bounden</HI> (thus speake the members heretofore) <HI>thereunto by the Lawes of God and man doe recognise,</HI> &amp;c. The answer we say might have beene easy, they would not have done it some time agon, they <HI>swore</HI> and <HI>Covenanted,</HI> and <HI>Covenanted</HI> againe <HI>they would, not now they will;</HI> Tyler is still <HI>Tyler,</HI> but <HI>his Liberty</HI> (false cheating liber∣ty) <HI>is every where free, both to will and dis∣like, as the safety of the Common-wealth shall require and carry him on.</HI> This was the faith and honesty of that age, by which we may guesse at the cause and men who acted for it, who were the undertakers, what <HI>trust is to be given</HI> to such perfidious knaves whose protestations, <HI>and Covenants of one day</HI> are <HI>wiped out by an inspiration of the next;</HI> We may say by an <HI>inspiration.</HI> It was wondrous fit for these changes. Our <HI>Proteus</HI> should bring <HI>inspiration</HI> in. <HI>All those of Estates, and Possessions, Bishops, Ca∣nons, Parsons of Churches, Monkes, we
<PB N="119" REF="66"/>
would have rooted out of the earth: onely the begging Fryers should have been preserved, who would have served</HI> (such sheep such She∣pheards) <HI>well enough for Church-duties,</HI> which we may wonder after all these pranks that they should thinke of; here would have beene a very plaine church, Questionlesse after all these actions the de∣votion of these Reformers could not have beene much; By that time our publick Theeves had cast lots for the Kings, Chur∣ches, Nobilities, and Gentries Revenues, what Boores of others Countries could have compared with the riches of our Pea∣sants and their Captaine <HI>Tyler. When there should have beene</HI> (so <HI>Straw</HI> goes on,) <HI>none</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Quib. su∣jecti regu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>i, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> <HI>left more great, more strong, or more wise then our selves, then we had set up a Law of our owne forging, at our pleasure, by which our Subjects should have beene regulated.</HI> Necessary it was the old Law should be voted downe; It condemned them in eve∣ry line. <HI>Then had we created us Kings, Tyler</HI> for <HI>Kent</HI> (a part too small for the Arch∣tyrant) <HI>and others for other Shires;</HI> Here was to be Monarchy still, not evill in it selfe, but where it ought to be of right, onely the Family was to be changed, the antient <HI>Saxon Norman</HI> stemme, for an up∣start dunghill brood of Vipere, <HI>Tyler</HI> to be
<PB N="120" REF="67"/>
advanced upon the ruines of <HI>Richard,</HI> the C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dar to be torne up, to make the Bram∣ble roome enough, while any of the roy∣all off spring had beene in being to claime the right, to have involved the miserable, perjured, foolish people in an everlasting civill Warre; never to have ceased while there had beene a veine of blood to run. The mainteinance of <HI>Tylers</HI> wrong, his usurpation (not to looke farther than the present World) would have beene more fatall then ten plagues. <HI>Iohn</HI> addes, <HI>no man thwarted these ends of ours more than the Archbishop, therefore we hated him to death, and made all the hast possible to bring him to it.</HI></P>
<P><HI>In the evening of that Saturday in which</HI> Wat <HI>perished, because the poorer sort of the</HI> Londoners <HI>favoured us, we intended to have fired the</HI> City <HI>in foure places, and to have divided the spoyles</HI> (So the faithfull Citi∣zens, as forward as they were, had at last paid for their love) he calls God to wit∣nesse these truths. The confessions of many others of the <HI>ingagement</HI> agreed with this of <HI>Straw.</HI></P>
<P>The Lawyers, and those (as one) who fled from the <HI>tyranny</HI> of the time, durst <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ow.</NOTE> now show their faces. Here is <HI>tyranny</HI> of the rout, <HI>tyranny</HI> of a savage Clown their
<PB N="121" REF="67"/>
bouteseu; whose few dayes of cruell usur∣pation, were more bloody, more destroy∣ing then the yeares of any <HI>Caligula,</HI> any <HI>Nere,</HI> any <HI>Domitian</HI> whatsoever. A Civill Warre (sayes a noble <HI>Frenchman)</HI> makes <NOTE PLACE="marg">Sieur de l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>vé.</NOTE> more breaches, as to a Country, as to Man∣ners, Lawes, and Men in six Moneths, then can be repaired in six yeares.</P>
<P>What then can be thought or said of those Monsters, who, against all ties of na∣ture and piety, shall raise a desperate civill Warre, meerely with the intent to over∣throw Religion, the Church, the Govern∣ment, Lawes, and Humanity, out of a cursed divelish ambition to advance themselves <HI>(Tylers</HI> and Sons of the Earth before) to an height which God (as some love to speake) never called them to. For though power is of God, it is onely so when the comming to it is by lawfull meanes. He that ordaines the power, allowes, not the usurpation of it, <HI>Tyler</HI> had the power to doe mischiefe, the power of rebellion, the power which must have ruined the church &amp; common wealth, but whether this be the power which Christians are to submit to, let the next Casuists judge.</P>
<P>The <HI>Septuagint</HI> translation of the Bible sayes of <HI>Abimelech,</HI> who slew his seaventy Brethren, (murder ushers usurpation in)
<PB N="122" REF="68"/>
<HI>He made himselfe King, by Tyranny.</HI> The Monk, who writes the lives of the <HI>Offa's,</HI> speaking of <HI>Beormred</HI> the <HI>Mercian</HI> Usurper, has these words: <HI>In the same region of the Mercians, a certaine Tyranne rather destroy∣ing and dissipating the Nobility of the Realm, than ruling, &amp;c. persecuting, banishing, &amp;c. Lest any one, especially of the Royall Blood, should be advanced in his place, he vehemently feared.</HI> The thirty <HI>Usurpers</HI> in the time of <HI>Gallienus</HI> are every where called <HI>Tyrannes. Paulus Diaconus</HI> writing of <HI>Valentine</HI> in the time of <HI>Valentinian,</HI> sayes, <HI>He was crushed in Britannie, before he could invade the Tyran∣nie;</HI> and of <HI>Maximus,</HI> that he was stout and valiant, and worthy of the Empire, <HI>had he not against the faith of his oath, raised himselfe</HI> per tyrannidem, <HI>by tyrannie.</HI> In other places, <HI>Eugenius, Gratian, Constance, Sebastian, created Tyrannes.</HI> The words <HI>Tyranne,</HI> and <HI>Tyrannie,</HI> and <HI>tyrannous par∣tie,</HI> being used often by him, are ever op∣posed to just and Regall power, never used in any other sense. <HI>Widdrington,</HI> to the ex∣ample of <HI>Athalia</HI> urged by <HI>Bellarmine</HI> a∣gainst Kings, sayes she was no lawfull <NOTE PLACE="marg">Apolog. 234.</NOTE> Queen, she had seized the Kingdome as an Usurpresse by <HI>Tyrannie,</HI> the Kingdome belonged to <HI>Ioash,</HI> in whose right, and by whose power she was justly slaine—Our
<PB N="123" REF="68"/>
most learned Prelate Bishop <HI>Abbot</HI> of <HI>Sa∣lisbury</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Antilog. c. 32</NOTE> tells the Cubs of <HI>Loyola, Athalia had snatched, had grasped, and held the king∣dome with no right, no title, but by butchery, robbery, rapine, and forcible entry—and that she was thrown down and killed by the com∣mon bounden duty and faith of Subjects to their Prince. Baronius</HI> a Cardinal, that the Maccabees of <HI>Levi</HI> or house of the <HI>Assa∣moneans,</HI> may not be made Usurpers, mat∣ches them with the royall line of <HI>David,</HI> else sayes he, <HI>absque labe tyrannidis,</HI> without <NOTE PLACE="marg">Apparat.</NOTE> <HI>the stain of Tyrannie,</HI> they could not meddle with the Kingdome. <HI>Rodolph</HI> Duke of <HI>Sur∣via</HI> or <HI>Suabenland</HI> set up for a false Empe∣rour by that devilish Pope <HI>Hildebrand</HI> a∣gainst the Emperour <HI>Hen.</HI> the IIII. is called by the Germanes a <HI>Tyranne</HI> upon this score. A full Tyrannie (sayes one of our Chiefe Justices, speaking of the Papall power in Church causes here) has two parts, without right to usurp, and inordi∣nately to rule, and the Statute 28 of <HI>King Henry</HI> the 8. against the <HI>Papall Authority,</HI> calls it an usurped <HI>Tyranny,</HI> and the exer∣cise of it a Robbery, and spoyling of the King, and his people.</P>
<P>The Statute 31 <HI>Henry</HI> 6. adjudging <HI>Iohn Cade</HI> another Impe of Hell, and successour of <HI>Wat</HI> to be a traitour, whcih are the words
<PB N="124" REF="69"/>
of the title, and all his Indictments, and Acts to be voide, speakes thus; The most abominable <HI>Tyrannie,</HI> horrible, odious, and arrant false Traytour; <HI>Iohn Gade,</HI> naming himselfe sometime <HI>Mortimer</HI> (he and <HI>Ty∣ler</HI> had two Names) taking upon him Roy∣all power, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> by false, subtile, and imagi∣ned language, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Robbing, Stealing, and spoyling, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> And that all his <HI>Tyranny,</HI> Acts, Feats, and false opinions, shall be voyded, and that all things depending thereof, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> under the power of <HI>Tyran∣ny,</HI> shall be likewise voide, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> and that all Indictments in times comming in like case under power of <HI>Tyranny,</HI> Rebellion, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> shall be voide in Law; and that all Petitions delivered to the <HI>King</HI> in his last <HI>Parliament,</HI> &amp;c. against his minde, by him not agreed, shall be put in oblivion <HI>&amp;c.</HI> as against God, and conscience, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>To proceed, The King, because all these risings were by the Ring leaders protested to be made for him and his Rights, and that the forces then raised, were raised by his Authority, and all their actions owned by him, issues out a Proclamation from <HI>London,</HI> to this effect.</P>
<P><PB N="125" REF="69"/>
RIchard <HI>&amp;c. To all and singular Sheriffes, Majors, Bayliffs,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>of our County of</HI> N. <HI>&amp;c. Because we are given to understand; That divers of our Subjects, who against our Peace,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>have raised and in diverse Con∣venticles and Assemblies,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>Do af∣firme, That they the said Assemblies, and Levies have made, and doe make by Our will and Authority,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>We make knowne to all men, That such Levies, Assemblies, and Mischiefes, from Our Will and Authority have not proceeded (He addes) they were begun, and continued much to His displeasure and disgrace, to the prejudice of His Crowne, and dammage of the Realm. Wherefore he injoynes and commands,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>To take the best care for the keep∣ing of his Peace, &amp; opposing of all such Levies with a strong hand: Farther, He commands every man to leave such Assemblies, and return home to his own house under penalty of forfeiture of Life, and Member, and all things forfeitable to the King,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P><PB N="126" REF="70"/>
These <HI>Clowns</HI> charge not the King to be transported Furiously, and Hostilely, to the destruction of the whole people, which can never happen, where the King is in his wits; But what is fully as mad, they will suppose him to Arme against his own life and power, against his own peace, and the peace of all that love him. This <HI>Proclama∣tion</HI> put life into the Royalists, into all ho∣nest hearts, and dismayes as much the Re∣bels, yet after this the <HI>Essex</HI> Traitors, ga∣ther again at <HI>Byllericay</HI> near <HI>Hatfield</HI> Peve∣rell, and send to the King, now at <HI>Wal∣tham,</HI> to know whether he intends to make good his Grants of Liberties, and require to be made equal with their Lords, with∣out being bound to any Suits of Court view of <HI>Frank-pledge,</HI> only excepted twice the year.</P>
<P>The <HI>King</HI> and his Counsell are startled at this impudence: The <HI>King</HI> answers the Agents, <HI>That if he did not look upon them as</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> <HI>Messengers, he would hang them up: Re∣turn</HI> (sayes he) <HI>to your fellow Rebels, and tell them, Clowns they were, and are, and shall continue in their Bondage, not as hitherto, but far more basely trampled on. While we live, and rule this Kingdom, by Gods Will we will imploy all our Means and Power to keep you under: So that your misery shall frighten all
<PB N="127" REF="70"/>
villeins hereafter: And your posterity <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> curse your memory.</HI> At the heels of the Messengers, the <HI>King</HI> sends his Unkle <HI>Tho∣mas</HI> of <HI>Woodstock</HI> Earl of <HI>Buckingham,</HI> and Sir <HI>Thomas Piercy</HI> with a body of Horse to quell them. The Rebels were intrenched according to the manner of <HI>Litsters</HI> Camp, in the midst of Woods; Ten Lances of the Avant Currours rout them; the Lords, when they were come up, inclose the Woods round, five hundred are killed, eight hundred Horses for carriage taken, the broken remainders of the defeat e∣scape to <HI>Colchester,</HI> a Town ever honest, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> and faithfull to the Prince, where the loyal Townsmen would not be gotten to stir; they sollicite the Townsmen (saies the <HI>Monk)</HI> with much intreaty, great threats, and many arguments; neither intreaties, nor threats, nor arguments would move them: From thence they get to <HI>Sudbury,</HI> making every where such <HI>Proclamations</HI> as of old they had used; where the Lord <HI>Fitz. walter</HI> (whose seat was at <HI>Woodham Wal∣ters</HI> in <HI>Essex)</HI> and Sir <HI>Iohn Harlestone</HI> rush suddenly upon them, kill and take them: The <HI>King</HI> meaning to visite <HI>Essex</HI> in his own person, comes to <HI>Havering</HI> at the bou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, a Mannour of his own demain, of the sacred Patrimony, and from thence to
<PB N="128" REF="71"/>
<HI>Chesmsford,</HI> where he appoints Sir <HI>Robert Tresilian</HI> chief Justice of his Bench of <HI>Pleas</HI> of the Crown, to sit and inquire of the Malefactours, and Troublers of the Coun∣try, and to punish the offendours accor∣ding to the custome of the Realm, known, and visible.</P>
<P>Five hundred of these wretched pea∣sants, who had no mercy for others here∣tofore, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals.</NOTE> cast themselves down before the <HI>King</HI> bare footed, and with heads uncove∣red, implore his pardon, which he grant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> them, on condition, They discover the great Conspiratours, the Captain Rogues. The Jurors are charged by the chief Ju∣stices to carry themselves indifferently, and justly in their Verdicts, neither swayed by love, or hatred, to favour, or prosecute any man: Many upon the Evidence given in, and the finding of the Jury, were condem∣ned to be drawn and hanged; nineteen of them were trussed upon one Gallowes. Heading had formerly been the execution of others in <HI>Essex, Kent,</HI> and <HI>London,</HI> be∣cause of the numbers of the guilty, which was now thought a death short of the de∣merits of the most foul and heynous offen∣ders; Wherefore according to the custom of the Realm, It was decreed (sayes the Monk) that the Captains should be hang∣ed.</P>
<P><PB N="129" REF="71"/>
The like was done in other Countries by the Justices in Commission, where the <HI>King</HI> was in person. Here the <HI>King</HI> with the advice of his Counsell, revokes his <HI>Letters Patents,</HI> the Charters granted to the Clowns: <HI>Although</HI> (so he speaks) <HI>we have have in the late detestable troubles,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>ma∣numised all the Commons, our Liege Subjects of our Shires, and them,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>have freed from all bondage and service,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>And also have pardoned the same, our Liege men and Sub∣jects all Insurrections by Riding, Going,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>And also all manner of Treasons, Felonies, Trespasses, and Extortions,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>Notwith∣standing for that the said Charters, were without mature deliberation, and unduly pro∣cured,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>To the prejudice of us, and our Crown, of the Prelates, and great men of our Realm; as also to the disherison of holy En∣glish Church, and to the hurt and damage of the Common-wealth, the said Letters we re∣voke, make void, and annull,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>Yet our intention is such Gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e upon every of our said Subjects to confer, though enormiously their Allegeance they have forfeited,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>As shall be usefull to us, and our Realm.</HI></P>
<P>The close commands <HI>to bring in to the King and his Councell all Charters of ma∣numission, and pardon to be cancelled up∣on their faith and allegeance, and under
<PB N="130" REF="72"/>
forfeiture of all things forfeitable,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>Witnesse our selfe at</HI> Chelmsford <HI>the</HI> 2. <HI>of</HI> July, <HI>and</HI> 5. <HI>year of our reign.</HI> False for the 4.</P>
<P>In the case of a Subject (and no reason Kings shall be more bound) every Act ex∣torted by violence, and awe upon the A∣gent is voyd. In the time of <HI>Edward</HI> the third, two Thieves (which was the case here) force a Traveller to swear that hee will at a day appointed bring them a thou∣sand pound; and threaten to kill him if he refuse their oath; He swears, and performe <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 3. 14.</NOTE> what he had sworn; by advice of all the Justices these two were Indicted of Rob∣bery, and the Court maintaines that the party was not bound by this Oath. Yet if this be denyed as unsafe, Violence, or Force, which strikes a just fear into any man, makes any Contract voyd, say the Casuists.</P>
<P>Bishop <HI>Andrewes,</HI> than most learned <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>esp. ad Apolog.</NOTE> Prelate, answers to the pretended resig∣nation of King <HI>Iohn,</HI> urged by <HI>Bellarmine,</HI> that what this King did, (if any such act was done) was done by force, and out of feare.</P>
<P><HI>Widdrington,</HI> the mostloyall of all Ro∣man Catholick Priests, who writ much a∣gainst <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nit. disp. dejur. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d. l. 1.</NOTE> the Gun-powder Jesuits, in defence
<PB N="131" REF="72"/>
of the right of Kings, against those Jesuits who would have cut off the King, the Roy∣all Family, the Bishops of the English Ca∣tholick Church, the Nobility and Gentry, as their Letter speaks, with one blow, sayes of this Resignation, or Donation, if we may (so he) call it so, That it was not freely given. The Jesuites challenge the perpetuall dictature, or regency of the University of <HI>Pontamousson</HI> by Bull of <HI>Six∣tus</HI> the fift, contrary to the Statutes of the foundation by <HI>Gregory</HI> the thirteenth. Were the Bull true (sayes <HI>Barclaie)</HI> yet it ougt not to be of force, because it was obtain'd presently after his Creation, when things are presumed to be rather extorted than obtained. <HI>Bodin</HI> denyes that a <HI>King</HI> deceived or forced can be bound by his grants. The justice of Contracts is that a∣lone which binds. The distinction of Roy∣all and Private acts is of more sound then strength, and answers not the injustice of the impulsive violence, which must be na∣turally vicious every where, and corrupt, and weaken the effects, and cannot be good and bad by changes, or as to this, or that. <HI>Grotius,</HI> who loves this distinction, in another place is positive, There must be Equality in all Contracts. He condemns all fear, or awe upon the person purposely
<PB N="132" REF="73"/>
moved for the contracts sake, and tels us out of <HI>Xenophon</HI> of those of <HI>Lacaedemon</HI> who annulled a sale of lands which the <HI>E∣lians</HI> had forced the owners to passe out of fear.</P>
<P>A Charter of King <HI>Henry</HI> the third im∣prisoned and forced, is said by <HI>Ald<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nhans</HI> to be voyd upon this reason, and I judge the justice of this revocation by the Law of <HI>England,</HI> by which, as ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> old Parli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣ments, such force is Treason. The fruits of <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>xil. Hug∣le de Spen∣cer pat. &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>il,</NOTE> w<SUP>ch</SUP> were here more justly plucked up than they were planted. He who gives up his money to Thieves, according to his oath, may lawfully take it away from them: however they are bound to make restitu∣tion. Nor can any prescription of time e∣stablish a right of possession in him, who <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ei <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>terna au∣thorita<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</NOTE> makes his seizure upon no other title but Plunder and Robbery. The 5<SUP>th</SUP> of this King, the Parliament declares these Grants to be forced and voyd. Enough to clear the honour of King <HI>Richard,</HI> as to this part.</P>
<P>At <HI>Chelmsford</HI> the King is informed of the whole History of mischiefs done at St. <HI>Albanes,</HI> and resolved in person with all his Guards and Cavalry to ride thither, and sentence the Malefactors with his own mouth; but Sir <HI>Walter Leye</HI> of <HI>Hartford∣shire,</HI>
<PB N="133" REF="73"/>
fearing the mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h impoverishing th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Country, if the <HI>King</HI> should make any long stay there with such numbers as then at∣tended him, beseeches him to make a tryal wehther things might not be composed without him, and offers to reconcile the <HI>Abbot</HI> and Townsmen, if the <HI>King</HI> would, which was consented to: The <HI>King</HI> grants him a <HI>Commission,</HI> and joyns with him <HI>Ed∣ward Benstude, Geofrey Stukelye,</HI> and others of the Gent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y of that County.</P>
<P>The coming of these <HI>Commissioners</HI> was noysed at St. <HI>Albanes:</HI> The fiercest of the Clowns knowing what they had done was condemned by the Law, and not to be de∣fended, but by force, which now they had not, began to shake and take fright, are plotting to get out of the way. <HI>Grindecob,</HI> Lieutenant of the late Idol, comforts them, he perswades to goe to Horse; Let us meet the Knight (sayes he) and see whether his looks promise Peace or not; if not, the Towns about us have engaged, they have associated, and are of our <HI>League,</HI> we are rich, and cannot want good fellows, who will assist us while our monies last: On St. <HI>Peters</HI> day this ill advised crue meets the Knight upon the Rode, who wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> igno∣rant of their resolutions, and conduct him
<PB N="134" REF="74"/>
honourably, according to their fashion to the Town: Sir <HI>Walter</HI> had with him fiftie Lances, and some Companies of A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>chers, listed at random, many of them being of the Churles, and confederates with them: The Knight cites the Towns-men and their Neighbours to appear before him in <HI>Der∣fold,</HI> to hear the pleasure and commands of the King; They fail not, <HI>There h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> tells them what Forces the King had assembled, how rigorously those of</HI> Essex <HI>were sentenced: That the King was highly inc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nsed at the troubles and seditions of this place of which he was the Patron and Defender: That with great difficulty he had procured of the King a Commission, by which himself, and others, not Strangers, or Enemies, but their Friends and Neighbours were authorised to do Iustice in the Kings stead; he concludes, if they will appease the King, they must find out, and de∣liver up the beginners of these broyls, and make satisfaction to the Lord Abbot, an holy, and a just man, for the wrong they had done him.</HI></P>
<P>This many of the hearers approve, and promise to obey. The Knight charges a Jury to be made ready the next morning, and make what discovery they can, and gives the people leave to depart. Towards
<PB N="135" REF="74"/>
night he send<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> for the Jury to his Cham∣ber, intending to have apprehended the Lieutenants, by the assistance of the Jury, without any noyse. These good men and true know nothing, it was the case of their fellows in mischiefe, and might be their own. They answer in a plain <HI>Ignora<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> they can indict no man, accuse no man. A∣mongst all the founder of these swine, there was not one who had been faithless and disloyal to his natural Liege Lord, not one breaker of his peace, not one who could appear so to them.</P>
<P>The Knight seems not to understand the falsnesse and cunning of these Hob n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ile perjured Jug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ers: He takes another way, and next requires them within a peremp∣tory time to bring him the Charters which they had forced from the Monastery, they return after a short consultation, and in the <HI>Abbots</HI> chamber, where the Knight then was, tell him, <HI>They dare not obey out of fear of the Commons, what was more, they knew not in whose custody the Charters were.</HI> The Knight grows angry, and swears, they shall not goe out of the Chamber till he have them, which they call imprisoning their persons. Here the <HI>Abbot</HI> intercedes, and though he knew them as very knaves and
<PB N="136" REF="75"/>
lyars as any <HI>Tyler</HI> had set on work, yet he will not (he sayes) distrust their honesty, he will leave things to their consciences, upon which they are freed.</P>
<P>Another Assembly is appointed at <HI>Bar∣net</HI> Wood, whither the Villagers about throng in multitudes. Three hundred Bow∣men of <HI>Barnet,</HI> and <HI>Berkhamsted,</HI> make here so terrible a show nothing is done.</P>
<P>The Commissioners privately charge the Gentry, Constables, and Baylifs to seiz: in the night <HI>Greyncob, Cadindon, Iohn</HI> the Bar∣ber, with some others, and to bring them to <HI>Hartford,</HI> whither themselves went in all haste, which was performed: The Es∣quires and servants of the Abby were sent with them to strengthen the company. This inrages the Townsmen afresh, they gather into Conventicles in the Woods, and Fields, so much frightful to the Mona∣stery, that the <HI>Abbot</HI> recalls his Esquires, lets the prosecution fall, and fearfully sum∣mons in his friends to guard him, <HI>Greynd∣cobs</HI> friends take advantage of this change, and bayl him for three dayes, within which time they were either tyed to agree with the <HI>Abby,</HI> or render up <HI>Greyndcob</HI> to the Justices again. The Townsmen fierce enough still, yet earnest to preserve their
<PB N="137" REF="75"/>
Worthy, are content to part with the Charters; But this <HI>Greyndcob</HI> (more fool∣hardy than wise) would not consent to, Nor does he, as knowing the stifnesse of his Clowns, whine in a Religious tone, never used by him.</P>
<P>He prayes them to consider how beauti∣full <HI>Liberty</HI> is, how sweet, how honoura∣ble; Dangerous <HI>Liberty</HI> (sayes he) is more valuable than safe and quiet slavery, let us live, or die with <HI>Liberty,</HI> in so generous, so honest a contention, it will be glorious to be overcome; whatsoever our feares are, worse we cannot be, than now we are about to make our selves; Successe too does not so often faile men as their owne industry and boldnesse; Feare not for me, nor trouble your selves at my dangers, I shall thinke my selfe more happy than our Lords, if they prosper, or their <HI>King,</HI> to die a Martyr of the <HI>Cause,</HI> with the repu∣tation <NOTE PLACE="marg">Per tale Martyrium vitā fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ire.</NOTE> of such a gallantry. Let such cou∣rage as would have hurryed you forward to all brave and signall mischiefs, had I <NOTE PLACE="marg">Si Hertfor∣dia, He∣sterno decol∣lat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, &amp;c.</NOTE> lost my head at <HI>Hartford,</HI> inflame your hea∣vy sprights: Methinks I see the Heroe <HI>Ty∣lers</HI> Ghost chiding our sluggish cowardice, and by the blazes of his fire-brands kin∣dled in Hel, and waved by Fiends about
<PB N="138" REF="76"/>
his head, leade on to noble villanies.</P>
<P>Let dreaming Monks and Priests trem∣ble at the aery sounds of God, and Saints; he who feares Thunder-bolts is a religions heartlesse Coxcombe, and shall never climb a Molehill. Thus our buskin'd Martyr swag∣gers, after the raptures put upon him by <HI>Walsingham; Greyndcobs</HI> stubbornnesse hardens on the Clownes, they now accuse themselves of basenesse, that they did not cut off the Knights Head, and naile it on the Pillory, to the terrour (say they) of all Judges, and false Justices. <HI>Greyndcob</HI> had raised spirits which he could not lay when he would.</P>
<P>Three dayes being expired, he is againe sent to <HI>Hartford</HI> Gaol, where hee heares news from his Brother, who mediated for him in the Court, not very pleasing, which he communicates to his Townsmen. His intelligence was to this effect; That <HI>Rich:</HI> of <HI>Beauchamp</HI> Earl of <HI>Warwick,</HI> and Sir <HI>Thomas Percie</HI> with a thousand armed men were appointed to visit S. <HI>Albanes.</HI></P>
<P>At this report the Rebels startle, they fall to new Treaties, offer the Charters and Book, in which the old <HI>Pleas</HI> betwixt the <HI>Abby</HI> and the Town were recorded, with 200 l. for amends. The Booke is received,
<PB N="139" REF="76"/>
the rest put off till the next day. The Earl of <HI>Warwick</HI> sends onely excuses, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>he heard his own house was on fire, that the Clowns of his own Lordships were up, and hee leaves all thing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> else to quel them. This raises the fallen courages of those of St. <HI>Albanes,</HI> they now laugh at their late fear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, <HI>If the Commons,</HI> say they, <HI>must quit their right of Conquest, and surrender their Char∣ters, yet will not we (the renowned Mecha∣nicks) of</HI> St. Albanes <HI>be their president.</HI> And as in all tumults (which can never be ob∣served too often) lying is necessary, and must not bee uselesse, whatsoever else is; They lay the blame of their obstinacy upon the Inhabitants of <HI>Barnet</HI> and <HI>Watford,</HI> who threaten (so they would have it belie∣ved) to burn their Town if they deliver up their <HI>Liberties.</HI></P>
<P>Which Inhabitants of <HI>Barnet,</HI> and <HI>Wat∣ford</HI> had humbly surrendred their<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> before, and submitted to the <HI>Kings</HI> mercy: Thus we find these Rebels of St. <HI>Albanes</HI> again swaggering in their old <HI>Rhodomontadoes.</HI> An Esquire of the <HI>Abbots</HI> acquaints the <HI>King</HI> with these turnings, who vows to sit personally in judgement upon these ever∣lasting male-contents.</P>
<P>The <HI>Abbot</HI> full of pitty and charity, who
<PB N="140" REF="77"/>
had saved some of these enemies of his House from the Axe by intercession at <HI>London:</HI> continues his goodness still, he sol∣licites Sir <HI>Hugh Segrave,</HI> Steward of the Houshold, and others of his friends to mi∣tigate the Kings displeasure, and hinder his journey thither, which was not in their power. Now again are the Townsmen de∣jected, and seek by all means to keep off the tempest which threatned them: They fee Sir <HI>William Croyser</HI> a Lawyer to make their defence, and mediate with the <HI>Ab∣bot,</HI> where there was no danger: an agree∣ment is concluded the day of the <HI>King</HI>'s entry, by which they would bind the <HI>Ab∣bot</HI> not to disclose them, or inform against them.</P>
<P>He promises (if they fail not in perfor∣mance on their part) not to make any complaints to the <HI>King</HI> of them, that he would be a suiter for their peace if his prayers may be heard, but that here he cannot assure them, Pardons were Acts flowing meerly from the <HI>Kings</HI> Grace. <HI>No</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">See 27 H. 8. c. 24.</NOTE> <HI>man had any power or authoritie to pardon or r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mit treasons,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>but the King;</HI> and whe∣ther he could prevail for them he knew not. This doubtfulness troubles them, it seems to call their innocency too much in∣to
<PB N="141" REF="77"/>
question: They tell him, his good will was sufficient, and that as to what belong∣ed to the Royal Dignity they should satis∣fie the <HI>King.</HI></P>
<P>After Vespers the <HI>King</HI> made his entry into the Town, being met by the <HI>Abbot</HI> and <HI>Covent,</HI> the Bels rang aloud; and the Monke sang merrily his welcome: He was followed by some thousands of Bowmen, and Cavaliers. In this train was Sir <HI>Robert Tresilian</HI> Chief Justice of the <HI>Kings Bench,</HI> who the next day, being Saturday the 13. of <HI>Iuly,</HI> and first of the Dog-dayes sate in judgement at the Moot-hall (saies <HI>Wal∣singham)</HI> at the Town-house.</P>
<P><HI>Greyndcob, Cadindon,</HI> and <HI>Iohn</HI> the Bar∣ber are fetched from <HI>Hartford,</HI> and said fast till Munday, against which time new Jury∣men are chosen, and charged to be ready with their Verdicts: Prophet <HI>Baal,</HI> the <HI>Ser∣gius</HI> of the new <HI>Alcaran,</HI> the Priest of the Idol, and his Calves, the <HI>Martin of the yoak, of pure discipline of the Eldership,</HI> was taken by the Townsmen of <HI>Coventry,</HI> brought to St. <HI>Albanes</HI> the day before, and this Saturday condemned by the Chief Ju∣stice to be Drawn. Hanged, Beheaded Im∣bowelled, and Quartered which was done on the Munday following.</P>
<P><PB N="142" REF="78"/>
He confessed to the Bishop of <HI>London</HI> (to whose Christian Piety he ought the two last dayes of his life, which were beg∣ged for his repentance) that certaine hot, and <HI>powerfull Pastours of the Separation, Brethren of simple hearts, called by the Spi∣rit</HI> (he named six or seven) <HI>had covenanted, and engaged to compass</HI> England <HI>and</HI> Wales <HI>round, as Itinerant Apostles to propagate the Gospel, beat down all abomination of the out∣ward Man, Antichristian Hierarehy, and Ty∣ranny of the Nimrods of the Earth, to cry up the great and holy Cause, and to spread the Law, Principles, and Heresies of</HI> B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l, <HI>which Disciples</HI> (saies this <HI>Rabbi) unlesse they be prevented, and taken off wil destroy the Realm in two years:</HI> Hee might have said, <HI>two moneths,</HI> and been believed, as to the Civi∣lity, Humanity, Order, and Honour (never intermitted but in the confusion of a bar∣barous, impious age) which made <HI>England</HI> glorious, they had been destroyed, and torn up in a less time, A few licentious ill Acts easily beget a custom, and an hundred ill customes quicklier grow and prevaile than one single good one, there is a proneness in unruly man to run into deboshments, and no wonder that the arrogant, misled, silly multitude capable of any ill impressions
<PB N="143" REF="78"/>
should deprave and disorder things, where all ties of restraint are loosened, hay, where disorders are not onely defended by the corrupt wits of hirelings, but bidden, streng∣thened by a Law, and Villainies made legal Acts.</P>
<P>Had the Idol King <HI>Tyler,</HI> with his Councll not gone on too far in the way of exami∣nation, but endeavoured to repair the brea∣ches of his entrance; it would have been no small labour to have restored things to any mean and tolerable condition. If <HI>Presby∣ter VVicklief,</HI> and his <HI>Classes</HI> by their per∣nitious Doctrines (as they are charged to this day) did first pervert and corrupt the people, and broach that vessell with which Father <HI>Baal</HI> and <HI>Straw</HI> poysoned them, they must have ruined themselves by the change, sure enough they had been no more comprehended in any of <HI>Tylers Toleration</HI> than the <HI>Prelatical or Papistical party.</HI></P>
<P>In the turmoiles and outrages of this <HI>Tyrannie,</HI> had it taken, Innocence, Vir∣tue, Ingenuity, Honesty, Faith, Learning, and Goodnesse had been odious, and dan∣gerous. The profit, and advantage of the new Usurpers had been the measure of Justice and right: The noble and ignoble
<PB N="144" REF="79"/>
had dyed Streets and Scaffolds with their blood, not by Laws and Judgement, but out of malice to their height and worth, out of fury and covetousness to inrich publicke Theeves and Murtherers. The jealousies too and feares of <HI>Tyler</HI> had made all men unsafe. Yet the repute, the renowne of the Founders could not have been much: The glory of successe cannot be greater then the honesty of the enter; prise; there must be Justice in the quar∣rell, else there can be no true honour in the prosperity. <HI>Cato</HI> will love the con∣quered Common-wealth: <HI>Iugurtha</HI>'s fame, who is sayd to bee Illustrious for his Parricides and Rapines, will not make all men fall down and worship.</P>
<P>On <HI>Munday</HI> the fifteenth of <HI>Iuly</HI> (not of <HI>October,</HI> as <HI>VValsingham</HI> is mis-printed) The Chiefe Justice <HI>Tresilian</HI> calls before him the Jury for Inquiry, who faulter, and shamel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sly protest they cannot make any such discovery as is desired. The Chiefe Justice puts them in minde of the <HI>Kings</HI> Words to them upon the way, promising pardon if they will finde out the offendors, else threatning them with the punishment they should have suffered, who through such silence cannot be appre∣hended.</P>
<P><PB N="145" REF="79"/>
Out they goe againe, and the Chiefe Justice follows them; He shewes them a Roll of the principall Offendors names, tells them they must not thinke to delude and blinde the Court with this impudence, and advises them out of a care to preserve wicked mens lives not to hazard their own.</P>
<P>Hereupon they Indict many of the Towne and Country, which Indictments are allowed by a second Inquest appointed to bring in the Verdict, and againe affi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣med by a third Jury of twelve, charged onely for the fairenesse of the Tryall: So no man was pronounced guilty, but up∣on the finding, of thirty sixe Jurors. Then were the Lieutenants <HI>Greyndcob; Ca∣dingdon,</HI> and <HI>Barber,</HI> and twelve more Condemned, Drawne, and Hanged. <HI>VVallingford, Iohn Garleck, VVilliam Be∣rewill, Thomas Putor,</HI> and many more; with eightie of the Countrey, were In∣dicted by their Neighbours; and Impri∣prisoned, but forgiven by the Kings Mer∣cie, and discharged. They were forgi∣ven most by the Kings Mercie; for hee had forbidden by Proclamation, all men to sue or begge for them, a command which the good <HI>Abb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> sometimes disobey-
<PB N="146" REF="80"/>
and hee shall bee-well thanked for it.</P>
<P>No benefic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> oblige some men <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> true rugged ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> can never be made fast never bee tyed by any merit whatsoever Nothing can so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> him: See an unhe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rd of shamelesness till then; These lazi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>▪ tender-hearted Clowns, who could hard∣ly be got to discover the guilty, now runne with full speed to betray the innocent: They indict the <HI>Abbot</HI> as the principall Raiser, and contriver of these Tumults, which struck at his own life, and the be∣ing and safetis of his Monastery. The Ab∣bot, as it is said, sent to <HI>Tyler,</HI> upon his <HI>or∣dinances</HI> some of the Town and Monastery, but to temporiz, and secure himself. This is now supposed by the very Traytors in∣deed, <HI>Treason by Common Law and Sta∣tute against the King his naturall l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ige Lord.</HI> This <HI>having not the feare of God in his heart<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> &amp;c. <HI>but being seduced by the instigati∣on of the Devill, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> compassing the death,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>the deprivation and deposing of his So∣veraign Lord from his Royal State,</HI> &amp;c. (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> such Indictments use to run) this must goe for <HI>levying VVar against our Lord the King, adhering to, comforting, and a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ding his enemies by opon fact;</HI> which are the words of the Statute of Treason, declarative of the <NOTE PLACE="marg">25 Edw. 3.</NOTE> Common Law.</P>
<P><PB N="147" REF="80"/>
The Chief Justice, abominating and cur∣sing the treacherous malice, and perfidious∣ness of these Bruits, makes them tear the Indictment, which themselves, though ur∣ged, are not wicked enough to swear to: nay, which publiquely they confess to bee false in the face of the Court.</P>
<P><HI>Villeinage</HI> was not now abolished, though so methink otherwise, but by degrees ex∣tinguished since this reigne. Besides, the Letters of Revocation before, restoring all things to their old course, A Commission, which the Abbot procured from the King out of the Chancery, then kept in the Chapter-house of this Monastery, makes this manifest, which speaks to this effect:</P>
<P>RIchard <HI>by the grace of God King of</HI> England, <HI>and of</HI> France, <HI>and Lord of</HI> Ireland, <HI>&amp;c. To his beloved</HI> John Lodowick, Jo: Westwycomb, <HI>&amp;c. We command you, and every of you, upon sight of these presents, &amp;c. That on our part, forthwith ye cause to be proclaimed, That all and singular the Tenants of our beloved in Christ, the Abbot of S.</HI> Albane, <HI>as well free
<PB N="148" REF="81"/>
as bond; the Works, Customes and Ser∣vices, which they, to the foresaid Ab∣bot ought to doe, and of ancient time have been accustomed to performe; without any contradiction, murmur, &amp;c. Doe as before they have been ac∣customed.</HI></P>
<P>The disobedient are commanded to be taken, and imprisoned as Rebels.</P>
<P>In the time of <HI>King Henry</HI> the seventh there were villains. This I observe, to make <NOTE PLACE="marg">11 H. 7. 13</NOTE> it appeare how little it is which the misera∣ble common people, without whom no famous mischiefe can be attained, are gai∣ners by any of their riots, or seditions; whatsoever the changes are, their conditi∣on is still the same or worse; if some few of them advance themselves by the spoiles of the publique shipwrack, the rest are no happier for it; the insolent sight offends their eyes, they see the dirt of their owne ditches Lord it over them, and the body of them (perhaps) more despised than ever. <HI>Tyler</HI> (who could not but have known that nothing can be so destructive to Govern∣ment, as the licentiousnesse of the base Commons) would doubtlesse (when his
<PB N="149" REF="81"/>
owne work had been done) quickly have chained up the Monster, he would have perched in the Kings sacred O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke; all the Forrest should have beene his, Bishopricks, Earledomes, nay the Kingdomes had been swallowed by him; instead of a <HI>just ligall power</HI> by which the Kings acted, an <HI>arbi∣trary, boundlesse, unlimited power</HI> must have beene set up; instead of a fatherly royall Monarchy, a <HI>Tyranni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> after the Turkish mode, a Monarchy seignioral; and had he brought in upon the fall of the Christian Faith and Worship, which must have fol∣lowed his <HI>establishment,</HI> Circumcision, and the Creed of <HI>Maho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>et:</HI> as the spirits of men were then debased, he must have been obeyed. All the Kings right (and more) must have been his; <HI>Sultan Tyler's Prero∣gative</HI> would have been found more grie∣vous, more heavy, more killing than all the yokes and scorpions of our Kings; no man, when he went to sleep, could assure himself that one Law would he left next morning; the <HI>Ordinances</HI> of <HI>Tyler</HI> and his Council slew about in swarms, killing and rooting up the Laws: one Proclamation of this Tyrants was of force to blow up the anci∣ent Foundation; enough to have made men mad, if ever they could wake, and under∣stand:
<PB N="150" REF="82"/>
when the <HI>French</HI> had conquere<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>Naples,</HI> the people looked for a Golden World, they thought their new Master would (as the King of <HI>Mexico's</HI> Oath used to say) do Justice to all men, make the Su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> to shine, the Clouds to rain, the Earth to be fruitfull: They promise themselves <HI>Li∣berty,</HI> and that the accustomed Imposts of their former <HI>Kings</HI> of the House of <HI>Arra∣gon</HI> should not onely be taken off, but the very word <HI>Gabelle</HI> driven out of the King∣dom, ther should be no such thing in nature last; but foolish dolts as they were, they found an alteration quickly, instead of a Court Cavalrie before (the new Masters ill <HI>established</HI> and assured, not daring to trust any thing) standing Armies were continu∣ally to be kept on foot, instead of one Tax, intolerable of late, they are oppressed with ten, their backs and shoulders crack under the load.</P>
<P>Upon this fancy of these abused <HI>Italians,</HI> sayes the Historian, <HI>This is the custome, for the most part of all people weary ever of the presens condition, and inconsiderately gaping after a change, but they receive such wages of their fond and disorderly lightness.</HI></P>
<P>The War undertaken against <HI>Lewis</HI> the 11 of <HI>France</HI> by the House of <HI>Burgundy.</HI>
<PB N="151" REF="82"/>
Dukes of <HI>Berry, Brittaine,</HI> and <HI>Burbon,</HI> called the <HI>Weale publick</HI> was not made a∣gainst the King (say the Allies) but against evill order, injustice in the Government, and for the <HI>publick good</HI> of the Realm. In the Treaty for Peace these fine things are forgotten, the wretched Peasants torn, and ground with Taxes, left to shift for them∣selves.</P>
<P>The Prince of the <HI>Burgaundies</HI> demands the Townes upon the <HI>Some</HI> for himselfe: <HI>Normandy</HI> for the Duke of <HI>Berry,</HI> and o∣ther places, Offices, and Pensions for the rest, some overtures were made for the <HI>Weal publick</HI> (sayes the History) that is all, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Commen.</NOTE> the <HI>Weal publick</HI> was the least of the que∣stion, the <HI>Weal publick</HI> was turned to <HI>Weal particular, self seeking</HI> was the sum of the business. This has been the fashion of all Rebels hitherto, and will bee to the worlds end. After these proceedings the <HI>Hartfordshire</HI> men betwixt the ages of 15 and 60 present themselves according to command, and take the Oath of Allegi∣ance; they are sworn too to unkennel and apprehend the late Incendies.</P>
<P>The <HI>King</HI> having now quieted the com∣motions removes to <HI>Berkhamsted</HI> eight miles from St. <HI>Albanes,</HI> a royal Castle then,
<PB N="152" REF="83"/>
and at <HI>Easthamsted</HI> where he hunts, is in∣formed, That the bodies of the Traytors executed were taken down from the Gal∣lows, hereupon he directs his Writ or Let∣ter to the Bailies of St. <HI>Albanes,</HI> comman∣ding them under penalty of forfeiting all things forfeitable to hang up again the said bodies now rotten, and stinking in Iron chains, which the Townsmen are forced to do with their own hands.</P>
<P>A <HI>Parliament</HI> sitting in <HI>May</HI> the fift year of this <HI>Kings</HI> Reign, <HI>Iohn Wraw</HI> Priest of the Reformation at <HI>Mildenhall,</HI> and St. <HI>Edmundsbury</HI> was taken, and upon the Pe∣tition of the house of <HI>Commons</HI> to the <HI>King,</HI> judged to be drawn, and hanged. In the same <HI>Parliament</HI> too it was enacted, <HI>That wheresoever any Clowns by six or se∣ven in a company kept suspicious Con∣venticles, the Kings good and faithfull Sub∣jects should lay hold of them, and commit them</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Wals. Hypod.</NOTE> <HI>to the next Gaol without staying for the Kings VVrit.</HI> In the same Parliament of the King it was made Treason to begin a Riot, Rout, or Rumour, by this Parliament, and that of the 6. Provisions are made for those whose Deeds were burnt or destroyed in the late insurrection, and in the 6. of <HI>Rich∣ard,</HI> the King pardons the multitudes for
<PB N="153" REF="83"/>
their misdemeanours in the cumul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>. The Clowns now every where return'd to thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> old Obedience, and the winds were laid in all their quarter. <HI>Richard,</HI> a Prince born for troubles, shall be turmoiled with the Re∣bellion of his <HI>Peers</HI> and <HI>Parliaments,</HI> de∣posed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd murthered by them, his his me∣mory shall be sacred, his <HI>Peers</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d <HI>Chans▪</HI> shall dig for him in his grave, Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ity too shall owe all th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> to his person. Af<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="7 words" DISP="〈7 words〉"/></NOTE> the death of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d bloody thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>f a cruel tyrane <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d the <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣man</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <HI>Capit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/>, tory Petter writtn by <HI>Claud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> Consul to the Emperours <HI>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>us</HI> and <HI>Balbinus,</HI> whom he ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s <HI>Pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>vers and Re∣deemers of the Common wealth,</HI> there the Consul tels them they had resto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d to the Senate (the house of Lords) their ancient dignity, to the <HI>Romans</HI> their Laws, Equity, and Clemency abolished, their lives, their manners, their liberty, the hopes of succes∣sion to their heirs He adde they had freed the Provinces from the insatiable covetous∣ness of tyrannes, no voice, language, not wit can express (saies he) the publick happi∣nesse.</P>
<P>King <HI>Richard</HI> restored to the Church and Universities their rights and possessions, to
<PB REF="84"/>
the Nobilitie their honour, to the <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> their respect, to the Cities their free, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the plenty of his harvest to the ind<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Countryman, Security, Peace, and Libert<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> to all Orders, what Prince could best <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> greater benefits upon a people? he was the Stator, the Saviour of the Nation, a Nati∣on not worthy of him, whose ingratefulness to his sacred head, whose perfidiousness and impiety in advancing an usurper upon his ruins, were punished with a fatall Civill War, which lasted ages, with an issue of blood which could not be stopped till the true and lawful heir of this Prince was seat∣ed in the Imperial Throne, according to the, Faith and Oathes of this people (which whatsoever may be pretended no power on earth can dispence with) and accord∣ing to the Fundamental Laws of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

