<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A copie of the articles agreed upon at the surrender of the city of Bristol betweene Colonell Nathaniel Fiennes governour of the said city, on the one party, and Colonell Charles Gerrard and Captain William Teringham for and on the behalfe of Prince Rupert, on</TITLE><AUTHOR>Fiennes, Nathaniel, 1607 or 8-1669.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A34506</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing C6203</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R8115</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12090150</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12090150</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">53836</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A34506)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53836)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 239:E63, no 15)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A copie of the articles agreed upon at the surrender of the city of Bristol betweene Colonell Nathaniel Fiennes governour of the said city, on the one party, and Colonell Charles Gerrard and Captain William Teringham for and on the behalfe of Prince Rupert, on</TITLE><AUTHOR>Fiennes, Nathaniel, 1607 or 8-1669.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>8 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Henty Overton ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>[1643]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Rupert, --  Prince, Count Palatine, 1619-1682.</TERM><TERM>Fiennes, Nathaniel, 1607 or 8-1669.</TERM><TERM>Macclesfield, Charles Gerard, --  Earl of, 1618?-1694.</TERM><TERM>Teringham, William.</TERM><TERM>Bristol (England) --  History --  Siege, 1643.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A34506">
<STC T="W">C6203</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12090150</BIBNO>
<VID>53836</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A
COPIE OF
THE
ARTICLES
Agreed upon at the surrender of the
City of
BRISTOL▪
Betweene Colonell <HI>Nathaniel Fien∣nes,</HI>
Governour of the said City, on the one
Party, and Colonell <HI>Charles Gerrard,</HI> and Cap∣taine
<HI>William Teringham,</HI> for, and on the behalfe
of Prince <HI>Rupert,</HI> on the other party, the
26. of <HI>Iuly,</HI> 1643.</P>
<P>With a Letter hereunto added, in which this
Copie of Articles was Inclosed: wherein is mani∣fested
how well those perfidious Cavaliers have kept
the said Articles▪ and may serve as a warning to the whole
Kingdome, how to trust againe the Faith
of such CAVALIERS.</P>
<P>Published according to Order.</P>
<P>LONDON
<HI>Printed for</HI> Henry Overton <HI>in</HI> Popes-head Alley.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="treaty">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>ARTICLES
AGREED ON,
AT THE CITY
OF
BRISTOLL,
Between Colonell Nathaniel Fiennes,
Governour of the said City, on the one party,
and Collonel Charles Gerard, and Captain
William Teringham, for, and on the behalf
of Prince Rupert, on the other party,
<DATE>the 26. of Iuly, 1643.</DATE></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hat the Governour <HI>Nathaniel Fi∣ennes,</HI>
together with all the Officers
both of Horse and Foot, now within
and about this City of <HI>Bristoll,</HI> Ca∣stle
&amp; Forts, may march out to mor∣row
morning by 9. of the clock, with their full Arms,
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
Horses, bagge and baggage, provided it be their
owne goods; and that the Common Foot Souldiers
March out without Armes, and the Troopers with
their Horses and Swords, leaving their other Arms
behind them, with a safe Convoy to <HI>Warmister,</HI> and
after not to be molested in their March by any of
the Kings Forces, for the space of three dayes.</P>
<P>2. That there may be Carriages allowed and
provided, to carry away their Bagge and Baggage,
and sicke and hurt Souldiers.</P>
<P>3. That the Kings Forces march not into the
Towne, till the Parliament Forces are marched
out, which is at 9. of the clock.</P>
<P>4. That all Prisoners in the Cite be delivered
up, and that Captain <HI>Eyres,</HI> and Captaine <HI>Gookin,</HI>
who were taken at the Devises, be released.</P>
<P>5. Th<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Sir <HI>Iohn Homer,</HI> Sir <HI>Iohn Seymoure,</HI>
Mr, Edward <HI>Steevens,</HI> and all other Knights, Gen∣tlemen,
Citizens, and other persons, that are now
in the City, may if they please, with their Goods,
Wives and Families, Horses, Bagge and Ba<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gage,
have free Liberty to returne to their owne homes,
or else where, and there to rest in safety, or ride and
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
travell with the Governour and Forces; and such
of them and their Families as shall be left behind,
by reason of sicknesse or other cause, may have liber∣ty,
so soon as they can conveniently, to depart this
Towne with safety, provided that all the Gentle∣men
and other persons, shall have three dayes li∣berty
to reside here, or depart with their goods,
which they please.</P>
<P>6. That all the Inhabitants of this City, shall
be secured in their Persons, Families and Estates,
free from plundering, and all other violence or
wrong whatsover.</P>
<P>7. That the Charters and Liberties of this City,
may be preserved, and that the antient Government
therof, and present Governours and Officers may
remaine and continue in their former condition,
according to his Majesties Charters and pleasure.</P>
<P>8. That for av<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yding inconveniencies and di∣str<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctions,
the Quartering of Souldiers be referred
or left to the Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or and Governour of the same City
for the time being.</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="4"/>
9. That all such as have carryed any goods into
the Castle, may have free liberty to carry the same
forth.</P>
<P>10. That the Forces that are to March out, are
to leave behind them all Cannon and Ammunition,
with their Colours, and such Armes as is before
expressed.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A Copie of a Letter sent from Bristoll.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>SInce my last unto you by the Post, and the
post hitherward intercepted by the enemie, the
case is changed; for on <HI>Thursday</HI> last wee rendred
the Citie of <HI>Bristoll,</HI> as by the Articles here inclosed
you may perceive, but what faith hath beene kept
there after, let the robberies and spoyles of every
particular person declare; amongst which, I praise
God, I am escaped with my life to the towne of
<HI>Southampton,</HI> with my sonne <HI>Iohn;</HI> but before I
could come forth of the gates of the City of <HI>Bristol,</HI>
I was deprived of my money, plate, and baggage
from behind my servants, who were throwne off
their horses, and the same cut off their backes, and
utterly lost, and themselves and their horses in like
condition, for ought I know, and onely wee our
selves, with some other gentlemen, escaped hither
with our lives on <HI>Friday</HI> night last; and on <HI>Satur∣day</HI>
came in also the late Governour of <HI>Bristoll,</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
Col. <HI>Fiennes,</HI> and his brother, with the remainder
of the whole soulderie, who were served with the
like sauce, such is the faith held with the present
Victors. My wife and family in all this time not
knowing whether we are alive, or where we are;
nor know wee which way to send home, in
regard all the Wayes are full of the enemies sorces,
unlesse the Carryer of <HI>Wells</HI> hold his course from
<HI>London</HI> thither, which if hee doth, I pray let your
man <HI>Jonathan</HI> by that Carrier, present his mother
with a line or two of our safetie in this place and
still beseech you, though our fortunes be altered,
to shew your good affection to <HI>Ionathan</HI> and <HI>Io∣seph,</HI>
with my best respects to my loving Gossip
and your selfe, remaine</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your faithfull friend
and servaut, I. P.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>Southampton,
<DATE>July 31. 1643.</DATE></DATELINE>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<P>Pray let your man <HI>Ionathan</HI> write out two or three
copies of this inclosed, and deliver one of them to my
son <HI>Chillingworth,</HI> with my love to him and my daughter;
a second to Mr <HI>Shephead,</HI> with my commendations, in
hope to see him and you all, with what speed wee may,
which should be very speedily, did not the Kings horse
lye in our way to <HI>London;</HI> and a third to Mr. <HI>Peter Va<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣depu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</HI>
my commendations also to him and his wife, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

