<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Some mistaken scriptvres sincerely explained in answer to one infected with some Pelagian errours / written by Benjamin Cox when he was first prisoner in Coventrie, now published by the author for the clearing of the truth.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Cox, Benjamin, fl. 1646.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A34848</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing C6715</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R32491</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12706406</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12706406</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">66023</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A34848)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66023)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1524:23)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Some mistaken scriptvres sincerely explained in answer to one infected with some Pelagian errours / written by Benjamin Cox when he was first prisoner in Coventrie, now published by the author for the clearing of the truth.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Cox, Benjamin, fl. 1646.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 6 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Tho. Paine ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1646.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>"Licensed and entered according to order."</NOTE><NOTE>Page 5 misprinted 7.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Theology, Doctrinal.</TERM><TERM>Pelagianism.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Celeste Ng</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Celeste Ng</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A34848">
<STC T="W">C6715</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12706406</BIBNO>
<VID>66023</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Some
MISTAKEN SCRIPTVRES
Sincerely explained.</P>
<P>In answer to one infected with some
Pelagian Errours.</P>
<P>VVritten by <HI>Benjamin Cox</HI> when he was
first Prisoner in <HI>Coventrie.</HI> Now published▪
by the Author for the clearing of the truth.</P>
<P><Q><BIBL>1 Cor. 2. 14.</BIBL>
<P>The naturall man rcceiveth not the things of the spirit of
God, for they are foolishnesse unto him: neither can he know
them, because they are spiritually discerned.</P></Q></P>
<P><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="license">
<P>Licensed and entered according to Order.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P>LONDON,
Printed by <HI>Tho. Paine,</HI> living in Red-crosse-Street in
Gold-Smiths Alley, over against the Suger loafe. 1646.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Some mistaken Scriptures sincerely explai∣ned,
in an Answer to one infected with
<HI>some Pelagian Errours.</HI></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Hereas you say that some Scriptures seeme too hold forth
unto you that a man hath free-will, I desire you for your
better information to take notice of these two Proposi∣tions.</P>
<P>1. <HI>Propos.</HI> We do not simply deny that a man hath a∣ny
freedome of will: but only do hold that no naturall man, nor any
man of himself, hath a sufficient power, or freedom of will, unto the
choosing of that way, which is good and right, and acceptable in the
sight of God. To the choosing of evill wayes; wee grant that every
naturall man hath freedome enough, if so be this may be termed by so
good a name as Freedome. Consequently, we doe not hold that any
man is compelled or enforced by violence to choose the evill, or to re∣fuse
the good: but that through the corruption of nature man unre∣newed
doth willingly and wilfully refuse the good way, and choose
the evill. And whereas the unregenerate person can do no otherwise,
this is not the fruit of any force or compulsion laid upon him, but only
of the obstinate wickednesse, or wicked obstinacy of his own corrup∣ted
and depraved will. The truth hereof appeares by these Scriptures,
<HI>Gen.</HI> 8. 21. <HI>Eccles.</HI> 9. 3. <HI>Jerem.</HI> 17. 9. <HI>Math.</HI> 15. 19. <HI>Rom.</HI> 3. 9, 10, 11, &amp;c.
<HI>Rom.</HI> 8. 6, 7, 8. <HI>James</HI> 1. 13 14, 15. <HI>Joh.</HI> 8. 44.</P>
<P>2. <HI>Propos.</HI> The elect do indeed with unfained willingnesse obey the
Gospell of Jesus Christ, and choose the Lord to be their God: but this
they do when they are effectually called, and not before: and this they
doe, not of themselves, nor only by the well using of an ability or
power given to all men; but by the speciall grace of God to them af∣forded,
who worketh in them both to will &amp; to do, &amp; this according
to the good pleasure of his owne will concerning them from all eter∣nity.
The trueth of this appeares in these places; <HI>Isai.</HI> 54. 13. compared
with <HI>Joh</HI> 6 44, 45. 64, 65. <HI>Ezek</HI> 36. 26, 27. <HI>Rom.</HI> 8. 28, 29, 30. <HI>Ephes.</HI> 1. 4, 5,
11. <HI>Philip.</HI> 1 29. <HI>Philip.</HI> 2. 13. <HI>James</HI> 1. 18.</P>
<P><PB REF="3"/>
These <HI>Propositions</HI> being thus laid downe and cleared, I come now
to consider those Scriptures w<SUP>ch</SUP> you name to prove that a man hath
free will, or free choice; <HI>viz. Deut.</HI> 30. 19. <HI>Josh.</HI> 24. 15. 22. <HI>Judg.</HI> 10. 14.
<HI>Isaiah</HI> 65. 12. and 66. <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="scratched out" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>3. 1 <HI>King.</HI> 3. 5-11. <HI>Psal.</HI> 119. 30. <HI>Luk.</HI> 10. 42.</P>
<P><HI>Deut.</HI> 30. 19 <HI>I call heaven and earth to record this day against you, that
I have set before you life and death, blessing and cursing: therefore choose
life,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>This place shewes what was the duty of the <HI>Israelites</HI> to doe: but
doth not proove that they had any abillity of themselves to doe it; or
that God gives any such abillity to all men. Compare this place with
2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 3. 5. and <HI>Deut.</HI> 29. 4.</P>
<P><HI>Josh.</HI> 24. 15. <HI>And if it seeme evill unto you to serve the Lord, chuse you
this day whom you will serve,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>Here I somewhat question what part of the verse you would have
especially to be opened: whether this: <HI>Choose you this day whom you
will serve,</HI> &amp;c. Or this; <HI>But as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord.</HI>
The first implyes that Idolaters doe freely choose those Idolls, with
which they commit spirituall whoredome. Freely, that is to say, not
being enforced or compelled thereunto by any violence constraining
them to this motion of their will. This is not denyed, but acknow∣ledged
and held by us, as you may see in the first proposition. The
l<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st part of the verse holds forth the free and constant resolution of the
Saints to serve the Lord. This also is taught in my second propositi∣on▪
But there you must likewise remember, that this is the fruit of the
speciall grace of God afforded to the Elect, who worketh in them
both to will and to doe; <HI>Philip.</HI> 2. 13. And this worke is wrought by
the infinite power of God. <HI>Ephes.</HI> 1. 19. and 3. 20.</P>
<P><HI>Josh.</HI> 24. 22. <HI>Yee are witnesses against your selves, that you have Chosen
you the Lord, to serve him.</HI></P>
<P>This is meant directly and only of that which went before in <HI>vers.</HI>
21. <HI>The people said unto Joshua, Nay, but we will serve the Lord.</HI> They
that were Israelites indeed, did in truth and sincerity make this pro∣mise
and choice; but this they did not of themselves, but through
the speciall grace of God, as hath been already proved.</P>
<P><HI>Judg.</HI> 10. 14. <HI>Goe and cry unto the Gods which yee have chosen.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Isaiah</HI> 65. 12. <HI>When I speake, yee did not heare, but did evill before mine
eyes, and did chuse that wherein</HI> I <HI>delighted not.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Jsaiah</HI> 66. 3. <HI>They have chosen their own wayes, and their soule delighteth
in their abominations.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="3" REF="3"/>
These three places imply no more then what we cleerly hold; as
you may see in my first proposition.</P>
<P>1 <HI>King</HI> 3. 5. 6. 9. 10. <HI>God said, aske what J shall give thee. And Solo∣mon
said, Give thy servant an understanding heart,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>And the speech plea∣sed
the Lord, that Solomon had asked this thing.</HI></P>
<P>This place seemes to you to import, that <HI>Solomon</HI> did freely make
choice to aske of God understanding to heare judgement. This we de∣ny
not. But consider also that this choice and petition was the fruit of
the wisedome and grace which God had already given him. Com∣pare
this place with <HI>Zechar. 12. 10. J will poure upon the house of David,
and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the spirit of grace, and of supplicati∣ons.</HI>
See also <HI>Rom.</HI> 8. 26.</P>
<P><HI>Psal.</HI> 119. 30. <HI>J have chosen the way of truth.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Luke</HI> 10. 42. <HI>Mary hath chosen that good part.</HI></P>
<P>True, but it was the speciall grace of God; the speciall, gracious and
powerfull worke of Gods spirit, which caused <HI>David</HI> and <HI>Mary</HI> to
make that good choice: as also hath been already prooved. And
thus have I done with your first catalogue of texts of Scripture.</P>
<P>Your second catalogue containes certaine places, in which (as you
conceive) the promises of God doe depend upon our doing of his
commands. Hereto I answer first more generally.</P>
<P>The Scripture promiseth eternall life to those that obey the Gospel
of Christ: <HI>Heb.</HI> 5. 9. &amp; threatens eternall destruction to the disobedient,
<HI>Io.</HI> 3. 36. 2 <HI>Thes.</HI> 1. 8. This we acknowledge, and thus we teach But con∣sider
that which I have also already proved, that the elect of God per∣forme
this obedience through Gods speciall Grace; and that this
speciall grace is freely given to them of God according to this own
purpose concerning them from all eternitie; and that God hath free∣ly
promised this grace to his elect. All this appeares by places of
Scripture already aleadged for the confirmation of my second pro∣position.</P>
<P>Thus I descend to consider more particularly the places of Scrip∣ture
that you here present unto me. <HI>viz. Levit.</HI> 26. 3. and <HI>Isaiah</HI> 1. 19.
<HI>Prov.</HI> 1 23. <HI>Jer.</HI> 7. 13. <HI>Mat.</HI> 19. 17. <HI>Mat.</HI> 11. 28. <HI>Mat.</HI> 11. 21. <HI>Mat.</HI>
23. 37. <HI>Luke</HI> 16. 16. <HI>Ier.</HI> 3. 22.</P>
<P><HI>Levit.</HI> 26. 3. &amp;c. <HI>If ye walke in my statutes, and keepe my commande∣ments,
and doe them, then</HI> I <HI>will give you,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>Here we must remember; 1. That since <HI>Adams</HI> fall no meere man
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
either did or could keep Gods commandements, &amp; do them, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ording
to the rigor and strictnesse of the Law. <HI>Eccles.</HI> 7. 20. 2. That where∣as
the Elect among the <HI>Israelites</HI> did truly beleeve in the promised
Messiah, and did shew the truth of their faith by the sincerity of their
obedience to Gods revealed will in every thing; this was the fruit of
Gods speciall grace to them afforded. <HI>Numb.</HI> 14 24. <HI>Psal.</HI> 119 32. 36.
These cleare truths may also free you from your doubts that seemes
to arise from the next place by you mentioned, <HI>viz. Isaiah.</HI> 1. 19.</P>
<P><HI>Prov.</HI> 1. 23. <HI>Turne you at my reproofe, behold,</HI> I <HI>will poure out my spirit
unto you,</HI> I <HI>will make knowne my words unto you.</HI></P>
<P>The former part of this verse is an exhortation. It is the conceit
of some that such exhortations doe alwayes imply that the persons
exhorted have a sufficient ability in them to obey the exhortation
directed unto them. But this conceit is a meere presumption, not only
without ground, but also against the Scripture, as appeares in <HI>Iohn</HI> 6.
65. and other places. It is demanded, why then are such exhortations
used? I answer, 1. To mind the persons exhorted of their duty, and
to leave them the more inexcusable in their willfull disobedience.
2. Because the Lord is pleased to worke powerfully upon the Elect by
such exhortations</P>
<P>The latter part of this verse containes a promise. You (as it seemes)
conceive the promise to be here made only unto those that obey the
exhortation afore going. Be it so. Only remember then, that they
which obey the exhortation, doe obey the same through Gods spe∣ciall
grace; and that the promise serves to assure them of the conti∣nuance
and increase of grace.</P>
<P><HI>Jer.</HI> 7. 13. <HI>And now because ye have done all these workes, saith the Lord▪
and</HI> I <HI>spake unto you, rising up early, and speaking, but ye heard not; and</HI> I
<HI>called you, but you answered not.</HI></P>
<P>If you consider this verse only, and read no further, it only hold
forth the goodnesse and patience of God, in admonishing and exhor∣ting
the stubborne Jewes; and their willfull and obstinate disobedienc<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
to Gods word. If ye read the verses following also, this Scriptur<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
minds you that the disobedience and obstinacy of the Iewes was th<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
cause of their distruction. All these things we readily acknowledge
neither doe they make any thing at all against us.</P>
<P><HI>Mat.</HI> 19. 17. <HI>If thou wilt enter into life, keepe the commandements.</HI></P>
<P>Here you must consider to whom our Saviour sp<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="scratched out" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ake this, <HI>viz.</HI>
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
one that sought to establish his owne righteousnesse, and to get Hea∣ven
by his own doing of the good works w<SUP>ch</SUP> the Law required, who
accordingly had propounded this question? <HI>What good thing shall</HI> I <HI>doe
that</HI> I <HI>may have eternall life?</HI> The meaning of our Saviours answer is
this; If thou wilt thinke to get eternall life this way thou must keep
the commandements; that is, thou must be found a person not any
way guilty of any transgression against Gods commandements. This
was a thing of meere and utter impossibillity, and our Saviours scope
in returning to him this answer, was to discover unto him the vanity
and madnesse of his proud and foolish imagination. Thus this place
rightly understood hath not in it the least shew of opposition against
our doctrine.</P>
<P><HI>Mat.</HI> 11. 28. <HI>Come unto me all yee that labour, and are heavie laden,
and</HI> I <HI>will give you rest.</HI></P>
<P>Here Christ promiseth to give rest, not to all Persons whatso∣ever,
but only to those labouring and heavie laden ones which come
to him, namely by a true faith in him. This maketh nothing against
us, it still remaining true, that they, and they only, doe thus come unto
Christ, in whose hearts God worketh lively faith. And this God wor∣keth
in his Elect, and only in them.</P>
<P><HI>Mat.</HI> 11. 21. <HI>Woe unto thee Chorazin, wo unto thee, Bethsaida: for if
the mighty workes which were done in you, had beene done in Tire and Sidon,</HI>
<HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>The manifest scope of our Saviour in this place, is to shew the open
in excusablenesse of the impenitency and unbeliefe of Chorazin and
Bethsaida. The last words of the verse, from which your doubt ari∣seth,
may be understood to be a figurative speech, like unto that in
<HI>Luke</HI> 19. 40. <HI>If these should hold their peace, the stones would immediately
cry out.</HI> Otherwise the words may be thus rendered. <HI>They had possibly
repented; or, They would possibly have repented.</HI> This translation would
be found well to agree to the signification of the potentiall particle
which is here used in the Greeke. And then this will be the true and
easie interpretation of this passage: <HI>viz. A man would thinke they should
have repented.</HI> Beyond this, this place must not be stretched. For no in∣terpretation
must be given of any place of Scripture, which shall in∣deed
make it to contradict the Scripture it selfe in other places.</P>
<P><HI>Mat.</HI> 23. 37. <HI>O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, how often would</HI> I <HI>have gathered
thy children together, even as a Hen gathereth her chickins under her wings
and yee would not.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
The meaning is this; How often have I graciously afforded unto
the people of Jerusalem excellent meanes of salvation? but the stub∣borne
people of Jerusalem have wilfully refused to accept of those
meanes of salvation, and to profit by the same. This is all that this
place doth import: and this maketh nothing at all against us.</P>
<P><HI>Luke</HI> 16. 16. <HI>The law and the Prophets were untill Iohn: since that
time the kingdome of God is preached and every man,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>The words in this verse which you would have to be opened are
thus commonly rendered: <HI>The kingdome of God is preached, and every
man presseth into it.</HI> Suppose this translation to be right and the mea∣ning
to be the same that our common expositors have held forth in
this ensuing interpretation; <HI>Every man,</HI> that is to say, many men or
every order and degree of men <HI>presseth into it;</HI> that is, with willingnes
and forwardnesse receiveth the doctrine of the kingdome; and so en∣treth
into the kingdome of God. Suppose I say that this were indeed
the meaning of this place; yet it would be found to make nothing at
all against us. For still it will remaine true, that the Elect doe this
through Gods speciall grace. But the truth is, that this interpretation
doth not reach our Saviours meaning in this place. The words should
thus be rendered; <HI>every man offereth violence unto it.</HI> The meaning is
this; <HI>every man;</HI> that is, the whole world of ungodly men. <HI>Offereth viol¦lence
unto it,</HI> that is, makes a violent opposition against the kingdome
of God and the preaching thereof. See <HI>Mat.</HI> 11. 12. compared with
<HI>vers.</HI> 16. 17, 18. &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Jer. 3.</HI> 22. <HI>Returne yee backslding children,</HI> &amp;c. In this verse is contained.</P>
<P>1. An exhortation. <HI>Returne yee back sl<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>g children.</HI></P>
<P>2. A promise. I <HI>will heale your back slidings.</HI> This promise you understand to be∣long
only unto those that obey the aforesaid exhortation. Even so this maketh no∣thing
against us, but perfectly agreeth with our doctrine. But let me here mind you
that this promise may be understood not only to be a promise of pardon to them that
repent, but also a promise of the gift of repentance to the Elect. See <HI>Jer.</HI> 31. 33. 34.
and <HI>Acts</HI> 5. 31. The particle <HI>and</HI> here inserted, seemes to make against this. But this
need not trouble us, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th it is only a supplement or addition of the translators, and is
not in the text.</P>
<P>3. A profession of repentance and faith, <HI>Behold, we come unto thee, for thou are
the Lord our God.</HI> You must understand this to be the speech of the Elect endued with
Gods speciall grace. See <HI>Ier.</HI> 31. 18, 19.</P>
<P>Thus according to your request, according to the abilitie which God hath given
me, I have opened the Scriptures that you have mentioned. The Lord open your un∣derstanding,
that you may discerne the truth and ackowledge the same to the glory of
God.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="5"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

