<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Apocalyps, chap. 11 its accomplishment shewed from the Lady Eleanor.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Eleanor, Lady, d. 1652.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A36390</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing D1969</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R3587</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12375540</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12375540</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">60580</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A36390)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60580)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 937:14)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Apocalyps, chap. 11 its accomplishment shewed from the Lady Eleanor.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Eleanor, Lady, d. 1652.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>8 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London? :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>164-?]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</NOTE><NOTE>Caption title.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XI.</TERM><TERM>Spiritualism --  Controversial literature.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A36390">
<STC T="W">D1969</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12375540</BIBNO>
<VID>60580</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="1" MS="y"/>
<HEAD><BIBL>APOCALYPS, <HI>Chap.</HI> 11.</BIBL> Its accomplishment shewed from the Lady <HI>ELEANOR.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THus Reader in a word to thee, what the unsealed words of this Prophesie imports; VVe even in the same Estate with them, called well Spiritually hardned <HI>Egypt,</HI> and sinful <HI>Sodoms</HI> great City (pointing expresly to the Spiritual calling in the last days what incurable Blindeness Arrogan∣cy begets: Here impeached of the sin against the Holy Ghost, guilty of the blood of these his sacred Ambassa∣dors slain by them: the Prophet <HI>Da∣niel</HI> and <HI>John,</HI> no inferior prophets, their Books being interpreted by the same Spirit they wrote, and these Im∣printed
<PB N="2" REF="2"/>
at <HI>Holland, Anno</HI> 1633. imme∣diately seized on, shrowded in a loose sheet of paper: their embalmd bodies about Doctors Commons, the good hour waiting for of their resurrection wounded in that barbarous manner, assaulted by merciless, desperate men, unto a senceless, saltless age sent; bid∣den, <HI>Remember her looking back, Lots faithless Wife,</HI> who neither discern the time, know not the voyce of the pro∣phets, enemies to the Churches deli∣verance <HI>(Micah</HI> 4.) promised, at last, the downfal of her foes, come upon themselves have fulfilled it: By fil∣ling the measure up, reaching to Hea∣ven: an account but current hereto∣fore, never compleat till now the holy Ghost in such manner blasphemed: The invincible truth tearm'd mad∣ness,
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
the Prophets Testimony as ex∣tant on Record, and published, sen∣tenced detestable, as if any thing were too hard for the <HI>Lord</HI> in his appointed time: whose dead bodies trodden un∣derfoot daily, or swept out like week∣ly Occurrences, those truths; and pro∣ceeding with the bruitish fact com∣mitted on these sacred VVitnesses, or Ambassadors arived what their enter∣tainment; though not ignorant what power extraordinary indued with: wonders of the highest kinde at their word, waters turn'd into blood, VVar foreshewed, Heaven shut, and the like, smite the Earth with plagues as often as they speak the word, yet these rash wretches such a vexation their presence, clad in Sackcloth, &amp;c. gratifie with presents making merry,
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
as the maner by stoping one anothers mouths, to make up the Breach; tri∣umphing over their corps slain by the Beast coming out of the smoking pit or Abyss, as appears, making VVar with them, with his furious Train, armed at all points this British beast.</P>
<P>Not a little wilde concerned in it, because shewed in this maner: <HI>He must be killed</HI> (verse) which harms them, touches a leaf of the Tree of Life, a violent death, whose doom be he whatsoever, <HI>vers.</HI> 5. <HI>cap.</HI> 11.</P>
<P>And though since see it true, visible as their unexpected Resurrection and Ascension, beheld by their very Ene∣mies, eye witness of it: Gentlemen no less slighted, then by those im∣pious persons insenced at their Testi∣mony, supposed such an impossibility
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
in those profane feasting days, adored by his riotous Lords, Courted by his Concubines, with <HI>Belshazzar,</HI> born under a like malevolent Planet: And though needless any farther shewing, concerning in the last time, the last days approach to be revealed out of the Prophet <HI>Daniel</HI> and the <HI>Apocalyps,</HI> one a Phenix of great <HI>Babylon,</HI> the other an Eagle, his flight from <HI>Pat∣mos</HI> Isle, of times tyranical Reign cut off, and his cashiered Generation; suffering for which glad tidings mur∣thered by wretched caytiffs (vers.) confirmed both by their Resurrection and Ascending: &amp; whose scaled writs reserved for the end, not opened to be till then or served. Notwithstand∣ing of Times mystery thus, his being bidden, <HI>Arise and measure the Temple;</HI>
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
after the seven thunders voyces utter∣ed, proclaiming of a certain in what century, sworn in his wrath, Times being no longer; He forbidden to measure the Court, leave it out, given to the Gentiles; of whose treading un∣der foot 42 moneths the City, as fol∣lows, signified by the <HI>Temple of God,</HI> the year of God how about 1642. from his leaving the High Court, &amp;c. un∣to <HI>Nazebies</HI> blow given him, just three years and a half, even from <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641. unto <HI>Anno Dom.</HI> 1644. compleat, that Ascensions feast and cities solemn thanksgiving. And thus as the hea∣vens one contained in another, under that great victory obtained, shadow∣ed out the general day of Iudgement not far off; whereat the holy prophets and Elders not more rejoycing, then
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
the ireful Nations inraged; like those so many thousand prisoners brought up, &amp;c. filling every place like Hell, likened to that great Earthquake 1645. after the aforesaid feast, when a List re∣turned with Names, &amp;c. ver. <HI>a rem∣nant onely escaping, giving glory to God,</HI> or took their flight, as shewed (v. 13.) all pointing to the present century; as moreover 7000 slain by the cities fall, the tenth part of it in the same hour, &amp;c. confirm'd by the divided number of Seven, <HI>a time and times and half</HI> (or part.) And so much for measuring out of these times of division never such; and the third wo said <HI>to come quickly,</HI> shewing the other two are past: what signs and woful tokens visited with (to wit) monstrous levied Taxes devour∣ing yong and old, and Engines of war those pieces in a moment destroying,
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
men by Sea and Land innumerable, as though Hell let loose, the Devils short, &amp;c. And for these in special, let so much suffice of Heaven opened, or the Temple of GOD, &amp;c.) with the two <HI>Candlesticks, and two Olive-Trees anointed</HI> ones, passing over the Gene∣ral, what war hath bin waged against the Old and New Testament, and two Sacraments, the sum of it, <HI>oyl in their lamps,</HI> or watchful, &amp;c. including your <HI>Holland</HI> Ambassadors welcom, &amp; that the Cedar if not spared, or the root, let the Firtree beware, the branches must not be too bold, between whom (the King &amp; Bishops in hot blood) to judge referd to those two divided brethren, one returning a cross answer, the yon∣ger as free of his fair language, prohi∣bits deferring to give God the glory, or going about to deceive him, with <HI>I, I,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="5"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

