<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A defence of the papers written by the late king of blessed memory, and Duchess of York, against the answer made to them</TITLE><AUTHOR>Dryden, John, 1631-1700.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A36614</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing D2261</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R22072</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12123886</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12123886</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">54485</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A36614)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54485)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 92:14)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A defence of the papers written by the late king of blessed memory, and Duchess of York, against the answer made to them</TITLE><AUTHOR>Dryden, John, 1631-1700.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 126, [3] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by H. Hills ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1686.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>A reply to Edward Stillingfleet's "An answer to some papers." The "papers" in question concerned Charles II's inclination towards and Anne Hydis conversion to Catholicism.</NOTE><NOTE>Written by J. Dryden. Cf. Wing.</NOTE><NOTE>"By command"</NOTE><NOTE>Errata: p. 126.</NOTE><NOTE>Advertisements on p. [1]-[2] at end.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685. --  Copies of two papers.</TERM><TERM>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Answer to some papers lately printed.</TERM><TERM>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2002-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A36614">
<STC T="W">D2261</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12123886</BIBNO>
<VID>54485</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A
DEFENCE
OF THE
PAPERS
Written by the Late
KING
<HI>Of Blessed Memory,</HI>
AND
Duchess of York,
AGAINST
The ANSWER made to Them.</P>
<P>By Command.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by <HI>H. Hills,</HI> Printer to the King's Most
Excellent Majesty for His Houshold and
Chappel. 1686.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>PREFACE.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>IS acknowledg'd, that Sove∣reign
Princes, when They en∣ter
into the Lists of Dispu∣tation,
may be answer'd, as
well as Private Men: for
then they Command not, but only Argue,
speak their Opinion, and Instruct. The An∣swerer
is not therefore blam'd for appearing
on the contrary Side to our late Sovereign of
Blessed Memory, whose Papers were for that
Reason made Public, that every man might
have the liberty of considering them, and of
making a free and upright Iudgment con∣cerning
them. Accordingly it hath pleas'd
Almighty God, by means of them, to open
the Vnderstanding, and direct the Will of
many sober and well-meaning Readers, in the
knowledge of his only True Church, and the
desire of being united to it. The great Suc∣cess
of them, as it is manifest to the World,
<PB REF="3"/>
so in all probability hath occasion'd the An∣swer,
by one who calls himself <HI>a Son of the
Church of England;</HI> and who gives it as
the Reason of the publishing his Pamphlet,
<HI>That the Papers thus dispers'd in Print,
may fall into many Hands, who, without
some Assistance, may not readily resolve
some Difficulties started by them.</HI> Vpon
which Consideration, this Author thought it
<HI>not unbecoming his Duty to God and
the King, to give a clearer Light to the
Things contained in them:</HI> Which not long
after he explains, in relation at least to the
First Paper, <HI>wherein he could have been
glad to have found as much Reason to
convince, as there was a fair Appearance
to deceive.</HI> Now whether the King intend∣ed
to deceive his People, or that the Deceit
might be occasion'd by His Writings, I leave
our Author to expound. But in general, to
clear Difficulties, and discover a Cousenage, I
freely grant, not to be unbecoming of our Duty.
An Answer then may be made, even to a
King; but the Manner of Answering is like∣wise
to be consider'd. And surely there is
somewhat more of Respect to be given to a
Sovereign Prince, than to a common or pri∣vate
<PB REF="3"/>
Disputant; especially if the Answerer
be his Subject. The Cardinal of <HI>Peronne,</HI>
tho' a Forreigner, has observ'd this Decency in
the Controversie manag'd betwixt our King
<HI>JAMES</HI> the First and him. <HI>Luther,</HI> on the
other side, has made a <HI>German</HI> Quarrel
with <HI>HENRY</HI> the Eighth, without allowing
Him so much as the Name of King; but in
the beginning of his Answer, calling Him
barely by His Christn'd Name, and using Him
afterward as familiarly and scurrilously, as
if <HI>Martyn</HI> and <HI>Harry</HI> had been two <HI>Sophi∣sters,</HI>
set up to wrangle in the Schools, at
their two confronting Desks. After the same
manner, and not without a convenient share
of Impudence, has <HI>Milton</HI> treated King
<HI>CHARLES</HI> the First; but he had cast off
the Yoke of Dominion before he answer'd, and
of a Subject was become a Rebel. To speak
evil of Dignities, is not much recommended
to us in the Holy Scriptures: and whether
he be <HI>Catholic</HI> or <HI>Protestant, (Tros Rutu∣lusve
fuat—)</HI> who manages a Dispute in
this manner, neither Church ought to be over∣proud
of such a Champion. Now whether
our Answerer has follow'd the Example of
<HI>Peronne,</HI> or whether he has not some little
<PB REF="4"/>
tincture of <HI>Luther</HI>'s Mannerliness, and the
Civility of <HI>Milton,</HI> let the impartial Rea∣ders
of his Pamphlet, nay, let even all mo∣dest
and dutiful Protestants be Iudges. I
name not here the Passages, which are
either disrespectful in relation to the Late
King, or to the Present, nor the Pedan∣tique
Cavils, nor the private Scoffs, which
have render'd our Author justly odious to the
sober Men even of his own Party: But if he
will look upon this as a bare Accusation, with∣out
Proof, I shall endeavour to make it good
upon his Summons. In the mean time, tho',
as he alledges, it be no Reflection on the Au∣thority
of a Prince, for a private Subject to
examine a Piece of Coin as to its just Value,
notwithstanding that it bears his Image and
Superscription on it; yet the Answerer ought
to be cautious of decrying that Coin among
his Fellow-Subjects, unless he can fully prove
it to be Counterfeit: But he might have made
a more proper, and less invidious Similitude,
by comparing the King's Paper to a Medal,
rather than to Coin'd Money; It bears the
Figure of one Monarch, and is Distributed
to the People by another: 'Tis a Largess, not
impos'd on any Man; it may either be taken,
<PB REF="4"/>
or refus'd. But both those Actions ought to
be accompanied with Respect; the Metal and
the Weight may be examin'd, without phil∣lipping
it up into the Air: for the Image, the
Superscription, and the Donor, ought all to
secure it from Contempt.</P>
<P>To conclude, If the Answerer thinks it not
unbecoming his Duty to God and the King, to
give a clearer Light to the Things contain'd
in those Papers, I know it not to be unbecom∣ing
mine, to defend the Honour of both our
Princes, and the Truth of that Religion pro∣fess'd
by them, which has descended without
interruption from our Blessed Saviour and
his Apostles, even to us. In so doing, I hope
I shall discover the foul Dealing of this Au∣thor,
who has obscur'd, as much as he is able,
the Native Lustre of those Papers, and re∣commended
by a false Light his own sophi∣sticated
Ware; part of which may certainly
deserve the clearest Light which can be gi∣ven
it by the Hands of the Vnder-Sheriff, or
of somebody whom I will not name.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="defense">
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB N="1" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>A
DEFENCE
OF THE
PAPERS
Written by
The late KING of Blessed
Memory, and Duchess of York,
AGAINST
The Answer made to Them.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">A Defence of the First Paper.</HEAD>
<P>AS I think the Answerer may, with as
little need of Apology, become the
Antagonist, as I the Champion of a
King and Princess, and that the cowar∣dise
of delaying Time, suits ill with
the Presumption of entring into such a Quarrel; I
<PB N="2" REF="6"/>
shall lose none in scanning the Preliminary Discour∣ses
of my Adversary, or making any for my self.</P>
<P>His Majesty says in his first Lines, That <HI>it is as
visible, as that the Scripture is in Print, that none can
be the One Church which Christ has here on Earth, but
that which is called the Roman Catholic Church;</HI> and
that there is no need to <HI>enter into the Ocean of Par∣ticular
Disputes, when the main, and in truth only
Question is, Where that Church is.</HI></P>
<P>The Answerer, who had a mind to flourish, before
he offered to pass, says first: That <HI>if particular Con∣troversies
could be ended, by a Principle as visible as
that the Scripture is in Print, all Men of sence would
soon give over Disputing.</HI> And what if they did?
The sooner, the better, I should think. For Chri∣stians,
sure, might without any harm become unani∣mous
in their Sentiments, all of one Heart, and one
Soul again, and lay Disputing aside: As truly I
believe they would, if the Apostle could prevail
with them, to lay aside all Anger, and Malice, and
Indignation. For Disputes, alas! continue, not
because Truth is not visible, but because Men will
not submit their Sence to Grace, but strain it, in stead
of ending Disputes, to keep them up, and render
invisible the most visible things in the World.</P>
<P>In our present Case, if His Majesty, in stead of
<HI>as visible,</HI> had said, the Church is <HI>more visible</HI> than
Scripture, He would have had a very great Man to
take His part. For which do's the Answerer think
is the more visible of the two, the thing <HI>which is
seen,</HI> or that <HI>by which it is seen?</HI> And he knows
who said,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Authoritas. Aug. Cont. Epist. Fund. c. <HI>v.</HI></NOTE> <HI>I would not believe the Gospel, unless the
Authority of the Catholic Church had moved me.</HI>
<PB N="3" REF="6"/>
And this is, in truth, the Case of every Body. But
evidently S. <HI>Augustin</HI>'s Eyes, as good as they were,
did not see the Scripture, but by the Catholic, that
is, the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic Church. For that, the An∣swerer
knows, was the Catholic Church with which
he communicated.</P>
<P>Then he gives a Reason why Disputing would
cease, <HI>viz.</HI> Because <HI>none who dare believe what they
see, can call</HI> Scriptures being in Print <HI>in question;</HI>
which by making nothing visible, which can be cal∣led
in question, makes it not visible that Scripture is
in Print. For he knows the far greatest part of
Mankind, all Infidels and Mahumetans, do actually
call Scripture in question at this day; he knows ma∣ny
Christians have questioned divers Parts of it
heretofore; and He himself still questions some, as
visibly in Print as any of the rest. But to question
whether the Book in Print be Scripture, is manifest∣ly
to question whether Scripture be in Print. And
so in one breath he says <HI>it is,</HI> in the next <HI>it is not
visible</HI> that Scripture is in Print. But we will not
fall out about Matters which import not.</P>
<P><HI>But,</HI> goes he on, <HI>what if the Church, whose Au∣thority
it is said they must submit to, will not allow
them to believe what they see?</HI> Why then that
Church, if he take Believing <HI>strictly,</HI> agrees with
all Mankind. For as every body knows that Faith
is <HI>of things not seen,</HI> none can allow we properly
believe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> we see.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> </NOTE> But if he take the Word <HI>large∣ly,</HI>
I know of no Church which allows not People
to believe all they see. I do indeed know of one,
which would be glad People would not believe they
see, what they see not, nor by thier Senses can see.
An Eye may see the Colour of a thing, and an Ear
<PB N="4" REF="7"/>
hear the Sound it makes, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> but what this colour∣ed,
or sounding thing is, often needs more than the
Senses to discover. For the <HI>What</HI> of a thing is not
the Object of any Sense.</P>
<P><HI>How then,</HI> says he, <HI>can this be a sufficient Reason to
persuade them to believe the Church, because it is as visi∣ble
as that the Scripture is in Print?</HI> I am sorry,
that to know our Duty, is not with him sufficient
reason to do it. We all know by the Evangelist,
that <HI>Christ</HI> left Commission <HI>to teach all Nations;</HI>
and by the Apostle, that there are <HI>Pastors and Do∣ctors
appointed to build us up into the Vnity of Faith,
and prevent our being Circumvented by Errour.</HI> And
whatever he do's, I take it to be my Duty to learn
of those, who are appointed, and have Commission
from <HI>Christ</HI> to teach, when 'tis visible who they
are.</P>
<P>His following conceit of using and renouncing
our Senses, and indeed, all hitherto said, might have
very well been spar'd: For there is nothing yet which
relates to our Business. If he thinks Kings and their
Writings are not above Sporting, the Matter I am
sure is.</P>
<P>The substance of what he says, when he thinks to
pass in earnest, is, 1. That <HI>a Part is not the Whole,</HI>
and the <HI>Roman</HI> he takes to be only a part of the Ca∣tholic
Church. 2. That <HI>Roman Catholic</HI> is an Ex∣pression
found, neither in <HI>the Creeds, nor Office of
Baptism</HI> even at present. 3. That the <HI>Roman do's
not her self believe she is the Catholic Church of the
Creeds,</HI> because she admits the validity of Baptism
administred out of her Communion. And lastly,
That there <HI>may be different Communions of Christi∣ans,
which may still continue parts of the Catholic;
<PB N="5" REF="7"/>
Church;</HI> for instance, the Holy Bishops and Mar∣tyrs,
who, he says, were Excommunicated hereto∣fore
in <HI>Asia</HI> and <HI>Afric,</HI> and the Eastern Christians at
this Day.</P>
<P>For his first Riddle of a <HI>Part,</HI> and <HI>Whole,</HI> we may
thank his Inadvertence. The Paper do's not say,
that the <HI>Roman</HI> is the <HI>Catholic Church;</HI> but that the
<HI>Roman Catholic is the one Church of Christ.</HI> As <HI>Ro∣man</HI>
alone may signify the Diocess under the imme∣diate
Government of the Bishop of <HI>Rome,</HI> which ne∣ver
did, nor can more pretend to be the Catholic
Church, than the Church of <HI>Laodicea,</HI> or <HI>Ephesus,</HI>
or any other particular Church; the Paper by joyn∣ing
Catholic to it, shews it speaks of her, and all
joyn'd in Communion with her, and all who be∣lieve
as her Communion believes, whether they be
joyn'd in External Communion or no. For it is ap∣parent,
by his Majesties talking all along of matters
of Faith, and no where of any thing else; that he
minded nothing but Faith, and considered the
Church with respect only to Faith. Now I beseech
him, is this <HI>Roman Catholic,</HI> ever the less visibly the
one Church of <HI>Christ,</HI> because a Part is not a
Whole? Of what will he make that Whole, but of
all the Parts? And do's not <HI>Catholic</HI> signify all the
Parts? Or is it the less Catholic; is any part taken out,
because the particular <HI>Roman</HI> is put in? By the way,
because He often mentions the <HI>Roman Church,</HI> with∣out
adding <HI>Catholic,</HI> let me here, to avoid Repetiti∣ons,
declare once for all, That I shall understand
him of the <HI>Roman Catholic,</HI> wherever the Circum∣stances
of the place determine not the Sense to the
particular Church of <HI>Rome.</HI> For he means not I
suppose, to talk of one Church, while His Majesty
talks of another.</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="8"/>
Upon the Second Head, he asks, <HI>If those who
made the Creeds for our direction, had intended the
Roman Catholic Church, why was it not so expressed?</HI>
He might have answered himself. For he knows,
as well as I, that the Reason was, because Language
always changes with Times. As there were no such
Dreams of the <HI>Roman</HI> Church, when the Creeds
were made, as now, it had been a very superfluous,
and a very unaccountable piece of Care, to have
said <HI>Roman</HI> in a Word by it self, which was already
said by the Word <HI>Catholic,</HI> and so by all the World
understood. Now there are who will have her,
some a corrupt Part of the Catholic Church, some
none at all; who have a mind to let People know,
they take her for a Part, and a sound, and the prin∣cipal
Part, and yet would save Words, have light on
a thrifty way of saying all in short, by <HI>Roman-Ca∣tholic.</HI></P>
<P>He says besides, That this <HI>Limitation,</HI> as he calls
it, <HI>of the Sense of Christ's Catholic Church to the
Roman, was never put to Persons to be Baptiz'd, in
any Age of the Church.</HI> And, That <HI>he finds not in the
Office of Baptism, that it is required that they believe
the Roman Catholic Church.</HI> As if the <HI>Roman</HI> Bap∣tism▪
by requiring belief of the Catholic, did not
require belief of the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic Church. If
he think in earnest that it do's not, let him present
a Man to this Baptism, who professes not to believe
the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic Church, and try whether his
professing to believe the Catholic Church will ob∣tain
it. He reflects not that the Limitation, which
is in this Expression, <HI>Roman Catholic Church,</HI> comes
not from <HI>Roman,</HI> but from <HI>Church.</HI> That Word in∣deed
always limits the Expression to those who be∣lieve,
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
and sometimes to those who practise the Do∣ctrine
of Christ. <HI>Roman</HI> neither makes nor marrs,
as to Limitation, but owns the <HI>Romans</HI> for such
Christians. Taking in those, whom Injustice would
keep out, is, it seems, Limitation in his Language.</P>
<P>As it griev'd him in likelihood, that this Expressi∣on,
<HI>as visible as that the Scripture is in Print,</HI> should
be applied to the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic Church, he had a
mind to retort it upon her; but very unluckily chu∣ses
to do it, in an Assertion contrary to the sense of
all the World, besides himself; and by an Argument
contrary to the sense of the whole Church, not ex∣cepting
his own. He says then, in his third Head,
That <HI>it is to him</HI> equally <HI>visible, that the Church of</HI>
Rome <HI>it self do's not believe that it is the one Ca∣tholic
Church mentioned in the two Creeds;</HI> and this
every body, but he, plainly sees it do's: And proves
it by this Argument, Because, if it did, <HI>it must void
all Baptism out of its Communion, which it hath ne∣ver
yet done;</HI> when 'tis plain, that all the Church
agrees, it ought not to be voided. This he very
well knows is a Plea over-ruled by the whole Church
many Ages ago, and which I little expected he
would have borrow'd from Men, who, he says, were
excommunicated, because they made, and stood to
it; especially wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> he, I think condemns it him∣self.
For he excludes the <HI>Donatists,</HI> I suppose, and
<HI>Novatians</HI> from the Catholic Church, because they
re-baptized. When he bethinks himself, he will
not sure have the Church heretofore not believe her
self the Catholic Church, because she would not
void Baptism with the Re-baptizers; nor exclude the
<HI>English</HI> from the Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> holic Church, because she voids
it not. The truth is to say in one breath, That the
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
<HI>Donatists</HI> were not Catholics, because they Re-bap∣tized;
and in the next, That <HI>Roman</HI> Catholics can∣not
believe themselves Catholics, because they do
not, is a cross piece of Business, and much too hard
for me. As far as I can understand, the very Reason
he gives why they should not, is one Reason why
they should believe themselves the Catholic Church.
For, in not voiding the Baptism of Heretics, they
do as the Primitive Catholic Church did. And had I
made such an Argument for a Friend, I am afraid he
would have thought I plaid booty.</P>
<P><HI>The Answerer nevertheless strives to make it good
by this Discourse:</HI> As long as Baptism doth enter
Persons into the Catholic Church, it is impossible that
all who have the true Form of Baptism, though out of
the Communion of the <HI>Roman</HI> Church, should be Mem∣bers
of the Catholic Church, and yet the Communion
of the <HI>Roman</HI> and <HI>Catholic</HI> be all one; as it must be,
if the <HI>Roman</HI> Church be the Catholic and Apostolic
Church professed in the Creeds. <HI>This, if I under∣stand
it, is in short; Persons Baptized out of the</HI> Ro∣man
<HI>Communion, are Members of the Catholic, but
not of the</HI> Roman <HI>Catholic Church; and therefore
the Catholic, and</HI> Roman <HI>Catholic, are not the same
Churches.</HI></P>
<P>He was not, I perceive, aware, that he supposes
what he should prove, and when he has done,
proves it by means of that Supposition: For he could
not make a Member of the Catholic, not to be a
Member of the <HI>Roman Catholic,</HI> unless he suppose
that those are two different Churches. And this is
the very Point in Dispute, which he should prove,
and which he puts for proved in his Conclusion.
But we are all subject to oversights.</P>
<P><PB N="9" REF="9"/>
I wonder more how it could scape him, that the
Baptized Persons he speaks of, are as much Mem∣bers
of both Churches, as of either. (I speak in his
Language, as if they were different Churches, that
his Argument may go on.) Those Persons are not
truly Members either of the Catholic, or <HI>Roman</HI> Ca∣tholic
Church; but as far as Baptism makes Mem∣bers,
they are altogether as much Members of the
<HI>Roman</HI> Catholic, as of the Catholic. And He, if
he will recollect himself, knows very well, that both
Points have been long since determin'd, and that by
the whole Catholic Church.</P>
<P>The old Contest, about Rebaptisation, puts it past
Dispute, that they were not truly Members of any
Part of the Catholic Church. For the Contest was,
How they should be made Members? Whether by
a new Baptism, or only by Imposition of Hands?
Both Sides therefore, that is▪ the whole Church,
agreed, That they were not Members of the Church,
till, one way or other, they were receiv'd into it.
And to think they did not agree in this, is to make
very wise Men of them; Men who fell out with
one another, even to Excommunication, if we will
believe the Answerer, how those should be brought
into the Church, who were in already. Again, That
they were nevertheless as much Members of the Ca∣tholic
Church, tho' baptised out of its Communi∣on,
and so of the <HI>Roman,</HI> tho' baptised out of the
<HI>Roman</HI> Communion, as Baptism could make them,
he knows too was carried against the Re-baptisers by
the rest of the Church, in whose Judgment the
whole Church ever since has acquiesced. And he
stands single against that Judgment, when he thinks
a Man baptised out of the <HI>Roman</HI> Communion, is not
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
a Member of the <HI>Roman</HI> Communion, as much as
Baptism makes a Member, and as much as if he were
baptised in her Communion.</P>
<P>In truth, there is nothing to dispute of, but Words.
When he says, that Baptism <HI>enters</HI> the Baptised into
the Catholic Church, if he mean, that those who are
duly baptised by Men who are out of the Commu∣nion
of the Catholic Church, need no other Bap∣tism
to be brought into the Catholic Church, he says
very true, and no more than what the whole Church
has long since said before him. Neither do they need
any other Baptism to be brought into the <HI>Roman.</HI>
And if he will have this called an <HI>entry,</HI> and the
Baptised called <HI>Members,</HI> with all my heart. For I
think it time lost, to quarrel about the Names of
things, when we know what they signifie. But if
he mean, that their Baptism so enters them, that
they need nothing more, to be what every body un∣derstands
by Members, Men who believe and pro∣fess
the Faith of the Catholic Church, he contra∣dicts
every Member of the Catholic Church, and
every Man in the World. For all Men see they do
not profess that Faith, but the Heresies of their Bap∣tisers;
and all Christians know they need, notwith∣standing
their Baptism, to be receiv'd into the
Church; and that there goes Faith, as well as Bap∣tism,
to a Member of the Body of Faithful. And
as Faith signifies an Assent to the Doctrine of Christ,
the Answerer, sure, will not say, that they have
Faith, who, far from assenting, contradict the Do∣ctrine
of Christ; and so make the Church a Con∣gregation,
no longer of <HI>Faithful,</HI> but of <HI>Faithful</HI>
and <HI>not Faithful.</HI></P>
<P><HI>There is more ado about the last Head, and no∣thing
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
all the while to the Question. The substance
is, That some have been cast out of Communion</HI>
upon particular Differences, which were not supposed
to be of such a nature, as to make them no Members
of the Catholic Church: <HI>That therefore</HI> there may
be different Communions among Christians, which may
still continue Parts of the Catholic Church: <HI>And that</HI>
consequently no one Member of such a Division ought
to assume to it self the Title and Authority of the One
Catholic Church. <HI>And what is all this, even suppo∣sing
it all true, to the Question of the Paper,</HI> Whe∣ther
the Roman Catholic be the One Catholic Church
of the Creeds?</P>
<P>Suppose his divided Christians do continue Parts
still of the Catholic Whole; cannot the <HI>Roman</HI> Ca∣tholic
therefore be that Whole? Suppose no one
Member of the Division ought to assume to it self
the Title and Authority of the One Catholic Church;
ought not therefore both, and all the Members to
assume it? What is, or can there be, to assume it be∣sides?
Or would he not have it assumed at all, but
the Name of Catholic Church banish'd out of the
World by every such Division which happens in it?</P>
<P>His Majesty, as I observ'd before, included in the
<HI>Roman</HI> Catholic Church, of which He speaks, all
Christians whom a different Faith excluded not, and
said that this Church, or these All, are the One Ca∣tholic
Church of the Creeds. The Answerer, to
shew they are not, tells us, That among these All,
there may be Divisions, notwithstanding which, they
may remain Parts still of the Catholic Church.
Why, if they remain Parts of the Catholic Church,
they are of the number of the All, who make it up,
and remain Parts of His Majesty's <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
Church, which takes All in. Is that Church ever
the less <HI>Catholic,</HI> by having never so many Mem∣bers?
Or ever the less <HI>One,</HI> because divided Christi∣ans
believe as she do's? For if they do not, She and
They both cannot be Members of one Catholic
Church, and the Answerer must needs exclude ei∣ther
Her or Them.</P>
<P>For it being as palpable Nonsence, that one Church
can be with more than one Faith, as that one Man
can be with more than one Soul; the Churches,
which make up the Catholic Apostolic One Church,
can have but one Faith among them All: And who
knows the Faith of any one, knows the Faith of all
the rest. Now since the Answerer, with his Com∣pliment
of <HI>Corrupt</HI> Faith, (which, as Compliments
often are, is Nonsence too) makes the <HI>Roman</HI> Ca∣tholic
a Part, at least, of the one Catholic Whole,
all the other Parts must believe as she do's, or cannot
themselves be Parts. And so his Reason, why All
those who believe as she do's are not the Catholic
Church, is because All believe as she do's, notwith∣standing
some Divisions.</P>
<P>As it is not to our purpose, I inquire not whether
his divided Christians do indeed, by continuing the
same Faith, properly continue parts of the Catholic
Church; a Question which belongs to the propriety
of Language; nor how far so much Title to the
Church avails to their Salvation. Since Divisions,
especially of long continuance, seem hardly con∣sistent
with Charity, and Charity is as necessary to
Salvation as Faith, I pray God of his Mercy to pre∣serve
me from ever being divided, whether I be said
to belong still to the Church or no, and make them
sensible of their condition who are. Neither will I
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
examine how 'tis with the Eastern Christians at this
Day, or was with those of <HI>Afric</HI> and <HI>Asia,</HI> whom he
makes Excommunicated heretofore by the Bishops
of <HI>Rome;</HI> a Point of which if he have a mind to Dis∣pute,
he may chuse his Man among those who de∣ny
it. Whether the <HI>Roman Catholic,</HI> comprehend∣ing
all of the same Faith with her, be the one Ca∣tholic
Apostolic Church of the Creeds, is our Que∣stion;
not who they are, who have the same Faith.
And that this <HI>Roman Catholic</HI> Church is the One
Church which <HI>Christ</HI> has on Earth, or that he
has none on Earth, is as visible as that Scripture is
in Print, or any thing more visible, if any thing can
be. For if it be not, we must look for <HI>Christ</HI>'s
Church, either among Infidels, who believe not in
<HI>Christ</HI> at all, or Heretics, who believe not his Do∣ctrine.
And there, I for my part despair to find it.</P>
<P>The truth is, I suspect by his talking, that he
would be content People should think, that the one
Catholic Church of the Creeds, requir'd not any
one Faith, but were made up of as many Men as
own <HI>Christ,</HI> whatever they believe of his Doctrine:
Except, perhaps, those who Rebaptise, and those
who assume the Title of the Catholic Church. By
which means the notion of <HI>Catholic</HI> would be well
enough provided for, but <HI>One</HI> and <HI>Church</HI> left to
shift for themselves. But he do's not directly say it,
and 'tis not fair to put my suspitions to his account.</P>
<P>Divers other Passages there are in his Discourse
which relish not with me. He by saying the Visible
Church might have been easily shewn in the first
Blessed Times, insinuates, she is less visible now, or
rather invisible; for visible things may be easily seen
at all times: And I conceive the same marks, which
<PB N="14" REF="12"/>
shew'd her then, will with as little difficulty shew
her now. Christians were then admonish'd to mind
those <HI>who abide in the Doctrine of</HI> Christ; who <HI>come
and bring not that Doctrine;</HI> and to <HI>contend for the
Faith once delivered to the Saints.</HI> And we have
but to do so still.</P>
<P>Again, I comprehend not how his unheeded, and
yet remarkable difference between People cast out of
Communion, <HI>viz.</HI> That <HI>some did, and some did not
challenge the Title of the Catholic Church,</HI> was the
cause of any great misapplication. It sounds as if he
would have that Title never rightly apply'd, but to
those who do not challenge it, in likelihood because
they have no pretence to it. But I less understand
how it comes to be <HI>Presumption</HI> and a <HI>cause of
Schisms</HI> in one part of a Division to assume it. It is
not well intelligible, when there is a Division, how
more than one part can bear it. For the Language
of the World has always preserv'd that Title to one
Part, and given the name of Sect, or part cut off,
to the other. And it is more unintelligible, how it
should be Presumption in that one Part, to take
what all the World gives, and that Presumption be
the cause of Schisms, which happen'd, and of ne∣cessity
always must happen before the Presumption.
For till there be Schism, that is, <HI>Division,</HI> there can∣not
be <HI>Part of a Division</HI> to presume.</P>
<P>His account too of the breach betwixt the <HI>East</HI>
and the <HI>West,</HI> is, I think, very wide of the mark.
He would have the Popes Supremacy bear the blame
of all, which, if my Memory fail me not, was not
so much as made a Pretence, till near Two hundred
Years after the Schism began, nor any where more
acknowledged than in <HI>Greece,</HI> nor by any body
<PB N="15" REF="12"/>
more, than by him who began the Schism. When I
read the Story, I apprehended the cause of that breach
was National Feuds, heightned into violent hatred, by
several Accidents which chopt unluckily in, and the
malitious Ambition of Men, who found their pri∣vate
Accounts in the Public Calamity. Indeed I
think they denied the Popes Supremacy at last, as
all, who will continue in Schism, at long run must;
because to acknowledge and not regard it, is self
condemnation: Otherwise their Quarrel was to the
Latin Church, or perhaps more truly, Nation, not
the Supremacy, of which they speak so inconstantly,
that I am persuaded it would break no squares even
now, if they could be brought on any terms to a∣gree
with Men whom they hate. I would be more
diligent in this Matter, if it concern'd our Question.
But as they are parts of His Majesties <HI>Roman</HI> Ca∣tholic
Church, if they believe as she do's, and are
not if they do not, and it is equal whether they do
or no, I leave them to Gods Mercy, and return from
straying thus far, into our Road again.</P>
<P><HI>This Principle being remov'd (which ought,</HI> he says,
<HI>be taken for granted, since it can never be prov'd)</HI>
By the way, he do's not, sure, mean this for a bob
to the King, as if he took his Principle, <HI>viz.</HI> That
<HI>the Church is as visible as Scripture,</HI> for granted,
because he knew not how to prove it. Whether the
Person to whom he directed his Paper were satisfy'd
before hand of this Point by their former Discourses,
or needed no Arguments to see a visible thing, or
however it were, the Answerer may perceive by the
Paper, that his Majesty thought it not to his purpose
to press the Visibility of the Church, but only sub∣mission
to it; and means not, I suppose, to tell the
<PB N="16" REF="13"/>
King, he knew not his own Design, or how to pur∣sue
it. His part is to answer what <HI>is</HI> said, and not
instruct the King what <HI>should</HI> have been said. He
must therefore mean, that it ought to be taken for
granted, that he has remov'd that Principle, which
is just, <HI>Lend me your Hand, Neighbour, to remove
my Block; I cannot stir it my self.</HI> Alas! it is very
visible he has done nothing towards removing it.
But he is in the right to play sure. Who have a flaw
in their Title, do well to get a Grant. By his say∣ing
<HI>it can never be prov'd,</HI> he has, I guess, a mind
to tempt somebody to prove over again, what has
been prov'd a hundred and a hundred times already.
But as much as his positiveness tempts me to be do∣ing,
and as easie as I think it to be done, I beg his
Pardon at present: Parrying is my business, not
Thrusting now.</P>
<P>Whatever he mean, I do not think that what he
concludes would follow, even tho' the Principle
which he dislikes were removed. The Principle is,
<HI>That the Roman Catholic is the One Church which
Christ has here upon Earth;</HI> and the Conclusion is,
<HI>That we must unavoidably enter into the Ocean of par∣ticular
Disputes.</HI> Why so, I pray him? Why will
not another Catholic Church serve turn? If he will
needs have it granted, that the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic is
not the One Church of Christ, 'tis but shewing us
the other Catholic which is. <HI>Roman,</HI> or <HI>not Roman,</HI>
imports not. But believing the Doctrine of Christ,
imports as much as Salvation is worth; and the
Commission which Christ gave to teach it the World,
is now in force, and shall be as long as there is a
World. Let him but direct us to the Men who
have it in this Age, that we who live in this Age
<PB N="17" REF="13"/>
may learn it of them; let him but tell us which is
the One, not <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic Church, which Christ
has here upon Earth; and it will do our business
every jot as well as the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic, and as
much save us from being plunged into the Ocean of
particular Disputes. Otherwise, to tell us, the <HI>Ro∣man</HI>
Catholic is not that Church, and not tell us
which is, is as much as to tell us, that Christ has
none upon Earth. For evidently, She, or some
other, must be that Church, if there be any at all.
But let him not send us to a Church, whereof the
several Parts agree not in one Faith. Besides that
we should never understand how such a Church, let
it be never so Universal, could be One, and make
account Christ taught One determinate Doctrine,
not the 1, and the <HI>No,</HI> both; it would be otherwise
useless. For if <HI>This</HI> Part teach one Faith, and the
<HI>Next</HI> another, we should not know which to be∣lieve,
and in all likelihood believe neither.</P>
<P>But <HI>he knows no Reason any can have to be so
afraid</HI> of the Ocean of particular Disputes, <HI>since we
have so sure a Compass as the Holy Scripture to di∣rect
our Passage.</HI> I am sure there can be no Reason
to venture to Sea, when we are already safe in our
Port; The Holy Scripture assures us, that the
Church is <HI>the Foundation and Pillar of Truth,</HI> and
Truth is plainly the Port to which his Compass
should direct us. But pray what Compass can be
sure, where the Needle is not suffer'd freely to play?
Wrangling is Iron to this Needle, and turns it to all
Points. It will indeed direct the humble, and do∣cile,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Per. 1. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 0</NOTE>
and the sincere, who <HI>first know, that no Pro∣phecy
of Scripture is of private interpretation,</HI> and
we see it will, by the Third Paper. But it is not
<PB N="18" REF="14"/>
for the bold and self-conceited Disputers.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 11. 16.</NOTE> <HI>If any
will be contentious, we have no such custom, nor the
Church of God,</HI> is what the Scripture it self says to
them. <HI>To contend with them at
Scripture,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Quoniam nihil proficiat congressio Scripturarum, nisi plane ut aut sto∣machi quis in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> at eversionem aut ce∣rebri—Non ad Scripturas provo∣candum est: nec in his constituen∣dum certamen, in quibus aut nulla aut incerta victoria est, aut parum <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> erta. Tertull. de Praescrip. c.</HI> 17, 19.</NOTE> <HI>Tertullian</HI> tells, us, <HI>is
good for nothing, but to turn the
Brain or the Stomach; and that we
ought not to try it this way,</HI> be∣cause
<HI>the Issue will be uncertain, or
but little certain, or none.</HI> Alas!
this Gentleman, with the security he promises, <HI>errs</HI>
all this while, <HI>not knowing the Scriptures,</HI> nor so
much as the End for which they were made. He
would do well to remember what St. <HI>Austin</HI> says to
him in Words directed to another.
<HI>If you will not have me believe Ca∣tholics,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Si dixeris, noli Catholicis credere, non recte facies per Evangelium me cogere ad Manichaei sidem, quia ipsi Evangelio Catholicis praedicantibus credidi. Quod si forte in Evangelio aliquid apertissimum de Manichaei Apostolatu invenire poteris, infir∣mabis mihi Catholicorum authori∣tatem, qui jubent ut tibi non cre∣dam. Qua infirmata, jam nec E∣vangelio credere potero, quia per eos illi credideram, ita nihil apud me valebit, qui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> quid inde protule∣ris. Si inde aliquid manifestum pro Man<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> chaeo legeris, nec illis (cre∣dam) nec tibi, <HI>Aug. cont. Ep.</HI> Fund. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 5.</NOTE>
<HI>you are quite out, to think to
draw me to you by Scripture, be∣cause
it was for their sakes that I
believed Scripture. You would in∣deed,
if you could evidently prove
your Doctrine by Scripture, invali∣date
the Authority of Catholics, who
bid me not believe you. And when
you have done, neither shall I be∣lieve
the Scripture, which I had be∣lieved
upon their Credit; and so
what you alledge out of it, will be
of no force with me. If you find it manifest for you,
I shall neither believe Catholics nor you.</HI> Here I
will stop: For truly after so much said of this Sub∣ject,
and so long Experience of his sure Compass, I
grieve too much to dispute it farther, when I observe
that neither Reason nor Experience will do; and
<PB N="19" REF="14"/>
fear there are who more desire the Ocean of Con∣troversies
should never be past, than truly think it
will be past this way.</P>
<P>But he is merry, whatever I be. For sure he is
in jest, when he talks of clear Evidence of Scrip∣ture
against us, and the Church of <HI>Romes</HI> notori∣ously
deviating from it. Under the Face he sets on
this Matter, there is nothing in the World, but that
he has the Art to make the Words of Scripture bear
a Sense of his own, or Friends invention; no great
matter to brag on, Alas! no not so much as for
Learning.<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Pet. 3. 16</NOTE> For even the Unlearned, he knows, have
Wit enough to pervert the Scriptures to their own
Perdition. And because the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> has
no mind his Word should be past upon her for God's
Word, he runs away with it, with a sure Compass,
and clear Evidence, and the infallible Rule; Words,
which, as big as they sound, signifie nothing but the
Whimsies of possibly a single, possibly an unlearned
Man; but yet who will needs be wiser than the
Church.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Si unaquae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> c disciplina, quamquam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> lis &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> percipi possit, doctorem aut magi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> trum re∣quirit: quid temerariae su∣perb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ae pleni∣us, quam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>∣norum Sacra∣mentorum libros, &amp; ab Interpretibus suis nolle cognoscere, &amp; incognitos ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> e damnare <HI>Aug. de Util. Cred. c. 17. tom.</HI> 6.</NOTE> To take upon us to understand the mean∣ing
of the Books of Divine Mysteries, otherwise
than by learning it of their Interpreters, when no
Trade, the most trivial and easie, is learnt without
a Master, and condemn what we understand not, as
we do when we will not embrace that Meaning, is,
not to mince his Words, <HI>rash Pride,</HI> in the Opinion
of S. <HI>Austin.</HI></P>
<P>But to go on, the Answerer knows very well,
that the meaning of his Majesties next Paragraph,
is not what his Question would put upon it, and yet
<PB N="20" REF="15"/>
he must needs suppose it has another, as if he did
him Grace. His Majesty asks no Grace of him, but
to put the Period entire; <HI>It is not left to every
Phantastical Mans Head to believe as he pleases, but
to the Church, to whom Christ left the Power on
Earth,</HI> (where I think the Compositor has left out a
Comma) <HI>to govern us in matters of Faith, who
made the Creeds for our direction;</HI> and then to un∣derstand
English. But he will needs suppose the
meaning is, that those who reject <HI>the Authority of
the</HI> Roman <HI>Catholic Church, do leave every Man to
believe according to his own Fancy.</HI> Still he takes it
not right. Not but that rejecting that Authority
infers setting up private Fancy. But as inconse∣quent
as it is, there are, who, for all their rejecting
that greater Authority, are severe enough in requi∣ring
punctual obedience to their own little or no
Authority, and this too visibly for his Majesty to
say they do not. His words, I conceive, cannot
fairly be suppos'd to extend farther, than they were
directed, to a single Person in all likelihood, who
had the honour of his Confidence, and whom he
thought fit to put in mind, That <HI>it is not left to
every Phantastical Mans Head to believe as he pleases.</HI>
What has the Answerer to say to this? is it true?
or is it not true?</P>
<P><HI>Certainly,</HI> says he, <HI>those of the Church of</HI> England
<HI>cannot be liable to any Imputation of this Nature.</HI> And
who can tell by this, whether he say I, or no? or
what kind of Answer that should be which says nei∣ther?
or what it serves for, but to do the Church of
<HI>England</HI> the same good Office which they do them∣selves,
who, when Vice is ridicul'd on the Stage, fall
out with the Actors or Poet, and will needs be the
Fools of the Play.</P>
<P><PB N="21" REF="15"/>
But if he will be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , needless Apologies, why
must he needs make one fifty times worse than the
attempt to make it? All Heretics since the first Four
General Councils, may say the very same which he
says for the Church of <HI>England,</HI> and all before them,
the Equivalent. <HI>Arius</HI> himself could say, I receive
the Apostles Creed, and why should more be requir'd
of me, when that has hitherto been thought suffici∣ent
for all Christians? Moreover, I embrace all for∣mer
Councils, but think I have very great reason to
complain, that a Party in the Church, the most
corrupt and obnoxious, assuming the Title of a Ge∣neral
and Free Council, takes upon it self to define
new Doctrine, which has neither universal Traditi∣on
(divers heretofore, and all the Orthodox, that
is, my Abetters, being on my side) and so plainly
no Scripture, that because they could find none
there, they were fain to Coyn a new Word for their
new Faith. <HI>Macedonius, Nestorius,</HI> and <HI>Eutiches</HI>
might have said as much of the Creeds and Councils
before them, and all Heretics since of the Creeds
and Councils alledg'd by the Answerer, and all
complain of the Villanous Factions, call'd General
Councils. He has plainly justify'd them all, if it
be a justification of a Doctrine, that it is not found
condemned in Councils, held before it was broach'd.
For the Doctrine of none of them was condemn'd by
any former Council nor indeed well could. For as
Councils seldom meddle with more than the exi∣gence,
for which they were call'd, requires, it is
not to be expected, that more Faith should be found
in their Creeds or Acts, than was Controverted
when they sat. Wherefore, unless one will fancy
that every part of Christs Doctrine was denied so
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
early, or that no body since can deny some part,
which was not denied then, it is as wild as unseaso∣nable,
to plead in behalf of a Doctrine now, that it
was not condemn'd by the first Four General Coun∣cils,
or Three Creeds, where there was no occasion
to mention it. And yet he thinks this an Apology
fit to be made for the Church of <HI>England.</HI> Truly I
have long thought, and there are of her Members
who know my Thoughts, that she has ill luck, when
she has much better things to say for her self, to have
such things as these said for her: things which fit
the greatest Enemies she has, every jot as well as her
self; and which I therefore wonder not, when I see
alledg'd by them, as Pleas for her. For They have
reason, when They will not be brought to Her,
to bring Her to Them, if they can. But to see them
produc'd by those who will be, even unseasonably
zealous for her, is a Riddle, with which it is not for
me to meddle.</P>
<P>What he adds, <HI>of</HI> holding <HI>nothing contrary to any
universal Tradition of the Church from the Apostles
Times, and</HI> putting <HI>it upon that Issue,</HI> (for <HI>profes∣sing</HI>
and <HI>offering,</HI> as he expresses it, is no great mat∣ter,
unless they do what they profess and offer) is
indeed to purpose, and spoken like a Friend of the
Church of <HI>England,</HI> and a Lover of Peace. And I
hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tily wish, and as earnestly, as I can, pray to Al∣mighty
God, that this Trial may be brought speedi∣ly
on; which I can safely undertake shall neither be
declin'd, nor delay'd by the Church of <HI>Rome.</HI></P>
<P>Then he passes on to her, and says, That <HI>who be∣lieve
her to be the Catholic, believe, as they please,
without any colour of Scripture, Antiquity, or Reason.</HI>
This Ball has been tost already, and in my Opinion
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
enough. Only, lest he, whoever <HI>believe,</HI> be thought
to <HI>speak</HI> as he pleases, he would do well to shew
what Scripture or Reason tells him, that the <HI>Roman</HI>
Church, with the rest of her Belief, (for sure he
talks not of a Diocess) was not always believ'd the
Catholic Church. Antiquity I know he has, as
much as since <HI>Luther.</HI> Any other Colour, from all
these three, I see none. Divers other Points he
brings in, I know not why, unless that he has per∣haps
a mind to be sailing on the Ocean of particular
Disputes. As I have not, I mean to stay on firm
Ground, with S. <HI>Austin,</HI> and content my self, that
<HI>It was thought fit by the Catholic Church spread
throughout the World,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Neque <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> parvi momen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> est, qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> d cum &amp;c. Hoc per universam Ca∣tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> , <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣fundit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> r, ob∣servari placuit, quod tenemus. <HI>August. con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> r. Cre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> on. l. 1. c</HI> 32.</NOTE> <HI>to observe what we hold:</HI>
And that, <HI>Because the things we hold are observ'd by
the Vniversal Church, they are believ'd not other∣wise
deliver'd and recommended, than by the Apostles.</HI>
Who has a mind to put to Sea with the Answerer,
will, I think, find the same Saint's Counsel good:
<HI>When he has been tost enough, and has a mind to be at
ease, to follow the way of Catholic Discipline, which
descended from Christ himself,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Quam consue∣tudinem credo ex <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> traditione venientem, sicut multa quae non inveniuntur in litteris eorum, neque in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> liis posteriorum; &amp; tamen quia per universam custod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> untur Ecclesiam, non <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> tradita, &amp; commendata creduntur. <HI>Aug. de Bap. con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> . Donatist. l. 2. c.</HI> 7. Si jam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> tibi jactatus videris, finemque hujusmodi laboribus vis imponere, sequere viam Catho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> disciplinae, quae ab ipso Christo per Apostolos ad nos usque manavit, &amp; abhin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ad <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> manatura est. <HI>Aug. de Util. Cred. c.</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>by the Apostles, even
to us, and shall to Posterity.</HI></P>
<P>He shall, if he please, excuse me from rambling
after him into the Authority they allow the Church;
which gay word, if it should signify no more, as I
suspect it sometimes do's not, than that it do's oblige
People, whatever they think, to hold their Tongues,
and not to thwart her decisions in public, for fear of
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
losing their Benefices, it were great pity: Lik<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e
into free Councils, and Factions, and what else he
fills a Page with. For whatever he do, I remember
our Question all the while is, whether it be well or
ill said, <HI>That it is not left to every Phantastical Man's
Head to believe as he pleases.</HI> And when he pleases
to speak to it, I am for him.</P>
<P>In the next Section he tells us, That all <HI>they plead
for in this case, is the right which Loyal Subjects have
under an Vsurper, so far to interpret the Laws as to
be able to understand their duty, &amp;c.</HI> I will not ask
him who the Usurpers are, and who the Loyal Sub∣jects?
For he makes account, I find▪ that to receive
Faith from him, who thought it no Usurpation to be
equal to God, and keep it when People have it, and
tell other folks what it is, is Usurpation; and that
who is so bold, as to deny it, stands in danger of be∣ing
hurried into the Ocean of Controversies, with the
Answerers fancy of Scripture, for a sure Compass to
direct him out again. All this while we have other
Business in hand. We have an Assertion, and an
Answer to mind. The Assertion is, That <HI>it were a
very irrational thing to make Laws for a Country, and
leave it to the Inhabitants to be Interpreters and
Iudges of those Laws.</HI> And the Answer is, That <HI>it
is as irrational to allow an Vsurper to Interpret the
Laws to his own advantage.</HI> Is this, I, or No, a∣gain?
or what do's it say? That both are Irratio∣nal?
which is to say, that the Assertion is true: Or
that both are Rational? or one Rational, the other
not? Let him say, if he please, what he would be
at, and leave Usurpers till we have Business with
them.</P>
<P>His Majesty supposes next, that the goodness of
<PB N="25" REF="17"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> would not leave Men uncertain of the way to
Heaven, which they would be, if Scripture were
the Rule, and every Man his own Judge.</P>
<P>He by way of Question says first, That <HI>the Rule is
capable of being understood by those to whom it was
given, in order to the great end of it,</HI> Salvation.
Which is next to saying, that it is not capable of be∣ing
understood, by those to whom it was not given,
that is, by any but the Church, to whom alone it
was given. In which he may be sure I shall not
contradict him. But is it understood with certain∣ty,
by every Man who will be his own Judge? or
are we left to uncertainty? These are our Questions,
to which, how this which he says, should be any step
towards an Answer, I cannot imagine.</P>
<P>Next he tells us, That <HI>the main end of the Rule
was to direct us in the way to Heaven, and not meer∣ly
to determine Controversies.</HI> Here is work enough
for him that needs it. For who shall understand
what other end there is of a Rule to determine Con∣troversies,
but determining Controversies? Hea∣ven
is indeed the end for which it is necessary Con∣troversies
should be determi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 'd; but that is to be the
end of the Determination, not the Rule. How a
Rule made to determine Controversies should have
any end besides determining them, when the end of
a thing is what it was made for; or why directing
to Heaven, and determining Controversies, should
here be separated, where the Determination is the
very direction of a Rule to determine them, they
may Dispute who love Disputing. All shall pass for
me, till I find something which concerns our Que∣stion;
<HI>certain</HI> or <HI>uncertain.</HI></P>
<P>His next words suppose <HI>Scripture</HI> is the Rule, a
<PB N="26" REF="18"/>
little odly me thinks for an Answerer. For when it
is objected against its being a Rule, that we should
be left at uncertainties, it would have shew'd better,
to have taken some notice of the Objection, before
he take for granted, the thing which is in Dispute.
But I shall not stop him. What will he do with his
Rule, now he has suppos'd it?</P>
<P>Why, <HI>It is fit to examine and compare</HI> Controver∣sies
<HI>with this Infallible Rule;</HI> and then we shall de∣termine
them Infallibly, I hope. I expected this
should follow, but was much mistaken. What he
says, is, That <HI>when that is done, to help us in our
way to Heaven, is that which it was chiefly intended
for.</HI> He may, if he please, keep his <HI>Intended</HI> till
some body doubt what was intended in every thing
which God do's for Man, and tell us in the mean
time, what his examining and comparing will <HI>do.</HI>
Whether it will determine Controversies, or no? and
whether certainly, or no? or whether it be no mat∣ter
whether they be determined or no? but we shall
get to Heaven by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> are <HI>examining,</HI> which side soever
of the Controversie examined we chuse, and whe∣ther
any or none. Whatever was <HI>chiefly</HI> intended,
<HI>determining Controversies</HI> sure was intended by a
Rule to determine them, and our comparing them
with that Rule. Pray let him tell us how we shall
succeed, whether hit or miss, in compassing <HI>that</HI> In∣tenti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> n.
'Twill be afterwards time enough to talk
of his other <HI>chief</HI> Intention.</P>
<P>He says further, That <HI>no Man can think it of e∣qual
consequence to him, not to be mistaken, and not
to be damned.</HI> As if mistakes in our case would not
damn a Man. For who can hope to be saved with∣out
pleasing God, and every body knows, that
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
without Faith it is impossible to please him. But
whether do's he mean to lead us? All hitherto seems
quite out of the way to our Question. For what has
the chief end for which a Rule was made, to do
with, whether it will guide us certainly, or no? Hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
refusing to Answer, is, in truth, confessing that
Scripture, after all, is not the Rule of Controversi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> s.
For they are not ended, till one side or other be
certain. But let us go no farther than we needs
must.</P>
<P><HI>In Matters of Good and Evil, every Man's Consci∣ence,</HI>
he says, <HI>is his immediate Iudge; and why not in
Matters of Truth and Falshood? Vnless we suppose
Mens involuntary Mistakes to be more dangerous,
than their wilful Sins.</HI> How! Are we, before we
were aware, come to Conscience at last? and all his
Magnificent Talk, his Evident, his Sure, and his In∣fallible,
his Care in examining and comparing, for
nothing, but to establish this Maxim; <HI>Do every one
what seems good in his own Eyes, and believe what
seems true?</HI> Is this the <HI>clearer light</HI> he will <HI>give to
the things contain'd</HI> in His Majesty's Papers? and
the loss of such a Liberty, the great danger they run
of being <HI>deceiv'd</HI> with their <HI>fair appearance,</HI> whom
he will secure with his safe Instructions of trus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ing
their Conscience, both for Good and for True? Do∣ctrine,
or not Doctrine of Christ, is no such idle
Circumstance sure, that hitting or missing is equal,
so the Conscience be strait, and the Mistake invo∣luntary.
By the way, I see not how this <HI>involun∣tary</HI>
can thrust in here: For, who forces any Body
to mistake? or take the deceitful ways which lead
them to it?</P>
<P>But to say nothing to that matter, and but little
<PB N="28" REF="19"/>
to his Plea of Conscience, as copious as the Theme
is, I only ask, what Conscience can do more than
secure a Man from being judg'd for sinning against
his Conscience? But if it lead him to do ill things,
or embrace a wrong Faith, what can he answer for
the Sin of having that Conscience? Reason certainly
never <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ramed such a Conscience, and there is nothing
besides which could frame it, but Passion, that is
Affections wrong set, or, in plain English, very wil∣ful
Sin. Shall he, who has this to answer for, be
safe, because he has nothing to answer for the Sin
against Conscience? As if that were the only Sin to
be accounted for in the next World.</P>
<P>For the rest, This, to say the truth, is an An∣swer.
For Uncertainty do's not prove that Scrip∣ture
is not the Rule, if it be no matter whether we
be uncertain or no; nor indeed, whether there be a
Rule, or Faith. For if Conscience will carry those
to Heaven who believe wrong, Faith, I think, may
be spared, and a Rule for it. But as it is an Answer
which I believe would not have taken with His late
Majesty, because he had too much Experience of the
bad Eff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cts of mistaken Conscience, to think it
would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at the Tribunal of God, more than it
did at His, I am confident it will take as little with
the Reader. At least I will venture it without more
words.</P>
<P>For I m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> an not to stay at a new Apology of his
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of <HI>England,</HI> as unseasonable as the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> orm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> r, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> something were objected to her, and
as little <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> . At the rate he talks, one woul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> do's, what he undertakes She do's not,
<HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> every Man to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e his own Iudge.</HI> For this he
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>in what concerns his own Salvation,</HI>
<PB N="29" REF="19"/>
that is, in all Faith; for Faith concerns Salvation.
<HI>Who believes not,</HI> every body, who believes Scrip∣ture,
knows, <HI>shall be damned.</HI> Then his Seducers,
with their dangerous Mistakes, as such there are, it
seems, for all his Conscience-security; And his <HI>Spiri∣tual
Guides</HI> with <HI>their assistance,</HI> would make work till
Doomsday. Nor can Quarrels about them be end∣ed,
till those about Faith be settled. For till then,
who shall know which is the Guide, and which the
Seducer? As Christ appointed no body to teach
other Doctrine than he taught, They are plainly
no Guides of his appointing who do. The Ancient
Creeds too are brought in again, as if they would
be serviceable to the Church of <HI>England,</HI> and no
Liberty of Conscience allow'd to judge against
them, or any <HI>Doctrines as universally receiv'd;</HI> as if
any part of universal Christian Doctrine were lost,
and all had not been always as universally retain'd as
the Creeds. But I have my Answer, and will be
going.</P>
<P>In the next Section the King asks, <HI>Whether it be
not the same thing to follow our own Fancy, or to in∣terpret
Scripture by it?</HI> And he answers, <HI>There
might be some colour for such a Question,</HI> if They
did not do so and so. Pray what colour has he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> or
such a Reply? Might not the King have colour to
say what he thought fit to be said, to him to whom
he spoke, whether there be, or be not colour, to
say the same to the Church of <HI>England?</HI> He w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> t
not to her, nor were His Writings publish'd with
any relation to her, but to satisfie the Curiosity of
those who desir'd to see them, and could not come
by written Copies, and to assure them they were
His.</P>
<P><PB N="30" REF="20"/>
In stead of concerning her, where she is not con∣cern'd,
let him, if he please, answer the Question,
and tell us whether it be or be not the same, to fol∣low
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> own Fancy, or interpret Scripture by it.
Till he say <HI>I,</HI> or <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ,</HI> all besides is leaving the Work
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ut out for us, to cut out new of our own, which
twenty to one we shall never make up. For which
Reason. I will pray him to keep his many Questi∣ons,
t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ll the Dispute be between the two Churches,
and I appear for the Church of <HI>Rome.</HI> Till then,
he cannot rationally expect an Answer from me.
He perhaps may be able to manage two Disputes at
a time or think the best way to end one is to begin
another; I think it too much for me to defend a
King and a Church at once. And so, much good
may his pleasant Fancies do him, about <HI>a Rule and
its Interpretation,</HI> which he talks as if he would
have belong to those who do not know the Sense of
it; about the <HI>Intention of Almighty God,</HI> as if we
knew not what he intended, and did make the
Pillar and Ground of Truth; about <HI>reforming Dis∣orders,</HI>
which he makes unreformable, even in Com∣monwealths,
where the Supreme Judge has the ill
luck to be principally accus'd; about <HI>Oaths,</HI> as if
any were taken to defend an unjust Authority, or
could bind, tho' they were; about a <HI>Iudge of Tra∣dition,</HI>
as if a Man who sees Pictures in one Church,
and none in another, needed a Judge to pronounce
to him, that those Churches practise differently. His
<HI>Vsurpers,</HI> and all, shall do what he would have them
for me. I wish, in stead of all this, he would have
minded his Business, but mean however to mind
mine.</P>
<P>What he replies to the next Section, shews more
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
like an Answer, than any thing said yet. <HI>I would
have any Man shew me,</HI> says the King, <HI>where the
Power of deciding Matters of Faith is given to every
particular Man.</HI> He distinguishes, and says, The
Power of Deciding so as to oblige others, is not
given to every particular Man; the Power of Deci∣ding
so as to satisfie the particular Decider, is. De∣nial
is a fair Answer; and this seems to deny what
His Majesty says, and yet in truth says nothing to
it. <HI>Deciding</HI> of particular Men; being <HI>our own
Iudges;</HI> following our <HI>own Fancy,</HI> or <HI>private Spirit;</HI>
believing <HI>as we please,</HI> and the like Expressions,
signifie all the same. And the King, as Men use to
do, who mind Sense more than Words, and have
Language at will, takes now one, now another, as
they come in His way. As it could not scape an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ye
less piercing than His, that he judges every jot as
much who believes upon the Authority of the
Church, as he who believes upon his own Fancy of
Scripture; and that every Assent is a Judgment, and
so the Assent of Faith, as well as the rest: it cannot
be imagin'd that He would have Men not judge at
all. But He meant, as all the World means by those
Phrases, that they should not judge unreasonably.
For as they are blamed, who will be their own
Judges; and no body blames another for doing well▪
and Judging is of it self a good thing, an Exercise
of a Faculty planted in us by God; there is nothing
to be blamed, but the ill use of that Faculty, by suf∣fering
Passion to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it, which should only be gui∣ded
by Reason. That Men <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mean thus by those
Expressions, we see by the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to which they ap∣ply
them. He who being <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , or Con∣ceit
of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="32" REF="21"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the Advice of his unpassionate and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> or he, who has no skill in Physic or
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> will commence and prosecute Suits,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> against the Advice of able Law∣yers
and Doctors, is said to be his own Judge: He
is not, who understanding Jewels, or Pictures, buys
them at his own Rate, tho' never so many, of less
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> than himself, persuade him to the contrary;
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> is said to be his Judge. Now the King
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , because Christ taught his Apostles and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , who, with those that believ'd his Doctrine
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Preaching, and their Successors through
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> , are called the Church, that he could not
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> reasonably, who would pretend to find out
that Doctrine by his own Wit, or Study, or any
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , but by learning it of the Church, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
at first from Christ, and preserv'd it ever
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> . And this unreasonable Judgment, made on
their own Heads or Fancy, against the Judgment of
those whose Profession it is, His several Expressions
strike at. The Answerer reflected not on the mean∣ing
of them, but would persuade us, That to say
particular Men must be satisfied of the Reasons why
they believe, is an Answer to the Question, Whether
there be indeed any Reasons why they should be∣lieve,
besides the Authority of the Church?</P>
<P>To go forward, <HI>Christ,</HI> says his Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> sty, <HI>left his
Power to his Church, even to forgive Sins in Hea∣ven,
and left his Spirit with them, which they exer∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> d
after his Resurruction.</HI> He answers, as if he
were at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> purposes, <HI>where then was the</HI> Roman
<HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> </HI> What has <HI>where was she?</HI> to do
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>left to her?</HI> 'Tis a strange Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> stion
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , and he, I believe, the first, who ever ask'd,
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
where a Church was, before she was. The <HI>Roman</HI>
was a part of the Catholic, as soon as she was a
Church; till then she was where all the Churches <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
the World besides were, except that of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ierusalem,</HI>
and where the Church of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ierusalem</HI> too was, be∣fore
<HI>Christ</HI> was born, in the order of Providen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
But <HI>how can it be hence inferr'd, that these Power<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
are now in the Church of</HI> Rome <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Roman</HI> Cath<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>
Church, I suppose, he means▪ <HI>exclusive to all others,
unless it be made appear that it was Heir-General to
all the Apostles?</HI> As if there needed Logic to infer▪
that Powers left for the Salvation of Mankind, re∣main
in being as long as there remains a Man<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>
to be saved; or Powers left to the Church of <HI>Christ,</HI>
are in the Church of <HI>Christ;</HI> and those excl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ded
from the Powers, who are not incl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ded <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> n the
Church; or to make appear She is Heir-General
to all the Apostles, who as visibly as that the S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> rip∣ture
is in Print, is the One Chur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> h <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
he could be content to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
Point: but since his Majesty <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
purpose to do more than barely mention it; I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
it not to mine, to stray from the Papers I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> .</P>
<P>In the process of his Discourse, he would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
the ordinary Power of the Keys out of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ;
and shall with all my heart, so he remove it not
out of the Church. For since it was, with the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ,
given only to her, I do not see what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
Title there can be to it, but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
Her. He is, by his good favour, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> re∣moving
Miraculous Power out of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
God, who slights not the <HI>Roman</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
so much as he, continues <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
her. And would he be content to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> on Miracles, I would be content to undertake
the Proof. But alas! I fear there needs a Miracle
to make People willing that Differences of Religion
should have any Issue.</P>
<P>He would have it question'd, <HI>What part of the
Promise of the Infallible Spirit was to expire with
the Apostles; what to be continued to the Church in
all Ages?</HI> And <HI>how f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> r that</HI> Promise <HI>extends?</HI>
Strange Questions for Christians to dispute, after
they have been answer'd by Christ himself. When
Christ has extended the Assistance of that Spirit to
<HI>All</HI> his Doctrine, and <HI>All</HI> Time; for us to ask
which part of that Assistance shall cease? or to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ? is to ask, Which is the Part of Christ's Pro∣mise
which he will not perform? Neither indeed
are these Questions, with his Distinction between
Sin and Errour, and subtle Speculations upon it, for
any thing, but to bring in Deposing Doctrine, a Com∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> on-place
bang'd in every Book of late.</P>
<P>It is a Theme, than which, as much as it is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
upon, I do not think a worse can be taken
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> an Invective against Infallible Assistance, pick
a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> d chuse through the whole Bundle. When I con∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> er
what has past, and reflect there wanted neither
Power nor Propension in Men, and nevertheless that
the Persuasions about Deposing were never settled, as
those in other Matters which displease the Answerer,
what he takes for an Argument against Infallible
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> tance, I take for a strong Argument for it. For
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> else could be the Cause of that Effect, but that
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Power even of willing Men was directed by an
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Assistance of the Divine Spirit? He may
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> shew he pleases, with the Errours of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , who will not reflect they never ex∣ercis'd
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
the Power of Church-Guid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> upon <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Errours, or, in his Language, <HI>so as to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> ;</HI>
which yet he knows very well no Council, of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
he had in his eye, ever did. As the Church to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
the Promise of Assistance was made, should <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
know what it means, none in the <HI>Roman</HI> Cathol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Church ever understood it would always preserve,
even those who by their Functions are Church-Guides,
from Errour any more than Sin, save when
they perform the Office of Church-Guides; or ex∣pected
more, than that They should not Authorita∣tively
declare that to be Christ's Doctrine, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
not; or that not to be, which is. Since it is un∣deniably
certain, that our Church-Guides have ne∣ver
made any such Declaration, in stead of profit∣ing
by their Pains, we stand wondring what Prote∣stants
mean, by repeating so often a Tale which has
nothing in it. Whoever errs among us, Church-Guide,
or not Church-Guide, errs on his own Head,
and not misguided now, or at any time, by the
Church or her Gnides. And so long it is as wildly
unreasonable to impute those Errours to the Church▪
or any but the erring Particulars, as to bring <HI>Peter</HI>
in guilty for the Faults of <HI>Paul.</HI></P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="36" REF="23"/>
imper<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ect, as half-periods use to be: but who read
the whole, will, I believe, understand it perfectly
enough, and if he had no mind to speak to this part
of it, he might have said so, without imputing to it
an Imperfection of his own making, by severing it
from its fellows. As imperfect as it is, I find by it,
that the Power, of which his Majesty speaks, was
the Power of deciding Matters of Faith; and so, that
when he talks of the Gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> t of Tongues, and the like,
he talks of what his Majesty did not. It informs us
too, that, as great Prerogatives as the Apostles had
above other Men, subsequent Councils took upon
them to make Creeds as well as they; Creeds which
declare they will undoubtedly perish eternally, who
believe not entirely what they contain: And so might
have put us in mind, that those who do as much in
latter Ages, have Precedents for what They do:
Matters, which it seems, he takes no delight to
speak of.</P>
<P>As it had been something rugged to have said this
Part, for all it was left out, deserv'd no considerati∣on,
he smoothly passes to <HI>that which next do's.</HI> And
that is, <HI>That the Church was the Iudge even of Scrip∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> re
it self, many Years after the Apostles, which
Books were Canonical, and which were not.</HI> To which
he replys, That there is <HI>a Iudge of Law, and a
Iudge of Fact,</HI> and that <HI>the Church Iudges of Fact,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Law.</HI> Let him call it how he pleases, if the
Church Judges whether a Book be Canonical or no,
the Church is the Judge of that Matter, and the King
said true; and 'tis but so much erudition lost, to
Dispute by what name Her Judgment shall go. He
says besides that, <HI>The Church of</HI> Rome <HI>hath no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
priviledge in this Matter, but gives its Iudg∣ment
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
as other parts of the Christian World do.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> if
the Clause he answers, spoke of any <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Church, or Priviledge. It says, <HI>the Church,</HI> that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ,
the <HI>whole,</HI> made up of the <HI>Roman,</HI> and the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ,
whose same Faith intitles them to the same App<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ll<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣tion,
was the Judge of Scripture, which Books were
Canonical, and which were not. One may perc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> ve
the Answerer thinks this is true, and he m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ght <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
said, what he thought, in two words. But he
thought fit to spin it out into a Section, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
the Matter so, that one Member of his Division is not
included in the Matter divided; he alone knows, why.</P>
<P><HI>And if They had this Power then, I desire to know,</HI>
says his Majesty next, <HI>how They came to lose it▪</HI> And
the Answerer desires to know <HI>who are meant by</HI> They,
<HI>and what is understood by</HI> This Power. He had not
the Paper by him sure, when he askt these Questions.
For it is there as plain, as words can make it, that
by <HI>They</HI> is meant <HI>the Church,</HI> and by <HI>this Power,</HI> the
<HI>Power of deciding Matters of Faith,</HI> exercised in
making Creeds, and judging of Canonical Boo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> .
Then he falls to his D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> stinctions again, and tells us,
<HI>It is one thing for a part of the Church to give Te∣stimony
to a matter of Fact, and another to assume the
Power of making Books</HI> Canonical, <HI>which were not so.</HI>
Pieces of Learning, which he may, if he please,
keep in reserve till he have to do with some body,
who talks of a <HI>Part of the Church,</HI> or <HI>making Boo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> </HI>
Canonical <HI>which were not.</HI> By the way, he means,
I suppose, making Books not written by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣spiration,
to be written by Divine Inspiration. For
if he mean making it appear, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> ,
and with obligation of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that a
Book, of which it is doubted whether it were <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="38" REF="24"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page〉"/>
<PB N="39" REF="24"/>
that truly Catholic and Apostolic Church, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
which, by separting from the <HI>Roman,</HI> they keep <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
their stricter Union, and with which the <HI>Roman</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
none. For sure he do's not talk of a strict Union
with nothing. Let him tell us in what Countr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
the Men live, that People may go to them, and lear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of them what their Faith is, and see whether it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
be all one with that of the Answerer and his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
and have something, more than his word <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
stricter Union, which he says, is between <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> .</P>
<P>What He, and those who take his part, do, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<HI>separating of themselves,</HI> he tells us, <HI>but being <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
out by an Vsurping Faction in the Church;</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
the Conditions of Communion <HI>impos'd by t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> at F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣ction,</HI>
and requir'd by him who is own'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> or Hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of that Church, <HI>are unjust and unreasonable, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Authority <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e challenges a meer Vsurpation;</HI> and t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> at
<HI>They are not to be condemn'd for such a Separation,
which was unavoidable.</HI> Why unavoidable, I beseec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
him, even supposing Usurpation, and whatever <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
would have? Cannot they who are, let <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> t he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
so unjustly, separated from the Communion, avoi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
being separated from the Faith of a Church, if they
please? Is there any Church, or Power on Earth,
which could hinder them from believing, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
they were out of Communion, what they did <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
they were in it? Which if <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> had done, Excom∣munication
it self had not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them from the
Church, of which these Papers speak. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="40" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> their voluntary Change of Faith. And that
Change indeed casts them unavoidably out; because
to be of the same Faith with a Church, and of a
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Faith from her, is inconsistent. Other cast∣ing
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , by which he means, I suppose, Excommu∣nication,
there is none that I know. 'Tis true,
there is a general Excommunication of those who
ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e chang'd their Faith into Heresie: And some
are particularly named; but not a word of the
Church of <HI>England,</HI> or any relating to <HI>England,</HI> but
the <HI>Wickli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ists.</HI> If any of his <HI>We</HI> be included in it,
'tis because they have voluntarily thrust themselves
in, by embracing the Anathematiz'd Heresies. And
yet he, with his Flourishes and big Talk, would have
their casting off the Church, pass for the Churches
casting them out; and their voluntary Act be call'd,
a being cast unavoidably out. Cross Language, in
my Opinion, and a very sorry Justification of Se∣paration.</P>
<P>But what has he in reserve (I see what he alledg∣es
to justifie his confident Reproach of <HI>Vsurpation?</HI>
The Sacred Head of the Church, on whom he cries
out for an Usurper, has shew'd, by his reiterated
Approbation of the Bishop of <HI>Meaux</HI> Book, that
he is content with that Submission and Obedience
which the <HI>Holy Councils and Fathers have always
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> aught the Faithful.</HI> Pray with what propriety of
Language, or what Sense, do's he call challenging
of so much, Usurpation? What Scripture, or Anci∣ent
Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> rch, or Part of the Christian World, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
with him that 'tis so? not excepting the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of <HI>England</HI> her self. For there is more rea∣son
to take the Expositor's word, who speaks in her
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , than his, for the Sense of the Church of
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
<HI>England.</HI> And from him I learn, it sticks not at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Point, since she <HI>will be content to yield the Pope that
Authority which the Ancient Council<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of the Primi∣tive
Church have acknowledged, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Fa∣thers
have always taught the Faithful to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> </HI>
And She▪ I suppose, would not yield to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>∣pation,
nor the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> xpositor for her.</P>
<P>But pray for what is this Harangue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pon U<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> pa∣tion,
and a Spiritual Kingdom? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> would
know, how People come to separate from the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ,
that is, vary from the Common <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> aith of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> .
And the Answerer tells him, There is an Us<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> rper set
up in the West. Why, suppose there be, m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> st P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣ple
therefore needs believe otherwise than they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
before? needs believe there is no Change <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣stance,
no Purgatory, no more than two Sacraments,
and the rest? This Western Usurpation has no I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣fluence
upon the East, to make the Christians there
change their Faith. Why cannot the Refor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ation
believe of these Points as they believe, and as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Christians, besides themselves, ever have, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
do? So all Differences would be reduc'd to a sing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e
Point, and that, if we may believe the Expos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> r, ei∣ther
no Difference, or easily reconcileable. But t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
go about to make us believe, we must needs differ
about a hundred things, and can by no means <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
it lawful to pray to a Saint, or set up an Image▪ as
long as a certain Man takes more than c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mes to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> is
share, shews the Answerer was either in a very <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lea∣sant
Humour, or hard put to it for something <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
say.</P>
<P>I have follow'd him, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
my way. To return again. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
do Men separate from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="42" REF="26"/>
Church? says the Question. We own no Separati∣on
from that, but are disjoyn'd from the <HI>Roman,</HI>
says the Answerer. Since that Church is nothing
but the <HI>Roman,</HI> and the rest united in the same Faith,
as a Man's Body is nothing but the several Members
animated by the same Soul; and no Part can be cut
off from any of the Members, no Part of a Finger,
for example, from the Finger, without being cut off
from the whole Body: This is in truth to say, We
are not separated, we are only disjoyned; or, We
are not separated, but separated. But to let this
pass, and not stray further after him into the many
Questions which his Reply would start; As, Whe∣ther
there be any Catholic, besides the <HI>Roman</HI> Catho∣lic
Church? Whether there can be Reason for be∣ing
disjoyn'd from any Part of it? Whether Dis∣joyning,
and Union, be not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lat Contradiction?
since Disjoyning signifies a different Faith, and Uni∣on
the same? And the like, in which, whatever
concern his <HI>We</HI> have, I do not believe he has Au∣thority
from the Church of <HI>England</HI> to concern her.
All these things apart, I observe the Answerer do's
here as elsewhere, appears himself, and leaves his
Answer behind. For who they are that separate,
and what they own, and from what part they pro∣fess
to be dis-joyn'd, is nothing to what Authority
they have to separate from the whole, who do?
The Kings Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> stion is a step to an end of Contro∣versies:
For let People once know, that they, who∣ever
they be, are in a deplorable condition, who live
separated from the one Church of <HI>Christ</HI> upon Earth,
those among them, who ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e any care of their
Souls, will bethink themselves, and be glad to find
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> er out, and by piecing with her, if they be broken
<PB N="43" REF="26"/>
off, help to make that One, the only Church on
Earth, and all Christians of a mind again. And I
wish the Answerer had gone that one step without
staggering. It had been a safe step for every body,
who is sure he do's not separate. For it takes off no
weight from any Reason, by which he can shew
that he do's not. But I am afraid, the youngest
Man in Christendom shall never live to see one step
made towards an end of differences in Religion; at
least, if the Answerer were inclin'd that way, he
might, me thinks, without boggling, have frankly
own'd there is, or there is not Authority to separate.</P>
<P>The last Paragraph asks, when pretences are made
of separating from the Church, <HI>Who shall judge of
them? the whole Church, or particular Men?</HI> He an∣swers,
That <HI>the whole force of this Paragraph depend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
upon a Supposition, which is taken for granted, but will
never be yielded by Them, and they are sure can never
be prov'd by the Church of</HI> Rome. Let the Para∣graph
and its force, depend on what it will, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
not have answered a plain Question plainly, and told
us whether the Judgment of pretences do, or do not
belong to the Church, and if not, to whom else<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> He
pretends here, that things are taken for granted <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
one side, which can never be prov'd, and will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
be yielded by the other. Let him tell us if he please,
before he proceed, who shall judge of thus much▪
Who pronounce whether those of the Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> rch <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<HI>Rome</HI> can prove or no, and before whom they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ,
when it comes to their turn, produce their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Who likewise, whether the other side <HI>oug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> t</HI> to yield.
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="44" REF="27"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page〉"/>
<PB N="45" REF="27"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page〉"/>
<PB N="46" REF="28"/>
why he drives all to the Judgment of a particular
Church, unless he think all sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e there, and the Judg∣ment
of that Church not to be submitted to any far∣ther
Judgment. Which if he do, he plainly thinks
there is no Judge between Churches whatever may
be, betwixt Churches and particular Men. This in∣deed
is a full Answer, and which takes the Question
quite away. For it can no longer be ask'd, who is the
Judge, if there be none at all. But he do's not explain
himself, and 'tis not for me to make him say more
than he do's. This I see; that either this is his Answer,
or he gives none. For there is nothing besides, but
what pretences they make, and who made them, and
upon what account. All which is nothing to, <HI>who is
the Iudge of them?</HI></P>
<P>His Usurper is a strange importunate fellow to
thrust in so often, where he has nothing to do, and I
have no more to say to him. At the last consideration
I am as much surpriz'd as the Answerer. For I thought
no Interest should have been remembred in our Case,
but One, <HI>what it avails a Man to gain the whole
World and lose his Soul.</HI> I see no great cause he has
to wonder, that Princes and the Clergy should be of
different minds in Matters of Religion. He knows
the Case has happened heretofore, and that there had
been no change of Religion in <HI>England,</HI> if the whole
Body of the Clergy, and their Advice had been re∣garded.
But not to pry into Mens Hearts, to see
what Interest sways them, This is certain, that those
Princes, who prefer their Eternal, before their Tem∣poral
Interest, when they are for the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> good example; And I cannot conclude better,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> praying God to give every body the Grace
to follow it; and in behalf of Princes, thanking him
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> minding his Reader, that they are not all drawn
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of <HI>Rome</HI> by Interest.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="defense">
<PB N="47" REF="28"/>
<HEAD>A
DEFENCE
OF THE
Second Paper.</HEAD>
<P>THE first Paragraph, as the Answerer has
handled it, concerns the Church of <HI>England</HI>
more than me. If She, when the King
talks of Heresies, and Heresies crept in,
think her self oblig'd by the Answerers thinking pre∣sently
of her: or when she is brought in, by his
turning immediately to justifie the Dissenters, and
that by an Argument alledged formerly in her be∣half,
with something more favour to them too than
her; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for he allows Them Six Councils, and but Four
to Her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I have nothing to do with it. They are Mat∣ters
between themselves. Are there Heresies in <HI>Eng∣land,</HI>
or are there not? Is it a sad thing there should,
or is it not? These are the Questions at present; and
'twill be time enough to talk of the Church of <HI>Eng∣land</HI>
and Dissenters, when they are answered. What
Power the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> has <HI>to define Hereti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
Doctrines,</HI> will keep cold too. For 'tis not ask'd,
How Heresies come to be, or are known to be Here∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
<PB N="48" REF="29"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> </P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 paragraph" DISP="〈1 paragraph〉"/> </P>
<P>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> should lay the stress of his Answer on a
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> This Expression, <HI>as competent as the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> </HI>
is b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> t an ordinary way of saying very compe∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>
As when we say, <HI>This</HI> Man is as strong as <HI>Sam∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> </HI> as wise as <HI>Solomon;</HI> we mean no more
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that they are very strong and wise. And he can
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , that Not just so competent as the Apostles, is
an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to, Whether Competent or no? and to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at a Word, fit matter in a Dispute with a King.
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> us see. The Apostles, for what concerned
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , could do no more with their Infallible
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , than judge for themselves, and act in order
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Salvation according to that Judgment. And
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the Answerer contends is the right of every
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> . Why then, every body is in rigour as com∣petent
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> for himself, as the Apostles. And he
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> His Majesty affirmed, by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
himself: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> or His Majesty only said,
<PB N="49" REF="29"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page〉"/>
<PB N="50" REF="30"/>
ther understand, nor mean to inquire. It concerns
those Guides, and it is not for me to thrust my self
into the Concerns of other Folks.</P>
<P><HI>And 'tis no wonder,</HI> says the third Paragraph, <HI>it
should be so, since that Part of the Nation, which
looks most like a Church, dares not bring the true Ar∣guments
against the other Sects, for fear they should
be turned against themselves, and confuted by their
own Arguments.</HI> To this he says first, That <HI>it is
directly level'd against the Church of England.</HI> As
if an Arrow were the sharper, or blunter, for the
Mark at which it is aim'd. Let him tell us whether
the Assertion be true, or not true, and talk of Le∣velling,
when Levelling is in question. He is out
even in that too. For the Paragraph is in truth le∣vell'd,
not against the Church of <HI>England,</HI> but her
Misfortune. It is an Expression of Compassion, not
Reproach, that she has been overaw'd from using the
true Arguments against Sectaries.</P>
<P><HI>Then he answers, That</HI> if there can be no Authority
in a Church, without Infallibility; or no Obligation to
submit to Authority, without it; then the Church of
<HI>England</HI> doth not use the best Arguments against Se∣ctaries.
But if there be no ground for Infallibility,
<HI>as if his won Goodness were not Ground enough
for God to give it to a Nature which needs it, and
his Word not Ground enough to believe he has given
it;</HI> then, for ought he can see, the Church of <HI>England</HI>
hath wisely disown'd the Pretence of Infallibility, and
made use of the best Arguments against Sectaries,
from a just Authority, and the Sinfulness and Folly
of the Sectaries refusing to submit to it.</P>
<P>I take for granted, he speaks of Authority to guide
Souls to Heaven, such as was in the Primitive
<PB N="51" REF="30"/>
Church, when the Civil Laws were all against her.
And pray him, if he please, to instruct us how such
Authority can be in a Church, without Infal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> bility.
We see no body will believe a Man, who, after he has
told his Story, should add, It may be all fal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e, for any
thing he knows; nor lend his Money upon a Pro∣mise
to be repaid, which the Borrower declares be∣fore-hand
he knows not whether he can keep or no.
And we are persuaded there should be better Secu∣rity
for our Souls, than for our Money, or uncon∣cerning
Opinions. To say a Church is fallible, is
to say she may be deceiv'd; and if she may be de∣ceiv'd
her self, They may be deceiv'd who follow
her. Wherefore to tell us, that such a Church has
notwithstanding Authority to guide us, and that we
ought submit to it, is to tell us, we ought be led
by a Guide, who cannot answer he knows the way
we should go, and venture eternal Happiness or
Misery on a Security, which he who gives, tells us
plainly before-hand may fail us.</P>
<P>Pray let us consider. Christians, every body
knows, are oblig'd to lose all things; their Goods,
their Liberty, their Lives, rather than their Faith.
Can it be reasonable to do this for a Faith, of which
they are conscious to themselves, that it may be
false, for any thing they know? And do's not his
own Heart tell him, who knows nothing of it but
by the Relation of a fallible Relator, that it may
be false, for ought he can tell? Wherefore, to make
the Faith of Christians depend on a fallible Authori∣ty,
is to make Christianity, with its obliging Du∣ties,
the most unreasonable thing in Nature.</P>
<P>What do I say, <HI>unreasonable?</HI> It is to make it
absolutely impossible. For, can I be a Christian
<PB N="52" REF="31"/>
without believing? Is not Belief a judgment that
the thing is true which I believe? Can I have such
a Judgment without a cause able to produce it? And
is a fallible Authority able to make me judge more
than that the thing is <HI>fallibly</HI> true? When Christi∣anity
therefore obliges me to believe the thing <HI>abso∣lutely</HI>
true, it there be nothing to make me believe
but a fallible Authority, it obliges me to an Effect
without a Cause, that is, to a downright impossibi∣lity.
And indeed to flat Contradiction. For as a
thing cannot possibly be true, and not true at once,
to judge it is true, is to judge it cannot at the same
time be false. But I must of necessity judge both, if
I judge upon a Motive which I know is fallible: <HI>That
it is true</HI> by the Judgment to which Christianity
obliges me; and <HI>that it may be false,</HI> by the same
Judgments being grounded on my fallible Authority.
For by judging it fallible, I judge it may deceive me,
that is, that what it recommends to me for true,
may be false. At which rate he is the only good
Christian who contradicts himself.</P>
<P>When the Answerer shall make out, that such
things can be, we may hope to see his Church Au∣thority
without Infallibility. Till then he will per∣mit
us to be persuaded that Infallibility is the true
Argument, which he confesses has not been us'd a∣gainst
Sectaries.</P>
<P>If it be true, that the Church of <HI>England</HI> cannot
pretend to this Argument, which <HI>if she did, Secta∣ries,</HI>
he says, <HI>might justly turn it against her,</HI> it is so
much the worse, and the Kings Discourse is indeed
levelled against her. But I see no such matter. Why
may not she, if she please, pretend to her share in
the Infallibility of the Whole, by remaining, as I
<PB N="53" REF="31"/>
think, her best Advocates plead she do's, a part of
the Whole? Because, says he, <HI>tho' Church Authori∣ty
be asserted, infallibility is deny'd in her Articles.</HI>
Where I beseech him? for I cannot find infallibility
deny'd, save to particular Churches, whereof any
one undoubtedly may forfeit her pretence to Infalli∣bility,
by changing her former Faith, and so ceasing
to be a Member of the Body, to which it was pro∣mised.
But this is her concern not mine. I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it be
so with her, she may thank those against whom the
Kings Discourse is truly levell'd; those who have
pull'd this Argument out of her Hands, and reduc'd
her to have nothing to urge against Sectaries, but the
sinfulness and folly of their Separation: as if she
could take it ill of other folks that they separate from
her, if she be brought to separate from other folks:
Or, as if there were any sin, or folly in Peoples de∣siring
to make their Salvation sure, and when they
cannot find security in a Fallible Authority, seeking
it elsewhere.</P>
<P>There follows that <HI>the Church of</HI> England, <HI>as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> is
cal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> d.</HI> This <HI>as ' tis call'd</HI> makes him teachy; and
he <HI>would fain know what she wants to make her as
good a Church as any in the Christian World;</HI> she that
wants neither <HI>Faith, if the C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> eed contain it,</HI> nor <HI>Sa∣craments,</HI>
nor <HI>Succession of B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> ps,</HI> nor a <HI>Li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> </HI>
Never so little Indulgence for a King, would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
suffered him to speak as he thought fit, espec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>
when he had apply'd the Word, which offends the
Answerer, to the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> too. For he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
of the <HI>Roman,</HI> the Church which is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
Catholic.</HI> But if the Answerers Zeal for the Church
of <HI>England</HI> be so very nice, it might have been em∣ploy'd
much more <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="54" REF="32"/>
something material for her, than in picking a need∣less
Quarrel.</P>
<P>If the <HI>Church of</HI> England <HI>really be not what she is
call'd,</HI> it is long of her self, and the influence she suffers
those to have, who will needs possess the World,
that she sets up Separately for her self with a diffe∣rent
Faith, from that of the great Body. As the
Whole is but One Church, made up of as many
Members, as there are particular Churches which
profess the same Faith; it is unintelligible how there
can be a particular Church otherwise, than by being
a Member of this Body. If the Answerer have a
mind to shew she is a Church, he should shew she is
a Member, and believes as the rest, not alledge
for her things common to as very Heretics as ever
were in the World. For how many of them receiv'd
the Creed, had Sacraments, Succession of Bishops,
and Liturgies? Not to touch the rest (in which, for
all the Answerers confidence, there are difficulties
more than he or any Man will be able to clear.) Is
it not palpable that Christians are as much oblig'd to
believe every thing which <HI>Christ</HI> taught, when 'tis
known he taught it, as what is contain'd in the
Creed? And is it not as certainly known he taught
much more, as that he taught what is there contain'd?
Is it not palpable, that she her self believes more? I
for my part, understand not the Zeal of talking, as if
she quitted her only sure hold, to stand upon Ground
which will certainly founder under her, and upon
which arrant Heretics are forc'd to stand, because
they have no better. But this again is her concern.
Our business is with the remaining part of the Para∣graph,
which says, that she <HI>would have it thought, that
she is the judge in matters Spiritual, yet dares not say
positively, there is no appeal from her.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="55" REF="32"/>
His Answer, dilated with several Examples, is,
That They are ture Judges, from whom there lies
an Appeal. Still catching at Words, and saying no∣thing
to the Thing! His Majesty was solicitous of
freeing the Nation from the Heresies crept in, and
convincing the Sects by Arguments, to which there
could be no return. Till the Church of <HI>England</HI>
can determine Spiritual, as a Judge do's Temporal
Differences, by a final Sentence, conclusive to the
Parties, He thought so great a Benefit could not be
expected from her. The Answerer, with his Zeal,
never thinks of shewing which way she can conclude
any body, but, as if the Name of a thing were All,
tells us, There are true Judges, who nevertheless
cannot conclude the Parties which come before
them. Why, His Majesty, and every body else,
knew this, without needing to trouble his Rhetor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and Erudition for the Matter. But what are those
Judges to our purpose? What Benefit shall we get
by them? And how much the nearer will our Dif∣ferences
be to an end? If there were no other in the
World, Suits would be endless in a Nation, and
Controversies in a Church; as I pray God there be
not who desire no better. In short, His Majesty
talks of Judges, from whom there lies no Appeal;
He, of Judges, from whom there do's; and gives us
this for a satisfactory Answer.</P>
<P>He might peradventure have made something a
better shew, by saying, That His Majesty, by expect∣ing
the Church of <HI>England</HI> should judge without Ap∣peal,
expects more than can be had from a particular
Church; because Appeals must needs lie from all such.
But every particular Church may judge as the rest of
the Body do; and it is to our purpose all one, to
<PB N="56" REF="33"/>
judge without Appeal, and to judge as they judge
from whom there is none. For that Judgment is
without Appeal, tho' not purely in vertue of the Au∣thority
of the particular Church. So the Church of
<HI>England</HI> may judge without Appeal; and if she do
not, may thank those who will not let her.</P>
<P><HI>His Majesty goes on, proving what he had said:</HI>
For either they must say, that They are Infallible,
(which they cannot pretend to, <HI>that is, otherwise
than by giving the right-hand of Fellowship to those
who are)</HI> or confess, that what they decide in Mat∣ters
of Conscience, is no farther to be followed, than
it agrees with every Mans private Iudgment. If
Christ did leave a Church here upon Earth, and We
were all once of that Church, How, and by what
Authority, did we separate from that Church? If the
Power of Interpreting Scripture be in every Mans
Brain, what need have we of a Church, or Church∣men?
To what purpose then did our Saviour, after
He had given his Apostles Power to bind and loose in
Heaven and Earth, add to it, That <HI>He would be
with them, even to the end of the World?</HI> These
Words were not spoken Parabolically, or by way of
Figure: Christ was then ascending into his Glory, <HI>and
left his Power with his Church, even to the end of
the World.</HI></P>
<P>All this the Answerer leaves out; what <HI>relates to
the Churches Authority,</HI> and <HI>every Mans following
his own Iudgment,</HI> having, he says, <HI>been answered
already.</HI> I wish he had told us where. For, tho' I
remember some Speech of Persons who separate
from the Church, and of their Pretences, I cannot
call one Word to mind, of the Authority by which
they separated. If this be the Answer he means, he
<PB N="57" REF="33"/>
compliments His Majesty's Papers; For to insist
upon it, is to consess he has none. He said too,
and that too often to be forgotten, That every Man
is to judge for himself, tho' not for others. What
need then of a Church, or Church men, says His
Majesty, when every body is provided without
them? It seems he thinks they are indeed needless,
but had no mind to say so.</P>
<P>He takes the matter of Appeals more to heart, in
which he takes occasion to proceed from these words:
<HI>What Country can subsist in peace or quiet, where
there is not a Supreme Iudge, from whence there can
be no Appeal?</HI> From whence, the <HI>natural Consequence,</HI>
he says, <HI>appears to be, That every National Church
ought to have the Supreme Power within it self.</HI> In
the Comparison here made, a National to the Whole
Church, is as a Shire to a Kingdom. And a very
natural, and very consistent Consequence it is, That
every Sheriff should be a King.</P>
<P><HI>But how come Appeals to a Forreign Iurisdiction,
to tend to the Peace and Quiet of a Church?</HI> He
would peradventure, if one should press him, be
hard enough put to it, to make Sense of his Forreign
Jurisdiction in our Case. For how can any thing be
Forreign, but by not belonging to that Aggregate,
whether Civil or Spiritual, in respect whereof they
are said to be Forreigners. Forreign, I think, comes
from <HI>Foris,</HI> and signifies <HI>out.</HI> So that unless the
ultimate Jurisdiction of the Church be out of the
Church, it seems as hard to understand how it can
be Forreign to any part of the Church, as how a
Native of any part of <HI>England,</HI> can be a Forreigner
in <HI>England.</HI> The several Nations, which make the
Church, are Forreigners to one another in respect of
<PB N="58" REF="34"/>
the several Temporal Bodies, which they compose
too, but Fellow-Citizens All in respect of the Ec∣clesiastical.</P>
<P>But let this pass, and the Answerer, if he please,
inform us, how the Appeals, of which we talk, can
be made, but to what he calls Forreign Jurisdiction.
The King aim'd at an end of Differences in Religi∣on,
and as he thought every one ought believe as
the Catholic Church believes, which Christ has
here on Earth, calls their Agreement in Faith, a De∣cision;
and knowing or searching what it is, an Ap∣peal.
As no Particular can be the Catholic Church,
let him make it intelligible, who can, how the Faith
of a Church, compos'd of many Nations, can be
known, without knowing the Faith of the Nations
which compose it; that is, of those Churches
which he calls Forreign. It is therefore so far from
hard, to comprehend how Appeals to Forreigners
tend to the Peace and Quiet of a National Church,
that when that Peace is disturbed by Dissentions in
Matters of Religion, it is absolutely impossible to
resettle it without them.</P>
<P><HI>We,</HI> says the King in the Period before, which
the Answerer, I know not why, puts after, <HI>have had
these hundred years past, the sad Effects of denying
to the Church that Power in Matters Spiritual, with∣out
an Appeal.</HI> And <HI>our Ancestors,</HI> says the Answe∣rer,
<HI>for many hundred years last past, found the in∣tollerable
Inconveniences of an Appeal to Forreign
Iurisdiction.</HI> Which after he has a little dilated, by
reckoning up the Particulars, he tauntingly adds,
<HI>But these were slight things, in comparison to what we
have felt these hundred years, for want of it.</HI> This
Taunt is unexpected, and, by his good favour, might
<PB N="59" REF="34"/>
have been spared, for more Reasons than one. For
what? Do's he in earnest think, that the Incoveni∣ences
he has thought of, and may think of here∣after,
hold comparison with the Inconvenience of
Heresie? Are not all temporal Concerns, let them be
what they will, slight things in respect of the eter∣nal
Ruine of so many as Heresie has swallow'd up in
Perdition? Will he compare the gain of the whole
World, to the loss even of a single Soul?</P>
<P>For the rest, 'tis strange a Man should toss a Word
so long, and never mind what it means. The King
us'd the Word <HI>Appeal</HI> with respect to the Allegory,
in which he speaks: The Answerer will needs un∣derstand
it in the Law-sense, and talks all the while
of another matter. For the Impoverishment, the Ob∣struction
of Justice, and what else he mentions, are
Consequences all of Legal Trials betwixt Plaintiff
and Defendant, according to the Methods of Courts.
In which, where-ever those Courts be, Princes can,
and, when they see fit, do preserve their own Prero∣gatives
from diminution, and their Subjects from
Oppression, without shocking their Religion. There
is nothing of all this in the Appeals of which the
King speaks, no feeing of Lawyers, nor need to tra∣vel
from home. Who will but step to St. <HI>Iames's,</HI>
and see what they do, and hear what they say, has
appeal'd as much as the King desir'd he should. To
his Conclusion, That <HI>it is a very self-denying Hu∣mour
for those to be most sensible of the want of Ap∣peals,
who would really suffer the most by them;</HI> I
shall say no more than that it is very unreasonable,
because no body dreams of such Appeals as he un∣derstands,
and I wish that no body may think worse
of it, and of him and other Folks for it.</P>
<P><PB N="60" REF="35"/>
<HI>Can there be any Iustice done,</HI> says the next Pa∣ragraph,
<HI>where the Offenders are their own Iudges,
and equal Interpreters of the Law, with those that are
appointed to administer Iustice?</HI> He cross interrogates,
and asks, Whether <HI>there be any likelihood Iustice
should be better done in another Country, by another
Authority, and proceeding by such Rules, which in
the last resort are but the arbitrary Will of a Stran∣ger?</HI>
I have already observ'd, That <HI>another Country,</HI>
and <HI>another Authority</HI> is un<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ntelligible where all are
Countrymen; and arbitrary Rules are altogether as
unintelligible, where the Law is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ixt and known. At
present I pray him to tell us how he answers the
Question. <HI>Can Iustice be done?</HI> Or, which is the
same, Is there a Judge without Appeal? signifies,
he knows, <HI>Can Controversies be ended?</HI> And he
knows the Answer is, <HI>They can,</HI> or <HI>They cannot.</HI> And
yet he will not say either the one or the other, but
amuses us with his Descant upon the Metaphor, ne∣ver
touching the Plain-song Question. Subordinate
Judges may be as true Judges, and Appeals do as
much harm as they will; Justice too may be as well
administred at home as abroad, for any thing we
are the wiser, or the better. For what is it to us,
what becomes of those Matters? We can inform our
selves time enough of Lawyers, and those who un∣derstand
Government, how they go, when it im∣ports
us to know. At present let the Answerer tell
us, whether Controversies can or cannot be ended?
Whether we can be secure that we are in the right
way to Heaven, or must live on at a venture, never
knowing whether we live as we should, till we come
into the next World, and find perhaps by a sad Expe∣rience,
how we have liv'd in this?</P>
<P><PB N="61" REF="35"/>
We are all Travellers to the Country of Happ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
and as a wrong way can never lead right, it imports
us, as much as Happiness imports, to travel in t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
right Road. He who undertakes <HI>to assist</HI> us in <HI>the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣ficulties
started by these Papers,</HI> acquits himself by
taking an Allegorical Expression in a Literal sense, and
then by shewing Erudition upon it, turning our
Thoughts from the Moral. For while we are enter∣tain'd
with literally true Judges, and Appeals, and
Justice, unless we think of two things at once, there is
no minding Differences in Religion. So that the Assi∣stance,
which it seems he meant, was his Assistance
to remove those Difficulties out of sight; and the
Danger he apprehended, the Danger lest people
should once perceive how 'tis with those who are
out of the Catholic Church; that they have no ac∣countable
Means to end a Controversie, or satisfie a
Difficulty, save by cleanly conveying it out of the
way, if it become importunate. But for any Assi∣stance
towards the only difficulty which imports,
Whether People be in the right way to Heaven, or
no? Whether Controversies can, or cannot be end∣ed?
we have none from the Answerer; but may
guess from his silence, he either thinks They cannot,
or wishes They would not.</P>
<P>He asks again, Whether <HI>such a one, pretending
to a Power he has no right to, must be Iudge in his
own Cause, when he is the greatest Offender▪</HI> This
<HI>Such a one,</HI> if he take it, as in all rea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> on he should,
as His Majesty do's, signifies Him, or Those who
<HI>are appointed to administer Iustice.</HI> Do's such a
one, in his conceit▪ pretend, without right, to the
Power of Administring Justice? And if they be ap∣pointed
to administer it in all Causes, must they
<PB N="62" REF="36"/>
not administer it in their own? Pray turn this Do∣ctrine
to another Subject, and suppose a Question
started in <HI>England</HI> about the king's Prerogative▪
By what Authority should, or could this Question be
judg'd, but the king's? As much his own Cause as
it is, we must not have another Authority set up in
His Kingdom to judge of Differences belonging to
His Kingdom. For, deciding Differences being one
Part of the Kingly Office, it would be to set up
another King. It is palpable, that to apply the Ex∣ception
of ones own Cause to Supreme Powers, is
to make them not Supreme; and yet as irrational
and as destructive as it is, People take the confidence
to do it.</P>
<P>But if the Answerer mean by his <HI>Such a one,</HI> a
<HI>Stranger proceeding by his arbitrary Will,</HI> there nei∣ther
is nor can be such a one. No Member of the
Church can be more a <HI>Stranger</HI> in the Church, than
an <HI>Englishman</HI> in <HI>England.</HI> And for <HI>arbitrary Will,</HI>
in our Case, there cannot be a wilder Fancy. Christ
commanded his Apostles to teach his Doctrine to all
Nations. They obey'd his Command, and <HI>their
sound is gone forth through the whole earth.</HI> Can
the arbitrary Will of any Mortal, stretch it to the
utmost extent of Imagination, alter, or conceal, or
disguise a Doctrine known and practis'd by a great
many Nations, some very remote, and those which
are Neighbours agreeing in few things besides that
Doctrine? Then as the king would have his Appeal
for Justice made to the Catholic Church, so many
Millions, as make up that Church, are a very plea∣sant
<HI>arbitrary such a one.</HI></P>
<P><HI>This, says</HI> His Majesty, <HI>is our Case here in</HI> Eng∣land
<HI>in matters Spiritual. For the Protestants are
<PB N="63" REF="36"/>
not of the Church of</HI> England, <HI>as 'tis the true Church,
from whence there can be no Appeal, but because t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Discipline of that Church is conformable at that pre∣sent
to their Fancies, which as soon as it shall contra∣dict,
or vary from, They are really</HI> (he out of an un∣correct
Copy says <HI>ready) to imbrace or joyn with the
next Congregation of People, whose Discipline and
Worship agrees with their Opinion at that time.</HI> His
Copy has <HI>whose Discipline or Worship agrees with the
Opinion of that time.</HI> Here is the Moral of the Al∣legory,
which we find by <HI>Iustice to be done,</HI> under∣stood
<HI>deciding differences in Matters Spiritual,</HI> that
is, in Faith: By those <HI>who are to administer Iustice</HI>
the <HI>Church from which there is no Appeal.</HI> Because
Protestants do not think themselves concluded by
the Decisions of the Church of <HI>England,</HI> but adhere
to her because they like them at present; The king
infers there is no Authoritative deciding of Spiritual
Differences in <HI>England,</HI> no thrusting out the Here∣sies
crept in; but every one, in consequence of his
Principles, is to leave the Church of <HI>England</HI> as of∣ten
as she decides against his Perswasions, and take
up with the next Congregation which is more to his
humour. What says the Answerer to this.</P>
<P>Why, that <HI>the Sense of this Period is not so clear,
but that one may easily mistake about it.</HI> Very easily
without question. For there is not an easier thing
in the World, than to mistake, when one will give
his mind to it. He is the first, tho', I believe, who
thought his late Majesty did not speak intelligible
English. But the Answerer will help him out, and
tell us <HI>what is aim'd at.</HI> As if what a Man says, and
what he aims at by saying it, were not two things,
as dif<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ere<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> t as End and Means. But let him set the
<PB N="64" REF="37"/>
Cart before the Horse for me, and tell us what was
aim'd at. <HI>That we of the Church of</HI> England <HI>have no
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> upon us, but that of our own Iudgments; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> nd
when that changes, we may joyn with Independents or
Presbyterians, as we do now with the Church of</HI> Eng∣land.
For one half, His Majesty, I believe, did
think the Church of <HI>England,</HI> as things go, has no
tie upon her Members; but his aim was, she might;
and it depends on her self whether she will or no.
The other half was not only aim'd at, but directly
said, and more; that who adhere to Day to the
Church of <HI>England</HI> in vertue of their own Fancies,
not only may, but ought, quit her for the next Con∣gregation
which is more agreeable to those Fancies.
How do's the Answerer avoid that Consequence.</P>
<P>Why truly by talking of another Matter. For he
asks, <HI>What security can be greater than that of our
own Iudgments?</HI> As if it pinched there. His Maje∣sty
talks of those who do not believe, as the Church
of <HI>England</HI> do's, for this reason, because they are
taught by a Church from which there is no Appeal,
that is, who have not that Motive for their Judg∣ments
which he took for the only, truly reasonable
Motive. And while he is speaking of Motives, the
Answerer falls a talking of Judgments. The difficul∣ty
is not whether Judgment affords Security: (A
Judgment grounded on true Reason, can no more
change than Reason:) but whether there be any se∣curity
in those Judgments, which are made on unse∣cure
Motives. Or if you will, what Security there
is in that Judgment, which the Answerer offers for
Security. 'Tis as in Land. The Security is good,
where the Title is unquestionable; but if that be
doubtful, there is no Money to be borrow'd on the
<PB N="65" REF="37"/>
Land. And he will have us take for Security the
Judgment of which we are not satisfy'd▪ that it is it
self secure.</P>
<P>Once again, His Majesty thought Church-secu∣rity
the only Security in this Matter. And it rests
with the Answerer to shew that Protestants either
have this or other true Security; to shew what o∣ther
Foundation and Pillar of Truth there is, besides
the Church; how it can be a Foundation without
Infallibility, and People have reason to trust their
Souls to what may deceive them; In short, what
good account they can give of the Hope which is in
them, who learn the Faith by which they think to
please God, otherwise than from those whom he ap∣pointed
to teach it. Till he do this, as obscurely as
his Majesty speaks, People will see, they have no∣thing
to trust to for their Salvation, but Fancy, nor
the Church of <HI>England</HI> for their company.</P>
<P>But He <HI>dares appeal to the World, whether They
have not made it appear, that it is not Fancy, but
Iudgment which hath made them firm to the Church
of</HI> England? Dares he, in earnest, put it to the Ca∣tholic
World, any more than we to the Protestant?
To what purpose these great words, when he knows
before-hand, nothing will, nor can come of them?
It had been a great deal more to purpose, since Fancy
and Judgment, in this place, signifie a rational or
not rational Persuasion, to have shew'd, that they
truly have Reason, who are firm to the Church of
<HI>England,</HI> and that They are indeed firm. For that
Firmness may as well be pretended, as Reason for it<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and they may desire to pass for firm to Her, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
make her not firm to her self. But for big <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ,
none are better at it than Cowards out of Gun-shot.</P>
<P><PB N="66" REF="38"/>
<HI>Might it not,</HI> asks he on, <HI>as well have been said,
That the P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> tants of the Church of</HI> England <HI>adhe∣red
to the Crow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in the Times of Rebellion, out of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> , and not out of Iudgment?</HI> His Zeal for the
Church of <HI>England</HI> is wondrou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> unlucky. As no
body thought of detracting from the just Praises of
the Church of <HI>England,</HI> and every body must ac∣knowledge
her Doctrine in this Point is very Or∣thodox,
and her Practice in the Times of Rebellion
conformable to it, there was no need to mention this
matter. And yet he will by all means bring it in
against himself. Many, he knows, did desert her,
and her Doctrine in this Point, at that time; so
many, that the Rebellion peradventure was indebted
for its Success to those Deserters. For had not the
ill-affected Rabble been countenanc'd and headed, by
Men who had, perhaps, all their Life before con∣form'd
to the Church of <HI>England,</HI> the Rebellion
either would not have been at all, or not so unfortu∣nately
prosperous. Now, as it is plain, that if those
who deserted, had ever adhered to her, with a per∣suasion,
that they were oblig'd to believe what she
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> aught, They could not have deserted her in this
Point, who always taught Loyalty; This very Case
proves what the King asserts, That till they do so,
there is no security of their adhering to her. For
they may desert her in any other Point of Christ's
Doctrine, as well as they did in this, and for ought
appears will, when they meet with the same Interest,
or whatever Motive They had to desert her then.</P>
<P>In the last place, He tries to turn the Argument
<HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pon the Church of Rome, to which,</HI> he asks, <HI>why
any adhere, but because it is agreeable to their Iudg∣ment
so to do?</HI> This Actor went off the Stage but
<PB N="67" REF="38"/>
now, and needed not return so soon, with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
a Part. For what do's he mean by <HI>Adhering<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> </HI> Be∣lieving,
I suppose, that the Church of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
right. For he talks not sure of acting <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
conformity to our inward <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
but Hypocrites, do in all their Actions. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> he
mean it of the inward Persuasion, to ask, <HI>why They
adhere, but because they judge they ought,</HI> is in other
words, <HI>Why do they adhere, but because they adhere▪</HI>
For their Judgment is their Adhesion. To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
People adhere to a Church, with every body <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
signifies, What Reason or Motive have they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
adhering?</P>
<P>To which Question, with respect to the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> oman</HI>
Catholic Church, the Answer, in the words of the
Paragraph, is, That People <HI>are of her, as 'tis the true
Church, from whence there can be no Appeal;</HI> or be∣cause
she is the Church which Christ has now on
Earth, with whom his Doctrine was deposited, and
from whom only it can be learn'd. In the words or
<HI>St. Austin;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> </NOTE> <HI>I am kept in the Bosom
of the Catholic Church, by the consens
of People and Nations; by an Au∣thority
begun by Miracles, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
by Hope, increas'd by Charity, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
by Antiquity; by a Succession
of Bishops from St.</HI> Peter, <HI>to whom <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="68" REF="39"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> where Catholics meet, none of them have
the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> him to their Congregations.</HI>
The Answerer will tell us when he thinks sit, what
Answer he thinks proper to be made for other
Churches. In the mean time, let us reslect what
he has answer'd to the Paragraph.</P>
<P>He has told us, That there is no Security greater
than that of our Judgments: That theirs is Judg∣ment
not Fancy, and particularly was so in the times
of Rebellion: And that they Judge in the Church of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> too. What is all this to the Paragraph, which
says in short, That because Protestants have no firm
Motive for their adhering to the Church of <HI>England,</HI>
they cannot be firm to her. Do's he make it appear
their Motive is firm? Or how They will be firm
without one▪ This little is all there was before him;
is their Judgment solidly grounded, or is it not? the
only and whole business. What need was there to
talk of Judgment in common, when the Question is
of their Judgment in this Particular? Or what serves
it for, but to make a shew, and fill up a Page?
There may be as much Security in the Judgment as
there will, and Protestants be never the better, unless
there be Security in <HI>their</HI> Judgment. They will, I
hope, since their Souls are at stake, consider what
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> do to venture them, where those, who write <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
are not able to shew they have any
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> . It is enough to my purpose to have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
that his Majesty asks for a secure Motive, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> no Answer.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to see, by his Objections against
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> , what he takes for Fancy, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> . According to him, They <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
and They
<PB N="69" REF="39"/>
<HI>Iudge,</HI> who to be sure of a right <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/>∣rences
in Religion, look out for a <HI>Fallible Iudge,</HI>
and hazard their Salvation, on what may deceive
them. They <HI>Fancy,</HI> who are for an <HI>Vnwritten
Word;</HI> They <HI>Iudge,</HI> who think the Word of God
is made by Writing. <HI>Giving Honour to God by
the Worship of Images, is Fancy;</HI> and <HI>Iudgment,</HI> that
giving Honour to God, is not giving Honour to
God. For giving Honour any way, is plainly gi∣ving
Honour. <HI>Mediators of Intercession besides the
Mediator of Redemption</HI> are <HI>Fancy;</HI> and so to think,
because only one could Redeem us, no body besides
can Pray for us, is <HI>Iudgment. The Doctrine of Con∣comitancy,
Fancy;</HI> and true Christian <HI>Iudgment,</HI> that
the Body and Blood of <HI>Christ</HI> can n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e sep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> rated,
and he die again. A <HI>Substantial change in the E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣ments,
Fancy;</HI> and right <HI>Iudgment,</HI> that the Apo∣stles
did not understand what <HI>Christ</HI> said to them, or
not instruct the Church as they believ'd themselves.
So 'tis with his last instance of Pargatory, and all
the rest. Our Judgment is the Judgment of <HI>the
Church from which there is no Appeal,</HI> and it rests
with the Answerer to shew, how any other Judg∣ment
can be more than <HI>meer Fanc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ,</HI> to
dispatch the next Paragraph under one. Men are
giddy, or settled, as they are guided or not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
by Reason; and he should shew <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Reason besides
can settle them, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> </P>
<P><PB N="70" REF="40"/>
<HI>I desire to know therefore,</HI> says His Majesty, <HI>of
every serious Considerer of these things, whether the
great Work of our Salvation ought to depend on such
a sandy Foundation as this?</HI> That is, says the An∣swerer,
the <HI>Private Iudgment.</HI> Can a Man expect
there should be any Answer to this, but that our Sal∣vation
ought, or ought not depend on Sand; or
that the Foundation of Private Judgment is, or is not
Sandy? And yet the Answerer makes a shift to spin
out a Paragraph, without one word of either.</P>
<P><HI>I,</HI> says he, <HI>have seriously considered this matter,
and must declare, That I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ind no Christian Church
built on a more sandy Foundation, than that, which
pretends to be settled on a Rock,</HI> as to part of her
Faith. If that Church build on Sand too, she will,
I suppose hear on't in due time. At present, he
who considers so much, might consider, that he is
not ask'd what he has considered, or what he has
found; but, whether any Church▪ That, if he will,
among the rest ought to build on Sand? and whe∣ther
Private Judgment be more than Sand? Plain <HI>I,</HI>
or <HI>No,</HI> if it please him first, and then <HI>a l' autre.</HI></P>
<P>Then he tells us That <HI>no understanding Man builds
upon his own Iudgment.</HI> He takes, I suppose, the
Advice of his Friends in Compliment: For after all,
he is to be his own Judge. But is his Judgment,
and their Advice, and what you will, besides the
Judgment of the Church without Appeal, a Foun∣dation
to build upon? There is the Knot which the
Answerer should now untie.</P>
<P><HI>But no Man of understanding can believe without</HI>
his Judgment. Sure enough; nor no Man of not∣understanding
neither: for his Belief is his Judg∣ment.
But I am cloy'd with this Dish. What
<PB N="71" REF="40"/>
Stand there is to set it upon, is now the Question.</P>
<P><HI>I appeal,</HI> says the Answerer, <HI>to any ingenuous
Man, whether he doth not as much build upon his
own Iudgment, who chuseth, the Church, as he that
chuseth Scripture for his Rule?</HI> Every ingenuous
Man, who reads these Papers, will tell him, that <HI>to
build upon ones own Judgment,</HI> is the same with <HI>fol∣lowing
ones own Fancy,</HI> being <HI>ones own Iudge,</HI> and
what other Terms a Master of <HI>English,</HI> in all Sen∣ses,
used, to express, in variety of Phrases, <HI>Iudging
unreasonably.</HI> Let the Answerer, in stead of telling
us what we all know as well as he, That every one
Judges, who Judges, tell's what we do not know,
what Reason they have to chuse the Scripture, not
the Church, for their Rule.</P>
<P><HI>He that chuseth the Church, hath many more Diffi∣culties
to conquer, than the other hath.</HI> How so?
For this sounds like a Paradox. Those many more
Difficulties, to my thinking, must be conquer'd, be∣fore
one can come at Scripture. For unless we first
chuse the Church for a Rule to find out Scripture, by
whom alone St. <HI>Austin</HI> has told us we know it, there
will be no assurance of Scripture for us to chuse.
And then in the choice of the Church, there is but
one thing to mind, and that no difficulty neither,
<HI>where, or which the Church is?</HI> When that is set∣tled,
a Man has no more to do, but believe as he is
taught, and live as he believes. Who thinks he has
conquer'd the difficulties about the Letter of Scrip∣ture,
as which Books belong to the Canon, which
not? which is a right Translation or Reading,
which wrong? and whatever falls in his way; has at
least as many remaining, as he has past, and which
if he find not insuperable, he is, I believe, the more
<PB N="72" REF="41"/>
beholding to his <HI>Will.</HI> For I know not how to have
any Opinion of his <HI>Iudgment,</HI> who, only because
such words will bear his Sense, as they will, it may
be twenty others, all abetted by Men of Name, ven∣tures
his Soul upon't that his is just the Sense meant
by the Holy Ghost. But let us hear his Reason.</P>
<P><HI>For the Church can never be a Rule without the
Scriptures,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Quid autem si neque Apostoli qui∣dem Scripturas reliquissent nobis, nonne opportebat ordinem sequi Traditionis, quam tradiderunt iis quibus committebant Ecclesias? cui ordinationi a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lentiunt multae Gentes Barbarorum, eorum qui in Christum credunt, sine charta &amp; atramento scriptam habentes per spiritum in cordibus suns salutem, &amp; veterem Tra∣ditionem diligenter custodientes. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> advers. Haere<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> . Lib. 3. col.</NOTE> <HI>but the Scriptures may, without the
Church,</HI> that is, without Faithful. For a Congrega∣tion
of them is a Church. Will he persuade us there
were no Faithful in the World before <HI>Moses?</HI> No
Christians before the <HI>New Testament,</HI> which was
written by Christians? and no part of it till several
Years after the Resurrection. Do's not St. <HI>Irenaeus</HI>
inform us, that more than one Na∣tion
had the Doctrine of <HI>Christ</HI> and
no Scriptures? And will he make us
believe, that all these were Faithful
without any Rule for their Faith?
and that the Church depends on
<HI>Writing,</HI> which if it should be lost
in the World, there would be an
end of the Church? Again, of
what, and to whom should Scrip∣ture
be a Rule, if there were no Faith, nor Faithful?
Paradoxes a part, and the attempt to unriddle one
by another, let the Answerer tell us, if he please,
whether our Salvation ought to stand upon Sand;
and to deal plainly, whether he think that they who
stand, whether on the Church, or Scripture, do not
build both on Sand? For by saying nothing for
Scripture, and yet making it worse on the Churches
side, one would guess he is of Opinion, there is no
steadiness in either. And it would be well to speak
<PB N="73" REF="41"/>
plain, that People may leave off dealing, where
there is no Security, and troubling themselves no
longer with the uncertainties of Religion, turn their
Thoughts to more solid things.</P>
<P>Whether it be <HI>easie</HI> or no <HI>to find the Churches In∣fallibility
in the Scripture,</HI> has been answered by Her
Royal Highness; and I will not presume to answer
where she has, especially when the Question has no
relation to our Business.</P>
<P>In the last place, who has found the Churches In∣fallibility,
has yet, says the Answerer, <HI>a harder
Point to get over,</HI> viz. <HI>How the Promises relating to
the Church in general, came to be appropriated to the
Church of</HI> Rome? By the way, the Promises of
which he talks, are they not in Scripture? and no
harder to be found there by another, than by him?
How comes the Churches Infallibility to be easily
found there in this Period, which was not easie to
find in the last? For who has found the Promise, has
foun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Infallibility, as certainly as that the Promises
of <HI>Christ</HI> never fail. But why are we not all agreed
now? That there are Promises of Infallibility made
to the Church in general he agrees, and doubts not,
I suppose, but that those Promises are made good.
I suppose, too, he will allow that the Church in Ge∣neral,
and the General Church are all one, and that
the General, and the Catholic Church▪ are but two
Names for the same thing. And so we are arriv'd
at Infallibility in the Catholic Church. Yes; but it
must not <HI>be appropriated to the Church of</HI> Rome▪
Why, it shall not, if that will content him. We
ask no more, than what he allows. That the Ca∣tholic
Church be Infallible, and the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI>
with all her faults, one of the many Churches which
<PB N="74" REF="42"/>
make it up. To allow so much, is to allow the <HI>Roman</HI>
Catholic Church is Infallible. For <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic
is nothing but the Catholic with the <HI>Roman</HI> in. What
remains then, but to take the Infallibility promis'd
to this Catholic Church for the Foundation of our
Salvation, inquire and believe what she teaches, and
leave off disputing? For they are undoubtedly firm∣ly
grounded who build on the Promises of God.</P>
<P>It is true, the Answerer has not all this while an∣swered
the Question. For he says not, whether
Salvation ought to depend on a Sandy Foundation;
or whether the private Judgment be a Sandy Foun∣dation.
But he has done much better, by instruct∣ing
People the Catholic Church is Infallible, and
shall for me keep his Thoughts of that Matter to
himself, since he has no mind to reveal them. Peo∣ple,
I hope, will profit by his Instructions, and for
their own sakes chuse Infallible, rather than Fallible
Security for their Souls, now they know where 'tis
to be had.</P>
<P>There follow several lines in his Majesties Paper,
which are not transcrib'd by the Answerer, because
they are, he says, as effectual for the Church of
<HI>England, as Rome.</HI> And truly I am of his mind, that
the Church of <HI>England</HI> has her share in those favours
as much as any particular Church, if she be, as they
are, incorporated into the General. For neither do
they claim otherwise; nor can the Favours granted
by God to the Faithful, be imagined extended to the
not-faithful. It is for this Reason I have always
thought them no Friends of hers, who make her of a
d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fferent Faith from all, or indeed any part of the
Catholic Church, that is, no part her self. For evi∣dently
there is no pretending to the Priviledges of
<PB N="75" REF="42"/>
a Body, but by being a Member; nor pretending to
be of the Body of Faithful, but by Faith.</P>
<P>And pray consider, <HI>says the King,</HI> on the other side
that those who resist the Truth, and will not submit to
his Church, draw their Arguments from Implications,
and far fetch'd Interpretations, at the same time that
they deny plain and positive words; which is so great
a disingenuity, that 'tis not almost to be thought, that
they can believe themselves.</P>
<P>Here are two particulars mentioned; drawing Ar∣guments
from Implications, and denying plain
words. In answer to the first, out of the whole heap
of Controversies, the Answerer chuses Three, in
which they have, he says, <HI>plain and positive words
on their side.</HI> Now it had been altogether as easie,
and as short, to have produc'd those plain and posi∣tive
words, if there had been any, as to have past his
word that there are such. Besides that People love
to see with their own Eyes, and plain things may
easily be seen; He is a Party, and even Supreme
Powers, according to him, must not judge in their
own Cause. It rests then with him, to shew where
the Scripture says <HI>No,</HI> of what the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic
Church says <HI>I,</HI> or contrariwise. For this is what Peo∣ple
understand by plain and positive, and all besides
is Implication. And by the favour of his Confi∣dence,
I affirm to him, that who argue against the
<HI>Roman</HI> Catholic Church, out of Scripture, argue <HI>al∣ways</HI>
from Implications: tho' it be more than needs
to justifie His Majesties Assertion. For if they draw
their Arguments from Implications <HI>at any time,</HI> they
draw Arguments from Implications.</P>
<P>In answer to the Second, he pitches upon a point
wherein he acknowledges the words of Scripture
<PB N="76" REF="43"/>
<HI>seem</HI> plain and positive on our side, and their Sense
to be <HI>from Implications and far-fetch'd Interpreta∣tions,</HI>
and alledges what he has to say, why, not∣withstanding,
they are not plain and positive. As
if there were any other way of denying plain Words
of Scripture, but by denying them to be plain. No
Christian has the confidence to deny what Scripture
plainly teaches; but who has no mind to believe
what it teaches, denies that it teaches contrary to
him, and for a Pretence to deny That, raises some
Mist or other, to obscure the Clearness of every
Text alledg'd against him. The Answerer then is
far enough from shewing, that they do not deny
plain Words of Scripture, by pretending that they
are not plain, not did not could His Majesty mean
they denied them otherwise, who knew very well
that there is no other way to do it, and that no
Words are so plain, but who will make it his busi∣ness,
may find something to say against them. This
which the Answerer alledges, was far from a Secret
to Him.</P>
<P>In short, the Answerer would have them cleared
from arguing from Implications, by saying, they
have, in three Points, plain Words, which he thought
it needless to produce; and from denying plain
Words, by denying that they are plain. And this
is all his Answer. What he says of Implications in
the Pope's Bulls, might, if he could shew the Church
of <HI>Rome</HI> builds her Faith on those Implications, be an
Argument against her, but none for himself. For
<HI>Paul</HI> is not a just the less a Thief, because <HI>Peter</HI> is
caught stealing too. But, some in the Church of
<HI>Rome</HI> argue from Implications, upon which they do
not build their Faith, therefore others may build
<PB N="77" REF="43"/>
their Faith upon Implications, seems to me but an
odd Argument.</P>
<P><HI>The King's Conclusion is;</HI> Is there any other
Foundation of the Protestant Church, but that, if the
Civil Magistrate please, he may call such of the Cler∣gy
as he thinks fit for his turn at that time, and turn
the Church either to Presbytery, or Independency, or
indeed what he pleases? This was the way of our Pre∣tended
Reformation here in <HI>England.</HI> And by the
same Rule and Authority, it may be alter'd into as
many Shapes and Forms, as there are Fancies in Mens
Heads.</P>
<P><HI>This,</HI> says the Answerer, <HI>looks like a very unkind
Requital to the Church of</HI> England, <HI>for her Zeal in
asserting the Magistrates Power against a Forreign Iu∣risdiction;
to infer from thence, That the Magistrate
may change the Religion here which may be pleases.</HI> I
need not observe, that this is no Answer, because
I suppose it was not meant for one. It seems rather
a kind of Complaint, to my thinking very unrea∣sonable.
For he is a great deal more justly to be
complain'd of, who takes a concerning Truth un∣kindly,
then he who speaks it. Religion, I think,
should not depend on Compliments; and I pray
God preserve me from the Kindness, which, not to
fail in the Punctilio's of nice Civility, forbears to
tell me what may be useful to my Salvation. Again,
Zeal against Forreign Jurisdiction very well might,
and, much more according to knowledge, actually
did appear in <HI>England,</HI> without any alteration in
Religion: a thing to which I am persuaded neither
Magistrate not Church have reason to think them∣selves
beholding; because it was the Gap at which
the Heresies crept in, of which His Magesty com∣plains,
<PB N="78" REF="44"/>
and which not long since ruin'd Both. Nei∣ther
is any inference made from that Zeal; but a
plain Question ask'd, to which a plain Answer
would much better become the Part he now acts,
and shew much more Zeal to Truth, and to the
Church of <HI>England,</HI> than talking of her Zeal un∣seasonably.</P>
<P><HI>But although we attribute the Supreme Iurisdiction
to the King, yet we do not question, but there are in∣violable
Rights of the Church, which ought to be
preserv'd against the Fancies of some, and Vsurpa∣tions
of others.</HI> Rights! and Fancies! and Usur∣pations!
Pray let him keep these things till their
time come, and tell us at present, why the Prote∣stant
Church may not be alter'd, as it was made,
by the Authority of the Magistrate, and Concur∣rence
of such of the Clergy as are for his turn?
This, if he have forgot it, is the Question. For the
Rights of the Church, his Care will be more seaso∣nable,
when he has settled the Foundation.</P>
<P><HI>We do by no means make our Religion mutable ac∣cording
to the Magistrates Pleasure.</HI> But only ac∣cording
to the Pleasure of other Folks, perhaps. If
it be immutable, let us see the immutable Foundati∣on,
which makes it so, and have some Reason to
think it so. There it sticks. Barely to say it is
immutable, costs nothing; nor was there ever so
great a Criminal, who could not say, <HI>Not guilty.</HI></P>
<P><HI>For the Rule of our Religion is unalterable, being
the Holy Scripture.</HI> Not to turn our present Que∣stion
into a Dispute about the Rule of Faith, I pray
him to make it appear that the Holy Scripture is
such a Foundation as makes the Protestant Church
unalterable. The Letter of Scripture is common to
<PB N="79" REF="44"/>
all, who bare the name of Christians, and may be
as much a Foundation to every, as to any one. The
Sense is not a Foundation of Religion, but Religion
it self. As Protestants build Protestancy upon Scrip∣ture,
the Presbyterians build Presbytery, the Inde∣pendents
Independency, and every one his own Re∣ligion.
Their several Religions are nothing but
their several Expositions of the same words. Why
now, is this Foundation more unalterable, in respect
of the Protestant Church, than any other? It su∣stain'd
a Catholic Building heretofore; It sustains a
Protestant now. Why may not the same Hands
which removed the Catholic, and set up the Prote∣stant
in its, place, remove the Protestant, and set up
the Presbyterian, the Independent Building▪ or what
you will; this is the Question, to which a Body
would have expected an Answer from an Answerer.
But he in stead of thinking of that Matter, gives us
for an unalterable Foundation of Protestant Religion,
a Foundation upon which all the Alterations of Reli∣gion,
which are, and perhaps ever have been, pre∣tend
to stand as much as the Protestant.</P>
<P><HI>But the exercise of</HI> Religion <HI>is under the Regula∣tion
of the Laws of the Land.</HI> Must the Laws
which regulate the Exercise of Religion be obey'd,
<HI>not only for Wrath but for Conscience,</HI> or must they
not? If they must, People are oblig'd to exercise a
new Religion, as often as the Laws appoint a new
Exercise. For they cannot exercise one Religion,
and be of another. And then they are oblig'd in
Conscience to alter their Religion, as the Laws al∣ter,
from Protestant to Presbyterian or Independent,
or as the Law pleases. If such Laws are not to be
obey'd, that the exercise of Religion is under the
<PB N="80" REF="45"/>
Regulation of the Laws, signifies, that People may
be punish'd for not doing what in Conscience they
are not oblig'd to do. So Christianity is under the
Regulation of Pagan, or Turkish Laws, and every
weaker Man under the Regulation of a stronger;
which to may Ears sounds odly. But take it which
way you will, the Case is equal. If there be an Ob∣ligation
from the Laws, there may be an Obligation
to the Presbyterian, or Independent Exercise and
Religion when the Law pleases: And if there be
none, Presbytery indeed, and Independency cannot
be impos'd upon our Consciences by Law; but they
may be as much settled as Protestancy is now. For
all are under the same Regulation, with the same
either Obligation, or not Obligation from that Re∣gulation.</P>
<P>He concludes with a Prayer, with which it is as
with Scripture. Take it right, and 'tis a good
Prayer: but yet they may joyn in it, who will be
<HI>Good Christians,</HI> and <HI>Loyal Subjects</HI> no longer, than
their King is a <HI>Nursing Father to their Church.</HI></P>
<P>But now he is parting from His Majesty, it will
not be amiss to reflect how it stands between them.
His Majesty, as he had perhaps more reason than
other Men, was deeply sensible of the sad effects of
Differences in Religion, which he saw must needs
last, till an effectual course be taken to compose
them. Wrangling about particular Points, that is,
turning Religion into Ergotery, He had reason to
think would never do it. For there never came so
bad a Cause into <HI>Westminster-Hall,</HI> nor ever will
into the Church, for which no Argument can be
made. As long as Men have Tongues, they will
never want something to say, which 'tis but dressing
<PB N="81" REF="45"/>
up in handsome Language, and it may take with
those who distinguish not the Plausible from the So∣lid.
The bare name of an Answer, is enough to
make a shew, and keep up the Reputation of not be∣ing
overcome, and so much is Victory to one side.
In short, Men die, and Disputes live, and all that
comes of them is what was long since observ'd, <HI>There
is no end of writing many Books.</HI> He saw besides,
that it agrees not with the Goodness of God, and
His care of Man, to leave us at uncertainties, which
without Infallibility he saw unavoidable. And therefore
wish'd People, in stead of floating uncer∣tainly
up and down in the Ocean of Disputes, to
take Port in that one Church which <HI>Christ</HI> has upon
Earth, and to which Power was given to govern us
in Matters of Faith, and a promise of perpetual assi∣stance.
Which Church, he says, is vibsily the <HI>Ro∣man</HI>
Catholic.</P>
<P>The Answerer flatly denies the <HI>Roman</HI> Catho∣lic
to be the one Church of <HI>Christ,</HI> for Reasons,
ever since St. <HI>Cyprians</HI> Days, condemn'd by all
Christians; and never minds that he denies two
terms the same with a third, to be the same be∣tween
themselves. For Church of <HI>Christ,</HI> and Ca∣tholic
Church, are the same, both signifying all
the particular Churches which believe the Do∣ctrine
of <HI>Christ.</HI> Again, <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic, is the
same too with Catholic: for both signifie likewise
all the same Churches, with the <HI>Roman</HI> for one of
the number, which the Answerer acknowledges she
is. Catholic, says All, and who says All says <HI>Ro∣man,</HI>
if she be one; And who says <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic,
says those very All, neither more nor less; And
yet the Answerer can fancy a difference. For the
<PB N="82" REF="46"/>
rest he gives no direct Answer, that I remember to
any one Question, yet hovers so about it, that one
must keep his thoughts very attentive, not to have
them diverted quite another way. As for Certain∣ty
or Uncertainty, they are Matters which he
seems not to mind. Not but that he talks of a
sure Compass, and Infallible Rule: but he never
tells us, whether, or how a Man shall be sure, that he
do's indeed steer by that Compass, or is guided by that
Rule. Those great sounds vanish into Conscience
at last, and that Conscience may be right or wrong,
for any care he takes; as perhaps he thinks it e∣qual,
whether the one, or the other. The King
desired People should have sure hold, and shews
them where they may: He is only solicitous to
keep them from fastning there, and leaves them to
find another, if they can of themselves, or be con∣tent,
if they will, without any. If he have a Pique
to the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic, he may shew them another
Catholic Church, or, if a Church be needless, on
what they may rest securely without a Church. If
on Scripture, he may shew them, how they may
safely stake their Souls, that they do not mistake
it: If on Conscience, how they may securely trust
it. Let People be but safe, and I ask no more.
But as there is, after all but one way to Heaven,
the King shews it, and he imputes deceit to him
for his pains; and then sets up for the faithful
Friend himself, who will neither let them go that
way, nor shew them that there is any other. And
thus it stands between them.</P>
<P>It is for the Reader to consider, which of the
two gives him better Counsel, and where he can
find better Security, than what His Majesty offers,
<PB N="83" REF="46"/>
or whether Security be needless. One would think
is not like to take up much Consideration in our
Country, whether, in a concern of infinite more
value than all the Money, which troubles so ma∣ny
Lawyers and Scriveners, one should deal with∣out
looking after Security. And yet, by what∣ever
charm it happens, there needs a great deal
of Grace, to make People sensible in this Case, of
what in all others they are but too much, their
greatest concerns. <HI>God of his Mercy grant it to
all who ask it, and to all, who by not asking it, shew
they more need it.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="defense">
<PB REF="47"/>
<PB N="85" REF="47"/>
<HEAD>A
DEFENCE
OF THE
Third Paper.</HEAD>
<P>I Dare appeal to all unprejudic'd Readers, and
especially to those who have any sense of Piety,
whether upon perusal of the Paper written by
Her late Highness the Duchess, they have not found
in it somewhat which touch'd them to the very
Soul: whether they did not plainly and perfectly
discern in it the Spirit of Meekness, Devotion, and
Sincerity, which animates the whole Discourse;
and whether the Reader be not satisfied, that she
who writ it has open'd her Heart without disguise,
so as not to leave a Scruple that she was not in ear∣nest.
I am sure I can say, for my own particular,
that when I read it first in Manuscript, I could not
but consider it as a Discourse extremely moving,
plain, without Artifice, and discovering the Piety
of the Soul from which it flow'd. Truth has a
<PB N="86" REF="48"/>
Language to it self, which 'tis impossible for Hypo∣crisie
to imitate: Dissimulation could never write
so warmly, nor with so much life. What less than
the Spirit of Primitive Christianity could have di∣ctated
her Words? The loss of Friends, of worldly
Honours, and Esteem, the Defamation of ill Tongues,
and the Reproach of the Cross, all these, though
not without the struglings of Flesh and Blood, were
surmounted by her; as if the Saying of our Saviour
were always sounding in her Ears, <HI>What will it profit
a man to gain the whole world, and lose his Soul!</HI></P>
<P>I think I have amplified nothing in relation ei∣ther
to this Pious Lady, or her Discourse: I am sure
I need not. And now let any unbias'd and indif∣ferent▪
Reader compare the Spirit of the Answerer
with hers. Do's there not manifestly appear in him
a quite different Character? Need the Reader be
inform'd, that he is disingenuous, soul-mouth'd, and
shuffling; and that, not being able to answer plain
Matter of Fact, he endeavours to evade it, by Sup∣positions,
Circumstances, and Conjectures; like a
cunning Barreter of Law, who is to manage a sink∣ing
Cause, the Dishonesty of which he cannot other∣wise
support, than by defaming his Adversary? Her
only Business is▪ to satisfie her Friends of the inward
Workings of her Soul, in order to her Conversion,
and by what Methods she quitted the Religion in
which she was educated. He on the contrary, is
not satisfied, unless he question the Integrity of her
Proceedings, and the Truth of her plain Relation,
even so far as to blast, what in him lies, her Blessed
Memory, with the imputation of Forgery and De∣ceit;
as if she had given a false Account, not only
of the Passages in her Soul, and the Agonies of a
<PB N="87" REF="48"/>
troubl'd Conscience, only known to God and to her
self, but also of the Discourses which she had with
others concerning those Disquiets. Every where the
Lie is to be cast upon her, either directly, in the
Words of the Bishop of <HI>Winchester,</HI> which he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ▪
or indirectly, in his own, in which his spiteful De∣ligence
is most remarkable.</P>
<P>In his Answer to the two former Papers there
seems to have been some restraint upon the viru∣lence
of his <HI>Genius,</HI> though even there he has mani∣festly
past the Bounds of Decency and Respect: But
so soon as he has got loose from disputing with
Crown'd Heads, he shews himself in his pure Na∣turals,
and is as busie in raking up the Ashes of their
next Relations, as if they were no more of kin to
the Crown, than the New Church of <HI>England</HI> is to
the Old Reformation of their Great-Grandfathers.
But God forbid that I should think the whole Epi∣scopal
Clergy of this Nation to be of his Latitudi∣narian
Stamp; many of them, as Learn'd as him∣self,
are much more Moderate: And such, I am con∣fident,
will be as far from abetting his Irreverence
to the Royal Family, as they are from the jugling
Designs of his Faction, to draw in the Nonconfor∣mists
to their Party, by assuring them they shall
not be prosecuted (as indeed, upon their Principles,
they cannot be by them); but in the mean time
this is to wrest the Favour out of the King's Hands,
and take the Bestowing it into their own; and to re∣assume
to themselves that Headship of the <HI>English</HI>
Church, which their Ancestors gave away to King
<HI>Henry</HI> the Eighth. And now let any Loyal Subject
but consider▪ whether this new way of their Pro∣ceeding
do's not rather tend to bring the Church of
<PB N="88" REF="49"/>
<HI>England</HI> into the Fanatics, than the Fanatics into
the Church of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>These are the Arts which are common to him and
his Fellow-labourers; but his own peculiar Talent is
that of subtle Calumny and sly Aspersion, by which
he insinuates into his Readers an ill Opinion of his
Adversaries, before he comes to Argument; and
takes away their Good Name rather by Theft than
open Robbery. He lays a kind of accumulative
Dishonesty to their Charge, and touches 'em here
and there with Circumstances, in stead of positive
Proofs, till at last he leaves a bad Impression of 'em;
like a Painter who makes Blotches of hard Colour∣ing
in several Parts of the Face, which he smooths
afterwards into a Likeness. After this manner he,
or one of his Brethren in Iniquity, has us'd <HI>Mon∣sieur
de Condom,</HI> by picking up Stories against him
in his Preface, which he props up with little Cir∣cumstances,
but seldom so positive that he cannot
come off, when their Falsity shall be detected. In
the mean time, his Cause go's forward with the
Common Reader; who, prepossest by the Preface, is
made partial to his Answer. The same kind of Ar∣tifice,
with some little variation, has been us'd in
other of their Books, besides this present Libel
against the Duchess.</P>
<P>But, the Cloven-foot of this our Answerer, ap∣pears
from underneath the Cassock, even in the first
step he makes towards his Answer to the present Pa∣per:
<HI>Which,</HI> he tells us, <HI>is said to be written by a
great Lady.</HI> How doubtfully he speaks, as if there
were no certainty of the Author. But surely 'tis
more than barely said; for 'tis Publish'd by the same
Authority, which order'd the two other Papers writ∣ten
<PB N="89" REF="49"/>
by His late Majesty to the Press; and the Origi∣nal
of it, is still remaining in the Hands of the pre∣sent
King▪ Indeed the Bishop of <HI>Winchester</HI> may
seem to have given him some encouragement for this
in the Preface to his Treatises, where he tells us,
<HI>That</HI> Maimbourg <HI>the Iesuite recites something which
he says was written by the late Duchess;</HI> and which
he afterwards calls <HI>the Papers pretended to be writ∣ten
by Her.</HI> But if that Bishop had liv'd to see what
our Answerer has seen, Her Paper Printed and Pub∣lish'd
by His Majesty, I cannot think he would
have been so incredulous as to have made that doubt.
It may be allow'd him to suspect a Stranger of For∣gery;
but with what face can this Son of the Church
of <HI>England</HI> suspect the Integrity of his King? In the
mean time, observe what an excellent Voucher he
has got of this dead Bishop, and what an excellent
Argument he has drawn from him. Because he
would not believe what he did not think she said, we
must not believe what he know the did say. Let
our Author therefore come out of his Mists and
Ambiguities, or give us some better Authority for
his unreasonable Doubts: For, at this rate, if it be
already suspected, whether what she writes be Mat∣ter
of Fact, and indeed, whether she writ it at all;
it may be doubted hereafter, whether she chang'd,
and perhaps, whether there were ever such a Woman.</P>
<P>After he had thus begun, That <HI>this Paper was
said to be written by a Great Lady, for the satisfacti∣on
of her Friends;</HI> he shuffles in commodious Words
for an Answerer, and which afford him Elbow-room:
For he talks of the Reasons and Motives which she
had, for her leaving the Communion of the Church
of <HI>England, &amp;c.</HI> and of the Right which all Readers
<PB N="90" REF="50"/>
have to judge of the strength of them. Now, as
Luck will have it, none of those Motives and Rea∣sons
are to be found in the Paper of her Highness:
She expresses her self clearly to write for the Satis∣faction
of her Friends, not as to the Reasons she
had her self for changing, but as to the Censures
which she might expect from them for so doing:
and her whole Paper shews this was only her De∣sign.
So that, against the Law of all Romances, he
first builds the Enchanted Castle, and then sets up
to be the Doughty Knight who conquers it. It
seems he found, that a bare Denial, which is the
proper Answer to Matter of Fact, was a dry Busi∣ness,
and would make no sport; and therefore he
would be sure to cut himself our sufficient Work.
But it is not every Mans Talent to force a Trade;
for a Customer may chuse whether he will buy or
not.</P>
<P>This Great Person chang'd not lightly, nor in
haste; but after all the Endeavours which could be
us'd, by a Soul which was true to it self, and to its
Eternal Interest. She was sensible, as I before hint∣ed,
that she should lose her Friends and Credit, and
what to her Condition at that time was more sharp∣ly
piercing, expose the Catholics of <HI>England</HI> to the
danger of suffering for her sake. On these Consi∣derations
she makes a plain Relation of all the Pas∣sages
in her Change; and expecting severe Censures
from the World, took care to satisfie her Friends
concerning it. As for the Reasons of it, they were
only betwixt God and her own Soul, and the Priest
with whom she spoke at last. What a wonderful
Art has this Gentleman, to turn a bare Narrative
into Motives and Inducements? When he is arriv'd
<PB N="91" REF="50"/>
to the Perfection of calling down a Saint from Hea∣ven,
he may examine her concerning them; in the
mean time he must be content with the Relation
which she has left behind her here on Earth; and if
he will needs be mistaking her Scruples for her Mo∣tives,
who can help it?</P>
<P>His Design, as he tells us a little after the begin∣ning,
<HI>is to vindicate the Honour of the Church of</HI>
England, <HI>so far as it may be thought to suffer by the
Paper of her late Highness.</HI> I might here tell him,
that he has on Obligation antecedent to the Honour
of his Community, which is that to God and his
own Conscience. But the Honour of the Church of
<HI>England</HI> is no farther concern'd in the Paper of her
Highness, than in relation to the Persons of two
or there Prelates; and those he leaves at last to shift
for themselves as they are able, with this melancho∣ly
Farewell, That <HI>God be thanked, the Cause of our
Church do's not depend upon the singular Opinion of
one or two Bishops in it, wherein they apparently re∣cede
from the establish'd Doctrine of it.</HI></P>
<P><HI>In the next place,</HI> he is sensible how nice and ten∣der
a thing it is to meddle in a Matter wherein the
Memory of so Great a Lady is concern'd.</P>
<P>Here he is sensible, once for all; for after this one
Civility, you hear no more of his Good Manners
to the end of the Chapter; but the Honour of the
Church of <HI>England</HI> so wholly takes up his thoughts,
that he forgets the Respect which is due to her Sex,
her Quality, her Memory, her Relations, and con∣futes
her as coursly as the Parson did <HI>Bellarmine.</HI></P>
<P>He go's on to inform us, how hard a Task he has
undertaken in answering these Papers, <HI>wherein such
Circumstances are mention'd as cannot fully be clear'd,
<PB N="92" REF="51"/>
the Parties themselves having been many years dead;
yet he shall endeavour to keep within due Bounds, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>These due Bounds either are, or ought to be, Re∣spect
to the Great Lady, and Caution in regard of
Circumstances, which I hope he will not put upon
his Readers for Arguments, the Parties being dead
so long ago.</P>
<P>But let the Reader here take notice, that in this
very Place he is clapping his Cups together, and
shuffling his Balls from Hand to Hand, to lay the
Foundation of his Jugling, and to prepare the way
for all the Tricks which he is to play hereafter.</P>
<P>For the Parties being dead long since, that is, the
Duchess, in the first place, not being alive to justifie
the several Conferences which she had with the Bi∣shops;
not they, in the second, to answer as in the
sight of God, whether she had such Discourse with
them, the Field is open for him, as he vainly ima∣gines,
by laying Circumstances of Time and Place
together, and racking her own Paper till it seem∣ingly
speaks against her, to render it suspected to
his good Friends the Rabble, that she has falsified the
whole Matter.</P>
<P>Well, we shall see what he builds upon this Foun∣dation:
Let him speak for himself.</P>
<P>The way of her Satisfaction was very extraordinary;
for towards the Conclusion she confesses she was not
able, nor would she enter into Disputes with any body.</P>
<P>Commend me to him for a Man of quick dispatch.
At the first dash he is bringing the two Ends of her
Paper together; for he says, <HI>Towards the Conclusion
she confesses.</HI> 'Twas well search'd of him, however,
to hunt counter, and run to the End of her Discourse
for the Beginning of his own. He will lose no Ad∣vantages,
<PB N="93" REF="51"/>
I warrant him. Press that home, Doctor.
She modestly owns, that she was neither able nor
willing to enter into Disputes; therefore she had no
other way to satisfie her self: When the whole drift
of this Pious and sincere Discourse is to inform her
Friends of the Methods by which God Almighty
brought her into his Church; her Paper being a
plain and short History of her Conversion.</P>
<P>The Answerer is of Opinion, there is nothing to
be done, no satisfaction to be had in Matters of Re∣ligion
without Dispute; that's his only Receipt, his
<HI>Nostrum</HI> for attaining a true belief. But Doctors dif∣fer
in this Point. For another<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Sir.</HI> Her. Wootton.</NOTE> Witty Gentleman of
his Church desir'd no other Epitaph upon his Tomb
than this; <HI>Here lies the Author of this Sentence,</HI>
Disputandi pruritus, scabies Ecclesiae— <HI>The itch of
Disputation is the Scab or Tetter of the Church.</HI>
Now if the Learned avail themselves so little of Dis∣pute,
that it is as rare as a Prodigie for one of them
to convince another, what shall become of the Ig∣norant,
when they are to deal with those fencers
of Divinity? Who can hit them in Tierce and
Quart at pleasure, while they are ignorant how to
stand upon their guard. And yet such poor Peo∣ple
have Souls to save as precious in the sight of
God as the grim <HI>Logicians.</HI> Must they be damn∣ed
unless they can make a regular approach to
Heaven, in Mood and Figure? Is there no entring
there without a Sillogism? or Ergoteering it with
a <HI>nego, concedo, &amp; distinguo?</HI> The best on't is,
Our Saviours Disciples were but poor Fishermen,
and we read but of one of his Apostles who was
bred up at the Feet of <HI>Gamaliel.</HI> I would be∣seech
our Answerer to consider whether he has ar∣gued.
<PB N="94" REF="52"/>
upon his own Principles, in affirming, that
none can be satisfied as to the grounds of leaving
one Church and going to the other without entring
into Dispute? Has he not allow'd, that every Man
is to Interpret the Scripture for himself, in reference
to his own Salvation? With what Face then can he
positively say, <HI>That this Lady,</HI> who had not only
read the Scriptures, but found them in her Judg∣ment
plainly to decide the great Controversie be∣twixt
Catholics and Protestants, <HI>might not leave his
Church, and enter into that of Christ, by Interpre∣ting</HI>
this is my Body, <HI>in the Litteral and Obvious
meaning?</HI> If from a Catholic she had become a Pro∣testant
by expounding those Words in a Figurative
Sense, he would have applauded her for not discern∣ing
the Lords Body, and said she was in the right
to interpret for her self. But she, it seems, must be
an exception to his General Rule, and not have
that priviledge allow'd her which he dare not deny
to any Sectary of the Nonconformists. The Phana∣tics
think the Scripture is clear in all Matters of Sal∣vation,
and if so, what need, say they, of those
Spiritual Directours? Even the Pillars of the
Church by Law establish'd, from their own Concessi∣ons
are found to be but broken Staffs: For after all
their undertaking to heal a wounded Conscience,
when the Arrows of the Almighty are stuck into it,
they leave their Proselytes finally to the Scripture;
as our Physicians, when they have emptied the
Pockets of their Patients without curing them, send
them at last to <HI>Tunbridge Waters,</HI> or the Air of
<HI>Montpelliers.</HI></P>
<P>But if Persons be resolv'd before hand what to do,
<HI>says our Answerer,</HI> there is no such way as to declare
they will not enter into Dispute.</P>
<P><PB N="95" REF="52"/>
Here he would make us believe, that she swal∣low'd
a new Religion without chewing it, because
she Disputed not, I have shew'd already what is the
common fate of Disputation: But had she no other
way of satisfying her Conscience? (as he immedi∣ately
infers she had not.) If he were not obstinate∣ly
blind, or rather had not an intention to blind his
Reader, he might have observ'd the Methods and
Gradations of her change, and that tho' she Dispu∣ted
not; yet she Discoursed (which is entring into
Matter of Dispute) with some of the ablest of the
<HI>English</HI> Clergy, even with him particularly who
was left by the Bishop of <HI>Winchester</HI> to be her Spi∣ritual
Directour; by which it plainly appears, not∣withstanding
all the jugglings and glosses of our
Answerer, that the better part even of his own Pre∣scription
was put in practice by her, though with∣out
effect, as to her satisfaction. Why then do's
he ask so many idle Questions? <HI>Had she no Divines
of the Church of</HI> England <HI>about her? none able and
willing to afford her their utmost assistance,</HI> when she
takes care to inform the World, that she had
such Divines, that she imparted her Scruples, and
after all, remain'd unsatisfied with their Answers.</P>
<P>Persons of Learning, <HI>indeed he says,</HI> may possibly
be satisfied without entring into Disputes of Matters
which she had neither the leisure to examine, nor the
capacity to judge of.</P>
<P>Then as I said before, the Kingdom of Heaven is
chiefly, if not only for the Wise and Learned of this
World, though our Saviour was not of this Judg∣ment.
But is not every Man to be satisfied <HI>pro
modulo suo?</HI> according to the measure of his own
Understanding? Can an ignorant Person enter into
<PB N="96" REF="53"/>
the Knowledge of the Mysteries of our Faith, when
even the most Learned cannot understand them?
Can the Answerer himself unriddle the secrets of the
Incarnation, fadom the undivided Trinity? Or the
Consubstantiality of the Eternal Son with all his
Readings and Examinations? From whence comes
it then that he believes them? since neither the
Scripture is plain about them, nor the Wit of
Man can comprehend them? As for her comparing
the Doctrines of both Churches, no question she did
it to the best of her Ability; for if he will believe
her in any thing, she both read the Scriptures, and
conferr'd with the most Learned Protestants before
she had any Discourses with a Catholic Priest: But
if she had not, as he rudely says, the capacity of
judging in deep Controversies, 'tis very probable she
might want that of understanding the instructions of
her Guides: For if I may similize in my turn, a dull
fellow might ask the meaning of a Problem in Eu∣clide
from the Bishop of <HI>Salisbury,</HI> without being
ever the better for his Learned Solution of it: So
then, her Capacity will break no squares, at least
from the Doctrine of the English Church, and the
Presbyterians, put them both together as they now
stand united; for either the Scriptures are clear, and
then a mean Capacity will serve to understand them,
or though they are never so obscure, yet the upshot
of all is that every Man is to Interpret for himself.</P>
<P>What farther quarrel he can have against the La∣dy
in this particular I know not, unless it be upon
the Bishop of <HI>Winchesters</HI> account; namely, That
she refus'd to advise with him, and admitted the
two others to a Conference, and what reason she
had for so doing, if I were as penetrating as my
<PB N="97" REF="53"/>
Author I should undertake to demonstrate by the In∣fallible
Evidence of Circumstances and Inferences;
but since the parties are dead, and so long since, I
will not give my own Opinion why she refus'd
him, and of what Principles she might possibly have
thought him: At present I will not trouble my self
farther with that Prelate of rich Memory, whom I
warrant you our Author would not commend so
much for his great Abilities and willingness to re∣solve
the Ladies doubts, if he had not some Journey∣work
for him to do hereafter: neither will I meddle
much with the long Impertinent Story of his Letter
to the Duchess, and her silence at <HI>Farnham,</HI> where
she would not consult him in any of her doubts:
Whatever great matters are made of these by our
Answerer, she had a very sufficient reason for not ask∣ing
his Advice, as will instantly be made appear:
but now our Author is at another of his dodging
tricks, comparing Times and Dates of Letters, the
Bishops bearing Date the Twenty fourth of <HI>Ianuary,</HI>
that very Year in which she chang'd; but that he
may not puzzle himself too much in reckoning, I
will unriddle the Matter of Fact to him, which I
have from a most Authentic Hand; the Duke and
Duchess were at <HI>Farnham</HI> in the beginning of <HI>Sep∣tember,</HI>
where they continued about three Days, in
the Year 1670. Her Highnesses Paper bears Date
the Twentieth of <HI>August</HI> 1670. by which it is ma∣nifest,
that it was written twelve or fourteen Days
before her visit to the Bishop. Now where, I be∣seech
your, is the wonder, that she spoke nothing to
him concerning any points of a Religion in which
she was already satisfied? Wou'd any Man ask ano∣ther
what's a Clock, after he had been just looking
<PB N="98" REF="54"/>
upon a Sun-dial? So that all his aggravations,
dwindle at length into this poor inference, that it is
evident she did not make use of the ordinary means
for her own Satisfaction; at least (mark how he
mollifies for fear of being trap'd) as to those Bishops
who had known her longest.</P>
<P>Now this is so pitiful, that is requires no Answer:
for it amounts to no more than that she lik'd not the
Bishop, and therefore, from the begining conceal'd
her Scruples from him; and she chang'd her Religion
the same Year (tho' before he writ to her) because
she was satisfied of another; but do's it follow from
hence, as he infers, that in the mean while she did
not use the ordinary means for her satisfaction? sup∣posing
she had lik'd the other two Bishops, as little as
she did him, had she no other ordinary means but by
those two, or even by any other Bishops? Satisfied, to
be sure, she was, or she had not chang'd; and if the
means had been wholly extraordinary from the In∣spirations
of Gods Holy Spirit only, she had there∣by
receiv'd the greater favour; but not omitting to
give God thanks for his Supernatural Assistance,
she us'd also, the ordinary means.</P>
<P>It appears that her first Emotions were from her
observing the Devotions of the Catholics in <HI>France</HI>
and <HI>Flanders,</HI> and this is no news to any Traveller;
ask even our Protestant Gentlemen at their return
from Catholic Countries, and they cannot but con∣fess,
that the Exercises of their Devotion, their Mor∣tifications,
their Austerities, their Humility, their
Charity, and in short, all the ways of good living are
practis'd there in a for greater measure than they are
in <HI>England:</HI> But these are the Vertues from which
we are blessedly reform'd by the Example and Precept
<PB N="99" REF="54"/>
of that Lean, Mortified Apostle, St. <HI>Martin Luther.</HI></P>
<P>Her first Scruples were rais'd in her by reading
Doctor <HI>Heylins</HI> History of the Reformation, and
what she found in it we shall see hereafter; it ap∣pears,
that History had given her some new appre∣hensions,
and to satisfie them, she consider'd of the
Matters in difference betwixt the Catholics and Pro∣testants,
and so considered them as to examine
them the best she could by Scripture, which she
found to speak clearly for the Catholics, and she up∣on
our Authors Principles, was Judge of this: after
which she spoke with two of the best Bishops in
<HI>England,</HI> and their doubtful, or rather favourable
Answers did but add more to the desire she had to be
a Catholic: All these ordinary ways she took, before
she could persuade her self to send for a Priest, whose
endeavours it pleas'd the Almighty so to bless that she
was reconcil'd to his Church, and her troubled Con∣science
was immediately at rest.</P>
<P>I have been forc'd to recapitulate these things,
and to give them the Reader at one view; for our
Answerer is so cunning at this Trade, that he shews
them only in Parcels and by Retail, that it might
not be thought she us'd the ordinary Means. One
thing I had omitted, which was, that the Bishop
affirms in his letter to her Highness, that she had
made him a Promise, in case any Writing were put
into her Hand by those of the <HI>Roman</HI> Church, she
would send it either to him, or the Bishop of <HI>Oxford.</HI></P>
<P>Why do's our Author put down that Promise
thus at large? If he means any thing more by it,
besides a Justification of his Bishop for having done
his part, which signifies just nothing, he would ta∣citely
insinuate, that she broke he Word, by not
<PB N="100" REF="55"/>
sending any such Writing to him. If so, he is at
his Legerdemain again. He would have it thought,
she kept not her Promise, but do's not positively af∣firm
it: But since it is manfsest, by the order of time
in her Paper, that she neither sent for any Priest,
nor conferr'd with any Learn'd Catholic, till after
she had done with the two Bishops, it may, and
ought to be suppos'd, that she receiv'd no Writings
from any of that Religion; for if she had she would
certainly have mention'd them.</P>
<P>If then the Bishop of <HI>Winchester</HI> would insinuate,
that she had such Papers, which she sent not to him,
according to her Engagement, I may at least answer
with my Author, That the Lady was dead long be∣fore
the Bishop publish'd his Letter, so that the Cir∣cumstances
therein mention'd cannot be so fully
clear'd.</P>
<P><HI>But to return to our Answerer: He has brought
us at length to the several Discourses which her
Highness had with the two Bishops, his Grace of</HI>
Canterbury, <HI>and the Bishop of</HI> Worcester; <HI>and since he
has thought fit to put all that concern'd this Matter
into one long Paragraph, quoted from the Duchess,
I must follow his Example. These are her Words.</HI>
After this, I spoke severally to two of the best Bishops
we have in <HI>England,</HI> who both told me, there were
many things in the <HI>Roman</HI> Church which it were very
much to be wish'd we had kept; as Confession, which
was no doubt commanded of God; that Praying for the
Dead was one of the ancient things in Christianity;
that for their parts, they did it daily, tho' they would
not own it: And afterwards pressing one of them very
much upon the other Points, he told me, That if he
had been bred a Catholic, he would not change his Re∣ligion;
<PB N="101" REF="55"/>
but that being of another Church, wherein he
was sure were all things necessary to Salvation, he
thought it very ill to give that Scandal, as to leave
that Church wherein he had receiv'd his Baptism. All
these Discourses did but add more to the desire I had to
be a Catholic, and gave me the most terrible Agonies
in the world, &amp;c,</P>
<P><HI>This,</HI> he confesses, <HI>seems to be to the purpose.</HI>
And where he confesses the least Advantage on our
side, the Reader may swear there is somewhat more
than ordinary in the matter: But he retrenches im∣mediately,
and kicks down the Pail, by adding this
Restriction, <HI>If there were not some Circumstances
and Expressions very much mistaken in the Representa∣tion
of it.</HI> Yet in the next Line again, as if he
were asham'd of his own fearfulness, he is for ma∣king
a bold Sally, and putting all to the push: For,
<HI>supposing the utmost to be allow'd,</HI> says he <HI>there could
be no Argument from hence drawn for leaving the
Communion of our Church:</HI> But he restrains that too
with this Caution, <HI>If the Bishops Authority and
Example did signifie any thing with her.</HI>
Thus from yielding at first he comes to modifie his Concession,
and from thence to strike out magnanimously.</P>
<P>But then he retreats again with another (<HI>if.</HI>) 'Tis
a sign he is uneasie, when he tosses and turns so
often in a Breath; and that he is diffident of his
Cause, when he shifts his Plea. 'Tis evident that
the Duchess laid a great stress on these Concessions;
and well she might: for what a startle would it
give to a doubting Soul, which already had taken
the Alarm, to hear two Bishops, whereof one was
Primate of All <HI>England,</HI> renouncing and condemn∣ing
two of the establish'd Articles of their Church?
<PB N="102" REF="56"/>
But 'tis well known, that those two Prelates were
not, nor, if they were now living, would be the on∣ly
Clergy-men of the Church of <HI>England</HI> who are
of opinion they have over-reform'd themselves, in
casting off Prayers for the Dead, and consequently,
the Doctrine of a Third Place: But these are Church
of <HI>England</HI> Men of the old stamp, betwixt whom,
and the Faction of this Answerer, there is just as
much difference, as betwixt a true Episcopal Man,
and a <HI>Latitudinarian:</HI> and this latter, in plain terms,
is no otherwise different from a <HI>Presbyterian,</HI> then
<HI>by whatsoever Titles and Dignities he is distinguish'd.</HI>
So that our Answerer was much in the right, to
skip over the first half of this Paragraph without an∣swering
in this place, and to gallop to the last Sen∣tence
of it, which begins with Bishop <HI>Blandford</HI>'s
saying That <HI>if he had been bred in the communion of
the</HI> Roman <HI>Church, he would not change his Religion:</HI>
Whither, as in Duty bound, I follow him.</P>
<P>To over-ballance the weight of these Concessions,
our Author would have us think, that the subsequent
Words of the Bishop ought to have had greater force
to have kept her in the Communion of the Prote∣stant
Church, than the former to have drawn her
from it; for the Bishop comes off with this Excuse,
<HI>That being of another Church, wherein he was sure
were all things necessary to Salvation, he thought it
very ill to give that Scandal, as to leave that Church
wherein he receiv'd his Baptism.</HI></P>
<P>First, take notice, That the Duchess says, the Bi∣shop
was pressed by her very much, before he made
the Concession; That if he had been bred a Catho∣lic,
he would not have chang'd: which shews, that
a Truth was forc'd out of him, which he would
<PB N="103" REF="56"/>
willingly have conceal'd. For, both in regard to his
own Credit, and the retaining of so Great a Person
in his Church, it was not his Interest to have yield∣ed
that a Catholic might be saved, at least on as easie
Terms as Protestant. But he goes farther, when he
confesses, That if he had been bred a Catholic, he
would not have alter'd his Religion: For therein he
seems even to regret his being bred a Protestant;
at least he yields, that all things necessary to Salva∣tion
were in the <HI>Roman</HI> Catholic Church; for other∣wise,
had he been educated in it, he ought in con∣science
to have chang'd, which he owns he would
not have done. Now this is manifestly more than
what he said for the Church of <HI>England;</HI> for his fol∣lowing
Words are rather an Excuse for his Continu∣ance
in his Church, than Argument to dissuade
her Highness from turning Catholic. He thought
it very ill to give that Scandal to leave the Church,
wherein he was Baptiz'd. Now the Word <HI>Scandal</HI>
plainly relates to his own Person, and signifies no
more, than that he was asham'd to change: For it
was impossible for him to think he should sin against
his Conscience in changing, who had declar'd, That
he would not have chang'd, in case he had been
bred a Catholic. And the Reason he gives is made
of the same yielding Metal, (<HI>viz.</HI>) That he had his
Baptism in the Protestant Church; for that Argu∣ment
in it self is of no weight, since the Right Re∣verend
well knew, that the Baptism even of Heretics
is good; so that if he had been Christn'd in the
<HI>Lutheran,</HI> the <HI>Abyssine,</HI> or the <HI>Russian</HI> Church, he
must for that reason have continu'd in it: But he
timerously pleads his fear of giving Scandal; which
is, as I said, no Justification of himself, no Dissua∣sive
<PB N="104" REF="57"/>
to Her, but only a mean, interessed Apology for
his not changing.</P>
<P>As for his intimating, That all things necessary
to Salvation were to be had in the Church of <HI>Eng∣land,</HI>
let any reasonable Man be Judge, whether he
could possibly have said less in defence of himself,
for continuing in it: For this only shew'd, that he
thought Salvation was to be had in both Churches,
as even this Author himself is forc'd to confess af∣terwards,
in these words: <HI>The utmost that can be
made of this, is, That a certain Bishop of our Church</HI>
(who in the mean time has prov'd himself an un∣certain
one) <HI>held both Churches so far Parts of the
Catholic Church, that there was no necessity of going
from one Church to another.</HI></P>
<P>That which he calls the utmost we can make of
it, is in truth the least which the Bishop's Words
will naturally bear; and I may safely put the Cause
upon this Issue, Whether such a Discourse might not
reasonably add more to the desire she had to be a
Catholic?</P>
<P>Let us hear now what he has to answer; and I
will reply briefly, because I have taken away the
Strength of his Argument already.</P>
<P>First, He says in effect, That the Bishops Autho∣rity
and Example ought to have prevail'd with her
on the one side, more than his Concessions on the
other.</P>
<P>I reply; Not his Authority, because he spoke
more for the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> than against it: Nor
his Example; for he gave her no encouragement to
follow it, by saying, That if he had been bred a
Catholic, he would not have chang'd. His Exam∣ple
of Praying daily for the Dead, shew'd his Opi∣nion
<PB N="105" REF="57"/>
at the bottom; but his not publicly owning that
he did so, has prov'd him little better than a Black Bi∣shop,
who was enter'd privately into the White ones
Walk.</P>
<P>Our Author asks in the second place, Why any
Person should forsake the Communion of the Prote∣stant
Church, wherein the Bishop affirm'd were all
things necessary to Salvation? And I enquire, How
she could be bound to believe him, since Confession,
and Prayers for the Dead are wanting in it; one of
which he had before acknowledg'd to be command∣ed
of God; the other, to be one of the ancient things
in Christianity?</P>
<P>Thirdly, He urges, That the Bishop had told her
it was an ill thing to leave the Church of <HI>England.</HI>
And I reply, That the Answerer has falsified his
Words. <HI>The Bishop only thought it very ill to give
that Scandal, as to leave the Church wherein he was
Baptiz'd.</HI> First, he spoke of himself only, not of
her. Mark that Fallacy. And then he said not, It
was ill to leave the Church; but, very ill to give
that Scandal, as to leave the Church; relating again
to his own particular.</P>
<P>Fourthly, He says, 'Tis evident that the Bishops
Concessions could have no influence upon her (tho'
she positively says, those Discourses, in which were
those Concessions, did but add more to the desire
she had to be a Catholic.) This is full upon the Vi∣zor;
but the Dead are to take all things patiently.
Well! How if he can convince her of Falsity from
her own Words? Why, then he will carry his Argu∣ment,
as well as his Good Manners, to the height;
and how broad soever the Word may be which he
has slily given her, yet he will tell you, That Free∣dom
<PB N="106" REF="58"/>
ought to be permitted him, as sustaining the Ho∣nour
of the Church of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P><HI>His Argument is this:</HI> She declares afterwards,
That she would not have chang'd, if she had thought
it possible otherwise to have saved her Soul: But the
Bishop had told her, That all things necessary for Sal∣vation
were in the <HI>English</HI> Church: Therefore the Bi∣shop
contributed nothing to her Change.</P>
<P>So the Miter be safe in its Reputation, no matter
what becomes of the Ducal Coronet. Now I can
be very well content that the Bishop should have no
part in the Honour of her Conversion; for, 'tis plain,
that he desir'd it not: and why should he do good
against his will?</P>
<P>I wish my Author would have furnish'd me with
an Argument to have brought him wholly off; but
I will bring him on his way as far as by the help of
the Answerer's Scarf I can fairly drag him. I say
therefore, That tho' her Highness chang'd not her
Belief upon the Concessions of the Bishop, yet his
Concessions were an occasion of her farther Scruples,
in order to her Change: For, she says, <HI>they added
to the desire she had to be a Catholic.</HI></P>
<P>The Bishop did indeed tell her, That all things
necessary to Salvation were in the <HI>English</HI> Church;
but tell me, Sir, I beseech you, was that all he told
her? By your favour, you have left out the better
half of what he said: for he told her also, That <HI>if he
had been bred a Catholic, he would not have chang'd.</HI>
And she had reason to believe what he said to the ad∣vantage
of a Church of which he was no Member,
as being sure he would say no more than scanty
Truth. And he acknowledges into the Bargain,
That <HI>Confession was commanded of God;</HI> and, that
<PB N="107" REF="58"/>
<HI>Praying for the Dead was one of the ancient things
in Christianity.</HI> What a shameful way of arguing is
this, to make a general Negative Conclusion from
half the Premises? Or, in other Words, to maintain
that the Bishops Concessions could have no influence
upon her, because they had not the greatest influence?
And you in a manner confess it before you were
aware, in the close of your Argument, where you
say, <HI>There must therefore have been some more secret
Reason, which increas'd her desire to be a Catholic af∣ter
these Discourses.</HI> Now some more secret Reason
do's not hinder the Bishops Concessions from being
one; nay, it argues, that they were one of the
Reasons, though not the most prevalent, because
there was one more secret. You have now contra∣dicted
your self so plainly, that you have wholly
justified the Duchess, and the broad Word, without
naming it, is fairly brought back to your own door.</P>
<P>After this, our Answerer do's but piddle, and play
at small Game, as if her Highness might possibly
take encouragement from the Bishop's calling the
Church of <HI>Rome</HI> the Catholic Religion: But she was
too much in earnest to lay hold upon a Word. Nei∣ther
is more advantage to be taken from his calling
the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> the Catholic Religion, than we
receive disadvantage from the playing upon the
Word of <HI>Roman Catholic.</HI></P>
<P>Next, for want of a Quarrel, he is falling on his
late dear Friend the Bishop: <HI>Was he,</HI> says our An∣swerer,
<HI>so weak, to mean the Word</HI> Catholic <HI>in the
strictest sense, he must then have contradicted himself,
there was an inconsistency in his Words,</HI> and so forth.</P>
<P>From the inconsistency of the Bishop's Words, in
this and other Places, our Answerer, perhaps, would
<PB N="108" REF="59"/>
make a secret Inference, That he never said them;
and obliquely draw the Duchess into the Statute of
Coining: So that the two Spiritual Hectors may
make a Sham-duel of it, for ought we know. For
'tis a common trick with Robbers to clash their
Swords together in the dark, to draw Company to∣gether,
and then some third Person pays for it. Take
it in this manner, and then the Argument against
her Highness will stand thus: The Sayings which
she relates are inconsistent, and therefore she must
not be believ'd, though she affirms she heard them.
Why, do not as many as have Ears hear inconsistent
things said every day? and must every body needs
lie who reports them again? That Inconsistency of
the Words is, in truth, an Argument that the things
were said: For what bids fairer for adding to the
desire she had of being a Catholic, and of giving her
the terrible Agonies she felt? But after all, if the
Answerer's Quarrel be in earnest with the Bishop, 'tis
pity they should fall out for such a Trifle: As weak
as the Bishop was, and as strong as our Answerer
makes his Inconsistencies appear, I dare answer for
him, he meant nothing less than to convert her.</P>
<P>You do ill therefore to play the Bully with a
peaceable Old Gentleman, who only desir'd to pos∣sess
his Conscience and his Bishopric in peace, with∣out
offence to any Man, either of the Catholic Church,
or that of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>But if he held, that both Churches were so far
Parts of the Catholic, that there was no necessity of
going from one Church to another to be sav'd if he
asserted that you say, he must overthrow the Neces∣sity
of your Reformation; and then down go's his
Belief of your Homilies and Articles (Thirty nine
<PB N="109" REF="59"/>
at a Tip), and consequently he could be no true
Member of the Church of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>And now what can I do more for the poor Bishop?
For most certainly he did imply thus much in saying,
That <HI>if he had been bred a Catholic, he would not
change his Religion.</HI> Therefore, Take him <HI>Topham;</HI>
there's no help, but he must be turn'd out of the
Church of <HI>England,</HI> even so long after he has been dead.</P>
<P>In the mean time, let us a little examine this Pro∣position.
Our Answerer affirms, <HI>That he cannot be
a true Member of the Church of</HI> England, <HI>who asserts
both Churches to be so far Parts of the Catholic Church,
that there is no necessity of going from one Church to
another to be sav'd.</HI> If this be true, then, to be a
Member of the Church of <HI>England,</HI> one must as∣sert,
That either both Churches are not Parts of the
Catholic, or, That they are so Parts, that there is
a necessity of going from one to another. Of these
two, the first is not for the Honour of one of the
Churches, and the second is direct Nonsence. A Ne∣cessity
of Change consists not with their being both
Parts; for Parts constitute one Whole, and leave
not one and another, to go to or from. There
is no Church in <HI>France</HI> or <HI>Italy,</HI> to which a <HI>Spanish</HI>
Catholic can go, but what he left in <HI>Spain;</HI> nor can
he leave his own, by going to either of them. He
may be under other Governours in the same Church;
but let him go wheresoever he shall please, he can∣not
be of another, so long as he remains a Catholic.
In short, Necessity of Change makes it absolutely
impossible for both Churches to be Parts of the Ca∣tholic,
and forces the Church of <HI>England</HI> to main∣tain,
either that she is a Part, and the <HI>Roman</HI> Catho∣lic
none; or else, that 'tis no matter whether she be a
<PB N="110" REF="60"/>
Part or no; to which, I wish, they may not, with the
Pretence of Zeal for her Honour, desire to drive her,
who have nothing better to say in their own behalf.</P>
<P>But though our Answerer has laid one Bishop slat,
I warrant you he has another in reserve: For now
the Bishop of <HI>Winchester</HI> (who, as I said formerly,
was not commended so much for nothing) is brought
back in Triumph from his Palace of <HI>Farnham,</HI> to
make a short end of the Dispute. At first he doubts,
whether ever there were any such Bishops who made
such Answers; and then affirms, that he believes
there never was <HI>in rerum naturâ</HI> such a Discourse as is
pretended to have been betwixt this Great Person,
and two of the most Learned Bishops in <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>This is downright indeed; for our Answerer, to
do him Justice, has <HI>often</HI> collaterally accus'd the Du∣chess
for her good Invention at making Stories: but
here is plain <HI>English</HI> upon the Point. What pity is
it in the mean time, that my Lord of <HI>Winton</HI> gives
not so much as one single Reason either for his
Doubt, or his contrary Belief? So that having only his
Lordship's <HI>Opinion,</HI> and her Highness's Affirmation
before me, I might say, with at least as much Good
Manners as that Prelate, That I believe as little of
his pretended Letter sent to the Duchess so long af∣ter
her Decease, as he do's of her pretended Discourse
with the two Bishops.</P>
<P>In the mean time, what use would my Gentle∣man
here make of his Lordships doubts, his belief,
or his affirmation? Are the Embers too hot for him,
that he uses the Bishops Foot to pull out the Ches∣nut?
Suppose our Prelate had believ'd there were no
Antiphodes, is this a time of Day to give him cre∣dit?
But I wonder the less, why our Author attri∣butes
<PB N="111" REF="60"/>
so much to his <HI>ipse dixit</HI> upon all occasions;
for the whole body of his Answer, to this Paper, is in
effect a Transcript from the Bishops Preface: He
purloyns his Arguments, without altering, some∣time,
so much as the property of his words. He has
quoted him five times only in the Margent, and
ought to have quoted him in almost every line of
his Pamphlet. In short, if the Master had not eaten,
the Man (saving Reverence) could not have vomited.
But it is easie to be seen through all the grimaces of
that Bishop, that he found himself aggriev'd, he has
not thought on, when her Highness spoke of the
two best, or most Learned Bishops of <HI>England;</HI> and
that his Opinion was not consulted, when, indeed,
he had offer'd it, though unask'd.</P>
<P>I know his Defender will reply, That his Lord∣ship
has modestly disclaim'd any such Pretence to
Learning, in his Preface, where he says, <HI>No, I am
not, I know I am not, I am sure I am not the most
Learned Bishop.</HI> See how he mounts in his Expres∣sions
at three several Bounds. 'Tis true, all these
Asseverations, like his three <HI>Nolo</HI>'s, needed not; for
any reasonable Man, who had read his Works, would
have taken his bare word, without Repetition. Yet this
notwithstanding, he might have some inward grudg∣ings,
that his Pupil thought him not so great a Doctor.</P>
<P>But it is not fit that a Matter of such importance
should end in a bare <HI>Ay</HI> and <HI>No</HI> on either side; for
though the Parties have been so long dead, yet there
is a Witness still alive, and such a one, that all Loyal
Subjects are bound to joyn with me in Prayers for
the long continuance of His Life, and even for His
continuance in the True Religion, as far as the <HI>Eng∣lish</HI>
Liturgycan oblige them.</P>
<P><PB N="112" REF="61"/>
The Duchess thought her self bound to make his
Royal Highness acquainted with every one of these
several Conferences, which she had either with
Archbishop <HI>Sheldon,</HI> or Bishop <HI>Blandford,</HI> and that
account was the very same in substance with what
she communicates to her Friends in this present Pa∣per,
as he is pleas'd to permit me to assure the
World after having had the Honour to hear him so∣lemnly
affirm it which puts an end to the whole
Matter of Dispute, and this which follows is as Au∣thentic.</P>
<P>The Day it pleased Almighty God to call her
Highness to his Mercy, some Relations of hers, who
are yet living, were desirous that she should speak
with the Bishop of <HI>Worcester;</HI> which the Duchess
did not absolutely refuse upon their importunity;
but requested the then Duke to stop the Bishop a lit∣tle
in the Anti-chamber and prepare him, according
to her directions, before he enter'd the Bed-chamber:
accordingly His Highness having met the Bishop ac∣quainted
him, <HI>That she was actually reconcil'd to the
Catholic Church;</HI> he then enquir'd, <HI>Whether she
were fully satisfied in all Points of the Doctrine which
she had embrac'd,</HI> and the Duke answer'd, <HI>that she
was entirely satisfied in the Doctrine of the Catholic
Church;</HI> at length the Bishop ask'd, <HI>Whether she had
already receiv'd the last Sacraments of the Church, na∣ming
particularly those of the Blessed Eucharist, and the
Extreme Vnction;</HI> and it being reply'd by the Duke
that she had receiv'd them, the Bishop answered,
<HI>That then he doubted not but that her Soul was in a
very safe condition;</HI> before they parted, His Royal
Highness told him, <HI>That it was the desire of the Du∣chess,
he would not trouble her with any Matter of
<PB N="113" REF="61"/>
Dispute, nor offer to Pray with her, but if he had any
Spiritual Counsel fitting for a Person in her condition,
in order to prepare her for her Death, he might free∣ly
tender it;</HI> upon this he was admitted to her Bed∣chamber,
and made her a brief Exhortation; after
which, his stay there was very short.</P>
<P>This being matter of Fact, and of unquestionable
Truth, I hope the Answerer will acquiesce in it,
What he will think of his Bishop concerns not me,
but as a Protestant he has reason for his thanking
God, that the Cause of his Church do's not depend
on the singular Opinion of one Bishop in it. It ap∣pears
plainly by this Relation, that the Bishop of
<HI>Worcester</HI> was ignorant, almost to the last, of her Con∣version;
so that, if that will serve our Authors turn,
he is acquitted from intending any such Act of Cha∣rity,
but that he contributed to it without any such
intention is apparent.</P>
<P>Yet our Author will not so sit down; he will
condemn her Highness from her own words again;
and prove from her saying, <HI>that she ow'd the Blessing
of her Conversion to God Almighty,</HI> that therefore
the Bishop could have no hand in it.</P>
<P>What obligation has he to defend the Honour of
his Church by a piece of Sophistry? she ow'd it
wholly to Almighty God; <HI>for of our selves we can do
nothing:</HI> but as the Answerer confesses this excluded
not her own endeavours; God inspir'd her with a
desire of being reconcil'd to his Church, in answer
to her frequent Prayers, not by immediate illumina∣tion,
or shewing her the right belief miraculously,
but by affording her the ordinary means, and con∣ducting
her by his good Spirit in the use of them:
If she had been immediately enlightn'd she needed not
<PB N="114" REF="62"/>
to have recourse to any of the Bishops, but it pleas'd
God, who often works Good out of Evil, that the Ar∣guments
they us'd, or rather, the Answers which they
made, produc'd a contrary effect, and added more
to the desire she had to be a Catholic; in this sense,
therefore it may be said, that the Bishops sent her
to the Priest; for an unresistable, over-ruling Power,
made them contribute to her change by opposing it;
and the very hands which labour'd to hold her fast
in the Protestant Perswasion, carried her half Seas
over, and put her into other Hands, which carried
her the other half. Truly they would have receiv'd
hard measure, if they had been found guilty on the
Statute of Perswasion, who far from endeavou∣ring
to make her change, disswaded her from chang∣ing,
tho' the Protestant Flints happen'd to strike Ca∣tholic
Fire: So that I cannot but think there was an
extraordinary Hand of Providence in her Case; and
of which she had reason to be extraordinary sensible.
But we must have, I perceive, a care of Praying, and
owning benefits from God; for that, or nothing
made her pass for an Enthusiast with the Answerer:
She did nothing besides Praying, which our Author
do's not acknowledge it her duty to have done. She
read the History which was put into her Hands, to
confirm her in her first belief; she examin'd the
Scripture, she conferr'd with her Divines; and yet
he can make an obstinate Woman of her for doing
that very thing, to which he wou'd advise her.
<HI>But,</HI> says our Author, <HI>All pretenders to Enthusiasm
do as solemnly and wholly ascribe the Blessing to Al∣mighty
God, and look on it as the effect of such Prayers,
as she made to him in</HI> France <HI>and</HI> Flanders.</P>
<P>They ascribe it indeed wholly to God in our Au∣thors
<PB N="115" REF="62"/>
Sense, but not in hers; for she meant not im∣mediate
illumination by the word <HI>wholly,</HI> as I have
already prov'd; they may look on their false light,
as the effect of their Prayers, but she looks on her
Conversion as the effect of hers, after having used
the means.</P>
<P>He had thought, <HI>he says,</HI> that the pretence to a pri∣vate
Spirit, or Enthusiasm (for he joyns them both
afterwards) had not been at this time allowed in the
Church of <HI>Rome.</HI></P>
<P>Somebody once thought otherwise, or he had never
diverted the young Gallants of the Town, with his
merry Book concerning the Fanaticism of the Church
of <HI>Rome.</HI></P>
<P>He next enquires what need she had of an infalli∣ble
Church, if she owed her Change so wholly to Al∣mighty
God?</P>
<P><HI>Wholly</HI> is already explain'd to him, and then his Ar∣gument
is of no more force against her, then against
all Catholics who have once been Protestants; which
is a new Subject of Dispute, and forrein to the Argu∣gument
in hand.</P>
<P>Her Conclusion, <HI>as he tells us,</HI> is, That she would ne∣ver
have chang'd, if she could have sav'd her Soul other∣wise;
<HI>Whereupon he infers,</HI> If this were true, she had
good reason for her change; if it were not true (as most
certainly it was not) she had none.</P>
<P>But her words (which he hath falsifi'd in this place)
are these, <HI>I would never have chang'd, if I had thought it
possible to have sav'd my Soul otherwise.</HI> He never mis∣quotes
without design. Now by altering these words,
<HI>If I had thought it possible to save my Soul,</HI> into these, <HI>If
I could have sav'd my Soul,</HI> he would shuffle off her true
meaning; which was, That her Conscience oblig'd
<PB N="116" REF="63"/>
her to this change. And that's a Point he would not
willingly have touch'd: for he cannot deny upon his
own Principles, but that after having examin'd the
Scriptures, as she professes to have done as well as
she was able, concerning the Points in dispute, and
afterwards using the assistance of her Spiritual Guides,
the two Bishops, she was to judge for her self, in the
last resort; and the Judgment she made according
to her Conscience, was, That the Scripture spoke
clearly in behalf of the Catholic Church, (or Church
of <HI>Rome,</HI> as he calls it:) Therefore according to his
Principles, and her Conscience, she was to be of that
Church, of whose Truth she was thus convinc'd;
so that whether she could be otherwise sav'd or no,
was not the Proposition to be advanc'd, but whether
she thought it possible to be otherwise sav'd. And
therefore though it were true, that she could other∣wise
be sav'd, yet she had a sufficient reason for her
change▪ (though he says she had none) which was
her Conscience; and supposing that were erroneous,
yet upon his Principles she must be the Judge of it
without appeal.</P>
<P><HI>Her Scruples began upon reading</HI> Dr. Heylin<HI>'s Hi∣story
of the</HI> Reformation; <HI>and there she found such a∣bominable
Sacriledge upon</HI> Harry <HI>the Eighth</HI>'s <HI>Divorce,
King</HI> Edward<HI>'s Minority, and Queen</HI> Elizabeths <HI>Suc∣cession,
that she could not believe the Holy Ghost could
ever be in such Councils.</HI> Thus he compendiously
quotes her Paper, as being it seems asham'd of the
Particulars therein mention'd; but for once I will
follow him his own way.</P>
<P>To read Dr. <HI>Heylin</HI>'s History in order to settle her,
he confesses, was none of the best Advices given to
such a Person. He is much in the right on't, as appears
<PB N="117" REF="63"/>
by the success; and I add, nor any other, either Pro∣testant
or Catholic Writer then extant: for no Paint is
capable of making lovely the hideous Face of the pre∣tended
Reformation. <HI>But,</HI> says he, <HI>there are two di∣stinct
Parts in the History of it, the one Ecclesiastical,
the other Political; the first built on Scripture, Anti∣quity,
and the Rights of particular Churches; the other
on such Maxims as are common to Statesmen at all Times,
and in all Churches, who labour to turn all Revolutions
and Changes to their own Advantage.</HI></P>
<P>But why might not her Highness consider it her
own way, which is that of Nature, in the Causes
which produc'd it, and the Effects which it produc'd;
though I doubt not but she consider'd it his way too,
because a Child could not have mist it, that very Di∣stinction
being inserted into the History by the Au∣thor
himself. Now the immediate Cause which pro∣duc'd
the Separation of <HI>Harry</HI> the Eighth from the
Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> was the refusal of the Pope to grant
him a Divorce from his first Wife, and to gratifie his
Desires in a Dispensation for a second Marriage. Nei∣ther
the Answerer, nor I, nor any Man, can carry it
so high as the original Cause with any certainty: for
the King only knew whether it was Conscience and
Love, or Love alone, which mov'd him to sue for a
Divorce: But this we may say, that if Conscience had
any part in it, she had taken a long Nap of almost
Twenty years together before she awaken'd, and
perhaps had slept on till Doomsday, if <HI>Anne Bullen,</HI> or
some other fair Lady, had not given her a Jog; so
the satisfying of an inordinate and a brutal Passion
cannot be deny'd to have had a great share at least, in
the production of that Schism which led the very
way to our pretended <HI>Reformation:</HI> for breaking the
<PB N="118" REF="64"/>
Unity of <HI>Christ</HI>'s Church was the Foundation of it.</P>
<P>I pass over the manner of those first Proceedings,
and the Degrees by which they came to terminate in
Schism, though I doubt not but her Highness was
sufficiently scandaliz'd in both, and could not also
but observe some of the concomitant Causes, as Re∣venge,
Ambition, and Covetousness; all which, and
others, drew with a strong Biass towards it. But the
immediate Effects even of this Schism, were Sacri∣ledge,
and a bloody Persecution of such as deny'd the
King's Supremacy in Matters wholly Spiritual, which
no Layman, no King of <HI>Israel</HI> ever Exercis'd, as is
observ'd by my Lord <HI>Herbert.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Herbert Hen 8. pag. 402.</NOTE> As for the <HI>Reforma∣tion</HI>
it self, what that produc'd is full as obvious in
the Sequel of History, where we find, that Chante∣ries
and Hospitals undevour'd by <HI>Henry</HI> the Eighth,
were left only to be Morsels for <HI>Edward</HI> the Sixth,
or rather for his Ministers of State; and the Reason
was given, That the Revenues of them were fruitlesly
spent on those who said Prayers for the Dead. Now
this was as naturally produc'd from the <HI>Reformation,</HI>
as an Effect is from the Cause; so that as it is ob∣serv'd
by some, had that young King Reign'd any
considerable time longer, the Church of <HI>England</HI> had
been left the poorest of any one in Christendom; the
rich Bishoprick of <HI>Duresme</HI> having been much re∣trench'd
by him, and 'tis probable those of <HI>Rochester</HI>
and <HI>Westminster. Harry</HI> the Eighth had indeed eaten
so much of the Churches Bread out of his Son's
Mouth beforehand, that even <HI>Calvin</HI> complains of it
in a Letter to <HI>Cranmer,</HI> (concerning the paucity of
good Pastors in <HI>England</HI>) in these words: <HI>Vnum aper∣tum
obstaculum esse intelligo quod praedae expositi sunt
Ecclesiae redditus; One open obstacle I find to this,</HI> (he
<PB N="119" REF="64"/>
meaneth the increase of good Pastors) <HI>is, That your
Church Revenues are expos'd to Rapine.</HI></P>
<P>Besides these things, what an Usurpation this change
of Religion caus'd, is most notorious; that of the
Lady <HI>Iane Gray</HI> being evidently grounded on the
Testament of <HI>Edward</HI> the Sixth, by which she was
made his Successor, because she was of the Prote∣stant
Religion.</P>
<P>As for the Title of Queen <HI>Elizabeth</HI> to the Crown,
the Histories lie open, and I shall not be over forward
to meddle with the Rights of Princes, especially since
the Answerer has avoided that Dispute. 'Tis enough
in general to say, that her Interest carry'd her a∣gainst
the Pope, whose Power, if good, she was Ille∣gitimate:
She had also been inform'd by the <HI>English</HI>
Resident at <HI>Rome,</HI> that the Pope expected she shou'd
acknowledge her Crown from him, and not take up∣on
her to be Queen without his leave. These were
strong Solicitations in a new unse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> led Succession, for
her to shake off a Religion, whereof his Holiness is
Head on Earth. What matter of Conscience was in
the case, I say not, but her Temporal Interest lies
bare-fac'd and uppermost to view, in reassuming of
the Supremacy, and to make the Breach yet wider)
in subverting the Foundations of the Faith. For the
Affront is the same to turn round a mans Hat, and to
strike him on the Face; but the advantage is the
greater in a lusty Blow.</P>
<P>But the Handle by which our Answerer would
have the <HI>Reformation</HI> taken, is not by the Causes and
Effects, the Means and Management, and indeed the
whole Series of History; these are nothing to con∣cern
his present Enquiry, though they rais'd such
Scruples in the Duchess, and will do in any other
<PB N="120" REF="65"/>
conscientious Reader; he will have the <HI>Reformation</HI>
consider'd his own way, that is, in the Political part
of it, and the Ecclesiastical. Now the Political part
(if you observe him) he gives for gone at the first
dash; <HI>It was grounded</HI> (he says) <HI>on such Maxims as are
common to Statesmen at all Times, and in all Churches,
who labour to turn all Revolutions and Changes to their
own Advantage.</HI></P>
<P>That is, 'tis common for Statesmen to be Atheists
at the bottom; To be seemingly of that Religion
which is most for their Interest; To crush and ruine
that from which they have no future prospect of Ad∣vantage,
and to joyn with its most inveterate Ene∣mies,
without consideration of their King's Interest;
and this was the Case of the Duke of <HI>Somerset.</HI> All
which together amounts to this▪ That 'tis no matter
by what Means a <HI>Reformation</HI> be compass'd, by what
Instruments it be brought to pass, or with what
Design, though all these be never so ungodly, 'tis
enough if the <HI>Reformation</HI> it self be made by the Le∣gislative
Power of the Land. The matter of Fact then
is given up, only 'tis fac'd with Recriminations; That
<HI>Alexander</HI> the Sixth (for example) was as wicked a
Pope as King <HI>Henry</HI> was a King: As if any Catho∣lic
deny'd that God Almighty, for Causes best
known to his Divine Wisdom, has not sometimes
permitted impious Men to sit in that supream Seat,
and even to intrude into it by unlawful Means. That
<HI>Alexander</HI> the Sixth was one of the worst of Men, I
freely grant, which is more then I can in Conscience
say of <HI>Henry</HI> the Eighth, who had great and Kingly
Vertues mingled with his Vices. That the Duke of
<HI>Somerset</HI> rais'd his Estate out of Church Lands, our
Author excuses no other ways than by retorting▪ that
<PB N="121" REF="65"/>
Popes are accustom'd to do the like in consideration
of their Nephews, whom they would greaten.
But though 'tis a wicked thing for a Pope to mis∣pend
the Church Revenues on his Relations, 'tis to be
consider'd he is a Secular Prince, and may as law∣fully
give out of his Temporal Incomes what he
pleases to his Favourite, as another Prince to his.
But as our Author charges this Miscarriage home
upon some late Popes of the former, and the present
Age; so I hope he will exempt his present Holiness
from that Note. No Common Father of God's
Church, from St. <HI>Peter</HI> even to him, having ever
been more bountiful, in expending his Revenues for
the Defence of <HI>Christendom;</HI> or less interessed, in re∣spect
of his Relations, whom he has neither greatn'd,
nor so much as suffer'd to enter into the least Admini∣stration
of the Government.</P>
<P>But, after all, what have these Examples to do
with this Ladies Conversion? Why, our Author
pretends that these bad Popes, and their ill Proceed∣ings,
ought as reasonably to have hindred the Du∣chess
from entring into the Catholic Church, as the
like Proceedings under <HI>Henry</HI> the Eighth, <HI>Edward</HI>
the Sixth, and Queen <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> might move her
Highness to leave the Protestant.</P>
<P>The Subject in hand was the Pretended Refor∣mation;
The Duchess observ'd the scandalous and
abominable Effects of it; that an inordinate Lust
was one principal Cause of the Separation; that the
Reformation it self was begun by worldly Interests
in the Duke of <HI>Somerset,</HI> and carried on by the
Ambition of Queen <HI>Elizabeth.</HI> Have the Exam∣ples
produc'd by our Author on the contrary side
any thing to do with a Reformation? Suppose in
<PB N="122" REF="66"/>
the first place, that she had never read nor heard
any of those things concerning Pope <HI>Alexander,</HI>
or the advancing of Nephews by profusion of the
Church-Treasure; the first is very possible, and
she might interpret candidly the latter. But make
the worst of it; on the one side there was only a
Male-administration of a settled Government, from
which no State, either Spiritual or Temporal, can
always be exempt; on the other side, here is a total
Subversion of the Old Church in <HI>England,</HI> and the
setting up a New; a changing of receiv'd Doctrines,
and the Direction of God's Holy Spirit pretended for
the Change; so that she might reasonably judge,
that the Holy Ghost had little to do with the Pra∣ctices
of ill Popes, without thinking the worse of
the Establish'd Faith: but she could never see a new
one erected on the Foundations of Lust, Sacrilege,
and Usurpation, without great Scruples whether the
Spirit of God were assisting in those Councils.</P>
<P>As for his Method of Enquiry, <HI>Whether there was
not a sufficient Cause for the Reformation in the
Church? Whether the Church of</HI> England <HI>had not suf∣ficient
Authority to reform it self?</HI> and, <HI>Whether the
Proceedings of the Reformation were not justifiable by
the Rules of Scripture and the Ancient Church?</HI> I may
safely joyn Issue with him upon all three Points, and
conclude in the Negative. That there was no suffici∣ent
Cause to reform the Church in Matters of Faith,
because there neither were, nor can be, any such
Errours embrac'd and own'd by it. The Church of
<HI>England</HI> has no Authority of Reforming her self,
because the Doctrine of Christ cannot be reformed,
nor a National Synod lawfully make any Definitions
in Matters of Faith, contrary to the Judgment
<PB N="123" REF="66"/>
of the Church Universal of the present Age, shewn
in her Public Liturgies; that Judgment being equi∣valent
to that of a General Council of the present
Age. And for the third Point, The Proceedings of
the Reformation were not justifiable by the Rule of
Scripture, according to the right Interpretation of it
by the Fathers and Councils, which are the true
Judges of it; nor, consequently, by the Rules of the
Ancient Church. But <HI>Calvin</HI>'s Excuse must be your
last Refuge, <HI>Nos discessionem a toto mundo facere co∣acti
sumus: We are compell'd to forsake the Commu∣nion,
or to separate from all the Churches of the
World.</HI></P>
<P><HI>These</HI> (says our Author) <HI>She confesses were but
Scruples.</HI> According to his mannerly way of argu∣ing
with the King, I might ask him, <HI>These what?</HI>
Do's he mean, these Scruples were but Scruples? For
the Word (<HI>these</HI>) begins a Paragraph. But I am
asham'd of playing the Pedant, as he has done. I sup∣pose
he means these Passages of <HI>Heylyn</HI> only rais'd
some Scruples in her, which occasion'd her to ex∣amine
the Points in difference by the Holy Scripture.
<HI>And now</HI> (says he) <HI>she was in the right way for Sa∣tisfaction,
provided she made use of the best Helps
and Means for understanding it, and took in the Assi∣stance
of her Spiritual Guides.</HI></P>
<P>That she did take in those Guides, is manifest by
her own Papers; though both of them (the more
the Pity) did but help to mislead her into the Ene∣mies
Country: But then, for our comfort, neither
of them were true Church of <HI>England</HI> Men, though
they were both Bishops, and one of them no less than
Primate of All <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="124" REF="67"/>
And now for a relishing bit before we rise, he has
kept in store for us, the four Points, which about
the midst of her Paper, the Duchess told us, she
found so easie in the Scripture, that she wondered
she had been so long without finding them. He
will needs fall into Dispute with her about them,
tho he knows before hand, that she will not Dis∣pute
with him. This is a Kind of Petition to her,
that she will permit him to make that difficult,
which she found easie: for every thing becomes
hard by chopping Logic upon it. I am sure enough,
that the Wall before me is White, and that I can go
to it: but put me once upon unriddling Sophisms,
I shall not be satisfied of what colour the Wall is,
nor how 'tis possible for me to stir from the place in
which I am. Alas, if People would be as much in
earnest as she was, and read the Scriptures with the
same disposition, the same unprejudic'd sincerity in
their Hearts, and docility in their Understanding,
seeking to bend their Judgments to what they find,
not what they find to their Judgments, more I be∣lieve
would find things as easie as she did, and give
the Answerer more frequent occasion for his derision
of a willing mind.</P>
<P>But not to dilate on that matter, I presume he
will not pretend by his Disputing, to make any
thing plainly appear against her: If he can, let him
do it, and end Controversie in a moment; for every
one can see plain things, and all Christians must be
concluded by the Scripture. But he knows well e∣nough
there is no such thing to be perform'd. A
Mist may be raised, and interposed, through which
the Eye shall not discern what otherwise it would,
if nothing but the due medium were betwixt, and
<PB N="125" REF="67"/>
the Object before it. And that is all the fruit of this
sort of Disputation, and all the Assistance, for which
the Answerer was so earnest. Upon the whole, his
mortal quarrel to the Duchess, is that she would
not become an Experiment of the perfection to
which the Art of Learned Obscurity is improv'd in
this our Age. And the Honour he has done to the
Church of <HI>England,</HI> is, that he has us'd her Name
to countenance the Defamation of a Lady, I
suspected whether he would bring it, when I saw
that Honour pretended, in the beginning of his
Pamphlet: If he thinks his Bishops have reflected a
Scandal on his Church by their Discourses with the
Duchess, he ought to have proceeded a more reaso∣nable
way, than to insinuate that she forg'd them,
without proving it. If she had been living, and he
had subscrib'd his Name to so infamous a Libell, he
knows the English of a <HI>Scandalum Magnatum;</HI> for an
<HI>Innuendo</HI> is considered in that case: and three indi∣rect
insinuations, will go as far in Law, towards the
giving a downright Lie, as three Foils will go to∣wards
a Fall in Wrastling.</P>
<P>To Conclude, I leave it to the Judgment of the
Impartial Reader, what occasion our Answerer has
had for his Song of Triumph at the end of his Scur∣rilous,
Sawcy Pamphlet; I have treated him as
one single Answerer, tho' properly speaking his
Name is <HI>Legion;</HI> but tho the Body be possessed with
many evil Spirits, 'tis but one of them who talks;
let him disguise his defeat by the ringing of his
Bells: 'Twas an old <HI>Dutch</HI> Pollicy when the Duke
had beaten them to make Bon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ires, for that kept
the Populace in Heart. Our Author knows he has
all the Common People on his side, and they only
<PB N="126" REF="68"/>
read the <HI>Gazetts</HI> of their own Writers; so that
every thing which is called an Answer is with them
a Confutation, and the Turk and Pope are their
Sworn Enemies ever since <HI>Robin Wisdom</HI> was In∣spir'd
to joyn 'em together in a Godly Ballad:
In the mean time the Spirit of Meekness and Hum∣ble
Charity would become our Author better than
his boasts for this imaginary Victory, or his Re∣flections
upon Gods Anointed; but it is the less to
be admir'd that he is such a Stranger to that Spirit,
because, among all the Volumes of Divinity writ∣ten
by the Protestants, there is not one Original
Treatise, at least, that I have seen, or heard of,
which has handled distinctly and by it self, that Chri∣stian
Vertue of Humility.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<HEAD>ERRATA.</HEAD>
<P>PAge 25. l. 24. for, <HI>not the</HI> read, not of the. p. 39. l. 7. <HI>it will be, r.</HI> it
be p. 79. l. 1. <HI>bare.</HI> r. bear. p. 81. l. 17. for <HI>vibsily</HI> r. visibly. p. 98.
l. 22. <HI>that</HI> r. his p. 111. l. 11 <HI>has</HI> r. was. p. 113. l. 22. <HI>Conversion to</HI> r. Con∣version
wholly to.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="catalogue">
<PB REF="68"/>
<HEAD>A Catalogue of Books Printed for Henry
Hills, Printer to the King's most Excel∣lent
Majesty, for his Houshold and
Chappel, 1686. And are to be Sold
next door to his House in Black-fryers,
at Richard Cheese's.</HEAD>
<P>REflections upon the Answer to the <HI>Papist Mis-represented,
&amp;c. Quarto.</HI> Price stitch'd <HI>2d.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Papists</HI> Protesting against <HI>Protestant-Popery. Quarto.</HI> Price
stitch'd <HI>4d.</HI> 29.</P>
<P>Copies of Two Papers Written by the late King <HI>Charles</HI> II.
Together with a Paper Written by the late Dutchess of
<HI>York. Folio.</HI> Price <HI>2d.</HI></P>
<P>The Spirit of Christianity. <HI>Twelves.</HI> Price bound <HI>9d</HI>
in Quires <HI>7d.</HI></P>
<P>Six Sermons Preach'd before their Majesties in <HI>English,</HI> by the
Reverend Father <HI>Dom. Ph. Ellis,</HI> Monk of the Holy Order
of St. <HI>Benedict,</HI> and of the <HI>English</HI> Congregation. Chap∣in
Ordinary to His Majesty <HI>Quarto.</HI> Price stitch'd <HI>2s. 3d.</HI></P>
<P>An Exposition of the Doctrine of the Catholic Church in Mat∣ters
of Controversie. By the Right Reverend <HI>Iames Benigne
Bossuet,</HI> Counsellor to the King, Bishop of <HI>Meaux,</HI> formerly
of <HI>Condom.</HI> Done into <HI>English</HI> with all the former Appro∣bations,
and others newly Publish'd in the Ninth and Last
Editions of the <HI>French. Quarto.</HI> Price stitch'd <HI>9d.</HI></P>
<P>A Sermon Preach'd before the King and Queen, in Their
Majesties Chappel at St. <HI>Iames</HI>'s, upon the <HI>Annunciation</HI>
of our Blessed Lady, <HI>March</HI> 25. 1686. By <HI>Io. Beth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> m</HI>
Doctor of <HI>Sorbon. Quarto.</HI> Price stitch'd <HI>4d. 2q.</HI></P>
<P><PB REF="69"/>
An Abstract of the <HI>Douay Catechism,</HI> for the Use of Childrer
and Ignorant People. Now Revis'd, and much Amended
<HI>Twenty fours.</HI> Price <HI>2d.</HI> stitch'd in Blew Paper and cut.</P>
<P>A Pastoral Letter from the Lord Bishop of <HI>Meaux,</HI> to the
<HI>New Catholics</HI> of his Diocess. <HI>Quarto.</HI> Price stitch'd <HI>4d. ob.</HI></P>
<P>The Answer of the <HI>New Converts</HI> of <HI>France,</HI> to a <HI>Pastoral
Letter</HI> from a <HI>Protestant Minister. Quarto.</HI> Price <HI>1d. 2q.</HI></P>
<P>The Ceremonies for the Healing of them that be Diseased with
the Kings Evil, used in the time of King <HI>Henry</HI> VII. <HI>Quarto</HI>
in Latin, Price <HI>4d. 2q.</HI> English in <HI>Twelves,</HI> Price <HI>2d 2q.</HI></P>
<P>A Short Christian Doctrine. Composed by the R. Father <HI>Ro∣bert
Bellarmin,</HI> of the Society of <HI>Iesus,</HI> and Cardinal, in
<HI>Twelves.</HI> Stitch'd in Blew Paper and cut <HI>2d.</HI></P>
<P>A Vindication of the Bishop of <HI>Condom</HI>'s Exposition of the
Doctrine of the Catholic Church. In Answer to a Book
Entituled, <HI>An Exposition of the Doctrine of the Church of</HI>
England, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> With a Letter from the said Bishop. <HI>Quarto.</HI>
Price stitch'd <HI>1s. 2d.</HI></P>
<P>Two Sermons Preach'd before the King and Queen. By the
Reverend Father <HI>Iohn Persall,</HI> of the Society of <HI>Iesus.</HI>
Professor of Divinity. <HI>Quarto.</HI> Price stich'd <HI>9d.</HI></P>
<P>The Life of St. <HI>Ignatius,</HI> Founder of the Society of <HI>Iesus.</HI> In
<HI>Octavo.</HI> Price in Quires <HI>1s. 8d.</HI> bound <HI>2s▪ 4d.</HI></P>
<P>An Amicable Accommodation of the Difference between the
Representer and the Answerer, in Return to the Last Reply
against the <HI>Papist</HI> Protesting against <HI>Protestant Popery.
Quarto.</HI> Price stitch'd <HI>4d. 2q.</HI></P>
<PB REF="69"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

