<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Novembris monstrum, or, Rome brovght to bed in England with the whores miscarying / made long since for the anniversary solemnity on the fift[h] day of November, in a private colledge in Cambridge, by A.B.C.D.E. ; and now by conquering importunity made publique, for a small memoriall of England's great deliverance from the powder-treason, by E.M.A.D.O.C.</TITLE><AUTHOR>A. B. C. D. E.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A38409</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing E3</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R36130</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">15609177</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 15609177</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">104101</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A38409)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104101)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1590:36)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Novembris monstrum, or, Rome brovght to bed in England with the whores miscarying / made long since for the anniversary solemnity on the fift[h] day of November, in a private colledge in Cambridge, by A.B.C.D.E. ; and now by conquering importunity made publique, for a small memoriall of England's great deliverance from the powder-treason, by E.M.A.D.O.C.</TITLE><AUTHOR>A. B. C. D. E.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>E. M. A. D. O. C.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[10], 136 p. : ill.  </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by F.L. for Iohn Burroughes ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1641.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>In verse.</NOTE><NOTE>Added t.p.: Made long since, for the anniversary solemnity on the fift[h] day of November in a private colledge at Cambridge.</NOTE><NOTE>Part 2 (p. [55]-136) has separate t.p.: Novembris monstruvm, or, The historical narration of the damnable pouder-treason.</NOTE><NOTE>Imperfect: p. 17-18, 41-44, torn. Photostatic copy of p. 17-18 inserted after t.p.; p. 30-59 from defective Harvard University Library copy spliced at end.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Poetry.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A38409">
<STC T="W">E3</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">15609177</BIBNO>
<VID>104101</VID>
</IDG>
<GROUP>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P><HI>Novemberis Monstrum.</HI></P>
<P>OR ROME BROVGHT TO BED IN <HI>ENGLAND.</HI> with The Whores Miscarying.</P>
<P>Made long since for the Anni∣versary Solemnity on the fift day of <HI>November,</HI> In a private Col∣ledge at <HI>Cambridge.</HI></P>
<P>By<HI> A. B. C. D. E.</HI></P>
<P>And now by conquering importunity made publique.</P>
<P>For a small memoriall of <HI>England's</HI> great deliverance from the <HI>Powder-Treason.</HI></P>
<P>By<HI> E. M. A. D. O. C.</HI></P>
<Q>Monstrum, Horrendum, Informe, In∣gens, cui lumen ademptum.</Q>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed by <HI>F. L.</HI> for <HI>Iohn Bur∣roughes,</HI> at the signe of the Golden Dragon in Fleetstreet. 1641.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="frontispiece">
<PB N="17" REF="2"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="3" REF="3" MS="y"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Frontispeece Discovered.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THe DEVILL plots, the POPE will owen</L>
<L>The JESVITE must act or none.</L>
<L>One God doth SEE and SMILE, and BLAST,</L>
<L>What <HI>Hell,</HI> and <HI>Rome,</HI> and all forecast.</L>
<L>'Tis not the blacknesse of the <HI>Pit</HI></L>
<L>Can cloud this EYE from seeing it.</L>
<L>'Tis not the deepenesse of the <HI>Pit,</HI></L>
<L>Can straine this ARME from reaching it.</L>
<L>Tis not the terrour of the Pit</L>
<L>Can scare this SMILE from daring it.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>eye</HI> can chase the thickest mist,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eav'ns <HI>Arme</HI> can conquer, when it list,</L>
<L>One <HI>looke,</HI> one <HI>touch,</HI> one <HI>Smile</HI> can quell</L>
<L>The <HI>Pride</HI> and <HI>Pollicy</HI> of <HI>Hell;</HI></L>
<L>And l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t them yet more forces call,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e God will be too hard for all.</L>
</LG>
<P><PB REF="4"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>I See</P>
<P>He <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>last y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
<P>I Smile</P>
<P>Prodigye</P>
<P>Tragidye</P>
<P>I plott</P>
<P>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e actye</P>
<P>I owne</P>
</FIGURE></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
<P><HI>Made long since.</HI></P>
<P>FOR THE ANNI∣VERSARY SOLEMNITY on the fift day of <HI>November</HI> In a private Colledge at <HI>Cambridge.</HI></P>
<P>By<HI> A. B. C. D. E.</HI></P>
<P>And now By conquering import<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> made publique.</P>
<P>For a small memoriall of <HI>Engla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> great deliveranc from the <HI>Powder-Treason.</HI></P>
<P>By<HI> E. M. A. D. O. C.</HI></P>
<Q>Monstrum, Horrendum, Informe, In∣gens, cui lumen ademptum.</Q>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed by <HI>F. L.</HI> for <HI>T. Slater,</HI> at the signe of the <HI>Swanne</HI> in <HI>Duck-lane.</HI> 1641</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="6"/>
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>THE DEDICATORY.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">G</SEG>Oe litle Booke, (my unlick't Poetry)</L>
<L>And be a Patron to thy selfe and mee,</L>
<L>Shift it among the crowd, and never stay</L>
<L>To dresse thy selfe, like other trim and gay,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith borrow'd Titles, pluckt from great Ones, who</L>
<L>Are honoured by the Honour that they doe,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eare thy owne cloathes, and thinke it more to be</L>
<L>Knowne by thy face, then by a livery.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e're trust unto fond ficklenesse, that may</L>
<L>Afford a smile at first, and then betray,</L>
<L>That hisse and kill, that by embraces smother,</L>
<L>With one hand take, and throw away with th' other,</L>
<L>That ow'n a Booke, because the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ownes them,</L>
<L>Or else they'd never ow'n the Booke agen,</L>
<L>Let those that can warpe Conscience in a straine</L>
<L>And count it but a Poets <HI>Spencer</HI> veine</L>
<L>To fawne and flatter, and have learnt to call;</L>
<L>One Good, because he's Great, though worst of all;</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
Let those who can weigh vertue by the pound,</L>
<L>Where it is scarce by Drammes and Ounces foun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Who make it then chiefe Masterpiece of wit,</L>
<L>To Banckrupt Honour by out-rayling it</L>
<L>Who can say I, or No, sweat, freeze, as hee</L>
<L>Is hot or could, who is their Deity.</L>
<L>Let such Idolatours of Greatnesse shew,</L>
<L>They dare not walke abroad unlesse they goe</L>
<L>Vnder some Hee or Shee-Protection:</L>
<L>My Muse shall venture in another fashion</L>
<L>Make thine owne licence (little one) and bee</L>
<L>Protection to thy selfe, a Passe to mee.</L>
<L>And let such scratching Patron-mongers know</L>
<L>Thou'lt not on stilts, nor yet on Crutches goe,</L>
<L>On thy own feet thou'lt either runne or crawle</L>
<L>And if thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> anst not stand on them, thou'lt fall,</L>
<L>Weigh neither smile nor froune, but when you see</L>
<L>Best usage say, this shall my Patronbee:</L>
<L>And as for others that disdaine, say thou</L>
<L>My Master ownes me not, and why should you?</L>
</LG>
<CLOSER>Ʋade (nec Invideo) sine me Liber Ibis▪</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>To the Reader.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>REader, goe on; but first pray wash your eyes</L>
<L>Fom Criticisine curiosityes.</L>
<L>Then thou mayest see the clearer, judge the better:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pend a licentious verdict on each letter,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e peremptorie to condemne or praise,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ubscribe to this with boldnesse, and that race</L>
<L>With a judicious pen, and make it fit</L>
<L>For naught but Drugsters shops wast-paper it</L>
<L>And spare not (Reader) if thy courtesie</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id them peruse that, which it made thee by</L>
<L>There are but two I feare, and they shall make</L>
<L>My feare more carelesse for their empty sake</L>
<L>As for the the nicer, squeasy, wanton tast</L>
<L>That's alwaies picking, but still loves to wast,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> weigh not his court phancy: let it be</L>
<L>Spent on his wanton <HI>Thais</HI>-poety.</L>
<L>And for that carping rout that love to be</L>
<L>Still following <HI>Momus</HI> in his livery,</L>
<L>That thinkes their judgements never shine, untill</L>
<L>They finde some blots dropt from anothers quill</L>
<L>Let them still grin, and snarle, I'le sayno more</L>
<L>Then th' <HI>Spart<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n</HI> Prince to an Amhassador,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
Who being found by him sporting away</L>
<L>The tedious howers of a Summer-day;</L>
<L>Amongst his little children did request</L>
<L>The Ambassadour to let his censure rest,</L>
<L>Till he had children of his owne, just so</L>
<L>Till thou hast something of thine owne to show:</L>
<L>Leave off, or if thou wilt still snarling be,</L>
<L>Let me see thine, Ile doe as much for Thee.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="introduction">
<PB N="1" REF="8"/>
<HEAD>The Introduction.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1.</HEAD>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Here are those cristall floods, which from our eyes</L>
<L>Should make a second Sea? Those briny streames,</L>
<L>Which from the swelling veines of griefe should rise</L>
<L>And flow like surgy <HI>Neptune,</HI> when he teames</L>
<L>His daily incomes to inrich his Bride,</L>
<L>And still with new revenewes swelles his tyde</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2.</HEAD>
<L>Where are those gales of sighes, a windy gale</L>
<L>To drive my paper Pinnace that it may</L>
<L>Mounted upon a briny ocean saile,</L>
<L>And through a See of teares finde out the way</L>
<L>Vnto the sea of <HI>Rome,</HI> and there descry</L>
<L>Hells masterpiece of hell-hatcht villany?</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<PB N="2" REF="9"/>
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>There rides the whore in state, that purple whore,</L>
<L>Mounted on high upon a scarlet beast;</L>
<L>That man of sinne, quite surfetted with goare,</L>
<L>Gorg'd with the flesh of Saints at <HI>Plutos</HI> feast.</L>
<L>Bathed in <HI>Nectar</HI> blood, pancht with mans flesh,</L>
<L>As if it were high Ioves <HI>Ambrosia</HI> dish.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>4</HEAD>
<L>Foure Cardinalls coupled beares him up in state,</L>
<L>Lending their shoulders to support his pride,</L>
<L>No lesse then Kings and Emperours must waite</L>
<L>To hold his stirrop when he meanes to ride;</L>
<L>And for their paines perchance shal kisse his To<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Whether his highnesse doe weare socks or no.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="5">
<HEAD>5</HEAD>
<L>He beares his coate from truest Heraldry,</L>
<L>A Lyon-Rampant in a sanguine field,</L>
<L>Bulls the supporters, fit for crueltie,</L>
<L>A Drago in the crest, which flames doth yeeld</L>
<L>Belsht from sulphurious lungs into a flood;</L>
<L>The word, or motto is, Nothing but blood.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="6">
<HEAD>6</HEAD>
<L>His pastimes little else but crueltie,</L>
<L>To murther Princes is a recreation,</L>
<L>Spurning downe throanes is sporting jollitie,</L>
<L>Nay to doe all of these is true religion,</L>
<L>Gives marrow to their meritts, wins the prize,</L>
<L>And rids them soon to heaven with easy thighes</L>
</LG>
<LG N="7">
<PB N="3" REF="9" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>7</HEAD>
<L>To curse to Purgatori's but the fashion,</L>
<L>And therefore 'tis a sinne it should goe downe,</L>
<L>To finde out tortur's but to wrack invention,</L>
<L>Worthy a Card'nalls cap, or Fryers Crowne.</L>
<L>An inquisition is a mercy seate</L>
<L>Pitty, compared to their venome heate.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="8">
<HEAD>8</HEAD>
<L>No fire burnes so cleare, or warmes so well,</L>
<L>As that, that's kindled at a stake to burne</L>
<L>Whole legions of Heretiques to hell,</L>
<L>Who stubborne in the truth denie to turne.</L>
<L>The common bonfyre of a whole nation,</L>
<L>Is but a festivalls right celebration.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="9">
<HEAD>9</HEAD>
<L>To strangle infant Majestie before</L>
<L>The cradle suffers it to weare the crowne,</L>
<L>And dye it's mantle in a purple goare,</L>
<L>That it may never know a scarlet gowne</L>
<L>Is but true doctrine at a Councellread,</L>
<L>And therefore must by them be practised.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="10">
<HEAD>10</HEAD>
<L>They'l fire whole solemnities, and burne</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he sacrificers to a sacrifice,</L>
<L>Thus make the Temple but a common urn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To hold a quier of Martyre Saints, who dy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Before they dye, seeing their destinie</L>
<L>March towards them before it commeth nigh.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="11">
<PB N="4" REF="10" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>11.</HEAD>
<L>To make of Church and people but one fire,</L>
<L>(Surprizing them within that sacred wall,)</L>
<L>Is nothing but to kindle their desire,</L>
<L>Warming their zeale least it should faltring fall</L>
<L>Into a colder chilnesse, and so spoyle</L>
<L>The blaze of their good workes for want of oy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="12">
<HEAD>12.</HEAD>
<L>They whet the knife of cruelty and cut</L>
<L>The tongues from living men, that they may try</L>
<L>To tempt downe heaven from heaven it selfe, &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The Gods unto a miracle, if they</L>
<L>Expect the prayses due to Deity,</L>
<L>Well warbled from a tun'd fidelity.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="13">
<HEAD>13.</HEAD>
<L>They dig the infant from its living grave</L>
<L>(That fearelesse innocency, which doth lye</L>
<L>Prison'd ith' parent wombe untill it have</L>
<L>Queene natures mandat for its liberty.)</L>
<L>And then they dandle it on a pike till it</L>
<L>Fall to its first and last sleepe at their feet.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="14">
<HEAD>14.</HEAD>
<L>Have not you seene a fetter'd prisoner loose</L>
<L>The burden of his shackled teathering,</L>
<L>And scape his uncouth dungeon-repose,</L>
<L>Only that he may be conveyd agin</L>
<L>Into some closer goale, where he shall lye,</L>
<L>Till death his yron cables doth untye?</L>
</LG>
<LG N="15">
<PB N="5" REF="10" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>15.</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> else till with the hands of justice knit</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> faster twist (made for his destiny)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eades him from th' prison to that place, where it</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is soule and body must at once untie.</L>
<L>Iust thus the infant from its prison wombe</L>
<L>Is freed to be imprison'd in a tombe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="16">
<HEAD>16.</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut yet we're hardly halfe the way, put on</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de faster in the roade of cruelty,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u'l see perhaps a sucking babe anon,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hich smiling to the mothers lullaby,</L>
<L>Hangs on her melting breast, and whilst it takes</L>
<L>The hony flowing from those milkie lakes,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="17">
<HEAD>17.</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me fist, that's brawnd with frequent cruelly,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ite spoyles the draught, snatching it frō her breast,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd to compleate determin'd villany</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reeth the Parent for to doe the rest.</L>
<L>Making her turne <HI>Medea,</HI> rend and scatter</L>
<L>The tender softnesse of that infant matter.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="18">
<HEAD>18.</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> yet, oretake but Tiger-<HI>Neroes</HI> traines,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ose ten that nursed persecution,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st with the blood that sprang frō Martyrs veines</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> after gave it flesh to feede upon,</L>
<L>Till it out-liv'd foure ages, and did turn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Three hundred yeares into an ash-heapt urne.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="19">
<PB N="6" REF="11" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>19</HEAD>
<L>Could I but speake his butcher-crueltye?</L>
<L>Twould make my mouth spit blood at every word</L>
<L>Blacker then incke, and force my penne to dye</L>
<L>Each line into a scarlet thred: his sword</L>
<L>Learnt murther from him, whom it would not sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But first must trie her skill another way.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="20">
<HEAD>20</HEAD>
<L>When <HI>Nero</HI> knew not how to live or die,</L>
<L>(For dye he would not though he knew the way)</L>
<L>His venome's such, that when he doth but try</L>
<L>To slay himselfe, he must another slay.</L>
<L>Then to his servant slay thy selfe sayd He</L>
<L>That I may learne to kill my selfe by Thee.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="21">
<HEAD>21</HEAD>
<L>This <HI>Nero,</HI> grandsire of grand-crueltie</L>
<L>Begot that brat of persecution,</L>
<L>And seeming pious in impietie,</L>
<L>Left it to a succeeding guerdion.</L>
<L><HI>Domitian, Hadryan, </HI>and<HI> Antonius verus</HI></L>
<L><HI>Trajanus, Maximinus, </HI>and<HI> Severus.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG N="22">
<HEAD>22.</HEAD>
<L>Those Brother-Emperors of <HI>Hydra-Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Who rise like ten heads from that dragon-beast,</L>
<L>And out of their enflamed mouthes did foame</L>
<L>A venom'd froath upon the Christian breast.</L>
<L><HI>Hydra</HI> indeed! No sooner once was dead,</L>
<L>But in the roome sprang up another head.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="23">
<PB N="7" REF="11"/>
<HEAD>23</HEAD>
<L>Next flames out <HI>Decius,</HI> who did commit</L>
<L>A sacraligious rape on chastitie,</L>
<L>And in a ruder flame at once unknit</L>
<L>The chaster zoanes of pure virginitie.</L>
<L>Commanding <HI>40</HI> vestalls for to turn</L>
<L>True virgin-Martyrs in one common urn.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="24">
<HEAD>24</HEAD>
<L>What shall I speake of t' other viper-brood</L>
<L><HI>Galerius</HI> and <HI>Peternus,</HI> which did leade</L>
<L>The brat by both the hands, till it withstood</L>
<L>That stoutest Martyre champion, who did bleed</L>
<L>I' th' face of persecution, <HI>Laurence,</HI> he</L>
<L>That taught the <HI>Gridiron</HI> to sing Poetrie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="25">
<HEAD>25</HEAD>
<L>Next sprange <HI>Aurelian</HI> from that Tyrant race,</L>
<L>Who first did season his unnaturall hand</L>
<L>For after murthers, in that infant place</L>
<L>Where his owne blood did run, cutting the band</L>
<L>That ty'd his sister unto him more neere</L>
<L>Had but he priz'd her, as his sister, deare.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="26">
<HEAD>26</HEAD>
<L>But heaven fate Iudge, aud censur'd; saw, that H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n this first act had spent snch blood, as might</L>
<L>Have fed ten persecutions, and be</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull tyranny; Heaven therefore stops him quite,</L>
<L>And will not suffer him to quench his thirst,</L>
<L>That made himself quite drunk with blood at first</L>
</LG>
<LG N="27">
<PB N="8" REF="12"/>
<HEAD>27.</HEAD>
<L>Iove summons up his Cyclops, and commands</L>
<L>The thunder to proclaime an open way,</L>
<L>Breaking in sunder the clouds faster bands,</L>
<L>That th' lightning may her brighter face display:</L>
<L>Thus frightned with the flashings of that eye▪</L>
<L>Which glanc'd on him, He leaves his crueltie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="28">
<HEAD>28.</HEAD>
<L>Next raging as a whirlewind riseth he,</L>
<L>That swept before him like the wanton dust</L>
<L>Whole Christendomes of Saints, and made them be</L>
<L>Like atom'd crummes under his foot-stoole thrust.</L>
<L>Stay not to aske his name, Reader, goe on,</L>
<L>You'l finde him nothing but Ambition.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="29">
<HEAD>29.</HEAD>
<L>Twas He, that crouded for the Imperiall throne</L>
<L>Soaring on Eagles wings Ambition gave him,</L>
<L>Till he at length reacht it, to rule alone,</L>
<L>By doing that his concubine would have him.</L>
<L><HI>Druas</HI> commands, A wild boare must be slaine,</L>
<L>He thrusts at <HI>Aper,</HI> and begins to reigne.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="30">
<HEAD>30.</HEAD>
<L>'Twas He, that dawbd Ambition ore with pride,</L>
<L>Being once an Emperour, he must be God;</L>
<L>Hees <HI>Phoebus</HI> brother, brother to his Bride,</L>
<L>Hee'l sway both earth and Heavens imperiall rod.</L>
<L>Whenonce Ambition doth begin to fly,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Icarus,</HI> 'twill either mount, or dye.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="31">
<PB N="9" REF="12" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>31.</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d now He poasteth out a swift decree</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>led with waxe, that cannot melt away)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t hee'l be worshipped for dietie</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>people kisse his feet, those stumps of clay,</L>
<L>And take him for a God; he'l be no man:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iddle his name; 'twas <HI>Dioclesian.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG N="32">
<HEAD>32.</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> who but <HI>Dioclesian</HI> could doe that,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h Pride commanded, with a prouder hand,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>low a furnace up, that might outdate</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> yeares; and hotter then Ten could command</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efore him with their bloodyest decrees:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e was the bottom, and so gave the lees.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="33">
<HEAD>33.</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Rome,</HI> looke backe and blush upon the guilt</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ose that markt thee on th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> forhead so,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> cruelty they suckt, twas thy breasts spilt,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> then they spend it on their forreigne foe.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hese, these were thy <HI>Decemviri,</HI> that made,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n persecutions a ten-age trade.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="34">
<HEAD>34.</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>act the quintessence of villanie,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sie the horridst deeds, that ere were don;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to the depth of Phlegeton and see</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t cruelties the furies thinke upon.</L>
<L>All is but sucking malice to that they</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe execute on those, on whom they prey.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="35">
<PB N="10" REF="13" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>35</HEAD>
<L>Cruelty's turnd an Art, 't hath gott to be</L>
<L>Among the liberall sciences, most fitt</L>
<L>For him, that would be rich in pollicie,</L>
<L>He's the best Scholler, that's best skild in it.</L>
<L>The top of honour is to vale her throane,</L>
<L>Be without this you must let that alone.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="36">
<HEAD>36▪</HEAD>
<L>The Iesuit that climbs by step degrees</L>
<L>From his shorne crowne unto a Card nalls cap,</L>
<L>And thence upon Ambitions pineon flees</L>
<L>To <HI>Peters</HI> Chayre that he may take a nap,</L>
<L>Winnes all by forging out some skulking trea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Not by his judgement but inventi on.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="37">
<HEAD>37</HEAD>
<L>Charity dwells not now in Hospitalls,</L>
<L>'Thath left her Country house, and's come to to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Wintring her selfe within the frozen walls</L>
<L>Of some cold dungeon upon <HI>Tellus</HI> downe.</L>
<L>Merits swarme thicker from a <HI>Lollards</HI> Towe</L>
<L>Then from the maint'nance of a beeds-man bow</L>
</LG>
<LG N="38">
<HEAD>38</HEAD>
<L>Hee'l sooner passe for heaven, that dying leaves</L>
<L>A legacie to build an inquisition;</L>
<L>Or else his scrapt up silverlings bequeathes</L>
<L>To nurture up some tart invention.</L>
<L>Which may delve out new waies for villany,</L>
<L>And teeme forth' tother bastard-cruelty.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="39">
<PB REF="13"/>
<HEAD>39</HEAD>
<L>To flie to forraigne nations on the wind,</L>
<L>And crosse the seas that they may crosse the land,</L>
<L>So get more worlds, if more were left behind,</L>
<L>And with a paper bull them all command,</L>
<L>Is the Ambition burnes within their breast,</L>
<L>And keepes their busie soules from taking rest.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="40">
<HEAD>40</HEAD>
<L>To puffe up States and Kingdomes at a blast,</L>
<L>To plucke downe Crownes and Septers at one fall,</L>
<L>To swallow Realmes to breake a mornings fast,</L>
<L>And yet scarce satisfied there with all;</L>
<L>Is but course fare at a Lent ordinary,</L>
<L>Such is there raving-craving cruelty.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="41">
<HEAD>41</HEAD>
<L>But soft a while, take fresher breath (my muse)</L>
<L>Leave off to lash her former whoredomes still,</L>
<L>She hath bin scourg'd enough for old abuse,</L>
<L>And yet her fornication-cup doth fill</L>
<L>With new-brew'd poyson; spare thy whip that it</L>
<L>May take new strength, &amp; not the latter quit.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="42">
<HEAD>42.</HEAD>
<L>Had every persecution bin ten,</L>
<L>Aud each had burned longer then them all</L>
<L>Maintained with fresh fury, till all them</L>
<L>That were but Christned Protestants had fall,</L>
<L>'Thad made but a straw bonfier compar'd</L>
<L>With that hell-fuell they of late prepar'd</L>
</LG>
<LG N="43">
<PB REF="14" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>43.</HEAD>
<L>Fuel in oyle, which had but <HI>Plato</HI> seen</L>
<L>Heapt up, He, staggerd at the sight, would sweare</L>
<L>Envy's <HI>Idea</HI> had existent bin,</L>
<L>And on the stage ne're durst before appeare.</L>
<L>Fuell stor'd up to feede revenge, and be</L>
<L>A plot to puzzle all <HI>Hyperbole.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG N="44">
<HEAD>44.</HEAD>
<L>Had but <HI>Pythagoras</HI> diviner soule</L>
<L>By <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ransmigration dwelt in other men,</L>
<L>And so out liv'd his owne age, and then stole</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nto another, and at length had bin</L>
<L>One of our owne; He, seeing this alone,</L>
<L>Might well out-vie all ages with this one.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="45">
<HEAD>45.</HEAD>
<L>Call up Chronology, and bid her bring</L>
<L>Her bunch of keyes to open Historie;</L>
<L>Ransack that cabinet, and view each thing,</L>
<L>That she hath lockt up from her infancy.</L>
<L>Call aged Time, and bid him search his file</L>
<L>That he this cruelty may parallell.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="46">
<HEAD>46▪</HEAD>
<L>Arrest the Sunne, and stay his Coach for thee,</L>
<L>That thou mayst parly with him; aske him then</L>
<L>If riding all his circuit He could see</L>
<L>Such treachery, as in this age hath bin.</L>
<L>Chronology must tye up Historie,</L>
<L><HI>Time</HI> hang his file, and <HI>Phoebus</HI> silent be.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="47">
<PB N="13" REF="14" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>47</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en summon up the Furies from their cell;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ock at the doores of darkenesse, and there see,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thou canst speake with <HI>Pluto,</HI> King of Hell,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to <HI>Proserpina</HI> admitted be.</L>
<L>Sue for a Synod, and then try if they</L>
<L>Can match themseles agin, or match the day.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="48">
<HEAD>48</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll stands amaz'd. <HI>Pluto</HI> is mad that he</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ould be outvi'd on earth: The Furies sweare</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ey went beyond commission; and decree</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll shall afford no more, if they come there.</L>
<L><HI>Megera</HI> loaths her service, and decrees</L>
<L>To dwell on earth to learne new cruelties.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="49">
<HEAD>49</HEAD>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>berus</HI> howles for madnesse, and opes wide</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> triple throate, from which a whirlewind came,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ich made the rivers rage into a tyde,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d roar'd, as if they threatned all hells frame.</L>
<L>That <HI>Pluto</HI> thought therabble had come downe</L>
<L>Missing their plot on earth, to get his crowne.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="50">
<HEAD>50</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld but the gelid feare, that freezeth mee,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d cloysters up my blood in coldest veines,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ease my speech, and set my tongue but free,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uld unfold a treachery, containes</L>
<L>The <HI>Elixar</HI> of the bitterest druggs, that are</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Mong all th' Apothecary <HI>Pluto's</HI> ware.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="51">
<PB N="14" REF="15" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>51</HEAD>
<L>Then cease thy Styx-dy'd mantle (tragedy)</L>
<L>And buckle soone thy bloody busking on</L>
<L>Dipt ten graines deeper in their goary dye,</L>
<L>Doe thou attend us, while we treate upon</L>
<L>Seven headed <HI>Hydra,</HI> hatcht long since in <HI>Ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L>And what conceptions teeme within her wombe▪</L>
</LG>
<LG N="52">
<HEAD>52</HEAD>
<L>But where's the quill that can drop lines of blo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But where's the tragick pensell that can paint</L>
<L>Such hideous cruelty scarce understood?</L>
<L>Or fathom'd with the thoughts of man or Saint.</L>
<L>But wher's the fiery muse that can discribe,</L>
<L>The treachery of that infernall tribe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="53">
<HEAD>53</HEAD>
<L>Nor thoughts, nor words are ready to unfold</L>
<L>That hideous tragedy, whose plot was found</L>
<L>And first contriv'd in hell, but never could</L>
<L>With prologue once salute the English ground,</L>
<L>Although the stage was built, the sceane was m</L>
<L>On which that Tragick act was to be playd</L>
</LG>
<LG N="54">
<HEAD>54</HEAD>
<L>That tragick act, the thought whereof doth ma</L>
<L>My quivering muse affraid, my ague-quill</L>
<L>Shakes in desiphering it, my hands doe quake;</L>
<L>My teare-drownd eyes a fresh supply d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>still</L>
<L>And yet at length grow dry; my haires t' untw</L>
<L>And stand an end like quills o'th' Porcupin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="55">
<PB N="15" REF="15" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>55</HEAD>
<L>But soone my Muse recovered, and my quill</L>
<L>Obeyd the hand that guided it; mine eyes</L>
<L>Clear'd up, and would no farther showers distill,</L>
<L>Then soone I set upon the enterprize.</L>
<L>Turne o're the page, draw but the curtaine, there</L>
<L>You'l see the Monster-Tragedy appeare.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="summary">
<HEAD>Argumentum.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>AFfrica multa dedit, vix vix dedit Affrica tan∣ta</L>
<L>Quant a uno peperit Roma <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> monstro.</L>
<L>Nec miranda cano: <HI>Romae Lupa</HI> namque Noverca,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lla dedit monstrum, cur non dabit Illaque monstrum</L>
<L><HI>Sic canibus eatuli similes, Lupa Sicque Lupillo.</HI></L>
<L>Primulus en<HI> monstri conceptus; Adultera matrix:</HI></L>
<L>Tartareo spurcamspargit dum <HI>semine</HI> matrem</L>
<L>Roma ferox, caetae generatur <HI>Filia noctis.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Monstri fama </HI>fugit, tantae quoque<HI> Nuncius aurae</HI></L>
<L>Pegaseis volitat pennis: mox qualia monstra</L>
<L>Roma dabit,<HI> dubio meditatur pectore </HI>quisque.</L>
<L>Cujus ope proles latebrosis parta tenebris</L>
<L>Prodeat in lucem, <HI>Obstetrix</HI> è Tartare surgit.</L>
<L>Expectata dies celebranda est; Romaque gestit</L>
<L>Conceptu partus, sed mox prorepit <HI>abortus.</HI></L>
</LG>
<P><PB REF="16"/>
<TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>1 <HI>Proditionis conceptus.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>1</CELL>
<CELL>Upon the first plotting of the Treason.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>2 <HI>Matrix, in quâ pubescit embryon.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>2</CELL>
<CELL>Upon the vault in which this Trea∣son was hatcht
<LIST>
<ITEM> 1 Upon the buying of it.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Upon the digging of it.</ITEM>
</LIST></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>3 <HI>Tempus quo generatur monstrum.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>3</CELL>
<CELL>Upon their working in the night.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>4 <HI>Ipse generandi actus.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>4</CELL>
<CELL>Upon the bringing of the Pouder from Lambeth and laying it in the Cellar.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>5 <HI>Concepti fama.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>5</CELL>
<CELL>Upon the Letter sent to my Lord Mounteagle.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>6 <HI>Famae mercurius</HI></CELL>
<CELL>6</CELL>
<CELL><LIST>
<ITEM>1 Upon the quill that writ the Letter.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Upon the sending of it to the King.</ITEM>
</LIST></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>7 <HI>Partus determinatio</HI></CELL>
<CELL>7</CELL>
<CELL>The Kings discovering of the plott.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>8 <HI>Praeelecta Obstetrix</HI></CELL>
<CELL>8</CELL>
<CELL>Upon Faux, the Man-Midwife ready to deliver it</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>9 <HI>Natalis expectata celebratio</HI></CELL>
<CELL>9</CELL>
<CELL>The Match of hunting appointed to surprize the Lady Elizabeth.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>10 <HI>Abortivum monstrum</HI></CELL>
<CELL>10</CELL>
<CELL>The miscarying of the birth▪</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>11 <HI>Parturientis periculum.</HI></CELL>
<CELL>11</CELL>
<CELL>Romes Downefall in Black-Fryers upon their fift day of No vember.</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB N="17" REF="16"/>
<HEAD>PRODITIONIS CONCEPTVS.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Vpon the first plotting of the Treason.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>Nd see; the Pope hath travail'd once againe</L>
<L>With a new <HI>Affrick</HI> Monster, worse then came</L>
<L>From their she-popedome, when a woman prov'd</L>
<L>The Churches head, &amp; all the body mov'd.</L>
<L>(Poore headlesse she-church, where was thy head then </L>
<L>When <HI>Ione</HI> did loose her maiden-head with men? </L>
<L>Oh she tooke care for that, least <HI>Rome</HI> should need </L>
<L>Succeeding Popes, she would her self popes breed) </L>
<L>But whither roves my muse? come backe againe, </L>
<L>And see another of that breeding traine</L>
<L>Goe big with envie, labouring with a birth,</L>
<L>Swell'd with a plot, nay brought to bedith' earth.</L>
<L>Ready to teeme forth from a monstrous thigh</L>
<L>A strange delivery, the birth was nigh.</L>
<L>Twas comming forth, but had not the strength to give </L>
<L>So big a monster, as it did conceive.</L>
<L>Fye <HI>Rome!</HI> thou wantst a midwife, or a <HI>Ione</HI></L>
<L>That can without an helpe bring forth alone.</L>
</LG>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="section">
<PB N="18" REF="17"/>
<HEAD>II. <HI>Matrix, in quâ pubescit embrion.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Vpon the vault, in which the treason was hatcht.</HEAD>
<DIV3 TYPE="subsection">
<HEAD>1. Ʋpon the buying of the vault.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Downe with price of blood, if you would faine</L>
<L>As you have sold out soules, buy in againe.</L>
<L>The purchase you have got by emptying</L>
<L>Your purgatorie may well fiil't againe.</L>
<L>Looke on this arched vault, how will it make</L>
<L>An high way passage to the Stygian Lake?</L>
<L>The price you had the last soules you did sell,</L>
<L>Will buie the Catholiques this way to hell.</L>
<L>Where's He that beares the bag, your <HI>Iudas</HI> tro</L>
<L>That feeketh to betray his Mother so?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the vault is sold</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>oney told.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ny you hee'l sweare</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ne relique are.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, and we</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> as he</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>; And be it so,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L>
</LG>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="subsection">
<PB N="19" REF="17"/>
<HEAD>2 <HI>Vpon the digging of the vault.</HI></HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd what are you that Tribe, who doe denye</L>
<L>Your black guard thus, the honour of a bed?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ho make it death once with a bride to lye,</L>
<L>Tis Symony to buy a maiden head.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd yet forsooth you'l dare to ravish all</L>
<L>At once your common mother, force a birth</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hether she will or no a monster shall,</L>
<L>Teeme from her wombe out of the groaning earth</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>You'l rent her matrix else, which nature taught</L>
<L>By closing such an incest to deny:</L>
<L>As if she had foreseene, that Rome had thought</L>
<L>To grapple with her mothers secrecy.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>4</HEAD>
<L>What steepes your frolik spleenes in choller so?</L>
<L>What mooves your touchy blood to such a tide.</L>
<L>How came your pampred carkasses to doe</L>
<L>Such ravisht rapes unto your mothers side?</L>
</LG>
<LG N="5">
<HEAD>5</HEAD>
<L>And must you needs with pickaxe, and with spade,</L>
<L>Threaten unlesse she grant your villany?</L>
<L>Have you no milder Rhetorique to perswade,</L>
<L>And woe a yeeld to such a curtesie?</L>
</LG>
<LG N="6">
<PB N="20" REF="18"/>
<HEAD>6.</HEAD>
<L>What made you strike so deepe? was your inte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>To fathom <HI>Styx,</HI> or sound blacke <HI>Acheron?</HI></L>
<L>To cast a causy to <HI>Don Vulcans</HI> tent,</L>
<L>Thus fetch provision he had wrought upon</L>
</LG>
<LG N="7">
<HEAD>7.</HEAD>
<L>No no; you dreamt perchance that you shou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> find</L>
<L>Some yron veine, which nature minted there</L>
<L>Of purpose to helpe forward such a mind,</L>
<L>And runne Art out of breath in a prepare.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="8">
<HEAD>8.</HEAD>
<L>To such a stratagem; dreame on, take out</L>
<L>A rib of yron from Dame natures side,</L>
<L>Fall in your dreame again, then cast about</L>
<L>To make your rib the hottest brunt abide.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="9">
<HEAD>9</HEAD>
<L>Dig deeper yet, perchance at length you'l finde</L>
<L>That nature hath dung'd their Salt-peter too</L>
<L>And left her wooden legs and stilts behinde,</L>
<L>To nourish up the flames, all these for you▪</L>
</LG>
<LG N="10">
<HEAD>10</HEAD>
<L>But hold your hands, sweat no more marrow now</L>
<L>Spend the earths ball no farther, nor your strength</L>
<L>I feare the proverbe will prove true, below,</L>
<L>You dig'd so deepe, there came a damp at length</L>
</LG>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="section">
<PB N="21" REF="18"/>
<HEAD>III. <HI>Tempus, quo generatur monstrum.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Vpon their working in the night.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>Sleep <HI>Phoebus</HI> sleepe;</L>
<L>What makes thee peepe?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe not so soone thy sable curtaines draw,</L>
<L>Lie downe againe in <HI>Thetis</HI> lap,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>was late before thou wentst to bed we saw,</L>
<L>O pry thee take another nap.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f thou beginst to rise, these night owles then</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust leave their work, when others do begin,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Phoebus</HI> stay,</L>
<L>You will but make an Holy day.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>What made thee wake?</L>
<L>Couldst thou not take</L>
<L>Thy rest to night, thou heardst such knocking</L>
<L>Let not thy fiery steedes yet sup</L>
<L>Their mornings draught, nor run their full careere here?</L>
<L>Why dost thou call <HI>Aurora</HI> up?</L>
<L>They plotted not against thy Deity.</L>
<L>Then <HI>Phoebus</HI> stay,</L>
<L>You will but beg another play.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<PB N="22" REF="19"/>
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>Goe drowsie droanes,</L>
<L>Make, make your moanes,</L>
<L>To your dead-living Saints; sigh prayers that th</L>
<L>May intercede for you and get,</L>
<L>The Sunne to stand ith' heavens, and so delay</L>
<L>The dawning of the morning, yet</L>
<L>Cry lowder, let another beade yet fall;</L>
<L>Make up your prayers compleate, or you'l marr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>For want of sleepe,</L>
<L>Your prayers awake you cannot keepe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>4</HEAD>
<L>See see, the day</L>
<L>Makes no delay.</L>
<L>Then <HI>Phaeton</HI> doe thou mount up the coach,</L>
<L>Let loose the horses carelesse raines,</L>
<L>That they may run away the days approach.</L>
<L>On faster wheeles, with easie paines</L>
<L>Whip on thy foaming fteeds, that we may feare</L>
<L>The ratling of thy coach like thunder heere.</L>
<L>Come draw away,</L>
<L>That night shee sooner hasten may.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="5">
<PB N="23" REF="19"/>
<HEAD>5</HEAD>
<L>Tis here, the night</L>
<L>Hath scar'd the light.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he day hath new undrest her self, I saw</L>
<L>But now her under-peticoat.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y thought 'twas dyed in a red more raw</L>
<L>Then any flesh of sheepe or goat;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut as she stript her selfe of that, she drew</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> modest Curtaine, thicke as night, to shew,</L>
<L>She Vail'd her head,</L>
<L>As <HI>Vesper</HI> sent her downe to bed.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="6">
<HEAD>6</HEAD>
<L>Now all the light</L>
<L>Is claspt in night.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orpheus</HI> hath woed all things to rest you see,</L>
<L>The'rs no dog moves unlesse it barke</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or madnesse at the Moone, least she descry</L>
<L>Their deedes of darkenesse in the darke.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut never feare: bid <HI>Phoebus</HI> kisse his Bride</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat she may blush to see her evening tide.</L>
<L>Worke while you may,</L>
<L>Then let him come to wake the day.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="7">
<PB N="24" REF="20"/>
<HEAD>7.</HEAD>
<L>Up <HI>Phaeton,</HI></L>
<L>Up, up, be gone.</L>
<L>Goe guide thy Father to his mate, that he</L>
<L>May court her with his rosie lips;</L>
<L>Then in conjunction goe with her, till she</L>
<L>Embraced be to an ecclips.</L>
<L>Thus vaile her face that she may never be</L>
<L>Privie to such a monstrous villany.</L>
<L>Away, Away</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> is rise to call the day.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>IV. <HI>Ipse generandi actus.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Vpon the bringing of the Gunpowd from <HI>Lambeth</HI> over the <HI>Thames,</HI> and lay∣ing it in the Cellar.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>Where is thy Legate <HI>(Rome?)</HI> Let him provid</L>
<L>His sparkling Spanish jennet straight,</L>
<L>Coapt in his trappings made of gold</L>
<L>When th' golden fleece came from your fold</L>
<L>His feet well shod with Indy plate:</L>
<L>His crisping maine to twisted lockes divide,</L>
<L>Fit for the riders pride.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<PB N="25" REF="20"/>
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>See how the horses prauncing doth foretell</L>
<L>How he expects his rider, see</L>
<L>In what a language he doth pray</L>
<L>His master for to come away,</L>
<L>And deck him with his company.</L>
<L>Heare how hee neighes, his neighing doe but spell</L>
<L>It hastens his farewell.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uicken thy legate then; doe, bid him seale</L>
<L>His fiery steed, and winged poast</L>
<L>With thy Embassage unto hell;</L>
<L>There once arived let him tell</L>
<L><HI>Don Pluto</HI> Primate of that hoast,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at <HI>Charons</HI> footy keele must hoise his saile</L>
<L>Waiting a trusty gale.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>4</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd to thy tackling then <HI>(Styx-Ferry-guide)</HI></L>
<L>The winde hath sight a softer gale.</L>
<L>Lanch out, glide o're the <HI>Stygian</HI> lake</L>
<L>A fairer harbour yo umust take.</L>
<L>Doe but your beaten pinnece hale</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o our <HI>Thamefis,</HI> there it shall pride</L>
<L>It selfe in <HI>Neptunes</HI> tide.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="5">
<PB N="26" REF="21"/>
<HEAD>5</HEAD>
<L>Those silver streames shall wash hell from thy boate</L>
<L>And turne that dye, <HI>Styx</HI> left it last</L>
<L>Into a Cignets purer white,</L>
<L>By their reflection made more bright.</L>
<L>Who when they first thy ferry past,</L>
<L>Dabling in that thy keele there set a float,</L>
<L>Got there so black a foot.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="6">
<HEAD>6</HEAD>
<L>But faster <HI>Charon;</HI> sweat a little more,</L>
<L>What maketh <HI>Aeolus</HI> thus blow?</L>
<L>Me thinkes he seemeth out of breath,</L>
<L>Or else his wind is pent beneath,</L>
<L>That he becomes shortwinded so,</L>
<L>On <HI>Charon,</HI> worke the harder; you are sore</L>
<L>Expected long before.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="7">
<HEAD>7</HEAD>
<L>See how the swelling barrells, stuft with fire,</L>
<L>Are big with expectation:</L>
<L>They long untill they see thy boat,</L>
<L>In which they must be set a float,</L>
<L>To take another station.</L>
<L>Srange contract, see the water slakes her ire</L>
<L>and entertaines the fire.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="8">
<PB N="27" REF="21"/>
<HEAD>8</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t stay, what meanes those well growne vessels there?</L>
<L>What? have you poudred up your plot</L>
<L>In barrels, least it should not keep,</L>
<L>Or be discovered when you sleepe?</L>
<L>Sure then some vent your treason got</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat 'twould not keep so long, untill you were</L>
<L>To set abroach <HI>November's</HI> beere.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="poem">
<HEAD>V <HI>Concepti fama.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>on the letter sent to my Lord <HI>Mounteagle.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mystery enwrapt in misteries,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mment farre obscurer then the text,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fit that thou should meet an Eagles eyes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h might peirce through the vaile, &amp; tell what's next</L>
<L>Never mount Eagle: gaze not on the Sun</L>
<L>Glance downe-wards to the depth of Phlegeton.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>loisterd up in darkenesse, hid in hell,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tled with night, prison'd in <HI>Acharon,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> barrel'd up in natures misty cell.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e but the letter, and the danger's gone.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>trange plot! doe burn't: the blaze will let thee see</L>
<L>How to discover this darke mysterie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="28" REF="22"/>
<L>The letter burnt, the danger's past, and all</L>
<L>The mysterie must then be over too,</L>
<L>And yet this burning makes it mysticall,</L>
<L>How can I spell it when 'tis burned so?</L>
<L>However burnt it, in it burnt you'l see,</L>
<L>That which you reade not, when you read it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Darke letter! folded up in flames indeede,</L>
<L>And therefore needs no wax to seale it fast,</L>
<L>Let who will reade, at most he can but reade,</L>
<L>And whn h' hath done, must burne it too at la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Fyer must tell thee what it meanes alone</L>
<L>And when the fyer▪s out, the dangers gone.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>VI.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Famae Mercurius.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="subsection">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Vpon the quill that writt the letter▪</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>What molting Seraphim did spill</L>
<L>That speaking, silent muttering quill?</L>
<L>That spake yet spake not, speaking parables▪</L>
<L>Which kept and told the truth in miracles.</L>
<L>That two toung'd Oratour that spake</L>
<L>Still twise at once, and still did make</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="22"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ystery unknowne by clearing it,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d knowne by making it obscurer yet.</L>
<L>A quill, that could not speake th' intent</L>
<L>Of him that writt, to whom 'twas sent.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d yet could blab the secraest meaning too</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him, for whom 'twas maskt, and muffled so.</L>
<L>A pen that by discovering cover'd,</L>
<L>And yet by covering was discovered.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>anus</HI> face, that smiled one way now,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d frown'd the other with a furrow'd brow.</L>
<L>A pen snatcht from <HI>Apollo's</HI> hand;</L>
<L>That spake pure <HI>Delphos</HI> language, and</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uld vent nought else but pure <HI>Amphibolies</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>king this that, and that this, this and this;</L>
<L>A danger great by lening it,</L>
<L>And none by making it so great.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ckt from an Eagles wing, 'twas such an He,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at brought it to our Sovereighng's Diety.</L>
<L>Or from that tatling goose which pratled</L>
<L>The foes approaches, when shee cackled.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> from some <HI>Sphynx</HI> his standish it did fall,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at it unriddl'd in a riddle all.</L>
</LG>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="subsection">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>on the sending of the letter to the King.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>A letter to the King is sent,</L>
<L>To riddle what the meaning meant;</L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="23"/>
A letter writ indeede from Babylon,</L>
<L>Speaking confus'on, in confus'on.</L>
<L>Tis true, one language, onely came,</L>
<L>And yet that language languages transpos'd</L>
<L>A Letter in a Letter was enclos'd</L>
<L>So that the same seem'd not the same.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>How well may Rome true Babell be,</L>
<L>That speakes thus in a mysterye?</L>
<L>A masked tongue kept Babell from her height▪</L>
<L>And Rom's confused language spoyles hir quite</L>
<L>Plaine English speake, when you write nex</L>
<L>Your letter meant, nought lesse then what it me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Therefore 'twas sent, to whom it was not sent,</L>
<L>Pray henceforth comment on your text.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>'Tis brought unto the King we see,</L>
<L>That he may dive the mysterie.</L>
<L>Why? what's the matter! Are our Island's eye</L>
<L>Growne dimme with age, The Vniversities?</L>
<L>Why had not they the letter read?</L>
<L>They would at first strike deepe; 'tis true, but s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>That they looke through their Soveraigne, y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> kn</L>
<L>The eyes are alwaies in the <HI>Head.</HI></L>
</LG>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="section">
<PB N="31" REF="23"/>
<HEAD>VII. <HI>Partus determinatio.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Vpon the Kings discovering of the plot.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat Kings are sometimes Prophets too we see,</L>
<L>What made our <HI>Iames</HI> else prophecie?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rue vertue oftenn crownes Nobilitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow true was he the King of Schollers fam'd,</L>
<L>That Rome with her owne sword hath tam'd?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell Schollers King, well King of Schollers nam'd,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he paper bids him burne the paper, so</L>
<L>The danger would be over to.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e saves himselfe and paper with a No.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow so? we reade the danger is not o're</L>
<L>unlesse the Letter burnt before.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen burne it, and the danger is no more.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut reade againe, and then perhaps you'l see,</L>
<L>How bravely you are danger free,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t be so soone o're-past, how soone wil't be?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>his made our <HI>Iames</HI> more nimble then the fire,</L>
<L>This thought did make his thoughts retyre</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o search out what was tangled in that bryer.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="32" REF="24"/>
<L>He dived therefore somewhat lower yet;</L>
<L>And truely such a dive was fitt,</L>
<L>To sound the intralls of so deepe a pitt.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>His Nobles now as well as He must move,</L>
<L>And presently his verdict prove,</L>
<L>Searching out that below, he saw above.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>They seeke, but see not: Did you never heare</L>
<L>Too nigh an object is too neare?</L>
<L>I can see better farther off then here.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The King sees yet: He bids them search agin:</L>
<L>They goe, then bring the message in.</L>
<L>Nothing before, is now the very thing.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>(Thus have I seene a beagle soone o'rerunn,</L>
<L>The new-borne sent but now begunn,</L>
<L>Then counterhunt it when it is halfe donn.)</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>They, that made nothing of it, found it somethi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Reade backwards, if you meane the King,</L>
<L>Who making something of it, made it nothing.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="section">
<PB N="33" REF="24"/>
<HEAD>VIII. <HI>Praeelecta obstetrix.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<HEAD>Vpon <HI>Faux</HI> ready to deliver it.</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut Monster-Tiger, a fell vipers brood,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat would'st such with thy milk, thy mother's blood</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>awn'd with a <HI>Richards</HI> tush, not toothles borne,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rawing the fountaine-breast, thou wouldst have torne</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> passage to hir heart, gnawd that for food,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd like <HI>Prometheus</HI> Vultur suckt on blood.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou'lt suck, but so that thou mayst open too</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>conduit-veine whence blood with milke may flow</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onder that thy mother wean'd Thee not</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om hir, whence thou this Viper-nature got.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy step-nurse, Rome I meane, that purple whore</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hose breasts milkt venome from a putrid soare.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t see, Rome nurst Thee, therefore thou wilt be</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hir brought up unto this villany.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me</HI> once a <HI>Nero</HI> had to kill a mother,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast <HI>Rome</HI> should want one now, thou prov'st a∣nother.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d hath not she hir Jesuits, that thou</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust prove a Mid-wife to hir treason now?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat would you have the whore when all is done</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y at our doore hir new borne bastard sonne?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ant grosse excrement: know thus much, that</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ngland</HI> doth scorne to Father such a brat.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="34" REF="25"/>
<HEAD>Vpon the same.</HEAD>
<L>Vp night-owle, and breake o'pe thy sealed eyes,</L>
<L>Venter to looke upon the mantled skyes.</L>
<L><HI>Sol</HI> hath remov'd his court, the glorious day</L>
<L>And all his followers have packt away.</L>
<L>Night is full mounted in her seate of jet,</L>
<L>And lies wrapt in her cloudy cabanet.</L>
<L>Feare not, <HI>Apollo's</HI> gone; his prying eye</L>
<L>Can neither see nor blab thy villanie.</L>
<L>Envie hath gone her time, and doth begin</L>
<L>To be in travell with her full-growne sin.</L>
<L>Vp then, and see that all things ready be</L>
<L>'Tis thou must hasten her delivery,</L>
<L><HI>Pluto</HI> hath sent his Pursivant away</L>
<L>To summon thy appeareance, make no stay:</L>
<L>Goe, take thy charge, that thou maist licenc't be,</L>
<L>And show a pattent for thy viilany.</L>
<L>Fetch thy darke-lanthorne, that true <HI>Gyges</HI> ring,</L>
<L>Which, thou unseene, makes Thee see ev'ry thin</L>
<L>Take that turn'd-Hypocrite, whose outward sho</L>
<L>Is night, but inward like the day doth glow.</L>
<L>Foule as a mist without, all fayre within,</L>
<L>Vice would seeme vice sometimes to cloake a si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Thy darke companion will still be true,</L>
<L>And by denying light, will lighten you.</L>
<L>Then downe with hast to that infernall cell,</L>
<L>Where fur ous envy, and hid treason dwell.</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell them Hell's suffrage hath elected you</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>roome of that chamber, where death lyes below</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd you must call it up as soone as day</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e christned, as the Sunne whips night away.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ooke then unto your charge, and see that he</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eepe not beyond his time, but stirring be;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se all his breakefast may be spoyl'd, and He</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill misse his morning's draft of Majestie.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or you (proud factors for the Netherlands,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gent for hell) must suffer <HI>Morpheus</HI> bands</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tye your eye-lids up: what if the birth</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iscarry, e're the night expires her breath.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> stead of being Sainted, you shall be</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rol'd for purgatory, and there made free.</L>
<L>Then girt thy selfe for Rome, and charge thine eyes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at they like watchfull <HI>Argus</HI> keepe the prize.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thou an <HI>Heirogliphick</HI> to the hare,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eepe waking with thine eyes unclos'd, and bare.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d when the day begins to ope her eyes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke <HI>Nilus</HI> with the rising Sunne arise.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat though thou saile through the <HI>Aegaean</HI> sea,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st up and downe with fear's perplexity?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inke every one thou seest is come to bring</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee tydings of a kingdome to a King.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou seek'st a throne: who would not think it</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> swim-unto it through a sea of blood?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut heaven looks on, &amp; <HI>Love</HI> is comming down good</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s milkie pavement with a furrow'd frowne</L>
<L><PB N="36" REF="26"/>
Iustice sits in his eye (and yet 'tis blinde:</L>
<L>It sees but sees not; smiles that it should finde</L>
<L>Such secreasie in Treason) vengeance lyes</L>
<L>Wrapt in the wrinckles round about his eyes.</L>
<L>Next, down the Regent walke, <HI>Astraea</HI> came</L>
<L>Following high Iove to Iudge the world againe.</L>
<L>Iustice tooke wing before, and left the earth,</L>
<L>But seeing crueltie recover breath,</L>
<L>And grow to such a Gyant-stature, shee</L>
<L>Returnes bedeckt with greater Majestie.</L>
<L>The <HI>Cyclops</HI> arm'd with thunder round about,</L>
<L>Attends them both to drive those Traitors out.</L>
<L>Then tremble treachery; treason unmaske</L>
<L>Thy muffl'd face; make bare thy knees, and ask<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A pardon of the Gods: hold up thy hand,</L>
<L>Guilt doth indite Thee, and for guilty stand.</L>
<L>Iustice is come to visite once againe,</L>
<L>Tenders hir hand to kisse, if you'l reclaime.</L>
<L>Or else (by that impartiall soule, that guides</L>
<L>Hir hand) the sword your soule and clay divides</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>No no: (Grand Enginere of crueltie)</L>
<L>Ne're startle at the newes: what's this to thee?</L>
<L>Thou hast an <HI>Heliotrophian</HI>-stone, which will</L>
<L>Put out the eyes of Iustice, blinde hir still.</L>
<L>Send for Don <HI>Pluto's</HI> sheild, that thou maist see</L>
<L>Approaching justice, and she not see Thee.</L>
<L>Stare in the face of vengeance, and outdate</L>
<L>Those executioners, that comes to skare</L>
<L>Thee from thy charge: Laugh at their thunder-peal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And let them heare the Eccho oft from hell.</L>
<L><PB N="37" REF="26"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy? thou'rt prepar'd for this; can this be newse,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen thou such prodigies thy selfe dost use?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rden thy cruell heart, untill it grow</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd like a Sea-calfe to withstand the blow</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hotter vengeance: crowne thy head with bayes,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> scare the <HI>Cyclops</HI> from thy hidden wayes.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll scarse doe: with thine owne plot begin,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w them from earth up into heaven agin.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou know'st thy charg; what Rome expects from Thee;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w she hath cram'd thee for this crueltie?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rite after hir, and when the coppy's writt;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t all that reade, see thou'rt hir counterfeit.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>like hir, but more cruell in thy wit,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rite by the coppie, but still better it.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mulus</HI> suck'd a wolfe, and was as shee,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou suckst of Rome, then thou like Rome must bee.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat <HI>Romulus</HI> did suck, to Rome he gave,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat Rome from <HI>Romulus,</HI> that thou must have.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tvie them all, Rome, <HI>Romulus,</HI> and Hir</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at nurst thy cruell grand progenitor.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="section">
<PB N="38" REF="27"/>
<HEAD>IX <HI>Natalis expectata celebratio.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Vpon the match of hunting appointed o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the birth day, where they intended to surprize th Lady <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> but in the meane time they themselves were surpriz'd.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><HI>Actaeon's</HI> gone to hunt, the day we see</L>
<L>Appointed is, and where the game shall be.</L>
<L><HI>Actaeon</HI> as he hunted glanc'd a side,</L>
<L>And there <HI>Diana</HI> in a thicket spy'd.</L>
<L><HI>Diana?</HI> No, it was a fairer she,</L>
<L>Her Nymphs it may be might <HI>Diana's</HI> be.</L>
<L>And yet me thinkes <HI>Diana</HI> it should be</L>
<L>Rather <HI>Diana's</HI> true Divinity.</L>
<L>For as <HI>Actaeon</HI> spies that beauty there,</L>
<L><HI>Actaeon's</HI> turn'd <HI>Actaeon</HI> like a Deere.</L>
<L>He that came forth to hunt is hunted straight,</L>
<L>They lye in waite for him, that lay in waite.</L>
<L>The yelping Ecchoes of the hound's are done,</L>
<L>The Hue and Cry after the Hunter's gone:</L>
<L>I see that Poets now can prophesie,</L>
<L>And in a parable tell what shall be.</L>
<L>I see that fables are not alwaies lyes,</L>
<L>Time often doth a fable moralize.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>X <HI>Abortivum Monstrum.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Vpon the miscarrying of the birth.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Oft have I knowne a child prove Parracide,</L>
<L>Dividing soule and clay as't did divide</L>
<L><PB N="39" REF="27"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Parent's gasping wombe, through which her soule</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent with the body of the child for tole</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pay the infant's passage, and repreive it</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om th' falling prison, if not quite releive it.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mtimes a child the Parent's name doth smother,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lling the mother 'fore it had a mother,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t have I heard a woman travail'd so</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at in the sigh her sonle did come and goe.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ange travell! when her soule is faine to take</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> farre a journey for her infants sake.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen thus the Parent mother must begin</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> leave the world to bring her infant in;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust dye, to teach hir child how first to live,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d being dead in it learne to revive▪</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> if <HI>Pythagoras</HI> had taught her soule</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s transmigration, And it knew no Pole:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Paradise, but presently did passe,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d in the infant clay informant was.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat? did you never see a wombe deny</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e burthen, but unload it presently.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me proves it selfe an <HI>Hierogliphick</HI> well</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> speake what I have spoke, and yet shall spell</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e truth once over to you more; if yet</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our cloak't-capaciti's are hid from it.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>deede their fruitfull shee-Pope tarry'd not,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t brought forth soone, as if she had forgot</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce to bespeake a midwife, or else thought</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> brew as well as she had bak't for nought.</L>
<L><PB N="40" REF="28"/>
And yet see, how shee's brought to bed in State</L>
<L>How many thousands hir congratulate</L>
<L>Being at hir labour met. I wonder she</L>
<L>Was brought to bed alone in companie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But now ther's no such matter; Rome would faine</L>
<L>Once travaile with a second birth againe.</L>
<L>And see, the Pope grows big indeede: How now</L>
<L>What, hath not Rome had breeding Popes enough</L>
<L>How did your Card'nalls misse the chayre, that they</L>
<L>Have let another she-Pope slip away?</L>
<L>Oh 'tis no matter, they'l take care that she</L>
<L>Be not deliver'd now too openly.</L>
<L>The heav'n no more shall prove a Canopie</L>
<L>The Market place no more a chamber be.</L>
<L>When this shall be deliver'd Rome will bye</L>
<L>A privie-chamber for this secrecie.</L>
<L>(Had not Pope <HI>Ione</HI> bin brought to bed so patt,</L>
<L>She would have found a vault too for hir Bratt.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But see, the birth day's come; Conduct your who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Vnto hir privie-chamber, where ther's store</L>
<L>Of <HI>Pluto's</HI> Pothecarie drugs that be</L>
<L>Provided for her safe delivirie.</L>
<L>What? Is she yet in labour? hath she got</L>
<L>Hir Predicessors faculty or not?</L>
<L>Had she an harder travaile then your <HI>Ione?</HI></L>
<L>What hath God sent hir tro? what two or one</L>
<L>I feare she was so overbig, that shee</L>
<L>With Bratt miscarri'd in deliverie.</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat was the matter Rome? did not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe full the time she reckon'd on before?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as this hir first conceived bratt, that shee</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efore hir time met hir deliverie?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat? Is the child still borne? Tis so I see</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he birth's abortive, though the mother be.</L>
<L>Thus have I seene an hasty apple drop</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bortive from the tree before the crop.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut then 'twas rotten, blasted, withered</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lthough the mother-tree was no way dead.)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he still-borne batt hath thus miscarried,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>was not deliver'd though delivered.</L>
<L>The womb that casts before the time doth still</L>
<L>Threaten the Infant, if not alwaies kill.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her's now the Infant which new borne had slaine</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t once both <HI>England</HI> &amp; her soverainge?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hich had spitt living coales as he begann</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o live, and dy'd as they had dyed than.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat meanes <HI>November's</HI> fift day and the store</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rovided for the birth so long before?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he purple whore this day expected shee</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ould have beene blest with her deliverie.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>his day once come, the birth was nigh indeed;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t th' Bratt was still borne, we delivered.</L>
<L>The child, which dyes before it lives, doth still</L>
<L>Threaten the Mother Parent, if not kill.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="11" TYPE="section">
<PB REF="29"/>
<HEAD>XI. <HI>Parturientis periculum.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Vpon the whores downefall in <HI>Blackfrye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> on their fift day of <HI>November.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>What makes us then sigh prayers for <HI>Babel's</HI> fall</L>
<L>As if that <HI>Babylon</HI> ne're fell at all?</L>
<L>Wher's <HI>Rome's</HI> Armado <HI>Spaine</HI> so stood upon,</L>
<L>No Navie but a wand'ring <HI>Babylon?</HI></L>
<L>Is not that fallen? True; how could it stand?</L>
<L>It was a <HI>Babel,</HI> but 'twas built o'th' sand.</L>
<L>The wind's they whisl'd to the wav's a charge,</L>
<L>The wav's brake out, and roaring speake at large</L>
<L>Their message to the Sands: the sands obey</L>
<L>After the cap'ring waves they dance away.</L>
<L>When th' wind thus blew, when thus the water co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>There Babel built upon the sands, prov'd lame.</L>
<L>What makes us then sigh prayers for Babels fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>As if that <HI>Babylon</HI> ne're fell at all?</L>
<L>But on, what meanes <HI>November's</HI> Holy-day?</L>
<L>Her fift dayes chiefest royalty, which may</L>
<L>Be calculated with the reddest letter,</L>
<L>To speake their bloody Stratagem the better▪</L>
<L>Rome then began to build a Babel too,</L>
<L>She dig'd for a foundation so low;</L>
<L><PB REF="29" MS="y"/>
And then had thought to plucke downe</L>
<L>Out of her ruines to repaire their owne.</L>
<L>But as they built they were surpriz'd, that they Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Were faine to leave their Babel halfe the way.</L>
<L>Thus not to rise is nothing but to fall,</L>
<L>Who'l say that Babylon ne're fell at all?</L>
<L>But once more reade, and then perhaps you'l see</L>
<L>Babel a third time fall a third degree.</L>
<L>Water did once o'retop Rom's Babel's so,</L>
<L>That though 'twere Babel it did Rome o're throw</L>
<L>Babell first fell by water, next by fire,</L>
<L>Not that it burnt, but that it slack't it's ire.</L>
<L>Fire and water, though they disagree</L>
<L>Become now sister Elements we see</L>
<L>And joyne their forces to enact heav'ns will,</L>
<L>Th' one by fighting, th' other standing still.</L>
<L>What fire and water doth, that earth will doe,</L>
<L>For earth did swallow falling Babell too.</L>
<L><HI>November</HI> twice saw Babel fall on day,</L>
<L>This makes her fift day twice an holy day.</L>
<L>And <HI>Eighty Eight</HI> told Babell by her fall,</L>
<L>That, that was then her Climacteticall.</L>
<L>And yet is Babell still? where doth she stand?</L>
<L>She fell by water, and she fell by land.</L>
<L>Thrice Babylon we see hath got a fall,</L>
<L>But oh that she were fallen once for all!</L>
<L>Babel's so high it is no wonder she,</L>
<L>Is so long falling to her last degree.</L>
<L><PB REF="30" MS="y"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> tis well that she three stories fell;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> but the fourth, 'twill bring her downe to hell▪</L>
<L>Me thinkes I see those knotted rafters there</L>
<L>Like carv'd-out <HI>Atlases,</HI> which well might beare</L>
<L>A burthen greater then the Spheares could lend</L>
<L>An <HI>Aetna</HI> if it once began to bend.</L>
<L>Enough to keepe up mountaines, and support</L>
<L>From nodding even <HI>Babel's</HI> stoutest fort.</L>
<L>And yet when <HI>Babel's</HI> Bratt loaded with sinne,</L>
<L>Comes on the Stage to act her part therein;</L>
<L>It makes the oake to yeeld, the Cedar bend</L>
<L>And roots up the foundation from their end.</L>
<L>That which before did make the prouder walls</L>
<L>Sprout up to heav'n, tript up by heav'n, it falls</L>
<L>Downe levell with the earth, and that which knew</L>
<L>No crookednes, bends like a twig of ewe</L>
<L>Sin makes the creatures groane, &amp; bowing downe</L>
<L>Lye in the dust for that, man won't bemoane.</L>
<L>Fye purblind Rome! what-made your bald-pate crew</L>
<L>Outface the face of heav'n in such an hew?</L>
<L>Did heav'n your fift days treachery betray</L>
<L>That you might turne it to an Holy-day?</L>
<L>Went on your plot so well, that you must call</L>
<L>A day a part for a set Festivall?</L>
<L>What ignorance hath brawn'd your fottish soules</L>
<L>That when the arme of strength stretcht out con∣troules</L>
<L>With a proclaim'd defiance what you did,</L>
<L>Poynting out that from heav'n, which lay so hid?</L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="30"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou nod at the finger in a triumph straight,</L>
<L>And shout the conquest being lead captivate?</L>
<L>What made you sound the Trumpet so and call</L>
<L>Such a rifie-raffle to your Stygian hall?</L>
<L>Was it that you might beltch out a defie</L>
<L>In open. Court upon the Gods, 'cause they</L>
<L>Opening the casements of the spangl'd spheare</L>
<L>Lookt downe from heaven, and so discov'rd there</L>
<L>That mantled project, which you thought to keep</L>
<L>From them; no, no, The gods are not a sleep.</L>
<L>Or was it ▪cause that <HI>Albion</HI> baukt your ire</L>
<L>You'd curse us to a Purgatories fire?</L>
<L>Rather purchance you felt an hell within</L>
<L>Still glowing in each conscience, which the sin</L>
<L>Had newly kindled; and dispaire had blowd,</L>
<L>Till it to a consuming fire glowd.</L>
<L>And therefore you must thither poast to take</L>
<L>The refuge of your holy water-lake;</L>
<L>Sprinking your selfe with it, that you might tame</L>
<L>The fury of your selfe consuming flame.</L>
<L>Or wash your hands in it, and so might be</L>
<L>As innocent as <HI>Eden</HI> puritie.</L>
<L>Fondnesse! as if that niter could cleanse sinne,</L>
<L>Which may show faire without, when foule with∣in.</L>
<L>Or else to blesse your selves from after losses,</L>
<L>Crossing your selves to keep your selves from cros∣ses</L>
<L>Nor this nor that: you thought that rable crue</L>
<L>(Which in a Catholique bravado threw</L>
<L><PB N="46" REF="31"/>
There carelesse lives a way, that they might get</L>
<L>More Kingdomes to your Triple Coronet)</L>
<L>Were hang'd to Saints, &amp; that their unjust doome</L>
<L>Was nothing but to suffer Martyrdome.</L>
<L>And therefore you'd be sure the fift day too</L>
<L>Should be as well an Holy-day to you.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus winged with a fault'ring zeale thy flye</L>
<L>Vnto their consecrated Friery</L>
<L>T'adore those new-made Saints, and gratulate</L>
<L>Their safe arrivall at the <HI>Eliz'an</HI> state.</L>
<L>And now to them, wh' alive were dead in feares,</L>
<L>Being dead, they pray to rid them of their cares.</L>
<L>Then by a gen'rall councell they agree</L>
<L>To celebrate their yearely memory,</L>
<L>Thus rob the yeare of dayes, that so they may</L>
<L>Give to each Saint his sev'rall Holy-day.</L>
<L>Or' cause they jointly suff'red as one member</L>
<L>They give an All-Saints-day unto <HI>November.</HI></L>
<L>Fond zelots! you had better turne the page,</L>
<L>Convert your feasts into a pilgrimage.</L>
<L>Walke with repentant feete to forreigne Isles</L>
<L>Their sigh your selves to sadder syllables:</L>
<L>And ev'ry desert, that you softly tread</L>
<L>With naked pennance feete, let fall a Beade.</L>
<L>That so all passengers in after age</L>
<L>May count the paces of your pilgrimage.</L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="31"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut downe your Saints, that by their merits found</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> new way up to heaven, above the ground.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hose ropes will serve for cords to gird about</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our hairie loynes to doe your pennance out?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r else preserve them, till you steale away</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Poles, on which their head's march in array,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen send them o're, I'le warrant you they'l be</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> choicer Relique for posteritie.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut whisper softly (muse) a while, you'le drive</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hose empty droanes out of their borrow'd hive.</L>
<L>You'l coole their hot divotion, put them out</L>
<L>Before their Ceremony's brought about.</L>
<L>You'l turne the Priest besides the cushion straight,</L>
<L>Make him scratch mem'ry from his balder pate.</L>
<L>Before h'hath found it, he will loose the text,</L>
<L>And scarce the first word out, forget the next.</L>
<L>You'le make the other from his palsie fist</L>
<L>Drop downe his wafer God-Emmanualist.</L>
<L>And then some sawcy dog will snatch it there,</L>
<L>And transubstantiate it, I know not where.</L>
<L>The third disturb'd, will sprinckle unawares</L>
<L>The Holy-water on the sacred sta'res.</L>
<L>Stand backe a while, keepe off, vengeance will come</L>
<L>And summon them to silence e're they've done.</L>
<L>Looke what that right hand speakes unto the wall,</L>
<L>See there imprinted fairely Babels fall.</L>
<L><PB N="48" REF="32"/>
The hand from heav'n hath charg'd the walls, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Withdraw their shoulders, and the walls obey.</L>
<L>Nay there stands <HI>Sampson,</HI> him whom they bega</L>
<L>With sulphur'd lungs to spitt their venome on,</L>
<L>And like the wanton Philistimes to play</L>
<L>Some pranks upon him on their holy-day.</L>
<L>But he the truer-<HI>Sampson</HI> verifi'd</L>
<L>What Typically t'other <HI>Sampson</HI> did.</L>
<L>He toucht the posts with a command, they fall</L>
<L>Striking all dead into one funerall.</L>
<L>Perchance they thought He was as blind as He,</L>
<L>But henceforth see, the eye of heaven can see.</L>
<L>A <HI>Video rideo</HI> smil'd on you before,</L>
<L>He saw you then how durst you tempt him more</L>
<L>But when the Asse, that falles into the pit</L>
<L>Will not take heede, Hee'l fall agin it it.</L>
<L>Who bolder then blind Bayard, who more blin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Then such a sottish, stockish, rabble kind</L>
<L>Where ignorance doth murther zeale, a brat</L>
<L>As blind as their carv'd God, as cold as that?</L>
<L>But now by this I hope they've learnt to see</L>
<L>They strike at heaven, that aime at Majestie.</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Gygantaean</HI> race, leave off to move</L>
<L>In Martiall fight the unconquerd Gods above.</L>
<L>What? will you get 'gainst Iove your seiges lay?</L>
<L>And still before the walls of heaven display</L>
<L>Hells blacker banners, raise the siege at length,</L>
<L>Retrait, ne're stay to trye out strength with strength</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="32"/>
You felt the weight of his immed'tate hand,</L>
<L>Who beck'ning only just at his command:</L>
<L>Destruct'on posted plum'd with Fury's wing</L>
<L>And stay'd not for a solemne summoning</L>
<L>By Gods owne pursevants which commonly</L>
<L>Doe use to be destruct'on's <HI>Mercury.</HI></L>
<L>Fire or water, stormes, or darts of thunder,</L>
<L>These use to be his messengers of wonder.</L>
<L>Sometimes he post's to batle in array,</L>
<L>Wrapt in a whirlewind, fur'ous of delay.</L>
<L>Sometimes he rides upon a prouder wave</L>
<L>And thence he doth his stoutest foes outbrave.</L>
<L>Sometimes againe he marcheth through a cloud</L>
<L>Girt with a scarfe of light'ning, and aloud</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>end's forth his watchword to the <HI>Cyclop's</HI> there</L>
<L>Who rank's the squadron's out, &amp; keeps the reere)</L>
<L>Bidding them with as loud a voyce discharge</L>
<L>A volly of thunder, which may rend at large</L>
<L>The duskish mantle of the skyes, and make</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. passage through the clouds, that wrath may take</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> freer Aime to shoote her vengeance right</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd execute what he decree'd hath quite.</L>
<L>Now this, and this, now that's his messenger,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et alwaies God hath not a harbinger.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ometimes his hand doth smite without a sword,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ometimes without an hand, he sends his word,</L>
<L>Whereof the softest accent is enough</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o rend the world if once sent out in wrath.</L>
<L><PB N="50" REF="33"/>
Then see (proud Rome) thy seeded villany,</L>
<L>That Majestie it selfe must deale with Thee.</L>
<L>Creatures those Proxie-searjants of the King,</L>
<L>Hee'le hardly trust at thy grand suffering.</L>
<L>To rid a way thy execution,</L>
<L>Hee'l be in presence there to see it done.</L>
<L>He might have rent the bowells of the earth,</L>
<L>That roaring <HI>Bor'as</HI> with his blust'ring breath,</L>
<L>And whirle wind-nostrills might rush forth, &amp; cast</L>
<L>The Fabrick levell at one rendring blast.</L>
<L>He might have op't the treasury's of the ayre,</L>
<L>And sling'd his hayle downe, to untop it bare.</L>
<L>Thus made a way for thicker stormes to fall</L>
<L>And fling downe death on each in ev'ry ball.</L>
<L>He might have bidden <HI>Neptune</HI> call a way</L>
<L>His white plum'd hills to march in set aray.</L>
<L>And with his Trident-mace command each wave</L>
<L>To swell unto a tide, and thus out-brave</L>
<L>The proudest top that peirc't above the rest,</L>
<L>And swept thy building too a way at last.</L>
<L>He might have caus'd a showre of brimston fall</L>
<L>And rain'd downe flames of Gunpowder withall</L>
<L>Not to blow up it, but to burne downe all.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But neither fire did fall, nor water rise</L>
<L>Nor wind, nor storme joyn'd in this enterpize.</L>
<L>The word, that with a word did make all these</L>
<L>Without them, can doe when, and what he please</L>
<L><PB N="51" REF="33"/>
When he intends to make his glory ride</L>
<L>Tryumphant, shining with a sacred pride:</L>
<L>He lay's a side the meanes with his left hand,</L>
<L>And with his right doth, what he please, com∣mand;</L>
<L>Then tremble Babylon to see thy fall,</L>
<L>Twas God himselfe was in the reeling wall.</L>
<L>He set himselfe to do't: that all might see</L>
<L>Twas his right arme that gate the victory.</L>
<L>His presence made the trembling stones to shake</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a quivering ague, and the rafters quake,</L>
<L>Till all their unknit joynts were loos'd, the wal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Before his sacred presence downe did fall.</L>
<L>He charg'd the finewes of the house to shrinke▪</L>
<L>And bid the pinns unty, that all might sincke.</L>
<L>They heare his voyce, and at his voyce obey,</L>
<L>Thus thus the crumbling fabrick pines away.</L>
<L>What makes us then sigh prayers for Babels fal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>As if that Babylon ne're fell at all?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fell, and sure the fall was great; it fell</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s if it had prepar'd away to hell;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aking a passage with it's weight, to send</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat rable rout unto their <HI>Styg'an</HI> end.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fell, and in the fall below'd so loud,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s if two rocks, falling at once, did crowd,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ushing each others side, and strove which shall</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ccho the neighbouring hills the louder call.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fell, and struck so, it could not more harme</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad it beene hurled from a Cyclop's arme.</L>
<L><PB N="52" REF="34"/>
It fell but holloo'd out, so loud i'th' fall,</L>
<L>As if it would the dead, it kil'd, recall.</L>
<L>It fell; stop there! Lett's heare a while what Fome yeare</L>
<L>Can say unto this second Martyrdome.</L>
<L>Should they but pilfer out more dayes from th'</L>
<L>To cannonize for those that suffer'd there</L>
<L>They must create new Alma nacks, and make</L>
<L>Their next yeare longer for their Martyr's sake.</L>
<L>Or else joyne two Saints to make up one day</L>
<L>A sunkin, and a gimkin Holy-day.</L>
<L>Now plodding Rome, what have your pie-ball trick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Gendred in plotting 'gainst the Heretic kes.</L>
<L>Goe, goe, divide the spoyle that is come in,</L>
<L>Wee'le cast up ours, and let them laugh that wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>You thought to make us rise, by rising fall;</L>
<L>You fell at once, but never rise at all.</L>
<L>If we had fell, by falling we had rise</L>
<L>Hell's sometimes the high-way-roade to blisse.</L>
<L>Had you then rise, yet rising you had fell,</L>
<L>Heaven is sometimes the broadest way to hell.</L>
<L>You fell, we stand, heaven downward striks we s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And hell aimes upwards; what's the mistery?</L>
<L>Is Rome's <HI>America</HI> plac'd in the Ayre,</L>
<L>Their new found Purgatory founded there?</L>
<L>That <HI>Pluto</HI> plot's such stratagems to guard</L>
<L>The English Catholiques up thither-ward.</L>
<L>'Tis so I see; their Purgatory's there;</L>
<L>I thought it was a Castle in the ayre.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="section">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>The Corollary.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>STrange birth! the Pope he is the Holy Father,</L>
<L>The Earth the Mother is, the Master rather.</L>
<L><HI>Pluto</HI> the Grandsire, and the Deputyes</L>
<L>Not two or foure, but all the infernall fryes</L>
<L>Of Monk's, and Iesuit's, Priests, Masse Priests too</L>
<L>Intended are as witnesses unto</L>
<L>This Affrick birth; would you the midwife yet?</L>
<L><HI>Faux</HI> was appointed to deliver it,</L>
<L>It was begot in Hell, conceiv'd in Rome,</L>
<L>And should have beene deliver'd here at home.</L>
<L>But <HI>England</HI> would not lend that life, which fell</L>
<L>To be a Mongrell betwixt Rome and and Hell.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="35"/>
<PB REF="35"/>
<P>NOVEMBRIS. <HI>MONSTRVM.</HI></P>
<P>OR The Historicall narra∣tion of the damnable <HI>Pouder-Treason.</HI></P>
<P>WITH The dayes <HI>Is</HI> for <HI>England's</HI> Mira∣culous deliverance.</P>
<P>PARS IIa.</P>
<P><HI>London, </HI>Printed by<HI> Frances Leach.</HI></P>
<P>1641.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="36"/>
<HEAD>To the Iuditious Reader.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>NOt biting Satyr, nor an hony stile</L>
<L>Dropt only from a Parasite I will.</L>
<L>A bitter sweet is good, wormewood in wine</L>
<L>Is to a Poet the best Hypocreene.</L>
<L>Thou art the Man uuto the man of Sinne</L>
<L>Is the Musit'ans hitting the right string.</L>
<L>Her's nothing whipt and stript but Babels Bratt,</L>
<L>Which long agoe hath beene condemn'd to that.</L>
<L>Thence all not bitter sweet, nor sweetnesse bitter</L>
<L>If you finde both, you will finde both together,</L>
<L>And so both mingled, both together shall,</L>
<L>Prove to bad stomackes a good Cordiall.</L>
<L>Be but judicious in thy censure then,</L>
<L>And if thou rellish gall dropt from the pen,</L>
<L>Conclude it is not hony, nor should be:</L>
<L>Or that thou bringest a sick taste with Thee.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="36"/>
<HEAD>NOVEMBRJS MONSTRVM.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hus have I seene Ambition's Min'on soare</L>
<L>To teach the towring Mount of cob∣wed-fame,</L>
<L>Counting it Piety, t'imbrace in goare</L>
<L>His blood-renc't hands, so He may get a name.</L>
<L>Though He like <HI>Tantalus</HI> both live and dye:</L>
<L>Catch at the Apple, that doth most Him flye.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>Thus that proud Impe, that thought to ware his glory▪</L>
<L>Before the <HI>fire</HI> of <HI>Diana's</HI> shrine,</L>
<L>And make his name blaze forth in his own story▪</L>
<L>Brighter then did the glowing Temple shine,</L>
<L>Must needs attempt that sacriledge to have</L>
<L>His name &amp; Him joynt-tenants of one grave.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>Thus have I knowne a Monke and Fryers pride</L>
<L>Iustle for th' wall of cruelty, and see</L>
<L>Which of them should prove better Regicide,</L>
<L>That they for Saints may canonized be.</L>
<L>Whil'st he that thinkes to blazon forth their glory,</L>
<L>Blots out their names in setting out their story</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<PB N="58" REF="37"/>
<HEAD>4</HEAD>
<L>He that doth looke, from honour's hands to hav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The Lawrell wreath, to crowne his works withal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Must with the hands of virtue it receive</L>
<L>Virtue gives scutch'ons to a funerall.</L>
<L>Else he, that would be heire of Fame, shall be</L>
<L>Excecutor of nought, but Infamie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="5">
<HEAD>5</HEAD>
<L>If <HI>Icarus</HI> doe strive with borrow'd wings</L>
<L>To reach the Sun, and graple with his bride,</L>
<L>You'le see how soone his false Ambition flyngs</L>
<L>Him downe, and drownes his honour in the tyde</L>
<L>He that makes wings to flye to fame, shall see</L>
<L>Fame will be ready to take wing and flee.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="6">
<HEAD>6</HEAD>
<L>What did proud <HI>Phaeton's</HI> ambitious minde</L>
<L>(In coveting his Father's reines to guide)</L>
<L>Provide him for a Trophye, did he finde</L>
<L>That was the rode, where Fame and glory ride?</L>
<L>No, Fame will ne're Ambition's yoake-mate b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Hell must lend fire to light his infamie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="7">
<HEAD>7</HEAD>
<L>Then thinke no more (Proud Rome) of building stayres</L>
<L>That those may seale to heav'n, and Sainted be,</L>
<L>Who were chiefe agents for thy hell-affaires,</L>
<L>In plotting treason, and hid Tyranny.</L>
<L>Thou can'st not raise a Babell halfe so high:</L>
<L>Ne're think to top those walls, or come so nigh</L>
</LG>
<LG N="8">
<PB N="59" REF="37" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>8</HEAD>
<L>But if thou will needs have thy factors ride</L>
<L>Full mounted on the <HI>Pegasus</HI> of Fame,</L>
<L>Wee'le helpe them up, a <HI>Pegasus</HI> provide,</L>
<L>But wing'd with infamy, and plum'd with shame.</L>
<L>Blacke deedes are Cronocled that they may be</L>
<L>Enrol'd for hatred, not for memory.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="9">
<HEAD>9</HEAD>
<L>Then Historie fetch thy brazen penne, and send</L>
<L>For incke from blacker <HI>Acharon,</HI> that I</L>
<L>May (guided by thy hand) in brasse commend</L>
<L><HI>Rom's Monster</HI>-Bratt to all posterity.</L>
<L>That sager Time, may point out Rome to see,</L>
<L>And make her blush, at her owne progeny.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="10">
<HEAD>10</HEAD>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Mauricius,</NOTE> That dreaming Emperour, whose phancy prov'd</L>
<L>Truer then <HI>Phocas</HI> did, that did succeed,</L>
<L>Thought in his sleepe he slept, &amp; death was mov'd</L>
<L>By th' murd'rous hands of <HI>Phocas</HI> to proceed.</L>
<L>Deames prove not alwaies night-mayres, coun∣terfie</L>
<L>Murderes awake, when we least dreame of it.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="11">
<HEAD>11</HEAD>
<L>This <HI>Phocas</HI> dranke ambition's <HI>Mercury,</HI></L>
<L>Which kindled such a fire within his breast,</L>
<L>Nothing would quench his thirst, but Dignity,</L>
<L><HI>Mauricius</HI> must die, and <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">His wife and his Daughters.</NOTE>all the rest.</L>
<L>Thus waded through his blood unto his throne</L>
<L>This pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d a dreame to him: the other none.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="12">
<PB N="90" REF="38"/>
<HEAD>12</HEAD>
<L>Once mounted to the high imperiall seate</L>
<L>Brim-full of Honour, honour must runne o're,</L>
<L>Let but th' Imposture Pope his consc'ence cheat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>With a full pardon, and quit murder's score</L>
<L>Phocas will ope a sluce, from which shall flee</L>
<L>Supremacy to swell the Bishops <HI>See.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG N="13">
<HEAD>13</HEAD>
<L>'Twas he, was Rom's grand Patron, and fir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The Triple Crowne to th' Papall dignity,</L>
<L>And that Rome might as horrid treasons have gav</L>
<L>He left his murthers for a legacy.</L>
<L>A cruell Monster must that honour be,</L>
<L>That's got of murder, and full Tyranie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="14">
<HEAD>14</HEAD>
<L>Rome proves his wil, and then makes hast to tak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A full possession, next he seekes to find</L>
<L>Some cruell skulking Iesuite to make</L>
<L>Him treasurer of what was left behind:</L>
<L>Where warres doe nought, there treason mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> begin</L>
</LG>
<LG N="15">
<HEAD>15</HEAD>
<L>So have I seen a scattered army lye</L>
<L>(The conqu'rer's strength soon conquered by slight</L>
<L>And yet the next day rise with victory,</L>
<L>Getting by forging, what they lost by flight.</L>
<L>Our foe may teach us how to winne the prize</L>
<L>By falling often times wee learne to rise.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="16">
<PB N="61" REF="38" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>16</HEAD>
<L>The Iesuite makes much of what h'hath got,</L>
<L>Phocas his lcgacy shall not be spent,</L>
<L>And yet he will be prodigall; but not</L>
<L>Spend on the Principle, ▪tis his intent</L>
<L>To trade with Hell, and put it out to use,</L>
<L>That, which the Feinds return, shall feed abuse.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="17">
<HEAD>17</HEAD>
<L>And well he hath improv'd what Phocas left:</L>
<L>For envy, Mallice full inveterate;</L>
<L>For murther, Murthers, mixt with skulking theft:</L>
<L>For Regicide, both King and kingdom's Fate:</L>
<L>To kill a king is petty treason, fit</L>
<L>For lay-murder, not a Iesuite.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="18">
<HEAD>18</HEAD>
<L>Those poled Pates have quite impov'rish't hell,</L>
<L>And mate the Duke of darkenesse morgage all</L>
<L>His hidden plots to them, treason shall dwell</L>
<L>No more within Don Pluto's Stygian Hall,</L>
<L>All's fell to them, they'l turne the Feinds out quite,</L>
<L>And Hell shall be their owne before the night.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="19">
<HEAD>19</HEAD>
<L>With jaws as wide, as the vast arch of heav'n</L>
<L>They gape for Kingdomes, royall blood's their draft</L>
<L>With treason's blacker feet they'r headlong driven</L>
<L>Murther is counted but on handy craft.</L>
<L>See all in this one plot, which though but one</L>
<L>Hath all in it, the other all are none.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="1">
<PB N="62" REF="39"/>
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>WHen blest <HI>Eliza</HI> swai'd proud <HI>England▪s</HI> rod</L>
<L>And ballanc't in her hands the golden ball:</L>
<L>Peace sat by hir, laid downe her head to nod</L>
<L>Within her Princely lap, and there did fall.</L>
<L>Into a slumbring sweet-security.</L>
<L>Peace flyes not Scepters, but dread Tyranny</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>This quiet Empresse hardly could enjoy</L>
<L>The sweetnesse of that royall maiden bed.</L>
<L>But something would her present rest annoy,</L>
<L>And with a surly joy, divorce her Head.</L>
<L>Or treason's rage at home, or warr's abroad,</L>
<L>Kings must not alwaies look for peace aboad</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>But alwayes as Queene-Peace <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>awak't, she turn'd</L>
<L>Lending a glance to blest <HI>Eliza</HI> still,</L>
<L>And smiling on her Angell-face, shee burn'd,</L>
<L>And blusht, as if she long'd to speake her will.</L>
<L>But pluckt an Olive branch to give her still,</L>
<L>And so laid downe her head to sleepe her fil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>4</HEAD>
<L>Then, then it was, that time look't young agin,</L>
<L>Wiping his hoary foretop from his eyes</L>
<L>He lookt, and thought the golden age had bin,</L>
<L>And deeming of himselfe in paradice,</L>
<L>Began to count his age, and scarce beleiv'd</L>
<L>(Seeing <HI>Eliza)</HI> he so long had liv'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="5">
<PB N="63" REF="39"/>
<HEAD>5</HEAD>
<L>The earth was watred with a milder dew,</L>
<L>Which peace did sprinkle from her fruitfull hand,</L>
<L>That <HI>Tellus</HI> in her sparkling coate did show,</L>
<L>As if sh'had on, that couler'd swadling band,</L>
<L>Which wrapt her infancy with var'ous wreaths</L>
<L>Like those which lovely <HI>May,</HI> for <HI>Phyllis</HI> weaves</L>
</LG>
<LG N="6">
<HEAD>6</HEAD>
<L>The plough-men earlyer then the morne, did rise</L>
<L>Whistling <HI>Apollo's</HI> steeds to watering,</L>
<L>Whil'st with their chearefull notes, they did devise</L>
<L>How to divide the day with quavering,</L>
<L>Thus play themselves to worke, &amp; then divide</L>
<L>The earth to furrowes, as the plough did glide.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="7">
<HEAD>7</HEAD>
<L>They put Dame nature to the sword, and made</L>
<L>Her open wide her wombe, to lodge the graine,</L>
<L>The plow ne're knew the share, the earth no spade</L>
<L>But <HI>Mars</HI> did make away for <HI>Ceres</HI> traine.</L>
<L>New plow'd with swords, they beat their armor out</L>
<L>For horseshoes, or to plate their wheeles about</L>
</LG>
<LG N="8">
<HEAD>8</HEAD>
<L>Neglected helmets then were cast away,</L>
<L>The spideres tooke them for their shops to weave</L>
<L>Their thinner-softer, Taffety, where they</L>
<L>Kept a continuall working-day with leave,</L>
<L>And made them monuments, that they might∣ly</L>
<L>There, softly wrapt in their owne destiny.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="9">
<PB N="64" REF="40"/>
<HEAD>9</HEAD>
<L>The hoarser throates of Cannons bellow'd forth</L>
<L>Not for Bellona's sake to summon warre,</L>
<L>But when soe're they thund'red, 'twas the worth</L>
<L>Of some great triumph to be blowed farre:</L>
<L>And that about the world, did give the fire,</L>
<L>Or celebrate Eliza's crown'd desire.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="10">
<HEAD>10</HEAD>
<L>The Taratant'ring sound was never heard,</L>
<L>Which when the horses e're once soopeth up,</L>
<L>It makes them mad for battaile, and unscar'd</L>
<L>He runnes at push of Pike, the flame doth fup</L>
<L>Into his fiery nostrills, till it come</L>
<L>Out of his mouth like to a seathing foame.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="11">
<HEAD>11</HEAD>
<L>The drumme unbrac't lay speechlesse al the while</L>
<L>The flute had got a cold i'th' rusty throate:</L>
<L>Insteed of these we heard the <HI>Philomele</HI></L>
<L>Sing to the Musick of the Lute her note.</L>
<L>Peace lay a sleepe under hir Olive tree,</L>
<L>Charm'd with the winged Quier's Lullaby.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="12">
<HEAD>12</HEAD>
<L>Devotion in her whiter robe, more white</L>
<L>Then th' unborne Snow within her region,</L>
<L>Go's to the Altar with a soule more bright</L>
<L>Then th' spotlesse spotted Bride of heav'n, the moon</L>
<L>And there with holy-hands, and washed eyes</L>
<L>Offers her undisturbed sacrifice.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="13">
<PB N="65" REF="40"/>
<HEAD>13</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>straea keepe her state; both eyes doe see</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd yet they both are blind: her eares both deafe</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd yet both open too: she keeps a Key</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o lock out bribes, and open for reliefe</L>
<L>'Twas shee that lasht Erynnis out and then</L>
<L>Came peace &amp; calm'd the troubled earth again</L>
</LG>
<LG N="14">
<HEAD>14</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut night doth close the eyes of dying day;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> storme doth alwayes follow fairest weather</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> never saw Proud <HI>Cynthia's</HI> aray</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>imselfe in glory for a Month together,</L>
<L>But sometimes mourne, weepe in his Southern weeds</L>
<L>And glister sometimes in his Easterne beades.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="15">
<HEAD>15</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s constant is a Kingdom's fading state:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow Peace doth shine on it from open Spheare:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd then a Counter-warre doth change his fate</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rawing on it a gloomy cloud of Feare.</L>
<L>Fortune's Queene regent of all things below:</L>
<L>And Kingdoms, like the Moon, do ebb, &amp; flow▪</L>
</LG>
<LG N="16">
<HEAD>16</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>once <HI>Eliza</HI> shine so bright that she</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n Earth is like the Sunne in his owne spheare,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arting forth Glory from her Majesty,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nough to make the lesser Princes bleere;</L>
<L>The world will gather clouds to blind her too,</L>
<L>Least earth in glory should the heav'n outgrow.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="17">
<PB N="64" REF="41"/>
<HEAD>17</HEAD>
<L>Envy, which can't endure aequality</L>
<L>Ne're lookes at parallels, she aimeth higher.</L>
<L>An Eagle scornes to make her game a flye:</L>
<L>Let th' bramble take acquaintance with the bry</L>
<L>'Tis the tall Ivie, that growes above the rest,</L>
<L>Is shaken with the wind, and most opprest,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="18">
<HEAD>18</HEAD>
<L>Mallice still layes her seige against that tower,</L>
<L>Where vertue keepes the doore, honour the ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>One of them is not worth her mustred power.</L>
<L>A Cat doth scorne to play with a dead mouse.</L>
<L>'Tis cowardize to sticke one on the grou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Who falls to earth, can be no lower found▪</L>
</LG>
<LG N="19">
<HEAD>19</HEAD>
<L><HI>Spayne,</HI> envy's mother, Mallice nurserie,</L>
<L>Squinting with both those eyes at her, that m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>This stripling Ile in strength the world outvie,</L>
<L>Building a walking wall, and fence to shade.</L>
<L>This little vine from forraigne foemen's stren<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Summons her forces, and invades at length.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="20">
<HEAD>20</HEAD>
<L>Have not you seene the wood's greene God de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Like a stout <HI>Amazon</HI> begirt with bays,</L>
<L>Marshalling all her troopes of Trees t' withstan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The insurrect'on of the wind, that playes</L>
<L>With them, &amp; makes them seeme to march wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Whil'st others seeme to rise, and others fall.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="21">
<PB N="65" REF="41"/>
<HEAD>21</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he placeth in the front the lofty Pine,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he sturdy Cedar, with the Pine doth goe,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd then she calles the oake in his ball crine:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hese march a breast t' withstand the strongest</L>
<L>And keepe out <HI>Aeolus</HI> from darting feare</L>
<L>At th' young Artillery, which march i'th' reare. blow</L>
</LG>
<LG N="22">
<HEAD>22</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st thus Spain's Coronell did march away</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efore that wandring wood, which danc't o'th</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s if that <HI>Orpheus</HI> had bin there to play,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd leade them, with his musick, captive slaves. waves,</L>
<L>The little ships about the great, did dance,</L>
<L>As maids of <HI>May,</HI> about the May-pole prance.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="23">
<HEAD>23</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ollicy joynes, with virtue, hands to helpe,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he greater vessell rides before the lesse,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey set the Lyon for to guard the whelpe,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat's couchant, whilst the other rampant is▪</L>
<L>But all together seem'd so vaft, we thought</L>
<L>Neptune had in his fist, an Iland caught.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="24">
<HEAD>24</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Captaine of each ship, Ambition:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Master, Pride: Envie, the Gunner was▪</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Pilot, Ignorance her blinder sonne:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Sailers, prest from <HI>Charon's</HI> keele, did passe,</L>
<L>Over his ferry, and arriv'd at Spaine,</L>
<L>The Feinds were glad such pay to entertaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="25">
<PB N="68" REF="42"/>
<HEAD>25</HEAD>
<L>Their sailes did swell in hope of victory,</L>
<L>That made them bring so much of ware-house roo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>As if they meant the Iland should not lye;</L>
<L>But they would ship it over into Rome.</L>
<L>They rid so proudly all, as if they all</L>
<L>Were of the narrow Seas, joynt Admi rall.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="26">
<HEAD>26</HEAD>
<L>They look't, when <HI>Neptune</HI> would give up his ma</L>
<L>And make them primate-lords of <HI>albion's court</HI></L>
<L>They make no friends unto <HI>Bellona's</HI> pace</L>
<L>For warre munition, but to Pluto's host,</L>
<L>They send for scorpion-whips, as if they mea</L>
<L>To whip us from our Iland Tenement.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="27">
<HEAD>27</HEAD>
<L>But mountaines do oft times bring forth a mou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>High towers weakely built the sooner dy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L>A Castle in the aire is not an house,</L>
<L>Conquest in <HI>Arras</HI> is no victoy.</L>
<L>Bold confidence will ne're prove armour stro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Who stands upon his own leggs, stands not lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="28">
<HEAD>28</HEAD>
<L>Heav'n from the ships discry'd each towring m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And fear'd they went <HI>Ioves</HI> Pallace to invade:</L>
<L>For as the sailers climb'd the ropes with hast,</L>
<L>They seem▪d to saile heav'n's cristall wals, &amp; ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A passage through the clouds to enter there,</L>
<L>And of her fpark'ling <HI>Diadems</HI> rob the sphear</L>
</LG>
<LG N="29">
<PB N="69" REF="42"/>
<HEAD>29</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd now the Gods began to count the warre</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>heir owne, and joyn'd their forces with us too▪</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eav'n shootes a warning pen to end the jarre,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r else to tell them theire a common foe.</L>
<L>Then muster'd up the sea▪s, and prest the wind</L>
<L>To joyne in battell; heav'n and earth combind.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="30">
<HEAD>30</HEAD>
<L><HI>Aeolus</HI> with a gast break's ope his denne,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd ragiug sailly'd forth to graspe each wave,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen with his wider throat call'd <HI>Neptune's</HI> men</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rom calme security, and made them rave.</L>
<L>The winds o're take winged ambition's flight,</L>
<L>Their I ride, a Prouder wave did swallow quit.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="31">
<HEAD>31</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome hang on <HI>Neptune,</HI> fawning on his ceck,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oping to bribe wit'h prayers their enimy,</L>
<L>He straight receives them with a foaming check,</L>
<L>Yet with his full embraces makes them dye.</L>
<L>Some drown'ed in drinking seas ne're see the land</L>
<L>Some feele the land, but sinck in drunken sands</L>
</LG>
<LG N="32">
<HEAD>32</HEAD>
<L>Others before they're drown'd are drown'd in</L>
<L>And therefore flye to harder rocks for pitty,</L>
<L>The rocks do borrow brine to drop downe teares fears</L>
<L>That they may mourne for them, but lends no pit∣ty.</L>
<L>Those, that enjoy'd the mercies of the seas,</L>
<L>Are cast away upon the rocky lays.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="33">
<PB N="68" REF="43"/>
<HEAD>33</HEAD>
<L>Some flye, and ferry o're the newes to Spaine,</L>
<L>Some yeeld, as glad to veiw our conquering Isl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Though they dye Captives here in living paine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Some sharke away by some preventing wile,</L>
<L>But all being conquer'd all together yeeld</L>
<L>To wind or warr, to rocks or <HI>England's</HI> sheil</L>
</LG>
<LG N="34">
<HEAD>34</HEAD>
<L>Have you not seene how in th' Olympick game,</L>
<L>After the Conquerer hath wonne the prize;</L>
<L>The people raise the dust, to choake up fame:</L>
<L>Vnlesse she tell the world his enterprize.</L>
<L>One plucks from <HI>Daphnes</HI> head a lock of bay</L>
<L>Another tunes his victory in lays.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="35">
<HEAD>35</HEAD>
<L>So lov'd <HI>Eliza</HI> came from <HI>Tillbury</HI></L>
<L>Attended with her conquering loyall traine,</L>
<L>Led by the Gods, who did discend the skie</L>
<L>To leade her forth, and bring her back againe;</L>
<L>That tongue be silenced, which cannot keep</L>
<L>Her memory from an <HI>Endineion's</HI> sleepe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="36">
<HEAD>36</HEAD>
<L>Glad peace reviv'd, and decked with the spoyle,</L>
<L>That came from <HI>Spain's</HI> Armado, she did stand</L>
<L>At <HI>London's</HI> prouder gates, and with a smile</L>
<L>Welcom'd <HI>Eliza</HI> home, then kist her hand,</L>
<L>Who greiv'd, that peace had hurt her waiting eye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Sate down, that she might rest upon her thighe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="37">
<PB N="69" REF="43"/>
<HEAD>37</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e slept, and for her former watchings tooke</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e licence of a longer graunted sleepe;</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iza</HI> reckning her, would often looke</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on her face, and still for joy did weepe.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rinces love peace, &amp; should their combates mea∣sure</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o keepe their own, not get a forraigne treasure</L>
</LG>
<LG N="38">
<HEAD>38</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace slept, but as she slept did often start,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s if some dreame mudded her phancy still,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd in hir sleepe, she tooke <HI>Eliza's</HI> part,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s if she had foreseene approaching ill</L>
<L>March towards her, &amp; then within hersleeep</L>
<L>Shee'd prate <HI>Eliza's</HI> name, and closer creepe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="39">
<HEAD>39</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t slept she, 'till amazement made her rise,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen in her sleepe she wak't, till <HI>Morpheus</HI> tooke</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r heavie shackles from her leaden eyes,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rst op't her sluce of teares, and then awoke.</L>
<L><HI>Eliza</HI> melting ask't what feinds opprest</L>
<L>Her start▪ing phancy, scar'd her from her rest.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="40">
<HEAD>40</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>his Empresse with a milder voyce</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om <HI>Philomele,</HI> when she did prostrate lye, then came</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efore the bryer ravisht with the same)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eplyed thus: (Heroick Royaltie)</L>
<L>I dreamt, and thought I saw Rom's Synod sett</L>
<L>In a close celler, full as darke as jett.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="41">
<PB N="72" REF="44"/>
<HEAD>41</HEAD>
<L>There sate sad envy with thin-chapt despaire,</L>
<L>Dull Ignorance, with superstition,</L>
<L>And nexr <HI>Erynnis</HI> with disheav'led haire</L>
<L>Like to uncombed Snakes: Devotion</L>
<L>The incestuous brood of blinder zeale, wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ther<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Which turn'd the <HI>Synod</HI> like the wandring</L>
</LG>
<LG N="42">
<HEAD>42</HEAD>
<L>Me thought I hear'd their councell deep as Hell spheare</L>
<L>They did decree to act on hidden sage,</L>
<L>Where treason Prolouge was, and sceane as wel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And thus make <HI>England's</HI> Throne goe equipage.</L>
<L>With lower earth, and yet no eye should kno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The hand that struck, nor yet the hidden blow</L>
</LG>
<LG N="43">
<HEAD>43</HEAD>
<L>I saw the Feind, that drew the Tragick plot</L>
<L>With buried eyes, Lent-cheeks, in Less'us plight</L>
<L>I knew not what he was, a man or not,</L>
<L>But by his ball-pate seem'd a Iesuite.</L>
<L>Hell gave a Plaudit to the Tragaedy,</L>
<L>Which clapt mee from my sleepe security.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="44">
<HEAD>44</HEAD>
<L>But Innocency straight came swing'd from Iove,</L>
<L>And bid <HI>Eliza</HI> shake off drooping feare:</L>
<L>The Gods of late did in their armour move</L>
<L>Fighting for her, and will they now forbeare:</L>
<L>No, no, the Dove shall fly with carelesse wing</L>
<L>And never feare the Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hawkes to wreing.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="45">
<PB N="73" REF="44"/>
<HEAD>45</HEAD>
<L>Then Poast from heav'n <HI>Iov's</HI> cheifest Herald came</L>
<L>Mounted on Plumes pluckt from a Cherubin:</L>
<L>His coate was azure, spangled with the traine</L>
<L>Of <HI>Vesper's</HI> glittering-crue: which late was seene</L>
<L>About <HI>Orion,</HI> for he snatcht it thence,</L>
<L>As he came downe from <HI>Lov's</HI> high excellence.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="46">
<HEAD>46</HEAD>
<L>Passing through Heav'ns rich wardrobe in his flight,</L>
<L>Where starres enamel'd round with blew appeare</L>
<L>He tooke a longer robe more bright then light,</L>
<L>But as he past the purer fierie Spheare,</L>
<L>Dipt in the Element his robe, did seeme</L>
<L>Like flaming <HI>Phabus</HI> yellow Saphton beame.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="47">
<HEAD>47</HEAD>
<L>As he came downeward in his journey lower</L>
<L>He overtooke the gloomy hoast, that shrouds</L>
<L>Heav'ns face in darkenesse: <HI>Phaebus</HI> sent before</L>
<L>His beames to mixe a Rainebow in those clouds,</L>
<L>That he might take it for a scarfe, and tye</L>
<L>About his arme, in signe of Victorie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="48">
<HEAD>48</HEAD>
<L>Next as he cut the lower Region,</L>
<L>His wings struck Musick in the airy Spheare,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen all the feather'd Queristers began</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd strove, to raise a consort with him there,</L>
<L>Thus plaid heav'ns herald w<SUP>th</SUP> their musiek down</L>
<L>Directing him the way to <HI>Albion's</HI> Crowne.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="49">
<PB N="74" REF="45"/>
<HEAD>49</HEAD>
<L>Arriv'd at length with loyall feet, he goes</L>
<L>(Faith and good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>speede are wings for <HI>Mercury)</HI></L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Eliza's</HI> Court, there to disclose</L>
<L>His whole Ambassage from Iov's Majestie.</L>
<L><HI>Eliza</HI> dranke the newes: appoynts a day</L>
<L>To heare, what <HI>Iav's</HI> Ambassadour shall say.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="50">
<HEAD>50</HEAD>
<L>And now her busie soule is full possest,</L>
<L>Wrapt in the deepest robes of richest glory,</L>
<L>Shee 'dornes her selfe, against <HI>Iove</HI> prooves a gues</L>
<L>That with a reall acted fuller story</L>
<L>Of brighter Majestie, she might receive</L>
<L>Old <HI>Atlas</HI> Nephew, and more luster give.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="51">
<HEAD>51</HEAD>
<L>Thus have I seene the lovely <HI>Nymphs</HI> trip 'ore</L>
<L>The Mountaines from <HI>Pactolus</HI> sand,</L>
<L>Laden with all the treasure they there store,</L>
<L>All following Hymen at his first command.</L>
<L>Then round about the lovely bride they g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To crowne hor, with a wedding Coronet:</L>
</LG>
<LG N="52">
<HEAD>52</HEAD>
<L>One doth unfold her richer lap, a shop,</L>
<L>Where Corall, Christall, Amber, Rubye shine,</L>
<L>Another takes them from her <HI>Indy</HI>-lap,</L>
<L>And doth them into cunning bracelets Coine,</L>
<L>Placing them with such art to such a twist</L>
<L>That evry one lends glory to the rest.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="53">
<PB N="75" REF="45"/>
<HEAD>53</HEAD>
<L>One curles her tresses with rich Diadems,</L>
<L>Another sends a pendent to her eares,</L>
<L>Hir neck, one bindeth with a lace of Gemmes,</L>
<L>A fourth to deck her robes the glittering Spheares</L>
<L>But on <HI>Diana's</HI> carefull breast there be</L>
<L>An <HI>Onyx,</HI> friend to purer Chastity.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="54">
<HEAD>54</HEAD>
<L>Thus <HI>Amphetrite</HI> met her bride-groome going</L>
<L>Deckt with those Diadems fond <HI>Neptune</HI> sent</L>
<L>As tokens to her; when He went a woing:</L>
<L>Thus girt with luster, Goddesse <HI>Iuno</HI> went,</L>
<L>When first she came in all her wedding state</L>
<L>With open lap high <HI>Iove</HI> to recreate.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="55">
<HEAD>55</HEAD>
<L>But brave <HI>Eliza's</HI> glory did not shine</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om her owne Spheare alone, she round about</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as circled with a luster more divine,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen that of <HI>Sols,</HI> which doth the Starres put out.</L>
<L>Thus <HI>Cynthia</HI> have I seene Queene-Regent ride</L>
<L>Whil'st all her court of stars shine by his side.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="56">
<HEAD>56</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e sister <HI>Graces</HI> were her virgin-maides</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> honour, clad with full variety,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee did for them with chast <HI>Diana</HI> trade</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ho spunne a thread of flaxen purity.</L>
<L>Then wove it into roules more white then white▪</L>
<L>And broyder'd them, about with various light.</L>
</LG>
<PB REF="46"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="46"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="47"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="47"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="58" REF="48"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="59" REF="48"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<LG N="89">
<PB N="85" REF="49"/>
<HEAD>89</HEAD>
<L>Thinks earth, I feare her troopes by land▪ or sea</L>
<L>Thinks Heav'n tho <HI>Cyclops</HI> battaile I doe feare?</L>
<L>My forces are as strong as both can be,</L>
<L>I care not for those claps, that mock the ayre.</L>
<L><HI>Iov's</HI> thunder will but drown our bellowing noi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>His flashings will bnt light our dark'ned joye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="90">
<HEAD>90</HEAD>
<L>You, you are our beloved; we repose</L>
<L>Great confidence in Rome: and with full joy</L>
<L>Wee'l lay our Scepters at your fee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, depose</L>
<L>And pawne our Kingdomes for you to annoy</L>
<L>Those that disturbe your peace: Tis you defen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Our right, and we will ours to you intend.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="91">
<HEAD>91</HEAD>
<L>Thus said (Deare Empresse, dearer to the Gods</L>
<L>Then <HI>Rome</HI> to bell) theire Legate sallyed forth,</L>
<L>And riding with the wind, did get the ods,</L>
<L>He poasted on so fast to tell the worth</L>
<L>Of his Ambassage to his Lord from hell,</L>
<L>And greet his Highnesse from th' infernall c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="92">
<HEAD>92</HEAD>
<L>Gladnesse now plumps their veines, their bones are fraugh</L>
<L>With marrow's fatnesse: <HI>Bacchus</HI> runnes so free</L>
<L>He with his staggering feet light <HI>Venus</HI> caugh</L>
<L>The stews keept open house: and patents flee</L>
<L>With a new licence from the Pop's broad-sea</L>
<L>To admit all, to that she common-weale.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="93">
<PB N="86" REF="49"/>
<HEAD>93</HEAD>
<L>Have you not heard how proud <HI>Darius</HI> steed,</L>
<L>With open neighings did his Lord proclame</L>
<L>King regent, just as if he meant indeed</L>
<L>To show in his new kind of laughing straine</L>
<L>How glad he was that day to celebrate</L>
<L>Which chose him Iennet for his riders state.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="94">
<HEAD>94</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen at the horses suffrage all the rest</L>
<L>With shouting give their voyces to the King,</L>
<L>As if they would joyne triumph with the beast</L>
<L>To guil'd the day with making up the thing</L>
<L>One throwes into the aire his frolick cap,</L>
<L>That it may dally in her wanton lap.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="95">
<HEAD>95</HEAD>
<L>Another from his purse dilated wide</L>
<L>As his free heart, let's flye a mint of gold</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat the poore commons there, may see him ride</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull mounted on his horse in printed mold.</L>
<L>Whil'st every cottage brings it's fagget mite</L>
<L>To eake the day with a lent bonfiers light.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="96">
<HEAD>96</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust thus the Romane crew</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere prickt up with the Message Hell return'd after their eares</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rom their God Pluto's darker-clouded spheares)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith joy begun to rage with envy burn'd.</L>
<L>Their hearts runne o're their hogs head found a vent,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith brimfil'd hearts, and full cups not content.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="97">
<PB N="86" REF="50"/>
<HEAD>97</HEAD>
<L>Now their exchange is tost with no discourse,</L>
<L>Bur who shall be installed Monarch here,</L>
<L>Who Prince of Wales, and who in royall cour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Shall orderly succeed each royall Peere?</L>
<L>What Iesuite or Bellarmine shall be</L>
<L>In <HI>Canterburies</HI> Arch-ship, or <HI>Yorke</HI> See.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="98">
<HEAD>98</HEAD>
<L>With what a couching plott, and hidden bate</L>
<L>They'd catch the Realme: nay England is their own<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To their Infernall King it's confiscate</L>
<L>They'd only come to take possession,</L>
<L>Not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or to fight or conquer) and they'l bring</L>
<L>Nothing but <HI>Peter's</HI> Keys to make them King</L>
</LG>
<LG N="99">
<HEAD>99</HEAD>
<L>But is Iove deafe, because he hath no care,</L>
<L>Or blind because no eye to see withall.</L>
<L>The waking eye, to which all things appeare;</L>
<L>The open eare, in which each thing doth fall,</L>
<L>Saw what he heard, and heard what he did s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The eye, and eare in God's his Diery.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="100">
<HEAD>100</HEAD>
<L>Seeing what envy had conceiv'd in <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Hearing what treason whispered in the dark,</L>
<L>The God into their councels-chamber come</L>
<L>Zealous to fence this swimming Iland barke,</L>
<L>Opening the booke of life, they cast up th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><HI>Eliza's</HI> vertues Chronocl'd in heaven.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="101">
<PB N="87" REF="50"/>
<HEAD>101</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd thus Conclude: what shall <HI>Eliza</HI> be</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o loyall to the Gods, so true to men,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith's sheild in making Faith her sheild, shall we</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rowne her to stand and fight for truth, and then</L>
<L>Suffer Rebellion from our common foes</L>
<L>To Snatch both Crowne from her, and truth depose?</L>
</LG>
<LG N="102">
<HEAD>102</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o, no, <HI>Eliza</HI> is to us more deare:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur truth's as deare to her: we will defend</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Faith's defender from all forraigne feare</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et us to her a love-ambassage send.</L>
<L>Goe Mercury, said they, to <HI>Albion's</HI> Throne</L>
<L>Vnfold Heaven's secrets unto her alone.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="103">
<HEAD>103</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd now (dread Queene) know thus much, all was true</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat fell from heaven in that prophetiek dreame,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hich grace unfolded in his sleepe to you,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he boyling fury of your foes did steeme</L>
<L>Into a fog, and all the heaven's or'e spread,</L>
<L>But by Ioves brighter shine 'tis scattered.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="104">
<HEAD>104</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Gods have lent you as their choicest gemme</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om heavens rich cabanet to <HI>England▪s</HI> front,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat you might shine within that Diadem,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd quite blinde Envy as shee looks apon't.</L>
<L>Spain Sees, &amp; covers, fame would steale it thence</L>
<L>That England's faith might loose her reverence.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="105">
<PB N="88" REF="51"/>
<HEAD>105</HEAD>
<L>But at <HI>Ioves</HI> councell-table 'tis decreed,</L>
<L>The world no longer shall this gemme retaine,</L>
<L>'Twas onely taken from the richer breed</L>
<L>To show the world and put it up againe.</L>
<L>Iewells of richer prize are not long worne;</L>
<L>Virtues unto more crownes then one is borne</L>
</LG>
<LG N="106">
<HEAD>106</HEAD>
<L>Kings have their change of robes: <HI>Eliza</HI> shall</L>
<L>Have change of crownes, and royall Scepters to</L>
<L>If earth won't suffer her to shine at all</L>
<L>In her unborrowed brightnesse here below,</L>
<L>The Gods will place her as a fixed starre</L>
<L>Shooting forth glory from a richer spheare.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="107">
<HEAD>107</HEAD>
<L>No (blest <HI>Eliza) Rome</HI> shan't circumvent</L>
<L>With buried treason or coucht pollicie</L>
<L>Thy Majesty or state at Parliament;</L>
<L>The Gods decree <HI>Eliza</HI> first shall dye</L>
<L>They all are set in Parliament above,</L>
<L>Unto the upper honse thou must remove.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="108">
<HEAD>108</HEAD>
<L>At their late <HI>Synod</HI> thou wert chose to be</L>
<L>With the ioynt sufrage of that royall house</L>
<L>One of <HI>Ioves</HI> privy-councellers, that he</L>
<L>His royall secrets might to. The disclose,</L>
<L>Heav'n hath prepar'd a crowne, that thou ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> reign</L>
<L>Among the Gods to judge both <HI>Rome</HI> &amp; <HI>Spa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></L>
</LG>
<LG N="109">
<PB N="89" REF="51"/>
<HEAD>109</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>his measur'd out the length of heaven's decree;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>his was <HI>Ioves</HI> A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iassye in full gommission.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> humble pride <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Queene as shee</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eceiv'd the news <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> renew'd condition,</L>
<L>And straight shee▪s sick of love, sick to enjoy</L>
<L>Her chang, her crown, her all, then dye for ioy.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="110">
<HEAD>110</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut first before death did divorce her soule.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r heav'n espouse it to another bridegroome.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s peace did by the love-sick bed condole</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er dying Patron in the fainting Roome;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Eliza</HI> turning but her eye (her eye</L>
<L>Through which death looked out with maiesty.)</L>
</LG>
<LG N="111">
<HEAD>111</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id there espy her ancient servant peace,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bout to dye for griefe, as if she'd faine</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe with <HI>Eliza</HI> to the grave, de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>case</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>liza</HI> dead, and with her still remaine.</L>
<L>Shee saw her, and then said I must leave thee</L>
<L>Unto my kingdome as a legacy▪</L>
</LG>
<LG N="112">
<HEAD>112</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ake from my fainting head this fading Crowne</L>
<L>That I may lay mine honour in the dust)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen from thy facred hand present renowne</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nto our dearest <HI>Iames,</HI> whilst you intrust</L>
<L>His honor'd temples with our Diadem,</L>
<L>And with thy presence still attend on him.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="113">
<PB N="91" REF="52"/>
<HEAD>113</HEAD>
<L>With this <HI>Eliza</HI> ended: For her soule</L>
<L>(As if it meant to goe along with peace)</L>
<L>Departed flying to the highesti Pole</L>
<L>Translated to a crowne of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>liffe, and case</L>
<L>Death opened wide a gate of life to her</L>
<L>That she through Death might scape both dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> &amp; fear</L>
</LG>
<LG N="114">
<HEAD>114</HEAD>
<L>Have not you seene a palsie feare possesse</L>
<L>The guilty Traitor, as he dying stands</L>
<L>In expectation of a Death that guesse</L>
<L>Made over to him from the Iudges hands,</L>
<L>Feare making suite to death, that standeth by</L>
<L>Death bring a Pardon, that he may not die.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="115">
<HEAD>115</HEAD>
<L>Iust thus when <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Spaine</HI> rid circvite∣jud</L>
<L>Of lise and Death on <HI>Englands</HI> Soveraigne,</L>
<L>Both brib'd to falsehood by a festred grudge</L>
<L>Shee sentenc'd was to dye, but all in vaine</L>
<L>Iove sends his privy seale the death, and he</L>
<L>Brings her a parden, that shee may not dye.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="116">
<HEAD>116</HEAD>
<L>Shee dyes; yet dyes not, dying doth escape</L>
<L>Thy tyranny, which hov'ring o're did move</L>
<L>Vpon death's borrowed wings, to make a rape</L>
<L>With fastned tallys on this virgin dove.</L>
<L>Iove takes Her from his Crowne, that so her Crow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>May not be tooke from her, e're she go down</L>
</LG>
<LG N="117">
<PB N="92" REF="52"/>
<HEAD>117</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd now <HI>Eliza's</HI> dead; who did bequeath</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir virtues as a royall shrine to Crowne</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uceeding Iames with a true noble wreath,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ommending peace to him as <HI>Guardion.</HI></L>
<L>All shined in him with so full a blisse,</L>
<L>As if her soule had beene espous'd to his</L>
</LG>
<LG N="118">
<HEAD>118</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd these had bin her portion: Can you tell</L>
<L>What was full Regent in her royall breast,</L>
<L>Which was not in our <HI>Solomon</HI> as well</L>
<L>Say what in her, and that in him was best,</L>
<L>As if that nature kept her mol'd to fash</L>
<L>Him after her in each proportion.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="119">
<HEAD>119</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd so this Peere did reigne, that had not shee</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rst swayd the Scepter with so full a grace</L>
<L>Thad bin a sin to thinke that sex could be</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Masculine to keepe him equall p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce</L>
<L>But Iove did disinherit all their Kin</L>
<L>To make this woman, and this Masculine.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="112">
<HEAD>112</HEAD>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>haebus</HI> can doe no more then call the day,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd Phebe lesse, shee can but guild the night,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or he can lend the night an helping ray,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or Shee put out to use a minut's light.</L>
<L>Night gives to day, and day to night the way</L>
<L>But these maintained still a constant day.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="121">
<PB N="91" REF="53"/>
<HEAD>121</HEAD>
<L>As soone as blest <HI>Eliza</HI> did goe downe.</L>
<L>Iames rise with glory on our Hemi-spheare.</L>
<L>Thus Scepters yeeld to Scepters, crowne to crow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In constancy is always constant here</L>
<L>Kingdomes like <HI>Ianus</HI> have a double face;</L>
<L>They look on both sides with an equall grac</L>
</LG>
<LG N="122">
<HEAD>122</HEAD>
<L>Have you not seene the ray enous Lyon run</L>
<L>With roaring stomack for to seek a prey,</L>
<L>Snuffling the until'd forrest once begun</L>
<L>With hunger-biting nose to finde the way</L>
<L>Rending the aire now, with a thundring throa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Then bounding o're the Hills, bequeath's a no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="123">
<HEAD>123</HEAD>
<L>Of terror to the trembling vallie by,</L>
<L>Where innocency shroud's it selfe for feare</L>
<L>Among the little lambs, that there doe lye</L>
<L>And frightned often doe their food forbeare,</L>
<L>Then when in hot pur suite sh'hath lost the da</L>
<L>Shee follows night more eager for a prey.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="124">
<HEAD>124</HEAD>
<L>Thus, thus the Lyon of the infernall tribe</L>
<L>Out run <HI>Eliza's</HI> dayes in hot careere,</L>
<L>Thinking his ya wning stomack thus to bribe</L>
<L>By making her a prey; and faine would tare</L>
<L>Her selfe and throane in sunder, till they be</L>
<L>Made Morsells for his whelpish pedegree.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="125">
<PB N="92" REF="53"/>
<HEAD>125</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd then once loosing his desired prey,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is cheated stomack barks with hotter rage:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow nothing will goe downe, but Majesty</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e rounds the Iland to renew his age</L>
<L>With some well married prey, at length he saw</L>
<L>Another game provided for his paw.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="126">
<HEAD>126</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he buṙied Embers of that ash-heapt treason,</L>
<L>Which lay like quenched coales in sawdust hid,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome rakes up with the hand of blinded reason</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd blows them with false zeale, untill they breed</L>
<L>With hatching heate a treason, which may be</L>
<L>A plot-forme unto all cōnspiracy.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="127">
<HEAD>127</HEAD>
<L>What though proud <HI>England</HI> lately lost her head</L>
<L>The crowne hath luster still: the right hand's gone,</L>
<L>But where's the Scepter though? <HI>Eliza's</HI> dead,</L>
<L>But <HI>Iames</HI> is from her Phaenix-ashes sprung</L>
<L>Starrs rise &amp; fall; the clouds are low and high</L>
<L>Princes decease, but kingdomes never dye,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="128">
<HEAD>128</HEAD>
<L>The crowne is placed on a sager Head</L>
<L>Shining in golden Fleece: From thence will spring</L>
<L>More rays of wisdom: deep fetcht councel's breed</L>
<L>And nimble pollicy where reignes a King.</L>
<L>A stronger arme the Scepter now doth sway,</L>
<L>A woman's but a warrier for a day</L>
</LG>
<LG N="129">
<PB N="95" REF="54"/>
<HEAD>129</HEAD>
<L>Yet stout <HI>Eliza</HI> like a Gyant rose</L>
<L>And with an heart hoopt in, with valour stoo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>At Tillburie our forces to appose</L>
<L>And scattered like the wind th' <HI>Armade</HI> wood</L>
<L>But now we meet both strength &amp; wisedom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> doo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Pollicy may, but both must overcome.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="130">
<HEAD>130</HEAD>
<L>If once their Queene was such a whip to <HI>Spain</HI> tam</L>
<L>Their King will be a Scorpion: was shee</L>
<L>Rom's feare? hee'l make Hell shake and Pluto</L>
<L>Strength must not guide the sterne, but Pollicy</L>
<L>Close wrapt in treasons must sit there, if w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Or hope to get, or get the victory.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="131">
<HEAD>131</HEAD>
<L>And now that treason, which did seeme to sleep</L>
<L>And slept, <HI>Eliza</HI> sleeping; they awake.</L>
<L>The Goaler-Iesuite, which her did keepe</L>
<L>Close Prisoner in his dungeon, now must take</L>
<L>The fetters from her, let her loose, that shee</L>
<L>May range about, and sit on Majesty.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="132">
<HEAD>132</HEAD>
<L>Thus have I seen foul guilt, and sad despaire</L>
<L>Making the Malefactor guilty cry,</L>
<L>And after they condemned Him to feare</L>
<L>Forced the Iudge to sentence him to dye,</L>
<L>And yet at length hath sue'd his pardon too,</L>
<L>Which graunted, he more villanous doth gro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="133">
<PB N="96" REF="54"/>
<HEAD>133</HEAD>
<L>What though the treason slept, the Traitors still</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ept scouting eyes, &amp; watchfull heads from fleep:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asting so long from villany, they will</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reake up their Lent, a cruell Easter keepe.</L>
<L>And murther innocency, that they may</L>
<L>Really cellebrate that Holy-day,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="134">
<HEAD>134</HEAD>
<L>When slight and strength doe in a Duell fight,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rength seemes the conquerer, flight feares that day</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o takes her heeles, &amp; with a <HI>Parthian</HI> flight,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee kills her foe by running thus away;</L>
<L>So have I seen a Ram retreate, that he</L>
<L>With stronger hornes may butt his enemie,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="135">
<HEAD>135</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he aged hoary Winter now had seen</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ummer thrice wrapped in her winding sheetes,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hree races <HI>Phaebus</HI> with his steedes did winne</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut running the fierce Lion at three sweats,</L>
<L>That he was faine to get the crab to pace</L>
<L>His horses back, as he came from the race.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="136">
<HEAD>136</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd all this while hid treason buried lay,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd never knew a resurrection;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t length Rome thinkes to call a judgement day</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd summon <HI>Iames</HI> to know his censur'd doome.</L>
<L>A Spanish twigg shall strike the Poppys head.</L>
<L>The royall seed be sowen in Romish bed.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="137">
<PB N="95" REF="55"/>
<HEAD>137</HEAD>
<L>The Heroick top-bow of that noble stemme</L>
<L>Shall wither at the root, the branches fall.</L>
<L>The twiggs stript off, shall grafted be on them</L>
<L>That grow in <HI>Rome,</HI> till fruit sprout forth like g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Fed from the sop that fats the Iesl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ite</L>
<L>Forgetting all the former nurture quite.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="138">
<HEAD>138</HEAD>
<L>They'l reigne o're them that reigne or not at a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>They'l have more crown's then one or els have no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Lets tripling trees for them or rise or fall;</L>
<L>They'l aime at <HI>Cedars</HI> or let all alone</L>
<L>They weigh not London's mace, that pretty staff</L>
<L>They'l write at once all <HI>Englands</HI> Epitaph.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="139">
<HEAD>139</HEAD>
<L>At length the Gates of Darknesse open wide</L>
<L>Through which Hell's Ministers doe sally out</L>
<L>Though night-shades, sainted Devills, very pri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Those putrid poasts with false zeale gilt about,</L>
<L>With them their arch-ringleeder Iesuite,</L>
<L>Who vows allegeance to the Prince of migh</L>
</LG>
<LG N="40">
<HEAD><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>40</HEAD>
<L>He like his predicessor <HI>Iudas</HI> well</L>
<L>Comes compas't round with his riffe-raf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e rout,</L>
<L>The excrement of earth, the scumme of Hell;</L>
<L>Who er'e hath brawny hands, hearts steel'd abo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>For rapes, for murthers, and new cruelty</L>
<L>Are his assistants in this villany.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="1S1">
<PB N="97" REF="55"/>
<HEAD>1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>1</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n Euglish seed, which with rebellious lungs</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pit venome in their mothers face, and then</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>un o're to Rome, &amp; their bound heart &amp; tongues</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o serve Aprentiship, sent o're againe:</L>
<L>At home they toyle in journey worke for <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'entrap both mother, and her Soveraigne.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="142">
<HEAD>142</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>his done, He calls them round about t' unclose</L>
<L>His sealed heart: But first he makes them sweare</L>
<L>That none shall prove a comment to their foes</L>
<L>On this obscurer text: That all should feare</L>
<L>Th' unmanlike forfet of fidelity</L>
<L>If they intend to feed on Majestie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="143">
<HEAD>143</HEAD>
<L>Before he doth unlock his mind, hee'l first</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast bolt it too, aud barre it with an oath:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reason's companions are guilt, Feare, mistrust:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> telling it to tell it he is loath:</L>
<L>And yet hee'l tell it blabbing guilt alone</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irst feares himselfe, then her companion</L>
</LG>
<LG N="144">
<HEAD>144</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e brings the booke of life that they may seale</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaths warrant with it: they straight with a kisse</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o close both heart and lipps, that neither tell</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he secreacy, that now deliver'd is</L>
<L>Thus making Heav'n subscribe to Hell in sinne,</L>
<L>And seale the bond that they are all bound in</L>
</LG>
<LG N="145">
<PB N="98" REF="56"/>
<HEAD>145</HEAD>
<L>After wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h sacrilegious hands he steels</L>
<L>The Priests blood wine, and gives the Laitye;</L>
<L>They kisse the cup, and with a kisse each seales</L>
<L>His closest heart to keep this secrecy</L>
<L>Thus life to Death just transubstantiating</L>
<L>Whil'st they in one cup life and death suck i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="146">
<HEAD>146</HEAD>
<L>And now they stand prest vassells at the nod</L>
<L>Of <HI>Pluto</HI> to exact what e're he will,</L>
<L>He must serve Hell, that will not serve his God;</L>
<L>One servant cannot have two masters still</L>
<L>Their Captaine Iesuite conducts the way,</L>
<L>They lead by that false fire goe astray.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="147">
<HEAD>147</HEAD>
<L>Thus, thus those Hell combined Feinds doe mee</L>
<L>To satisfie blood thirsty appetite.</L>
<L>They march like threatning Comets through <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Which once appearing to th' amazed fight</L>
<L>Presage some bloody deluge or the Fate</L>
<L>Of Majestie or overthrow of state</L>
</LG>
<LG N="148">
<HEAD>148.</HEAD>
<L>At length their greedy feet o'retake the place</L>
<L>(Revenge doth seldome creep, but poasts awa</L>
<L>That place where treason stood to end the race▪</L>
<L>And did for them in expectation stay.</L>
<L>With death presaging engines that did show</L>
<L>Their foes had not a guard for such a blo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="149">
<PB N="99" REF="56" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>149</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th▪ English Troy-novant they pitcht the treason;</L>
<L>That royall seate, which beares the mother name,</L>
<L><HI>England's Pernassus,</HI> where diviner reason</L>
<L>Hath built her Throne, and honour rais'd her fame</L>
<L>The City, which this day hath <HI>Europe</HI> set</L>
<L>Above her sisters in full glory dight.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="150">
<HEAD>150</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat, which commands the <HI>Indys, France, &amp; Spain</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tripping them all of all their choicest treasures</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f wine and Spices, of the golden chaine,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd yet to all the world her bounty measures.</L>
<L>Feeding the hungry with a belly full:</L>
<L>The naked cloathing with her nappy woo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="151">
<HEAD>151</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l countrys worship Her, strive, and which shall</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esent her with the richest offering;</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rabia</HI> comes with her perfumed ball</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd gives it her as to the fairest Queene:</L>
<L><HI>Hydaspes</HI> flatters her with Odours too</L>
<L>Striving <HI>Arabia's</HI> sweetnesse to outgoe</L>
</LG>
<LG N="152">
<HEAD>152</HEAD>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aine</HI> drinks to her, and then send o're the cup</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at she may pledge her in the selfe same grape;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <HI>Parthians</HI> richer Diadems put up,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d come to her, with a rich laden lap.</L>
<L><HI>Ʋirgeinia</HI> sends Her that diviner weed,</L>
<L>Which had <HI>Iove</HI> tasted, he would begge the seede</L>
</LG>
<LG N="153">
<PB N="100" REF="57"/>
<HEAD>153</HEAD>
<L>Her streets no stree<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s but pleasant gardens are</L>
<L>Where little <HI>Hyacinth</HI> that lovely boy</L>
<L>Sports up and downe with young <HI>Narcissus</HI> faire</L>
<L>Tell me what is not there for Palate joy?</L>
<L>First fruits are duely paid to her, as if</L>
<L>Shee were Queene mother, of all Cities chief</L>
</LG>
<LG N="154">
<HEAD>154</HEAD>
<L>There you shall see the bloodbright cherry gro</L>
<L>With blushing ripenesse, e're Dame nature can</L>
<L>Couler her sister's paler-cheekes, which grow</L>
<L>In other places, with a faintish wan</L>
<L>The unprest wine full bottel'd you may se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In forward bunches, tempting of yonr eye</L>
</LG>
<LG N="155">
<HEAD>155</HEAD>
<L>Their various flowers dresse the rising spring,</L>
<L>As she hath new got up, and make her show</L>
<L>So glorious with her frequent varying,</L>
<L>That <HI>Iuno's</HI> bird being by would seeme a crow</L>
<L>Nay forward <HI>Hiblas</HI> top may well confesse;</L>
<L>To that, shee's but a wild spread wildernesse</L>
</LG>
<LG N="156">
<HEAD>156</HEAD>
<L>Tell me (Brave Citizen) if e're the day</L>
<L>Got up, <HI>Arabia</HI> did not call on thee:</L>
<L>If whil'st on tender downe each member lay</L>
<L>Thy bed seem'd not a <HI>Phoenix</HI>-nest to thee:</L>
<L>Thence from that gather'd garden did aris<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Such odours for thy morning sacrifice.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="157">
<PB N="101" REF="57"/>
<HEAD>157</HEAD>
<L>There planted is within her fruitfull wall</L>
<L>The tree of life, which spreads faire branches o're</L>
<L>Her confines, and with fatnesse feeds them all;</L>
<L>Their sprouts the tree of knowledg more &amp; more,</L>
<L>No worme, nor canker in the apple is:</L>
<L>'Tis not a garden, but a paradise.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="158">
<HEAD>158</HEAD>
<L>Close by Her swelling <HI>Thamasis</HI> doth glide</L>
<L>Fencing it with a snakelike twinning wall:</L>
<L><HI>Neptune</HI> doth every day come downe the tyde</L>
<L>And brings his Bride to see those stately halls</L>
<L>who veiwing them amaz'd such state to see</L>
<L>Sincks downe into an ebb, and back doth flee.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="159">
<HEAD>159</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust on her smelling breast a Towne doth floate,</L>
<L>The arched bridge <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thickset double row</L>
<L>Of houses hedge it, through it boates doe shoote</L>
<L>As swift as arrows from the <HI>Parthian</HI> bow.</L>
<L>With whose vast weight the river's prest so soare</L>
<L>'Tis forc't with louder murmurings to roare</L>
</LG>
<LG N="160">
<HEAD>160</HEAD>
<L>Beyond it you may see along her side</L>
<L>That monument of grace antiquity,</L>
<L><HI>Londons</HI> chiefe fort, the towning towers Pride:</L>
<L>Where <HI>Mars,</HI> and his munition prisoners lye:</L>
<L>Till peace disturbed by her foes put in</L>
<L>Sufficient bale to fetch them out againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="161">
<PB N="102" REF="58"/>
<HEAD>161</HEAD>
<L>Next neighbour to it stands oth sandy mold</L>
<L>That house, which with her dayly customes fils</L>
<L>Th' excheqnor with refined fleece of gold</L>
<L>Richer then <HI>Iason</HI> brought from <HI>Causa's</HI> hills,</L>
<L>Thither the <HI>Indian</HI> ships their riches bring</L>
<L>Vnloading yearely tribute to their King.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="162">
<HEAD>162</HEAD>
<L>Where <HI>Thamisis</HI> is broader set below</L>
<L>Running in deeper waves with lesser noise,</L>
<L>There you may see a navy proudly goe</L>
<L>Whilst full mouth'd <HI>Zephjrus</HI> their sailes doth hoise</L>
<L><HI>Thamis</HI> is <HI>London</HI> wall: the ships are all</L>
<L>The watchmen, <HI>London</HI> sets to keepe the wall</L>
</LG>
<LG N="163">
<HEAD>163</HEAD>
<L>Some lye returned from their two yeares race</L>
<L>And bring the prize with them which they did</L>
<L>By tilting with their Masts, running apace</L>
<L>At th' golden line to cut the Ecliptique string. winne</L>
<L>Some overcharg'd with wine begin to recle▪</L>
<L>But some discorging it they save the keele</L>
</LG>
<LG N="164">
<HEAD>164</HEAD>
<L>Some after they the fowler feas do scower</L>
<L>Licking his slimy filth on either side,</L>
<L>Rerurne with crazy ribs, beat with the power</L>
<L>Of thunder tempests, and a raging tyde</L>
<L>And there all furr'd with grasse in harbour lye▪</L>
<L>That they may cure their green-fick mala dye▪</L>
</LG>
<LG N="165">
<PB N="103" REF="58"/>
<HEAD>165</HEAD>
<L>Whilst others round about them sporting play</L>
<L>Not troubled with that lazy sloath defease)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>amaskt about their decks with glittering ray</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atched with beauty like <HI>Ioves</HI> cristall lays,</L>
<L>Sounding the trump to welcome <HI>Thetis</HI> down</L>
<L>Whil'st she conveys the Eccho to the towne.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="166">
<HEAD>166</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut on, and see that wooden Gyant rise</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith such a Monster crest, and threatning front</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou'd thinke hee'd wage new warrs against the skyes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd like the <HI>Gyant</HI> race soone set upon't</L>
<L>A ship so vast as if ten woods had beene</L>
<L>Cut downe to build it, when they did begin.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="167">
<HEAD>167</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ship, enough even of it selfe to make</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> navy, and hold stoutly out in play</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith an Armado: had it bin oth' lake</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith it, alone 't had frighted them away.</L>
<L>When once it plowes the feas, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪le boldly say</L>
<L><HI>Neptune</HI> will dive that he may give it way.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="168">
<HEAD>168</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> pallace fit for Majesty where he</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay keepe his court, and did he deeme it meet</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight ride a progresse in it: should it be</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sieged, with an hoast, till all their mea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Provided were devoured, they might plant</L>
<L>Plough, sowe within it to supply their want.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="169">
<PB N="104" REF="59"/>
<HEAD>169</HEAD>
<L>Bnt yet come back againe, and with the tide</L>
<L>Recover <HI>London</HI> bridge, that you may passe</L>
<L>(Whilst on a smoother wave you thorough glide</L>
<L>With safety on the equall tract of glasse,</L>
<L>Then feast your eyes on each side by the way,</L>
<L>Veiwing those frames, that cast so bright aray</L>
</LG>
<LG N="170">
<HEAD>170</HEAD>
<L>Leading to that, from whence <HI>Apollo</HI> spake</L>
<L>In <HI>Englands</HI> Oracle, renowned <HI>Iames;</HI></L>
<L>Where once that Prelate Monarch <HI>Woolsie</HI> took</L>
<L>His Primate dignities, those swelling names,</L>
<L>Which flow'd, and ebb'd at last like th' Emble<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>That rise, and fell so oft by's pallace side.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="171">
<HEAD>171</HEAD>
<L>White-Hall, where he once sate upon a Throne</L>
<L>Without a Crowne, and kept a Court, as if</L>
<L>His king were Prelate, and he King alone</L>
<L>Swaying both King and Scepter; till his life</L>
<L>Proclaim'd him Traitor, and his Pride prov'd s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Not lifting him so high, as't left him low.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="172">
<HEAD>172</HEAD>
<L>On either side faire <HI>Fabricks</HI> beautified</L>
<L>With <HI>Dedall</HI> cunning border it about:</L>
<L>On this the Minster mounts her facred head,</L>
<L>Where Britaines Kings in Christned pomp go o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Being then first crown'd with the Diadem</L>
<L>After dead <HI>Caesar</HI> yeeldeth up his stemme</L>
</LG>
<LG N="173">
<PB N="105" REF="59"/>
<HEAD>173</HEAD>
<L>There lyes the royall dust, and quiet bones</L>
<L>Of all our <HI>Henries,</HI> the Marble their</L>
<L>Weeps o're our famous <HI>Edwards</HI> and bemoanes</L>
<L><HI>Eliza's</HI> urne, paying a tribute teare</L>
<L>To her dead Soveraigne; till all the store</L>
<L>Quite spent, it drys to stone, and weeps no more</L>
</LG>
<LG N="174">
<HEAD>174</HEAD>
<L>On that side stands a Frame whose prouder spires</L>
<L>(Guilt on there crests with a deep <HI>Saphron</HI> beame)</L>
<L>Doe court the clouds, and kisse <HI>Ioves</HI> taper fires</L>
<L>Goe equipage with Heaven. and often seeme</L>
<L>To lend themselves to <HI>Atlas,</HI> while they beare</L>
<L>(To ease Him) on their tops the moving spheare</L>
</LG>
<LG N="175">
<HEAD>175</HEAD>
<L>A goodly Hall, which dares vye statelinesse</L>
<L>With all the patterns of our former dayes,</L>
<L>Brazen <HI>Colossus,</HI> tall <HI>Pyramides,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Ephesian</HI> temple shrin'd about with bays.</L>
<L>That high-fam'd structure, &amp; that polisht frame</L>
<L>Founded, and finished by th' <HI>Assyrian</HI> dame</L>
</LG>
<LG N="176">
<HEAD>176</HEAD>
<L>A well knit unity this house divide</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nto an upper, and a lower region,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o planets in their severall spheares abide</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et keepe a constant and united motion</L>
<L>The King like <HI>Titan</HI> from his flaming crest</L>
<L>Sparkles his mutuall glory to the rest.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="177">
<PB N="106" REF="60"/>
<HEAD>177</HEAD>
<L>With him, the Pawne of <HI>England's</HI> hopes, those twiggs</L>
<L>That sprouted from the aged royal Sire,</L>
<L>Shrin'k, as if <HI>Phaebus</HI> lent them pery wiggs;</L>
<L>Budding forth glory, which was blowen there</L>
<L>To fuller bightnesse, sitting next the King,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Ʋenus</HI> next <HI>Sol</HI> more light borrowing.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="178">
<HEAD>178</HEAD>
<L>With him, those two tops of <HI>Pernassus</HI> Hill,</L>
<L>Those tapers, which upon our altars stand</L>
<L>The two Arch Prelates, who with luster fill</L>
<L>The senate; luster, which poore oile maintain'd</L>
<L>Sincerer wisedome shin'd in them so bright,</L>
<L>Like th' greater put-out honours lesser light.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="179">
<HEAD>179</HEAD>
<L>With him, the rest of Brittain's noble traine</L>
<L>Those scarlet troopes, that shine in royall blood</L>
<L>Array'd in spotted Furres, richer then can</L>
<L>Be dapple dyed in <HI>Assyrian</HI> flood.</L>
<L>Glittering in brisker gemms then e're was set</L>
<L>On best of <HI>Parthian</HI> King or Coronet.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="180">
<HEAD>180</HEAD>
<L>With him, the Iudges all in cloath of goare</L>
<L>To Embleme that they sit on guilty blood;</L>
<L>Vnbrib'd <HI>Astraea</HI> beares the sword before,</L>
<L>They must not strike till justice thinke it good,</L>
<L>And draw the sword: She guides both blade and hand</L>
<L>Iudges condemne, but 'tis at her command.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="181">
<PB N="107" REF="60"/>
<HEAD>181</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll these with full united glory meet</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ike tapers mingled lights, which stronger shine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he trumpets <HI>Eccho</HI> triumphs to the street</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s they ride on with majesty divine.</L>
<L>The thronged commons twist their votes 'ith reare</L>
<L>Teaching the birds to sing an <HI>Ave</HI> there.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="182">
<HEAD>182</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey're ready now to mount that judgement hall</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>here Iustice sword stands bare, her ballance e∣ven</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce shink▪ her head, &amp; Impudence looks pale</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aring <HI>Astraea</HI> is come downe from Heaven</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>here stands <HI>Romes</HI> whipping post; the Iefuite</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lucks in his horns, &amp; thinkes of couching slight.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="183">
<HEAD>183</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow prayers <HI>Elysinm</HI> seale with winged flight,</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>natius</HI> cannot rest within his grave</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ey howle such votes to that grand Iesuite,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith prayers both whipt and stript his aide they crave</L>
<L>At length the Devill doth a plot infuse</L>
<L>And they sing Hymnes unto Ig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>atius.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="184">
<HEAD>184</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nder that stately house sly cellars creepe</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o adders under fairer flowe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou'd)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere <HI>Bacchus</HI> doth in drov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sie hogsheads sleep,</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enus</HI> there his bottel-nose doth crow'd</L>
<L>Night spreads her sable wings in dismall fort</L>
<L>Over the vault, and keeps continuall court.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="183">
<PB N="108" REF="61"/>
<HEAD>183</HEAD>
<L><HI>Pluto</HI> that treason-Patron from deepe Hell</L>
<L>Seing the <HI>Caverne</HI> with convenience set</L>
<L>So nigh his confines; and so apt a cell</L>
<L>To further their designe, he doth them greet</L>
<L>With larger summes from his owne treasury</L>
<L>To Stock the treason, and the cellar buy.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="184">
<HEAD>184</HEAD>
<L>Then summons all ▪pon paine of Hel's displea su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To midnight silence, whilst with equall dole</L>
<L>He doth his royall charge to each deliver,</L>
<L>Which did from him like louder thunder role.</L>
<L>They shiver all in cold amazement, while</L>
<L>They heare the thing, and yet they do it toyle.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="185">
<HEAD>185</HEAD>
<L>Tis thus <HI>(Heroick</HI> soules, our royall breed,</L>
<L>Borne for no meane disignes) let crackling bays</L>
<L>Whize out their slender fame, who onely bleed</L>
<L>In an <HI>Armado,</HI> that's not worth our praise</L>
<L>Wee'l build our <HI>Trophys</HI> on a Kingdom's rui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Or wee'l have none: The iron's hot, be doin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="186">
<HEAD>186</HEAD>
<L>Tis red for striking▪ Opportunity</L>
<L>Iust now hangs out her bush, catch hold on tha</L>
<L>Or else occasion's gone, sh'ath wings to flye:</L>
<L>If once the Synod rise, Time shows his pate,</L>
<L>Then fasten on his lock, and make him stay</L>
<L>To see and Chronicle November's day,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="187">
<PB N="109" REF="61"/>
<HEAD>187</HEAD>
<L>Iust when that furnish't fabrick shall begin</L>
<L>To swell with Pride, because in her the flower</L>
<L>Of drest nobility is compast in,</L>
<L>When Majestie sits under her spread bower,</L>
<L>Shining like <HI>Phebe</HI> in the azur plaine</L>
<L>Amids bespangled Uesper's glittering traine.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="188">
<HEAD>188</HEAD>
<L>When every state is plact, beginne your play,</L>
<L>Strait draw the curtaine from the Tragick s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eane,</L>
<L>Let hell appeare in her owne shape that day;</L>
<L>And let destruction sally forth unseene</L>
<L>When th' King with sugred speech is charming al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Send him a plaud it from th' infernall Hall.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="189">
<HEAD>189</HEAD>
<L>Then bullet up from that munition'd cell</L>
<L>Thy splintred barres, &amp; broken rocks to teare</L>
<L>The prouder walles in sunder, let all feele</L>
<L>What sands the bankes of <HI>Acharon</HI> doe beare.</L>
<L>Blow up the bottoms of their towers to heav'n</L>
<L>Levell their prouder top with <HI>Tellus</HI> even.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="190">
<HEAD>190</HEAD>
<L>Each haves his charge, all like the baite so well,</L>
<L>They chew upon it with a full delight:</L>
<L>Thrice watery stomachs long, untill they fill</L>
<L>Themselves with Majestie, they long for might.</L>
<L>Hope claps them on the back, &amp; cheeres them so</L>
<L>They feare not, care not what they undergoe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="191">
<PB N="110" REF="62"/>
<HEAD>191</HEAD>
<L>Have not you seene how aged summer casts</L>
<L>His shedding haire by handfulls from her head;</L>
<L>Her leaves tost up and downe by <HI>Autumn's</HI> blasts</L>
<L>Fall in full shoales till earth be covered:</L>
<L>Iust so in swarmes Hell's Harbingers doe fly</L>
<L>Sent to take up this shop of cruelty.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="192">
<HEAD>192</HEAD>
<L>And now as soone as night gave day the fall</L>
<L>They creepe into that caverne vaulted deepe,</L>
<L>But yet, not nigh enough to <HI>Pluto's</HI> Hall,</L>
<L>Where they they their engines &amp; munition keepe</L>
<L>They must delve deeper yet, 'tis their intent</L>
<L>To borrow <HI>Ʋulcan's</HI> forging tenement.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="193">
<HEAD>193</HEAD>
<L>With spades, and mattock forces they goe down</L>
<L>Like <HI>Hannabal</HI> they'l finde or make away;</L>
<L>They then besiege earth's closed dungeon</L>
<L>And carve out trenches in the mangled clay.</L>
<L>Break through resisting rocks, teare up the ground</L>
<L>The rivers trembling back at th' noyse resound.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="194">
<HEAD>194</HEAD>
<L>With beamy-yron-rowes they sticke the heart</L>
<L>Of Mother earth, that neigbouring <HI>Thamis</HI> grew</L>
<L>Sill to have shaking fits as day did part,</L>
<L>The earth so quak't with a quotidian ague.</L>
<L>They dig'd so farre <HI>Pluto</HI> was faine to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nd,</L>
<L>(Fearing an undermine) to bid them end,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="197">
<PB N="112" REF="62"/>
<HEAD>197</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd now they are within Hell's liberties</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rrived close at black <HI>Cocytus</HI> layes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey heare strong neighings, which do mock the skys,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hundring from steeds, that on <HI>Cocytus</HI> gaze.</L>
<L>They like the <HI>Omen,</HI> and petitiones make</L>
<L>That they that harnest teeme from Hell may take</L>
</LG>
<LG N="196">
<HEAD>196</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell grants commission, that they may unteather</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he <HI>Stygian</HI> brood, and knock their fetters off,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he coale-blacke double brace come up together</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urvetting over <HI>Aetna's</HI> hilly roofe.</L>
<L>All hooft with thunder, prancing as they came</L>
<L>They make each flint with lightning flashes flame</L>
</LG>
<LG N="197">
<HEAD>197</HEAD>
<L><HI>Aethon</HI> throwes mist into the thickned ayre</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om furnace-lungs breathing forth <HI>Sulphure</HI> fogs</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icteus</HI> with bushy taile doth sweepe it cleare,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill it all lyes on earth in scummy bogges.</L>
<L><HI>Orphaeus</HI> staring eyes with fire glow.</L>
<L>And in the ayre like kindled Meteors show.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="198">
<HEAD>198</HEAD>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lastor</HI> like swift <HI>Pegasus</HI> doth flee,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is wings deepe dipped in the <HI>Stygian</HI> booke</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe drop downe clouds of darkenesse, which doe</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Ile in sable black, &amp; makes her looke,</L>
<L>As if sh'ad bought her mourning, which she went dye</L>
<L>To hang on <HI>England's</HI> funerall monument.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="199">
<PB N="112" REF="63"/>
<HEAD>199</HEAD>
<L>Treason's wide warehouse now prepar'd, they yoa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>This blackbread broode unto Hells midnight <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Whose axletree well loaded 'gins to croake</L>
<L>Like death's Ambassadour, as Ravens jarre</L>
<L>In untun'd harmony, and croaking tole</L>
<L>A passing bell for some departing soule▪</L>
</LG>
<LG N="100">
<HEAD>100</HEAD>
<L>Full stuff't out barrells presse the groaning wain</L>
<L>Whose rising wombs, and empty nerves are fill'</L>
<L>With black blue <HI>Peter,</HI> that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nkindled gaine,</L>
<L>Which is through <HI>Stygian</HI> salted sand distill'd.</L>
<L>A little seede scattered on <HI>Erebus,</HI></L>
<L>And there to dryer mould, was parched thu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="201">
<HEAD>201</HEAD>
<L>The fiery horses draw this loade of sinne,</L>
<L>With staring maines, and racked joynts so long</L>
<L>Till foaming sweat doth dapple their black skin</L>
<L>And quite weare out the carmans whipping thon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>At length th'unload the wain, that they may loa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><HI>Bacchus,</HI> whil's they with these his barrels crou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="202">
<HEAD>202</HEAD>
<L>Thus adding fire to that tinder-fuell,</L>
<L>They strive to lick up with this dryer dust</L>
<L>That oylie liquor: faine would make a duell,</L>
<L>Whilst these, at those wel marshall'd barrels thru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But straight conclude their private quarrell so</L>
<L>That they joyne forces 'ganst a common <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="200">
<PB N="113" REF="63"/>
<HEAD>200</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd now the Horses draw with easer thighes,</L>
<L>Wantoning back to hell with frisking limbs</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pitting forth boyling foame abroad, which flyes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rom their unruly chaps in hizzing hymnes.</L>
<L>Quench in the colder ayre like cinders bright</L>
<L>Which in the water hizzing, quench their light.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="201">
<HEAD>201</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey feed on provinder of <HI>Stygian</HI> graines,</L>
<L>While <HI>Sterops</HI> and <HI>Pyracmon</HI> are at jarrs</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd sweat in blood of yellow <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ythians,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>triving who shall beate forth more Iron barrs.</L>
<L>Great store of sturdy <HI>Thracian</HI> Iron's sent</L>
<L>To forge at <HI>Ʋulcan's</HI> furnace-tenement.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="202">
<HEAD>202</HEAD>
<L>With this large minerall the second time</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey loade the cart, and weigh so ponderous</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t made hells baited horses blow againe:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ike slow Bootes now from <HI>Erebus</HI></L>
<L>They creepe along; their fiery mettall dyes</L>
<L>Yet night bring's all into their treasuryes.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="203">
<HEAD>203</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>here in that cavern's deepe abysse, they heape</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n Iron Pyramis, the Basis layd</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon the barrells, but the top shall creepe</L>
<L>Forc't up wards) to the heavens, and Iove invade</L>
<L>Had you but seene that monster you'd have thought</L>
<L>Peryllis there his brazen bull had brought.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="204">
<PB N="114" REF="64"/>
<HEAD>204</HEAD>
<L>They stay not, but with <HI>Pegasean</HI> speede</L>
<L>(Treason's suspitious alwaies of a vent)</L>
<L>They lash their horses backe with twining reed</L>
<L>Who swift as thawing winter's current went;</L>
<L>Then cut downe woods to billets, batter down</L>
<L>Their rotten woodden Gods to bring to town<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="205">
<HEAD>205</HEAD>
<L>Cast down their images, all gnawne within</L>
<L>To putred worme-holes, but dawb'd o're with pain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>That emblem, nay there God head, trunke divine▪</L>
<L>These they build o're for fuell coverment.</L>
<L>You would have sworne had you that pile but seene</L>
<L>The wooden horse had entred <HI>Troy</HI> agin.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="206">
<HEAD>206</HEAD>
<L>With pickaxes as sharpe as those that breake</L>
<L>The tougher yee of glazed <HI>Tanais,</HI></L>
<L>They next into some craggy paved creeke</L>
<L>(Where angry seas 'gainst foaming rocks do rise)</L>
<L>Launch forth, that they may cutt Don Neptunes warts</L>
<L>Hew downe I meane those raving rockes in parts.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="207">
<HEAD>207</HEAD>
<L>Digging whole quarryes from his monstrous side</L>
<L>Then dashing them to lesser thunderbolts,</L>
<L>Next downe the bankes of <HI>Phlegeton</HI> they glide,</L>
<L>And there take Captives all the damned doubts:</L>
<L>Make the day labourers to gleane the land,</L>
<L>Gathering the stones lye on th' unpav'd sand.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="208">
<PB N="115" REF="64"/>
<HEAD>208</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hilst others with rude mattocks dig up all</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>els regent-walke, and levell it alone</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith cinder dust, which from their forge doth fall;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay they'l not leave for <HI>Sysaphus</HI> a stone:</L>
<L>All joyne to build a fort for envy's hall</L>
<L>And hedge in treason with a rampant wall.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="209">
<HEAD>209</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d now 'tis built: they first dig deepe to lay</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> strong foundation, with a mixed rout</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f barrels stu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t with wine, and pouder-clay</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ake up, they build upon that bottom stout</L>
<L>Vpon the fire they heape on fuell wood,</L>
<L>Vpon the fuell barrs of Iron stood.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="210">
<HEAD>210</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon the Iron, stones their forces send</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ixing a quarrye with a Minerall:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast with a faintish flame the fire send</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t coldly upward Iron keepes downe all:</L>
<L>And, least the Iron with a falling <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it</L>
<L>Sinck downe, to blow it up the fier's set.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="211">
<HEAD>211</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us strength resisted growes the stronger still,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us contradicted passion rageth more:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Cammamell trod downe grow upward will,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bended bowes fly up, and strike more soare,</L>
<L>They hide the treason; darts foreseene will</L>
<L>Not hurt so much, forewarn'd forearmed still.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="212">
<PB N="116" REF="65"/>
<HEAD>212</HEAD>
<L>Now match the patterne: Let me see who dar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Discover his ranck blood, and say that he</L>
<L>Is of that kindred, envie will not share</L>
<L>With them, or take in more affinity.</L>
<L>These have ingrost the saile of blood; no fees</L>
<L>Can bribe up hell to grant more Patentees.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="213">
<HEAD>213</HEAD>
<L>Now treafon's ready drest to goe abroad,</L>
<L>And <HI>Faux</HI> hath borrow'd <HI>Plutos</HI> livery</L>
<L>To manne her: Hee's the Pimp to helpe her trad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>She never stirrs but in the night, and he</L>
<L>Is faine to snatch a fire-brand from Hell,</L>
<L>Which his dark-lanthorne-lights to guide h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sti</L>
</LG>
<LG N="214">
<HEAD>214</HEAD>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aux,</HI> whose black blood stood in his face, &amp; the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Emblem'd the couler of his filthy heart</L>
<L>Sooted with blacker vice, and swarthy feare,</L>
<L>Yet blood-red pampar'd with raw flesh: his pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>At every meale was wovsh milke, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame</L>
<L>From those two soare breasts, festred Rome an Spain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<LG N="215">
<HEAD>215</HEAD>
<L>With too officious duty he prepares</L>
<L>To lay his mistris cloaths against she rise;</L>
<L>Marshalls the barrels, rancks the Iron barrs,</L>
<L>Then primes the powder, traines it till it lyes</L>
<L>Close by the barrells mouth, ready to broach</L>
<L>The Treason: lights, &amp; blowes the kindled matc</L>
</LG>
<LG N="217">
<PB N="117" REF="65"/>
<HEAD>217</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd now he calls on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lowpac't aged Time</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hinking his waxen wings are melted quite,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ach minute seemes a day, each day as nine,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he houre-glasse is stop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, or runnes not right.</L>
<L>He sweares the clocks doe lye, and Sextons fee's</L>
<L>Greasing their fists, that they the wheeles may grease</L>
</LG>
<LG N="217">
<HEAD>217</HEAD>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen sends to Time that oylie ju<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, the Moone</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon her Heifers sprinkles; bids him noint</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is stiffened limbs with that, which <HI>Phaeton</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>upples his steeds; and chafe each sleeping joynt.</L>
<L>And yet Times crazy-staffe doth softly goe,</L>
<L>And yet his tyred leggs as lazy show.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="218">
<HEAD>218</HEAD>
<L>At length he offers dayly mattins to him</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ropping as many beades as words do fall:</L>
<L>He knitts both prayers and promises to woe him,</L>
<L>Come (Nimble Time) come to our <HI>Stygian</HI> hall</L>
<L>Il'e let Thee in to see a Tragedy</L>
<L>Where the Spectators act; The standers by</L>
</LG>
<LG N="219">
<HEAD>219</HEAD>
<L>Shall neither see nor heare; nor act, nor sceane</L>
<L>Doe measure it; no sugred words collouge</L>
<L>With peevish eares to begge a plaudit in:</L>
<L>The proloug here, shall be the Epiloug</L>
<L>And clap it selfe: a Tragaedy just donne</L>
<L>As soone as it is but in thought begunne.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="220">
<PB N="118" REF="66"/>
<HEAD>220</HEAD>
<L>Wee'l hang no false lights out to entertaine</L>
<L>The actors that their luster may more shine:</L>
<L>The candles here shall be the Tragick flame</L>
<L>Not lighted 'force the Tragedy begin.</L>
<L>A thought both light them shall, and put the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ou</L>
<L>So quick an <HI>exit</HI> brings the Sceane about.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="221">
<HEAD>221</HEAD>
<L>No musick here shall call the Prologue in,</L>
<L>But thunder-claps, &amp; shreeking cryes (which com</L>
<L>From tortur'd Princes to those Ecchoing,</L>
<L>This ceac't the play beginnes not, but 'tis done.</L>
<L>Nay, whilst the Sceane is acting you shall see</L>
<L>The stage pluckt downe: My sterious Tragedy</L>
</LG>
<LG N="222">
<HEAD>222</HEAD>
<L>Chiefe actors are but three, and they all drest</L>
<L>Iust in the whores attyre like puppet Rome:</L>
<L>Dull Ignorance comes out before the rest;</L>
<L>Hir maides are Errour, Superstition.</L>
<L>These follow ignorance still but on this stage</L>
<L>They all goe hand in hand just equipage.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="223">
<HEAD>223</HEAD>
<L>The stage is rudely built as low as Hell,</L>
<L>Hang'd round about with darker clouds &amp; mists</L>
<L>The walls thicke mud, caru'd out of Natur's cell</L>
<L>The roofe for Majesty faire bowers twists.</L>
<L>Set up in <HI>England,</HI> but the Actors come</L>
<L>Out of th' attyring house of puppets Rome.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="224">
<PB N="119" REF="66"/>
<HEAD>224</HEAD>
<L>Ignorance enters first, a wizled Dame</L>
<L>Wrapt in the seamelesse coate her Saviour wore:</L>
<L>So old, she's in her dotage; blind, and lame</L>
<L>Led by the Church, on crutches of the whore</L>
<L>In one hand there's a Bible clasped fast,</L>
<L>In th'other a dimme light, which can not last</L>
</LG>
<LG N="225">
<HEAD>225</HEAD>
<L>Next Errour staggers in, drunk with the wine</L>
<L>Of Fornication, reeling up and downe;</L>
<L>Tost with the wind of Church-faith varying</L>
<L>Walking with naked feete all scurfy growen</L>
<L>With dirty pennance: In one hand's a pardon,</L>
<L>Th' other a purse to pay for his salvation.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="226">
<HEAD>226</HEAD>
<L>After her gaudy superstition</L>
<L>In chang of costly cloaths still varying:</L>
<L>Her maid is counterfit Devotion,</L>
<L>Who carrys after her some holy shrine</L>
<L>Stole from the Virgin Ladies sacred brows,</L>
<L>To which with supple knees she humbly bows.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="227">
<HEAD>227</HEAD>
<L>Shee proudly walkes with tinckling feet, &amp; shines shrines,</L>
<L>In that same purple robe Christ once put on</L>
<L>Hung round about with beads, &amp; crown'd with</L>
<L>Wearing the God sh' adores with such renowne.</L>
<L>In one hand ther'es a candle ne're goes out,</L>
<L>A bell in th' other cursing all about.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="228">
<PB N="120" REF="67"/>
<HEAD>228</HEAD>
<L>Sometimes shee's loofely drest in Hermite leaves,</L>
<L>Girt with that cord about her hairy loyne,</L>
<L>With which, Christ whipt those buying selling</L>
<L>Out of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>emple, who did there conjoyne (theeve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Both God and Beliall in one house together,</L>
<L>Thus girt for pilgrimage, she wanders thither.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="228">
<HEAD>228</HEAD>
<L>Where all the sacred reliques treasur'dlye</L>
<L>To see the Angell <HI>Gabriel's</HI> plumes, who brought</L>
<L>The first newes of her Lords Nativity,</L>
<L>The thirty peeces which her Saviour bought,</L>
<L>The crosse, the nayles, the tombe, the spunge, reed,</L>
<L>The very vinegar, which he drank, is there (speare</L>
</LG>
<LG N="229">
<HEAD>229</HEAD>
<L>These three leade forth an old, blacke, meagar wight</L>
<L>With fatted eyes, blown cheeks, &amp; brothel crown,</L>
<L>Wrapt close in weeds of darkenes life grim night,</L>
<L>With necke into his shoulders shrouded downe,</L>
<L>With fleering chaps, his gag-teeth threatning all.</L>
<L>His very image was Hereticall.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="203">
<HEAD>203</HEAD>
<L><HI>Ignatius</HI> eldest sonne, an Epicene,</L>
<L><HI>Proteus</HI> in doctrine; a iust courtier Priest;</L>
<L>A wolfe in wooll; a glow-worme that doth shine</L>
<L>Most in the darke: a Sainted feind at best:</L>
<L>Rome in a Surplice, ranck hypocrisie,</L>
<L>Rotten, but painted o're divinitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="130">
<PB N="121" REF="67"/>
<HEAD>130</HEAD>
<L>A Iesuite; that monster pharifie</L>
<L>That fasts with sweet means, keeps a box forth' poore,</L>
<L>But <HI>Iudas</HI> like them fils his treasury.</L>
<L>What not? A just darke Lanthorne and no more.</L>
<L>Whose tongue is nothing but equivocations,</L>
<L>His heart made up of mentall reservations.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="231">
<HEAD>231</HEAD>
<L>He brings a map upon the stage wherein</L>
<L>Crownes pictur'd are, and Scepters cast aray:</L>
<L>But close by swordes are draw'n by coulering,</L>
<L>A cup of poyson's placed in the way.</L>
<L>Dasht braines, rent limbs, blood spiltly's pictur'd by</L>
<L>Thus Crownes they win, aud weare by cruelty.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="232">
<HEAD>232</HEAD>
<L>With that, he soone descends a loathly cell▪</L>
<L>And sets him downe just like <HI>Diogenes</HI></L>
<L>In's hogshead, where full barrels round Him well</L>
<L>And there upon a plot he shewing is,</L>
<L>Thinking to compasse more in's tub alone,</L>
<L>Then Alexander can upon his throne.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="232">
<HEAD>232</HEAD>
<L>At length he calls those Three, that set him on</L>
<L>Vpon that hideous task<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to doe this deed,</L>
<L>Ignorance, Error, superstition;</L>
<L>They 'plaud the deepenesse of his reaching head,</L>
<L>Promise to raise assistance, who shall cry</L>
<L>Out of his plot to make a Tragedye</L>
</LG>
<LG N="133">
<PB N="122" REF="68"/>
<HEAD>133</HEAD>
<L>One error bribes, another Ignorance,</L>
<L>But Superstition with her conjuring charm's</L>
<L>Commands them all, straight after her they dance▪</L>
<L>Hypocrifie religion soone takes arms</L>
<L>The chiefe were those three furys sent from Hell</L>
<L>To stand for treason, and keepe sentinell</L>
</LG>
<LG N="134">
<HEAD>134</HEAD>
<L><HI>Faux, Percy, Catsbey,</HI> Romes Trium-viri</L>
<L>Those Parri-regick people-regnicides;</L>
<L>Spirits incarnate, abstract blasphemy,</L>
<L>Who thrust at <HI>Iove</HI> through kings and Princes sides</L>
<L>White gun-powder, who kill without a noyse:</L>
<L>True lime who seeming quencht, then most a n∣noyse.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="135">
<HEAD>135</HEAD>
<L>A trebble twisted courd of relatives</L>
<L>Bound Percy over both to king and state;</L>
<L>And yet with masked zeale he falsly strives</L>
<L>Guarding the King, the King to captivate:</L>
<L>A fence hath thorns, and he chose Pensioner</L>
<L>(Honor'd, with lending Majesty such honour)</L>
</LG>
<LG N="236">
<HEAD>236</HEAD>
<L>Made his strict homage a back doore, where He</L>
<L>Might let in treason and rebellion:</L>
<L>Over much zeale's a blast of pollicy</L>
<L>To blow up parisite presumption.</L>
<L>Thus an ungratefull snake doth often string</L>
<L>The breast, that warm'd it, once recovering.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="137">
<PB REF="68"/>
<HEAD>137</HEAD>
<L><HI>Faux</HI> strives to cloath his couching villany</L>
<L>In <HI>Percys</HI> livery, goes for his man,</L>
<L>Waites on him in the roade of Tyranny,</L>
<L>But rides before him, striving to out <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne</L>
<L>His master, and his mate; they softly came,</L>
<L>Whilst he in hot careere pursues the game.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="238">
<HEAD>238</HEAD>
<L>A traitor to himselfe, that would betray</L>
<L>(Posing the aire, that breathed Him a soule)</L>
<L>The Patron of his life, before his day</L>
<L>Hastening to Pluto's file, and their enrole</L>
<L>Himself for darknesse, and present his King,</L>
<L>His Countrey too for a burnt offering</L>
</LG>
<LG N="139">
<HEAD>139</HEAD>
<L>These are the true borne of that Father Feind,</L>
<L>A <HI>Cadmus</HI> brood sprung from the scattered seed</L>
<L>Of that true serpent's teeth, and now they bend</L>
<L>Their forces that they may dissentions breed.</L>
<L>The purer blood of long liv'd unity,</L>
<L>Which ranne in Englands veines, they'l now let flye.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="240">
<HEAD>240</HEAD>
<L>So are they taught by theit Trivertick Father,</L>
<L>Such doctrine howles forth triple <HI>Cerberus;</HI></L>
<L>Mad wisdome! puddle knowledge; mudded ove<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Like flimy streames of filthy <HI>Erebus:</HI></L>
<L>Religion in the Lees! divotions mire!</L>
<L>A cold, false, foggy, wandring, fatuate fire</L>
</LG>
<LG N="241">
<PB REF="69"/>
<HEAD>241</HEAD>
<L>Oh 'tis the cause, that is so Catholique,</L>
<L>Rome's almost ready for her matyrdome▪</L>
<L>Our miters have beene shak't, if <HI>England</HI> strike</L>
<L>The second time, down comes our Triple Crown.</L>
<L>Religion cals, whilst her cause wee cry,</L>
<L>Tis virtue for to Sin, a price to dye</L>
</LG>
<LG N="242">
<HEAD>242</HEAD>
<L>Aleaprous Church, a Church from scars as free</L>
<L>As it is full of wounds; one onely soare:</L>
<L>Festred corruption springs and runs from thee,</L>
<L>So full of spots, uncapable of more</L>
<L>What horrid Tyranny dare show it's head,</L>
<L>That hath not first at Rome, beene licenced.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="243">
<HEAD>243</HEAD>
<L>These, these, that joyn'd to beare that common yoake</L>
<L>Fettred together with her sacrament:</L>
<L>Was by her sacrilegious hyre bespoke</L>
<L>To call up Tyranny, and they consent.</L>
<L>Let's on: the danger's sweet▪ a Bull shall be,</L>
<L>Our pardon; merrit, our security.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="244">
<HEAD>244</HEAD>
<L>Wee I goe no common road, away with that</L>
<L>Prefumption, which is obvious, what e're</L>
<L>Hath once beene heard shall never in our plot</L>
<L>Iugredient be: Presumption shall despaire</L>
<L>When she first heares of it; nay death shall be</L>
<L>Amaz'd to hearc of such a prodigy,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="246">
<PB N="125" REF="69"/>
<HEAD>246</HEAD>
<L>Wee'l take up hearts of steele, and triple brasse</L>
<L>Shall hoope them in: Then dastard Tyranny</L>
<L>To follow us to Hell; and there wee'l passe</L>
<L>With confidence toth' Stygian diety;</L>
<L>So learne new magick that we may extract</L>
<L><HI>Sulphurian</HI> sands from <HI>Styx</HI> his Cataract.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="247">
<HEAD>247</HEAD>
<L>Some scattered <HI>Atom's</HI> dust wee'l gather thence,</L>
<L>Which with impetuous rage, shall blow up all;</L>
<L>An Omnicidian blast to recompence</L>
<L>The fury of that thronged Capitall.</L>
<L>Nor sheild, nor bullwarke, nor that <HI>Iron</HI> coate</L>
<L>Which fenceth thunder, shall this blow keepe out.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="248">
<HEAD>248</HEAD>
<L>Nor strength, nor care, nor both, nor all shall be</L>
<L>A Remora to stop the full careere</L>
<L>Of instant ruine; which well arm'd shall flee</L>
<L>With close revenge, and bring a weapon with her,</L>
<L>Will all the acts of murther soone o'recome,</L>
<L>Put an whole Kingdome to a martyrdome</L>
</LG>
<LG N="249">
<HEAD>249</HEAD>
<L>That burning hill that keeps continuall sire</L>
<L>Casting live coales into <HI>Calabrias</HI> breast,</L>
<L>Doth but an hatching milder heate expire,</L>
<L>And rageth with a fury quite supprest</L>
<L>Compar'd to this; a furnace, had it beene</L>
<L>But kindled, Hell had had lesse fireing.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="250">
<PB N="126" REF="70"/>
<HEAD>250</HEAD>
<L>Nay <HI>Phoebus</HI> sealding beames (though he or'etake</L>
<L>The fiery Lyon at his raging denne)</L>
<L>In scorching <HI>Libya</HI> could never make</L>
<L>So hot a Solstice, burne as this had then</L>
<L>Wept or'e the flame they had not quenched this</L>
<L>Had with their running sives the Bel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ides</L>
</LG>
<LG N="251">
<HEAD>251</HEAD>
<L>A fruitfull age; barren in all but some,</L>
<L>Fruitsull in sending forth a forward spring</L>
<L>Of ripe impiety. What gulfe within</L>
<L>The deepe Abysse of <HI>Tartarus</HI> can bring</L>
<L>Bring forth such monsters with a direfull hand</L>
<L>Against anointed holinesse to band.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="252">
<HEAD>252</HEAD>
<L>Nor cholerick <HI>Seytha,</HI> nor yet <HI>Concanus,</HI></L>
<L>He that was pampred up with horses blood,</L>
<L>Nor he of <HI>Dacia</HI> servile <HI>Davns-Dacus</HI></L>
<L>Such Tyrant Mysteries e're understood:</L>
<L>Nay the <HI>Sicambri</HI> that red pated-race</L>
<L>Poison'd with slaughters at this vale their face:</L>
</LG>
<LG N="253">
<HEAD>253</HEAD>
<L>The affrighted aire with cold amazement shooke</L>
<L>Fearing the thumping blows it should receive,</L>
<L>The starrs doe quench their flames ith' misty brooke</L>
<L>Of <HI>Acharon,</HI> as if they would bereave</L>
<L>The Snblunary orbe of all it's light</L>
<L>Loathing so black a deed so strang a sight.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="251">
<PB N="127" REF="70"/>
<HEAD>251</HEAD>
<L><HI>Phoebe</HI> began her palsie head to shroud,</L>
<L>And seared at the sight pluckt in her horns▪</L>
<L><HI>Apollo's</HI> steeds did start into a cloud</L>
<L>And each with strange reluctancy suborns</L>
<L>The guider, that he would let loose the raine</L>
<L>That they might draw the day quite back again</L>
</LG>
<LG N="252">
<HEAD>252</HEAD>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> invests himselfe in sable black</L>
<L>Mourning to think upon so foule a birth.</L>
<L>The Axle-tree of heaven begins to crack</L>
<L>Fearing some new forg'ed thunder-bolts from earth</L>
<L>The heaven's begin to weep, &amp; with their teares,</L>
<L>Would make a deluge for to drowne their fears</L>
</LG>
<LG N="253">
<HEAD>253</HEAD>
<L>The unwreath'd snakes of the <HI>Eumenides</HI></L>
<L>Stood bolt upright upon the Fury's heads:</L>
<L>The hundred-headed beast at th' news of this</L>
<L>Hangs down his eares, his taile like twinig reeds</L>
<L>He twists betwixt his leggs, runns howling out,</L>
<L>The Ghosts in strange disorder range about</L>
</LG>
<LG N="254">
<HEAD>254</HEAD>
<L>The heaven stands still, the Earth seems now to round</L>
<L>In her diurnall circuit: the whole frame</L>
<L>Of nature seem'd unpin'd: disorder found</L>
<L>Her order now came in, and tooke the same</L>
<L>The world amaz'd, thought <HI>Iove</HI> had suffred</L>
<L>Or that the world now at an end had been then,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="255">
<PB N="128" REF="71"/>
<HEAD>255</HEAD>
<L>The sands of <HI>Bosphorus</HI> begun to groane,</L>
<L>They heard of it and murmure of the newes.</L>
<L>The <HI>Libyck Syrtes</HI> faine their heads would drowne</L>
<L>In <HI>Affrick</HI> sea, but <HI>Neptune</HI> doth refuse</L>
<L>The <HI>Arminian</HI> waves doe roare, and carry thus</L>
<L>The news to <HI>Taurus,</HI> and to <HI>Caucasus.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG N="256">
<HEAD>256</HEAD>
<L>The <HI>Hyperborean</HI> mountaines, which retaine</L>
<L>An equall portion of the day and night,</L>
<L>Halfe yeare in day, and halfe in night remaine</L>
<L>Scar'd from their course keep a continuall night</L>
<L>The <HI>Oakes</HI> on <HI>Gargon</HI> on their tops look farre</L>
<L>As if for madnesse they had toare their haire.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="257">
<HEAD>257</HEAD>
<L>The aged <HI>Alpes</HI> dissolve their frozen snow</L>
<L>Filling up <HI>Rhodanus</HI> with their melting teares,</L>
<L>And <HI>Rhodanus</HI> doth her rising bancks o'reslow</L>
<L>Blabbing to <HI>France</HI> and <HI>Italy</HI> our feares.</L>
<L><HI>Acturus</HI> will goe downe, <HI>Aericthon</HI> rise,</L>
<L>That they may leave tempestuous seas and skyes.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="258">
<HEAD>258</HEAD>
<L>And yet, and yet, that hell-hatcht crew controles</L>
<L>Both heaven and earth, goe equall with the stars,</L>
<L>With proudest heads confront the highest poles</L>
<L>Promise to warm with flames heav'ns coldest cars</L>
<L>Heark, hearken, Hell applauds us then they cry</L>
<L>And so applaud themselves in villany.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="259">
<PB N="129" REF="71"/>
<HEAD>259.</HEAD>
<L>And now the day's their owne, that glad-sad da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>That deare, that raising, that foule-faire weather,</L>
<L>Which must both raise a tombe, and Trophy lay</L>
<L>For <HI>England,</HI> and yet not for <HI>England</HI> neither▪</L>
<L>Britain's sad Epitaph hangs o're her hearre,</L>
<L>And Romes false Iubile is turn'd in verse.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="260">
<HEAD>260</HEAD>
<L>And now some pen that's Iesuiticall</L>
<L>Must forme a letter of equivocations,</L>
<L>Indited by a head politicall</L>
<L>To keepe the truth in mentall reservations,</L>
<L>'Tis sent unto some cull'd Nobility:</L>
<L>Goe one, and riddle me the mysterie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="261">
<HEAD>261</HEAD>
<L><HI>My Lord</HI> that Catholike affinity,</L>
<L>Which knitts relation betwixt me, and those,</L>
<L>Which are so nigh to you, makes me untye</L>
<L>What sacrament to you, which should keepe close</L>
<L>The dearest secreat of my breast, but see</L>
<L>How neare I prize your safe securitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="262">
<HEAD>262</HEAD>
<L>Then as you love that soule, which is espous'd</L>
<L>In such a fellowship, so neare your breast,</L>
<L>Let it not be divor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t: you are expos'd</L>
<L>Vnto a common danger with the rest:</L>
<L>Take up some forg'd excuse ontrust, which may</L>
<L>Sue at your absence on the Senate day.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="963">
<PB N="130" REF="72"/>
<HEAD>963</HEAD>
<L>The God's decree is past, and man consent</L>
<L>Both have conspir'd, and seal'd their minds, that they</L>
<L>Will muster up revenge to punishments,</L>
<L>This yron rusted age shall battered be.</L>
<L>A blow with sudden terror there shall be:</L>
<L>And yet the hurt, who hurts them, shall not see</L>
</LG>
<LG N="264">
<HEAD>264</HEAD>
<L>No motions these commotions shall betray;</L>
<L>Vshering the sequell with a prolog<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e in,</L>
<L>No trumpe shall sound initialls to the fray</L>
<L>To tell the foeman when he shall begin.</L>
<L>A thunder-clap shall fall with such a blow</L>
<L>The left hand here, shall not the right hand</L>
</LG>
<LG N="265">
<HEAD>265</HEAD>
<L>Nor slight you now this warning peice, you may know.</L>
<L>Escape the ruine horrours o're your head,</L>
<L>With-draw your selfe, take wing, and fly away,</L>
<L>Or else your life's already buried.</L>
<L>You may outlive the Fates; know, 'tis no more</L>
<L>But burne the letter, and the danger's or'e.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="266">
<HEAD>266</HEAD>
<L>Heaven warn's you, be sore-arm'd: I hope that she</L>
<L>That guided hath the hand, and penne to write,</L>
<L>Will ope'you eyes to reade the mysterie:</L>
<L>He that doth read, and understands not it</L>
<L>Is ready to neglect; neglect will make</L>
<L>An Index to't, let care keepe what you take.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="267">
<PB N="131" REF="72"/>
<HEAD>267</HEAD>
<L>The <HI>Aenigma's</HI> tyed in a Gordian knot,</L>
<L>The letter writ and sent, but who can spell</L>
<L>The meaning drawne in Ony'on juce, that's not</L>
<L>Reveal d at all unlesse the fire tell.</L>
<L>Burne but the letter, then perchance you'l see</L>
<L>And yet that burnt, tell me the mystery</L>
</LG>
<LG N="268">
<HEAD>268</HEAD>
<L>Who with the nimble strength of Daedall wit</L>
<L>Can loose these tangled lines? what <HI>Lynceus</HI> eye</L>
<L>Can sift the bottom of so darke a pit,</L>
<L>And there those hidden mineralls descry?</L>
<L>Who can this Labyrinth finde out, and trace</L>
<L>That Minotoure in this <HI>Meander</HI> maze?</L>
</LG>
<LG N="269">
<HEAD>269</HEAD>
<L>None but that eye, that sees without an eye,</L>
<L>None but that sun, that shines in midnight darke.</L>
<L>Could either see or reade this mysterie,</L>
<L>Or quench this fire in it's ember spark.</L>
<L>None but that Oracle, which never spake</L>
<L>By Oracles could this transparent make,</L>
</LG>
<LG N="270">
<HEAD>270</HEAD>
<L>God speakes by men, the Devill speakes, but by</L>
<L>His wodden carkasses, God speakes the truth,</L>
<L>The Lyer teacheth stockes, and stones to lye,</L>
<L>And yet a miracle doth breath from both.</L>
<L>The Devil's raines hangs loose sometimes, but so</L>
<L>That there's a curb commands him, too &amp; fro.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="271">
<PB N="132" REF="73"/>
<HEAD>271</HEAD>
<L>Let hell begin to open wide his jawes</L>
<L>Thinking to swallow heaven with yawning thro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Hell shall prepare his stomack, but for those</L>
<L>Of his owne Tribe, that beare her branded note.</L>
<L>A pit is often digg'd for other men,</L>
<L>But he that diggs, shall sometimes first fall in</L>
</LG>
<LG N="272">
<HEAD>272</HEAD>
<L>If <HI>Diomedes</HI> traynes his horses up</L>
<L>With living men in stead of fodder food,</L>
<L>An <HI>Hercules</HI> shall rise, and fill the cup</L>
<L>To drench an horse with <HI>Diomed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> blood.</L>
<L><HI>Peryllus</HI> may prepare a Bull, but he</L>
<L>Shall first in his owne Bull tormented be.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="273">
<HEAD>273</HEAD>
<L>Let hell send forth her paler <HI>Pegasus</HI></L>
<L>That treason may ride poast on it to bring</L>
<L>The newes of winged ruine unto us,</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Iove</HI> can hang a plummet on the wing,</L>
<L>And force the fates to hover till he hit</L>
<L>Vnder there wings, and make them fall it'h pit</L>
</LG>
<LG N="274">
<HEAD>274.</HEAD>
<L><HI>Iove</HI> calls his bird, that royall Eagle forth</L>
<L>Makes him his winged <HI>Mercury;</HI> goe fly</L>
<L>To <HI>Albions</HI> court, that Synod of true worth,</L>
<L>And there this mantled monster-brat discry.</L>
<L>Give <HI>Iames</HI> the Clue, that he may finde the way</L>
<L>Like <HI>Theseus,</HI> and that he <HI>Minotaure</HI> betray.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="275">
<PB N="133" REF="73"/>
<HEAD>275</HEAD>
<L>This Lord soares on the wings of loyalty</L>
<L>And faithfully conveys that riddle spell</L>
<L>To <HI>Caeasars</HI> councell, where true royalty</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate Iudge on it, and censur'd, each doth tell</L>
<L>His severall verdictt, but the meaning still</L>
<L>Was tyed fast within the knotty spell.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="276">
<HEAD>276</HEAD>
<L>Till heaven sent downe a light, and did infuse</L>
<L>The truer spirit of an Oracle</L>
<L>Into our Monarch's soule, to tell the newes</L>
<L>Where dire Reveng doth, with hid treason, dwell.</L>
<L>He reads the letter, and the language knowes</L>
<L>That confus'd <HI>Ideome</HI> of his Babel foes.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="277">
<HEAD>277.</HEAD>
<L>And now the miners soone are undermin'd,</L>
<L><HI>Ʋulcan's</HI> discovered in his loathly cell</L>
<L>Sitting with other Gods, who there combind</L>
<L>To summon ruine from the depth of hell.</L>
<L><HI>Vulcan</HI> sits next to <HI>Bachus</HI> caskye throne,</L>
<L>And <HI>Pan</HI> is mounted on a rocke of stone.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="278">
<HEAD>278</HEAD>
<L>The wooden God is first pluckt downe, and then</L>
<L><HI>Ʋulcan</HI> and <HI>Bachus</HI> are descried there</L>
<L>Calling toth' rockes to cover them from heaven,</L>
<L>Shrouding their Hogsheads under stones for feare</L>
<L>The fuell's snatched from th' unkindled fire</L>
<L>The fowle es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ps, the fowler's hang'd ith' bryer.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="279">
<PB N="334" REF="74"/>
<HEAD>279</HEAD>
<L>What candle was it, that could guide the eye</L>
<L>To spell the meaning of so darke a spell?</L>
<L>What hand could catch at treason, and fast tye</L>
<L>That captive, to remove him from his cell?</L>
<L>A light not lighted did those lines unfold</L>
<L>An hand, without an arme, the foe controld.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="280">
<HEAD>280</HEAD>
<L>That hand, which once did write without an arme</L>
<L>Printing full terrour upon Babels wall,</L>
<L>Guided this hand to write that hidden charme,</L>
<L>Which proved their's, as that did Babels fall.</L>
<L>This did <HI>Ʋriah</HI> in his letter beare</L>
<L>The sentence of his death, ere, death came neere</L>
</LG>
<LG N="281">
<HEAD>281</HEAD>
<L>That hand, which guided both, pluck me a quill,</L>
<L>From the choice pineon of a Seraphin</L>
<L>Dipt in diviner inck, that't may distill</L>
<L>Full characters of prayse, in charoling</L>
<L>The wonders of that arme, which could com∣mand</L>
<L>And loose fast treason from so dark a band.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="282">
<HEAD>282</HEAD>
<L>Infuse fresh Anthems in my duller muse,</L>
<L>That so it may outrunne a Poets straine</L>
<L>Lending the world new wonders to perufe.</L>
<L>My Muse wrapt up beyond <HI>Apollo's</HI> veine.</L>
<L>Then in one <HI>Halelu</HI>-Ile sing a consort</L>
<L>Shall drowne a quier of Angells full report.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="283">
<PB N="135" REF="74"/>
<HEAD>283</HEAD>
<L>Where lodgeth now that true authenticke soule,</L>
<L>Which was ne're out of tune iu <HI>David's</HI> breast,</L>
<L>But kept continuall harmony, the pole</L>
<L>Still heard him in the quier above the rest.</L>
<L>Wher's that sweet singers glory, who did make</L>
<L>Each string of his owne glory to pertake.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="214">
<HEAD>214</HEAD>
<L>Warbling his makers praise? where are those toungs,</L>
<L>Which run division out of breath, while they</L>
<L>Strove who should first outsing themselves in</L>
<L>And with a Cignets chame call death a way</L>
<L>All striving thus one consort for to make</L>
<L>Breaking the consort, each a consort take.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="285">
<HEAD>285</HEAD>
<L>Were but that old Philosophy in season,</L>
<L>Which makes the soule remove her lodging still,</L>
<L>Tuning in this, and then in th'other mantion,</L>
<L>By transmigration lending the same will</L>
<L>And power to enact, there were some hope,</L>
<L>I might have <HI>Davids</HI> soule for <HI>Davids</HI> scope.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="286">
<HEAD>286</HEAD>
<L>A way fond hopes! Blinde nature is no guide</L>
<L><HI>Elisha</HI> can't <HI>Elija's</HI> soule inhearit,</L>
<L>Then looke not where the Prophets soule doth hide,</L>
<L>Without his soule thou mayst have <HI>Davids</HI> spirit▪</L>
<L>The wind blows where it lists, Olet me finde</L>
<L>In the right corner of my heart the wind.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="287">
<PB N="136" REF="75"/>
<HEAD>287.</HEAD>
<L>Thus'winged with the wind my soule shall rife</L>
<L>To tune her Maker's prayse, farre, farre before</L>
<L>The early Larke doth charme the dawning skyes</L>
<L>My glory shall get up and ope the doore.</L>
<L>That from my enlarged breast a quire may goe▪</L>
<L>And learne the Spheares to play <HI>Novembers</HI> 10.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="75"/>
<PB N="30" REF="76"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="31" REF="76"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="32" REF="77"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="33" REF="77"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="78"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="35" REF="78"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="36" REF="79"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="37" REF="79"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="80"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="39" REF="80"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="40" REF="81"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="41" REF="81"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="42" REF="82"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="43" REF="82"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="44" REF="83"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="45" REF="83"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="46" REF="84"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="47" REF="84"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="85"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="85"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="50" REF="86"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="51" REF="86"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="52" REF="87"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="53" REF="87"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="88"/>
<PB REF="88"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="89"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="89"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="58" REF="90"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="59" REF="90"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="91"/>
<PB REF="91"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</GROUP>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

