<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The priviledges and prerogatives of the High Court of Chancery written by ... Thomas Lord Elsmere ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Egerton, Thomas, Sir, 1540?-1617.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A39243</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing E540</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R11911</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12835455</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12835455</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">94355</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A39243)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94355)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 867:10)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The priviledges and prerogatives of the High Court of Chancery written by ... Thomas Lord Elsmere ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Egerton, Thomas, Sir, 1540?-1617.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[24] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Henry Sheapheard,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1641.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>England and Wales. --  Court of Chancery.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A39243">
<STC T="W">E540</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12835455</BIBNO>
<VID>94355</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
PRIVILEDGES
AND
PREROGATIVES
of the High Court of
Chancery.</P>
<P>Written by the Right
HONOVRABLE
<HI>Thomas</HI> Lord <HI>Elsmere,</HI> late
Lord Chancellour of
ENGLAND.</P>
<P>LONDON,
<HI>Printed for</HI> Henry Sheapheard.
1641.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Preface.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>He gravitie and discretion of the Iudge in
a<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tient time, hath beene such, as in doubtfull
causes and especially for construction of Statutes,
they desired to conferre with the Kings Privie Councell,
whereof there be many examples, some are cited in the Case
of <HI>Post nati.</HI></P>
<P>And this ought to be specially regarded, where the authori∣ty
and Iurisdiction of the Kings Court is to be brought into
Dispute and question.</P>
<P>For <HI>gravius privatorum damno peccatur,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Bodm. lib. 3. Cap. 6. p. 425</NOTE> <HI>Cùm in∣ter
summos Magistratus Curiasuè majores de impe∣rio
certatur.</HI> And in these cases the Iudges should first
have private and loving Conference together,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Bodm. lib. 3. Cap. 6. p. 425.</NOTE> before
publique disputes, according to the Emperour's command.
<HI>Alloquere illum, nè rem injustam faciat.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="treatise">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>NOTES AND OBSERVA∣tions
upon the Statutes of Magna
Charta. cap. 9. and other Statutes concer∣ning
the proceedings in the Chan∣cery,
in cases of Equitie
and Conscience.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>He Statutes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mag. Chart.</NOTE> which be now urged and
stood upon against the <HI>Chancery,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Cap. 9.</NOTE> are
first <HI>Magna Charta,</HI> where the words be
<HI>Nisi per legale iudicium parium suoz vel
per legem terrae.</HI> It is <HI>lex terrae,</HI> that is, the
Iudges of the Common Law shall determine questi∣ons
in Law, and <HI>Pares &amp; Iurors</HI> to try matters in
fact, so the <HI>Chancery</HI> is to order and decree matters of
Conscience and Equity, which cannot be remedied
by the strict rules of the common Law: And the same
rule serveth for understanding,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Stat. 25. Ed. 3. Cap. 4.</NOTE> the Statute <HI>Anno</HI> 25.
<HI>Edward</HI> 3. <HI>cap.</HI> 4. Vpon these words, <HI>Sic niscit duem ent
mesne en-respons &amp; soriudg d'icells per voy de lege.</HI> And
it appeareth the cause of making that Statute, was
to restraine private suggestiōs made to the King or to
his Councell, but not meant to take away the ordina∣ry
judiciall proceedings and hearing of Cases of con∣science
and equity in the <HI>Chancery.</HI></P>
<P>Hath the same words,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Stat. 28. Ed. 3. Cap. 3.</NOTE> as <HI>Magna Charta, cap.</HI> 9 <HI>viz.</HI>
Without being brought into answer by due processe
of Law: For understanding whereof, that is to bee
remembred, that those that are sued in the <HI>Chancery</HI>
<PB REF="4"/>
are brought to another by due processe of law, for
cases of equity and conscience as it is <HI>per legem terrae.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Stat. 2. Ed. 3.</NOTE></P>
<P>That it shall not be commanded by the great Seale
or the little Seale,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Cap. 8.</NOTE> to disturbe or detaine common
right: and though such commandement doe come,
the Iustices shall not therefore cease to doe right in
any point.</P>
<P>For the understanding of this Statute.</P>
<P>The ordinary Iudiciall proceedings by the <HI>Chan∣cery,</HI>
according to conscience and equity, is not any
disturbance, or delay of Common right.</P>
<P>But is the doing of right and Iustice in cases, which
the common Law cannot helpe, for common right
standeth not only in the strict rigour, and extreamity
of the Law (for often <HI>summum ius oft summa injuria)</HI>
but rather in the doing of right, according to equity
and conscience: And the Iudges of the common
Law themselves, doe almost every day extend their
discretion, to stay and mittigate the rigour and strict∣nesse
of the common Law: and in so doing doe, well
notwithstanding the strict word of their oath.</P>
<P>Declareth the law concerning writs of search,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Stat. 14. Ed. 3. Cap. 14.</NOTE> and
in the end of the same Statute, these words, <HI>viz.</HI> That
by commandement of the great Seale, noe Privie
Seale, nor point of this Statute, (viz. concerning
Search) shall be put in delay.</P>
<P>Nor that the Iustices, of whatsoever place they be,
shall lett to do the common law by commandement,
which come to them under the Great Seale or Privie
Seale.</P>
<P>The Common Law hath alwaies allowed the pro∣ceedings
in the Chancery, in cases of conscience and
<PB REF="4"/>
equity; and therfore the words (to doe the Common
law) must not be construed too precisely, as thereby
stop all Courts of equity, for it standeth with the
common law, as well that equity and conscience bee
ministred, where the common law cannot helpe, as
that strict Iustice be ministred according to the com∣mon
law, when the common law may serve.</P>
<P>The Chancery doth not commonly send any Writ <MILESTONE N="2"/>
or Commandement to the Iudges, under the great
Seale cōmanding them to stay to do Iustice, but awar∣deth
Iniunction to the parties, that seeke to have the
advantage of the strictnesse of the common law, a∣gainst
equity and conscience: neverthelesse there be
plentiful examples that Writs of <HI>super sedeas,</HI> under the
great Seale have beene directed to the Iudges, in di∣verse
speciall causes, and have in all times (untill of
late) beene dutifully obeyed, as in cases of priviledge
and to stay their proceedings: <HI>Reges in consulto</HI> and
divers others, &amp;c.</P>
<P>Also it is to bee remembred, that many Iudges of
the common Law have complayned, and sued for re∣medy
in the Chancery; and have beene sued and an∣swered
there, and obeyed the orders of that Court in
cases of equitie and conscience, which could not bee
relieved by the Common law.</P>
<P>This Statute is persuing two former <HI>Stat.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Stat. 42. Ed. 3. cap. 3.</NOTE> one 37.
<HI>Edward</HI> 3. <HI>cap.</HI> 18. which giveth <HI>paenam Talionis,</HI> against
those, which make false suggestions to the King: the
other 38. <HI>Edward</HI> 3. <HI>cap.</HI> 9. which confirmeth the for∣mer
statute in all things saving <HI>pro paena Talionis.</HI> And
this 42. <HI>Edward</HI> 3. explayneth the two former, and
provideth that the people be not greived by false ac∣cusers
which doe often times make their accusements
more for vengeance and singular profits then for the
<PB REF="5"/>
profits of the King and his people, and therefore or∣daineth
that none bee put to answer (which is to bee
intended upon such accusation and false suggestions)
without. 1. presentment before Iustices, or 2. matters
of Record, 3 by due processe, or 4. by Writ originall
according to the onely law of the land.</P>
<P>In this Statute, the intent is to bee considered,
first to explaine, the second former statute <HI>Anno</HI> 27.
<HI>Edw.</HI> 3. and <HI>Anno</HI> 38. <HI>Edw.</HI> 3. as is before noted, 2.
that the antient law of the land bee observe, that is;
That for matters determinable by the common law,
none bee put to answer, but by presentments or mat∣ters
of Record, or by originall Writt, or by due pro∣cesse.
But therein is not meant, that the ordinarie iu∣diciall
proceedings in the Chancery, in matters of e∣quity
and conscience (not being remediable by the
Statutes of the common law) should be taken away
or restrained: But that in such cases, they may pro∣ceede
against parties called in by due processe, for
that is according to the antient law of the land.</P>
<P>So the practise and experience hath beene ever
since, which is the true and certaine interpretation of
that Statute and of all other Statutes.</P>
<P>The words be these:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Stat. 4. Hen. 4. Cap. 23.</NOTE> Whereas as well in plea Re∣all,
or as in plea personall after Iudgement given in
the Courts of our Soveraigne Lord the King, the
parties be made to come upon greivous paines some
time before the Kings Councell, &amp; sometime in the
Parliament to answer therof anew, to the impoverish∣ment
of the parties aforesaid, and subvertion of the
Common Law of the Land: It is ordained and esta∣blished,
that after Iudgement given in the Court of
our Soveraigne Lord the King, the parties and their
Heires thereof shall be in peace untill the Iudgement
<PB REF="5"/>
shall bee undone by attaint, or by errour, if there bee
errour, as hath beene used by the Lawes in the time
of the Kings progenitors.</P>
<P>For understanding of this Statute the questi∣on
is,</P>
<P>Whether there be any thing in the word or intent
of this Statute to take away, or restraine, or impeach
the Iurisdiction of the Chancery to give remedy and
releife according to conscience and equity in cases,
which cannot bee remedied by the strict rules of the
common law, by attaint, or by Writ of errour.</P>
<P>For the resolving of this question, is to bee consi∣dered,
what hath beene used by the lawes, before the
making of this Statute.</P>
<P>And to this point I must say, I have not seene any
record or President, that the Court of Chancery hath
beene restrayned to heare and determine causes of
conscience and equity, and to give reliefe according∣ly,
as well after, as before Iudgement given by the
Judges of the Common Law.</P>
<P>But before the making of this Statute;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ʋn. Stat. 29.</NOTE> there bee
many precedents and records to prove,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ed. 3. cap. 1.</NOTE> that the King
and his Councell, and the Kings Commissioners ap∣pointed
to be auditors <HI>querelarum</HI> &amp; Court of Rome,
&amp; some, pretending to have power and authority for
the Pope, did take upon them to examine such Iudge∣ments
to reverse and undoe the same, which seemeth
to be the point remedied by this Statute: And this
is within the direct and precise words of the Statute,
whereupon it may be inferred and concluded, that is
the words shall bee taken precisely in the strict
<PB REF="6"/>
sence; Then the King himselfe and his Coun∣sell,
and the Parliament, who in time of the Kings
progenitors, used to examine &amp; reverse Iudgements,
shall be bound and restrained by the <HI>Statute;</HI> But the
Chancery medleth not with the reversing of the Iudg¦ments
given by the Iudges of the common Law, but
in allowing the same to be good and just, according to
the strict rule of the Common Law (whereunto the
Iudges are sworne) doth examine only the equity
of the case, according to the rule of equity and con∣science,
and taketh order with the partie, to doe that
which in equity and Conscience ought to bee done,
which the Iustices of the Common Plees hath no
power to doe, and that seemeth to be the true reason
that the Statute doth not once mention the Chan∣cery.</P>
<P>And it cannot reasonably be conceived, that the
Parliament meant to bind the Chancery (which is
not named) or the King or his Counsell and the Par∣liament
it selfe, which are expressely named: That
they should not releive parties that are greived by the
Rigour of the common Law, against equity and con∣science
in cases, which the Iudges of the Common
Law cannot relieve thē by attaint, or errour, or other∣wise.
For <HI>sententia Iudicis non praeiudicat veritati:</HI> And
<HI>sicut res iudicata naturalem obligationem non tollit, Ita con∣spercatam,
laesamque conscientiam non purgat:</HI> And some
doe aptlie &amp; truely define equitie thus;<NOTE PLACE="marg">In Casus. 192. in quae.</NOTE> <HI>Equitas est pub∣lici
iuris moderatio apectore Regio, velut ab Oraculo petenda.</HI>
And another saith thus,<NOTE PLACE="marg">vel. &amp; novi. lib. pradict.</NOTE> <HI>Equitas in potestate moderato∣ris
esse debet, multa contra scriptum facere et dicere:</HI> Ano∣ther
saith,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Cap.</NOTE> <HI>Equitas iustitiae aciem retundit:</HI> And Saint
<HI>Augustine, Lex quiaese ipsam molire non potest mitiganda
<PB REF="6"/>
est &amp;. contemptus, fraus, &amp; dolus, in Curia Regal, neminisub∣uenire
debent.</HI></P>
<P>And furthermore for the true understanding of <MILESTONE N="1"/>
this Statute, and all other Statutes, this rule should be
observed: 1. to understand, and consider what was the
mischeife at the Common Law, which the Parliament
meant to remedie within this Statute. It appeareth to
have beene the reversing and undoing of Iudgements
by the King or his Counsell, or his Commissioners or
Parliament, which might and ought to be examined
by attaint or errour, as is aforesaid, but not the ordi∣nary
Iuditiall proceedings in Chancery, according to
equity and conscience to give releife to the partie
grieved, by the strict rigour of the Common Law or
in cases which could not be remedied by attaint or er∣rour,
or by any other ordinarie meanes by course of
the Common Law, and where they in that equita∣ble,
proceeding did not attempt to reverse or impeach
the judgement given by the Common Law, but to
admit and allow the same to be good and just, as is be∣fore
declared.</P>
<P>The next is how this Statute was understood and <MILESTONE N="2"/>
expounded at, and soone after the tyme of the making
of that, for in all cases <HI>contemporanea expositio</HI> is special∣ly
to be regarded: and for it (as I said before) I have
not seene any Record or Precedent that this Statute
hath beene expounded to restraine the Chancery, to
proceede in their ordinary courses, to give releife in
cases of equity, according to good conscience. Nere
the time of the making of it, or many yeares after.</P>
<P>And I suppose no such materiall or effectuall record
or precedent can be shewed. And for later times as
in the time of <HI>Henry</HI> the seventh, and since, the pro∣ceedings
<PB REF="7"/>
and examples bee so frequent, and so plaine
&amp; direct, as nothing is more common; and it is a cer∣taine
and true rule <HI>Intellectus currit cum praxi.</HI></P>
<P><MILESTONE N="4"/> And if any ambiguity, or doubt should bee concei∣ved
upon the words and intent of this Statute, sith it
concernes the jurisdiction of the Kings Courts, which
have no power, nor authority but from the King
whom they serve. One Court ought not to take upon
them to Iudge and deside their owne Iurisdiction, and
the Iurisdiction of another of the Kings Courts: But
then <HI>Bractons</HI> rule is to be holden:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Bracton. lib. 2. fol. 34.</NOTE> (that is) that the
King's interpretation is to be expected, Who is to de∣clare
and expound all doubtfull or obscure words in
<HI>Chartis Regiis &amp; factis-regum:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">cap. 16.</NOTE> For all Statutes are <HI>facta
regi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> made at the request and by the consent of the
Lords Spirituall and Temporall,<NOTE PLACE="marg">22. Edw. 3.</NOTE> and the Commons.</P>
<P>And where some new conceits have beene lately
imagined, that the partie grieved should have com∣plained
before Iudgement or else not to be heard or
relieved after Iudgement by reason of this Statute.
This is but a cavill and a Sophisticall distinction not
worthie the answering. For before hee bee hurt, he
<MILESTONE N="3"/> hath no cause to complaine, &amp; that, which hurts him,
is the Iudgement grounded upon the stricktenesse &amp;
rigour of the Common Law, against equity and con∣science,
and when he feeles the wound, it is time for
him to complaine to seeke remedie, by complaining
of the wrong, which is done unto him by the rigour
of the Common Law, contrary to equity and a good
conscience, and of this sort be the precedents and ex∣amples
before mentioned.</P>
<P>Lastly it is to bee lamented that the antient com∣mon
Lawes are so much neglected and contemned,
<PB REF="7"/>
and almost growne obsolete and out of use: that for
the most part, wee have not the substance but the sha∣dow
of the antient Common Law, <HI>Manet magni no∣minis
umbra:</HI> and therefore his Majestie at the first
beginning of his gratious raigne of <HI>England,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">King Iames.</NOTE> did most
princely, prudently, and iuditiously shew his mislike of
the incertaintie of the Iudicature in his Courts of
Iustice in <HI>England,</HI> and require and commanded his
Iudges to take mature consideration of it. What fol∣lowed
I will say nothing.</P>
<P>Wherefore let the Iudges now consider, how they
observe in their Courts and proceedings, the words
and intent of this Statute, whether after Iudgements
the parties be in peace, untill the Iudgement bee un∣done
by attaint, or errour, whether after Iudgements
in Writs of errour firme, they suffer not new Actions,
and verdict, against verdict, and Iudgement; against
Iudgement without attaint or errour to the manifest
deluding of the true and antient Maximes of the
common Law, and without regarding of the words
of the Statute. And thus suites for one, and the selfe
same cause, are carried from Court to Court, as pow∣er
and might of the parties, or favour or affection of
the Iudges, or corruption of Sheriffes or subordinati∣on
or periury of Witnesses or such like shifts or tricks
can best accomodate the businesse.</P>
<P>De Chartis regiis &amp; factis regum,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Bracton. lib.</NOTE> non debent, nec possunt
Iusticiarij,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. fol. 34. cap. 16.</NOTE> nec privatae personae disputare, nec etiam nisi illâ
dubitatio oriatur, possunt eam interpretari &amp; in dubiis▪ et ob∣scuris,
vel si aliqua dictio duos contineat intellectus Domi∣ni
regis erit expectanda interpretatio &amp; voluntas eius sit in∣terpretari,
cujus est condere. Maneant termini patrum, &amp;
inter fines proprios se quisque contineat,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Leo. Epist. 67. &amp; 94.</NOTE> Sufficiant limites,
<PB REF="8"/>
quos sanctorum patrum providentissima decreta Posucrunt.</P>
<P>Some notes and observations upon the Statutes
of <HI>Provisoes</HI> and <HI>Praemunire</HI> especialy concerning the
Chancerie and other Courts of equitie.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Stat. 25. Ed. 3. Cap. 22.</NOTE></P>
<P>The words be, 1. because some doe purchase in the
Court of <HI>Rome</HI> provisions, to have Abbies and Prio∣ries
in <HI>England</HI> in destruction of the Realme, and of
holy religion, it is accorded that every man that pur∣chaseth
such provisions of Abbies and Priories, that
he and his executors, and procurators, which doe sue
and make execution of such provisions, shall be out of
the Kings protection, and that a man may doe with
them, as of enemies of our Soveraigne Lord the King
and his Realme.</P>
<P>Note the usurpation of the Church of Rome
in this Case Iudged at this time,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Note.</NOTE> to be the di∣struction
of the Realme and of Religion.</P>
<P>And the partie himselfe and his Executors and pro∣curators
putting in execution such provisions, iudged
to be enemies of the King and Realme, and out of the
Kings protection, (and so in worse degree then Tray∣tors)
and that therefore every man might iustifie the
taking of their goods, and killing of them, and not to
be impeached for it.</P>
<P>There is another Statute entituled <HI>Statute de pro∣visorib.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Anno 25.</NOTE>
declaring the great mischeife that the King
and the Realme sustayned,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Edwad 3.</NOTE> by the usurpation of the
Pope, in cases of provisions and reservations of Bene∣fices,
reciting the Lawes ordained by King <HI>Edward</HI> the
first, and adding further remedie, and severe punish∣ment
against the offenders; and that no processe or
<PB REF="8"/>
sute should bee in these cases in the Court of <HI>Rome,</HI>
nor in no part else where.</P>
<P>Both these Statutes were specially provided
to restraine the usurpation of the Pope, and the
Churches of Rome in these cases of provisions,
and reservations.</P>
<P>By the Statute <HI>Anno</HI> 27.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Stat. 27. Ed. 3. Cap. 1.</NOTE> <HI>Edward</HI> 3. it appeareth,
That notwithstanding the two former statutes <HI>Anno</HI>
25. <HI>Edward</HI> 3. yet the usurpation of the Pope, and the
Church of Rome, was so exorbitant, that the Nobles
and Commons complained in this Parliament, and
prayed further remedie for the same, alledging that
divers of the people have beene drawne out of the
Realme, to answer of things whereof Counsance per∣tayneth
to the Kings Court, or of things whereof
Iudgements be given in the Kings Court, or which
sue in another Court, to defeate or impeach the
Iudgements given in the Kings Court, in prejudice
and disherison of the King and his Crowne, and of
all the people of his Realme, and the undoing and
distraction of the Common Law of the same Realme
at all times vsed.</P>
<P>This is the Mischiefe, which was complained of and
was desired to be remedied.</P>
<P>The Offenders, against whom remedie is sought, are
these, which draw any out of the Realme by plea.</P>
<P>Wherfore the Counsance being to the Kings Court
or of things, wherof Iudgements be given in the Kings
Court, or which doe sue in another Court, to de∣feat
<PB REF="9"/>
or impeach the Iudgements given in the Kings
Court.</P>
<P>Then the remedie provided is,</P>
<P>That such offenders shall receive punishment by
two moneths, to be before the King and his Coun∣sell,
or in his Chancery, or before the Kings Iustices
of the one Bench or other, or before the Iustices of
the King, which to the same shall bee deputed to an∣swer
in proper person to the King for their contempt
done in this behalfe, and if they come not, then to be
out of the Kings Protection, &amp;c. Provided, that
when they doe come before, they be out-lawed, they
shall be received to answer.</P>
<P>Now it will appeare manifestly that the intent of
the Parliament, was not to restraine or punish any
that complayned and sued in the Chancery, to bee re∣leived
according to equity and Conscience; In Cases
wherein, by the strict rules and rights of the Com∣mon
Law, the Iudges of the Common Law could
not releive them, neither are there any words in the
Statute, which can without violence bee strayned or
reathed to serve any such unreasonable Constructi∣on:
For the better understanding hereof, the parts
of the Statute are to bee devided and severally consi∣dered.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="1"/> 1. As first the mischeife complained of.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="2"/> 2. The offenders, against whom, the Complaint is.</ITEM>
<ITEM><MILESTONE N="3"/> 3. The remedie provided, and against whom, the
forme of proceeding therein.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>For the mischeife, the Parliament finding, that
the Pope and Court of Rome did not only con∣tinue
<PB REF="9"/>
their usurpation in the Cases mentioned in the
former Statute. <HI>An.</HI> 25. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. But did also extend it
further in drawing the people out of the Realme to
answer things, whereof the Counsance pertaineth to
the Kings Court, or of things whereof Iudgements
bee given in the Kings Court, or by suit in another
Court, to defeate or impeach the Iudgements given
in the Kings Court; In prejudice, &amp;c.</P>
<P>In the preamble, wherein this mischeife is declared,
it appeareth that the drawing of the people out of the
Realme to answer to those Cases, specially remem∣bred,
was the greife of the people, for which they pray∣ed
remedie.</P>
<P>But by suites in the Chancery to be relieved accor∣ding
to equity and conscience in cases, in which the
Iudges of the Common Law could not give remedy,
the people were not driven out of the Realme, nor
Iudgement given in the Kings Courts, were not
sought to be defeated or impeached, but conscience
and equity to be observed.</P>
<P>Nor such suites in the Chancery cannot bee ac∣compted
to be any other court then the Kings Court;
For the <HI>Chancery</HI> is one of the Kings supreame Courts
of Iustice, and as much or more greived by the inor∣dinate
usurpation of the Pope and his Courts as any
other of the Kings Courts: Neither could such suits
in the <HI>Chancery</HI> being the Kings own supreame court,
bee in prejudice or disherison of the King and his
Crowne, and of his people; or the undoing or di∣struction
of the Common Law at all times used; And
I suppose there can no record or warrantable prece∣dent
be shewed that such proceedings in the <HI>Chance∣ry</HI>
hath in times before used (that is before. 27. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3.)
Beene construed to be the undoing or destruction of
the Common Law.</P>
<P><PB REF="10"/>
And hereupon it may bee inferred and concluded,
that those, which complaine and sue in the <HI>Chancery</HI>
for releife and remedie, according to equity and con∣science,
in such cases as the Iudges of the Common
Law cannot remedie, are not any offenders within
the words or meaning of this Statute.</P>
<P>And this will appeare more plainely by the reme∣die,
which is provided; that is, that the offenders shall
have garnishment by two moneths, to appeare before
such Iudges, as are assigned to give remedie in the cau∣ses
before mentioned in the Statute, which are these:
The King and his Counsell the Chan. the Iustices
of one Bench or the other, or other Iustices of the
Kings, which shall be deputed.</P>
<P>Wherein is to be noted, that the Chancery is the
second Court that is appointed to give Iustice against
such offenders, as the Parliament meant, and is placed
next after the King and his Councell, and before the
Iudges of the one Bench or the other (between whom
the Parliament giveth no prioritie nor precedent) &amp;
addeth such other Iustices as the King shal depute: By
which power the King may by the Statute exclude
both these Courts, &amp; appoint other Iustices, if it shall
please him so to doe.</P>
<P>Now it is too absurd to say or imagine that
the ordinarie and juditiall proceedings in the
<HI>Chancery</HI> by the Kings owne Authority, in cases be∣fore
remembred can be in prejudice or disherision of
the King or his Crowne or destruction of the Com∣mon
Law; or that the Parliament did so meant or
understand, sithe they have designed the <HI>Chancery</HI> to
bee a speciall or prime Court to punish offenders
against the said Statute.</P>
<P>And to resort to the true rule <HI>Contemporanea expo∣sitio,</HI>
<PB REF="10"/>
for <HI>Intellectus currit cum praxi.</HI> I have not seene
nor heard that any person hath beene charged, or im∣peached
by suit in the nature of a Praemunire upon
this Statute for sueing in the Chancery in the Cases
before remembred, or in any other like cases.</P>
<P>The Statute 27. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. was grounded upon the ex∣orbitant
usurpations of the Pope and Church of
<HI>Rome,</HI> which were in some sort provided for, by the
former Statutes <HI>An.</HI> 25. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. But the Parliament
<HI>Anno</HI> 27. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. finding the same too weake, and the
Church of Rome did not only continue their former
usurpations, but did daily increase the same more
and more, did therefore devise further remedie a∣gainst
their insolent and outragious excesse.</P>
<P>Wherein appeareth that the speciall mark, where∣unto
both those Parliaments aymed &amp; directed their
Actions, was to provide and give remedy against
the wicked proceedings of the Pope and Court of
Rome, and not to restraine the jurisdiction and autho∣rity
of any of the Kings owne Courts in their ordi∣narie
and juditiall proceedings, either in law or equi∣ty,
and by that, which is before remembred, is suffici∣ently
declared, yet the same is made more manifest
by the Statute <HI>Anno</HI> 38. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. Stat. 2. <HI>cap.</HI> 1. 2. 3. 4.</P>
<P>By which it appeareth that in 9. yeares space, after
the Parliament <HI>An.</HI> 27. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. the Pope and Church of
Rome ceased not to goe on still in their wicked and
inormious usurpations upon the king &amp; the Crown,
and therefore that Parliament <HI>Anno</HI> 38. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. decla∣reth
plainely, that it was the Court of Rome, that
dealt in cases, whereof the Counsance and small dis∣cussions
pertaine to the King and his Royall Court;
and for remedie thereof ordaineth, that the for∣mer
Statute made <HI>Anno</HI> 25. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. and <HI>Anno</HI> 27. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3.
<PB REF="11"/>
shall be in all things affirmed and executed, adding
also some further punishments and provisions against
the offenders, directing the proceeding therein to be
before the King and his Councell, onely without
mentioning any other Courts, as 27. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. did.</P>
<P>So as upon conferring together these three Statutes
viz. 25. 27. and 38. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. it appeareth that the intent
of al these Parliaments was onely to punish offenders,
that maintained the usurped and pretended authority
of the Pope, &amp; Church of Rome, and prosecuted any
Action or sute by vertue of the same in any case,
whereof the Counsance and finall discussing pertey∣ned
to the King and his Courts; And therefore if a∣ny
doubt bee conceived upon any words in the Sta∣tute
27 <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. it is to be explained by the Statute 25.
<HI>Ed.</HI> 3. going before, and the Statute 38. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. com∣ming
after.</P>
<P>After all these Statutes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Stat. 16. Ric. 2. Cap. 5.</NOTE> yet ambitious usurpers,
and greedy covetous extortions of the Pope and
Court of Rome ceased not, but still continued and in∣creased
more and more, where-upon the Parliament
<HI>Anno</HI> 16. <HI>Rich.</HI> 2. <HI>chap.</HI> reciting some particular cases,
<HI>viz</HI> that Iudgments being given in the Kings Courts
for recoverie of presentments to Churches, &amp; Bene∣fices,
and the same Iudgements duly executed by the
Arch-bishop and Bishop as they ought to bee; That
thereupon the Archbishop and Bishop have excom∣municated
by the Popes censure for executing of the
same Iudgements.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="2"/> And also that the Pope did ordaine and purpose to
translate some Prelates out of the Realme, and some
from one Bishop-prick to another within the Realme,
without the assent or knowledge of the King, by
which the king should bee destitute of his Councell;
<PB REF="11"/>
and the treasure of the Realme to bee made away out
of the Realme, and so the Regality &amp; Crowne should
be made subject to the Pope in perpetuall distruction
of the King and his Crowne, and all the Realme.</P>
<P>In which cases, and in all other cases attempted a∣gainst
the King, his Crowne, and Regalitie, the Lords
Temporall and Commons, did promise to stand with
the King and the Crowne, and to live and die; and
the Lords Spirituall promised also, to stand with the
King in the cases before mentioned, and in all other
cases bound by their alleagiance with a speciall prote∣station
and saving of the Popes authority in excom∣municating
of Bishops, and translating of Prelates,
according to the Lawes of the holy Church, &amp; there∣upon
it is ordained and inacted, that if any purchase
or pursue in the Court of Rome or elsewhere, any
such translations, processes, and sentences of excom∣munication,
Bills, Instruments or other things, which
touch the King, against him, his Crowne and Regali∣ty,
or his Realme, as is aforesaid: And they, which
bring or receive the same within the Realme, or make
thereof notification or any other execution within, or
without that they, &amp;c. shal forfit, &amp;c. and to be put out
of the Kings protection, &amp; be attached, &amp;c. and sue in
processe of Premunire, &amp;c. And against others, which
sue in other courts in derogation of the Kings royaltie.</P>
<P>By this it appeareth plainely, that the Pope and
Court of Rome continued still, and proceeded fur∣ther
in their exorbitant usurpatiou upon the Crowne
and Kings Royaltie, and the common Lawes of the
Kingdome; So this Parliament endavoured to meete
with, and stand with the same, namely in the parti∣cular
cases, which are specially mentioned, <HI>viz.</HI> Con∣cerning
Iudgements given in the Kings Court in
<PB REF="12"/>
these pleas and cases, and in translating of Prelates
&amp;c. and in other cases attempted against the Kings
Crowne and Regality; But it is manifest, that the in∣tent
and the scope and drift of the Parliament was
onely against the Pope and Court of Rome, and
against those persons, that persue any such Translati∣ons,
processe, &amp;c. or other things, which touch the
King, or against his Crown, or Regality or his Realme
as is aforesaid, and which being, notifie or execute the
same within the Realme or without, these be offen∣ders,
which the Parliament had cause, and meant to
punish; and it is strange and improbable that any
learned Iudge of the Common Laws of <HI>England,</HI>
should stretch or extend the words of this Statute
further, then only against the usurped aurhority of the
Pope, and Church of Rome; But it seemeth that
some that take pleasure <HI>ludere in vorbis, dormitare in
sensibus,</HI> and to dispute <HI>de apicibus juris, equi &amp; boni ra∣tione
praetermissâ,</HI> and to professe learning <HI>peritiâ literali
non intelligentiâ spirituali;</HI> And so are contented <HI>verba
legis tenere &amp; vim legis ignorare,</HI> have gone about to
presse and straine the word of this Statute, not onely
against the Pope and Church of Rome, but also a∣gainst
the Kings owne High Court of Chancery, and
other his Majesties Courts of Equitie in <HI>England,</HI>
grounding, their opinion and conceit upon these
words of the Statute.</P>
<P>If any purchase, in the Court of Rome or else where,
any such Translations, or processes, or other things
which touch the King: And for the better understan∣ding
hereof, it is to bee remembred, that the Pope &amp;
Court of Rome kept their Seiges and Court not at
Rome onely, but sometimes at <HI>Avignion,</HI> sometimes
at other places; and divers Antipopes beeing at one
<PB REF="12"/>
and the selfe same time, kept their severall seiges and
Courts at severall places, and yet each of them chal∣lenged,
and pretended to have supreame jurisdiction,
power, and authority over and above the King and his
Crown, &amp; regality in the cases before remēbred; And
therefore it was requisite and necessarie for the King
and the Parliament to withstand and provide remedy
against the same.</P>
<P>And that is the true and right understanding of
<HI>Ou Aylors:</HI> For it is too absurd to say, or imagine that
the King or Parliament meant to extend the same a∣gainst
the Kings owne Courts of equity in <HI>England,</HI>
which dirived their authority and jurisdiction from
him onely: and heard and determined, as his substi∣tutes,
according to equity and conscience, such cases
as the Iudges of the common Law could not by the
strict rules of the Common law Iudge &amp; determine.</P>
<P>These Courts and the Iudges, &amp; Ministers therof,
the King had power to suppesse, altar, and punish at
his pleasure, and therefore against these the Lords
Temporall and Commons needed not to engage
themselves to stand with the King and the Crowne,
and to live and dye, Nor the Lords Spirituall &amp; Cler∣gie
to promise to stand with the King, as they were
bound by their alleageance, with their Cautious pro∣testations
for the ordinarie, legall &amp; iuditiall procee∣dings,
the Chancery and Courts of equity according
to conscience.</P>
<P>The King, nor his Crowne, nor Regality, nor the
Common Law were not in any danger, but the dan∣ger
was by the ambitious usurpation of the Pope, and
the Church of Rome, and by the proceedings in the
Courts holden by that usurped authority; and there∣fore
against them the Parliament provide this Sta∣tute
<PB REF="13"/>
following, the example of the former Parlia∣ment
25. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. 27. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. and 38. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. and those be
the Courts which this Parliament, &amp; the Parliament
<HI>Anno</HI> 27. <HI>Ed.</HI> 3. <HI>cap.</HI> 1. noted to bee in derogation
of the Kings regalitie and destruction of the Com∣mon
Law, but not the Kings owne Courts of equity
and Conscience. And for the further clearing of this
doubt, if it be worthy to be made a doubt, how these
words <HI>ou Ayllors</HI> shall be understood, in the 5. <HI>Ed.</HI> 4.
there is this note,<NOTE PLACE="marg">An. 5. Ed. 4. 6. 9.</NOTE> <HI>Nota, que le statute de premunire est
in Curiâ Romanâ Vel alibi: lequel alibi, est intendue en les
Courtes del evesques illmit, que sihome soite excompe en court
del evesques perchose que appent all Royall Maiestie ses shose
alcomen lep il aur premunire &amp; issent adiudge &amp; fith:</HI> a∣bridging
that case saith,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Premunire.</NOTE> that 11. <HI>Hen.</HI> 7. the opinion
of the Court was so, which he himselfe heard.</P>
<P>By which it appeareth, that the Iudges did then
understand the proceedings by the Bishops in the
Spirituall Courts, which was by authority derived
from the Pope and Church of Rome, was onely
meant by the word <HI>vel alibi.</HI> But not the procedings
in the Kings owne Court of Chancery by authority
derived from him onely in cases of equity and Con∣science
not remediable, otherwise for that were to set
the King against himselfe, which is too inconveni∣ent
and absurd.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="13"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

