<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The honour of marriage, or, The institution, necessity, advantages, comforts, and usefulness of a married life set forth in a sermon January 27, 1694, at Seven-Oak in Kent / by Joseph Fisher ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Fisher, Joseph, d. 1705.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A39528</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing F1010</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R14340</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13589164</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13589164</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">100635</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A39528)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100635)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 843:4)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The honour of marriage, or, The institution, necessity, advantages, comforts, and usefulness of a married life set forth in a sermon January 27, 1694, at Seven-Oak in Kent / by Joseph Fisher ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Fisher, Joseph, d. 1705.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[6], 25 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1695.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XIII, 4 --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Marriage --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A39528">
<STC T="W">F1010</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13589164</BIBNO>
<VID>100635</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<P><PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<HI>The Honour of Marriage:</HI> OR, THE Institution, Necessity, Advantages, Comforts, and Usefulness of a <HI>Married Life:</HI> Set forth in a SERMON <HI>JANUARY</HI> 27. 1694. AT SEVEN-OAK in KENT.</P>
<P>By <HI>JOSEPH FISHER,</HI> Master of Arts, and Fellow of <HI>Queens</HI> Colledge in <HI>Oxon.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI> Printed for <HI>Brabazon Aylmer</HI> at the <HI>Three Pigeons</HI> over-against the <HI>Royal-Exchange</HI> in <HI>Cornhill.</HI></P>
<P>1695.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To his much Esteemed Friend Mr. THOMAS LAMBARD.</HEAD>
<P>THAT this Sermon was first Composed, then Preached, and now Published, I must plainly tell you without a Compliment, is not so much to be attributed to Your Request, as to that great Respect and Kindness I have for You. In which, that I might not leave the Text I had pitched upon, and the Bible too, or spend upon the Subject a meer Flou∣rish of Words and pure Invention: I have confined my Thoughts and Meditations to the Word of God, or ra∣ther fetched them from it; because it is that only Rule which should regulate our Opinions and Practices in the weighty concerns of our Life and Salvation, and which ought to give an Authority, Life, and Pungency to all Pulpit-Discourses. A Rule this is which God has given us, and which every Christian especially must consider and study with Fear and Veneration. I know there are, and have been some Men in the World, (witness the <HI>Theologo-Political, Leviathan, Theory, Critical History, Annotation</HI> and <HI>History-of-Religion-Wri∣ters)</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
who by the Power of Criticisms and Ʋpstart No∣tions of Philosophy, either of their own, and some other mens Invention, <HI>i. e.</HI> in my Judgment, by the In∣fatuation of the Devil, and the Pride of their Hearts, all conspire to ruin and undermine it. Many Books of this kind have appeared in the World, which if the Ge∣nius of the Age had not disposed men to receive, and even to gape for, had been comdemned to flames, of which they are worthy; and their Authors censured, as becomes the Civil and Ecclesiastical Laws of the place they live in. Curiosity knows no Bound, either of Modesty or Satisfaction; and therefore, tho it has been my misfortune to look into such Books (of which I de∣sire You to beware, and not to follow the Wondering and Silly World, if Ten thousand such should again appear in it) and in some measure to consider the Subject-Mat∣ter and Tendecy of them; yet I thank God they have no more influence upon my Mind to destroy my Faith, or lessen my Veneration for the Holy Bible, than Debauch∣ed Morals, or Ingenious Discourses upon the Praises of Vice, shall by the Grace of God move me to approve them in my Judgment, or in my practice to follow them. I look upon an Ʋnsanctified, Proud, and Aspi∣ring Head, to be as dangerous, as an Ʋngodly Heart; nay, far more; because the issues of this run in open Contradiction to the general Reason of Mankind: Whereas a Learned <HI>Rabbi,</HI> or one who pretends to be so, is beyond the Sphere of Ordinary Intellectuals; which is the sole Reason why he is admired so much, even then, when he preys upon the Ignorance of Men, and spreads loose Principles, Irreligion and Atheism in the World. Now some such Men as these have been trying their Skill on the Subject of my Sermon, and have en∣deavoured
<PB REF="3"/>
from the Armoury of their Learning, some indulged Practices of former Ages, and unwary Ex∣pressions of Ancient and Modern Authors, to overthrow the Laws of God and Man for no other end at all, than to let the Reins loose to Lasciviousness, and in a manner to Brutalize the World. I have in the fol∣lowing Discourse, as I said before, confined my Thought; to the Word of God, and next to that, the Laws of Men; which are nothing less than the Ma∣ture Deliberations, Decisions, and Responses of the Wis∣est and most Authoritative Persons of former Ages. For by these are we to frame our Notions and Opi∣nions, and to solve all Doubts concerning Marriage, which is a Subject, perhaps, that affords as many Ne∣cessary, Ʋseful, and Nice Enquiries, as any falls un∣der Humane Cognizance. The only end I aimed at, was to shew the Institution and Design of it, that You may know what State and Condition of Life You are now entered upon, and therefore I offer it to Your se∣rious perusal. For I am perswaded, if we would but consider what God expects of us in every Stage and Station of our Life, we would soon live as becomes Reasonable Men and Christians. Be pleased then to ac∣cept this as a Testimony of my Kindness; and God in Heaven bless You and the Excellent and Virtuous Lady, which is now your Wife, with his Spiritual and Temporal Blessings, and give you Grace to do his Will; that so you may fulfil the Desires of Your most Loving and Tender Parents, and the good Wishes of all your Friends; that you may attain those ends for which God has given you Excellent Endowments of Mind, Body, and Fortune, and answer the Expe∣ctation of your Country; that you may follow the Ex∣ample
<PB REF="4"/>
of your Great Grandfather, of whose Learning and Charity, the Books he writ, and the Colledge he Erected at <HI>Greenwich,</HI> are lasting Monuments; And lastly, that you may not frustrate the earnest Pray∣ers for your Temporal Prosperity and Eternal Happi∣ness, of</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED>Your Quondam-Tutor and ever Affectionate and Unfeigned Friend, JOSEPH FISHER.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>From <HI>Broad-Street,</HI> London, <DATE><HI>Febr.</HI> 2.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE Honour of Marriage, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><BIBL>HEB. XIII. 4.</BIBL>
<P>Marriage is honourable in all, and the bed undefiled; but whoremongers and adulterers God will judge.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>N this Prophane and Profligate Age, wherein Men generally, either from the <HI>Pride</HI> and <HI>Fol∣ly</HI> of their <HI>Wit</HI> and <HI>Learning,</HI> or from the Open and Impu∣dent <HI>Debauchery</HI> of their Lives, clamour against the <HI>Holy Insti∣tutions</HI> of <HI>God,</HI> as things either above, or below, or contrary to their <HI>Reason,</HI> or rather as <HI>Appointments</HI> to curb that <HI>Licentiousness</HI> they give themselves up unto; I hope it will not be amiss, especially for Persons of my Function, to endeavour all they can, as becomes them to put a stop to such spreading Impiety as
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
now abounds every where, but more notoriously in the most populous Places. And for this end, I think there can hardly be taken a more effectual Course, than to demonstrate to mens Reason, That Revealed Religion, as to the Moral and Preceptive part of it, injoyns no Duty but what is in the very na∣ture of the thing agreeable to the unprejudiced Voice, and promotive of the Common Good of Mankind. Wickedness may cloud mens Understanding, and somewhat <HI>Stifle</HI> the Natural Dictates of <HI>Reason,</HI> but it can never wholly exstinguish them; and there∣fore Divines may have this comfortable prospect for all their pains which they shall take in this mat∣ter, that they may force the most Loose and Un∣reasonable to an inward Self-accusation, although their Arguments and Dealings with them may not prove Efficacious enough intirely to reform them.</P>
<P>It is our Duty to labour in the <HI>Ways</HI> and <HI>Truths</HI> of <HI>God,</HI> and to leave the success of our Industry to his All powerful Blessing. For as there are Seasons wherein he <NOTE PLACE="marg">Isaiah 55. 11.</NOTE><HI>makes his word to prosper in the thing for which he sent it;</HI> So are there times of Judi∣cial Blindness, in which, what Prophets or Preach∣ers soever <HI>God</HI> raises up amongst them, mens hearts are hardened, and <NOTE PLACE="marg">Isaiah 6. 9, 10. Matth. 13. 14, 15. Rom. 11. 8.</NOTE> <HI>in seeing they see not; and in hearing, hear not; neither will they understand.</HI> Thus we know it was twice, if not oftner with that Nation which <HI>God</HI> made choice of to be his <HI>Peculiar People</HI> and <HI>Church;</HI> and if ever the like Judgment seize and harden any other <HI>Nation,</HI> we have the greatest reason to think it is then, when the Word of God has no effect upon it. For then
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
Men seem to be cursed with an hardened Heart, with an obstinate and rebellious Temper, and to be given up to a Spirit of Delusion, which will infatuate and confound them more and more, till they are ripe for Vengeance. God in his Mercy avert this sad Judgment from us of <HI>England,</HI> which has been heretofore peculiarly remarkable for a Reli∣gious Disposition. And therefore why should that Complaint be as just against us, as it was once against <HI>Israel? <NOTE PLACE="marg">Jer. 1. 21.</NOTE>How is the faithful city become an Harlot! it was full of judgement, righteousness lodged in it, but now murderers.</HI></P>
<P>I am very sensible such a Preface as this, is too large for that Discourse, which the Nature and Design of the Words I have read, lead me to. Be it so; yet I am fully convinced, it is not whol∣ly impertinent. For is it not that same Prophane∣ness from which men deride, much more refuse to practice the Sacred Laws of God, and the <HI>Aweful Establishments</HI> of his Will, that prompts them now to revile that Sacred and Necessary Institution and State of Life I am to speak of; which one would think needed not any thing like a positive Law from Heaven at first to ratify it? If we can see any thing in the World without a borrowed Light, we may see the necessity of this. And when the Laws of God, and the Verdict of Rea∣son meet together in the same thing, what grea∣ter evidence can we have either of the Sacred∣ness or Obligation of it? There is no curing by meer Natural Means that Blindess and Boldness which dare rise up against such an Institution; and therefore when the will and Sanction of God
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
are made manifest to the Consciences of Men; if wicked Wretches will still open their Mouths against them, it is because they are judicially blinded and given up to <NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 1. 26. 1 Peter 2. 11. Eph. 4. 19.</NOTE><HI>vile affections, to filthy and fleshly lusts,</HI> and <HI>unto lasciviousness, to work all uncleanness with gree∣diness.</HI> </P>
<P>I have said thus much before hand, because I am sensible that Marriage has been decried and reviled of late by those, who abstain from it, not for their Virtues or Religion sake, that they may with the more freedom of mind <NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 7. 34.</NOTE><HI>care for the things of the Lord;</HI> but rather that they may feed those Vices, and take their Pastime in those abominable Sins; for the prevention of which, it was in a great measure appointed and permitted to all Men, and Christians; some of whom perhaps might otherwise with more Ease and Undisturbedness in their Functions have lived without it. He must be a Man of strange Reservedness and Solitary Life, who knows not this to be a common Sub∣ject to break Jests upon, and then to give Enter∣tainment for Mirth and Laughter, when the Un∣faithfulness of either Married Party, or the Vio∣lation of those Religious and Solemn Vows which they made to each other, is either <HI>truly</HI> or <HI>falsly</HI> talk'd of. But believe me, it is a very dangerous thing to jest upon the Iniquities of Men. This is to meddle with edged Tools, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 14. 9.</NOTE> <HI>to make a mock of sin,</HI> and to be pleased with that which should make us all both Fear and Tremble. Let there∣fore men say what they list (for that wicked Men will do in spite of every thing that is Sacred) it is the Duty of all Conscientious Persons to regard
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
the Word of God, and to frame Notions of things, and to have a Veneration for them according to that Sacredness they derive from his Will and Appoint∣ment. Now after this manner I intend at present to consider Marriage, from these Words of the Di∣vine Author.</P>
<Q><HI>Marriage is honourable in all, and the bed undefi∣led,</HI> &amp;c.</Q>
<P>And for this end, I design to premise a brief Explication of them. <HI>Marriage is honourable.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE>The Words may be rendred either by way of <HI>com∣mand,</HI> Let <HI>Marriage be honourable,</HI> and so those that follow, <HI>Let the bed be undefiled;</HI> or of <HI>Assertion,</HI> as we do; but whether Form of Speech be taken, the sense is still the same as to the genuine Sig∣nification of the Words themselves. And by the term <HI>Honourable,</HI> we may not only understand that Marriage is lawful in Opposition to some <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Encratites, Saturninus, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> Madmen (for no better I can call them) the <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Epiph Haer. 3. Sect. 2. &amp; Seq. &amp; Haer 47. Sect. 1, 2. Iren. l. 1. c. 22.</NOTE> Haeresiologists, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Euseb. 4, 28, 29.</NOTE> Historians, and other <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Cl. Alex. lib. 3. Tert. contr. Marc. lib. 1. Vid. 1. Tim. 4. 3. &amp; ibi Com∣mentatores.</NOTE> Writers of the Primitive Church mention and confute; but also, that it is highly Expedient, Necessary, and Commendable in its self. Or thus, Marriage is that State of Life, which is and ought to be much approved and reverenced in all Civilized Nations; It <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Ham. in loc. lit. a.</NOTE> gains Respect and Priviledges amongst them. <HI>Nature, Religion,</HI> and the <HI>Pro∣pagation</HI> of Mankind require it; and therefore for the good it produceth, for the Original Insti∣tution
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
and Design of it, it should be looked upon with Esteem and Honour. This Author adds, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE>in <HI>All, Marriage is honourable in all,</HI> that is, in all Men; it is not unlawful for any, naturally consi∣dered. No man, much less any Society of Men, are by the natural or positive Law of God de∣barred from it. So that it is in it self as honour∣able in <HI>All</HI> as <HI>Any;</HI> or the Words, <HI>in all,</HI> may sig∣nify, <HI>Omnino atque perfecte; Omnibus modis,</HI> or <HI>omni ex parte,</HI> or the like, <HI>i. e.</HI> altogether as some <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Estius.</NOTE> in∣terpret them, or as in the <HI>Aethiopick</HI> Version <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> in every place, in all Nations, Religions, and Pro∣fessions. The <HI>Arabick</HI> Interpreter, thus renders <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, that is, as I understand it, in all States or Conditions of Men; whether they be High or Low, Noble or Ignoble, Rich or Poor, Old or Young; in all these a Married Life doth justly challenge a worthy Esteem. It follows in the Text, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE>And <HI>the Bed undefiled.</HI> By which we may first understand a pure Virginal or Chast Life, which every one that is acquainted with the Pri∣mitive Writers knows to have been highly <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 7. 34. Chrysost. de Virgin. c. 15, 16. Eus. prop. Evang. 1. 9. Grot. in 1 Cor. 7. 34.</NOTE> valued and extolled by the first Christians; in respect of which Mar∣riage its self was accounted somewhat polluted, and much inferior in degree of Purity and Chastity. Or Secondly, By these Words may be noted a Bed kept free from the deadly and crying Sins of Fornication, Adultery, Un∣cleanness, and all manner of Lasciviousness, whe∣ther in Married or Unmarried Persons. If the first Sense be taken, then the term Honourable is again to be repeated, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, as Rhetoricians speak,
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
after this manner; <HI>And the bed undefil<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d is ho∣nourable:</HI> So that both the Conjugal and Virgi∣nal Life are to be esteemed. Both of them are in themselves lawful, in their ends useful, and sometimes with respect to the several Conditions of Men necessary. And therefore Marriage is ho∣nourable, and a Virginal single Life is honourable when they are undertaken upon good Accounts, and Prudently and Christianly mannaged for the attainment of them. But if these Words be ta∣ken, as I think they ought to be, in Opposition to all Uncleanness and Unlawful Beds, then their meaning is, that Marriage only makes the Co∣habitation and Mutual Knowledge of Man and Woman lawful. To every one besides the Mar∣ried, the Bed is defiled either by Fornication or Adultery, which are Sins of a very heinous and dreadful Nature; for <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE><HI>whoremongers and adulterers God will judge.</HI> I take the word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> in this place to signify Fornicators, properly so called, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Grotius.</NOTE> as a Learned Man does. And therefore in this last Clause of the Verse, is contained a dreadful Threatning or Tremendous Judgment on all the Unchaste, whether Married, or Single Persons. God will severely punish such Sinners; their Sins are of a polluted and damning Nature; they pro∣ceed from the most <HI>vile Thoughts, unreasonable Appetites, ungov<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rned Passions,</HI> and <HI>filthy Lusts:</HI> And consequently the God of all Holiness and Pu∣rity must needs hate and abhor them; and pursuant to that Detestation and Aversion he has for them, will his Judgments be.</P>
<Q><PB N="8" REF="8"/>
Whoremongers and adulterers God will judge.</Q>
<P>Having thus far premised an Explication of my Text, which might naturally offer these Subjects to be treated on;</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. Upon what account Marriage is honour∣able.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. The Excellence and Design of a Monastick and Single Life, and how serviceable it may be to the Ho∣ly Offices of Religion.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. A Comparison betwixt the Married and Un∣married Life, with respect to God's Service and Christian Piety.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. The horrid Sinfulness of Whoredom and Adul∣tery, and what dreadful Punishments God has pro∣vided for them.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>I shall in a manner wave all the Three last, and pitch upon the first, as it is represented to our Consideration from the first Words of it, <HI>Marri∣age is honourable.</HI> And that I may speak of it su∣tably to this Sacred Penman's Design or Assertion, I intend to shew wherein the Honour of Marriage consists, or for what reasons such a State of Life is to be accounted Honourable, and purchase a great Esteem in the World. And for the more clear and effectual Prosecution of this Point, what I have to say shall be cast into these four following Parti∣culars.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. I will consider the first Institution of Mar∣riage.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB N="9" REF="8"/>
2. The necessity of it for the Propagation of the World, and the good of Mankind.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. The Advantages, Comforts, and happy Con∣sequents of it.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. I will consider it as it is an Antidote against the most notorious and crying Sins.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P N="1">1. I am to consider the first Institution of Mar∣riage, as it was ordained, and as I may say, so∣lemnized <NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 2. 22. C. 1. 27.</NOTE> by God himself in the two first Progeni∣tors of Mankind. For Revelation assures us, That God did not only make them, but likewise that he made them with a design to joyn them toge∣ther in a Marriage-Union. He formed the Wo∣man out of one part of the Man; and as the Scripture saith, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 2. 21, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE><HI>brought her unto him;</HI> which Di∣vine Act <HI>Adam</HI> interpreted to intimate the Solemn Bond of Matrimony, whereby they were once more to be made the <HI>same Bone,</HI> and the <HI>same Flesh.</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. Hiedeg. Exercit. 1. Sect. 9. <HI>&amp;c.</HI> J. Meyer. Uxor. Christ. disler. prim. Sect. 1. cap. 3. p. 34, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> c. 2. p. 19.</NOTE> This I take with Learned Men to be that place of Scrip∣ture, whereon the Solemnization of Mar∣riage is first grounded; <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Matth. 19. 3, 4, 5, 6.</NOTE> and to this we know our Lord and Saviour refer∣red as to the Original Law of Marriage in a Case concerning Divorce that was put to him. Now Marriage as such, containing a Solemn Obliga∣tion of Man and Wife to each other, and consist∣sting in the closest Bond of Union that can be be∣twixt two Individuals of the same Nature (<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Lomb. 4. d. 27. lit. b. Aq. Sup. Q. 44. Art. 1, 2. Greg. de Val. Tom. 4, disp. 10. punct. 1. de Sponsal. c 27. Q. 2.</NOTE> for by these I find both the School-men and Canonists
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
to define it from <HI>Isidore)</HI> and both of them being plain∣ly represented to us in this Matrimonial Conjuncti∣on of the first Man and Woman; I shall offer these things as most remarkable from this place of <HI>Genesis;</HI></P>
<P N="1">1. That God, by what Manisestation of himself I know not, was actually interested in it. And that first of all by framing the Woman out of the Man, which made her the more an affectionate and suitable Companion for him. She was but a Part and Portion of himself, beautified and adorn∣ed to attract his Love, to charm and win his Af∣fections; so that she was but <NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccl. 36. 24.</NOTE><HI>himself in his own likeness,</HI> being originally Bone of his Bone. And therefore as the Apostle argues, as <NOTE PLACE="marg">Eph. 5. 29.</NOTE><HI>no man ever yet hated his own flesh, but nourisheth and cherisheth it:</HI> So it was impossible that Man should not be ena∣moured with a Creature that was framed on pur∣pose for his <HI>Society</HI> and <HI>Assistance.</HI> In which Act of God (altho I will not say, that Marriage is a Sacrament, yet I think it may be affirmed) there was some∣thing Sacramental, implying that <HI>Mutual Love</HI> and <HI>Dearness,</HI> that <HI>Familiarity, Society,</HI> and <HI>Oneness,</HI> there ought to be betwixt them. All this the very Manner and Circumstances of the Womans Creation seemed to presignify, and was so un∣derstood by <HI>Adam,</HI> as appears in the Sequel of the Sacred Story.</P>
<P N="2">2. <NOTE PLACE="marg">See Bp. <HI>Patrick</HI>'s Comment. Gen. 2. 22. Vid. Perer. in dissert. de formatione Evae ex Adam. l. 4. p. 157, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> in Gen.</NOTE>And then Secondly, Whereas it is said, That <HI>God brought her to the Man;</HI> however that matter of Fact was ac∣complisht, I take the words to denote
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
God's Intention to make them One again in a Bond of Marriage. He offered her to him like a Father amongst us; he as it were contracted them. and gave her unto him in Wedlock. And on the other side, the Man approved and consented to this Act of God, and received her to be his Wife at his hands; this is specified in the 23d and 24th Verses of the Chapter.</P>
<P N="3">3. And then lastly, in this Transaction may be considered that Bond and Union which resulted from hence; even such an One as seem∣ed to cancel, or at least, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. Theoph. ad Aut<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="over-inked" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣licum, l. 2. p. 104.</NOTE> to take place of all other Obligations. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 2. 24.</NOTE><HI>Therefore</HI> (says <HI>Adam) shall a man leave his Father, and his Mother, and shall cleave unto his Wife; and they shall be one flesh.</HI></P>
<P>Now from all this, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. Pro. 19. 14. &amp; ibi inter Chald. &amp; Syriac. item Glossas Ab. Ezrae &amp; L. Ger∣som. Waganscil. Sota, p. 66.</NOTE> not to mention that peculiar hand of Providence, which is observed to be in all Marriages; I shall infer these Three following Obser∣vations.</P>
<P N="1">1. That Marriage is to be lookt upon as a Religious Bond and Contract. It depended at first upon a Solemn Institution of God, as to all the Essentials of it. And surely, amongst all Men, either of Reason or Religion, for this Cause it ought to be highly esteemed and honoured. The Laws of God, you know, should regulate every Act of ours that is governable by Reason; they should controul and direct our Natural Appetites, and keep them within those Bounds and Limits which he has set them. And therefore, because
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
whatever has any Character of <HI>Religion</HI> stampt upon it, does as such proceed from God, and he is the <HI>Author</HI> of it, and in our use thereof we should direct it to those ends which he has ap∣pointed; we are to look upon Marriage as a Sacred Obligation, and to observe the Instituti∣on and Design of God, whenever we enter up∣on it.</P>
<P N="2">2. Whatever God has made lawful or unlaw∣ful in his written Word, with respect to Marri∣age, we must own and acquiesce in, as such; for his positive Law, and the Actual Revelation of his Will, is the Fundamental Director in this case. I mean not that God should determine eve∣ry thing that belongs to Marriage-Solemnity; but that whatever he has determined at several times, and upon several occasions, to be of per∣petual practice, ought and must be Religiously observed by them, who have and acknowledge his Revelation.</P>
<P N="3">3. All that are Married, must look upon them∣selves as obliged to each other under a Sacred Bond and Tye of Religion. They are to be <HI>faithful</HI> for fear of a Curse from God, or of being <HI>Betrayers</HI> and <HI>Perverters</HI> of his Holy Institution. They are to drive on no separate Interests; they must consci∣entiously discharge those Duties which the ends of Marriage, their Union, and God himself, requires of them. <HI>No man</HI> should act contrary to him∣self; and consequently, <HI>no Married Persons</HI> should prejudice each other, for they are made One by <HI>Promise,</HI> by <HI>Bargain,</HI> and by <HI>Vow.</HI></P>
<P N="2"><PB N="13" REF="10"/>
II. The next thing I am to consider, is the Necessity of Marriage for the Propagation of the World, and the good of Mankind. Indeed, if God had left Man as undetermined, as he has done other Creatures, which multiply their several kinds, then there would have been no such thing as Mar∣riage; but having not only framed Man, and made him fit to propagate his Species by multi∣plying Individuals; but likewise determined him as to the Manner and Lawfulness of it by a Solemn Matrimonial Contract, which he has done in no other Species besides that I know of; it must needs be a Sin in any to break the Rules of this Determination; because it is an open Vio∣lation of a perpetual Law, for which an Account must be given in the Day of Judgement. And hence is it, that if Men must contiune to the World's end, 'tis necessary that People marry; otherwise they must Sin against God, and their Off-spring will be unlawful. This I would not have so understood, as that there is a necessity upon every one in particular to Marry; but that Man∣kind ought not, and therefore cannot lawfully be perpetuated in the World, save on∣ly by Wedlock. I know the <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Tal. Babyl. Tit. Jeb. 65. 2. Shulcan Aruch. in E∣ben. Ezre. p. 3. N. 1. Sect. 1. &amp; sic passim. apud. a∣lios.</NOTE> <HI>Jewish</HI> Canonists and Civilians affirm, That all Men are obliged to Marry; and they ground their Opinion on these words of Scripture; <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Gen. 1. 28.</NOTE> <HI>Be fruitful and multi∣ply and replenish the Earth, and subdue it.</HI> This is the first Commandment according to their Account; and is by them from the words of the
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
Text, called <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, i. e. <HI>Lex ad procreatio∣nem &amp; multiplicationem liberorum obligans.</HI> But I think they mistake the Sense of the Text, which in my Opinion is not <HI>so</HI> to be interpreted, as if it laid an Injunction upon every one to Marry; for they themselves exempt from it, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. Ja<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="over-inked" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>chi in Gen. 1. 28.</NOTE> some the whole Female Sex <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Maim. Hal. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. cap. 15. Sect. 1, 2. Vid. Buxt. de Sons. p. 8, 9. Hottin. de Jur. Heb. p. 6. &amp;c. Seld. de Jur. N. &amp; Gent. 5. c. 3.</NOTE>, others some Men either intirely, or till later years than the Obligation of this Law ac∣cording to their Decisions generally com∣menceth. And <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Gen. 1. 22.</NOTE> again, the same words are spoken of other Creatures which are capable of no such positive Law. And therefore I judge they denote, by a figurative Manner of Speech, the inward <HI>Disposition, Frame,</HI> and <HI>Nature</HI> of Mankind for multiplying themselves and peopling the World. God hath <HI>so made</HI> and ordained Man, that he is naturally apt and prone to propagate his own kind. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 1. 27, 28.</NOTE><HI>God</HI> (says <HI>Moses) created Man in his own image, in the image of God created he him; male and female created he them. And God blessed them, and God said unto them, be fruit∣ful and multiply and replenish the earth, and subdue it.</HI> Where the <HI>Hebrew</HI> word, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, which we translate, <HI>and he blessed them,</HI> seems to intimate Gods furnishing Man in his very Nature with powers and willingness to answer the end of his Creation, particularly that of perpetuating his Po∣sterity to the end of the World. This is an Ob∣servation (<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Ex V. si Sy∣nopseos Au∣thori fides.</NOTE> tho borrowed from another) of a <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Mr. Le Clerk.</NOTE> Learned and Late Critick upon the 22 Verse of this Chapter: Whom with <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">F. Simon.</NOTE> another, that is ashamed very often of his Name, and therefore
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. def. des Sentemens, &amp;c. lettre 1. p. 3.</NOTE> goes under many other: I may justy call Auda∣cious and Ungodly Dealers with the Word of God. For they appear to me to labour on purpose by their Criticisms, of which to unbridled Wits, there will never be an end, to undermine the Scriptures (as others do by their Whimsical No∣tions of Modish Philosophy) and to render them altogether useless for the ends of Piety and Religion, which God designed them for. May he in his due time by ways best known to himself, and agreeable to his Wisdom, blast such attempts upon his Sacred Oracles, which these men look on as a <HI>good old Book</HI> they may Cri∣ticize upon, and not as it is the <HI>Rule</HI> of our <HI>Faith and Manners.</HI> In short then, the fore∣mentioned Text containing a Benediction founded in the Nature and Faculties of Men, the use and exercise of them ought to be, and are, (as I have shewed before) regulated by the Law of God, as all our Powers governable by Reason must be.</P>
<P>And therefore, as God has ordained Marriage as the only means for the Continuation of Men in the World, none can violate this method without sinning most heinously against him. For whoever is such a Transgressor, turns the <HI>Sin of his Soul</HI> into the <HI>Fruit of his Body;</HI> makes him∣self polluted and brutish; propagates the Seed of <HI>Baseness, Reproach,</HI> and <HI>Corruption;</HI> lets his Lusts and Vile Affections hurry him on to break the Laws of God, and he kindles and fans that burn∣ing Flame which will destroy him in the lowest Hell. God has restrained all licentiousness by a
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
Maraiage Institution; and why then should men transgress this Law which is so <HI>Sacred</HI> and <HI>Per∣petual;</HI> hardly any Sins are more provoking than Adultery, Fornication, and Uncleanness: God will avenge such severely, he will punish them dreadfully, if we may believe his written Word; and therefore those that are guilty of them, cannot escape Everlasting Fire. Now, from all this, you see what an Honour is reflected on Marriage from God; it makes the Bed unde∣filed; legitimates the World; makes Parents honest, credits their Off-spring, and derives a Blessing from Heaven. In fine, it gives <HI>Being, Honour, Privi∣ledges, Rights,</HI> and <HI>Blessings</HI> to Children, amongst all Civilized Nations.</P>
<P N="3">III. Having thus far laid before you the Ori∣ginal and Necessity of a Married Life, both of which proceed from the Natural and Positive Law of God, I shall now in the next place consider the Blessings and Consolations of it: For it is a State which has its present Com∣forts; and in the first Designation thereof, was ordained for the attainment of them; and for this reason neither Sex can complain that God has imposed a burthen too heavy for them to bear. For,</P>
<P N="1">1. First, <HI>Moses</HI> says, That after Man was crea∣ted, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 2. 18. Vid. Buxt. de Spons. 132. M. Ben. Israel. Concil. in Gen Q. 16.</NOTE><HI>The Lord God said it is not good that man should be alone; I will make him an help meet for him. It is not good;</HI> that is to say, it is no way <HI>convenient</HI> or <HI>comfortable,</HI> or <HI>agreeable</HI> to him
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
or his condition in the world, and therefore he created <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Ezet Ceneg∣do.</NOTE> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> a <HI>Help meet for him,</HI> as we in∣terpret it: But the words are variously translated by others, viz. <HI>Anxilium simile sibi,</HI> in the vulgar <HI>La∣tin,</HI> followed by the <HI>Syriack</HI> Version, a <HI>Help like unto himself,</HI> i. e. one of the same <HI>Nature</HI> and <HI>Constitu∣tion</HI> with him; one of equal <HI>Tenderness</HI> and <HI>Regard</HI> for him as he has for himself, or one created on pur∣pose to perform all those kind offices of assistance which his condition in the world requires from her; in the <HI>Septuagint,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, an Assistant according to himself; that is, according to his <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. Lud. de Dieu in loc.</NOTE> Na∣ture and wants and wishes. In the <HI>Chaldaick</HI> Version of <HI>Onkelos,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> in the <HI>Samaritan,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> a Help, a Support, a Prop, <HI>as before him;</HI> and in the <HI>Arabick,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> of the same meaning; so that in the sense of these three Translations, wherein the Grammatical signification of the word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> is expressed, and therefore put in the Margin of our <HI>English</HI> Bibles, the whole Sentence implies, that God created <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. Fag. &amp; Kimchi in Rad.</NOTE> one that would be a <HI>present</HI> and <HI>perpetual</HI> aid to man; one that should be <HI>always</HI> at hand, in his <HI>power,</HI> and <HI>helpful.</HI> The <HI>Jerusalem Targum</HI> is somewhat obsure and paraphrastical, I will make him <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>a Yoke-fellow that may go out with him.</HI><NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. Buxt. loc. praed.</NOTE> I shall pass by those extravagant Interpretations some <HI>Jews</HI> make on purpose to coun∣tenance their Opinions concerning Divorce, and shall content my self with <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. Nold. conc. p. 1003. Num. 1381.</NOTE> that Gloss of a Rabbi as I find him cited, because the <HI>Jews</HI> generally agree in it, <HI>I will make an help</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>which shall be always with him, or at hand, to minister un∣to, and to observe him.</HI> But what needs Criti∣cism?
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
the best way to interpret <HI>words</HI> is to con∣fider <HI>things,</HI> and to direct the meaning of <HI>those</HI> to the nature and use of <HI>these;</HI> and therefore by the word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> we may understand, that the Wo∣man was created, to perform all the Duties incum∣bent upon her towards the Man, not excluding his towards her; and consequently she was not or∣dained or given to him for the <HI>Gratification</HI> of his <HI>Lust,</HI> but for the <HI>Comfort</HI> of his <HI>Life.</HI> And from hence you see for what God made such a Fellow creature; <HI>It was not good for Man</HI> to be single and solitary, he wanted one to assist and cherish him; to be his individual Companion; a <HI>Constant,</HI> a most <HI>Intimate Familiar,</HI> and a <HI>Bosom-Friend.</HI></P>
<P>We of all God's Creatures are born for So∣ciety; of which Husband and Wife are the first two, a whole Family the next part, a City the third, and so on till you come to the last Com∣plement or Combination of it: And as all Socie∣ty is appointed for the good of every Individual of it, so is that of Man and Wife by the ex∣press Command and Counsel of God who made them. <HI>Adam</HI> in a Reply to God, calls her, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 3. 12.</NOTE><HI>The woman whom tho gavest to be with me.</HI> The <HI>Hebrew</HI> Words, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>The woman which thou gavest with me</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. Inter. Syr. Chald.</NOTE>, i. e. to stand by me (as some seem to suppose) are thus rendred by the <HI>Samaritan</HI> Version <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Nold. conc. p. 1059. Num. <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="over-inked" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>830.</NOTE>, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>The woman which thou broughtest to me,</HI> viz. which thou didst <HI>betroth</HI> unto me, give to be my <HI>Spouse</HI> or <HI>Wife,</HI> and join to me in the strictest Bond of Union. So that from the sense of these two places, we
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
fully learn what end God aimed at in the Crea∣tion of the Woman, and the Donation of her to the Man; namely, That they should mutually assist each other, and be one and the same Person almost in every Condition of Life. They were to <HI>com∣municate</HI> in each others <HI>Joys, alleviate</HI> their <HI>Griefs,</HI> assist by their <HI>Prudence</HI> their <HI>Labour</HI> and <HI>Industry,</HI> and earnestly <HI>promote</HI> the welfare of one another. For thus, and thus only could the neces∣sities of their Nature be <HI>supplied,</HI> and their Infir∣mities <HI>supported,</HI> which otherwise each of them must inevitably have laboured under if remaining Single. And if we will believe Inspired Writers, the Woman is not only the <HI>Comfort,</HI> but the <HI>Or∣nament</HI> of a Man's Life. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 12. 4. Prov. 31, 10, 11, 12.</NOTE><HI>A vertuous woman is a crown to her husband, Her price is for above ru∣bies; the heart of her husband doth fully trust in her; she will do him good, and not evil, all the days of her Life.</HI> To which I will add these words of <HI>Syracides, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ecclus. 36. 24.</NOTE>He that getteth a Wife, beginneth a Possession; a help like unto himself, and 4 Pillar of rest.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. That I may further shew how <HI>joyous</HI> and <HI>comfortable</HI> such a Life as this is; it may be suffi∣cient to observe, That <HI>Love</HI> which sweetens every thing we desire, or take in hand in this World, ought in Marriage to have a ruling share, or at least a very <HI>large Proportion.</HI> For it is not only that thing which <HI>may,</HI> but which <HI>must</HI> be the Bond of Matrimonial Union. 'Tis this which must move the Heart and Affections of each Party, determine the Choice, gain Consent, (<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Vid. decret. <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="over-inked" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Cans. 27. Q. 2. Matrimoni∣um &amp; Suffi∣ciat.</NOTE> which is the most Es∣sential Part of the Espousals) and which will cast a
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
perpetual <HI>Joy</HI> and <HI>Delight</HI> upon the <HI>Happy Pair.</HI> Every one that considers the State of Humane Nature, must know what an absolute Command this Passion has in the <HI>Bravest</HI> and <HI>Wisest</HI> Hearts. 'Tis this that makes Men ruin themselves, or pro∣mote their own welfare; for we often <HI>love</HI> what we should <HI>hate,</HI> and we <HI>hate</HI> what we should <HI>love;</HI> and from hence is it that we are made Mi∣serable. In truth, it requires <HI>great Art,</HI> much <HI>Watchfulness,</HI> strength of <HI>Judgment,</HI> a controuling <HI>Sway</HI> over our selves, a <HI>profound Fear</HI> of God, and <HI>Sense</HI> of <HI>Religion,</HI> to regulate this Passion, and to keep it upon right Objects, and within bounds of Moderation: But I may say, That in the Mar∣ried State it can hardly have <HI>exceedings:</HI> the <HI>dearer</HI> the <HI>Affection,</HI> the <HI>better</HI> it is; and the more <HI>intire,</HI> the more <HI>pure,</HI> the more <HI>lasting</HI> that love is, 'tis the more <HI>commendable,</HI> and makes Life more <HI>comfortable. Husbands</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Col. 3. 19.</NOTE> (says St. <HI>Paul) love your wives,</HI> for this <HI>cements</HI> them together into One; it mingles their Affections, gives them one <HI>Heart</HI> and one <HI>Soul;</HI> and whatever makes a Se∣paration, is either the <HI>bitterness</HI> of Death, or the more tormenting <HI>Flames</HI> of Contention. He knows not what Love is, nor the Joys that follow it, <HI>i. e.</HI> he has nothing at all of Humanity in him, who perceives not in his mind the many Consolati∣ons which must arise from such united Hearts, from such a <HI>redoubled force</HI> of <HI>Kindness</HI> and <HI>Affe∣ction.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. Further, Thirdly, That which may recom∣mend a Married Life to all but Prophane and Las∣civious Wretches is this, that it engages Men to
<PB N="21" REF="14"/>
<HI>Industry</HI> and <HI>Labour,</HI> to <HI>Honesty</HI> and <HI>Providence,</HI> and to be <HI>Religions</HI> and <HI>Useful</HI> in the World. For what are all <HI>Men,</HI> and the <HI>Riches</HI> of the World, but so many <HI>Monuments</HI> of Marriage Blessings? What is it else that maintains the <HI>Port,</HI> and car∣ries on the <HI>business</HI> of Humane Society? The Being and Well-being of Families and Kingdoms; nay, the Cloister it self which contends for Pre-eminence, does wholly depend upon it; dares therefore any be so bold and impudent as to think <HI>slightly,</HI> or talk <HI>scurriously</HI> of that which has produced so much good in the World! And of which he himself, unless he be <HI>Bise</HI> and <HI>Ignominious,</HI> is a <HI>Fruit</HI> and <HI>Production.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4. And lastly, When I have named <HI>Children,</HI> I have said enough upon this Head of my Dis∣course. For these are the greatest Worldly Bles∣sings that God can bestow upon any; they are the <HI>Repositories</HI> where <HI>Parents</HI> bestow the Fruits of their Industry and Labours; they are the <HI>Dar∣lings</HI> of their <HI>Affections,</HI> which ill Behaviour and Undutifulness can never wholly extinguish. Ex∣perience teaches us, and the young Part of Man∣kind may be glad of it, that nothing excites greater Love or Care in Parents than Children; for which this reason may be given, that Nature, whose Inclinations and Propensions are unconquer∣able, has implanted in them a deep Tenderness and Love for their Off-spring: whereas God knows they have too too often very little cause to be kind and loving. Oh! how do they rejoyce at the blooming <HI>Hopes</HI> and <HI>Welfare</HI> of their Children! They think no <HI>Pains</HI> too much, no <HI>Labour</HI> too te∣dious
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
for a happy Provision for them: And why should not Fathers do so? for their Children are nothing less than themselves <HI>multiplied,</HI> their <HI>Names</HI> and <HI>Beings</HI> in a manner made <HI>Immortal</HI> in the World, or continued down from <HI>Generation</HI> to <HI>Generation.</HI> This we find reckoned a Blessing from God on the Pious Man.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psalm 128. 1, 2, 3, 6.</NOTE><HI>Blessed is every one that feareth the Lord: that walketh in his ways. For thou shalt eat the labour of thy hands: happy shalt thou be, and it shall be well with thee. Thy wife shall be as a fruitful vine by the sides of thine house: thy children like olive-plants round about thy table. They shall see thy childrens children.</HI> Again, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Psalm 127. 3, 4, 5.</NOTE><HI>Children are an heritage of the Lord: and the fruit of the womb is his reward. As arrows are in the hand of mighty men: so are children of the youth. Hap∣py is the man that hath his quiver full of them: they shall not be ashamed, but they shall speak with the ene∣mies in the gate.</HI></P>
<P N="4">IV. The last thing I proposed, was to consider Marriage as an Antidote against the most <HI>notori∣o<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="over-inked" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> and <HI>crying Sins;</HI> and now what are these? Even the <HI>vilest</HI> that man can be guilty of, and which God has severely threatened and censured in his Revealed Word. They are such as neither Sex can commit till they have cast off <HI>all Modesty, all Man∣ners,</HI> and <HI>all Fear of God.</HI> The very naming of them (and for brevity and haste, I will but just name them) is enough to make all Men <HI>detest</HI> and <HI>dread</HI> them; they are <HI>Adultery, Fornication,</HI> and <HI>Acts</HI> of <HI>Uneleanness;</HI> the <HI>horrid</HI> and <HI>damning Nature</HI> of which may be manifested, if we consider,</P>
<P N="1"><PB N="23" REF="15"/>
1. That they are downright Violations of the Marriage Institution.</P>
<P N="2">2. They bring an infamy upon Humane Nature; for they bastardize the Race of Men, they entail a Disgrace upon Posterity, which is counted Ignomi∣nious and Base both in the Laws of God and Men. And then,</P>
<P N="3">3. Lastly, They are Sins against that Purity and Chastity both of Mind and Body, which our Lord requires in every one of his Disciples. <NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 6. 18.</NOTE><HI>Flee for∣nication,</HI> says the Apostle, <HI>Every sin that a man doth, is without the body: but he that committeth for∣nication, sinneth against his own body.</HI> Again, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ibid. v. 9, 10.</NOTE> <HI>Know ye not that the unrighteous shall not inherit the king∣dom of God? Be not deceived: neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, or abu∣sers of themselves with mankind, shall inherit the kingdom of God. O sad and tremendous judgment!</HI> In short, Such Sins as these when indulged in, and not punished as the Law requires, when the Actors of them are discoverd, are of <HI>Infection</HI> enough to spread over and debauch Mankind, and of <HI>weight</HI> and <HI>guilt</HI> enough to <HI>sink</HI> and <HI>condemn</HI> a Nation. For my Text tells us, <HI>Whoremongers and adulterers God will judge.</HI></P>
<P>I have now finished so far as the time would give me leave, the Four Particulars I at first proposed, and shall hasten to a Conclusion. You find from what has been said, from whence a Marriage had its Ori∣ginal, what are the Benefits and Blessings of it, which are <HI>so</HI> many and <HI>so</HI> great, that to men who consider what the World is, what the State and Condition
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
of Humane Nature is, it must both appear <HI>Neces∣sary</HI> and <HI>Praiseworthy.</HI> God and Nature has made it an <HI>Honourable State</HI> of Life; and where it is, there is <HI>Power,</HI> and a <HI>just</HI> and <HI>high Respect</HI> is due unto it. So that every Married Man as such, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 31. 23.</NOTE><HI>Should be known in the gates, when he fitteth amongst the el∣ders of the Land.</HI> To be a Father or a Mother, a Husband or a Wife, a Master or a Mistriss, are all of them Titles of Authority and Honour; and some of them are communicated to the greatest Monarchs, as Names of Endearment and Venerati∣on; for they are Fathers to the Kingdoms they go∣vern; and when they are such as that Name im∣ports, they then <HI>have</HI> Power, and they <HI>do</HI> deserve it. What now need I add more to recommend this State of Life to the good Opinion of all Men, seeing that by the Laws of God so much Honour is due to it? Yet, however, what I have said, must not be so understood, as that I would seem to lay a Necessity, or an Obligation in conscience up∣on all Men to Marry. No! I do not intend that, for I dare not censure Celibacy so severely, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Ber. Rabbah. par. 34. 21. 2. Ed. ven.</NOTE> as the <HI>Jews</HI> do; and it is sufficiently known what the Opinions and Practices of the Primitive Christians were with relation to the Unmarried and Married Life. A great deal, I think, is to be allowed to the Prudence or Tempers of Men in this case, and to their Circumstances in the World; and there∣fore, tho I dare not condemn any for remaining Single, yet I think no reason can be so <HI>excusable,</HI> or at least <HI>laudable</HI> for it, as when Men continue in it upon the account of Religion, <HI>viz.</HI> when they may serve God the better in <HI>that,</HI> than the Married Sta∣tion.
<PB N="25" REF="16"/>
Certainly to abstain from Marriage, from a principle of <HI>Looseness,</HI> a <HI>sordid</HI> and <HI>base</HI> Temper of Mind, from Sowreness, ill Nature, and the like, is a thing very sinful.</P>
<P>To conclude all, I shall from a Consideration of what has been said upon the <HI>Sacredness, Necessity, Consolations, Ends,</HI> and <HI>Ʋsefulness</HI> of a Married Life, shut up this Discourse with some Expressions of the wise Son of <HI>Syrach,</HI> whose Rules of Life, Judgment of Things, and Elegance of Speech, ani∣mated with a strain of Piety, shew him to be a Man of an extraordinary Spirit. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccl. 40. 23. and 26. 1, 2, 3.</NOTE> <HI>A friend and a companion never meet amiss; but above both, is a wife with her husband. Blessed is the man that hath a ver∣tuous wife, for the number of his days shall be double. A vertuous woman rejoyceth her husband, and he shall fulfil the years of his life in peace. A good wife is a good portion, which shall be given in the portion of them that fear the Lord.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="printer's note">
<P>MOnendas es B. L. quod ob defectum Typorum Aethiopicorum, Arabisorum, &amp; Samaritanorum, voces istarum linguarum quibus usi sumus Charactere Hebraico edi curavimus, vale &amp; boni consule.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

