<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The declaration of Colonell Goring vpon his examination touching the late intended conspiracie against the state, vvith the report of that worthy gentleman Mr. Fynes to the House of Commons from the Committee upon the examination of severall gentlemen concerning the same, Iune 1641.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Goring, George Goring, Baron, 1608-1657.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A41570</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing G1303C</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R40490</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">19340374</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 19340374</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">108712</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A41570)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108712)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1671:10)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The declaration of Colonell Goring vpon his examination touching the late intended conspiracie against the state, vvith the report of that worthy gentleman Mr. Fynes to the House of Commons from the Committee upon the examination of severall gentlemen concerning the same, Iune 1641.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Goring, George Goring, Baron, 1608-1657.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 9 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1641.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A41570">
<STC T="W">G1303C</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">19340374</BIBNO>
<VID>108712</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
DECLARATION
OF COLONELL
GORING
Vpon his Examination, touching
the late intended CONSPIRACIE
against the State.
VVith the Report of that worthy
Gentleman M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>FYNES</HI> to the House of
Commons from the Committee upon the
Examination of severall Gentlemen
concerning the same.
<HI>Iune</HI> 1641.</P>
<P>Printed in the yeare 1641.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="declaration">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Examination and Declara∣tion
of Colonell Goring, touching the
late Conspiracie.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>Aving been told there was an in∣tention
to unite the Forces of our
<HI>Armie,</HI> and to put it into a posture
of being <HI>able,</HI> if not of purpose
of being <HI>willing,</HI> to interpose in
the <HI>proceedings of Parliament:</HI> I hearkned to
the <HI>propositions</HI> of solliciting a <HI>redresse</HI> for the
miseries of the <HI>Souldiers,</HI> being the first step to
this, in respect of the present necessities of it,
not any future consequence of trouble to those
that were to procure our reliefe.</P>
<P>But, lest the manner of asking this, or the
effects of it being obtained, might be lesse just
then the thing it selfe which was desired, and I
might be involved in their <HI>crimes,</HI> that had fur∣ther
ends perhaps then meerly <HI>the redresse of our
Armies grievances:</HI> I thought it not unsafe, to
take some witnesses of mine integrity along
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
with me, and spoke to a noble <HI>Lord</HI> the very
same day, when I assured <HI>him,</HI> there were some
<HI>Officers</HI> of the <HI>Armie</HI> that were lesse thought on,
that had greatest zeale to the proceedings of
this <HI>House,</HI> And I thought there would be an
occasion to let him know more of it.</P>
<P>Within few dayes after this, M. <HI>Iermyn</HI> and
I were admitted into a consultation, where
wee were tyed to secrecie by an <HI>Oath,</HI> in the
company of those <HI>Gentlemen</HI> I have named
in my <HI>Depositions,</HI> where their <HI>purpose</HI> was de∣clared
to us in some <HI>propositions,</HI> which were to
this effect.</P>
<P>1. Putting an <HI>Armie</HI> into a Posture to serve
the <HI>King.</HI></P>
<P>2. Sending a <HI>Declaration</HI> to the <HI>Parliament,</HI>
containing, That no <HI>Act</HI> of <HI>Parliament</HI> should
bee made contrary to any former <HI>Act</HI> which
was expressed, That the Episcopacie should be
kept up as it is now.</P>
<P>3. And that the <HI>Kings revenue</HI> should be
<HI>established.</HI></P>
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<P>This I thought unlawfull for our under∣takings;
since I thought they intended to in∣terpose
the <HI>determinations</HI> of this <HI>House;</HI> and, it
belongs to an <HI>Armie,</HI> to <HI>maintaine,</HI> not to <HI>con∣trive</HI>
Acts of State.</P>
<P>I objected therefore against the <HI>propositions,</HI>
and pressed more the <HI>Follies</HI> and <HI>Difficulties,</HI>
then the <HI>illegalities</HI> of them; not onely because
I thought <HI>Reason,</HI> a greater Argument with
them, then <HI>Conscience,</HI> but because I am so un∣happy
of the two, to bee thought a worse
<HI>Common-wealths man,</HI> then a Souldier, and in
that quality, could procure most credit to my
words: And I endeavoured to shew them, that
as the <HI>Designe</HI> would be impious, if their most
<HI>Desperate Counsell</HI> had beene followed, so it
would have beene the weakest that ever was
undertaken, if it were admitted.</P>
<P>And whereas I am said to have a part in
this <HI>violent Counsell;</HI> till the day before this
meeting, I never heard word of it: I knew
not when I came to the Roome, whether theirs
were not the same with the other; this they
may witnesse for me; and that I declared, that
I would have to doe with neither, And that I
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
expressed a Contempt of our meeting in that
manner.</P>
<P>But I relye upon the <HI>Testimonie</HI> of some No∣ble
<HI>Lords</HI> of his <HI>Majesties Councell,</HI> and others,
how I protested against all those <HI>violent Coun∣sells,</HI>
even in the birth of them, and with what
pity I looked towards the person of his <HI>Ma∣jestie,</HI>
and the whole Kingdome, in this busi∣nesse.</P>
<P>I appeale also to <HI>them,</HI> and to some mem∣bers
of this House, what my carriage was to∣wards
these Gentlemen that were embarqued
in these undertakings, intending rather to pre∣vent
a mischiefe by abandoning their <HI>Coun∣sells,</HI>
then to ruine them, by disclosing them.</P>
<P>But mistake me not, for had I knowne of
any former plot proceeded in, that would en∣danger,
or disturb the quiet of his <HI>Majestie,</HI> or
the peace of this <HI>Kingdome,</HI> I should not have
beene contented with declaring mine owne
<HI>Innocencie,</HI> nor have stayed till the Command
of this <HI>House,</HI> or an Oath, extorted from mee a
Discovery; But by a hasty, open Declaration,
have broken the Lawes of <HI>Amity,</HI> and <HI>Friend∣ship,</HI>
and all former tyes, to preserve the duty of
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
a subject; and as freely exposed the Know∣ledge
of <HI>All,</HI> to the view of the world, as I
have beene tender in publishing these <HI>purposes,</HI>
even to my neerest friends, which had waight
enough to crush nothing but the underta∣kers
of it. And certainly, if they had stayed
where I left them, there was no <HI>conclusion</HI>
at all.</P>
<P>It appeares, there were two severall <HI>Inten∣tions,</HI>
digested by others before they were com∣municated
to me, and I knew not, whether
my hearkning to them were a <HI>fault,</HI> but I am
sure it was a <HI>misfortune.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="report">
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
<OPENER><DATELINE><DATE>June 19. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE></OPENER>
<HEAD>The Report of M<SUP>r</SUP>. Fynes, with
the examinations of severall Gentlemen,
concerning the late intended Conspiracie
against the State.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">M</SEG>Aster <HI>Fynes</HI> made a Report from the
<HI>Committee,</HI> to the House of <HI>Commons,</HI>
that the <HI>Conspirators</HI> in the new
<HI>Treason</HI> had a three-fold Designe.</P>
<P>First, concerning the <HI>Tower</HI> of <HI>London.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, the <HI>French Armie,</HI> to deliver <HI>Ports∣mouth</HI>
into their hands.</P>
<P>Thirdly, a Designe against the <HI>Parliament,</HI>
by working the <HI>Armie</HI> against it.</P>
<P><HI>Billingsleys</HI> Examination was read by Ma∣ster
<HI>Hambden,</HI> which shewes, That Sir <HI>Iohn
Suckling</HI> invited him to the imployment.</P>
<P>M. <HI>Nutts</HI> Examination was likewise read
by the said Master <HI>Hambden,</HI> which shewes,
The <HI>Earle of Straffords</HI> Escape was practised.</P>
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
<P>Then the Examination of the <HI>Lievtenant</HI> of
the <HI>Tower</HI> was read, which shewes plainely,
That the Earle of <HI>Strafford</HI> endeavoured an
escape, promising him 22000 pounds in marri∣age
with his Daughter to the <HI>Lievtenants</HI> sonne,
and to have made her one of the richest
matches in the <HI>Kingdome.</HI></P>
<P>Concerning the Army, <HI>Lievtenant Colonell
Ballards</HI> Examination was read by Sir <HI>Philip
Stapleton;</HI> which shewes, That Captaine
<HI>Chidley,</HI> brought downe to the Army many
<HI>propositions: viz.</HI> That Colonell <HI>Goring</HI> should
be <HI>Lievtenant</HI> of the <HI>Armie,</HI> and that the <HI>Prince,</HI>
and the <HI>Earle</HI> of <HI>Newcastle</HI> would meet in <HI>Not∣tinghamshire</HI>
with 1000 Horse; all which <HI>pro∣positions</HI>
came from Master <HI>Henry Iermyn,</HI> and
were dispersed by <HI>Sergeant Major Wallis,</HI> and
<HI>Captaine Chidley.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Wallis</HI> upon his Examination sayes, That
the <HI>French</HI> would have assisted them, and that
the <HI>Clergie</HI> would at their owne Charge have
sent 2000 Horse to the ayde of the <HI>Armie;</HI> And
that the Earle of <HI>Newcastle</HI> should be <HI>Generall</HI>
of the <HI>Armie;</HI> and that the <HI>Prince</HI> would come
downe with him.</P>
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>
<P>The Examination of <HI>Colonell Goring</HI> was
read by Sir <HI>Iohn Clotworthy,</HI> In which he sayes,
That hee was tyed up by an <HI>Oath</HI> of Secrecie,
and therefore durst not answer to all the <HI>In∣terrogatories;</HI>
and then mentioning the <HI>Oath,</HI>
which was given him by M. <HI>Percie</HI> in his own
Chamber at <HI>Whitehall,</HI> in presence of M. <HI>H. Per∣cie,
Willmot,</HI> Colonell <HI>Ashburnham,</HI> M. <HI>Hugh Pol∣lard,</HI>
and others, who then said, they had all
of them taken this <HI>Oath;</HI> and that hee was the
last of the Company that had taken the <HI>Oath</HI>
that M. <HI>Iermyn</HI> had passed under the <HI>Lievtenants</HI>
owne hand.</P>
<P>Mistris <HI>Plumwell</HI> said, That a French man,
<HI>Carver</HI> to the <HI>Queene,</HI> brought <HI>Armes</HI> to her
House, and desired her to keepe them, for that
the House of <HI>Commons</HI> had made an <HI>Order,</HI> that
no <HI>Papists</HI> should have <HI>Armes</HI> in their Custo∣die,
and that he fetcht them away again, about
the time that the Earle of <HI>Straffords</HI> Escape was
practiced.</P>
<P>Many Examinations were read, to shew
the practices of the <HI>French,</HI> and a Canon of
<HI>Burdeux.</HI></P>
<P>Then a Letter from Master <HI>Iermyn</HI> to Master
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
<HI>Mountague</HI> was read, wherein he writes, That
he hopes that the horse-leeches will be starved
for want of food.</P>
<P>And then another letter from <HI>Mountague</HI> to
<HI>Iermyn</HI> was read, which shewes, That they
expected the Earle of <HI>Strafford</HI> shortly with
them.</P>
<P>And after that, the Examination of Master
<HI>Bland</HI> was read, which shewes the desire that
M. <HI>Iermyn</HI> had to get <HI>Portsmouth</HI> into his hands.</P>
<P>And also two letters were read, sent from
one <HI>Roberts</HI> a <HI>Priest,</HI> to the <HI>Bishop</HI> of <HI>Calcedon,</HI> in
recommendation of two <HI>English Priests.</HI></P>
<P>And then M. <HI>Allens</HI> and M. <HI>Thorralds,</HI> which
doe contradict one another.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

