<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Virginia's cure, or, An advisive narrative concerning Virginia discovering the true ground of that churches unhappiness, and the only true remedy : as it was presented to the Right Reverend Father in God Gvilbert Lord Bishop of London, September 2, 1661 : now publish'd to further the welfare of that and the like plantations / by R. G.</TITLE><AUTHOR>R. G.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A41851</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing G1624</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R10987</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13568419</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13568419</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">100355</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A41851)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100355)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 456:15)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Virginia's cure, or, An advisive narrative concerning Virginia discovering the true ground of that churches unhappiness, and the only true remedy : as it was presented to the Right Reverend Father in God Gvilbert Lord Bishop of London, September 2, 1661 : now publish'd to further the welfare of that and the like plantations / by R. G.</TITLE><AUTHOR>R. G.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gray, Robert, 16th/17th cent.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Greene, Robert, 17th cent.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[6], 22 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by W. Godbid for Henry Brome ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1662.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>R. G. is determined to be Robert Gray by Wing and noted with a question mark by B.M. Sabin states R. G. was probably Robert Greene, a clergyman in Virginia and cites E. D. Neill, "Notes on the Virginia colonial clergy," 1877, p. 18.  However, most sources, including B.M. and Sabin, list the work under G. R.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Church of England --  United States.</TERM><TERM>Virginia --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2002-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A41851">
<STC T="W">G1624</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13568419</BIBNO>
<VID>100355</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="imprimatur">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Imprimatur,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>GEO. STRADLING</HI> S. T. P. Rever. in Christo Pat. <HI>GILE.</HI> Episc. Lond. à Sac. domest.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>Ex Aed. Sabaud. <DATE>Sept. 15. 1662</DATE>.</DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Virginia's Cure: OR An ADVISIVE NARRATIVE CONCERNING VIRGINIA. DISCOVERING The true Ground of that CHURCHES Unhappiness, and the only true Remedy. As it was presented to the Right Reverend Father in God <HI>GVILBERT</HI> Lord Bishop of LONDON, <HI>September</HI> 2. 1661. Now publish'd to further the Welfare of that and the like PLANTATIONS: By <HI>R. G.</HI></P>
<Q><P>And this Gospel of the Kingdome shall be preach'd in all the world, for a witness unto all Nations, and then shall the End come,</P>
<BIBL>Mat. 24.14.</BIBL></Q>
<Q><P>Is it time for y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u O ye to dwell in your ceiled houses, and this House lie waste? Now therefo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thus, saith the Lord of Hosts, Consider your wayes,</P>
<BIBL>Hag 1.4, 5.</BIBL></Q>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed by <HI>W. Godbid</HI> for <HI>Henry Brome</HI> at the Signe of the <HI>Gun</HI> in <HI>Ivy-lane.</HI> 1662.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A PREFACE.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hat the following <HI>Advisive Narra∣tive</HI> was not at first intended for publique view, there needs no other argument then it self, the occasion and manner of address to perswade belief.</P>
<P>The occasion of writing this. The present careful and ingenious De∣puty Governour of <HI>VIRGINIA,</HI> Col. <HI>Francis Morison</HI> sent Petitionary Letters with Propositions for bettering the state of that Church, which fell to my lot to present to the Right reverend Fathers in God the Lord Bishop of <HI>London,</HI> and the then Lord Bishop of <HI>Worcester,</HI> understanding the Propositions, I made bold to inti∣mate, that those Propositions, though good, would onely palliate, not cure the miseries of that Church. Whereupon my Lord of <HI>London</HI> was pleased to enjoyn me to set down in writing some Propositions concerning it I gladly embrac'd the injunction, and blest God for the occasion.</P>
<P>But when I had stated and digested the Propositions, upon a reflex, they seemed too Magisterial to present to such a r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>verend Father of our Church, without giving some account of the g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ounds and reasons enforcing their Necessity.</P>
<P><PB REF="3"/>In persuance whereof I thought fit to premise a brief and plain D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>scription of our Peopl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d manner of Planting <HI>VIRGINIA</HI>; which as to the in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>abitants, or those that have seen that Countrey, is I con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ess need∣less: But as to those he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, who can have no other Idea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of it, than such as others Rela<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ons frame in their Minds; as also to the Discov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rie of the Grounds of their present unhappiness, and the asse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ting the kind and manner of their Remedie (which is the argument of this Discourse) seemed to me no more then needful.</P>
<P>It is now publish'd, through the hopes some have, it may further the Publique Good designed, which I pray God it may do; and possibly it may, by some or other of these ways.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st,</HI> It may occasion s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me of greater Abilities to assert more copiously and fully the T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uth of that Proposi∣tion I have bri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fly proved, <HI>viz.</HI> Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t it is the Duty of Christians <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>especially of such Christians as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eat Planta∣tions among the Heathen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so to unite their Habitations in Societies in Towns and Villages, as may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est conve∣nience them constant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y to attend upon the publique Mini∣stery of Gods Word, Sacram<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nts and wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ship. A Duty of so cle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r consequence from Holy Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ture, and so ne∣cessary to be put in practise, for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll being of such Plantations (as I hope will app<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> by the e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uing Narrative and Dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ourse that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to promote it, thr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ugh mens want of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> gain their assent by the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vidence <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> means alone, the number of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> if they assent they will at least be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> may not a little advantage the putting this Du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y into P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,
<PB REF="3"/>
especially in <HI>VIRGINIA</HI> (the most considerable Coun∣trey under the Heavens, which hath so long been abused, and yet languisheth under the neglect of it) which is the main End design'd.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Secondly,</HI> It may possibly help to prevent the like Errors in Seating some new Plantations, which were committed, and are yet continued in Planting <HI>VIR∣GINIA.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Thirdly,</HI> It may direct noble Heroick Spirits (those liberal Souls that devise liberal things) to the most moving objects of Christian Compassion and Charity, that I think the whole Latitude of our most orthodox Prote∣stant Church can present them. Particularly it may direct their Charity to endow Fellowships in our Universities of <HI>Cambridge</HI> and <HI>Oxford,</HI> which may bear the Name of <HI>VIR<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>INIA Fellowships,</HI> and may be appropriated for supply of the Churches in <HI>VIRGINIA,</HI> upon the Con∣ditions specified in the fifth Proposition <HI>(pag. 10.)</HI> Nor need such Persons doubt to obtain by the Parliament a Confirmation of the Penalty therein specified, in case the Persons that shall be admitted to such Fellowships shall refuse to perform the Conditions of their Admittance, at the time limited to transport themselves to <HI>VIRGINIA,</HI> to Serve that Church in the Office of the Ministry. Nor can such Ministers plead their poverty and disability to do it, because there is sufficient Provision made to defray the Charges of their Transportation: of which they are desired to take notice by the seventh Proposal <HI>(pag. 22.)</HI> Nor is it the least considerable, that such Students knowing for the space of seven yeers before hand th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Work to which they are design'd, will be careful to order their Studies so, as may best fit them for it.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><PB REF="4"/>Other ways there are, by which the making this Pub∣lique may be subservient to the End design'd, which I purposely omit.</P>
<P>However it succeed, it may be some Testimony to my Friends there, that I am not altogether unmindful of procuring to my Power the welfare of that poor scatter'd Church, which indeed I am not, not onely upon the account of Duty, paying some solemn vows made in a time of trouble and extremity of Danger<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but even of Gratitude, for the kind reception I found among them for the space of above Ten years, when I could no longer endure <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he late Tyrannical Usurpations of my native Countrey.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Virginia's Cure OR, An Advisive NARRATIVE CONCERNING VIRGINIA.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>O shew the unhappy State of the Church in <HI>Virginia,</HI> and the true Remedy of it, I shall first give a brief Description of the Manner of our Peoples scatter'd Habitations there; next shew the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d un∣happy consequent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of such their scatter'd Living both in reference to themselves and the poor Heathen that are about them, and by the way briefly set down the cause of scattering their Habitations, then proceed to pro∣pound the Remedy, and means of procuring it; next assert
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
the Benefits of it in re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erence both to themselves, and the Hea∣then; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et down the cause why this Remedy hath not been hither∣to comp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and lastly, till it can be procured, give directi∣o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> for the present supply of their Churches.</P>
<P>That part of <HI>Virginia</HI> which hath at present craved your Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dships Assistance to preserve the Christian Religion, and to promote the Building Gods Church among them, by supplying them with sufficient Ministers of the Gospel, is bounded on the North by the great River <HI>Patomek,</HI> on the South by the River <HI>Chawan,</HI> including also the Land inhabited on the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>st side of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y,</HI> called <HI>Accomack,</HI> and contains above half as muc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Engl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd</HI>; it is divided into several Coun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies, and those Counties contain in all about Fifty Parishes, the Families whereof are dispersedly and scatteringly seated upon the sides of Rivers; some of which running very far into the Country, bear the <HI>English</HI> Plantations above a hun∣dred Miles, and being very broad, cause the Inhabitants of either side to be listed in several Parishes. Every such Parish is ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ended m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ny Miles in length upon the Rivers side, and usu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lly not above a mile in Breadth backward from the River, which is the common stated breadth of every <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lantation be∣longing to each particular Proprietor, of which Plantations, some extend them<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elves h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lf a mile<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> some a mil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, some two mile<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, some thre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> miles, and upwa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es of those Rivers, many of them are pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> from each other by small Rivers and Creeks, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mall Rivers and Creeks are seated after the manner of the great Rivers. The Families of such Parishes being seated after this manner, at such dist<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nces from each other, many of them are ver<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> remote from the House of God, though placed in the middest of them. Many Parishes as yet want both Churches and Gleabes, and I think not above a fifth part of them are supplyed with Min<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, where there are Ministers the People meet together Weekly, but o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce upon the Lords day, and sometim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s not at all, being hin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed by Extremities of Wind and Weather: and divers of the more remote Families being discouraged, by the length or tedious∣nesse
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
of the way, through extremities of heat in Summer, frost and Snow in Winter, and tempestuous weather in both, do very seldome repair thither.</P>
<P>By which brief Description of their manner of seating themselves in that Wildernesse, Your Lordship may easily ap∣prehend that their very manner of Planting themselves, hath caused them hitherto to rob God in a great measure of that pub∣lick Worship and Service, which as a Homage due to his great name, he requires to be constantly paid to him, at the times appointed for it, in the publick Congregations of his people in his House of Prayer.</P>
<Q><L>— Hinc illae Lachryma.</L></Q>
<P>This Sacriledge I judge to be the prime Cause of their long languishing improsperous condition, for it puts them under the Curse of God, according to that of <HI>Malachy</HI> 3.9. <HI>Ye are cursed with a Curse, because ye have robbed me.</HI> Which Curse we find executed upon the Jews, after such a manner, as any observing Person that knows <HI>Virginia,</HI> need not doubt to conclude, that it h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th been long executed upon her Planters in the sam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> kind and manner, as it is express'd to have been upon the Jews, in <HI>Hag.</HI> 1.9. <HI>Ye looked for much, and lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, it came to little: and when ye brought it home, I did blow upon it: Why, saith the Lord of Hosts? because of mine House that is wast, and ye run every man to his own house.</HI> By which Scriptures (comparing their Sins of Sacriledge together) it appears, that the Curse o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> God was executed upon the Jews, for the same Sacriledge <HI>Virginia's</HI> Planters are guilty of, the same Sin of robbing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od of his publick Worship and Service in his House of Prayer. For, was the Curse of God upon the Jews for not building his House according to the Prophet <HI>Haggai</HI>'s Sentence? But why did God regard his House, but for the re∣cieving the due tribute of his publick Honour, Worship, and Service in it? Or was his Curse upon them for detaining his Tythes and Offe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ings? But why did Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> regard these, but for
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
the maintenance and continuance of his publick Worship, and Service in his House? The Con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lusion therefore is, that their great Sin of Sacriledge, for which the Curse of God was de∣nounced and executed vpon them, was, that they robbed God of his publick Worship and Service in his Hou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e at the times appointed by God for it.</P>
<P>Which if <HI>Virginia's</HI> Planters do, it matters not whether they do it, by neglecting to build Churches, Hou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es of God amongst them, (which in great part they are guilty of;) or by with holding, or not assuring the maintenance of the Ministery of Gods publick Worship, Word, and Sacraments (which I cannot wholly excuse them of) or by planting themselves after such a manner, as may disable them to attend as constantly upon such Sacred publick Ministrations in the House of God, as the Equit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of the Fourth Commandement, the positive E∣vangelical Duties, to be performed in publick Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gregations, and the Law of the Church doth require (of which they are generally guilty) whet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er they rob God any of these wayes, the Sin hath the same stamp of Sacriledge, and therefore the same Curse attending it. But long experience hath ascertained, and the before described manner of their Planting makes it evident, that whilest our Planters in <HI>Virginia</HI> continue as at this day, dispersedly and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>emotely planted from the House of God, they will continue to rob God in a very great measure of his publick Worship and Service in his Hou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of Prayer. Which is the same Sin the Jews were Cursed for, and must needs put them under the same Curse of God.</P>
<P>But though this be the saddest Consequent of their dispersed manner of Planting themselves (for what Misery can be grea∣ter than to live under the Curse of God?) yet this hath a very sad Train of Attendants which are likewise consequents of their scatter'd Planting. For, hence is the great want of Christian Neighbourhood, of brotherly admonition, of holy Examples of religious Persons, of the Comfort of theirs, and their Ministers Administrations <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n Sicknesse, and Distresses, of the Benefit of Christian and Civil Conference and Commerce.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="6"/>And hence it is, that the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ost faithfull and vigilant Pastors, assisted by the most carefull Church-wardens, cannot possibly take notice of the Vices that r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ign in their Families, of the spiritual defects in th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir Conversatio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, or if they have notice of them, and provide Spiritual Remedies in their publick Mi∣nistery, it is a hazard if they that are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ost concerned in them be present at the application of them: and if they should spend time in visiting their remote and far distant habitations, they would have little or none left for their necessary Studies, and to provide necessary spiritual food for the rest of their Flocks. And he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce it is that through the licentious lives of many of them, the Christian Religion is like still t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> be dishonoured, and the Name of God to be blasphe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed among the Heathen, who are near them, and oft among them, and consequently their Conversion hindred.</P>
<P>Lastly, their almost general want of Schooles, for the educa∣tion of their Children, is another consequ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt of their scattered planting, of most sad consideration, most of all bewailed of Par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nts there, and therefore the arguments drawn from thence, mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t likely to prevail with them chearfully to embrace the Remedy. This want of Schooles, as it renders a very nume∣rous generation of Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>istians Children born in <HI>Virginia</HI> (who naturally are of beautifull and comely Persons, and generally of more ingen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ous Spirits then these in <HI>England</HI>) unserviceable for any great Employments eith<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r in Church or State, so like∣wise it obstructs the hopefullest way they have, for the Con∣ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ion of the Heathen, which is, by winning the Heathen to bring in th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir Children to be taught and instructed in ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Schooles, together with the Children of the Christians. For as it is th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uty and Glory of Christian <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>races, shining in the lives of Christians, which must make the Heathen that are men, in love with th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Christian R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ligion; so it is that love, which can o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wade them to bring in their Children to be taught and ins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ructed in it: But as it is unlikely th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch love should be wrought in them by the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y of Chr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>races, appear∣ing in the Chri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tians lives; who (as now planted) a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e for the
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
most part destitute of the ordinary means of Grace: so granting that this might be, yet it is very unlikely that any rationall Heathen should be perswaded to commit their Children to the teaching and education of such Christians, whom they shall per∣ceive to want Schooles of learning (the means of both) for their own.</P>
<P>It were easie to adde to these a heap of evill consequents of their scattered Planting, which hinder their Temporal, as well as Spi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ituall happinesse. But I forbear, it being a task unsuit∣able for my Profession, and for that I know the Remedy to be the same for both, and the removing the one will be the remo∣ving of the other.</P>
<P>Onely for conclusion of this part, discovering <HI>Virginia's</HI> Disease and Misery, Your Lordship may be pleased to repre∣sent to your thoughts the Evills of the fore-mentioned conse∣quents of their scattered Planting in reference to the poor Hea∣then; The effecting whose conversion, should be the great end desig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed by all, who would be subservient to the Pro∣vidence of God, in Transporting our Colonies thither.</P>
<P>The Heathen enter frequently into some of the remote dis∣pers'd habitations of the Christians, the premises considered, what can they see which should make them in love with their Religion? They see their Families disordered, their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hildren untaught, the publick Worship and Service of the great God they own, neglected; neglected upon that very day, which they heare call'd the Lords Day, and to be by the Christians peculi∣arly set a part for it; yea so farre neglected, that some of the Heathen have complained it was the worst of the seven to them, because the servants of the Christians Plantations nearest to them, being then left at liberty, oft spend that day in visiting their <HI>Indian</HI> Towns, to the disquiet of the Heathen, but cer∣tainly to the great Scandall of the Christian Religion, and little hopes have the poor Heathen of redresse, whilst they see that Day so far neglected by the Christians, that in many Parishes they see no publick holy Assemblies of our people, no Ministers provid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d for the holy Ministrations of such Assemblies, no Churches erected
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
and consecrated for such publique Sacred Ministrations; or such in such de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>olate Places, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o remote from many of their ha∣bitations that an ingenuous Christian would blush to tell a Hea∣then, that They are the houses of the Christians great <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od, that made the Heaven and the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arth of nothing, in which he is ho∣noured, worshipp'd, prayed unto, and his heavenly will taught from his holy Word: for if a sober di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>creet Heathen (and there are many such) should reply, Why hath not every Parish one of them, and Ministers belonging to them? why do not the Christians build their houses nearer them, that they may come oftner to them? wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> are they not better built? why will not all the Christians of a Pari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h bestow as much cost in build∣ing the house of their great God, as one particular <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hristian among them bestows upon his own house? what defence could an ingenuous Christian make, which should not at once both shame himself and the Christians he woul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> defend?</P>
<P>If then Sacriledge were so goodly a thing in the Heathens account, as to make them in love with the Christians and their Religion for it, they see the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hristians robbing God in all the fore-mentioned particulars, robbing him of his Days, Churches, Ministers, publick Worship and Service. But I can truly affirm (by what I have learn'd among divers Nations of those Hea∣then) that it is a Sin, which those Heathen by the Light of Na∣ture do most detest and abhorre, and the holy Scripture gives Testimon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to it: <HI>Mal.</HI> 3.8. <HI>Will a man rob his God? will a Heathen do it?</HI> Can they then ob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erve it in the Christians, and not abhorre and detest both them and their Religion for it? and in stea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of acknowled<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing them a seed which the Lord hath blessed, think on the contrary th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t both they and their offspring are a Gener<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tion whom the Lord hath cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed.</P>
<P>No hop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s therefore of bringing the Hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen in love with the Christia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Religio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> whil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o many evill an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> scandalous con∣seque<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts at<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nd the Christians sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tter'd manne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of planting in that w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lder esse. An their scatter'd Planning be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng the cause of such consequents, the co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ents will r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>main, so long as th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t continues, as at this day it doth. I have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atherto <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orborn
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
to mention the great danger that man<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of the Christians are in, of being destroyed by the Heathen, as formerly hundreds of them have been, because this consideration doth so easily o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fer it self upon the fore-mention'd description of their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cattered Seating: By which and the sad consequents of it, if your Lord∣ship shall please to contemplate the deplorable Estate and condition of the poor Church in <HI>Virginia</HI> (which implores your aid) it will present to your charitable heart such a moving object of your fatherly Care, Pitty, and Compassion, as will employ all your Interest in the Kings Grace and Favor, and your utmost power and endeavours to procure the Remedy.</P>
<P>The cause of their dispers'd Seating was at first a priviledge indulged by the royall Grant of having a right to 50 Acres of Land<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for every person they should transport at their own charges: by which means some men transporting many Ser∣vants thither, and others purchasing the Rights of those that did, took possession of great tracts of Land at thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pleasure, and by Degrees scattered their Plantations through the Country after the manner before described, although therefore from the premisses, it is easie to conclude, that the onely way of reme∣dy for <HI>Virginia's</HI> disease (without which all other help will on∣ly palliate not cure) must be by procuring Towns to be built, and inhabited in thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>everal Counties. Yet left any man be hereby injured in his just Right, even this Remedy ought to be procured after <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch a manner, as the present manner of plant∣ing the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>selves, their poverty and mean condition will permit. According to which, whether the building Towns in each Coun∣t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of <HI>Virginia,</HI> will be best pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oted by reviving a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ormer Act of that Country for Markets in Stated places of each County, where whatsoever should be transported into that Colony was onely to be sold (which Act was perhaps over-hastily repealed the next ensuing Assembly held <HI>March</HI> 27. 1656. for in my hearing, they who were the chief Agents in repealing it, have more then once repented it) or whether they may best be promoted by some other way (it being out of my Sphere) I dare not presume to determine, Your Lordship will
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
best inform your self in th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s by Con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ulting with <HI>Virginia's</HI> pre∣sen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onourable <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>overnour Sir <HI>William B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rkly,</HI> or their late <HI>Edward Diggs</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR></P>
<P>What wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oeve they determine to be best, I shall humbly in obedie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce to your Lords<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ips command endevour to contri∣but<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> towards the com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>assing this Remedy by propounding,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. That your Lordship would be pleased to ac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uaint the King with the nece<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sity of promoting the building Towns in each County of <HI>Virginia,</HI> upon the consideration of the fore-mention<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d sad Con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>equent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of their present manner of living there.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Your Lordship upon the fore-going consideration, be plea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed to move the pitiful, and charitable heart of His <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cious Majesty (considering the Poverty and need<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of <HI>Virginia</HI>) for a Coll<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ction to be made in all the Churches of his three Kingdom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s (there being considerable numbers of each Kingdome) for the promoting a work of so great Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rity to the Souls of many thousands of his Loyal Subjects, their Children, and th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Generations after them, and of numberlesse poor Heathen; and that the Ministers of each Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gregation be enjoyned with more then ordinary care, and pains to stirre up the people to a free and liberal Contribution towards it; or if this way be not thought sufficient, that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome other way b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> taken to do it.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. That the way of dispencing such collections for sending Work-men over for th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> building Towns and Schooles, and the assistance the persons that shall inhabit them shall contribute towards them may be determin'd here, by the advice of <HI>Virginia's</HI> present or late Honourable Governours if in <HI>London</HI>; and whom they shall make choice of for their assistants (who have formerly lived in <HI>Virginia</HI>;) and that the King (if he shall approve what is so determined) may be humbly Petitioned to authorize it by his special command, le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> what is duely ordered here, be perverted there.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB N="10" REF="9"/>Fourthly, That those Planters who have such a conside∣rable number of Servants, as may be judged may enable them for it, if they not willing (for I have heard some expresse their willingnesse, and some their aver<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nesse) may by His Majesties Authority be enjoyned, to contri∣bute the Assistance that shall be thought meet for them, to build themselves houses in the Towns-nearest to them, and to inhabit them, for they having horses enough in that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ountry, may be convenienc'd, as their occasions require, to visit their Plantations. And the Masters who shall in∣h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bit the Towns, having Families of Servants upon remote Plantations, may be ordered to take care, that upon Sa∣turdays Afternoon (when by the Custome of <HI>Virginia,</HI> Servants are freed from their ordinary labour) their Ser∣vants (except one or two, left by turns to secure their Plantations) may repair to th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir Houses in the Towns, and there remain with their Masters, until the publick Worship and Service of the Lor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Day be ended.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fifthl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, That for a con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inual supply of able Minist<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs for their Churches, after a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et ter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of years. Your Lord∣ship would plea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>evour the procuring an Act of Parliament, whereby a c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tain number of Fellowships, as they happen to be next proportionably vacant in both the Universities, may bear the name of <HI>Virginia</HI> Fellowships, so long as the Needs of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat Church shall require it; and none be admitted to th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m, but su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shall engage by promi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to hold them seven years and no longer; and at the expi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ation of tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e seven years, t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ort thems<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s to <HI>Virginia,</HI> and serve that Church in the Office of the Ministery seven ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs more, (the Church the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oviding for them) which being expir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, they shall be left to their own Liberty to return or not: and if they p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>m not the Condit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of their Admittance, then to be uncapable of any Prefe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>These things being procur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, I thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k <HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rginia</HI> will be in the most probable way (that her pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent condit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
admit) of being cured of the formentioned evils of her scatter'd Planting.</P>
<P>For hereby her Planters will be convenienced to give God the honour due unto his Name, by attending constantly in full Congregations upon his publick Worship and Ser∣vice, they will enjoy the benefits of Christian Offices, of frequent civil commerce and Society, which begets mu∣tual confidence, trust, and friendship, the best ground∣work for raising Companies of the best qualified, and most able persons to combine in Designs, most advantagious to their own and the publick Weal; they will enjoy the be∣nefits of vertuous Examples, of publick Catechizing and instructing their Children and Servants in the Principles and Duties of the Christian Religion, according to the Constitutions of the Church of <HI>England</HI>; whereby not only Children and Servants, but Parents and Masters who are ignorant, may (without being ashamed) be enlightned with true saving knowledge, and their Children in Schools of Learning, may grow up to be serviceable both in Church and State. And by good Discipline and careful tending, in well order'd Societies, under faithful Teachers and Ma∣gistrates, both Parents and Children would by the grace of God grow into habits of Christian Living, and the light of their Graces and good works shining before the Hea∣then, would above all other Oratory prevail with them, both to be desirous to learn themselves, and to bring their Children to be taught in the Christians Schools, how to glorifie the same God with them.</P>
<P>That the former benefits will accrue to themselves, needs no Proof: the experience of all united well order'd Christian Societies, sufficiently confirms it.</P>
<P>That the latter (<HI>viz.</HI> the gaining the Heathen to the Christian Faith) will be the hopeful Consequ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt of their habitual Christian living, of the united l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght of their graces and good works shining bef<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re the Heathen; I shall (not presuming to inform Your Lordship, but not knowing to
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
whom this Paper may be communicated) make bold to add a brief Confirmation of it. First, by the testimony of that vertuous Heathen Emperour <HI>Alexander Sev<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rus,</HI> who when he p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rceived two of his Servants to be per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wa∣ded to receive the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hristian Faith, by the Eloquent Ora∣tions <HI>Origen</HI> had made before him to prove the Truth of it. <HI>I perceive</HI> (saith he) <HI>Ye do wonder at the Learning of</HI> Origen, <HI>whereby ye are induced to embrace the Christian Profession: But tru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y, the Humility and Charity of the Christian People, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> do hear of, and daily b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hold with my E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es; do much more move me to believe that their Christ is God, then all his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>loquent Perswasion<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></P>
<P>This Heathen Emperour understood the Language of <HI>O∣rigen</HI>; and (as the History relates) w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s much moved with the convincing perswasive Arguments <HI>Origen</HI> u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed, to prove the Truth of the Christian Faith: yet he professeth he was much more p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rswaded to believe it, by the Humi∣lity and Charity, the graces and ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tues, which appeared in the Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>istians lives, which he heard of, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> daily be∣held. But the Heathen in <HI>Virginia</HI> neither understand the Christians language, no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Christians theirs; and although they did understand it, I think it too bar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en to expresse the Christian Religion by, and therefore they h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ve no o∣ther arguments left to convince them of the Tru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h of the Christian Faith, and to per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wade them to emb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ce it. But only (which that Emperor acknowledged most per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sive) the ami<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>blenesse of Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>isti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>races and Vertues <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hining in their lives, whose excelling beauty and b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nefit, when they appear in united <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ocieties of Christians, they may well per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de any rational He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>then, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t they are most conducing to procure th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> true h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ppin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll united So∣cieties and Commu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ities of Men, and therefo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the Reli∣gion, that teacheth t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>em, above all other to be embra∣ced.</P>
<P>This Consider<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on enforced the accute <HI>Acosta,</HI> after he had spent 17 years in conversing with the Heathen in that
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
new world (though he was of a Church that pleads much for Miracles) ingenuously to confesse, that the greatest, and even the only Miracle necessary to the Conversion of those Heathen, is the gracious lives of Christians, agree∣able to that Christian Faith they professe, and in this he subscribes but to St. <HI>Chrysostome</HI> affirming the same concer∣ning the conversion of the Heathen in his dayes. But long before <HI>Chrysostome,</HI> the Prophet <HI>Isaiah</HI> foretold the power of this Miracle, how powerful the glory of the Lord shi∣ning in the gracious lives of Christians should be, to fur∣ther the conversion of the Gentiles. <HI>Isa.</HI> 60.2, 3. Where speaking of the Church under the Gospel. <HI>The Lord</HI> (saith he) <HI>shall arise upon thee, and his glory shall be seen upon thee,</HI> and what followes? <HI>the Gentiles shall come to thy Light, and Kings to the brightnesse of thy rising.</HI> What is this Light, and Brightnesse, and Glory, which should be seen upon the Church under the Gospel, which should invite the Gentiles to come into it? The same Prophet tells us <HI>Isa.</HI> 6<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.2. <HI>The G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntiles shall see thy Righteous∣nesse, and all Kings thy Glory.</HI> 'Tis the Righteousnesse, the Holynesse, the graces shining in the lives of Christi∣ans; 'tis this should make their <HI>Seed known among the Gentiles, and their off-spring among the People:</HI> So that <HI>all that see <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hem should acknowledge them that they are the Seed which the Lord hath blessed. Isa.</HI> 61.9. And this shoul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> make them bring their Sons and Daughters to be nurst up at the Churches breasts. <HI>Isa.</HI> 49.22, 23. <HI>Isa.</HI> 6.4.</P>
<P>But when were these Prophecies fulfilled?</P>
<P>Two times are only remarkable for fulfilling them by Gods ord<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry way of Converting Heathen (except the way of Converting them by Miracles) and those were,
<LIST>
<ITEM>First, The Times of Persecution, when the Faith, Con∣stancy, Me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>knesse, P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tience, and Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rity of the Christian Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tyrs shi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so bright in the Heathens eyes, through the Flames, Wounds, and Tortures they endured, that it made
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
them wonder at the glory of the Lord, which was seen upon them, and fall in love with the Christian Religion, which brought forth such glorious Fruits in them: But neither doth this reach all States of the Church, not particularly <HI>Vir∣ginia's,</HI> so long as the Christians have the upper hand of the Heathen, which God grant may continue till the End of Times.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. The times of the Churches peace, when the Christi∣ans in their united Societies, having the Liberty of their publick holy Assemblies in the House of God, did con∣stantly attend upon the Service of God in them, and the Heathen comming in among them, and beholding the come∣ly order and beauty of their holy worship, perceiving their Unanimity and Uniformity in the same faith and worship of the same God, were so convinced of all and judged of all, that the secrets of their hearts were made manifest, and they fell down upon their faces and worship'd God, and confessed that God was in them of a Truth, as the Apostle saith Infidels would do such a Case. 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 14. 24, 25. And therefore no doubt but many of them did.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>And as for those of the Heathen who lived in the Ci∣ties and Towns with the Christians, or near unto them, and yet frequented not the Christians Churches (which I suppose few of them would wholly omit, men being ge∣nerally of the <HI>Athenians</HI> temper, inquisitive after what seems new to them) but if there were (as 'tis possible) any considerable numbers of such rigid Heathen; yet even these beholding the comely order of the Christians Government, the amiablenesse of their Conversations, their Meeknesse, Humility, Charity, their Righteousnesse shining as the Light, and their just dealing as the Noon-day: In sum, seeing the light of their good works, they were allured, and won by degrees to glorifie the same God with them: and these latter I take to be chiefly meant by the visible righteousnesse and glory of the Church, under the Gospel, which the Prophet <HI>Isaiah</HI> foretold (for he saith it should
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
be seen) which should be so prevailing with the Heathen; these the most ordinary wayes (though there were other) of Converting them to Christianity; which Interpretation, besides that it is cleared by the words of the Text cited, and the evidence of the matter, it exactly agrees with the judgement of the Learned <HI>Acosta</HI> and St. <HI>Chrysostome</HI> before mentioned.</P>
<P>Object. But it may be objected, that <HI>neither of these, nor perhaps any other Ecclesiatick Writers, have told us, that Christians for this end ought to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nited in Soc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eties in Towns, that it is the glory of the graces and virtues of many Christians shining, not in scatter'd Corners, but in¦visible united Societies, which is so perswasive and powerfully prevailing with the Heathen to embrace the Christian faith; nor do they use any arguments to perswade Christians to live together in Towns and to incorporate into Societies for this end.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answer.</HI> And no marvel; how could we reasonably expect it from them? The Christians whom they knew dispers'd through the the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> inhabited parts of the World (except <HI>Hermites</HI> who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ition of li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e is not here spoken of) were united in such Societies, planted together in the House of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o as they might co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stantly attend upon the pub∣liq<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e sacred Min<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>strations of his Word and Wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ship; and their light best shine before men to the glory of God. Therefore for this manner of Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>istians living together, as there was n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> need to argue; so they might charitably hope, there never would be, Christ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ans being bound to it by ver∣tue of Christs co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd. To seek first<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Kingdom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of God and the Righte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sness<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thereof, and to depend upon his promise, for adding all other things to them: of which Duty, that the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> might be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aily minded, Christ hath taught th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m by the metho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t daily Pra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er, which he hath set them, as to b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g of God, so to seek<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Hallowing of his
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
Name, the advancement of his Kingdome, and the doing of his will before their daily Bread; from whence it follows, that it is the Duty of all Christians to take care in the first place, so to unite their habitations in Societies, after such a manner, as they may be best convenienc'd constantly to attend upon the publick Ministery of Gods hol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Word, Sacraments, and Worship (which conveniency only Towns and Villages affor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> because God hath ordained the publick Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>istery of these to be the means by which (through his blessing upon the due using them) his Name should be glorified, his Kingdome advanc'd, and his will perform'd, and hath exprest it to be his will, that he will be glorified before all the People; honoured and praised in the great Congregations, and therefore calls for it by his Word, <HI>Psal.</HI> 100. <HI>O go your way into his Gates with thanksgiving, and into his Courts with praise; be thankfull unto him and blesse his name.</HI></P>
<P>And perhaps it may be truly affirmed, that <HI>Virginia's</HI> Planters were the first considerable numbers of Christians in the whole world, which first violated this stated Order of Christ, (I say not in a remote desert, and in the sight of the Heathen which hugely aggravates their fault) but the first that ever<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ted themselves after such a manner (<HI>Hermites</HI> as before excepted, whose manner of Life <HI>Virginians</HI> profess not) as might make their due and constant attendance upon the publick worship and Service of God impossible to them, and consequently di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>able them to glorifie the Name, and advance the Kingdome of God, in the way God hath ordained and commande<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
<P>It may suffice therefore for answer to the Object<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to say, that if neither ancient, nor modern Writers have told us, that Christians (if they have Liberty) ought to live together in visible united Societies, in Cities, Towns or Villages, for the fore-mentioned ends; it was, because they knew no present need of writing any thing of it, nor could charitably conjecture there would be any for the Fu∣ture.</P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="12"/>But d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er bought experience hath taught, that it i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> now necessary, which hath made me thus f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r presume upon Your Lordships Candor and Patience for this brief asserting it; There being no other Remedy for <HI>Virginia's</HI> Malady, but by reducing her Planters into Towns.</P>
<P><HI>Object.</HI> The common Objection against this way of being reduced into Towns, which I have often heard among them, is, <HI>that they shall be undone by it in their Estates.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answer.</HI> For Answer to which it may suffice to say,
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. The most knowing and prudent among them, have judg'd the contrary, and that it would be the only way to enrich them, and therefore have both wish'd and endeavour'd it though in vain, witnesse the above-mention'd Act for Mar∣kets, contrived by the prudent <HI>Edward Diggs</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> their sometime Governour, and the very many attempts and con∣trivances to compasse it, made and devised by the most Noble lover of <HI>Virginia</HI> Sir <HI>William Berkely</HI> their present Governour.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. It will be the most probable way of securing both their Persons and Estates against all attempts of the Heathen, the Rumours whereof (frequently spread through that Countrey) do oft a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fright them, for hereby, either the Heathen will be gained, after the manner before specified, or their power not fear'd.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Only Persons that are able will be enjoyned it, according to the Tenour of the fourth Proposition, and perhaps Colle∣ctions being made, and dispers'd according to the 2, and 3. Propositions, or agreeable Sums of money raised by a Rate set upon every Hogshead of <HI>Tobacco</HI> imported into <HI>England,</HI> according to the Honourable Sir <HI>William Berkleys</HI> Proposition in his view of <HI>Virginia,</HI> Workmen may be provided for them and the Planters be at little Charge, besides affording them Assistance and Dyet, which they have in so gre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Plenty
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
in that Countrey, that very few or none will account the affor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing that, any impairing to their Estates. If none of these answer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> will satisfie such Objectors.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. Yet let them consider seriously what hath been before asserted; That while they continue their present manner of scattered living (whereby they necessitate themselves to rob God of his due publique Worship and Service) they will con∣tinue under the Curse of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od, but by uniting their habitations in Towns, they will make themselves capable of giving God his due honour in his house of Prayer in the great Congregations of his People, and consequently of procuring his blessing; for them that honour God, God will honour, <HI>and they that are planted in the house of the Lord, shall flourish in the Courts of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouse of our God.</HI> Psal. 92.13. Now whether their living under the Curse, or under the Blessing of the Almighty will best improve their Estates, let themselves judge.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>These things considered, men may wonder why the attempts made by the fore-mentioned Honourable Governours to reduce <HI>Virginia's</HI> Planters into Towns did never succeed, and perhaps it may be hard for any that never lived among them rightly to conjecture. But the truth in plain <HI>English</HI> is this,</P>
<P>Whatsoever is of publick concernment in <HI>Virginia,</HI> is determined by their Grand Assemblies, which are usually held once a year, and consist of Governour and Councell, which make the upper house, and the Burgesses which represent the People, and make the lower house, and are chosen out of every County by the People, after the manner that Burgesses are chosen for Parliaments in <HI>England,</HI> and are more or fewer according as the People agree, who are to defray their charges<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Whatsoever passes into an Act of Assembly, must be agree'd upon by the Major part of Burgesses, and these are usually such as went over Servants thither, and though by time and industry, they may have attained competent Estates; yet by reason of their poor and mean education they are unskilful in judging of a good Estate either of Church or Common-wealth, or of the means of procuring it. No marvell therefore, if the
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
best proposals, which have been made to such persons, for reducing them into Towns, offending in the least against their present private worldly interest (though never so promising for the future) have been from time to time bandied against by such Major parts of their Burgesses, and the fewer wise heads over-voted by them.</P>
<P>And if at any time it hath so happened, that the Major part of the Burgesses have been so meetly qualified and tempered, as to enact any thing tending to such a publique good; The following Assemblies have usually repealed it. The consideration of which, is the true ground of the whole third Proposition: of the Contents of which and the rest, if Your Lordship shall become the blessed procurer. The forlorne Church which is now scattered in desolate Places of that wildernesse, without any comlinesse, which should make her desired, and sought after, may (through Gods blessing) in a few years, gain such beauty, wealth, and ornament, as may either enable her to nurse up Children of her own, to become her servants in the Gospel, or allure Strangers to court her for the Favour, and if it shall please God to prolong your Honourable dayes, till you shall hear of the promised blessed fruits of your labour of love and charity for that poor Church, (which God grant in mercy for his name and Churches sake) what ravishing joy and content∣ment will affect your pious and charitable heart, to contem∣plate at this distance, the Glory of the Communion of Saints, in their united holy Societies and Assemblies; the constant beauty of their publique Worship; of their holy Sacrifices of prayers and praises offered in a comely order in their publique congregations.</P>
<P>To contemplate the poor Church (whose plants now grow wilde in that Wildernesse) become like a garden enclosed, like a Vineyard fenced, and watch'd like a flock of Sheep with their Lambes safely folded by night, and fed by day; all which are the promised fruits of well ordered Towns, under Religious Pastours and Magistrates, with what joy, and delight may you likewise think upon their comely and most ingenious
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
Children, like hopefull plants growing up in Nurseries of learning and piety, and when their time of fruit is come, Transplanted into the enclosed gardens of God, and becoming fruitfull and usefull trees of righteousnesse; which is the pro∣mised happinesse and benefit of well ordered Schooles, in well governed Towns.</P>
<P>And lastly, wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t rejoycing will it be to your most Christian heart, to behold the glorious issue of that Prophecy, concerning the calling the Gentiles fulfilled in those numerous herds of Heathen in <HI>Virginia.</HI> Isa. 11.6. &amp;c. <HI>The Wolfe shall dwell with the Lambe, the Leopard shall lye down with the Kid, &amp;c.</HI> To contemplate the Heathen, who in that Prophesie are likened to Wolves, Leopards, Lyons, Bears, Apes, and Cockatrices; couching quietly &amp; harmlesly in the same fold of Christs Church with the Sheep and Lambes of Christ, which will be the hopeful Consequent of well ordered Towns and Schooles. And the procuring these, the only true effectual Remedy for <HI>Virginia's</HI> Disease, as hath been shewed.</P>
<P>But this is a Work of time to compasse; and we have an <HI>English</HI> Proverb, <HI>Whilst the grasse growes, the Steed Starves,</HI> before this can be compassed, many poor Christians there, may p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rish for want of their souls food, where there is no vision the people perish, and that is the case of the far greater part of that Colony.</P>
<P>The encouragement therefore of Ministers to adventure thi∣ther to help them, I humbly propound,
<LIST>
<ITEM>First, That your Lordship be pleased to procure, that the next grand Assembly in <HI>Virgin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a</HI> may enact. That what <HI>Tobacco</HI> any Parish agrees to pay their Minister, shall be payed of the best <HI>Tobacco</HI> of every Mans own Crop, and with Cask, other∣wise experience hath shewed, that a Ministers livelyhood there will be very uncertain.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Secondly, Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t at the same Assembly it be Enacted, that every Parish chuse a Vestry (in case they have not one already chosen) and the Vestry of each Parish be en∣joyned to subscribe what quantity of Corn and Tobacco
<PB N="21" REF="14"/>
of the best of their own Crops, with Cask, they will al∣low a sufficient Minister yearly.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thirdly, That in the next and every Assembly, the Act for paying 15 <HI>l.</HI> of Tobacco <HI>per annum,</HI> for every Tyth∣able person, in every Parish destitute of a Minister (which Act was made at an Assembly <HI>March</HI> 27. 1656.) be carefully executed, and strict Enquiry made, whether the Tobacco due by that Act, be duely collected, and employ∣ed to the ends express'd in that Act, <HI>viz.</HI> Building Churches, purchasing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leabes, and stocks of Cattel to belong to them. And if any Parish hath imployed any part of such Arrears to any other use, that they be enjoyned to make them good again.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fourthly, That the Act made in the same Assembly concer∣ning disposing intestate estates to publick uses, in case no Ad∣ministratour of Kin to the diseased Proprietour appears) may serve in the first place the needs of the Church, for furnishing each Parish with Gleabes, and the Gleabes with Stocks of Cat∣tel, before any part of such estates be employed to any other use.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fifthly, that there being divers persons already in the Colony fit to serve the Church in the office of Deacon, a Bishop be sent over, so soon as there shall be a City for his See, as for other Needs of that Church, so also, that after due Probation and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xamination, such persons may be ordained Deacons, and their Duty and Service be appointed by the Bishop.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sixthly, That the Ministers that go thither, be not hired by the year, as is now usual, but firmly instituted and in∣ducted into Livings of stated value by the Subscriptions of their Vestries, according to the second Proposition.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seventhly, That all Ministers desirous to go to <HI>Virginia,</HI> and not able to transport themselves, be acquainted with an Act of Assembly of that Country, whereby it is provided, that wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oever sufficient Minister, shall not be able to pay for his transportation, any Merchant that shall defray the charge of it (if such Minister agree not with him upon other conditions)
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
shall receive 20 <HI>l. Sterling</HI> for his passage, from the Parish that entertains him, or two Thousand pound of Tobacco, who shall also repay any Sums of money disburs'd for his ac∣commodation, and the Minister to be free to choose his Parish, which shall make such disbursements for him.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>This is all I can think meet to propound at present, only for a Conclusion I shall add for the Encouragement both of Bishop and Ministers, that shall adventure thither out of pity and com∣passion to the souls of so many of their poor Brethren, that as their reward will be great in Heaven, so also, they shall (in a very pleasant and fruitful Land) meet with a People, which generally bear a great love and respect to their Ministers; And (if they behave themselves as becommeth their high calling) they shall find their ready help, and assistance in their Needs; and (which should be much more encouraging) they will find a People, which generally bear a great love to the stated Con∣stitutions of the Church of <HI>England,</HI> in her Government and publick Worship; which gave us (who went thither under the late Persecutions of it) the advantage of Liberty to use it constantly among them, after the Naval force had reduced that Colony under the power (but never to the obedience) of the Usurpers.</P>
<P>Which Liberty we could not have enjoyed, had not the People generally express'd a great Love to it. And I hope even this will be a consideration (not of least regard) to move Your Lordship to use all possible care and endevour to supply <HI>Virginia's</HI> Needs with sufficient Orthodoxe Ministers, in the first place, and before any other of our forraign Plan∣tations which crave your help, because in the late times of our Churches Persecution, her people alone, cheerfully and joyfully embraced, encouraged, and maintained the Orthodoxe Ministers that went over to them<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in their pub∣lick Conformity to the Church of <HI>ENGLAND,</HI> in her Doctrine and stated manner of Publick Worship.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

