<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A Great conspiracy by the papists in the kingdome of Ireland discovered by the lords, justices and counsell at Dvblin and proclaimed there Octob. 23, 1641 : vvhich proclamation was sent to the Parliament here in England, and read before the Lords and Commons in Parliament on Munday Novemb. 1, 1641 : vvhereunto is annexed the copy of a letter written with the kings owne hand, and sent to Mr. Nicholas, Clarke of the counsell from Edenbvrgh Octob. 18, 1641.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A41891</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing G1680</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R29689</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12562162</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12562162</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">63256</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A41891)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63256)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 961:5)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A Great conspiracy by the papists in the kingdome of Ireland discovered by the lords, justices and counsell at Dvblin and proclaimed there Octob. 23, 1641 : vvhich proclamation was sent to the Parliament here in England, and read before the Lords and Commons in Parliament on Munday Novemb. 1, 1641 : vvhereunto is annexed the copy of a letter written with the kings owne hand, and sent to Mr. Nicholas, Clarke of the counsell from Edenbvrgh Octob. 18, 1641.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Clarke, Nicholas, 17th cent.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 4 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for John Thomas,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1641.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Sources.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A41891">
<STC T="W">G1680</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12562162</BIBNO>
<VID>63256</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<P><PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
A GREAT CONSPIRACY By the Papists in the Kingdome of IRELAND, Discovered by the Lords, Justices, and Coun∣sell at <HI>DVBLIN</HI> and Proclaimed there <HI>Octob.</HI> 23, 1641.</P>
<P>VVhich Proclamation was sent to the PAR∣LIAMENT here in ENGLAND And read before the Lords and Commons in Parliament on Munday <HI>Novemb.</HI> 1. 1641.</P>
<P>VVhereunto is annexed the Copy of a Let∣ter written with the Kings owne hand, and sent to Mr. <HI>Nicholas,</HI> Clarke of the Counsell from EDENBVRGH <HI>Octob.</HI> 18. 1641.</P>
<P>LONDON, Printed for <HI>John Thomas.</HI> 1461.</P>
<PB REF="2"/>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="document">
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>BY THE LORDS JVSTICES, AND Councell at <HI>Dublin</HI> in <HI>Ireland,</HI> Octob. 23. 1641.</HEAD>
<OPENER>W. Parsons, Io. Burlacie.</OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hese are to m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke known and published to all his Majesties good Subjects in this Kingdome of <HI>Ireland,</HI> That there is a Dis∣covery made by Us the Lords, Justices, and Councell, of a most disloyall and detestable Conspira∣cie intended by some evill affected <HI>Irish</HI> Papists, against the lives of Us the Lords, Justices, and Councell, and many others of his Majesties faith∣full
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
Subjects universally throughout this King∣dome, and for the seizing not onely of his Maje∣sties Castle of <HI>Dublin</HI> his Majesties principall Fort here, but also of the other Fortifications of the Kingdome. And seeing by the great goodnesse and aboundant mercy of Almighty God to his Majesty and this State and Kingdome, these wick∣ed Conspiracies are brought to light, and some of the Conspirators committed to the Castle of <HI>Dub∣lin</HI> by us, by his Majesties authority, so as those wicked and Damnable Plots, are now disappoin∣ted in the chiefe parts thereof: Wee therefore have thought fit hereby not onely to make it pub∣likely knowne for the comfort of his Majesties good and loyall Subjects in all parts of the King∣dome, but also hereby to require them, that they doe with all confidence and cheerefulnesse betake themselves to their owne defence, and stand upon their Guard, so to render the more safety to them∣selves and all the Kingdome besides, and that they advertise us with all possible speed of all occur∣rences which may concerne the peace and safety of the Kingdome, and now to shew fully that faith and Loyalty which they have alwayes shewen for the publike service of the Crowne and Kingdome, which we will value to his Majesty accordingly, and a speciall memory thereof, will be retained for their advantage in due time, and wee require that great care be taken that no Levies of men be made for forraigne Service, or any man suffered to march upon any such pretences.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Given at his Maje∣sties Castle at <HI>Dublin,</HI> <DATE>25. <HI>Octob.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE> <SIGNED><LIST>
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Names of those Lords Iustices, and Counsellours in the Castle of <HI>Dublin,</HI> at the dating of this Proclamation.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Robert Dillon.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Robert Digby,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Adam Loftus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Temple.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thomas Rothoram.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Francis VVilloughby.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iames VVare.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Robert Meridith.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
<CLOSER>God save the King.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A Copy of a Letter written with the Kings owne hand to Mr. <HI>Nicholas,</HI> Clarke of the Counsell, bearing date from <HI>Edenburgh,</HI> <DATE>18. <HI>Octob.</HI> 1641.</DATE></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Heare it is reported that at my returne I intend to alter the Government of the Church of <HI>England,</HI> and to bring it to that forme as it is here. There∣fore I command you to assure all my Servants, that J will be constant to the Discipline and Do∣ctrine of the Church of <HI>England</HI> established by Queene ELIZABETH and my Father, and that I resolve by the grace of God) to dye in the main∣tenance of it.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Charles Rex.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>From Edenburgh</HI> <DATE><HI>Octob.</HI> 18. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="4"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

