<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The love of truth and peace a sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, assembled in Parliament, Novemb. 29, 1640 / by Iohn Gauden ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A42489</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing G363</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R492</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13065040</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13065040</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">97043</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42489)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97043)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 739:19)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The love of truth and peace a sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, assembled in Parliament, Novemb. 29, 1640 / by Iohn Gauden ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[6], 46 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by G.M. for Andrew Crooke ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1641.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Bible. --  O.T. --  Zechariah VIII, 19 --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Truth --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Peace --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A42489">
<STC T="W">G363</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13065040</BIBNO>
<VID>97043</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
LOVE OF TRVTH
AND PEACE.</P>
<P>A
SERMON
PREACHED
BEFORE THE HO∣NOVRABLE
HOVSE
OF <HI>COMMONS</HI>
Assembled in PARLIAMENT.</P>
<P>Novemb. 29. 1640.</P>
<P>By IOHN GAUDEN, <HI>Bachelor in Divinity. Published by order of that House.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON</HI>
Printed by <HI>G. M.</HI> for <HI>Andrew Crooke</HI> in <HI>Pauls</HI> Church∣yard
at the <HI>Greene Dragon.</HI> 1641.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO
THE HONORABLE
HOUSE
OF
COMMONS,
Assembled in PARLIAMENT.</HEAD>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Vch is the powerfull, and universall</HI>
influence, <HI>which the great and
noble</HI> Constellation <HI>of your House
bath, under</HI> God <HI>and the</HI> King,
<HI>over all that are members of this</HI>
State, <HI>that none with modesty may deny your</HI>
desires, <HI>or with safety (at least of their discre∣tion)
<PB REF="3"/>
disobey your</HI> Commands; <HI>So irresi∣stible
a force must the intimation of that</HI> Will
<HI>carry, which proceeds from somany</HI> wise <HI>and
excellent</HI> judgements <HI>united together. This
may sufficiently</HI> justifie my obedience, <HI>in pre∣senting
this Sermon to your, and the publique
view: which not any</HI> self-forwardnesse, or
over-valuing <HI>hath obtruded. It was enough,
in the Authors opinion (if not too much) that so</HI>
sudden and abortive conceptions <HI>had once
adventured the</HI> Hearing <HI>of so Learned, Pious,
and Judicious an Assembly. Where obtaining
(through Gods blessing) some approbation, (by
doing some good, I hope) they were further, by the</HI>
vote <HI>of your</HI> Honorable House, <HI>required to
be Printed: Which they now are; and with all</HI>
Humilitie <HI>presented to your Acceptance. That
at once I may, both cast in a</HI> mite <HI>to</HI> Gods
glory <HI>in the</HI> publique good (<HI>which should be
the end of all our actions) and also testifie a
minde vehemently</HI> sensible <HI>of, and</HI> thankfull
<HI>for those free and Noble expressions of favour
generally from the</HI> whole House, <HI>and parti∣cularly
<PB REF="3"/>
from some</HI> members <HI>of it, my</HI> speciall
friends, <HI>conferred upon me. What good others
may now get from these notions, I know not: I
pray, and hope, they may not be wholly uselesse
to candid, pious, and unprejudiced mindes, since
your censure hath allowed them as fit and neces∣sary
for our times.</HI></P>
<P><HI>This I am sure,</HI> your wisedome <HI>and</HI> pietie
<HI>are (above all others) by the</HI> publication <HI>of
this Sermon, more straightly</HI> obliged in con∣science,
<HI>to justifie before God and man, your
desires and opinion of it, by your</HI> proceedings
<HI>answerable to the subject and intent of it; which
is</HI> the love of Truth and Peace. <HI>The splendor
of so many cleer mindes, concentred in</HI> Truth,
<HI>cannot but kindle to a</HI> publique love <HI>of it. And
from the sacred light, and heate of so many wise
and warm hearts, the life sweetnesse and a∣bundance
of our</HI> Peace <HI>cannot but grow and
flourish.</HI></P>
<P><HI>That this may be the</HI> happy successe, <HI>where∣with
<PB REF="4"/>
with God will be pleased to crown your</HI> pub∣lique
endevours; <HI>as also these, which from my
private Pen are now adopted unto your so</HI> great
<HI>and</HI> Honorable protection, <HI>is the earnest
prayer of</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your most
humble
Servant,
GAUDEN.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE LOVE
OF
TRUTH
AND
PEACE.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>ZACH. 8.19.</BIBL>
<Q>Thus saith the Lord, The fast of the tenth moneth, shall
be to the house of Iudah, joy and gladnesse, and cheere∣full
feasts; therefore love the Truth and Peace.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hough the weight of this Service
and Imployment be so great, that
it might well have required abler
shoulders to bear it, and longer time
to prepare for it, and not to
have put <HI>Sauls</HI> Armour on <HI>Davids</HI> backe:
Yet that I may not be wanting, to Gods
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
glory, my own conscience, or your desires and
expectation; I have adventured to appear this
day, in this place, before this Honorable, Grave,
and Judicious assembly. Nothing did more
encourage me, against the greatnesse of the Work,
the shortnesse of the Time, and the insufficiency
of my own Abilities, than the auspicious fitnesse
and readinesse of this Text, so every way sutable,
as I conceive; 1. To the Auditors. 2. To the
Times. 3. To the present Occasion.</P>
<P>1. To the Auditors; who are, or should be all
<HI>Filii veritatis &amp; alumni pacis:</HI> Lovers of <HI>Truth,</HI>
and <HI>Peace:</HI> professors of <HI>Truth,</HI> and protectors of
<HI>Peace:</HI> being called together by his sacred Maje∣sty,
and Deputed by the Countrey, to be Counsel∣lors,
and Vindicators of <HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>Peace.</HI></P>
<P>2. To the Genius of our Times▪ nothing is
more needfull to be preached than the love of
<HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>Peace.</HI> The Winters distemper of our
age is such, that the <HI>Love</HI> of many (if not most)
is grown cold to both: <HI>Truth</HI> much obscured, de∣praved,
blemished, prejudiced, undermined, dis∣countenanced,
suppressed: <HI>Peace</HI> very crazy and
shaken: rumors of wars, preparations for wars,
study of sides &amp; parts, great division of thoughts,
pertinacy in opinions, breeding disaffections; and
disaffections flaming to open contention and ho∣stility;
so far, as from the strife of pens and
tongues, writing, and disputing, we are come to
the terror of war, to swords and arms; That if
the great God, who is the Father of Truth and
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
<HI>Peace</HI> (who refraines the spirits of men that de∣light
in warre) had not been gracious unto us, and
inclined the heart of our King to Counsells of
Peace, you had not this day been Auditors, nor I
a Speaker of this Theam, but all of us miserable
actors, or spectators of the contrary, the suppres∣sion
of <HI>Truth,</HI> and utter subversion of our <HI>Peace.</HI></P>
<P>3. The Text suits to the present occasion of
the Sacrament: Your late fasting is this day hap∣pily
turned to a cheerfull feast: your Water
changed to Wine; the best viands, the best wine;
the soules provision for eternity, the body and
bloud of Christ. A soules feast, a feast of exceed∣ing
joy, of eternall gladnesse. A feast of love;
Gods love to us; Christs love for us; our love to
them, and to each other.</P>
<P>A Feast of <HI>Truth;</HI> the sealing and confirmation
of the highest, most necessary and comfortable
truth, which received by faith, is able to save our
soules. And a feast of <HI>Peace</HI> too; the most glori∣ous
peace between God and our soules, between
Christ and his Church; between one another.</P>
<P>So that nothing can come more seasonably af∣ter
your Fast, and with this Feast of spirituall joy,
the holy Sacrament, then this divine exhortation,
most worthy of God to teach, and of us to learn,
as men, and as Christians: both which names im∣port
a speciall relation we have, above all crea∣tures
under heaven, to Truth and Peace, as we are <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, rationall and sociall creatures;
as <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, regenerate and sanctified by the
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
Spirit, which raiseth our souls to the enjoyment
of the highest Truth and Peace, which is in God,
and from God, bringing the soul to God, and
uniting it ever with him.</P>
<P>The three words in the Text (whereon I pur∣pose
to insist) are a sacred Trinity. Three preci∣ous
Jewels; Truth, Peace, and Love; all eminent
in God, and from him: objects, and affections of
the highest capacity, use, and excellencie to our
souls; <HI>Truth,</HI> as the light of the Sunne; <HI>Peace</HI> as
the heat, which enlivens, fosters, quickens, makes
fruitfull all. <HI>Love</HI> makes us enjoy them both.
<HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>Peace</HI> are, <HI>Bona publica &amp; universalia. Truth</HI>
for the soule, <HI>Peace</HI> for the body and state; every
one hath a share and interest in them, Prince,
Peeres, and People.</P>
<P>Of these I intend to speak, not as a Statist or
Politician (to which I pretend not) but as a Di∣vine,
a Messenger from the God of Truth and
Peace; seeking to kindle and inflame your hearts
to such a love of them, as may be most happy to
your own souls, and most beneficiall to our
Church and State: in the good of both which,
you are all highly concerned: and in nothing can
you promote the prosperity of either or both of
them, more, then in your <HI>Love</HI> and advancement
of <HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>Peace.</HI></P>
<P>May God the Fountain of Truth, Christ the
Saviour of Love, the holy Ghost the Spirit of
Peace, assist me in speaking, you in hearing, all in
doing so, as we may shew a pure impartiall, and
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
unpassionate love of Truth and Peace.</P>
<P>In the words consider three things: First, the
inference, <HI>Therefore:</HI> Secondly, the objects pro∣pounded,
<HI>Truth,</HI> and <HI>Peace.</HI> Thirdly, the dutie re∣quired:
<HI>Love.</HI></P>
<P>Every word hath a weight, beauty and benefit
in it; so that they well merit and require your at∣tention.</P>
<P>First, the inference, <HI>Therefore:</HI> The greater
mercies God shewes to us, the stricter obligations
to love and obedience he hath upon us. When
our fasting and mourning are happily turned to
cheerfull feasts, our feares and jealousies cleered
up to joy and gladnesse, to hopes of better estate
and times, what doth God require of us, but this?
<HI>Therefore to love the Truth and Peace.</HI></P>
<P>When Gods infinite mercy and patience to
us hath beyond expectation, as well as desert,
brought back our Church and State, from the
brink and precipice of warre, ruine, and confu∣sion,
which threatned our <HI>Peace.</HI> From the
spreading, and prevailings of errours, heresies,
schismes, and superstition, which strive to oppress
or eclipse our Church and <HI>Truth:</HI> That there is a
breathing space, a lengthning of our tranquillity,
put into our hands, What doth God require of us
by way of gratitude to him, of loyalty to our So∣veraign,
of fidelitie to our Countrey, then to
<HI>Love</HI> the <HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>Peace;</HI> which are so happily
still continued to us; and by an active, serious,
and industrious love to study the setling and re∣covery
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
of them both.</P>
<P>Secondly, the Objects propounded: here we
will consider.</P>
<P>First, <HI>What Truth is.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, <HI>What Peace.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, The union of them: <HI>Truth and Peace.</HI></P>
<P>Fourthly, The <HI>lovelinesse in them: which best ap∣pears
in the benefit by them, so as to merit our affection.</HI></P>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>1. Of Truth.</HEAD>
<P>That question of <HI>Pilate</HI> to Christ, will here be
made: What is <HI>Truth?</HI> I answer. It is a con∣formity,
agreeablenesse, or answerablenesse of
our mindes or things to their Ideas, patternes,
rules or measures; As that Copy is true, which
agrees with the Originall; That weight or mea∣sure
true, which fits the Standard, That impres∣sion
true in waxe or paper, which exactly fits the
types and engravings, That notion or perception
true in the minde or sense, which agrees with the
nature of the thing or object, whereto they are
applyed.</P>
<P><HI>Truth</HI> is the increated light of the intellectaull
world, shining from God to Angels and Men.</P>
<P>The first <HI>Idea,</HI> rule, measure or Standard of
Truth, is God: his Will, which I call <HI>Veritas
Dei.</HI> Whereby he is, what he is, essentially, sim∣ply,
immutably: by which he wils all things to
be, what indeed they are, and knowes them to be,
such as they are most certainly. This Sunne of
Truth is in God: never clouded, spotted, or
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
eclipsed; never setting or changing. Eternall
light, day, noone, a constant serenity.</P>
<P>From this is the eradiation of <HI>Truth;</HI> or shi∣ning
forth of the Divine will by his Works and
Word. Which we call <HI>Veritas Rei:</HI> and this is
first <HI>Entitatis,</HI> whereby things are such as God
would have them to be, and so are true and good.</P>
<P>Secondly, <HI>Veritas mentis;</HI> whereby things are
known or believed by us to be such, as indeed
they are, either made or revealed by God to us:
this is the <HI>truth</HI> of science or faith;</P>
<P>Thirdly, Hence flows <HI>Veritas sermonis,</HI> of
<HI>dicti;</HI> when our words and orall expressions are
conformable to our knowledge, and belief or
things speaking the truth. <HI>Ephes.</HI> 4. 15.</P>
<P>Fourthly, <HI>Veritas facti &amp; Vitae;</HI> whereby our
actions are conformable to what we say, and
seem to know, judge, or believe of things, which
is the doing of the Truth. 1. <HI>Ioh.</HI> 1. 6. The <HI>Idea</HI>
or pattern of our actions are our words; of our
words, our minds and conceptions; of our minds
things themselves; of all things the Divine will,
most wise, powerfull, and immutably good.
All Truth as being, is originally from God, as a
Sea and Sun derived, and must by a right beam
and clear stream be reduced to him again: and
so it is; when we do as we speak: when we
speak as we think, know or believe; when we
know or believe, as things are either made, or re∣vealed
by God: Then doth the ray or veyn of
<HI>truth</HI> flow aright from God to us, and reflect back
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
again from us to him: When in any of these we
fail: there comes in hypocrisie and simulation in
our actions; lying in our words; error, falsity and
unbelief in our mindes, when our actions contra∣dict
our words, our words our mindes, our mindes
the nature and <HI>truth</HI> of things, made, or revealed
by God: whose will in his works and word, is
(as I said) the rule of <HI>Truth.</HI></P>
<P>There are divers manifestations of <HI>truth;</HI> though
it be but one, yet as light shining through divers
pores; or one Fountain derived in severall Con∣duits,
for the benefit of rationall creatures.</P>
<P>First, There is <HI>Truth,</HI> naturall or physicall in
the Works of God, which by sense and discourse,
by art and science we learn.</P>
<P>Secondly, There is <HI>Truth</HI> morall, politicall,
or civil; which is in the enacting, interpreting, and
executing of Laws according to the rules of
Justice.</P>
<P>Thirdly, there is a truth Theologicall, super∣naturall
or religious; which chiefly concerns
our Souls, and is immediately taught from
God.</P>
<P>The first is in the Works of God and Nature.</P>
<P>The second in the laws and edicts of men a∣greeable
to principles of reason.</P>
<P>The third is in the sacred Scriptures, the only
foundation and rule of faith and religion.</P>
<P>The first concerns us as creatures severally.</P>
<P>The second as sociable creatures joyntly in a
state or Common-wealth.</P>
<P><PB N="9" REF="8"/>
The third as <HI>Christians,</HI> in a Church and neerer
call or relation to God.</P>
<P>The first requires our love to it, as we love <HI>our
selves</HI> in a naturall way: the second, as wee love
<HI>our Countrey,</HI> relations and liberties: the third as
we love <HI>our soules.</HI></P>
<P>By the first, the health and welfare of our <HI>bodies,</HI>
and pleasure of our senses, fancies, and minds, are
maintained, while we know and enjoy the true ver∣tues,
power, and use of creatures; able to apply fit
meanes to our ends.</P>
<P>By the second, the health of the state, or <HI>body
politick</HI> is preserved; while <HI>Lawes,</HI> which are the
<HI>nerves and ligaments</HI> of civil societies, are groun∣ded
upon innate, infallible and eternall principles
of <HI>equity, reason, and justice,</HI> to which all men agree;
and being so constituted, are truly interpreted and
executed; not wrested, depraved, obscured, or
violently broken: this is <HI>veritas justitiae &amp; decisionis:
the truth in judicature,</HI> Zach. 8. 16. <HI>Execute the
judgement of Truth and Peace in your gates.</HI></P>
<P>By the third, <HI>our soules health and happinesse</HI>
are maintained; while we see, know, beleeve, and
rest upon those excellent and <HI>saving truths,</HI> which
God hath in his word revealed to us, in the plaine∣nesse
and simplicity of the sense, not denying or
doubting any thing, but humbly and willingly
embracing every <HI>truth</HI> revealed, as it agrees to the
generall <HI>rule</HI> and <HI>Analogy of Faith,</HI> contained in
the <HI>holy Scriptures,</HI> this is <HI>Veritas fidei &amp; reli∣gionis.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="9"/>
The first <HI>truth</HI> wee gaine by <HI>senses</HI> and <HI>dis∣course.</HI>
The second by common <HI>notions,</HI> or in∣bred
<HI>principles of reason.</HI> The third by <HI>divine reve∣lation;</HI>
depending upon the veracitie, infa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>libility
and authority of God.</P>
<P>No truth is to be neglected, because it is a
<HI>beame or lineament of God;</HI> but those are most
to bee loved and esteemed, which discover God
most cleerly to us; bring us nearest, and make us
likest to him! This, as the most excellent and
usefull <HI>truth,</HI> I chiefly here understand; which
exceeds all others, as much as the soule doth the
body; or eternity a moment. And in this, mens
hearts are most prone to be negligent, and coldly
affected.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>2. Peace.</HEAD>
<P><HI>Peace</HI> in any kinde, and under any notion is
<HI>sweet</HI> and <HI>lovely.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>
<HI>Naz.</HI> We can better tell what it is by the fruition,
than description of it: what <HI>health</HI> is to the body,
and <HI>calmnesse</HI> to the sea, and <HI>serenity</HI> to the day,
such is <HI>peace:</HI> which ariseth from the fit, orderly,
and proportionable disposing of things. It is a
kinde of sweet, divine, and heavenly <HI>concent, har∣mony</HI>
or <HI>beauty</HI> of things, subordinate one to ano∣ther.</P>
<P>Such it is: <HI>first, peace in nature,</HI> and the grea∣ter
World, from the wise and apt <HI>combination</HI> of
creatures; by symbolicall qualities so contem∣pered,
that all agree to make up one intire body,
the World.</P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="9"/>
2. In the <HI>lesser worlds</HI> of mixt bodies, <HI>Peace</HI>
is that <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> or <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> due <HI>temper</HI> and <HI>moderation</HI> of humours and parts, which keep their true place
and proportion; <HI>Quá quodlibet corpus non minus
appetit unitatem suam quam entitatem.</HI></P>
<P>3. In the <HI>rationall World; Peace is that compo∣sednesse,</HI>
and tranquillity of the soule, whereby
all the inferiour faculties, and the populacy of
affections or passions are regular, and subject to
the rule, and soveraignty of <HI>reason.</HI></P>
<P>4. In the spirituall world, the regenerate soule;
<HI>Peace</HI> is the humble and willing <HI>subjection,</HI> and
sutablenesse of the conscience in all things to the
Will and Spirit of God.</P>
<P>5. In the <HI>Politicall</HI> or <HI>civill world,</HI> the State,
or Church; <HI>Peace</HI> is the <HI>setling</HI> and due orde∣ring
of things by just <HI>Lawes</HI> of government; and
by true grounds or rules of Piety and Religion;
whereto all submit. It consists, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,
in the right <HI>skill</HI> of governing; and
<HI>will</HI> to be governed. When all agree in one thing,
all think, speak, and do by the same thing, all con∣spire
in one maine end, the <HI>glory of God,</HI> and the
<HI>publick good,</HI> which is the supreame Law: when
all are setled on one <HI>ground,</HI> move by one <HI>rule,</HI> and
tend to one <HI>end. Truth, Order,</HI> and <HI>Iustice,</HI> are
the only foundation and pillars of <HI>Peace,</HI> in both
Church, and Common-wealth.</P>
<P>2. The second consideration is <HI>the union of the
two, Truth</HI> and <HI>Peace;</HI> In <HI>God</HI> they are united: and so
in every <HI>good soule,</HI> &amp; well ordered <HI>Church</HI> or <HI>State,</HI>
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
they may, and doe best agree together: no <HI>firme,</HI>
or durable <HI>peace,</HI> which is not fastned and cemen∣ted
with <HI>truth:</HI> so false and pernicious a <HI>princi∣ple</HI>
is that of some; that the lesse men know of
<HI>truth,</HI> the more easily they will bee kept in <HI>Peace;</HI>
that the way to subdue men to an <HI>asinine pati∣ence,</HI>
is to cast them into an <HI>asinine ignorance.</HI>
Whereas on the contrary, no men or minds are
more obedientially disposed to an <HI>heroick pati∣ence,</HI>
as to the burthens, pressures, and exactions
upon their states and liberties, &amp;c. than they,
who are best informed, how little all these world∣ly
things are to be valued, having hopes of farre
better. And no men are more stubbornely contu∣macious,
refractory and prone to flame, to <HI>rebelli∣on</HI>
and <HI>munity,</HI> than they, who know, and expect
no better, or higher good than those of sense and
present life, who think you robbe them of their
heaven, God, and all happinesse, if you injure them
in their <HI>estates, honours,</HI> or <HI>liberties.</HI></P>
<P>Those <HI>subjects</HI> are most shie, and prone to
start from obedience, and fall from <HI>peace,</HI> who
live by <HI>Moone-light</HI> of humane reason, and senses
onely, which amazeth their minds with the <HI>sha∣dowes
of good</HI> in riches, pleasures, honours, and
liberties temporall, and walke not by the <HI>Sunne∣shine</HI>
of <HI>divine truth,</HI> which discovers the onely
necessary, excellent, and satisfactory objects, wor∣thy
of the soules love and acceptance; for <HI>no∣thing
is truly lovely, which is not spirituall and eter∣nall.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="10"/>
No such <HI>bonds of peace and unity,</HI> then, as the
<HI>spirit</HI> of <HI>truth,</HI> which ties the conscience to obe∣dience
and patience; <HI>The wisdome from above is
first pure, then peaceable,</HI> James 3. 17.</P>
<P>So that they best may march together; but first
<HI>truth,</HI> then <HI>peace. Truth</HI> must have the prece∣dence:
rather <HI>truth,</HI> than <HI>peace. Truth</HI> wee owe to
God, and our soules immediately; <HI>peace</HI> onely to
our bodies and states, &amp;c. If one must be despen∣sed
withall, it is <HI>peace,</HI> not <HI>truth:</HI> better <HI>truth</HI>
without publique <HI>peace,</HI> than <HI>peace</HI> without sa∣ving
<HI>truth. Truth</HI> alone will bring us peace, the
best peace, Christs peace, which the world can nei∣ther
give nor take away. <HI>Pax est omni bello tristior,
quae veritatis &amp; justitiae ruinâ constat.</HI> That <HI>peace</HI> is
farre to deare, which costs us the losse of <HI>truth,</HI> I
meane <HI>great, saving, necessary,</HI> and <HI>fundamentall</HI>
truth.</P>
<P>2 Where these <HI>truths</HI> are asserted, study to adde
<HI>peace</HI> to them; that <HI>truth</HI> may root, spread, fa∣sten,
and fructifie the more. Nor is the publique
<HI>peace</HI> to bee violated for every <HI>truth,</HI> such as nei∣ther
tends to <HI>faith,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Acontius. straing. Sat.</NOTE> nor much to <HI>good manners.
Dissidiis magnis, &amp; controversis non sunt redimendae
minores istae veritates.</HI></P>
<P>Wee must not by contention of tongues, or
pens, or hands, so farre vindicate <HI>truths of lesser
size,</HI> and consequence, as to break the <HI>peace</HI> of
our affections, words and conversations.</P>
<P>Let <HI>truth</HI> and <HI>peace</HI> then goe together, in our
<HI>loves</HI> and <HI>lives. Truth</HI> as the root, <HI>peace</HI> as the
fruit: <HI>Truth</HI> as the light, <HI>Peace</HI> as heat: <HI>truth</HI>
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
as the foundation, <HI>peace</HI> as the structure.</P>
<P>And certainely in the <HI>Church,</HI> those <HI>tenets</HI> and
propositions are likeliest to be true, which tend to
the <HI>peace</HI> of the <HI>Church,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing. 3. 25.</NOTE> as it was the <HI>true</HI> mo∣ther,
which pleaded against the dividing of the
child. And that <HI>peace</HI> in the <HI>civill state</HI> is like∣liest
to be lasting and sound, which is built on the
<HI>Truth</HI> of <HI>Reason</HI> and <HI>Religion</HI> both, and not upon
the fancies, opinions, dictates, traditions, exam∣ples,
and tyranny of custome and men.</P>
<P>Neither <HI>peace</HI> of <HI>Church</HI> nor <HI>State</HI> is to be pur∣chased
with the sale of <HI>Truth,</HI> saving and necessary:
nor yet are all <HI>truths</HI> to be prosecuted with such
<HI>vehemencie,</HI> heate, and contention, as to make
<HI>Shipwrack</HI> of eithers <HI>peace.</HI> The <HI>windowes</HI> and
<HI>lights</HI> of <HI>truth</HI> must not bee so enlarged as to wea∣ken
the firmenesse, solidity, and entirenesse of the
building: Nor may the <HI>Walls</HI> be so thick, close
and compacted, as to exclude or obscure the
light: which the Turks doe, who so farre <HI>secure</HI>
their peace, as they forbid the <HI>searching</HI> of Truth:
neither <HI>darknesse</HI> may make the house of God
uselesse; nor <HI>breaches,</HI> under pretence of letting
in more light, may bee made so wide, as to render
the edifice unsafe and tottering.</P>
<P>As <HI>divine Truth</HI> of <HI>Religion,</HI> so <HI>civill truth</HI> of
Judicature and Peace must kisse each other. Here
the <HI>veracity</HI> and conscience of <HI>Iudges,</HI> and Magi∣strates
is chiefely required; that they bee <HI>Men of
truth, Exod.</HI> 18. 21. For, <HI>false, corrupt,</HI> and <HI>un∣just
Iudges,</HI> like <HI>Comets,</HI> portend warres and com∣motions
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
in a state; scattering so malignant an in∣fluence
into mens minds, that every one had ra∣ther
adventure the injuries of <HI>warre</HI> than suffer the
injustice of <HI>peace.</HI></P>
<P>4 The <HI>Lovelinesse of them,</HI> which will best ap∣peare
by the <HI>benefits</HI> from them, why <HI>truth</HI> and
<HI>peace</HI> are to be <HI>loved.</HI></P>
<P>1 <HI>Civill</HI> or <HI>Politicall truth</HI> is the <HI>mind</HI> of the <HI>Law,</HI>
the rule of <HI>Iustice,</HI> the right measuring and distribu∣tion
of things to every one, according as <HI>equity</HI> and
<HI>reason</HI> require.</P>
<P>By this <HI>truth</HI> the propriety and enjoyment of
what is our own are maintained; fraud, injuries,
and violence, detected, punished, and restrained.
Innocencie releeved, industry maintained and in∣couraged;
due rewards to vertue and merit, as well
as punishments to sinne and vice are dispensed: In
a word, the <HI>safety</HI> of your persons, wives, children,
houses, lands, goods, honours, liberties, lives, and
all that is deare to you in this world, depends up∣on
this <HI>truth</HI> in <HI>Iudicature,</HI> without which no <HI>So∣ciety</HI>
of men can subsist, at least not flourish; but
degenerate to a poore and slavish <HI>vassalage,</HI> and
such a lazie despondency of minds, which sink
them next degree to beasts; seeking no more but
to live, having no thoughts or designes generous,
noble, or extending beyond the present supply of
back and belly.</P>
<P>See then how much <HI>they</HI> deserve <HI>publique ha∣tred,</HI>
who through feare or flattery, or base and si∣nister
ends, falsifie the minde of the <HI>Law;</HI> at once
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
<HI>cutting</HI> asunder that great <HI>Cable</HI> which holds the
state from shipwrack: turning the <HI>sword of justice</HI>
put into their unworthy hands, to cut the <HI>throat</HI>
of <HI>lawes</HI> and <HI>liberties.</HI></P>
<P>2 The <HI>lovelinesse and benefit of Divine truth</HI>
revealed, whereon our Faith, our Religion, our
Soules, our Church depends, is so great that no
time or words serve to let it forth.</P>
<P>By this light of <HI>sacred truth, we know our selves</HI>
in our worst, lost, sinfull, and damnable estate,
wherein else as heathen or beasts we should stupid∣ly
and miserably die and perish. By this we <HI>know
God</HI> in his infinite mercies through <HI>Christ, which
is life eternall,</HI> Ioh. 17.3. By this we discover his
<HI>grace</HI> and <HI>love</HI> to us: for our free <HI>justification</HI> by
the righteousnesse of Christ, and sanctificati∣on
by his Spirit.</P>
<P>By this <HI>truth</HI> the <HI>burthens</HI> of our sinnes, our
feares, our miseries, the horrour of death, hell, and
eternity, are disarmed and releeved: by this bles∣sed
<HI>light</HI> of <HI>truth,</HI> wee have many sweet and pre∣cious
<HI>promises</HI> to support us in all states, and all
tryals and temptions. But this as <HI>Moses</HI> from
Mount <HI>Nebo,</HI> we discover the pleasant and happy
<HI>prospect</HI> of heaven and eternity: the joyes, peace,
pleasure, happinesse, and security of that after-state
wee expect in the other world: we see a full,
though future, <HI>victory</HI> over sinne, fatan, flesh,
world, men, death, hell, and all; a full <HI>tryumph</HI>
and <HI>crowning</HI> of the soule and body in <HI>eternall
glory.</HI> You may see then how little experience or
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
knowledge they have of this <HI>truth,</HI> and the com∣forts
by it, who are weary of it, enemies, or indif∣ferent
to it: <HI>Better not have the truth, than having it
to want the love of it.</HI></P>
<P>3 The <HI>amiablenesse of peace,</HI> publick and Na∣tionall
in Church or State; it is like the <HI>smiling
of a beautifull face,</HI> when <HI>peace</HI> flourisheth with
<HI>truth:</HI> O how <HI>lovely</HI> is it, at once to serve God
with purity and safety; with sincerity and secu∣rity;
to enjoy the blessings of Gods right and left
hand together!</P>
<P><HI>To eat every man with joy and cheerfulness of heart
the fruit of his owne vine and plantings▪</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mich. 4. 4.</NOTE> to reape the
harvest hee hath sowed: to dwell in the house hee
hath builded: to enjoy the wife he hath espoused,
and the children he hath begotten.</P>
<P>Your owne long and happy <HI>experience</HI> may
best teach you, what is the beauty and sweetnesse
of the breasts of <HI>peace:</HI> whence <HI>plenty</HI> flowes;
<HI>Learning,</HI> Arts, industry, trading, thrive and prosper;
your private and in them the publike strength,
honour, and treasure increaseth.</P>
<P>God grant you be not taught to <HI>prize</HI> and be
thankfull for it, by the want of it your selves: look
over Sea on the sad and black Characters, which
<HI>fire, famine,</HI> and <HI>sword,</HI> have wrot, nay ingraven,
and ploughed upon the faces of men, women, and
children; on their houses, fields, vineyards, Ci∣ties,
Churches, &amp;c. and you may with weeping
and amazed eyes reade this lesson; <HI>O the sweet
and lovely blessings of Truth and Peace! O the
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
horrid, hideous deformity of errours and warres!</HI></P>
<Q><L>—En quo discordia gentes</L>
<L>Perduxit miseras.</L></Q>
<P>3 Wee come now to the <HI>third generall head:</HI>
having seene what <HI>truth</HI> and <HI>peace</HI> are; how well
they <HI>agree,</HI> how much <HI>they merit our love;</HI> now
we goe on to the <HI>last part,</HI> which is <HI>our duty. There∣fore
love them.</HI> Here wee will inquire two <HI>parti∣culars.</HI>
1. <HI>What need</HI> there is that men should
bee thus exhorted to <HI>love</HI> these, which have so
attractive a lovelinesse in them. 2. <HI>Wherein</HI>
most effectually wee must expresse our <HI>love</HI> to
them.</P>
<P>I Although nothing more deserve <HI>our love:</HI>
yet such is the ignorance, dulnesse, or depravednesse
of mens mindes, affections, and manners, that
few there are, which truely <HI>love</HI> them. First, some
<HI>love neither Truth nor Peace;</HI> of which temper
the <HI>Iesuitick spirit</HI> seemes to be, which <HI>deceives</HI>
the Nations with the <HI>Cup of errour,</HI> and <HI>scatters
coales of fire</HI> and dissention among men. Secondly,
some <HI>love truth, but not peace:</HI> zealously affected
to <HI>truth,</HI> but for want of sound and steddy know∣ledge,
or meeke and humble hearts, they are full
of violence and bitternesse; so prone to strife and
contention, that from words and disputes they
easily kindle to blowes: <HI>Some, when you speak to
them of peace, prepare for war, Quia multis utile bellum;</HI>
their best fishing being in troubled waters. Third∣ly,
some <HI>love peace</HI> but <HI>not truth;</HI> as <HI>Ishachar,</HI> slug∣gishly
<HI>couching between the burthens of Superstition
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
and Oppression,</HI> rather than trouble their <HI>Peace,</HI> in a
land of <HI>plenty.</HI> Out of a lazie, grosse, and sensuall
humour, so addicted to the <HI>enjoyments of peace,</HI> that
they care not what <HI>encroachments</HI> are made on
<HI>Truth.</HI> Fourthly, many <HI>seeme to love them,</HI> but not
<HI>simply, per se</HI> and <HI>propter se;</HI> but corruptly and parti∣ally,
for by-ends and advantages to bee had by
them, of profit, preferment, applause, and the
like; as <HI>Demas</HI> did 2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 4. 10. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.
It is <HI>neither truth nor peace</HI> so
much they love (though they stickle for both)
but their <HI>bellies,</HI> pleasures, plenty, and selves, which
they enjoy under the <HI>wings of truth and peace.</HI></P>
<P>5. Many <HI>love what they think truth</HI> (and happi∣ly
is so) yet not because it is so, but because they
think so; extreamely <HI>biased</HI> with selfe love and
pride; that they pertinaciously retaine, what ever
opinion they have once undertaken, though they
cannot maintaine it; only on this ground, <HI>Ne
videantur errâsse;</HI> so hardly drawne by overcom∣ming
themselves to <HI>triumph</HI> over their <HI>errours. Ita
perit judicium, ubi res transit in affectum, &amp; nostram
qualemcunque praevalere volumus sententiam, quia no∣stra
est:</HI> so much doe our affections blinde, bri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,
corrupt, and warpe our <HI>judgements.</HI></P>
<P>6. Many say they love truth; but not <HI>univer∣sally;</HI>
not such truthes as crosse their credits, opini∣ons,
ends, pleasures, sinnes and lusts; <HI>Nolunt id ve∣rum
videri, quod affectibus suis adversatur. He loves
not any Truth, that loves not all;</HI> as he likes not the
light or Sun, who is offended with any beame of
it.</P>
<P><PB N="20" REF="14"/>
7. <HI>Veritas animae sponsa; Truth is a pure Virgin,</HI>
which every soule should wooe and seeke to <HI>wed</HI>
to it selfe; Many <HI>pretend to love it,</HI> but not <HI>casto &amp;
honesto amore sed meretricio &amp; prudendo. Lascivientia
ingenia,</HI> such as fondly and <HI>wantonly</HI> out of a vanity
and curiosity only <HI>court</HI> that <HI>Truth,</HI> which they
see is countenanced and shined upon by publick
favour and authority; ready enough to discounte∣nance
and forsake it, if the streame of things
should change: <HI>Venales animae,</HI> vile and mercena∣ry
soules, that <HI>buy and sell the truth, prostituting</HI> it,
<HI>not</HI> intirely loving and <HI>wedding</HI> themselves to it.</P>
<P>8. Some to <HI>purchase their peace,</HI> are ready to sell
the Truth, by flattering, complying and mancipa∣ting
their judgements to other mens opinions and
errours, either discovered, which is very wicked, or
unsearched, which is very weak, <HI>Degenerate mindes</HI>
which so easily <HI>enslave</HI> that <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the noblest
and soveraigne faculty of the soule, which is the
<HI>understanding,</HI> to other mens errours never so great,
if their power be so too.</P>
<P>9. <HI>Veritas animae pabulum,</HI> there is as great an
aptitude and proportion betweene the <HI>minde</HI> of
man, and <HI>truth,</HI> as is betweene the <HI>eye</HI> and the <HI>object,
meat</HI> and the <HI>stomack:</HI> now we know, it must be
a pure and unblemished <HI>eye,</HI> that sees with certain∣ty
and constancie; a cleare, sound, and undiseased
<HI>stomack,</HI> that desires, likes, and digests wholesome
meats. Such must that minde bee which loves.
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Tim. 4 3.</NOTE> <HI>Wholesome Truths, sound Do∣ctrines.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="21" REF="14"/>
1. Many are so <HI>vitiated</HI> and distempered by sin,
the World, their Lusts and Vanities, that they
wholely refuse to take downe any <HI>truth;</HI> what the
eare may receive sometime, their heart <HI>casts</HI> up a∣gaine
profanely and reproachfully, by their words
and actions. <HI>Ita veritas odium &amp; nauseam parit.</HI>
The speediest way to <HI>lose</HI> the <HI>love</HI> of many is, free∣ly
to tell them that <HI>truth,</HI> which might doe them
most good,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Kings 22.</NOTE> for it seemes to them as <HI>Michaiahs</HI>
words to <HI>Ahab, odious</HI> and offensive, although it
gave him warning of his danger, and shewed him
the only way for his safety.</P>
<P>2. Many like choyse and <HI>wanton stomacks,</HI> re∣ceive
and digest indeed, some <HI>truths</HI> in their minds
and memories; but it is <HI>morbum alere non hominem;</HI>
only thereby the better to nourish and strengthen
their erroneous <HI>humours</HI> and <HI>conceits;</HI> and what ever
<HI>truth</HI> they meet with, is presently <HI>swallowed without
chewing</HI> by some <HI>monster of opinion,</HI> which they
maintaine. For <HI>errour</HI> is so <HI>feeble</HI> and unbottomed,
that it must have some buttresses and seeming <HI>ba∣sis</HI>
of <HI>truth</HI> to support it. By this meanes <HI>detayning
the truth of God in unrighteousnesse, Rom.</HI> 1. 18.</P>
<P>3. Many are of so <HI>hot,</HI> unquiet and <HI>cholerick sto∣macks,</HI>
that they love not <HI>truth sweetned with peace;</HI>
not calme and sober truths. Afraid to be thought
<HI>coldly,</HI> if <HI>peaceably</HI> religious, even in matters of lesser
moment. Interpreting that <HI>zeale,</HI> which is but na∣turall
<HI>passion</HI> and <HI>choler,</HI> an humane feaverish and
praedatorious, not that holy, gentle, and propiti∣ous
<HI>heate of love,</HI> which only well <HI>digesteth</HI> sacred
<HI>truths.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="22" REF="15"/>
So that most men we see had neede to be called
upon to <HI>love truth and peace.</HI> In some, <HI>hopes</HI> of pre∣ferment
will doe much to pervert, leaven, and sup∣presse
<HI>truth,</HI> warping which way the Sunne of fa∣vour
shines warmest. In others, <HI>despaire</HI> of prefer∣ment,
and <HI>popular</HI> inclinations may doe as much
to disturbe <HI>peace,</HI> and <HI>established truth:</HI> Every way
<HI>Pronus lapsus, major sit cautela. Few are</HI> true, sincere,
and hearty <HI>lovers</HI> of them; by the <HI>Antiperistasis</HI> of
others coldnesse, let the heat of your <HI>love</HI> grow
more intensive.</P>
<P>2 Which is the last particular: <HI>The way most effe∣ctually
to expresse the love we owe to truth and peace:</HI>
first to <HI>truth,</HI> then to <HI>peace,</HI> to <HI>both</HI> if possible. <HI>Amor
est pondus animae: Love</HI> is the <HI>weight</HI> and motor of
the soule, the <HI>Spring</HI> that sets all the wheeles on
worke. It is a vehement, active, industrious, un∣wearied,
invincible affection; if rightly placed on
worthy objects, it workes wonders. <HI>Amor non po∣test
abscondi,</HI> the fire <HI>of love</HI> is impatient to be hid or
smothered: <HI>Nescit nimium,</HI> never thinks it hath
done enough: <HI>Est extaticus, nec sinit amantem esse
sui juris:</HI> it hath a kinde of <HI>rapture</HI> and extatick
power, which <HI>transports</HI> the minde beyond it selfe,
and <HI>dispossesseth</HI> it of it selfe, to bestow it selfe on
that it loves. <HI>Delicata res est amor;</HI> It is a <HI>tender</HI> af∣fection,
impatient of any injury or dishonour cast
on what we love. <HI>Et sibi lex est severissima: Love</HI>
needs no <HI>motive</HI> but it selfe to carry it to the ex∣tremity
of its power.</P>
<P>If our <HI>love</HI> then to <HI>truth</HI> be reall, it will shew it
selfe.</P>
<P><PB N="23" REF="15"/>
1 In the serious and earnest <HI>searching</HI> for, <HI>find∣ing
out,</HI> and <HI>discovering</HI> of <HI>truth:</HI> for, <HI>Veritas in
profundo: Truth is not obvious in the surface of things,
but hath a depth,</HI> being sunk and retired from us,
as now we are. There is a great deale of <HI>false and
loose earth, rubbish of Opinions,</HI> probabilities, and
falsities to be cast away, before wee come to the
cleare <HI>streame</HI> of <HI>truth,</HI> which by secret <HI>derivations</HI>
flowes from the eternall <HI>Fountaine, God.</HI> There are
not only grosser <HI>clouds of errours</HI> and falsities, which
darken <HI>truth;</HI> but <HI>parelii</HI> too, <HI>verisimilia, seeming
sunnes of truth,</HI> which are but apparences and pro∣babilities,
of no long continuance. He then that
will <HI>seeke and finde</HI> certaine, and saving <HI>truth,</HI> must
apply himselfe to <HI>God,</HI> his <HI>Word,</HI> and <HI>Spirit,</HI> not
take it upon <HI>trust</HI> and <HI>credit</HI> of humane <HI>fancie,</HI> or
<HI>reason: Multi taedio investigandae veritatis ad proxi∣mos
divertunt errores:</HI> Many out of an easinesse,
lazinesse, or presumption, take up <HI>truths</HI> from cu∣stome,
education, prepossessed conceits, shew of
Antiquity, excellency of mens parts, &amp;c. prone to
count that <HI>truth,</HI> which themselves or others have
a long time beleeved to be such. <HI>Sed oculos à rebus
omnibus abducas, quae Deus non sunt si veritatem quae∣ras,</HI>
Esay 8. 20. <HI>To the Law and to the Testimony,</HI>
Joh. 5.29. <HI>Search the Scriptures;</HI> from these <HI>wells</HI>
must we draw the <HI>waters of life,</HI> purifying, refresh∣ing,
and saving <HI>truths;</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.
The <HI>Veyn</HI> and <HI>Mine of truth,</HI> hath many
windings, and intricate turnings, requiring a saga∣cious
and industrious minde to follow it.</P>
<P><PB N="24" REF="16"/>
2 Shew your <HI>love to truth,</HI> by <HI>propagating,</HI> and
<HI>imparting</HI> it to others, when your selves have dis∣covered
it. <HI>Veritas nihil erubescit, praeterquam ab∣scondi;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">T<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtul.</NOTE>
<HI>Truth is onely ashamed to bee hidden;</HI> as the
Sunne to be clouded, or eclipsed. <HI>Truth,</HI> as light,
<HI>wasts</HI> not by communicating it selfe to others.
<HI>Quò communius bonum eò divinitus.</HI> Shew your <HI>love</HI>
to it and to men, by <HI>teaching</HI> it to others, but in a
<HI>calme</HI> and unpassionate way; <HI>truth is best seene in
cleare and untroubled waters,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Ephes.</HI>
4. 15. <HI>Speaking the truth in love.</HI> Pittying not tri∣umphing
in others ignorance, or reproaching their
errors and weaknesse of judgement. Farther, shew
your <HI>love,</HI> by using all meanes to <HI>plant</HI> and <HI>nourish
truth,</HI> by setting up the lights of good and paine∣full
Preachers, in the dark, and obscure corners of
our Land, where, God knowes, many poore <HI>soules
perish for want of knowledge</HI> (such I meane) as <HI>can
and will rightly divide the Word of truth, 1 Tim. 2. 15.</HI>
There is <HI>no engine</HI> you can invent so effectuall, to
batter down and demollish the adverse party, or
to <HI>secure</HI> the prosperitie of our Church and State.
But this will hardly be done, without encouraging
men to the study and preaching of <HI>truth</HI> in the way
of necessary, competent, and liberall maintenance;
for it is most certaine, as Bishop <HI>lewell</HI> sometime
told <HI>Queen Elizabeth,</HI> in a Sermon, <HI>Tenuitatem be∣neficiorum
necessario sequitur ignorantia sacerdotum.</HI>
Never flatter your selves, that the <HI>Lampes of the
Temple</HI> will burne at all, or but very dimly, and
poorely, if you supply them not with <HI>Oyle</HI> suffici∣ent
<PB N="25" REF="16"/>
to enliven themselves and enlighten others.</P>
<P>3. Shew your <HI>love of truth,</HI> by a zealous, active,
and constant <HI>maintaining</HI> of it: <HI>Zeale,</HI> is <HI>flamma a∣moris:
Love raised to a flame:</HI> by all justifiable wayes
asserting the honour of it, and the professors of it,
against the profanenesse, idlenesse, envy, calumnies,
and oppositions of the enemies thereof, either A∣theists,
sensuall, ignorant, or superstitious, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI>
13. 8. <HI>We can doe nothing against the truth, but for the
truth,</HI> doe all you lawfully may: by severe, and
wholesome <HI>Edicts, fencing in, and fortifying truth</HI>
against the Seminary incursions of those, that
seeke to encroach upon its ancient bounds: also
against the bold, and impudent Preaching, Prin∣ting,
and Disputing for the contrary errors, which
have beene long agoe exploded and confuted;
which by misused power, or tacit connivence,
seeke to creepe in, and undermine our <HI>truth. Leakes
may sinke us, as well as rockes split us.</HI> Jude 3. <HI>Con∣tend
then earnestly for the truth;</HI> but with the <HI>power of
Gods,</HI> not mans arme of flesh; with a <HI>contention of
love, not of force;</HI> such as may not destroy men, but
their errors, which otherwise will destroy them.
<HI>Truth</HI> is so sufficiently <HI>armed</HI> with its owne <HI>power,</HI>
that it needes not the assistance of the <HI>Sword</HI> or
<HI>Canon,</HI> which reach not the minds of men; nor can
divide them from their errors, nor batter downe
the <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, strong holds of prepossessed false
opinions; That <HI>excellency if power which is in the
Word of God</HI> and his <HI>Spirit,</HI> is onely able to subdue
the understanding? Yet must not the <HI>Magistrate▪</HI>
<PB N="26" REF="17"/>
so farre be wanting to Gods glory, and the Chur∣ches
good, as to faile to <HI>defend truth</HI> against those
that by cunning or force seeke to subvert it, setting
up the just <HI>t<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>or of</HI> those <HI>Lawes,</HI> which may chase
away those <HI>Owles, and Bats, and ferall Birds,</HI> that
<HI>love</HI> darkenesse, and portend a night, where ever
they appeare; <HI>that cannot endure the light, because
their workes are evill,</HI> as well as their doctrines
false.</P>
<P>4. Shew your <HI>love to the Truth,</HI> as by <HI>doing for it</HI>
all you can; so by <HI>obeying the truth from the heart,</HI>
1 Pet. 1. 22. by <HI>living conformably to it:</HI> that there
be no <HI>solaecisme</HI> in your lives, that the <HI>truth</HI> of your
doctrine be not <HI>confuted,</HI> by the corruptnesse of
your manners: not onely <HI>seeking</HI> the truth, and
<HI>speaking</HI> the truth, and <HI>defending</HI> the truth; but far∣ther,
<HI>doing the Truth, 1 John. 1. 6.</HI> which is the
strongest vindication of its honour, and your be∣leefe
of it. There is a <HI>labour</HI> of <HI>love, which loves its
labour;</HI> ready <HI>to deny our selves,</HI> in any thing neere
or deare to us, <HI>rather than deny</HI> any saving <HI>truth:</HI>
chearefully <HI>suffering for it,</HI> rather than it should
<HI>suffer;</HI> a good minde, that <HI>loves the truth,</HI> suffers
more in <HI>truthes</HI> suppression, than its owne; yea, by
<HI>dying for it,</HI> if need be; and God choose us out for
his champions to <HI>crowne and improve the necessity of
death,</HI> with <HI>the glory of martyrdome,</HI> which is the
highest <HI>witnessing of our love to God and his Truth.
Difficulties</HI> rather <HI>wh<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> and twist to a firmer <HI>resolu∣tion,</HI>
than any way bl<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t or discourage a well pla∣ced
affection. The Heathen man set such a <HI>price
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
on truth,</HI> that he thought it worth our life;
<Q><L>—Vitamque impendere vero,</L>
<L>Nec propter vitam vivendi perdere causam.</L></Q>
It is a <HI>blind</HI> &amp; preposterous <HI>love,</HI> that loves life bet∣ter
then that, for which onely life is worth the ha∣ving;
better we <HI>dye,</HI> than <HI>truth decay,</HI> which as a Phoe
nix is wont to renew its life out of martyrs ashes.</P>
<P>5, Lastly, what we come short in doing or suf∣fering
for the <HI>love of truth,</HI> at least, seeke to <HI>supply</HI> by
our frequent and fervent <HI>prayers</HI> to God, that hee
would so make the way, and carry on his <HI>truth</HI>
that it may <HI>prevalile</HI> upon the hearts of men <HI>to a
love of it.</HI></P>
<P>But in this variety of Opinions, and Distra∣ction
of sides, <HI>every one challenging truth</HI> to be on
their party, How shall we know, <HI>what is that Truth,</HI>
which we ought to <HI>love</HI> and adhere unto?</P>
<P>I Answer, the <HI>Truth</HI> of God, like the light of the
Sunne, is best knowne and distinguished from all
other, by the beauty and excellency of its <HI>effects,</HI>
of life, heate, and fertillity; that is infallibly the
<HI>saving and necessary truth of God,</HI> most deserving our
love and study, which hath, and alwayes had the
greatest and best <HI>influence</HI> on mens hearts and lives:
that is, <HI>Gods truth</HI> which makes men more <HI>godly,</HI>
more holy, pure, just, good, humble, peaceable,
charitable, selfe-denying, and consciencious in all
their wayes: What brings us nearest, and makes
us <HI>likest to God,</HI> which conformes us most to that
highest and divinest patterne of <HI>Christs minde</HI> and
conversation.</P>
<P><PB N="28" REF="18"/>
It hath beene alwayes the <HI>Seale of honour</HI> set upon
Christian Religion: and that <HI>truth,</HI> whereon it is
founded, that it <HI>most magnifies God and goodnesse.</HI>
Those truths which have the greatest operation
on mens mindes, consciences, and lives, so as to a∣mend
them, are set beyond all question and
disputes: These let us chiefely study, love, and
live by.</P>
<P>2. If our <HI>love</HI> be thus rightly set to <HI>Gods truth,</HI>
he will take care to <HI>settle our peace:</HI> to which we
<HI>owe a love too,</HI> and must shew it in the second place.
First, by <HI>praying heartily and constantly for it, Psal.
122. 6.</HI> Every one should thinke himselfe called
upon in those words. <HI>O pray for the peace of Ierusa∣lem.
Prayer engages God on our side,</HI> and calls in
an omnipotent arme to settle, strengthen, and se∣cure
our <HI>peace.</HI> Secondly, by <HI>assisting really,</HI> to the
support and maintaining of it, against the pertur∣bers
of it. 1. By seasonable <HI>counsells,</HI> and faithfull
advise grounded on <HI>Truth and Iustice.</HI> 2. By <HI>ar∣ming
counsells with power</HI> and Subsidyes of purses
and persons; to suppresse all unjust and rebellious
practises, which seeke to violate our <HI>peace. Peace
is not safe, except there be power for warre;</HI> which is
<HI>the guard of peace;</HI> as <HI>power</HI> without counsell is bru∣tish,
and selfe confounding; so <HI>counsell</HI> without
power is feeble, and subject to be despised. 3. By
<HI>living orderly</HI> in a way of meekenesse, humility,
and subjection in the feare of God, and obedience
to the wholesome Lawes established; which is
that we are taught by the truth of God, <HI>Rom. 13. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.
<PB N="29" REF="18"/>
Let every soule be subject, &amp;c.</HI> This I am sure will
bring a man peace at the last. If not externall, yet
internall, which will be eternall. 4. By <HI>searching
out,</HI> and exemplary <HI>punishing</HI> those that are the
<HI>perturbers of</HI> our <HI>peace; justly troubling</HI> those <HI>that
have troubled Israel,</HI> as <HI>Ioshua</HI> to <HI>Achan. Psal. 34. 14,
Thus seeke peace and pursue it;</HI> by pursuing those that
would rob us of it. And certainely you will finde,
<HI>none are</HI> more enemies to, and perturbers of our
<HI>peace,</HI> then those that are the perverters and oppo∣sers
of our <HI>Truth:</HI> either in judicature, or Religion,
for these scatter and blow the <HI>coales</HI> of <HI>discontent</HI> in
every corner, that the whose house must needes be
set on fire, if they be not timely quenched.</P>
<P>And now give me leave by way of <HI>Conclusion,</HI> a
little to apply to you and my selfe, the weight and
force of this Text.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="conclusion">
<HEAD>Therefore love the Truth and Peace.</HEAD>
<P>Had we in this Church and State (Right Ho∣nourable,
and the rest) beene so happy in the <HI>love
of truth and peace,</HI> as we have beene in the long glo∣rious
injoying, and the miraculous preservation of
them among us, certainely, neither <HI>truth</HI> had this
day beene so clouded and perplexed, nor our <HI>peace</HI>
so broken and distracted.</P>
<P>The <HI>God of truth and peace</HI> declares his displea∣sure,
and high indignation against us, for the neg∣ligence,
coldnesse, and ingratitude of many; for
the profanenesse, Atheisme, and malice of some:
for the superstition, formality, and backe-sliding
of others. How many are there, that deny, or de∣spise,
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
spise, or suppresse, or oppose, or contemne, scorne,
and deride, and corrupt and belye the <HI>Truth?</HI> That
the Prophets complaint may come neare our
times, <HI>Esay 59. 15. Truth faileth, and he that depar∣teth
from iniquiry maketh himselfe a prey:</HI>
<Q><L>Nos patim<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r longae pacis mala saevior armis,</L>
<L>Luxuria incumbit—</L></Q>
<HI>Long peace,</HI> like faire weather, hath raised up the
vapours of sinnes to cloud our Sunne, and trouble
our Heaven withall; which almost of us, from
highest to the lowest are not guilty of one or more
of those forenamed degrees of <HI>neglect against truth:</HI>
which shewes, wee have either no love at all, or a
small love, a tepid, and <HI>Laodicean love,</HI> a shame∣faced,
which is a shamefull <HI>love,</HI> or a false and base
<HI>love</HI> of truth, not for it selfe, but for our selves: as
our <HI>Diana;</HI> the mystery, by which our gaine or
greatnesse are sustained. If wee have not <HI>loved truth
in peace,</HI> were it not just with God to make us
<HI>want truth in warre?</HI> And <HI>because men received not
the love of the truth, he should give them over to strong
delusions, to beleeve a lye, 2 Thes.</HI> 2. 10.</P>
<P>Certainely God will severely exact of this
Church and Nation, of Prince and People, of
Preachers and Hearers, an account for our long en∣joyed
and undervalued <HI>truth and peace.</HI> Have wee
so long beene a <HI>Vine</HI> planted, and watered, and
fenced, both to necessitie, and omament, by an ex∣cessive
indulgence of God, and doe wee <HI>bring forth
soure grapes;</HI> that neither <HI>please God, nor profit men?</HI>
May we not justly feare (what wee have deserved)
<PB N="31" REF="19"/>
to be laid wast and desolute, to be made a <HI>hissing
and astonishment to all Nations▪,</HI> that God should
remove, or extinguish the glorious Lampe of the
Gospell, in whose <HI>light</HI> we have <HI>not rejoyced,</HI> because
we have not <HI>loved</HI> it?</P>
<P><HI>Love is an affection of union</HI> and fruition. Doe we
<HI>love the truth</HI> if we are <HI>weary</HI> of it, tediously and pee∣vishly
affected to it, willing to leave it, and with∣draw
from it? The <HI>loathing</HI> and nauseating of this
<HI>Heavenly Manna,</HI> as if we have had so much, that
it is necessary to recover and quicken mens appe∣tites
to it, by a more scanty allowance of it, is
<HI>this to love the truth?</HI> The <HI>tampering</HI> and essayes of
someto clip, or wash, or new coyne, or allay, and
abase, with some <HI>Romish mixture,</HI> the gold and pu∣ritie
of our Doctrine; <HI>is this to loue the truth?</HI> That
pure and refined <HI>Truth,</HI> which hath passed the
fiery triall, hath beene baptized in the blood of
many Martyrs, sowne in a field, made fruitfull with
their ashes; who <HI>loved not their lives</HI> so much as the
Truth. To set up <HI>lying vanities,</HI> Pictures, and
Images, and to cry downe Praying and Preaching,
whereby those toyles may be usefull and necessary
to the ignorant (because untaught) people, <HI>Is this to
love the truth?</HI> To suffer <HI>Idolatry,</HI> or superstitious
formalities in serving God to get ground upon
our Opinions and practises. Is <HI>this to love the truth?
Quae quo nudior, eô venustior;</HI> which <HI>the lesse it hath of
painting,</HI> the <HI>more it hath of true lovelinesse and native
beauty.</HI> Are not the lengthen and increase of Ce∣remonious
<HI>shadowes,</HI> a presage and signe of the
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
shortning of our <HI>Day</HI> and setting of our <HI>Sunne,</HI> or
diminishing of our <HI>Light.</HI></P>
<P>To <HI>quarrell</HI> at those <HI>Truths,</HI> which have bin long
ago determined by the Scripture, in the publique
confession of our Church, and in the Writings,
or Preachings of our gravest &amp; learnedst Divines,
Prelates, and others; as in the points of <HI>Iustification</HI>
by faith alone; of <HI>Trasubstantiation,</HI> of auricular
<HI>Confession;</HI> of <HI>prayer for the dead;</HI> of <HI>worshipping be∣fore
Images;</HI> of fiduciary <HI>assurance,</HI> and the like;
which some doting and superstitious <HI>Spirits,</HI> dare
to question, and <HI>retractate; Is this to love the truth?</HI>
What hath been done by Preaching and Printing,
by <HI>correcting,</HI> or rather <HI>corrupting</HI> of Bookes
(where the <HI>correctors</HI> themselves deserve to <HI>be cor∣rected</HI>)
your piety and wisedome may best finde
out. Nay, such hath beene the shamelesse impu∣dence
and effrontery of some ridiculous heads,
that plaine and honest mindes shall be scorned, de∣rided,
and in judgling fashion, cheated out of
<HI>truth,</HI> and the <HI>power of Religion</HI> (which is a holy
life) if you doe not harden your faces, and con∣firme
your resolutions against, <HI>supercilious vani∣ty</HI>
of such men: Whether they have any intent to
<HI>reedifie Babels ruines</HI> or no, I cannot tell (some
vehemently suspect it) sure I am, there is
such a <HI>confussion</HI> and <HI>noveltie</HI> of Language
affectated by some men of <HI>Altars, Sacrifice,
Priests, Corporiety</HI> of <HI>presence, pennance; auricular
Confession. Absolute,</HI> that is, <HI>blinde obedi∣ence;</HI>
the <HI>holy</HI> of <HI>holys;</HI> and <HI>Adoration,</HI> which
<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
must bee salved from a <HI>flat Idolatry,</HI> or at best an
empty <HI>formality</HI> by some distinction or notion that
must be ready at hand; that most people know not
what they meane, what they would have, or what
they intend to call for next.</P>
<P>Not that I am ignorant how farre <HI>pious antiquity</HI>
did use these and such like words <HI>innocently,</HI> with∣out
ill mind or meaning, and without offence to
the Church, as then times were: yet let mee tell
you: 1. Such <HI>swerving</HI> from the <HI>forme of sound
words</HI> used in the Primitive and purest times, occa∣sioned
and strengthened after errours. 2. They were
not then <HI>ingaged</HI> to mainetaine Truth against such
erroneous and pernicious Doctrines as we now are
of the <HI>reformed Church:</HI> which Doctrines are now
eagerly maintained by a proud <HI>faction,</HI> who seeke
to abuse antiquity, and patronize their owne er∣rours,
by using those names and words to other
intents, and things, than ever was dreamed of by
the Ancient Church. 3. By such <HI>dangerous symbo∣lizing</HI>
with them in words, and some outward for∣malities,
we doe but <HI>prepare</HI> our mindes, and swee∣ten
them with lesse distaste to relish their Do∣ctrines
and Tenets; and as it were in a civill way
wee complement our selves out of our Truth; gi∣ving
the adversaries strong hopes and presumpti∣ons,
as they have discovered, that wee are inclining
towards them: To bee <HI>ashamed</HI> of frequent, serious
and conscientious <HI>preaching,</HI> which was the worke
of <HI>Christ</HI> and the <HI>holy Apostles;</HI> the honour and
chiefe imployment of the <HI>Primitive and best</HI> Bi∣shops
<PB N="34" REF="21"/>
and Ministers, in all ages, as that deservedly
famous Bishop <HI>Iewell</HI> in his Apologie prooves
out of the Fathers sufficiently against the Popes,
and other idle bellyes; which count preaching as
a work below their greatnesse, as indeede it is a∣bove
their goodnesse. Is <HI>this to love the truth?</HI> To
<HI>preach</HI> ridiculous, impertinent, flattering or cor∣rupt
matter, which is the <HI>shame</HI> of the <HI>Pulpit</HI> and
<HI>foolishnesse of preaching,</HI> in good earnest; so as to
bring an infinite <HI>contempt, odium</HI> and <HI>envie</HI> upon
the Sacred function of the <HI>Ministry,</HI> that men <HI>ab∣horre</HI>
the Services of God, and daily <HI>separate</HI> by
swarmes from our Church; are these the <HI>fruites of
our love of the Truth?—Pudet haec opprobria nobis,</HI> &amp;c.
Sure there is <HI>something extreamely amisse</HI> and dis∣pleasing
to God as well as men, either in our Do∣ctrine,
or manners, or hearts, or all. Else whence
should that burthen of <HI>dishonour,</HI> those loades of
reproaches be cast upon the <HI>Clergy,</HI> which makes
them drive so heavily: and this even among Chri∣stians,
and reformed Churches; whereas naturally
all men, though otherwise barbarous, and insolent,
yet are prone to pay a speciall reverence and dou∣ble
honour to their holy men, such as are in a
more immediate neerenesse and relation to their
<HI>deitie</HI> or <HI>gods:</HI> Now <HI>truth</HI> carries a <HI>Divine Majesty</HI>
and lustre with it, casting a glory on every <HI>Moses</HI>
or <HI>Man</HI> of God, who converseth with it. The
more <HI>truth</HI> there is in any religion, the more love
and honour will arise from the professours to the
Preachers of it; if they seriously <HI>affect</HI> the one,
<PB N="35" REF="21"/>
they cannot scornefully <HI>neglect</HI> the other. God
himselfe hath long agoe taught all men, especially
<HI>Church-men</HI> in <HI>Elyes</HI> heavy doome, this lesson as
an <HI>infallible maxime</HI> in point of True honour, 1 <HI>Sam.</HI>
2. 30. <HI>Those that honour me I will honour, and those
that despise me shall be lightly regarded.</HI> Saint <HI>Paul</HI>
gives a charge to <HI>Timothy, 1 Tim.</HI> 4. 12. and to <HI>Titus,
Tit.</HI> 2. 15. both Bishops, <HI>Let no man despise thee,</HI> &amp;c.
One would think the Apostle should rather have
charged the <HI>Ephesians</HI> and <HI>Cretians</HI> not to despise
them; but the Apostle shewes the true way for Mi∣nisters,
to be Masters of mens <HI>love</HI> and <HI>affections,</HI> is
to be a holy <HI>rule</HI> and <HI>example</HI> to mens life and acti∣ons.
To <HI>Timothy, But be thou an example in word in
conversation, in love, in spirit, in faith and in pure∣nesse,</HI>
1 <HI>Tim</HI> 4. 12. To <HI>Titus, Shewing thy selfe a
patterne, Tit.</HI> 2. 7.</P>
<P>Certainely had Divines both great and small,
beene more busied in preaching and practising
those great weighty and necessary <HI>Truths,</HI> that are
<HI>able to save their owne and others soules,</HI> they would
not have had such leisure, to have beene so inven∣tive
and operative in poore beggerly toyes and
<HI>trifles,</HI> which neither bring honour nor profit to
God, themselves or others. <HI>Nothing</HI> (I say) <HI>nothing,</HI>
will <HI>restore</HI> the Church and <HI>Church-men</HI> to their
Pristine honour, love and authority in mens hearts
and minds, but a <HI>serious setting</HI> of themselves to
the study, preaching and practising of <HI>Truth</HI> and
<HI>Peace in a holy life.</HI> These, these were the Arts, these
the <HI>Policies,</HI> these the pious fraudes, and <HI>stratagems</HI>
<PB N="36" REF="22"/>
by which anciently they won peoples hearts to
love God, his truth and of themselves the witnesse
of it. To such a <HI>height</HI> of honour and <HI>extasie</HI> of
love, that they received them as <HI>Angels of God,
Embassadors from Heaven;</HI> counting them deare as
their right eyes. <HI>Humility,</HI> Piety and industry, layd
the <HI>foundation</HI> of all those magnificent structures,
dignities, titles, places, revenues, priviledges wher∣with
Church-men were anciently indowed: what
hath or is likely to wast and demolish them is
easie to conjecture. <HI>Iisdem artibus retinenda qui∣bus
olim parabantur.</HI></P>
<P>O consider then (I beseech you) how precious
a <HI>jewell,</HI> how sweete and necessary a blessing we are
like to loose by our want of love to it. <HI>Solem e mun∣do
tollunt;</HI> what the <HI>Sun</HI> is to the world, that is
Gods <HI>Truth</HI> to our soule, the light, life, joy, day
and soule of our soules. As the darkenesse, barren∣nesse,
coldnesse and deformity of the earth would
be, if the Sunne were alwayes absent from it, or
clouded to it, such will the state of our poore
soules and our Church be, if the healing <HI>wings of
the Sun of righteousnesse, Truth,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mal. 4.</NOTE> be quite removed; or
onely a <HI>winters Truth,</HI> clouded, deaded and obscu∣red
by many superstitious Doctrines and pra∣ctifes.
If (I say) such a truth content us; where
will be the chearefull light of the promises, which
now wee enjoy? where that onely <HI>rock of the
soules</HI> comfort, which no temptation can shake
or undermine, the free <HI>Iustification</HI> of our soules by
<HI>faith</HI> in the merits of Christ onely? where the
<PB N="37" REF="22"/>
sound and well grounded peace of our conscien∣ces?
where the <HI>warmth</HI> of our zeale, love and
affections to God, from the fiduciary apprehen∣sions
of his <HI>love</HI> to our soules? where will be the
ravishing <HI>joy,</HI> hopes and expectation of a bet∣ter
life? where the <HI>zealous care</HI> of leading here a
holy life? will not all these faile us, if <HI>truth</HI> doth?
and is not <HI>truth</HI> like to faile if our <HI>love</HI> doth?
Are not all those flowers and beauties of our soules
and Church <HI>heliotropia,</HI> such as have their life
and motion from the sunne? following and de∣pending
upon that <HI>glorious truth;</HI> which so much
offends weaker eyes, is so little seene or desired by
blinde, darkned and sensuall minds? If this goe,
<HI>Ickabob;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 4. 21.</NOTE> <HI>The glory is departed from our land.</HI> Our
<HI>Goshen</HI> will soone turne to an <HI>Egypt:</HI> Our <HI>fruitfull
field</HI> and <HI>Garden of God,</HI> where so many famous
Preachers, and zealous professours of Christianity
have flourished, will be changed to a <HI>barren how∣ling,
and desolate wildernesse.</HI></P>
<P>If the <HI>love</HI> of our selves moove us not; nor <HI>the
love of truth and Peace,</HI> which have happily dwelt
together a long time with us, yet let us not bee so
barbarously cruell to <HI>posterity,</HI> as to put out their
<HI>soules eyes</HI> before they can <HI>see,</HI> and deprive them of
the <HI>light</HI> of the <HI>Gospell,</HI> before they enjoy the <HI>light
of the Sunne.</HI> What can you transmit to posterity
more desireable than <HI>Truth and Peace? Paix &amp;
peu. Peace and a little,</HI> but <HI>Truth and lesse,</HI> will doe
very well, and make you and them live and dye
happily: what will your honours, lands, offices,
<PB N="38" REF="23"/>
estates, houses, names doe them good, if they be
<HI>betrayed</HI> to ignorance, superstition and slavery of
conscience, which are in the <HI>bottome</HI> and <HI>dregs</HI> of
errour and confusion.</P>
<P>O then let the first care bee to <HI>cleare,</HI> and <HI>settle
Truth among us;</HI> and then <HI>Peace;</HI> sweete and most
desireable <HI>Peace,</HI> which we have had to the <HI>envie,</HI>
wonder and astonishment of all our Neighbours,
enemies and friends. Alas! have we so <HI>long drunk
of Peace,</HI> as to become <HI>intoxicate</HI> with so sweete
wine, and now do we fall to <HI>quarrell</HI> with tongues,
pens and swords!</P>
<P>That <HI>we</HI> in this <HI>Iland</HI> are <HI>divided</HI> from all Na∣tions
is our safety under God, and by the provi∣dence
of our gracious Soveraigne: but to be <HI>divi∣ded
among our selves</HI> will be <HI>infallibly our ruine. Si
collidimur, frangimur:</HI> as <HI>two strong armes</HI> united to
one body and under <HI>one head</HI> fighting against each
other; That censure of a great <HI>Captaine</HI> and <HI>States∣man</HI>
is remarkeable which hee gives of our State.
<HI>That it is a great and strong body which will never dye,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">D. de <HI>Rohan.</HI> Interest des estates. Angle terre est un∣grand animal, qui ne mourira ja mais si lue se tue luymesme.</NOTE>
<HI>unlesse it kill it selfe.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Civili in bello trist is victoria, Civill warres</HI> can nei∣ther
merit nor expect <HI>Laurells,</HI> triumphs nor tro∣phees:
the memory and monuments of them are
best, when buried in oblivion; <HI>victory it selfe is sad,</HI>
and ashamed of it selfe; <HI>weeping,</HI> dejected and blu∣shing
with its owne blood unnaturally and barba∣rously
spilt; as having fought not so much against
enemies as <HI>humanity;</HI> not so much conquering o∣thers,
as wasting and destroying it selfe.
<Q><PB N="39" REF="23"/>
<L>—Pax una triumphis</L>
<L>Innumeris potior.—</L></Q>
One faire and spotlesse <HI>Lilly of peace</HI> is a greater or∣nament
to a Princes Diadem, than to have it be∣set
round with many red <HI>Roses of bloody triumphs;</HI>
especially in civill, which are the most sanguinary
wars. O then let us not so easily <HI>abandon</HI> so great, so
precious, so hardly recoverable a blessing, if once
it be lost. The Orator said well: <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.
Any rash hand or
furious head may inflict a <HI>wound,</HI> or <HI>kindle a fire,</HI>
but it's God alone, who can <HI>heale up the breaches,</HI> or
extinquish the flames of a state or Church. The
<HI>miserable spectacles</HI> of other countries and Chur∣ches,
do they not, as <HI>foyles,</HI> sufficiently set forth
the beauty and lovelinesse of this <HI>Iewell of Peace?</HI>
O then let us all take up thoughts, words, counsels,
resolutions, prayers for <HI>Peace:</HI> away with all <HI>bitter∣nesse,
strife, malice, jealousies,</HI> and all those <HI>divelish
maximes</HI> of severing the <HI>Interests</HI> of the Prince and
the people as inconsistent; whereas rightly consi∣dered
they are, as the head with the body; united,
both are safe and firme; severed, both inevitably
ruine. <HI>Divide &amp; regnare desine: Devide</HI> them and
you <HI>destroy</HI> them. <HI>Love and union are the mutuall
safety of Prince and people.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Counsells of Truth and Peace,</HI> like light and fruitfull
showers, descend from above from Heaven, from
God: but <HI>falsity</HI> and <HI>dissension,</HI> like tempestuous
vapours and fiery exhalations, come from the
earth, from the divellish hearts, designes and pra∣ctises
of men.</P>
<P><PB N="40" REF="24"/>
O consider then (as I know you doe) how <HI>large
afield,</HI> how ample a province the mercy of God,
the favour of our King, the love of your Country
hath put into your hand, where to shew your <HI>love</HI>
of God, his <HI>truth,</HI> worship and religion; your <HI>loyal∣ty</HI>
to your King, his Throne, dignity and succes∣sion;
your <HI>fidelity</HI> and zeale to your Country, its
peace, liberty and prosperity. How great a <HI>disser∣vice</HI>
you must do them all (besides your selves in
particular) if you faile or slaken by any meanes in
your <HI>love to these</HI> two, <HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>Peace.</HI></P>
<P>Imagine with your selves you heare daily,
your <HI>Noble and famous progenitors</HI> (who <HI>being
dead yet speake,</HI> by those blessings of <HI>Truth</HI> and
<HI>Peace,</HI> which by their studies, prayers and endea∣vours
they have bequeathed to you) <HI>Imagine</HI>
(I say) these calling earnestly upon you all, <HI>O love
the Truth and Peace. Shame</HI> not our names, and your
selves by being wretchedly negligent of what
we esteemed the most <HI>precious Iewels,</HI> the honour
and happinesse of our times: which were dearer
to us than our lives: which we purchased for you
with our blood, with infinite expenses, hazards
and sufferings.</P>
<P><HI>Thinke</HI> you here the <HI>joynt prayers</HI> and importu∣nities
of all estates in the Kingdome, the <HI>Nobles,</HI>
the <HI>Gentry,</HI> the <HI>Commons;</HI> your parents, wives, chil∣dren,
friends, alliances, neighbours, all with <HI>one
voice</HI> calling to <HI>you, Pacem te possimus omnes. O love
the truth and Peace,</HI> and by your love preserve them
for us. <HI>Betray</HI> not us and your selves, to the dark∣nesse
<PB N="41" REF="24"/>
of errours, to the miseries of warre. Be you
as <HI>sunnes and shields</HI> to us, and the commonwealth:
Your populous <HI>Cities and Townes,</HI> your stately
houses, your fruitefull fields, your pleasant gar∣dens,
your costly cloathes, your plentifull tables,
your ancient <HI>liberties</HI> and Noble immunities,
wherewith <HI>above all subjects in the world</HI> you are in∣vested
and honour'd, all joyne in this voyce, <HI>O love
the truth and peace:</HI> which affords you all these
sweet enjoyments and Noble ornaments of life.
All complaints, all grievances, all petitions may
be resolved into this lesson, <HI>Love the truth and peace,</HI>
in so doing you shall <HI>remedy, releeve and satisfie</HI>
all.</P>
<P>O have a care then, that <HI>truth</HI> as the <HI>pillar of
fire</HI> may goe before us to enlighten and direct
our way to the <HI>heavenly Canaan;</HI> and <HI>Peace</HI> as the
<HI>pillar of the cloud</HI> may over-shadow, and refresh
us in our travailes; through the tedious <HI>wildernesse</HI>
of this life.</P>
<P>The way to <HI>peace</HI> is by the <HI>paths of truth, Never
hope to recover and settle your former peace, unlesse you
returne to your first love of the truth.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Truth</HI> is but one, as the <HI>Center,</HI> and drawes all
mindes to an <HI>unity,</HI> which tend to it. <HI>Errours</HI> and
falsities are <HI>various</HI> and full of crossings enterfi∣rings,
and contentions both with <HI>truth</HI> and <HI>them∣selves:</HI>
as severall <HI>Cards in a Map,</HI> whose lines
drawne out infinitely crosse, cut, and thwart each
other.</P>
<P>Here give me leave by way of short digression,
<PB N="42" REF="25"/>
in so great and publique an Assembly, to recom∣mend
to your favour, the noble endeavours of two
<HI>great</HI> and <HI>publique Spirits,</HI> who have laboured much
for <HI>Truth and Peace,</HI> I meane, <HI>Commenius,</HI> and
<HI>Duraeus:</HI> both famous for their learning, piety
and integrity, and not unknowne, I am sure by the
fame of their Works, to many of this Honourable,
learned and pious Assembly.</P>
<P>The one hath laid a faire designe and founda∣tion
for the raising up a <HI>Structure of Truth,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Dur<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s.</NOTE> Humane
and Divine, of excellent use to all man-kinde, for
the easinesse and exquisitenesse of attaining the
true knowledge of things.</P>
<P>The other hath long studied,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Cousmenius.</NOTE> and with great
paines, endeavoured and well advanced the <HI>peace</HI>
and unity of the <HI>reformed Churches</HI> (a blessing that
cannot be purchased at too dearea a rate) whereun∣to
hee hath the suffrages and assistance of many
learned Divines, and some of our owne, especially
the <HI>reverend Bishop of Salisbury,</HI> as you may see in
his letters to him, and his late tractate, <HI>De pace
Ecclesiastica,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>But alas, both these <HI>noble plants</HI> (to the infinite
shame and reproach of the present age, to the losse
and detriment of the future) a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> like to <HI>wither</HI> to a
barrennesse for want of publique incouragement
and aid to goe on in so noble, great and usefull un∣dertakings;
I leave it to your <HI>Wisedomes,</HI> at your
leysure to consider, whether it were not worthy
the name and honour of this State and Church, to
invite these men to you, to see and weigh their no∣ble
<PB N="43" REF="25"/>
and excellent designes; to give them all pub∣like
ayde and incouragement to goe on and per∣fect
so happy Workes, which tend so much to the
advancing of <HI>Truth,</HI>
and <HI>Peace.</HI><NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Whereunto if it shall please God to encline any of your thoughts for the effectuall promoting of so commenda∣ble purpos<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, notwithstanding the distances whereat they now are, the one being in <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣land,</HI> the other in <HI>De<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>marke,</HI> yet there is a faire, easie, and safe way of addresses to them both, opened by the industry and fidel<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ty of M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartli<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</HI> whose house is in Dukes place in <HI>London,</HI> a Gentleman who hath beene a constant furthe∣rer, and great coadjutor wit<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> them both, in their Work s: who hath correspondence with them; whose learning, pi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y and unwearied industry to∣wards the publike good, are so well knowne to the learned world, and many of your selves as well as to me, that he needs not the farther testimony of my Pen.</NOTE></P>
<P>But to return to your particular and neerer <HI>concernements;</HI> If <HI>you love your selves,</HI> your relations, wives, chil∣dren, houses, lands, li∣berti<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, lives and ho∣nours; if you <HI>love</HI> your King, your Country, your Church, your cō∣sciences, your soules, your Saviour, your God; <HI>Love the truth and Peace;</HI> but <HI>heartily, sin∣cerely, couragiously, con∣stantly.</HI> Let your <HI>faith</HI> in the <HI>truth,</HI> worke and shew it selfe by an active <HI>love of the truth.</HI> Shall the Adversaries of our <HI>Truth</HI> and <HI>Peace,</HI> be so bold, vigilant and <HI>de∣sperately active,</HI> for the bringing in of their shad∣dowes, lyes, paintings and adulteries of Truth and Religion; and shall we be cold, remisse and timerous? Shall they as <HI>Assasinates,</HI> be prodigall of their owne and our bloods, and shall we be spa∣ring of our words, estates or persons? <HI>Hoc agite.</HI>
<PB N="44" REF="26"/>
Doe then <HI>Gods</HI> businesse, and the <HI>Kings,</HI> and the <HI>Countries,</HI> and in them all your owne. Doe them worthy of <HI>your selves,</HI> worthy of the honour of this <HI>Church and State,</HI> worthy the memory and re∣nowne of your <HI>Ancestors,</HI> worthy the expectation of the <HI>world,</HI> both at home and abroad; the eyes of all <HI>Christendome</HI> being upon you especially the <HI>Re∣formed Churches,</HI> whose hopes and prayers meete in
you. Doe them worthy the Majesty and favour of our <HI>gracious King;</HI> worthy of the <HI>truth,</HI> worthy of the glory of our <HI>God,</HI> and great <HI>Redeemer:</HI> At once shew yourselves good <HI>Subjects,</HI> good <HI>Patriots,</HI> good <HI>Counsellors,</HI> good <HI>Men,</HI> good <HI>Christians.</HI></P>
<P>You have long enjoyed <HI>Truth and Peace, therfore love them;</HI> No Nation under Heaven, hath more cause, and will be lesse excusable, <HI>therefore love them;</HI> none hath had a clearer light of <HI>Truth,</HI> and a greater length of <HI>Peace, therefore love them;</HI> you and yours have long thrived by them, <HI>therefore love them:</HI> you have <HI>Fasted</HI> and <HI>Prayed</HI> for the preserva∣tion of them, <HI>therefore love them:</HI> you are this day
solemnely to renew your <HI>Covenant</HI> with God in the holy Sacrament, the <HI>Seale of Gods love</HI> to you, and yours to him, <HI>therefore love the truth and peace,</HI> for they are Gods. And upon the <HI>heate</HI> and <HI>sacred flames,</HI> which by this dayes duties possesse your affections, take up (I beseech you) serious <HI>resolu∣tions,</HI> and make tacit <HI>vowes</HI> in your selves to God, that you will <HI>love the truth and peace,</HI> and by all
<HI>lawfull wayes</HI> (for other they neitherneed, nor will allow) seeke to advance them.</P>
<P><PB N="45" REF="26"/>
None are fit and <HI>prepared to receive,</HI> but such as have hearts <HI>filled</HI> with this <HI>love;</HI> none will have the comfort of <HI>worthy receiving,</HI> but such as daily in∣crease, and <HI>persevere in this love.</HI></P>
<P>For Conclusion, I will use the <HI>last and weigh∣tiest argument in the world,</HI> which raised the victo∣rious soule of that great Apostle Saint <HI>Paul,</HI> to such an invincible <HI>patience</HI> and unwearied <HI>Active∣nesse</HI> for Gods glory and the Churches good, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 14. <HI>O let the love of Christ constraine you;</HI> that free, preventive, transcendent <HI>love;</HI> that humbled, sorrowing, sweating, bleeding, cry∣ing, crucified dying <HI>love,</HI> which this day is pre∣sented to you, who <HI>loved</HI> our soules more than
his owne <HI>life: Greater love can no man expresse,</HI> greater <HI>motive</HI> to love can no man desire.</P>
<P><HI>Quid amplius pro se facere aut pati potuit, quam pro te &amp; fecit &amp; passus est Christus?</HI> What could Christ have done, or suffered more, if hee had beene to <HI>redeeme himselfe,</HI> then hee hath both done and suffered to <HI>ransome</HI> thee and me. Con∣tent
to make himselfe the object of his Fathers <HI>wrath</HI> (whom he infinitely loved) that he might
<HI>procure our peace.</HI></P>
<P>O what shall wee render to him againe for this <HI>excessive love;</HI> but an unfained <HI>love</HI> of him and his Church, his Truth and Glory, an undaunted zeale for his Honour and Worship, for the purity and peace of his Church?<NOTE PLACE="marg">Zach. 8. 16.</NOTE> <HI>These are the things you shall doe, speake yee every man the truth to his neighbour.
Execute the judgement of Truth &amp; Peace in your gates.</HI>
<PB N="46" REF="27"/>
That so it may be fulfilled on you, and us all which the Prophet prayes, <HI>Esay. 26. 2. The gates of mercy and peace here, of glory and happinesse hereafter may be opened, so that the righteous nation which keepeth the truth may enter therein.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="27"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

