<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Megaleia theou, Gods great demonstrations and demands of iustice, mercy, and humility set forth in a sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, at their solemn fast, before their first sitting, April 30, 1660 / by John Gauden ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A42490</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing G364</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R16267</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">11851798</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 11851798</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">49943</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42490)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49943)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 31:4)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Megaleia theou, Gods great demonstrations and demands of iustice, mercy, and humility set forth in a sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, at their solemn fast, before their first sitting, April 30, 1660 / by John Gauden ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[10], 66 [i.e. 64] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by J. Best for Andrew Crook ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1660.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>First two words of title transliterated from Greek.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE><NOTE>Marginal notes.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>God --  Attributes --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Sermons, English.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A42490">
<STC T="W">G364</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">11851798</BIBNO>
<VID>49943</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>ΜΕΓΑΛΕΙΑ ΘΕΟΥ Gods great DEMONSTRATIONS AND DEMANDS OF Iustice, Mercy and Humility, Set forth in a SERMON PREACHED Before the Honourable House of Com∣mons, at their Solemn Fast, before their first sitting, <HI>April</HI> 30. 1660. By <HI>JOHN GAƲDEN,</HI> D. D.</P>
<BIBL>Prov. 21.3.</BIBL>
<Q>To do Justice and Judgement is more acceptable to the Lord than sacrifice.</Q>
<Q><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</Q>
<BIBL>Clem. Alex.</BIBL>
<Q>Apud nos quo religiosior quis{que} eo justior.</Q>
<BIBL>Minuts, Fel. de Christ.</BIBL>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>J. Best,</HI> for <HI>Andrew Crook,</HI> at the Green-Dragon in St. <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard. 1660.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE Honorable the Speaker, and other Members of the House of COMMONS,</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">N</SEG>O sooner had I done my duty to <HI>Gods commands</HI> and yours <HI>(Honorable and worthy)</HI> but <HI>(blessed be God)</HI> you presently applied to do <HI>your duty</HI> to <HI>God,</HI> the <HI>King</HI> and <HI>your Country</HI> with such <HI>Justice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>Humility,</HI> that you have by an <HI>astonishing joy</HI> revived the <HI>sunk spirits</HI> of all just, merciful, and humble men in these three Kingdoms, who had for many years <HI>been</HI> sorely de∣pressed and almost <HI>despaired</HI> under the <HI>importune injuries</HI> of some <HI>insolent and proud Masters;</HI> who with <HI>Cesar</HI> or <HI>Pompey</HI> were impatient of any superior or equal; yea with <HI>Lucifer and Antichrist</HI> they exalted <HI>themselves above all that were called God</HI> in the <HI>Bri∣tish Honour and Authority;</HI> advancing their unjust and <HI>merciless ambition</HI> so high, that at last it fell, not by force so much, as its own weight, and that <HI>just con∣fusion</HI> which God brought upon those <HI>Babel-builders;</HI> whose <HI>foolish building</HI> had indeed many <HI>pinacles of fanatick opinions</HI> and projects daily starting up, yet but one <HI>great Tower</HI> or <HI>Mole,</HI> whose <HI>moorish</HI> or <HI>sandy foundation</HI> was <HI>tumult</HI> and <HI>violence;</HI> its <HI>line</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
and <HI>measure, fancy</HI> and <HI>providence;</HI> its <HI>materials,</HI> the lives and estates of its <HI>Countrymen;</HI> its <HI>cement,</HI> the blood both of Kings, Priests, and People.</P>
<P>§. The gracious and glorious God, who <HI>alone doth wonders,</HI> hath by the <HI>Justice, Mercy and Humility</HI> of the two Houses of Parliament (added to the most <HI>renowned Generals</HI> humble valour, and <HI>loyal cou∣rage</HI>) soon made <HI>Nehustan</HI> of those brazen Ser∣pents and Idols which were made up of <HI>subtilty</HI> and <HI>hypocrisie, violence</HI> and <HI>impudence.</HI></P>
<P N="7"><HI>7.</HI> In a few days (even before I could print what I had preached) we have lived to see that holy Motto under the <HI>Kings Arms</HI> made good; <HI>Exurgat Deus, dissipentur inimici: Let God arise and his enemies shall be scattered,</HI> Psal. <HI>68.1.</HI> The royal <HI>(Dieu &amp; mon Droit) God and my right,</HI> hath like <HI>Moses his Serpent</HI> devoured the Serpents and rods of those Ma∣gicians, who usurped all things, yet nothing more falsly and unjustly than that Inscription <HI>Deus no∣biscum,</HI> God with us; when indeed they had neither <HI>his Word,</HI> nor the <HI>Laws of the land</HI> with them: with the like vain and arrogant ostentation did <HI>Dionysius</HI> boast of the gods <HI>good will</HI> and <HI>approbation,</HI> when after his sacrilegious <HI>pillaging one of their Temples,</HI> he had a very <HI>fair gale of wind</HI> to carry him and his booty home by sea.</P>
<P>§. Certainly, nothing is more <HI>remote from Gods gracious presence,</HI> and the <HI>power of godliness</HI> than that brutal <HI>power,</HI> and inordinate <HI>might,</HI> which is carried on with penal <HI>prosperities</HI> and <HI>successes,</HI> but without any <HI>right,</HI> as to <HI>Law</HI> and <HI>Justice,</HI> which are the only rules and <HI>boundaries</HI> of <HI>good conscience,</HI> also the soul and life of all <HI>righteous Government;</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
void of which the other is but <HI>(cadaverosa poten∣tia)</HI> a putid carkass of prevalent <HI>usurpation,</HI> which stinks in the Nostrils of God and all good men.</P>
<P>§. But <HI>You even You</HI> are those <HI>True Worthies</HI> who by your <HI>just, loyal</HI> and <HI>humble agnition</HI> of, and <HI>submission</HI> to the Kings <HI>lawful Authority,</HI> have made <HI>Mercy and truth meet together, yea righte∣ousness and peace kiss each other</HI>: You have fulfil∣led in the affirmative that old and ambiguous verse (which I remember to have heard many years before our sad troubles) which ends with <HI>Nullus;</HI> In which Negative the time-serving <HI>Astrologasters</HI> and others strongly fancied, they found a fatal period of the <HI>Bri∣tish Monarchy,</HI> at least of the <HI>Stuartian royal family,</HI> O how must it make <HI>those Diviners mad,</HI> to see (what I long ago hoped would be the meaning of it) that King who was made and esteemed as <HI>Nullus,</HI> (a per∣secuted, expulsed, and as much as lay in humane ma∣lice, a <HI>nullified King</HI>) to see him <HI>reign</HI> as surely and gloriously as any of those royal Predecessors did, who under the emblems of other words made up that strange verse.</P>
<P>§. To which so benign an <HI>interpretation</HI> and <HI>event,</HI> there wanted not some <HI>providential omens</HI> and <HI>sig∣natures;</HI> as first <HI>that star</HI> which appeared a little af∣ter noon on the day of the Kings birth,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>May 20.</HI> Anno <HI>630.</HI></NOTE> of which there were many eye witnesses in <HI>London</HI> and <HI>Westminster,</HI> Next were those <HI>meddals of silver</HI> which were then <HI>coy¦ned,</HI> with this Inscription, <HI>Hactenus Anglorum nulli,</HI> to denote that Prince to be the <HI>Nonsuch,</HI> who alone had the glory to be born <HI>Heir apparent</HI> to these three <HI>British Kingdoms;</HI> Nor was his signal preservation after <HI>Worster-fight</HI> a small pledge of Gods <HI>special
<PB REF="4"/>
protection,</HI> whose usual methods are to build up to an unwonted height and <HI>conspicuity of glory,</HI> there where he lays the deepest foundation of <HI>earthly af∣fliction.</HI></P>
<P>§. I confess I cannot sufficiently (with you and all good men) admire the wonderful <HI>revolutions</HI> and <HI>intricate ridles</HI> of Gods <HI>providence;</HI> punishing us justly for our sins, yet relieving us mercifully from our sufferings: We are yet in <HI>extacies</HI> of <HI>joy</HI> and <HI>wonder,</HI> as those <HI>that dream;</HI> hardly believing the strange <HI>undeserved</HI> and unexpected dispensati∣ons of God toward us; in which he hath made that pre∣cious <HI>stone</HI> which some <HI>builders</HI> refused, to become the <HI>corner,</HI> the <HI>capital,</HI> and <HI>crown-stone of the building;</HI> the only <HI>center</HI> and <HI>stability</HI> of that <HI>Arch,</HI> in which the loyalty and love, the joy and hopes of all <HI>good Subjects,</HI> and true <HI>English-Prote∣stants</HI> do meet and six.</P>
<P>May you go on prosperously and unanimously un∣der the <HI>Banner of the most high God</HI> to compleat your religious, loyal, just and valiant Counsels; not only to establish his <HI>Majesties Throne,</HI> and our civil rights in Truth, Mercy, and Peace; but also to cleanse and repair the <HI>Temple,</HI> the <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>house of the living God,</HI> whose miserable dilapidations, and sor∣did <HI>ruines</HI> in <HI>doctrine,</HI> devotion, <HI>discipline, order</HI> and <HI>government</HI> are such, that you cannot but pity to see <HI>all things sacred covered with dust;</HI> and the Ministery of the Church both <HI>Bishops and Presby∣ters</HI> almost buried with the rubbish of <HI>factions, con∣fusions, dissentions and despiciencies.</HI></P>
<P>I confess this Church-work ought (as the <HI>Kingdom</HI> of God,) to be first in every good Christians intenti∣on,
<PB REF="4"/>
(as no doubt it was and is in yours) But you are not to be <HI>blamed,</HI> by any unseasonable <HI>severitie,</HI> if, as to point of execution, you first applied your selves, in the present distress of our times and affaires, to <HI>settle</HI> and <HI>secure</HI> as to the <HI>main,</HI> those things which belonged to your civil rights, and National peace. The <HI>exigents</HI> or <HI>extreamities</HI> of which, not bearing any delayes, do sufficiently justifie your indeavors, to <HI>preserve</HI> the ship of the State, in which the <HI>Church is imbarqued,</HI> which being almost Ship-wrackt and sincking, it had been a very <HI>preposterous zeal,</HI> to have left the vessel to have <HI>contended</HI> with the <HI>Rocks</HI> and <HI>Sands,</HI> by a <HI>superdevout diligence to save</HI> the <HI>lading,</HI> or goods in it; Alas we had been much to seek for a reformed Church, in a ruined State.</P>
<P>Your discreet and orderly diligence <HI>took</HI> the right <HI>method,</HI> in making way for religion, by civil <HI>justice;</HI> nor need you fear the dictates, frownes and censures of any <HI>Anastarchusses,</HI> whose piety like <HI>Jacobs</HI> might hope to have supplanted this just necessary and honest policy, of restoring our civil laws, and royal authority, by which our Religion, as Cristian and reformed, was best <HI>esta∣blished.</HI></P>
<P>§. The setling or reforming of religion; in all its <HI>duties</HI> and <HI>devotions, discipline</HI> and <HI>decencies,</HI> together with its <HI>order,</HI> and <HI>Government,</HI> is a work which requires not only time, but that leisure which is attended with a <HI>calme</HI> and steddy <HI>posture</HI> of civil affaires: Men cannot build Gods Temple till they have first washed their hands and purged the land of <HI>inno∣cent blood.</HI> No prudent piety can think such a storme as we were in, was a meet season for Church <HI>reforma∣tion;</HI>
<PB REF="5"/>
It would only fit those who might hope to fish <HI>best</HI> for their <HI>parties</HI> &amp; opinions, in <HI>troubled waters,</HI> knowing their projects and models to be less consist∣ent with the true interests and pristine welfare of this <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State;</HI> doubtless they must have made strange work of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>reformation,</HI> before ever they had owned, and restored the Master-<HI>builder,</HI> the King, who is supream <HI>Governour</HI> of it under Christ, as to all extern order and Authority. We hope and pray, that God will shortly give both his <HI>Majesty,</HI> his <HI>Parliaments</HI> and his loyall <HI>people,</HI> such rest on every side, as may be most apt for those sacred and serious <HI>concernments</HI> of the <HI>Church</HI> and true <HI>Religion,</HI> which require first <HI>Justice,</HI> as to the rights of <HI>Christ</HI> and his <HI>Church,</HI> both <HI>Bishops, Presbyters</HI> and <HI>People;</HI> Secondly they require <HI>mercy,</HI> as to that remission, moderation and condescention, in things not necessary, to the being and well <HI>being</HI> of religion, which either tender consciences, or weak, but humble and harmless Christians do require, yea and expect, agreeable to Christs care of his little ones, and the A∣postles regard to weak brethren, yea and the Kings gracious expressions touching his regard to such, that they may not be needlesly offended, superciliously <HI>de∣spised,</HI> or <HI>rigorously oppressed, in matters that are</HI> neither of faith nor <HI>morality.</HI></P>
<P>§. Lastly, Religious <HI>composures</HI> require an <HI>unfein∣ed humility,</HI> and self <HI>denying,</HI> as the proper rule and measure, and of all Church-work, that nothing may swell out, beyond the <HI>plumline</HI> of <HI>verity</HI> and <HI>charity,</HI> order and decency, <HI>use</HI> and <HI>edification,</HI> either in the <HI>substances,</HI> or <HI>circumstances</HI> of Religion, nor yet in the controversies of it.</P>
<P><PB REF="5"/>§. In all which blessed counsels and endeavours, there will be need and use of the assistance of the best heads, the honestest hearts; and the softest hands which the Church of England affords; not only in the Nobility and Gentry, the Lords and Commons, but also among the Clergy, who are no doubt the Angels or Intelligences most proper, for those motions and that spheare of Religion.</P>
<P>But we hope by the good hand of our good God, up∣on his Majesty and your loyal counsels, for the best of blessings, a wise constitution, and well ordered admi∣nistration of religion, both as <HI>Christian</HI> and reformed, which will be the greatest glory and stability of all estates. As you have given to <HI>Cesar the things that are Cesars,</HI> so no doubt you will be <HI>ready to give to God the things that are Gods</HI>: In which just and humble retributions, you will both shew mercy to many thousands of souls, and obtain mercies for your own; for which ends as you have the prayers and thanks of all worthy persons, so you shall never want mine, whose freedome in speaking and writing I presume your sound minds can bear, as abhoring to keep your Mini∣sters like Parots in a cage, as at no great charge, so only for the pleasure to hear them speak; Your honor is, that you hear and know, and do the will of God; in which that you may enjoy his eternal rewards, is the Prayer of</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Your humble servant in Christ,</HI> I. GAƲDEN.</SIGNED>
<DATE>May 12. 1660.</DATE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>Books written by Dr. <HI>Gauden,</HI> and sold by <HI>Andrew Crook,</HI> at the green Dragon in St. <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard.</HEAD>
<P N="1">1. <HI>HIeraspistes,</HI> A Defence for the <HI>Ministry</HI> and <HI>Mi∣nisters</HI> of the Church of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. Three Sermons preached on publick occasions.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>Funerals</HI> made <HI>Cordials,</HI> in a Sermon preached at the Interment of the Corps of <HI>Robert Rich,</HI> Heir apparent to the Earldom of <HI>Warwick.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4. A sermon preached at the Funeral of Dr. <HI>Ralph Broun∣rig</HI> Bishop of <HI>Excester (Decemb.</HI> 17. 1659.) with an ac∣count of his <HI>Life and Death,</HI></P>
<P N="5">5. A <HI>Petitionary Remonstrace</HI> in the behalf of many thou∣sand Ministers and Scholars.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: <HI>sive Medicastri.</HI> Slight healers of publique hurts, set forth in a Sermon Preached in St. <HI>Pauls</HI> Church, <HI>London,</HI> before the right honorable Lord Mayor, Lord General, Al∣dermen, Common-Council, &amp; Companies of the honorable City of <HI>London, Febr.</HI> 28. 1659. being a day of Solemn thanksgiving unto God, for restoring the Secluded Members of Parliament to the house of Commons, (And for pre∣serving the City) as a Door of Hope thereby opened to the fulness and freedom of future Parliaments: The most probable means under God for healing the Hurts, and recovering the health of these three Brittish King∣doms.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="6"/>
<HEAD>Magna Dei postulata. Gods great Demonstrations and Demands. Set forth in A Sermon preached at a Solemn Fast
<DATE><HI>April</HI> 30. 1660.</DATE>
before the Honorable House of Commons, Upon
<BIBL>MICAH 6.8.</BIBL><Q>He hath shewed thee, O man, what is good; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do Iustice, to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</Q></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Am not so ignorant of my <HI>infirmi∣ties,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Preface.</NOTE> (Right Honorable and Be∣loved) as to have adventured on so great a <HI>province,</HI> before so <HI>noble an Assembly,</HI> in such an im∣portant time, and on so short warning; if my obedience to Gods call in your commands had not swayed more with me than any confidence of my own <HI>sufficiency,</HI> whose greatest <HI>ambition</HI> is to <HI>walk humbly with my God</HI> in the <HI>amplest services</HI> I were able to do for his <HI>glory,</HI> his <HI>Churches peace,</HI> and my <HI>Countries welfare.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="2" REF="7"/><NOTE PLACE="marg">The great and publique im∣portance of this Parlia∣ment,</NOTE>§. I well understand the great importance of this <HI>Parliamentary Convention</HI> as to the peace and <HI>setling</HI> of this <HI>Church and State</HI>; all things sacred and civil are imbarqued in your counsels, and ad∣ventured on your <HI>Justice</HI> and <HI>Mercy,</HI> your <HI>piety</HI> and <HI>Humility,</HI> your <HI>Equanimity</HI> and <HI>Moderation.</HI> You, under God, are the <HI>Ark</HI> in which the wea∣ther-beaten and scattered remains of our <HI>Religion, Laws, Estates, Liberties, Peace, Honors</HI> and <HI>Lives</HI> are deposited; so much of them as hath escaped the <HI>tedious tempest</HI> and the <HI>terrible deluge</HI> of our <HI>sad troubles</HI> and <HI>confusions</HI> these last score of years; in which the <HI>windows of heaven (the just wrath of God)</HI> and the <HI>fountains of the great deep (the lusts and passions of mens evil hearts)</HI> have met together to punish our sins.</P>
<P>§. You are looked upon as <HI>Noah</HI> and his <HI>family, (semen novi orbis)</HI> a <HI>seed</HI> and <HI>nursery</HI> of true <HI>Christi∣an Protestants,</HI> of <HI>right English Gentlemen,</HI> in which there may yet be a blessing; you (with the other <HI>Right Honorable House of Peers</HI>) are the hoped <HI>Repairers</HI> of the vaste breaches made upon our <HI>Laws,</HI> and the <HI>Restorers</HI> of our <HI>Reformed Religi∣on,</HI> so miserably deformed, defamed and almost quite desolated, as to any beauty, order, and anity.</P>
<P>§. You are the <HI>center</HI> in which all our secular Votes and hopes do meet; or rather you are the <HI>circumference, orbe</HI> and <HI>circle,</HI> in which they are all contained, that you may draw them all to their right point, and proper center, of fixed duty to God and Man: You are the <HI>answer</HI> of many <HI>prayers</HI> and <HI>tears</HI>; God forbid you should miscarry: yea,
<PB N="3" REF="7"/>
as St. <HI>Ambrose</HI> said to <HI>Monica</HI> of her Son St. <HI>Austin</HI> (while he was yet debauched in both <HI>morals</HI> and <HI>in∣tellectuals,</HI> in opinion and practice) I am not a little confident you will not miscarry; nay I am sure you cannot <HI>miscarry</HI> if you steer your <HI>counsels</HI> and <HI>acti∣ons</HI> by the <HI>compass of this Text, Doing Justice, loving Mercy, and walking humbly with your God. Pride, cruelty</HI> and <HI>Injustice</HI> have been and will be our un∣doing.</P>
<P>§. It will be your wisdom to look to this <HI>cyno∣sure</HI> or <HI>benign constellation</HI>; in which <HI>Law</HI> and <HI>Go∣spel, Justice</HI> and <HI>Mercy</HI> are joyned with <HI>humility</HI>; in these, your inward peace of conscience no less than your outward comforts, together with your honor and all our safeties are conjoyned. Beware you mistake not blazing meteors of partial and <HI>fanatick interests,</HI> for the fixed stars of our <HI>firma∣ment,</HI> our <HI>fundamental laws,</HI> and <HI>publique welfare,</HI> lest the hand of God break out <HI>against you,</HI> as it hath done against others, and cut you off by a fur∣ther <HI>abscission,</HI> as parts of desperate and incurable distempers, which are to be smitten no more by the fruitless stroaks and superfluous severities of a chastising Father, or an <HI>healing</HI> and <HI>searching Chy∣rurgeon,</HI> but with the <HI>wounds</HI> of such <HI>enemies,</HI> and <HI>cruel ones,</HI> as seek to cut us off from being a <HI>Refor∣med Church,</HI> and a <HI>Renowned Nation</HI> under hea∣ven.</P>
<P>I lately in a great (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) and <HI>publick Assem∣bly</HI> set forth the <HI>hurts and slight healings</HI> of the <HI>Daughter of my people,</HI> by a faithful scrutiny, and just severity, with which all honest hearts were af∣fected: I now bring a <HI>vial of Balm from Gilead</HI>
<PB N="4" REF="8"/>
very precious and soveraign, wherewith to present you, who are by a <HI>miraculous Providence,</HI> and the <HI>wise conduct of a modern Heroe,</HI> called by God, and chosen by men to be our <HI>Physitians</HI>: Not that I <HI>am to teach Senators wisdom</HI>; but I know you will not disdain to <HI>learn of God</HI>; for from the <HI>tree of life,</HI> his holy Word, together with the <HI>tree of know∣ledge</HI> of good and evill, (your own experience) this <HI>divine balsom</HI> is distilled;</P>
<P N="1">1. There is a <HI>Justice of expiation,</HI> to break off our sins by <HI>repentance,</HI> which is <HI>Debitum Deo &amp; animae,</HI> a debt to God and our souls.</P>
<P N="2">2. A <HI>Justice of compensation,</HI> by meet repairing our <HI>publique injuries</HI>; which is <HI>Debitum bonis,</HI> a debt due to all good men.</P>
<P N="3">3. A <HI>Justice of Vindication,</HI> to confirm our laws by inflicting such just <HI>penalties</HI> and restraints as some mens insolencies have deserved, which is <HI>debitum impiis,</HI> a debt you owe to wicked men, yea to all men, that they may hear and fear, and do no more <HI>presumptuously.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, Yet lest we should be terrified with the name of <HI>Justice</HI> only (which no men have more cause to dread, than those who once cried <HI>loudest Justice, Justice</HI>) there is the <HI>allay of Mercy,</HI> as to all such <HI>moderation, compassion</HI> and <HI>tenderness,</HI> by way of <HI>pardon, indempnity</HI> and <HI>oblivion,</HI> in order to close and compose our breaches (for <HI>praestat motos com∣ponere fluctus</HI>) as may not only best suit with your pitty and compassion to the publique, but most be∣come the humanity of <HI>Countrimen,</HI> and the <HI>charity</HI> of <HI>Christians</HI> to each other, without any reproach to the <HI>justice, piety</HI> and <HI>honor</HI> of the <HI>Nation.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="8"/>Thirdly, There is added the root and crown of all <HI>vertues</HI> and <HI>graces, Humility</HI>; which makes you surest of Gods <HI>acceptation</HI> and <HI>benediction</HI>; as to all your counsels and actions, your fastings and prayers, your sacred and civil endeavors: For <HI>Hu∣mility</HI> is the salt which must be mingled with every <HI>Sacrifice,</HI> a sweet <HI>perfume</HI> that must attend every <HI>Oblation</HI>; being the glory of all humane and <HI>divine perfections,</HI> the security of <HI>Justice,</HI> and sanctuary of <HI>Mercy</HI>; for from <HI>pride,</HI> and <HI>inordinate valuing</HI> of mens selves, come all those ambitious discon∣tents and contentions, for getting more than men have, or indeed deserve, of <HI>estate</HI> and <HI>power</HI>; hence they are betrayed to all those cruelties and con∣fusions, which we have not only read and heard, but to our cost both seen and felt in <HI>humane affairs,</HI> and never more than in those of our own Coun∣try.</P>
<P>§. If you intend to <HI>walk with God,</HI> and hope that God should go along with you; you must not only (<HI>vos totos subigere, sed &amp; in nihilum redigere,</HI> as <HI>Calvin</HI> on the place) <HI>deny,</HI> but so far utterly <HI>re∣nounce</HI> and annihilate your selves, as not to trust in or to seek your selves, but the <HI>living God</HI>; the less you lean to your own understandings,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 23.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> and the more you attend (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) the divine dictates of <HI>Justice, Mercy,</HI> and <HI>Humility</HI> (without Pharisaick <HI>boastings,</HI> popular <HI>complyings,</HI> and Popish <HI>presumptions</HI>) the more blessed you will be of God, and the greater blessing to your Country.</P>
<P><HI>The Lord will be with you while you follow him</HI> in these holy ways of <HI>Justice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>humility</HI>;<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Chron. 15.2.</NOTE> but if you pursue <HI>lying vanities,</HI> you will forsake and
<PB N="6" REF="9"/>
forfeit your <HI>own and all our mercies</HI>; if you attend <HI>passionate and partial interests, unjust</HI> and <HI>cruel coun∣sels</HI>; if your hearts (as <HI>Pharoahs</HI>) be <HI>lifted up</HI> a∣gainst God, and above your brethren, you also will be intangled in the <HI>wilderness of sin,</HI> your <HI>chariot wheels</HI> will be taken off; you will drive heavily, and at last engage your selves and all of us in a deeper sea of blood (if deeper can be) to the ut∣ter ruine of our <HI>Reformed Religion,</HI> and our justly <HI>endeared,</HI> but afflicted <HI>Country,</HI> which is the nest of our posterity.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">The way of our happiness.</NOTE>§. Give me leave therefore (O ye <HI>Heads of our Tribes</HI> and <HI>chief of our Families</HI>) to bespeak your attention (as <HI>Jotham</HI> did the men of <HI>Sechem) Hearken to me,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iudg. 9.7.</NOTE> <HI>that God may hearken to you</HI>; they are <HI>divine Revelations,</HI> not <HI>humane inventions</HI> that I offer to you; if you turn away from <HI>hearing</HI> and <HI>doing these few,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 28.9.</NOTE> <HI>clear,</HI> and <HI>necessary commands of God,</HI> your prayers and fasts will be <HI>abominable,</HI> your <HI>consultations confusions,</HI> and your <HI>actions</HI> will be as well <HI>unsuccessful</HI> as injurious to God, your selves, and others.</P>
<P>§. We have been many years as the <HI>Lepers</HI> in their <HI>desperate dilemma,</HI> between famine and sword,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Kings 7.8:</NOTE> <HI>oppression</HI> and <HI>confusion, sin</HI> and <HI>suffering, death</HI> and <HI>despair</HI>; if we returned to <HI>the City,</HI> or but looked to our former <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> to our excel∣lent <HI>laws</HI> and <HI>constitutions</HI> in Church and State, it was <HI>confiscation, plunder, sequestration, destruction</HI>; if we still advanced in the perplexed ways of some mens new inventions, and <HI>endless novelties,</HI> it was not only sinful <HI>confusion</HI> but <HI>sore oppression,</HI> and con∣tinual <HI>exhausting</HI> of our estates and honors, beside
<PB N="7" REF="9"/>
our peace and liberty, together with the baffling of the very <HI>orderly profession,</HI> no less than the <HI>power of Religion.</HI></P>
<P>§. Indeed we could neither have leave to live freely, as <HI>honest men,</HI> nor as <HI>good Christians</HI>; all our sacred, and civil, our temporal and eternal inte∣rests were and still are at stake. <HI>Terrent etiam nunc nubila mentem,</HI> our bodies and souls, our persons and posterities are still engaged; yea, and the Ark of God too, our Religion, as reformed and Chri∣stian.</P>
<P>§. In all these respects, our eyes and hearts are next God passionately toward you; we have many years been solicitous, with that <HI>Catholick Question, Who will shew us any good</HI>? we have long looked for the promised <HI>good things,</HI> of a <HI>glorious Church,</HI> of a <HI>flourishing</HI> and <HI>settled State</HI> but our iniquities have withheld them from us:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 5.25.</NOTE> Here the Lord hath shewed you in a few words what is good; <HI>Bonum Ecclesiae, patriae, conscientiae, animae; good for souls and bodies,</HI> for <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State</HI>; for <HI>Soveraign</HI> and <HI>Subjects,</HI> for <HI>rich</HI> and <HI>poor,</HI> for <HI>great</HI> and <HI>small,</HI> for <HI>their selves</HI> and their <HI>posterity,</HI> for <HI>civil</HI> and <HI>religi∣ous interests,</HI> for <HI>temporal and eternal concernments</HI>; namely, <HI>To do justice, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with your God</HI>: All our evils arise from either our want of <HI>justice or mercy,</HI> or <HI>humility,</HI> from our <HI>injuriousness, uncharitableness,</HI> and <HI>arrogancy,</HI> which knows not how to be either thankful and content <HI>before God,</HI> or merciful and just toward men.</P>
<P>§. The Text, as a full and liberal fountain,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Partition</NOTE> hath
<PB N="8" REF="10"/>
many <HI>emanations</HI> like the <HI>Rivers</HI> that watered the <HI>garden of God.</HI></P>
<P N="1">1. We have the main head or source, <HI>the Lord.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. The great cistern or receptacle, <HI>Thee O man.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. The (<HI>tria fluenta</HI>) three grand Derivations or streams.</P>
<P>First, <HI>Of doing Justice.</HI> Secondly, <HI>Of loving Mercy.</HI> Thirdly, <HI>Of walking humbly with God.</HI></P>
<P>All are clear, copious and comprehensive sub∣jects of our meditation, discourse and practice. For 1. <HI>In una justitia omnes virtutes.</HI> 2. <HI>In una mise∣ricordia omnes beatitudines.</HI> 3. <HI>In una humilitate omnes gratiae</HI>;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth. 5.7.</NOTE> all graces are in humility, all bles∣sednesses in shewing Mercy, and all moral vertues in Justice; for every vice and sin is an injury to God, our selves or others.</P>
<P>Nor have we God herein our Instructer only, but also our (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) great example; for we Christians serve not only (<HI>justum Dominum, &amp; be∣nignum Patrem, sed &amp; humilem Deum</HI>) a just Lord and a merciful Father, but even an <HI>humble</HI> God, <HI>He abaseth himself</HI> (saith the Psalmist) <HI>to behold the things done upon earth,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 13.</NOTE> to dwell with the Sons of men, especially with the <HI>humble and contrite spirit</HI>; yea,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Phil. 2.8.</NOTE> the Lord of glory, in order to save us from the sad effects of our pride, <HI>hath humbled himself even to the death of the cross</HI>; and is it time for us sinful worms to be proud, unjust, and unmerci∣ful!</P>
<P>§. There are four parts to be set forth.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, The Demonstrator or Shewer; <HI>The Lord.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or <HI>things Demonstrated, Justice,
<PB N="9" REF="10"/>
Mercy</HI> and <HI>Humility</HI>; indeed the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) <HI>whole duty of man.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>3. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; To whom this Demonstration is made, <HI>Thee O man.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>4. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, The manner of demonstration, how <HI>God sheweth to, and requireth of man these things.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>§. It is not my design to handle each of them af∣ter that ampleness which these subjects may bear or deserve, nor will the time and after duties per∣mit: but only to make such short <HI>remarques</HI> and touches of them, as may not so much teach you (who are knowing in all the will of God, as to Justice and Mercy, Law and Gospel) but only stir up your <HI>pure</HI> and <HI>holy minds</HI> to be not <HI>knowers,</HI> or <HI>hearers only, but doers also of the will of God,</HI> that you may be blessed of God and man; and <HI>Saviours</HI> indeed, not <HI>Deceivers</HI> and Destroyers of your selves and your Country.</P>
<P>§. I begin with the first, The <HI>Demonstrator,</HI> who,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The demon∣strator.</NOTE> <HI>The Lord.</HI> Here two things are to be considered, First, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the rise or occasion of this demonstra∣tion. 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> or <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the credit and authority of the Demonstrator.</P>
<P>§. First, The Occasion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 The occasion</NOTE> putting the Lord upon this way of remonstrating, to inculcate these <HI>(re∣quisita &amp; dictata)</HI> old lessons; this you will see in the foregoing words, <HI>vers.</HI> 6, 7. where we may observe the vaunting questions, and presumptuous postulations of a company of <HI>formal Hypocrites,</HI> who demand (<HI>in Dei dedecus &amp; legis contumeliam</HI>) to the reproach of God and his Laws, what he would have to please him? <HI>Burnt offerings</HI> or <HI>Rivers of oyl,</HI> or if need be, their very <HI>first-born</HI>; they will
<PB N="10" REF="11"/>
be at any cost to appease him, part with any thing, spare nothing but their sins.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 15.13.</NOTE>§. Thus they quarrel with God, and justifie themselves with <HI>Saul,</HI> that they had <HI>fulfilled the Law of God</HI>;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 58.3.</NOTE> as those devout <HI>Bulrushes</HI> in <HI>Isaiah,</HI> who are not ashamed to ask, <HI>Why have we fasted and afflicted our souls?</HI> when they had not parted with any sin, nor loosed any bands of oppression.</P>
<P>§. We may observe as in Scripture, so in all our late experiences, that no men are more <HI>supercili∣ous</HI> self-justifiers, and imperious retorters upon God and man, than those who are most defective in their duties to both; they are angry that God is angry, and unsatisfied that he is not satisfied with their <HI>Hypocritical chaff and formality</HI>; they plead ig∣norance when wilfully blind; and ask for light when they shut their eyes; they would know what to do, when they do not what they know.</P>
<P>Such proud and insolent <HI>vaporers</HI> (like <HI>Jehu</HI> and the <HI>Pharisee</HI>) are audacious and frontless Hypo∣crites,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezek. 18 15.</NOTE> as if their ways were <HI>equal,</HI> and Gods <HI>un∣equal</HI>; as if God were blameable, and themselves blameless: O what cost and pains will they be at to reform Religion, Laws, Liberties, Church and State when, they aim to be the most <HI>irreligi∣ous Depravers,</HI> and licentious oppressors of all? <HI>O the Temple,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 7.4.</NOTE> <HI>the Temple of the Lord</HI>! O his <HI>service, worship and Ministers</HI>; when they rob God, de∣stroy his <HI>Church,</HI> and debace his <HI>Ministers</HI>; these do not so much err as <HI>lye</HI> and <HI>dissemble</HI> in their hearts: They brag of precious <HI>liberties,</HI> when they bring in both <HI>slavery</HI> and <HI>licentiousness</HI>: They boast of great <HI>Reformations,</HI> when they are most
<PB N="11" REF="11"/>
<HI>deformed Reformers</HI>; they finde fault with God, and all men but themselves; all their aberrations are gracious, and their very sins must be glorious essays or successes; while they follow <HI>Providences,</HI> they flye from plain <HI>Scriptures,</HI> and known Laws; these prescribe to such new Saints (<HI>angustam mi∣nus justitiam</HI>) too narrow a <HI>loom</HI> for their wild ju∣stice; these talk <HI>high of successes,</HI> which are their racks, when they look not to their <HI>consciences</HI> which are as empty <HI>mangers</HI>: they talk of Reli∣gion, and neglect civil Justice; they are <HI>large-hearted</HI> to God, and <HI>strict-handed</HI> towards men; he shall have enough of praying, preaching, and fasting, provided they may <HI>proudly usurp,</HI> and <HI>cruelly oppress</HI> their <HI>Brethren and betters.</HI></P>
<P>§. Yet will they pretend, <HI>What will God have more? why doth he yet complain?</HI> when they have both <HI>wearied themselves</HI> and him too with the heapes of their formal services and vain obla∣tions.</P>
<P>God here (as elsewhere) sharply retorts upon them; ye need not go far, <HI>O you hard-hearted,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ioh. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Psal. 50.8. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sa. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>6.3. Psal. 51.17. 1 Sam. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.22. Hos. 6.6.</NOTE> and <HI>cruel-handed Hypocrites,</HI> to learn that <HI>God will have mercy and not sacrifice</HI>; that <HI>obedience moral,</HI> is better than <HI>burnt offerings ceremonial</HI>; that (com∣paratively) God hath not required <HI>these things at your hands,</HI> not solely, not chiefly; that he is <HI>sick</HI> and <HI>surfeited, and overladen</HI> with these <HI>sordid and sinful oblations,</HI> nothing is cordial to him, but <HI>humble hearts, charitable hands,</HI> and <HI>just actions.</HI></P>
<P>§. He requireth not so much the outward cost, pomp and ceremony of Religion, as that <HI>equal pi∣ety</HI>
<PB N="12" REF="12"/>
and <HI>pious equity,</HI> which is just to God and man; Thus in vain do some Papists highly urge and pro∣digally insist of the excessive cost they bestow on their <HI>Religion,</HI> when they applaud, yea almost adore the <HI>Papal pride</HI> and <HI>usurpation,</HI> persisting in that the <HI>Sacriledge</HI> and <HI>injury</HI> they do to God and man, by de∣nying the <HI>plenary doctrines,</HI> and <HI>donations</HI> of Christ in the <HI>Sacraments</HI> to all <HI>communicants,</HI> and in their communicating something of <HI>worship</HI> and <HI>merit</HI> to the creature, beyond what the divine glory and jealousie set forth in the word of God doth permit.</P>
<P>§. Not that God loves a lazy or a penurious, a <HI>hide-bound</HI> and <HI>illiberal Religion,</HI> which seeks to serve God of that which costs us nothing; much-less doth he approve those <HI>sacrilegious robberies,</HI> which are pretended for his <HI>glory,</HI> and the advan∣tages of his service: No, he is neither a <HI>covetous</HI> nor a <HI>cruel God</HI>; he gives all things, and is content every one in Church and State should enjoy their own, what ever by right (that is by Law) belongs to them.</P>
<P>§. From the occasion of this <HI>hypocritical insolency</HI> (the <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) or inquisitiveness, which they falla∣ciously use, as if solicitous to content him, the Lord himself by the Prophet inculcates not the <HI>Deutero∣nomy,</HI> but the <HI>Hecatontonomy,</HI> that law of justice, mercy and humility, which he had an hundred times repeated by <HI>Moses</HI> and the <HI>Prophets to the Jews,</HI> as the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) principal pleasure of the Lord, beyond all <HI>Holocausts</HI> and <HI>Hecatombs,</HI> all rivers of oyl, and sacrifices of the first born; God who is (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, as <HI>Dionysius</HI> calls him) all essence wholly
<PB N="13" REF="12"/>
substance, or self-subsistence, without any shadow or accident, cannot delight so much in any such shadows and leaves of ceremonious service with which the most <HI>barren Formalists</HI> may abound; as in those real fruits and <HI>solid effects</HI> of Equity, Cha∣rity and Sanctity, with which as none but the truly godly do abound, so whoever brings these to God from a pure and <HI>devoted humble heart,</HI> is more welcome with <HI>two mites</HI> or a <HI>little meal,</HI> then o∣thers are with all their luxurious costliness; of all which the very Heathens had pregnant con∣ceptions to offer to the gods.</P>
<Q><L>—Jus, fas{que} animi, sanctos{que} recessus</L>
<L>Mentis, &amp; incoctum generoso pectus honesto,</L>
<L>Haec cedo ut admoveam Templis &amp; farre litabo.</L></Q>
<P N="2">§. 2. We are to consider the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) <HI>credit</HI> and <HI>authority</HI> of this <HI>Demonstrator,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 The credit and authority of the De∣monstrator.</NOTE> which makes his words both for the truth and goodness of them (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) most worthy to be <HI>believed, received,</HI> and <HI>obeyed,</HI> since he is the most wise God, in and from whom are all treasures <HI>of wisdom,</HI> intellectu∣al, moral and political. He is the great eternal and inexhausted <HI>fountain</HI> of all power and order, natural, civil and spiritual; the <HI>Father of lights,</HI> the infallible Teacher, the <HI>Soveraign Dictator,</HI> (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) the great Law-giver, whose will is the highest Reason, and his Word the most unal∣terable truth; we have these <HI>lively Oracles</HI> of <HI>Justice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>Humility,</HI> not from <HI>Jupiter</HI> as <HI>Minos</HI> pretended; or from <HI>Egeria,</HI> as <HI>Numa</HI>; or <HI>Minerva,</HI> as <HI>Solon</HI>; or <HI>Apollo,</HI> as <HI>Lycurgus</HI>; or from
<PB N="14" REF="13"/>
<HI>fictitious artifices,</HI> as <HI>Mahomet</HI>; or from <HI>fantastick Enthusiasms,</HI> as <HI>Fanaticks</HI>; but from that <HI>King im∣mortal,</HI> the <HI>only wise God</HI>; who hath the authority of both Lord and Father, the sufficiency of <HI>infi∣nity,</HI> and the <HI>exemplary Ideas</HI> in him of all <HI>per∣fections</HI>; that being in him to the highest glory of goodness,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 94.10.</NOTE> which he sheweth to us, and requireth of us in his Law; This is he that teacheth man wis∣dom.</P>
<P N="2">§. 2. He is not more (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, than <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) able by his wisdom, than willing by his indulgence and love to <HI>instruct mankind</HI> in the way that is best for him, and in those Laws which are most <HI>just</HI> and <HI>equal,</HI> most easie and <HI>useful,</HI> most comely and <HI>honorable,</HI> for all conditions, single and social, pub∣lique and private, <HI>Soveraign</HI> and <HI>Subject,</HI> for <HI>Ma∣gistrate</HI> and <HI>Minister,</HI> for <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State:</HI> This is he who teacheth man by way of eminency, that one great and fundamental lesson,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iob 28.</NOTE> That <HI>the fear of God is the beginning of wisdom, and to depart from evil is understanding.</HI> He gave to the Jews the knowledge of his laws, not only ceremonial but political and moral; those are <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or <HI>magna moralia,</HI> in comparison of which the cere∣monies were but transient shadows, and begga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly elements, as the Apostle speaks; <HI>Statutes that were not good,</HI> that is, not absolutely and in themselves or materially, but relatively; as referring to the Imposers authority, and those better things of which they were emblems or types; they were as heavy burthens, so but <HI>temporary dispensations,</HI> during the poedagogy or <HI>minority</HI> of Religion, till the better ages (or worlds) should come, in which
<PB N="15" REF="13"/>
Evangelical <HI>Justice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>Humility,</HI> should most fully be not onely demonstrated from the <HI>moral law,</HI> but also from the glorious <HI>example</HI> of the justice of God satisfied and his mercy procu∣red, by the humiliation of <HI>Messias,</HI> the condescen∣tion and <HI>crucifixion</HI> of the Son of God.</P>
<P N="3">§. 3. The Lord <HI>hath shewed thee,</HI> these (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) most infallible and immutable rules of <HI>Ju∣stice, Mercy,</HI> and <HI>Humility,</HI> who is (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) the justest exacter, and the exactest observer of our obedience, and con∣formity to these laws; in other matters of cere∣mony and service, he is not so severe and rigid, but gratiously dispenseth, upon many occasions, as of necessity and infirmity, of prepotent custom, disuse and prejudice; but in the grand points of <HI>Iustice, Mercy,</HI> and <HI>Humility,</HI> there is no dispen∣sation or remission; no man can, as to these, be at any time <HI>unable,</HI> if he be not <HI>unwilling</HI>; here <HI>impotency</HI> is <HI>impiety</HI>; God strictly observes all wil∣full and <HI>presumptuous transgressions,</HI> and will be the avenger of them; not is he to be deceived or satisfied with any formal excuses and <HI>pretentions</HI> used by <HI>wily hypocrites,</HI> who offer <HI>chaff</HI> instead of <HI>good weat,</HI> no more than he can be escaped or re∣resisted by any <HI>tyrannique</HI> power and in∣solencies, when he maketh <HI>inquisition for these no∣torious omissions</HI> of <HI>Iustice, Mercy,</HI> and <HI>Humility,</HI> which are the summaries of all good Laws, and the seminaries of all piety, <HI>grace</HI> and <HI>vertue</HI>; nor shall these words of God, which <HI>drop like the rain and gentle dew</HI> from heaven return in vain, but will be <HI>swift witnesses</HI> against any soul, whose <HI>bar∣renness</HI>
<PB N="16" REF="14"/>
presages it is <HI>nigh to our sing</HI> and <HI>burning</HI>: for these laws and lessons (as from Mount <HI>Sinai</HI>) are with thunder and lightning; Gods <HI>demonstrations</HI> are not only true but terrible, armed with <HI>omni∣potency,</HI> never to be bafled, pregnantly shewed by their own perspicuity, and powerfully exacted by the divine <HI>severity,</HI> who will carry himself <HI>froward∣ly</HI> or <HI>contrarily,</HI> and as I may say, with an <HI>uncon∣descending height,</HI> and divine stiffness against those that are not <HI>humble in his sight,</HI> resisting the proud, and withdrawing <HI>mercy from the merciless</HI>; yea re∣quiring the justice of <HI>punishment on us,</HI> because the justice of <HI>obedience</HI> is not <HI>done by us. Ideo enim patimur justitiam quia non agimus,</HI> as St. <HI>Bernard</HI> speaks; for this is by the eternal vengeance still in∣culcated in hell (as <HI>Virgil</HI> expresseth)</P>
<P><HI>Discite justitiam moniti, &amp; ne temnite divos.</HI> while the Furies with their <HI>flaming iron whips (fla∣gellis ferreis &amp; flagrantibus</HI>) do compel wicked and unjust men to suffer that <HI>justice</HI> which they re∣fused to do to God, to Man, to themselves and others.</P>
<P>But I have done with the first general; in which I observed the occasion and authority of this De∣monstration.</P>
<P>§. Secondly, I now come to the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) thing demonstrated;<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Gen. the thing demon∣strated.</NOTE> the grand lesson which God teacheth so clearly and constantly to all men at all times, these are denoted under these three grand heads; <HI>Iustice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>Hu∣mility,</HI></P>
<P>These are considerable. 1. <HI>Conjunctim,</HI> joyntly. 2. <HI>Divisim,</HI> severally, in their united and distinct aspects.</P>
<P N="1"><PB N="17" REF="14"/>1. Consider them together, and they afford us six things considerable.</P>
<P>First, The paucity of these (<HI>magna mandata,</HI> or <HI>summè requisita</HI>) grand demands: The Lord lays but a <HI>few things upon us; Tria sunt omnia,</HI> a <HI>sacred Trinity of Precepts</HI> from the <HI>sacred Trinity</HI> of <HI>Iustice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>Humility,</HI> from the divine <HI>Wis∣dom, Power</HI> and <HI>Majesty.</HI></P>
<P>These make up that (<HI>monile sacrum</HI>) holy pen∣dent or jewel, which is the <HI>greatest ornament</HI> of <HI>humane nature,</HI> and blessing of all <HI>Societies,</HI> con∣sisting but of three <HI>gems</HI>; but they are <HI>paragons</HI> of great price; for what is brighter than the <HI>in∣vincible Diamond of Justice,</HI> which is <HI>scintilla Dei,</HI> a spark of God, as pearls are drops, and Diamonds sparks of the Sun? what more beautiful than the gentle <HI>Saphire of Mercy</HI>? what more amiable than the modest <HI>Emrald of Humility?</HI></P>
<P>§. The <HI>paternal indulgence</HI> of God is pleased to give us, in his teaching us short lessons, <HI>compendi∣ous Counsels,</HI> and holy <HI>Epitomes</HI> of his will and our duty.</P>
<P>§. At first he propounded but (<HI>decem verba</HI>) ten commands in the Decalogue, which is a summa∣ry of all <HI>Theological</HI> and <HI>Moral Institutions</HI>: After he reduceth these to a narrower compass, of <HI>loving the Lord thy God,</HI> and thy <HI>neighbor as thy self</HI>: So <HI>Solomon,</HI> To <HI>fear God and keep his Commandments; Christ</HI> makes up all in one grand sentence, of <HI>do∣ing as we would be done unto</HI>; whence the Emperor <HI>Severus</HI> took his famous <HI>Motto</HI>; the Apostle St.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth. 22.40.</NOTE> <HI>Paul</HI> brings all points and lines of the <HI>Laws</HI> and <HI>Gospels circumference</HI> to this one center, <HI>Love,</HI> as the fulfil∣ling
<PB N="18" REF="15"/>
of all in one word. Nor doth he permit <HI>Ti∣mothy</HI> to vary from that (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) <HI>wholesome form of words,</HI> the faith once delivered to the Saints, which he had taught him, as a short <HI>creed</HI> or <HI>sum∣mary</HI> (no doubt) of <HI>Christian doctrine,</HI> which other∣where is expressed in <HI>beleiving with the heart, and confessing the Lord Iesus with the mouth</HI>; so in the end of the commandment, which is <HI>Charity,</HI> out of a <HI>pure heart,</HI> and a <HI>good conscience,</HI> and <HI>faith un∣fained</HI>; So inexcusable are they who refuse to learn of God; whose commandments are neither grie∣vous nor numerous, but condescending to the weak∣est capacities, and frailest memories; to which, what ever is necessary in religion, is easie to be lear∣ned and retained.</P>
<P>§. For secondly, as the particular heads are few in <HI>number,</HI> so <HI>very short</HI> in the discourse: some points may by long <HI>Orations</HI> be (like gold) malle∣ated and extended to such great latitudes of <HI>dif∣fused expressions,</HI> as make them very combersom; as the volumes of our times, both in <HI>Dogmatick, Po∣lemick,</HI> and <HI>Practick Divinity</HI> do witness; while the superfluity of mans wit and eloquence glories to find out many <HI>inventions,</HI> definitions and di∣stinctions, even in plain things; wire-drawing re∣ligion into <HI>fine threads,</HI> and driving the solid <HI>mass of Divinity,</HI> as to Faith and Repentance, love of <HI>God</HI> and <HI>our neighbours</HI> to leaf gold, chopping, and hewing, and paring the pillars of wisdom into small chips and thin shavings. Doubtless (as <HI>Eras∣mus</HI> writes to <HI>Archep. Warrham</HI>) the Church of Christ was never in a more happy estate, than when it was (<HI>uno &amp; brevissimo symbolo contenta</HI>) both
<PB N="19" REF="15"/>
contented with and kept in the compass of that one <HI>short Creed,</HI> which we call the Apostles, and which was yet once shorter than now it is.</P>
<P>Thirdly, But, commonly <HI>brevity</HI> is attended with <HI>obscurity; Brevis esse laboro, obscurus fio</HI>; short and concise expressions many times wrap things up, as it were, in clouds; whereas Laws ought to be <HI>meridiana lumina, tanquam solis radiis scriptae,</HI> so clear, as none need complain; so <HI>legible</HI> that he that <HI>runs may read them</HI>; and so indeed are these divine demonstrations in the Text, where the wis∣dom of God reconcileth <HI>brevity</HI> and <HI>perspicuity</HI> to∣gether (as <HI>Pliny</HI> speaks of <HI>Trajans</HI> uniting <HI>Sove∣raignty</HI> and <HI>Liberty,</HI> by an happy temper of Govern∣ment or Empire, which neither diminished his own just Prerogative, as <HI>a Prince,</HI> nor oppressed the peoples legal immunities as <HI>his Subjects</HI>) so the Lord, designing these Laws for all sorts of peo∣ple, fits them for all capacities in such a way, that the very <HI>babes</HI> and <HI>simple ones</HI> may learn, and un∣derstand, and do them; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Laws (saith <HI>Plato</HI>) ought to be as <HI>common</HI> and <HI>catholick</HI> in their expressions, as they are in their injunction or obligation, that none may <HI>plead ig∣norance,</HI> either by the prolixity or obscurity, by the ennormious number, or by the tedious length of them.</P>
<P>Fourthly, We may observe the order and situa∣tion of the particulars; First, <HI>Justice.</HI> Secondly, <HI>Mercy.</HI> Thirdly, <HI>Humility</HI>; there is (as <HI>Calvin</HI> and others observe) an (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) inverting of the <HI>Primacy</HI> and order due to that dignity which <HI>hu∣mility</HI> (as the <HI>summary of all Religion,</HI> or piety to
<PB N="20" REF="16"/>
God) justly requires before that of <HI>justice</HI> toward man; yet this is placed first, as most obvious for mans advantages and discerning, though not as most eminent in nature; as if the Lord more minded the <HI>welfare of mankind</HI> than his own service; im∣portuning first for <HI>Justice</HI> and <HI>Mercy,</HI> and last for <HI>humble walking with himself</HI>; not but that religion toward God is and ought to be the <HI>chief intention</HI>; but <HI>Justice</HI> and <HI>Mercy</HI> may go before in the <HI>executi∣on,</HI> especially in case of <HI>eminent danger</HI> and <HI>distress</HI> pri∣vate and publick; here (<HI>necessitas pellit Sabbatum</HI>) the <HI>Sacrifice, Shew-bread</HI> and <HI>Sabboth</HI> yeild to necessity, not immoral; God will have Justice and Mercy rather then <HI>burnt-offerings</HI>; yea in cases of fire, shipwrack, or <HI>sickness,</HI> and like exigencies of life and safety; it is venial to break off <HI>fastings, pray∣ings, preachings,</HI> and <HI>communicating at the Lords Table,</HI> in order to save others or our selves.</P>
<P>§. As in private so in publick cases, when things are upon a <HI>precipice</HI> or <HI>extremity,</HI> the first care may be of the <HI>man,</HI> next of the <HI>Christian</HI>; to cure the <HI>Commonweals</HI> urgent <HI>paroxisms,</HI> and then the <HI>Churches chronick distempers</HI>; which was <HI>Davids</HI> method, who first composed the <HI>civil disorders,</HI> which war had occasioned, before he applied to bring the Ark to its rest, and establish the solem∣nities of religious services. It is certain (as <HI>Opta∣tus</HI> observes) that the Church is imbarqued in the Commonweal; and though the lading be better worth and more to be valued then the ship, yet there will be an ill account of the <HI>first,</HI> if the latter be not secured from great <HI>leaks,</HI> and desperate rocks of war and sedition, which to prevent is not
<PB N="21" REF="16"/>
only a <HI>mercy</HI> justly due to <HI>mankind,</HI> but an accepta∣ble <HI>service to God</HI>; He were a very <HI>preposterous Zealot</HI> and <HI>ridiculous Divine,</HI> who in the exigents of <HI>pleu∣ritick</HI> pains, and present <HI>faintings</HI> of spirits, would impose upon heart-sick Patients his <HI>long prayers,</HI> or tediously obtrude <HI>godly discourses,</HI> and other <HI>ghostly counsels,</HI> rather than give way to the <HI>Phy∣sitians</HI> or <HI>Chyrurgeons</HI> skill and <HI>applications,</HI> for blood-letting or cordials; this were to act the part not of a pious and <HI>prudent Confessor,</HI> but of a <HI>de∣vout</HI> and imprudent <HI>Executioner.</HI></P>
<P>§. It is certain (as <HI>Minutius Faelix</HI> observes, <HI>Apud nos Christianos, quo quis{que} religiosior, eo justior</HI>) among good Christians, the best are most ready <HI>to mercy,</HI> and exactest in justice. Yea reverend <HI>Calvin</HI> observes on the place, <HI>Injustitia erga homi∣nes est certissimum impietatis argumentum</HI>; although men may do many just things, and yet have no true <HI>Religion</HI>; yet injustice toward men is (as Leprosie on the forehead) a certain token of <HI>Irreligion</HI> toward God.</P>
<P>§. They are found <HI>lyars</HI> to God and man, and will be <HI>deceivers,</HI> yea <HI>damners</HI> of their own souls, who pretend to build Religion and <HI>Reformation</HI> on the <HI>ruines of Iustice</HI> and <HI>Civil Laws,</HI> by sacriledge, and <HI>violence,</HI> by robbery and <HI>rapine</HI>; they trust in <HI>ly∣ing words</HI> which cannot profit; who steal,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 7.9.</NOTE> and mur∣der, and lye, and swear falsely, and yet come, and <HI>stand before God in his house,</HI> and say We are <HI>deli∣vered to do all these abominations</HI>; these are the projects of <HI>Iohn of Leyden</HI> and his complices, full of <HI>Enthusiastick</HI> folly and fury; men cannot be holy men with <HI>Iohn Baptist,</HI> nor devout with <HI>Cor∣nelius,</HI>
<PB N="22" REF="17"/>
unless they be just with both; and also how can they be <HI>just to God</HI> whom they have not seen, if they be unjust to man <HI>whom they have seen</HI>! as St.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Ioh. 4.20.</NOTE> <HI>Iohn</HI> speaks of loving God! hence the blessed God puts the <HI>rendring to Caesar</HI> the things that are <HI>Caesars,</HI> before the rendring <HI>to God</HI> the things tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> are Gods; not as to the dignity or duty of our <HI>obedience,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luk. 10.25.</NOTE> but as to the <HI>evidence</HI> and outward te∣stimony of our inward subjection to God, by that which is outward to our lawful <HI>Superiors,</HI> who are in Gods stead, having both power and commissi∣on from God, and in serving of whom, in things lawful, <HI>we serve the Lord.</HI></P>
<P>§. After the like method is that of the <HI>Apostle,</HI> which tells us, that the grace of God that bringeth salvation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Tit. 2.11.</NOTE> <HI>teacheth us first to live righteously,</HI> next <HI>so∣berly,</HI> and then <HI>godlily</HI> in this present world; the first and pregnantest instances of <HI>pure Religion and undefiled</HI> are first to man and then to God; not but that the <HI>root of piety,</HI> and our Closet-religion to God is before the <HI>fruits of Iustice and Mercy,</HI> but those are more <HI>hidden,</HI> and these most <HI>manifested,</HI> so as men may <HI>see our good works, and glorifie our heavenly Father.</HI></P>
<P>Fifthly, Nor is the <HI>juncture</HI> of these three <HI>inob∣servable,</HI> because indeed they are inseparable where they are <HI>sincere</HI>; This is (<HI>sancta &amp; individua trias</HI>) an holy and <HI>undivided Trinity</HI>; where one is, all will be; the root of <HI>Humility,</HI> the leaf of <HI>Mercy,</HI> and the fruit of <HI>Iustice</HI>; if men be <HI>proud</HI> they will be cruel and covetous, void of Mercy and Justice too. So if they be <HI>unjust</HI> and uncharitable, you may con∣clude them to be without <HI>humility</HI>; for these <HI>three</HI>
<PB N="23" REF="17"/>
are as <HI>one,</HI> which united bear witness to <HI>God,</HI> our own Conscience and others: Proud men are prone to envy others, to over-value themselves, and to use such unjust means as may gratifie their inordi∣nate appetites, suitable to their high opinions of themselves; proud, and so unjust thoughts betray men to unjust actions.</P>
<P>Sixthly and lastly, We may observe the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) common epithite or predicate to all of them; The Lord hath shewed <HI>what is good</HI>; joynt∣ly and severally, absolutely and respectively, to all men at all times, in all occasions and conditions (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) in private and publick sta∣tions, for Church and State, in war and peace, in revenge and restitution, for souls, bodies, and estates, for selves and others; good to begin, con∣tinue and increase all <HI>blessings,</HI> that mankind can desire to enjoy in this life; for liberty, honor, peace and plenty, joyned with piety; these are (<HI>divinissima &amp; amaenissima bona</HI>) profitable and pleasant as well as most necessary.</P>
<P N="1">1. Without <HI>Iustice</HI> there can be no good in the greatest plenty, which either exposeth to injury, or prospers by rapine and violence.</P>
<P N="2">2. Without <HI>Mercy</HI> there is no relief or succor in the many miseries to which humane infirmities, and our mortal state is subject.</P>
<P N="3">3. Without <HI>Humility</HI> neither Equity nor Charity will profit us, or please God; when they are as the vertues of <HI>Heathens,</HI> more from <HI>Pharisaick pomp</HI> and love of <HI>applause,</HI> than any sence of duty to men, or <HI>devotion to God</HI>; these may have their reward from men, but neither <HI>good</HI> nor <HI>great,</HI> because pro∣portionable
<PB N="24" REF="18"/>
to what they sow, either <HI>formal</HI> or hypocritical, or <HI>incompleat</HI> and <HI>partial</HI>; while their lusts and passions either transport them beyond, or keep them short of that true and pure fountain of living waters, which while they forsake, to fol∣low <HI>broken cisterns,</HI> and unfaithful pits, they can∣not fail to suffer evil at last, because they do not follow that good which God hath set so free and full before them; <HI>Et ideo miseri quia mali</HI>; they are not miserable for Gods defects, as if he had <HI>de∣creed</HI> them to be so, or <HI>denied</HI> them, the way of being, doing and enjoying good; but because they do or easily may <HI>know the way,</HI> and works, and rewards that are good, but will not; <HI>Maxima pars humanae impotentiae fluit exvoluntate</HI>; the most if not all of our immoral and sinful infirmities, flow from our want of will rather than of skill. God is not wanting to teach us the good we should chuse and do; but we are wanting to chuse and do the good he evidently teacheth us; we cannot com∣plain of Gods not <HI>convincing us,</HI> but God <HI>complains</HI> justly of our not <HI>complying</HI> with, and <HI>converting</HI> to his conviction.</P>
<P>§. Thus I have considered these three things joyntly; now we may look on them distinct or se∣verally.</P>
<P>First, In the subject or substance, spirit and quin∣tessence of each of them, <HI>Justice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>Hu∣mility.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, In the predication or addition to each; to <HI>do</HI> Justice, to <HI>love</HI> Mercy, to <HI>walk</HI> humbly with thy God.</P>
<P>§. First, Lets take a summary view of the subject
<PB N="25" REF="18"/>
or substance of each; not by the way of <HI>common place,</HI> wherein the three Preachers of this day might have found matter enough to have enter∣tained both their meditation and your <HI>attention</HI>; but in such a short <HI>summary,</HI> as may only take the <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the topmost and <HI>fairest fruit</HI> of each, and leave the other large <HI>harvest</HI> or <HI>vintage</HI> to your own gathering.</P>
<P>§. The first is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>judicium,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, such ju∣stice as directs in judicature, not speculative,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 <HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stice.</HI></NOTE> or habitual and dispositive <HI>justice,</HI> but transitive, <HI>decisive</HI> justice; <HI>forensis justitia,</HI> which from an inward principle brings forth the fruits of Justice or Righ∣teousness to all.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI> 18.38.</NOTE> Here we are to enquire as <HI>Pilat</HI> did of <HI>truth, What is Iustice</HI>?<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Quest.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P N="1">§. 1. Some measure it by <HI>their power,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ans.</HI> What Iu¦stice i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> by the length of their sword, and strength of their arm; when indeed <HI>(Id tantum possumus quod jure possu∣mus) &amp; in maxima potentia minima debet esse li∣centia.</HI> The best and valiantest men neither can nor will do ought but what they lawfully may; they count (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) unjust things impos∣sible.</P>
<P N="2">§. 2. Others measure <HI>justice</HI> by their wills, <HI>passi∣ons, lusts,</HI> interests, <HI>&amp;c. quicquid libet licet (meram voluntatem imperii limites ponunt</HI>) what serves their ambition, and covetousness, or their revenge and envy, or their faction or partiality, this is just with them though never so unlawful.</P>
<P>§. There are that measure justice by their fan∣cies and imaginations, by their dreams and Enthu∣siasms, by their presumed <HI>gifts</HI> and <HI>graces,</HI> as if they had a right and merit to all they can get; that
<PB N="26" REF="19"/>
they are the only <HI>Israelites,</HI> who have Gods com∣mission to spoil the <HI>Egyptians</HI>; that all things are theirs, because they challenge Christ to be theirs; that civil dominion is founded in grace, and ju∣stice is to be measured only by <HI>faith and assurance of salvation,</HI> of which themselves will be the onely Judges; these are the <HI>paultry pretentions</HI> of some <HI>Hucsters</HI> of <HI>Religion,</HI> and <HI>devout Beggars,</HI> who with the <HI>Pharisees, Euchites</HI> and <HI>Circumcellians,</HI> find it easier to devour others by <HI>long prayers</HI> and <HI>preach∣ings,</HI> or (if these will not do) by <HI>fighting,</HI> than to get their own living by honest industry.</P>
<P N="4">§. 4. There are that measure <HI>Justice</HI> by <HI>necessity</HI>; as if necessity justified all its commands, and gave checkmate to all laws: Tis true in some publick exigencies, private rights must yield to publick ne∣cessities; yet so as to make just compensation, af∣ter the tide of necessity is retired: but there is no immoral necessity to be allowed. <HI>Nullum pec∣catum necessarium</HI>; no sin is necessary unless there be a necessity to be damned.</P>
<P>§. The first fallacy of <HI>measuring Justice</HI> by for∣cible power and possession, is a giant or monster arising from the earth; The second which <HI>mea∣sures gain by godliness,</HI> and <HI>godliness by gain,</HI> or propounds a necessity of <HI>doing evil that good may come thereby,</HI> are <HI>Meteors</HI> which rise from an higher region indeed, but they are both alike <HI>prodigious</HI> to any Church or State where they appear, and prove very pestilential to mankind in both respects civil and sacred.</P>
<P>§. My answer (then) to the <HI>Question, What Ju∣stice is</HI>? must be no other than that, which of old
<PB N="27" REF="19"/>
all wise men and the Apostle gives, that is, <HI>To render or preserve to every one their due; Justitia est quae suum cui{que} tribuit. Id suum cui{que} quod debitum; Id debitum quod à Deo &amp; natura datum, aut lege de∣signatum</HI>; that is a mans own and due to him which is either by God or Nature given, or is by Law assi∣gned to him.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>Platonists</HI> answer well to this (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) what is just? That which is according to law; <HI>What is lawful?</HI> That which is <HI>rational; What is rational</HI>? that which is <HI>diuine</HI>; what is <HI>Divine</HI>? that which is <HI>best and eternal</HI>; most worthy of God and most useful for mankind.</P>
<P>§. <HI>Justice</HI> is to be considered in <HI>three main things</HI>;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iustice in the fountain.</NOTE> first in its fountain and original, the wisdom and will of God, which is the exactest measure, and infallible rule of Justice in it self; <HI>sufficit quod Deus voluit,</HI> as <HI>Salvian</HI> speaks; <HI>voluntas Dei summa ratio &amp; lex suprema</HI>; not only in the divine nature, as the Arch-type of all <HI>perfections,</HI> but in those revelations of it to Angels &amp; mankind; either by those, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>common principles</HI> of <HI>reason,</HI> to which all men (in their wits) must and will consent, which are (<HI>lex nata</HI>) the law written in <HI>our hearts</HI>;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 2.</NOTE> as it were the common law of all mankind (<HI>jus gentium</HI>) or by those further express <HI>mandates</HI> which God gives to any either by immediate revelation, or by such credible derivations of it to others, for the traditi∣on of his word, by speech or writing, as his wisdom thinks fit to use.</P>
<P>§ Hence are all <HI>good laws of Church and State,</HI> of civil and religious concerns derived: By these all
<PB N="28" REF="20"/>
are tried and confirmed <HI>as good and just,</HI> and ac∣cordingly ought to be established as valid by <HI>civil sanction</HI> or consent; by these all matters of <HI>commuta∣tive</HI> or <HI>distributive justice</HI> are dispensed, which ei∣ther exchange for such <HI>compensations</HI> as are mu∣tually agreed upon, according as one <HI>wants,</HI> and another <HI>abounds</HI> in any thing; or else such distri∣butions are adjudged to any as are grounded on the law; Or lastly; such <HI>recompences</HI> are made to every man by reward or punishment as his <HI>actions</HI> do merit, either <HI>good or bad,</HI> in reference to the <HI>publick welfare,</HI> for the encouraging of <HI>well doing,</HI> or <HI>suppressing of evil.</HI></P>
<P>§. Here the <HI>moral law</HI> of God binds <HI>all men al∣ways</HI>; the <HI>Political laws</HI> of God bind no further than that <HI>proportion of moral justice, piety,</HI> and <HI>prudence</HI> which appears in them, according as the parallel state of times, <HI>and persons, and actions</HI> may be; in which the consent and <HI>submission</HI> of the <HI>major part</HI> of men, or <HI>long custom, and settled constitutions</HI> in any <HI>Polity</HI> have the <HI>force of a law,</HI> and are a rule of <HI>Politick Justice</HI>; provided they bind to nothing <HI>immoral</HI> or <HI>irreligious.</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iustice in the c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stern.</NOTE>Secondly, <HI>Justice</HI> is considerable in the grand cistern and conservatory (as the <HI>brazen Sea</HI> in the <HI>Sanctuary,</HI> which served the Temple with water) which is the <HI>Soveraign</HI> and <HI>Legislative power</HI> in every Society and Polity, as it is circumscribed and con∣tained in its proper <HI>bounds, and peculiar limits</HI>; this is the center of <HI>Order, Ʋnity, Justice and Peace politick</HI>; this dividing and dashing against it self by <HI>Caesar</HI> and <HI>Pompey,</HI> by <HI>Senate</HI> and <HI>People,</HI> by <HI>King</HI> and <HI>Parliament,</HI> by <HI>Emperors</HI> and <HI>Electors,</HI> all Ju∣stice,
<PB N="29" REF="20"/>
<HI>Order</HI> and <HI>Peace</HI> are destroyed; the leak in this sinks all; there must be a fixed <HI>Soveraignty</HI> un∣der God, to whose Justice <HI>and Power paramount,</HI> all must submit according to law; <HI>contestations</HI> in this run all things to <HI>confusions,</HI> as our sad experi∣ence hath taught us: Here either <HI>Prince,</HI> or <HI>State,</HI> or <HI>Peers</HI> or <HI>People,</HI> may severally have the <HI>Sove∣raignty of Justice,</HI> under several polities or forms of government; or there may be such a <HI>tempera∣ment,</HI> both as to <HI>legislation, jurisdiction,</HI> and <HI>execu∣tion</HI> of Laws by legal power, as may best relieve people in their grievances by <HI>Parliamentary repre∣sentatives</HI>; and best judge of differences by sworn <HI>Judges,</HI> and best execute all <HI>legal sentences</HI> and <HI>de∣crees</HI> by an <HI>eminent power</HI> in a <HI>Soveraign Prince, King</HI> or <HI>Emperor,</HI> which is best <HI>for all estates</HI>; and such is that admirable constitution of <HI>Soveraign Majesty</HI> in <HI>England,</HI> from which all Laws are <HI>en∣acted,</HI> by which they are <HI>declared,</HI> and with which they are justly and <HI>effectually executed,</HI> inclusive of and adapted to all <HI>just interests</HI> of <HI>King, Lords and Commons.</HI></P>
<P N="3">§. 3.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iustice in the conduits.</NOTE> <HI>Justice</HI> is considerable in the <HI>pipes and con∣duits</HI> of a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l <HI>subordinate Magistrates,</HI> through which, (as <HI>blood in the veins</HI>) it flows from the chief <HI>Justi∣ciaries</HI> to the very <HI>petty Constables,</HI> for the relief of all sorts of people, which are as parts and <HI>mem∣bers</HI> (noble or less honorable) of that <HI>Body Politick,</HI> according as the Law doth adjudge to every one their due; the measure of all is either <HI>(recta ratio) right Reason,</HI> or <HI>sacra Scriptura,</HI> the holy Scripture, or (<HI>lex terrae</HI>) the law of the Land, to which all are subjected by their <HI>consent; He is just</HI> who looks
<PB N="30" REF="21"/>
to these; <HI>who willingly</HI> submits to them, and ex∣actly observes them.</P>
<P N="1"><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iustice to God</NOTE>§. 1. There is a <HI>Justice due to God</HI> above all, on which his <HI>commands</HI> in the first table are founded; To <HI>own him, love, fear, reverence, adore, admire, obey, trust in, depend on, joy in and enjoy</HI> him as the su∣preme good:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mal. 5.6.</NOTE> <HI>If I be a Father or Master, where is my fear?</HI></P>
<P N="2"><NOTE PLACE="marg">Selves▪</NOTE>§. 2. There is a <HI>Justice due to our selves,</HI> in <HI>cha∣stity, sanctity, and sobriety,</HI> to keep up the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) <HI>Imperial power of Reason</HI> and <HI>Religion,</HI> above that (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) <HI>Democracy and Anarchy</HI> of lusts <HI>and passions</HI> which fight and rebell against God and the soul; here every <HI>vertue</HI> is a <HI>branch</HI> or fruit of <HI>Justice,</HI> as every <HI>vice</HI> is an act or habit of <HI>In∣justice</HI> (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, as <HI>Clem. Alex.</HI> out of the <HI>Platonists</HI> observes) every <HI>sinful</HI> and <HI>inordinate passion</HI> or <HI>action,</HI> either comes short, or shoots beyond, or wide of Justice, which con∣sists in the <HI>medium,</HI> as in a <HI>line</HI> or <HI>point indivisible.</HI></P>
<P N="3"><NOTE PLACE="marg">Others.</NOTE>§. 3. There is also a <HI>Justice</HI> to others, void of all <HI>fraud</HI> or <HI>force</HI>; of which as the Word of God in <HI>general,</HI> and the Laws of every Polity in <HI>special,</HI> so the <HI>dictates</HI> of every mans <HI>own reason,</HI> his duly reformed, <HI>and well composed conscience,</HI> are dome∣stick <HI>Dictators</HI> (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, as <HI>Synesius</HI> observes) God has made every mans <HI>rational Will the Monitor of justice</HI>; hence men are a law in many things to themselves, and their <HI>own thoughts</HI> do accuse or <HI>excuse</HI> their <HI>actions</HI>; hence unjust men, who act by <HI>fraud</HI> or <HI>force,</HI> though never so successful, yet are (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> &amp; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) <HI>self-condemned,</HI> and without any <HI>Apologie; Prima
<PB N="31" REF="21"/>
est haec ultio, quod se Judice nemo nocens absolvitur</HI>; And <HI>Exemplo quodcun{que} malo committitur ipsi Dis∣plicet autori</HI>; every unjust doer, as he is his own greatest <HI>tempter</HI> and <HI>Traytor</HI>; so he will be his own <HI>summoner,</HI> accuser, <HI>witness, tormenter</HI> and <HI>Executi∣oner; (sibi poena omnis inordinatus animus</HI>) as St.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 4<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>1.</NOTE> <HI>Austin</HI>: So <HI>Josephs brethren</HI> accuse themselves first as guilty of their <HI>brothers blood</HI>; they must needs be sooner or later (<HI>Magor-missabib</HI>) terrors to themselves, who are by their unjust dealings in∣jurious to others, and a <HI>terror</HI> to the <HI>land of the li∣ving</HI> by their oppressions. But I have done with the Theory of Justice, in its Source, Derivations and Practiques.</P>
<P>I come now to the second main <HI>Postulate</HI> or <HI>de∣mand</HI> of God; <HI>mercy,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>:<NOTE PLACE="marg">3 Demand, Mercy.</NOTE> <HI>mise∣ricordia,</HI> or <HI>benignitas</HI> as it is variously rendred; This is <HI>divinissimum in divinitate, &amp; humanissimum in humanitate opus.</HI> Mercy is the most orient <HI>gem</HI> in the Crown of Gods <HI>attributes,</HI> and the greatest <HI>or∣nament as well as relief</HI> of <HI>humane nature</HI>; It is the <HI>glo∣ry of God to pass by offences,</HI> to <HI>pardon sins,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 34.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> to tem∣per the rigor of his Justice: to supply <HI>defects,</HI> to help infirmities, and to save those sinners in his exceeding great <HI>mercy,</HI> whom he might have con∣demned in the <HI>extremitie</HI> of his Justice.</P>
<P>§. By <HI>mercy</HI> God is <HI>sui victor, &amp; seipso major,</HI> as it were <HI>greater than</HI> himself, and a <HI>conqueror of himself,</HI> A <HI>denyer of himself,</HI> and a sider with our <HI>interests</HI>; All our hopes and happiness are founded upon, and bound up in the <HI>mercy of God,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 103.8.</NOTE> which is above all his works and ours: In this fatherly be∣nignity all our blessings are contained; nor are we
<PB N="32" REF="22"/>
capable as St. <HI>Bernard</HI> speaks; of any other merit, than that is made up of <HI>Gods mercy</HI>; which is <HI>per∣ventive</HI> and <HI>plenary, beyond desert</HI> and <HI>desire,</HI> so ample, that none is denyed it, upon the tearmes offered;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 1 6</NOTE> Nor can it be ever exhausted for it indures for ever; yea and it is peculiar to mankind above the Angels.</P>
<P>§. From this great pattern of <HI>Gods mercy</HI> to such worthless <HI>wretches</HI> as we are, springs this demand, and demonstration, by which God requires us to be merciful as he our <HI>heavenly father</HI> is <HI>merciful</HI>; to imitate God in this, which is not more necessary so others, than our selves, since no man can shew so much mercy to others, as he either wants, or hath <HI>received himself.</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mercy in God.</NOTE>§. Mercy in God is a <HI>perfection of goodness,</HI> by which he moderates the <HI>severity of his Justice,</HI> to∣ward sinful mankind, yet without any diminution or blemish of his Justice, since it is by the suffering of <HI>Messias</HI> so satisfied, that while <HI>mercy rejoyceth,</HI> Justice hath no cause to <HI>complain.</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">In Man</NOTE>§. <HI>Mercy</HI> in man, is an <HI>affection,</HI> by which he lays to heart the misery of another, and is dispo∣sed to relieve them. Private mercies flow from a tender, soft, &amp; compassionate heart, sensible <HI>of Gods mercies to it self,</HI> which command it to recede in ma∣ny things from the <HI>rigor of Justice,</HI> and what of right it might either exact of, or inflict on another; No habit brings us neerer to God, or makes the face of man shine with a <HI>diviner</HI> beam of Glory, being the establisher of Princes Thrones,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 20.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>8.</NOTE> which are sup∣ported by Justice and Mercy.</P>
<P>§, In <HI>publique transactions,</HI> (whose weight most-what
<PB N="33" REF="22"/>
lyes upon, the <HI>cariage of Justice,) mercy</HI> doth not overthrow Justice, or divert it out of the way of rectitude (which is Gods High-way) but onely smooths the paths, and oyls the wheels, and sup∣plies the joynts, that Justice goes on with less cry and complaint, <HI>Mercy</HI> doth not take away the edge or point the of sword of Justice, but only that rust and cancker which makes it wounds fester too deep.</P>
<P>§. Mercy is an inseparable attendant to humane Justice; yea and to the Divine, in this world where God <HI>punisheth</HI> less and later than we deserve; and <HI>whatever is short of hell is mercy</HI>; It is <HI>because his com∣passions, fail not that we are not consumed.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Lam. 3.22.</NOTE> Saith <HI>Jeremiah</HI> in his <HI>bitterest lamenting.</HI></P>
<P>§. Where Justice falls heaviest on mens <HI>lives and estates,</HI> for the <HI>enormity of their sins,</HI> yet there is a beam of mercy to be shown them, as to their <HI>souls,</HI> by our prayers for their repentance and par∣don of God; the <HI>thief on the cross,</HI> justly suffering (as he confessed) for his <HI>misdeeds,</HI> yet tasted of the Divine <HI>mercy</HI> mixed with that bitter cup.</P>
<P>§. This mercy, <HI>benignity, moderation</HI> and <HI>compassi∣on,</HI> (of which you have had a large and good ac∣count in the former exercise) is a debt, or <HI>Justice,</HI> we owe to others, as much as we desire it our selves;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth. 18.27.</NOTE> and it is there seasonable, where common <HI>errors</HI> and <HI>infirmities,</HI> or <HI>vulgar simplicity</HI> and <HI>credulity,</HI> or <HI>easiness</HI> and <HI>sequaciousness</HI> do imitigate the ma∣lice, by mistake of doing Justice, or of reforming the Publique state (as in the silly peoples case,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Sam. 15.11.</NOTE> who followed <HI>Absolom</HI> in his popular rebellion) having so great a <HI>friend and wise a Counsellor as Achitophel</HI> to delude them <HI>Errabant sed bone animo,</HI> they ment
<PB N="34" REF="23"/>
well, though they did ill; Here Justice ought to look more at the <HI>malice</HI> of the heart, than the <HI>iniquity</HI> of the fact; As that is true (<HI>comittunt eadem diverso crimina fato</HI>; so <HI>diverso affectu</HI>) men do the same things from <HI>different designes</HI> and <HI>principles</HI>; some out of <HI>zeal</HI> to Justice, reformation and religion, others out of faction, Ambition, <HI>Courteousnes,</HI> Envy and Rebellion.</P>
<P>§. As <HI>common infirmities, epidemick errors,</HI> and <HI>popular delusions,</HI> do make way for mercy, so also multitudes of offenders. Christ had <HI>compassion on the multitudes</HI> more then once;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h. 9.36. and 14.14.</NOTE> not only <HI>quia mise∣ri,</HI> but <HI>quia multi</HI>; to make promiscuous massacres and <HI>havocks of</HI> them, when it is in the power of <HI>Justices to punish or spare them,</HI> is <HI>barbarous</HI> and <HI>in∣humane</HI>: It was a word of <HI>Clemency</HI> worthy of <HI>Ce∣sars</HI> great mind, at the <HI>Pharsalian battel, Parcite civibus</HI>: Spare our <HI>Countrimen</HI> and <HI>fellow Citi∣sens.</HI></P>
<P>§. Multitudes of <HI>Offenders</HI> are best punished in their Ring-leaders, setters, and agitators: whose sufferings due <HI>to their malice,</HI> are not more just and necessary for the publique, then remissions are to the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) many, who do as it were so <HI>crowd up Ju∣stice,</HI> that they pinion its armes; it cannot well ex∣ert its power upon them. Too much blood-letting is as dangerous, as some may be necessary for <HI>health.</HI></P>
<P>§. So also <HI>penitents</HI> are objects of mercy; who so con∣fess and deplore their former errors, and offences, that they give great hopes of future <HI>compensations,</HI> by the revenge they take of <HI>themselves. Pene inno∣cens <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uem peccasse poenitet Greg. M.</HI> when more
<PB N="35" REF="23"/>
ashamed for their sin, then affraid of their punish∣ment, these are objects of mercy and moderation; especially if there be any thing to plead for their excuse, as free from the great <HI>offences</HI> and <HI>presump∣tious sinnings,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 29.11, 13</NOTE> as in point of <HI>wilful murther</HI> and <HI>desti∣nate villany,</HI> of which God hath said thine <HI>eye</HI> shall not <HI>pitty, nor thy hand spare</HI>; least the Land be de∣filed <HI>with blood,</HI> or idolatry.</P>
<P>§. Here it is <HI>crudelis misericordia, &amp; stulta cle∣mentia,</HI> to spare such, whose impunity would not not onely seem to lessen the enormity of their sins, but <HI>expose the publique</HI> to <HI>infinite</HI> hazards: in gi∣ving encouragement by such <HI>cruel pitty and foolish clemency</HI>; In some cases, <HI>severe Justice</HI> is the great∣est <HI>mercy</HI> to the publique, that men may <HI>hear</HI> and <HI>fear</HI> and do no <HI>more so presumptuously; ne crudeli &amp; intempestiva miserecordia plectatur respublica; Thousands of innocents are oft punished,</HI> when some few <HI>facinorous nocents</HI> are spared; Their impuni∣ty becomes many times the publique <HI>sin and punish∣ment,</HI> and the Nation is make <HI>God-father,</HI> or <HI>dry nurse</HI> by not punishing those sins, of which it justly abhors to have been the <HI>Father</HI> or doer.</P>
<P>§. Yet are there but few <HI>cases,</HI> wherein <HI>summum jus is required</HI>; although that saying be true <HI>in grand and publiques concerns,</HI> which are the polar points and hinges of civil peace, <HI>fiat justitia ruat caelum</HI>; let Justice be done what evercome of it; Yet it is as true in most cases, which are capable of any <HI>remis∣sion</HI> and moderation, <HI>Fiat justitia, ruet caelum; if thou (Lord)</HI> shouldst <HI>be extream to mark what is done amiss,</HI> who <HI>can abide it</HI>;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 130.3.</NOTE> without Gods mercy to us, and ours to our <HI>brethren</HI> the offenders, our
<PB N="36" REF="24"/>
heaven is lost; judgment without mercy shall be to those,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iames 2.13.</NOTE> that shew no mercy.</P>
<P>§. <HI>Delayes</HI> also, as to execution of <HI>Justice,</HI> (as <HI>David</HI> used to <HI>Joab</HI> and others,) are publique mer∣cies many times, when the factious <HI>influence</HI> of <HI>cri∣minous</HI> men is so great and popular that they cannot at present <HI>be punished</HI> without endangering the <HI>pub∣lique</HI> peace.</P>
<P>§. But I have done with this <HI>second particular,</HI> which God requires, as to mercy; which who so shews to others, shews it to himself; for of all things we do well, the works of mercy shall not go unrewarded.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">3. Humility. Luke 17.10.</NOTE>Thirdly, <HI>Humility</HI> is required; which is a most <HI>most Christian grace,</HI> no less than a most <HI>manly ver∣tue,</HI> becoming all men. 1. In the sense of their <HI>common infirmities, and mortal condition.</HI> 2. In the conscience of their <HI>many sins, and deserved miseries.</HI> 3. In the reflexion upon their <HI>best actions,</HI> full of failing and defects; besides their unproficiency as to God when they have done all.</P>
<P>Here nothing becomes man more, or more sets off what he doth, than the <HI>deepest shadow of humility</HI>; both toward <HI>all mankind,</HI> who are of the same met∣tal, mould and make with him; and <HI>toward God,</HI> to whom he ows all he <HI>is,</HI> or <HI>hath,</HI> or <HI>can do</HI>; for what hath he in <HI>nature</HI> or <HI>providence,</HI> in soul, body or estate,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 4.7.</NOTE> <HI>which he hath not received?</HI></P>
<P>§. <HI>Pride</HI> destroys and sowres all the good even of <HI>Justice and Mercy</HI> that any man doth: It hath its first patern from the <HI>Devil,</HI> who by pride fell from the <HI>Heaven of blessed Angels,</HI> to the <HI>Hell of damned spirits: Humility</HI> hath God for the great
<PB N="37" REF="24"/>
example, no less than Justice and Mercy have; by this we draw nearest to God, and are fittest to ac∣cord with him; by this we are partakers of the <HI>divine nature,</HI> of <HI>Christs Spirit,</HI> graces, and <HI>re∣wards.</HI></P>
<P>§. <HI>Pride,</HI> (which is its <HI>own Idol and Idolater</HI>) its <HI>own Carver</HI> and <HI>Comforter,</HI> hath its <HI>reward</HI> onely from it self, or the vain world; for <HI>God resisteth the proud</HI>; and they must be sure to be destroyed <HI>who dash against God.</HI></P>
<P>§. Hell is the <HI>pit and prison of proud Angels and men</HI>;<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Per. 1.4.</NOTE> the first (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> &amp; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) they kept not <HI>their station</HI> or <HI>rank</HI>; but lifted up themselves to be like <HI>to the most high,</HI> beyond what was due to them: The second, because as <HI>Pharoah</HI> and <HI>Nebu∣chadnezzar,</HI> they rob God of his glory, both as to the <HI>justice</HI> which forbears to <HI>destroy them</HI> as they deserved, and as to that <HI>Mercy which was conferred upon them</HI> beyond any merit in them.</P>
<P>Secondly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">These three considered in their practicks</NOTE> As I have thus briefly considered these <HI>Three Subjects, Justice, Mercy and Humility</HI> in them∣selves; so I am with like brevity to consider the <HI>pre∣dicates</HI> or <HI>actions</HI> applied to each of them.</P>
<P N="1">1. To <HI>do justice.</HI> First, <HI>Materially,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">The acts or exercises of three Vertues.</NOTE> as to the <HI>me∣rit of the cause</HI> and <HI>person.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, <HI>Regularly,</HI> as to the Law prescribed by God or man, not by private <HI>opinion,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1. To do Iu∣stice.</NOTE> <HI>presumpti∣on</HI> or <HI>passion.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, <HI>Authoritatively,</HI> by due order and com∣mission derived <HI>to thee,</HI> from the lawful supreme power; for however all men must have the <HI>inward principles</HI> and desires for <HI>justice</HI>; yet the doing or executing of it is not given to all, but only those
<PB N="38" REF="25"/>
to whom the <HI>sword of justice</HI> is committed by the <HI>Law of God and man;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 13.4.</NOTE> <HI>Christs question</HI> must be asked before a man does justice, <HI>Who hath made me a judge or Ruler</HI>?<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luk. 12.14.</NOTE> A man may be very <HI>unjust</HI> in pu∣nishing the greatest and most <HI>notorious offenders, without due authority</HI> derived <HI>to him.</HI></P>
<P>Fourthly, <HI>Do justice, formalizer</HI>; as to the inward <HI>form, principle,</HI> or conscience, for <HI>justice sake,</HI> not for <HI>ambition</HI> as <HI>Absolom,</HI> or <HI>reward,</HI> or <HI>revenge,</HI> or <HI>glory,</HI> &amp;c. A Judge may give a just <HI>sentence</HI> before man, and yet be an <HI>unjust Judge before God,</HI> when he doth what is just <HI>materially,</HI> but not <HI>mentally,</HI> as to his end and design; in doing <HI>Justice</HI> men must be <HI>sincere (&amp; hoc agere)</HI> make it their (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) business for Gods sake; or from a good conscience; <HI>for judgement is the Lords,</HI> as <HI>Moses</HI> tells the El∣ders.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 1.17.</NOTE></P>
<P N="5">5. <HI>Do Justice, practice,</HI> effectually; not only <HI>think</HI> and <HI>meditate,</HI> consult, vote, decree, enact and declare, or talk and plead, and dispute, and cavil or contend, but bring forth the <HI>fruits of righteous∣ness,</HI> that all may see them, and enjoy the benefit of them; just Laws made and never executed are as good seed sown upon barren ground, which never comes up beyond <HI>straw</HI> and <HI>wilde oats.</HI></P>
<P N="6">6. <HI>Do Justice, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Impartially</HI> (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) in all things, to all persons, poor and rich, not op∣pressing the <HI>rich</HI> because his fleece is large, nor the <HI>poor</HI> because his strength is small, and friends few:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 11.25. and 23.3.</NOTE> <HI>Aequum dicitur, quia aequat leges omnibus,</HI> as <HI>Varro</HI> observes: Justice must be streight or right, without warping, as equal and indifferent to all, <HI>blind as to the persons,</HI> though <HI>Eagle-eyed</HI> as to the cause and <HI>rule.</HI></P>
<P N="7"><PB N="39" REF="25"/>7. <HI>Do it speedily,</HI> especially in such cases, when the <HI>effects of justice</HI> are not <HI>penal</HI> but <HI>beneficial</HI>; Delays of <HI>Justice</HI> are so far denials, and so long un∣just, when it is in the <HI>power of a</HI> Judge, or <HI>Prince,</HI> or <HI>Magistrate</HI> to do it; no <HI>usury</HI> is so unjust, as that which makes advantages by <HI>dilatory justice</HI>: In <HI>penal effects</HI> of Justice, there <HI>dilatory executions</HI> may be more <HI>venial, and tolerable,</HI> because they are <HI>mixtures of mercy,</HI> and <HI>reprieves</HI> in order to <HI>repentance</HI>; for which God gives us the great pat∣tern, in his giving us space to repent, and being so slow to excute <HI>vengeance</HI> on us,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 106.</NOTE> though daily pro∣voked by us.</P>
<P N="8">8. Do it <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> (not <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, in rigor, but) in <HI>measure, judgement</HI> and <HI>proportion,</HI> as they said of old (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) God is an <HI>axact Geometritian,</HI> duly <HI>measuring</HI> and <HI>weighing,</HI> or <HI>pondering the acti∣ons</HI> of all men, and proportioning his <HI>judgements</HI> to them; so ought men to demean themselves in <HI>doing justice calmely,</HI> as in the <HI>cool of the day,</HI> with∣out <HI>passion,</HI> or <HI>transport. Perit judicium quum res tran∣sit inaffectum</HI>; the eyes of judgement are blinded, when the mists of any <HI>passions arise</HI>; either preju∣dicating the <HI>person</HI> for the <HI>cause,</HI> or the <HI>cause</HI> for the <HI>person.</HI></P>
<P N="9">9. <HI>Do justice,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, with <HI>humanity, pitty</HI> and compassion to the person, in the greatest severities against, and justest detestations of <HI>their sins</HI>; Ju∣stice among men, much more among Christians, must have not only <HI>vulnera,</HI> but also <HI>viscera, bowels</HI> as well as <HI>blows</HI>; Ingenuous Justice (<HI>dolet quoties cogitur esse ferox</HI>) is afflicted when compelled to <HI>inflict punishment</HI>; and feels the strokes <HI>it gives,</HI>
<PB N="40" REF="26"/>
condemning the Judge to <HI>commiseration,</HI> when he condemns others to <HI>misery</HI>; this tenderness or tem∣perament it learns from God, who deplores when he executeth,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hosea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 11.8.</NOTE> or <HI>denounceth</HI> his <HI>judgements; his bowels are turned within him,</HI> when he is forced to give over his people to the <HI>destroyers</HI>; hence are his many <HI>forewarnings, importunings</HI> and <HI>beseechings</HI> of men to <HI>flye from the wrath to come; as why will ye die? &amp;c.</HI> and <HI>How shall I give you over to be as Ad∣mah and Zeboim?</HI> how <HI>shall I make thee as Sodom and Gomorah?</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">To love Mercy Isa. 28.21.</NOTE>Secondly, To <HI>love Mercy</HI>; here first the order <HI>is observable,</HI> That <HI>Justice</HI> must first be done before <HI>Mercy</HI>; else it is as very <HI>preposterous</HI> to exclude Justice to make way for Mercy, as it is <HI>presumptu∣ous</HI> to do unjustly under pretence of shewing Mercy.</P>
<P>§. Like the design of some mens cruel charity to get an estate by all imjurious ways, in order to do works of charity, or to build an Alms-house, like the giving alms or legacies before we pay our debts.</P>
<P>§. Such Sacrifices are abominable to God; we must not rob the Exchequer of Justice, to put into the Corban or <HI>poor mans box</HI> of the sanctuary.</P>
<P N="2">§. 2. We may observe the <HI>emphasis</HI> of the word put to <HI>Mercy,</HI> beyond that is to <HI>Justice</HI>; this must be done as a <HI>work</HI> and task, which is enjoyned us; but the other <HI>Mercy,</HI> must be loved and delighted in: <HI>Justice</HI> is <HI>opus necessarium &amp; alienum,</HI> a neces∣sary, but strange and unwelcome work, compared to Mercy; in this also we have the precedent of the <HI>divine goodness</HI>; whose <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, pleasure and
<PB N="41" REF="26"/>
delight is in shewing mercy, where there is any ca∣pacity; but his executions of Justice, are as it were a <HI>pressure</HI> and <HI>distress</HI> upon him; not that he is not <HI>infinitely just</HI> to all the extents of Justice, but he is <HI>superinfinitely merciful,</HI> so as to set <HI>even bounds</HI> to the <HI>infinity of his justice,</HI> which as a consuming fire would in a moment have destroyed the whole cre∣ation of lapsed sinful natures, if Mercy had not in∣terceded.</P>
<P>§. This <HI>Affection of Love</HI> is conjoned to Mercy:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mercy must be loved.</NOTE> First, As <HI>(res in se amabilis)</HI> a thing in it self most <HI>lovely</HI> and desirable, one of the brightest beams of the divine beauty. Secondly, As that which is most <HI>beautiful</HI> and comely for mankind,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Col. 11.</NOTE> especially the Church of God, and children of their heavenly Fa∣ther, who are commanded to put on, as <HI>the elect of God, bowels of mercy: Bowels,</HI> as to the inward principle or love of it, and putting them on, as to outward <HI>manifestation</HI> in good works, which are the royalest robes and richest ornaments of <HI>Christians.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>Love mercy,</HI> as that which is most beneficial to our selves and others too; He that shews mer∣cy to others, shews it to his own soul; by way of re∣bound it returns into his own bosom; Mercy is that which all need, all desire in their distress, all have tasted of, and received from God.</P>
<P N="4">4. Love it in obedience to Gods commands, and in imitation of his <HI>divine perfections</HI>; among which not any is so commended to us as this; Not be ye wise and strong, and infinite and great, as your <HI>heavenly Father,</HI> but <HI>merciful.</HI> What <HI>Mat.</HI> 5.48. is put Be ye <HI>merciful,</HI> is <HI>Luk.</HI> 6.26. Be ye <HI>perfect, &amp;c.</HI> as if (<HI>in una misericordia omnes perfectiones</HI>) this
<PB N="42" REF="27"/>
one prefection of <HI>mercy</HI> included all.</P>
<P N="5">5. Love mercy (in <HI>augmentum gratiae</HI>) for the advance of all <HI>graces,</HI> for this is the compass or <HI>ma∣nure,</HI> which makes the richest soyl of a Christian <HI>soul</HI>; as a man sows mercy liberally, so he shall reap graces.</P>
<P N="6">6. Love mercy in <HI>ornamentum religionis Christianae,</HI> the best trial of the <HI>best religion</HI> is, that which abounds most with <HI>mercy,</HI> as the true God, who is <HI>optimus maximus,</HI> is <HI>greatest by his goodness,</HI> and best in his <HI>mercifulness.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Kings 20.31</NOTE> The Kings <HI>of Israel</HI> are esteemed mer∣ciful Kings; as mercy is the most <HI>humane,</HI> so the most <HI>Princely quality,</HI> because the divinest <HI>endow∣ment. Cruelty</HI> is one of the highest scandals of Christianity, which makes <HI>Lambs of Lyons,</HI> and tames the feircest tempers.</P>
<P N="7">7. Love mercy (<HI>memor propriae. indigentiae &amp; mi∣seriae</HI>) remembring that sin which exposeth thee to misery, and that <HI>necessity</HI> thou hast of Gods <HI>mercy,</HI> yea and the want thou mayst have of <HI>mans</HI>; for no state of <HI>mortality,</HI> is so fixedly happy, but it may be (as <HI>Job</HI> was) the object of <HI>pitty,</HI> which the Tra∣gedies of our times have evidenced in the highest nature; <HI>voluit deus, ut sibi quis{que} sit mensura miseri∣cordiae,</HI> as St. <HI>Jerom</HI> tels us; they that flow most with mercy, shall be filled most with it.</P>
<P N="8">8. Love mercy (<HI>in spem &amp; Augmentum gloriae</HI>) in order to confirme thy hope, and increase <HI>thy re∣ward</HI> of Glory, there is no better evidence of a <HI>gracious heart</HI> and an <HI>excellent spirit,</HI> than this mer∣ciful <HI>propensity,</HI> even natural men, who have most <HI>humanity,</HI> are least distant from the Kingdome <HI>of hea∣ven</HI>; there wants but faith in Christ, (who is the
<PB N="43" REF="27"/>
highest instance, and <HI>grand exemplar</HI> of divine mercy, to raise up the grosser allayes of <HI>natural soft∣ness, compassion</HI> and <HI>gentleness,</HI> to the pure <HI>Elixir</HI> of that grace of <HI>merciful-mindedness,</HI> which God requires, and which denotes a Divine and <HI>heaven∣ly disposition</HI>; doubtless the <HI>mites of mercy,</HI> which we shew here to others for Christs sake, will be repayed with <HI>Talents</HI> in heaven, nor shall a cup of cold water be <HI>unrewarded.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. To walk humbly, the LXX.<NOTE PLACE="marg">3. To walk humbly with thy God.</NOTE> render it <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: to be ready and prepared to go with God, and the <HI>Latin vulg. humiliare se ambulan∣do</HI>; the words imply.</P>
<P N="1">1. A freedome and familiarity of <HI>conversation,</HI> which cannot be had unless two are agreed; nor can there be any agreement with God, except where the heart is humble. God <HI>resists the proud, (quia congreditur cum deo tanquam hostis ex parte ad∣versa)</HI> who doth not walk with God, but against him, as one that <HI>justles, assaults, encounters,</HI> and <HI>fights</HI> against him</P>
<P N="2">2. Walking as it is a social and friendly motion, so it is progressive and parellel, in a way of confor∣mity, not contrariety, when we keep pace with God, neither <HI>out-running</HI> his word by a precipitant wantonness, and over-righteousness of our own imaginations, nor yet so lagging behinde as we lose God, nor yet straying to the right or left hand di∣verticles, of prophanness or superstition, of <HI>de∣spare</HI> or <HI>presumption,</HI> but keeping close with God, who <HI>looks on the proud afar off,</HI> because they are still at distance from him, one way or other.</P>
<P N="3">3. As an humble man is onely fit for Gods
<PB N="44" REF="28"/>
presence, and company, so the more a <HI>man walks</HI> with God, the more he will <HI>grow humble,</HI> when he sees what an inconsiderable nothing himself is, <HI>Nihilo nihilius,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 19.4, 5. and 61.9.</NOTE> less then nothing; at <HI>his very best estate altogether vanity</HI>; at his worst <HI>onely sin, hell</HI> and <HI>misery,</HI> fit company for none but <HI>Divels,</HI> and that fatal sentence, <HI>Go ye cursed</HI>; nothing in merits, nothing in graces, nothing in guifts, nothing in duties, <HI>Toti sumus indigentia,</HI> we are altogether defect and emptiness, till grace fills us, and Christ supplies us; we shall easily vanish and disappear as to all self conceit, and pride of heart, when once we <HI>assiociate with God</HI>; then <HI>Abraham</HI> and <HI>Job</HI> abhor themselves in dust and ashes, (both eminent persons, the one the great <HI>Father of the faithful,</HI> the other the great <HI>pattern of patience</HI>) so <HI>Jacob,</HI> less then the least <HI>of Gods mercies</HI>; and St. <HI>Paul</HI> who was not inferiour to the <HI>chief Apostles,</HI> and laboured more abundantly then any one of them, yet sums up his all in this,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Cor. 11.12.</NOTE> <HI>though I am nothing,</HI> esteeming <HI>Christ</HI> to be all in all to him.</P>
<P N="4">4. <HI>Walk humbly (cum Deo quia Deus, &amp; quia tuus)</HI> because with God, and with thy God; a <HI>Son</HI> and <HI>Subject</HI> will know himself best when with a King and Father, who is their own; however they may carry themselves high to others their betters, yet not to those, whose neer relation and high merit command observance. If the thought of Gods ex∣cellency doth not abase us in our own eyes, yet the consideration of his condescending to us, to be ours in so many undeserved <HI>mercies,</HI> and <HI>favours,</HI> to a <HI>transcendency</HI> of desert, and <HI>unrequitable obligati∣ons,</HI> this will <HI>deplume</HI> us, and pull down all <HI>high
<PB N="45" REF="28"/>
immaginations</HI> in us, It is ignorance of God, and distance from him, which make us so conceited of our selves, a spark or star cannot glory in the light of the sun.</P>
<P N="5">5. Especially when we remember (<HI>humilem deum &amp; humiliatum Christum pro nobis)</HI> an humble <HI>God,</HI> in our <HI>humbled Saviour</HI> for us; the sight and sense of Christ on the <HI>Cross,</HI> for our sakes, will make us asha∣med of one <HI>proud thought</HI> or high look, which is not tolerable in any estate, in the greatest guifts and graces, the best endowments, and highest successes, wherein we are but instruments, and seconds, not principals; And in the greatest <HI>afflictions,</HI> when we are (<HI>humiliati</HI>) most humbled and debased by Gods providence, it is very <HI>insutable</HI> then to <HI>boyl</HI> and <HI>swell</HI> with thoughts of <HI>repining</HI> and <HI>murmuring</HI> against God, as if he injured us, or treated us unwor∣thy of us. No, here to be humble, is to be silent,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lev 16.41.</NOTE> and <HI>submisse</HI> to <HI>pray,</HI> to <HI>prostrate at Gods feet,</HI> to <HI>accept of the punishment,</HI> and own it as from <HI>a Father,</HI> who chastiseth us, that we may not be condemned, with the world; humility disarms God, and is a salve, shield and <HI>cordial,</HI> in the worst estate, which is then best for us when we grow more humble, as <HI>pride</HI> is a moth or curse, that blasts all, even the best we are, injoy or do, <HI>Alienating God</HI> from us, and driving away his good <HI>Spirit,</HI> when it finds us <HI>our own Gods</HI> and <HI>worshippers.</HI> It is but just to leave us to the <HI>heaven</HI> of <HI>our own fancies,</HI> and to be satis∣fied <HI>with our own delusions.</HI></P>
<P>Third General, <HI>Cui,</HI> to whom God shews,<NOTE PLACE="marg">so whom this Demonstrati∣on and de∣mand is made.</NOTE> and of whom he requires these great lessons and du∣ties; <HI>Thee O man.</HI></P>
<P N="1"><PB N="46" REF="29"/>1. To all <HI>mankind in general,</HI> as creatures ca∣pable to know good and evil, just and unjust, and accordingly to chuse and do as they are directed from the inward <HI>dictates of right reason,</HI> and those self-convincing principles which are within their own <HI>consciences.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. To <HI>thee O man</HI> more especially, who enjoyest the <HI>light of Gods Word</HI> in the <HI>pale</HI> and <HI>bosom</HI> of the <HI>Church,</HI> where the <HI>righteous precepts</HI> and <HI>merci∣ful commands</HI> of God are more evidently set forth, by laws repeated, by examples multiplied, by <HI>judgements</HI> and <HI>rewards</HI> proportioned to mens works; none here can plead <HI>ignorance</HI> of duty both to God and man.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>Thee O man,</HI> in thy particular station, as occa∣sion and power are put into thy hand, whether Jew or Gentile, great or small, rich or poor, Prince or Peasant, Lords or Commons, Priest or people; no man is unconcerned in these <HI>Demonstrations</HI>; to every one God says as <HI>Nathan</HI> did to <HI>David, Thou art the man.</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Of Kings and S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>aign Ma∣gistrates.</NOTE>§. God requires <HI>Justice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>Humility</HI> of thee <HI>O King,</HI> who sittest on the <HI>throne of Majesty,</HI> who art in <HI>Gods stead,</HI> as his <HI>Vicegerent,</HI> a kind of <HI>mortal Deity</HI>; honored with the name, and vested with the power of God, and much more with the <HI>imitations</HI> of the <HI>divine excellencies</HI> of <HI>Justice</HI> and <HI>Mercy</HI> toward man,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 22.15, 16.</NOTE> as of <HI>Humility</HI> toward God; <HI>Shalt thou reign because thou closest thy self in cedar, and art compassed about with strong guards? Did not thy Father do justice and mercy, and then it was well with him: He judged the cause of the poor and needy, was not this to know me, saith the Lord?</HI> Thou, even
<PB N="47" REF="29"/>
thou, O King art to <HI>fear him</HI> who is <HI>King of Kings and Lord of Lords, higher than the highest</HI>; the <HI>ter∣ror of Tytants,</HI> who pulleth <HI>Princes from their seat, and poureth contempt upon all their glory</HI>; thy surest policy is true piety, and the best reason of State is this <HI>pure Religion and undefiled,</HI> even to <HI>do Justice, to love Mercy, and walk humbly with that God by whom Kings raign, Whose thrones</HI> are not to be <HI>estab∣lished</HI> without <HI>Justice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>Humility</HI>; Nor can they be injured so much by any as by themselves; their <HI>Pride</HI> before God, like <HI>Nebuchadnezzars</HI> and <HI>Belshazzars,</HI> will abase them; and their oppression of <HI>their people,</HI> will most oppress themselves at last.</P>
<P>Secondly, Of <HI>Thee O wise man,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Of Counsel∣lors, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> and <HI>mighty Coun∣sellor,</HI> who art esteemed by others and thy self as a great <HI>State Intelligence</HI>; digging deep for coun∣sels, and wrapping up thy self in the darkness of thy cloudy projects and designs; thou who glori∣est in thy <HI>Oracular Policies</HI> as <HI>Achitophel</HI>; and disdainest to be <HI>nonplust</HI> in thy <HI>wisdom,</HI> or <HI>defeated</HI> in thy <HI>designs</HI>: Of thee the Lord requires to give no <HI>counsel</HI> but such as is just, nor to <HI>decree</HI> other than <HI>righteous decrees</HI>: To agitate nothing in <HI>Coun∣cils of State</HI> and <HI>Parliaments</HI> by partiality, faction, and oppression, to sinister ends and unjust inte∣rests either of Prince of people; because the <HI>Lord sitteth among Senators,</HI> and will cause a just de∣cree without mercy to be executed upon those who either execute or <HI>decree unrighteous</HI> and cruel things.</P>
<P>Thirdly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of Magi∣strates.</NOTE> Of <HI>Thee O subordinate Iudge</HI> and Ma∣gistrate: <HI>O great Lawyer</HI> and <HI>eloquent Pleader,</HI> the
<PB N="48" REF="30"/>
Lord repuires not to turn Justice into <HI>gall,</HI> and Judgement to <HI>wormwood</HI>; not to <HI>judge for reward,</HI> or pervert the cause of any, either for <HI>fear or fa∣vour,</HI> or for respect of persons; not to make plea∣dings of Law to be as <HI>gins</HI> and <HI>snares</HI> to <HI>innocent simplicity,</HI> by a <HI>fallacious sophistry,</HI> and <HI>dilatory fe∣lony,</HI> which robs the Clients purse, as the bushes and brambles do the sheep of his fleece, when he seeks and hopes for shelter from them.</P>
<P>§, No temporal advantage can counterpoise the detriment and danger which unjust and merciless actions bring upon those who willingly offend against the laws of the just and merciful God, and thereby incur eternal damnation, deserving to be <HI>beaten</HI> with many <HI>stripes,</HI> because they know the will of <HI>God,</HI> and do it not. St. <HI>Bernards Motto</HI> to all judges is, <HI>omnia judicata rejudicabuntur,</HI> what comes short in mans <HI>measure,</HI> or weight of <HI>Justice,</HI> shall be made up by Gods eternal recom∣pences.</P>
<P N="4"><NOTE PLACE="marg">Of Soldiers and men of might.</NOTE>4. Of thee O <HI>Soldier</HI>; O <HI>valiant</HI> and <HI>mighty man,</HI> who hast power in thy hand to <HI>save</HI> or <HI>destroy,</HI> to kill poor men, and lay wast <HI>fenced Cities,</HI> of thee God requires justice and mercy, which must be the measures of <HI>War,</HI> as well as of <HI>Peace</HI>; there are (<HI>jura belli</HI>) laws of <HI>righteousness</HI> and <HI>moderation,</HI> which God exacts in <HI>wars,</HI> even defensive, which seem the onely wars that can be <HI>just:</HI> For sure to make war without some <HI>precedent</HI> or <HI>threatned in∣jury,</HI> must needs be very <HI>injurious.</HI> Not <HI>might</HI> but right must be looked at, where the lives of men are <HI>concerned</HI>; justice is not to be measured by the <HI>length of thy sword,</HI> or the strength of thy Arme,
<PB N="49" REF="30"/>
or the number of thy Soldiers, but by the <HI>Laws of God,</HI> of <HI>Nations</HI> and of <HI>every polity</HI>: The Justest <HI>war,</HI> must not by passionate <HI>transports</HI> be carryed on to unjust, exorbitant, and cruel oppressions, either to <HI>harmless</HI> and <HI>unarmed</HI> people, or to <HI>immo∣derate demands,</HI> in point of reveng and compen∣sation, much less to build <HI>ambitious Babels,</HI> and <HI>co∣vetous confiscations,</HI> upon others <HI>ruines</HI>; The Sol∣diers had their <HI>lesson</HI> of <HI>John Baptist,</HI> what to do, when they had so much grace as to ask the <HI>question,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luk. 3 14.</NOTE> they are not commanded to lay down their Armes, but to do <HI>violence to no man, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P N="5">5. Of thee O man, (God requires Justice, mer∣cy and humility) whose prosperity either in <HI>violent</HI> or <HI>injurious ways,</HI> have made thee rich and great,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of the most prosperous.</NOTE> or who increasest thy estate by that, which is not thine in equity and conscience, who makest no scruple of <HI>Extortion, rapine, racking rents, sacriledge, op∣pression,</HI> and <HI>rigorous extortions</HI>; who hast built thy nest on high, and feathered it with the <HI>spoils,</HI> either of thy <HI>Neighbours</HI> and <HI>Tennants,</HI> or of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> of the <HI>Crown</HI> and <HI>Crosier,</HI> where cheap pur∣chases, witness to your faces, and upbraid both <HI>byars</HI> and sellers of the <HI>injustice</HI> of the <HI>bargain</HI>; thou, even <HI>thou,</HI> must so repent by making <HI>restitution</HI> of unjust <HI>acquisitions,</HI> as may make thee capable of <HI>Gods pardon,</HI> who will not be mocked by <HI>lame</HI> and crackt titles; nor may be robbed, without making the curse threatned to light on such injurious &amp; pre∣sumptuous sinners, who neither fear God nor reve∣rence man; though great, and rich, and many, though <HI>Courts</HI> and <HI>Councils,</HI> and <HI>Armies,</HI> and whole <HI>Nations conspire</HI> to do <HI>injustly,</HI> yet will God be a swift
<PB N="50" REF="31"/>
witness against them, and bring his Justice upon them.</P>
<P N="6"><NOTE PLACE="marg">O Ministersf of the Church</NOTE>6. Of thee O <HI>godly gull,</HI> and <HI>holy-cheat,</HI> who pleadest an hypocritical <HI>nonplus,</HI> and a state <HI>necessity</HI> of doing somthings, both <HI>injust</HI> and <HI>cruel,</HI> in order to do good, to <HI>advance Justice,</HI> to <HI>glorifie God,</HI> to <HI>reform Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> as if the <HI>reasons</HI> and <HI>inte∣rests</HI> of both <HI>Religion and Justice</HI> did sometimes want <HI>unjust proceedings,</HI> (as pills to keep them in health) which <HI>Aristides</HI> pleaded by way of <HI>Irony,</HI> to those who impatient of exact <HI>Justice,</HI> forced him somtimes to deviate from it, by their <HI>popular peevishness</HI>; he told them he did it (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) in order to the pub∣lick good: God will discover these impudent fal∣lacies, and so punish the <HI>presumption</HI> of doing evil, that good may come thereby, that all men shall shall hear <HI>and fear, and confess there is a God that judgeth the earth,</HI> when they shall see vengeance to overtake these men, and the iniquity of their heels to compass them about.</P>
<P>§. Better to follow Gods counsel by doing Justice, though we perish with <HI>Lazarus on a dung-hill,</HI> and suffer the last strokes of <HI>humane Justice</HI> in this world, than to fall under Gods <HI>eternal</HI> and <HI>inexerable</HI> Ju∣stice, which will strip thee of all the goods thou gettest, and bring upon thee <HI>infinitely more evil</HI> than that, which by unjust and wicked means thou soughtest to escape; there is no necessity (<HI>scelera sceleribus tueri</HI>) to make <HI>evil deeds</HI> good by doing worser; it is the Devils hardning Maxim to damn souls by <HI>desperation</HI>; as if a theif should plead it necessary to kill that man whom he hath rob∣bed,
<PB N="51" REF="31"/>
lest he be pursued and taken by him.</P>
<P N="7">7. Of thee,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of the glosing Hypocrites.</NOTE> O <HI>Minister of the Church and Pastor of souls,</HI> God requires, first to do justice to thy <HI>bro∣ther</HI> of the same tribe and calling, by not intruding thy self into his <HI>work,</HI> against <HI>right</HI> and <HI>reason</HI> and law, that thou mayst have a plea or pretence to the profits of his living, and so thou mayst feed thy self by <HI>feeding anothers flock</HI> against his will; when Justice requires us not onely to eat our own bread, but to do our own business, and not (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) to Vsurp on anothers either emolument or em∣ployment, which they are able and willing to per∣forme.</P>
<P>Of thee, O <HI>Church-man,</HI> great &amp; small God requires this Justice, to God, to Christ, to the Church, to peo∣ples souls, to the holy word and worship of God, to the truth of Doctrine, to the solemnity of his service, to the necessity of mens souls, by feed∣ing them with <HI>wholesome food,</HI> by giving them their <HI>portion in due season,</HI> by not denying the children their <HI>bread,</HI> for fear of dogs eating it, by admi∣nistring the blessed <HI>Sacraments</HI> duly and reverently, according as the Church, in which thou servest, hath appointed thee, not setting up and urging thy own fancies and <HI>whimseys,</HI> thy novel <HI>inventions</HI> and <HI>schismatical partialities,</HI> thy <HI>humane traditions,</HI> and <HI>unauthentick</HI> because <HI>uncatholick observations,</HI> in∣stead of <HI>Christs institutions,</HI> not so shy and startling at the shadow of some decent and innocent <HI>rites</HI> or circumstances and <HI>ceremonies</HI> in religion, as to fly from the <HI>unity, order, harmony</HI> and <HI>authority</HI> of the whole <HI>Church,</HI> by a supercilious, unjust and merciless severity, which savors too much of pride,
<PB N="52" REF="32"/>
and self conceit, hereby shaking and overthrow∣ing the faith of many poor souls, who are ignorant, weak and instable, by the <HI>perturbatious</HI> thy pragma∣tique and popular activity gives them.</P>
<P N="8"><NOTE PLACE="marg">Of the whole Nation.</NOTE>8. Lastly of thee, O <HI>whole Palestina,</HI> O <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> O my native <HI>County,</HI> and Nation, both in thy latitude and diffusion, and in thy <HI>Parliamenta∣ry▪ Epitome,</HI> or representation; of thee the Lord requires not only to do <HI>justice,</HI> but to shew mercy there, where is the cryingest injustice and cruelty in the world; There is a voyce from abroad and at home, which crys (<HI>Oro miserere laborum Tantorum, miserere animi non digna ferentis</HI>) O do not approve, confirm or adopt that pride, injustice and cruelty of some sons of <HI>Belial,</HI> who lifted up themselves above all that is called God; all <HI>Laws</HI> of <HI>God</HI> and <HI>man,</HI> all duty to their betters and Superiors.</P>
<P>§. If what hath been done in this sorely afflicted and abused nation, with expence of so much blood and treasures, with so much <HI>terror and extravagan∣cy,</HI> be well and worthily done; it will be an act of your Justice to assert it, and of your Mercy, to ab∣solve other of us poor scrupulous souls of those scruples of conscience which we have; of those fears and jealousies, lest the Nation lying under so <HI>great sins,</HI> may be exposed to Gods sorest judgements, even to an utter vastation.</P>
<P>§. But if it appear to your <HI>wisdom,</HI> piety, Justice and Mercy, to have been a <HI>violent</HI> and <HI>unparalleld</HI> method of <HI>presumptuous wickedness,</HI> of unjust cruel∣ty, and most cruel injustice; in which was neither <HI>matter</HI> nor <HI>form</HI> essential of Justice, under the for∣mality of high justice; if men have killed and co∣sened,
<PB N="53" REF="32"/>
and taken possession, even the spoil and <HI>price of blood</HI>: I doubt not but you will so far re∣member <HI>Gods Demonstrations and demands,</HI> as to do <HI>Justice to God,</HI> to your <HI>Country,</HI> to your <HI>Laws,</HI> to your <HI>Superior,</HI> to <HI>Soveraign power,</HI> to the whole <HI>Nation,</HI> and to all mankind, as to testifie a just ab∣horrence and <HI>perfect detestation</HI> of those things, to which as you would not have been <HI>Fathers,</HI> so I believe you will not be <HI>Godfathers.</HI> It is an usu∣al saying among <HI>Statists</HI> to excuse their <HI>excentrici∣ties</HI> and <HI>deviations,</HI> from the exact <HI>rules of justice (Nullum magnum exemplum justitiae sive aliqua in∣justitia</HI>; I am sure we have known <HI>magnum exem∣plum injustitiae sine aliqua justitia</HI>; a transcendent injustice, which had not any grains of justice in it) in the vindication of which, I do not so urge the rigor of <HI>justice,</HI> as not to require also such tem∣perament of <HI>mercy,</HI> as may distinguish between the flower and the bran, the <HI>vile</HI> and <HI>precious,</HI> the <HI>pertinacious</HI> and <HI>penitent</HI>; such as sinned with ma∣litious wickedness, with an high hand, and those that were only carried down the <HI>rapid torrent</HI> and strong <HI>delusions of times.</HI></P>
<P>§. There is yet one <HI>instance</HI> of doing <HI>justice</HI> and <HI>shewing Mercy</HI> to the whole Nation, which I cannot but recommend to my Country, and to you the <HI>Fathers of our families,</HI> and <HI>heads</HI> of our <HI>Tribes</HI>; which is in reference to the <HI>souls of many poor people,</HI> that in a <HI>land of plenty</HI> they may not be <HI>fa∣mished,</HI> for want of <HI>able and industrious Preachers,</HI> which cannot be had or expected (whatever ver∣bal severities are pretended of Reformation, of Religion, and propagation of the Gospel) unless
<PB N="55" REF="33"/>
there be some way found, by the wisdom, piety, honor and bounty of the <HI>Nation,</HI> of <HI>Prince, Parlia∣ment</HI> and <HI>People,</HI> for the competent <HI>maintenance</HI> of such Ministers as may do the <HI>work of God,</HI> and take <HI>care of mens souls</HI>: with what Justice or Mercy can you exact a <HI>full tale of bricks</HI> from poor <HI>Ministers when they have no straw</HI>? Alas, when shall the scandal of <HI>livings</HI> not worth fifty, or thirty, or twenty pounds a year be <HI>taken away</HI> by the <HI>ge∣nerosity, justice, liberality</HI> and <HI>mercy</HI> of <HI>England</HI>? How many years tax, how much treasure hath been spent, to maintain Soldiers and a war, of which the publick hath no <HI>fruit</HI> but those of tears, <HI>oppression</HI> and repentance; me thinks it should not seem much to <HI>allow one years tax</HI> to be gathered in some convenient time, by which to begin a banck or treasury (an <HI>aerarium sacrum</HI>) for the ma∣king some <HI>augmentations</HI> and purohases of <HI>Impro∣priations</HI> to <HI>poor livings</HI>: One good foundation laid for so great and good a <HI>work,</HI> many other super∣structures would easily be added by the <HI>piety, wis∣dom,</HI> and <HI>charity</HI> either of the publick or of the pri∣vate, and <HI>well-disposed persons.</HI></P>
<P>§. If this may not be put upon the account of <HI>Justice</HI> to be done to the <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>Clergy</HI> of <HI>Eng∣land</HI> in compensation of the many diminutions, de∣predations and indignities, which they have of late, or long since sustained, by the <HI>policies, powers</HI> or superstitions of <HI>later times</HI>; yet I beseech you look upon it as a signal and eminent act of <HI>Mercy,</HI> for which thousands of <HI>poor people</HI> in the Countries (<HI>who perish for want of knowledge,</HI> having <HI>no Pro∣phet nor seer among them</HI>) will bless God and you to many generations.</P>
<P><PB N="54" REF="33"/>§. And since God hath by a most miraculous <HI>re∣turn</HI> of mercy, brought you thus far to the morn∣ing <HI>of your redemption</HI> from civil slavery and op∣pression, where <HI>we were under Chams curse</HI> to be servants of servants. O bethink your selves, whe∣ther it be not worthy of your munificent piety and gratitude to offer some oblation of thankfulness as a <HI>peace-offering</HI> and Eucharistical monument to God and his Church; but I may not so far distrust your <HI>nobleness,</HI> as to urge you too far in this thing, which is so much its own Orator, and wherein many thousands both Ministers and people are silently and humbly importune for your favour in so great a concern of Church and State, yea of mens souls eternal welfare.</P>
<P>The Fourth and last <HI>General Head</HI> is (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) the manner of Gods <HI>shewing</HI> and <HI>requiring</HI> these duties of all sorts of men, in all occasions, times,<NOTE PLACE="marg">4. The man∣ner of Gods Demonstra∣ting.</NOTE> in all dealings and administrations, in the <HI>whole tenure</HI> of <HI>their conversation,</HI> to God and men, civil and re∣ligious.</P>
<P>I formerly gave an <HI>account of this,</HI> which will excuse me if I here briefly insist on some main heads only.</P>
<P N="1">1. God hath shewed it to mankind (<HI>in principiis internis</HI>) in those <HI>inward principles</HI> of <HI>right Reason,</HI> and that standard of Justice which is set up in each mans <HI>own heart,</HI> besides the <HI>Chancery of Mercy</HI>; both which he cannot but desire in his <HI>own case</HI>; yea he expects and <HI>exacts humility,</HI> reverence and submiss respect from those that are his descendents and in∣feriors, especially if <HI>many ways</HI> obliged to him, by undeserved favours; so as every <HI>mans case is to∣ward God.</HI></P>
<P N="2"><PB N="56" REF="34"/>2. <HI>Praeceptis scripturae,</HI> by the Letters pattents of the holy <HI>Scriptures,</HI> whereof no man in the light of Religion <HI>which shines</HI> in the <HI>Church</HI> can without sin be ignorant; because no lessons are easier to be learned, and set out in greater <HI>characters,</HI> or text letters, both of the ten <HI>Commandments</HI> and the <HI>Gospel,</HI> than these three of <HI>Justice, Mercy</HI> and <HI>Hu∣mility.</HI> Nor is any man meet to learn or observe the more abstruse <HI>mysteries</HI> of <HI>Christianity,</HI> who doth not first apply to these <HI>plain morals</HI> of <HI>humanity,</HI> and native Divinity; in which instructions who so pro∣fited most among the Jews or Gentiles, and lived accordingly, were most capable vessels of Gods Mercies, although they had not such an explicite faith in the <HI>Messias,</HI> as we Christians are now obliged to, as a condition of the Evangelical Covenant.</P>
<P N="3">3. God hath shewed us these demonstrations, <HI>magnis exemplaribus, &amp; exemplis</HI>; by the greatest exemplars of <HI>holy men</HI> in all degrees; in the best of Kings, and vvisest of Counsellors, yea in his bles∣sed self and his <HI>Son our Lord Jesus Christ,</HI> in whom Justice <HI>was satisfied,</HI> Mercy <HI>Magnified,</HI> and <HI>Humi∣lity</HI> most <HI>exalted</HI> for <HI>mans imitation</HI>; To these are added the great <HI>examples</HI> of his Judgements on those whose exorbitant <HI>lusts</HI> and <HI>passions,</HI> for∣getting God and themselves, presumed to do be∣yond these <HI>bounds</HI> and <HI>prescriptions,</HI> which the <HI>Divine Iustice</HI> and <HI>Mercy</HI> had set to mankind, run∣ning out to <HI>violence</HI> and cruelty, in order to gra∣tifie their pride: On the other side, God hath by many <HI>blessings</HI> on <HI>Prince</HI> and <HI>People</HI>; manifested his approbation of their <HI>ways,</HI> when conform to those grand Precepts, which suppress first all private ex∣travagancies
<PB N="57" REF="34"/>
by humility, and all publick oppressions by justice, mixed <HI>with mercy</HI>; no man that is hum∣ble can be unhappy, nor any people or Prince mise∣rable, who keep to <HI>Justice</HI> and mercy, except in <HI>mar∣tyrly cases</HI> for trial of their <HI>faith, patience,</HI> and <HI>con∣stancy,</HI> which are found most in those (if not onely) who are most endued with <HI>principles,</HI> and wonted, as to <HI>Justice,</HI> so to the practice of mercy, and <HI>humility.</HI></P>
<P>§. Lastly God hath shewed and <HI>required</HI> these things (<HI>cum gravi interminatione poenae</HI>) not <HI>lightly</HI> and <HI>arbitrarily,</HI> but with great <HI>earnestness,</HI> and frequent <HI>obtestation,</HI> threatning <HI>punishment,</HI> answerable to the <HI>neglect,</HI> and executing vengeance on the <HI>presump∣tous,</HI> nor are they Laws of (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) <HI>diur∣nal</HI> justice, to day <HI>loyalty,</HI> to morrow <HI>Treason,</HI> this week lawful and just, next week illegal and un∣just, like a <HI>Lesbian rule,</HI> but they are <HI>standards, fixed</HI> in Gods immutable <HI>Justice,</HI> mercy, and <HI>excellent Ma∣jesty,</HI> which no men at any time may dispense, with∣all, nor can they be dispensed with, as to Gods judg∣ments, if they break them.</P>
<P>§. But it is now time for me to releive your <HI>at∣tention</HI> with the variety of my <HI>successors</HI> paines; onely I crave your Christian patience so far, as to give me leave, to make some such improvement of this Text, as the <HI>grand</HI> occasion and present <HI>sollem∣nity</HI> do require.</P>
<P>§. You are all this day,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Application or Vses.</NOTE> as the <HI>Representatives</HI> of the <HI>Commons</HI> of this Nation met before the <HI>Lord,</HI> to <HI>fast</HI> and <HI>pray,</HI> to <HI>humble</HI> and <HI>afflict</HI> your souls, to confess your sins, and the sins of your people, a∣mong which none are more crying to heaven for vengeance, then the want of <HI>Justice,</HI> mercy, and
<PB N="58" REF="35"/>
humility; for <HI>pride, ambition, covetousness, cruelty,</HI> and <HI>oppression,</HI> the land hath mourned these many years, and the more <HI>deploredly,</HI> because it hath suffered by all these <HI>pests of Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> under the name and <HI>pretensions</HI> of <HI>humility, sanctity, liberty</HI> and <HI>equity.</HI> It was a small matter for us to be miserable by the <HI>insolency</HI> of some men; but we were <HI>commanded,</HI> by their hypocritical and cruel mocking to beleive our selves to be an happy, and <HI>free people</HI>; in a glorious and reformed way of Re∣ligion, laws and liberties.</P>
<P>§. It is a saying of that <HI>great Orator,</HI> as acute as true (<HI>Totius injustitiae nulla est capitalior, quam eorum, qui quum maximè fallunt, ita tamen agunt, nt viri boni videantur.</HI>) No men are more <HI>criminally injust,</HI> than those, who when they most deceive and op∣press, yet then boast of their <HI>justice</HI> and <HI>piety.</HI></P>
<P>§. What have been the effects of some mens <HI>ju∣stice,</HI> mercy and <HI>humility,</HI> all the English, yea British world hath seen, and your selves <HI>have felt</HI>; to whom have some mens factious and <HI>Phanatick hu∣mors</HI> shewed any tokens of these vertues, except to <HI>themselves,</HI> and their complices? to others who are <HI>persons</HI> far more <HI>righteous</HI> then themselves, their ve∣ry mercies have been <HI>cruel,</HI> and their highest ju∣stice the highest injuries <HI>to the publique</HI>; indeed it is of the Lords mercys that we have not been all con∣sumed; that a remnant is escaped to see the Salva∣tion of the Lord; in the land of the living. O with what pride, petulancy, haughtiness and disdain, have, <HI>mean</HI> men and <HI>vile persons</HI> carried them∣selves against the honorable, far their <HI>betters</HI> and <HI>su∣periors,</HI> yea against the whole <HI>honor</HI> and <HI>Majesty</HI> of
<PB N="59" REF="35"/>
this Nation! how have we seen servants riding <HI>on horseback,</HI> and <HI>Princes</HI> going on foot! this is their humility; they have flattered both Prince and Peo∣ple in their sore distresses, as if they would relieve them, when they proved at last Physitians of no value, miserable comforters, very severe exact∣ors, and tragical destroyers; This is their mercy; They have subverted all law, order, and govern∣ment, troubled the fountaines, cut off the con∣duits, and inverted all the course of civil Justice, and ecclesiastical authority, as well as unity; this is their Justice.</P>
<P>§. Can a Nation be sick of its <HI>health,</HI> and weary of its happiness, or thus dayly and bitterly com∣plain, if it injoyed such a glorious state of Justice; and mercy, by the humility and sanctity of its <HI>Gover∣nours</HI>; as some have pretended? Why doth the whole land cry out of <HI>burthens</HI> and <HI>bloodshed,</HI> of its <HI>oppressors</HI> and exactors, of its endless troubles and terrors? if our estate were so setled and blessed, as some men have told us, why, as <HI>Dromedaries,</HI> do they every month so traverse their <HI>ways,</HI> de∣stroying what they build, and building what they destroy, like so many foolish builders! it is strange, that neither these <HI>Baalams</HI> nor their asses which <HI>car∣ry</HI> them; in the ways, and after vvages of <HI>iniquity,</HI> can yet see the Angel of the Lord, vvith a dravvn svvord, stopping their vvay; all lavvs of God and man, all good mens votes, and prayers, are against their madness, pride, presumption, cruelty, hy∣pocrity and injustice, by vvhich they have brought shame and dishonour, a blot and great reproach, upon the nation and the <HI>reformed Religion.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="60" REF="36"/>§. You have enough to do <HI>(honorable and worthy)</HI> to undo vvhat some men have done amiss, to recti∣fie their crookedness, to bring to the <HI>standard of Ju∣stice and rule of mercy,</HI> vvhat their injurious cruelty and vvanton vvickedness have perverted and di∣stracted, as their pride, <HI>ambition,</HI> and <HI>various lusts</HI> have driven them.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iosh. 7.13.</NOTE>§. You vvork is not only as <HI>Josuah,</HI> to fall dovvn <HI>before the Lord,</HI> as ye do this day, but to <HI>Arise</HI> and to do <HI>the work of God,</HI> of the <HI>Church,</HI> and of the <HI>State,</HI> vvith justice, mercy and humility; For if you still fast <HI>for strife and oppression,</HI> to smite vvith the fist of <HI>wickedness,</HI> and to bind heavy burdens on us, you vvill be found <HI>mockers of God</HI> as others have been, your prayers vvill be turned into sin, and your counsels vvill turn to confusion.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>appeals</HI> and <HI>petitions</HI> of all honest-minded people (<HI>next God</HI>) are to your prudence, justice and charity, that you vvould judge betvveen the <HI>daugh∣ter of your people,</HI> and her shameless ravishers, her cruel vvounders, and endless oppressors.</P>
<P>§. Three antient and sometimes flourishing Kingdomes, and the adjacent <HI>Dominions</HI> call to you for mercy, and you cannot shevv them greater mercy, then to do them justice, in restoring them to their former happy governments, and excellent constitutions.</P>
<P>§. All estates of Soveranity, Nobility, Gentry, Clergy, Commonalty call upon you for <HI>justice</HI> and <HI>mercy</HI>; so the poor and rich, the City and Coun∣try, so God himself, and your Saviour, so true Religion and its novv so deformed Reformation, so your ovvn and your posterities interests, do
<PB N="61" REF="36"/>
dayly importune; it vvill be your justice and mer∣cy to them all and us, not to bring upon all our heads the guilt of that innocent blood, which the cruel∣ty, pride and injustice of some men have shed, even the blood of War in a time of peace, and after a long Treaty, When God makes inquisition for this blood, let him not find it, and avenge it upon you and your Children, by your not expiating, deprecating and detesting of that sin, with infinite horror and abhorence; to leave it unexamined and unpunished is every day to contract the guilt of a new regicide.</P>
<P>§. The Soveraign fountain of honor, civil power, and secular authority in Church and State, calls for, and expects your Justice, where it hath been inju∣red; your Mercy, where unrelieved; your humble subjection, where duly established.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>House of Peers</HI> cannot but own your Ju∣stice, Modesty and Humility, in removing those obstructions which some mens pride and injurious insolency had for many years put in the way of that House, which was ever one of the highest points of this Kingdoms Wisdom, Honor, stability and hap∣piness.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>House of Commons</HI> also, and whatever becomes the dignity and freedom of a Parlia∣ment of <HI>England,</HI> calls to your Justice and Mercy, to redeem that almost sacred <HI>Senate</HI> (than which in its full constitution, the world had not any thing more august and venerable; when Lords Spiritual and Temporal, when the Gentry and Commons, all concurred to advance next the glory of God, the majesty of this Empire, and the Throne of its
<PB N="62" REF="37"/>
Soveraign;) to redeem this (I say) from those abominable desolations of tumultuary and military insolencies which for many years have made that house a Charnel house, or a kind of <HI>Augean</HI> stable, full of all faction, fury and and fanatick filthi∣ness.</P>
<P>§. Our <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>Religion,</HI> our <HI>Bishops</HI> and <HI>Pres∣byters,</HI> our <HI>Ministers</HI> and <HI>Ministry,</HI> all call to your Ju∣stice and Mercy to redeem them from popular de∣pendencies, from vulgar impudence and usurpation; at least to relieve them from those <HI>Harpyes</HI> which have driven them to, and defiled them with so many shameful disorders; divisions and distractions unbe∣coming men, much more Christians and Ministers, who are pretenders to Reformation.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>famous Ʋniversities,</HI> and all <HI>Nurseries</HI> of good <HI>literature</HI> implore your Justice and Mercy, to defend these eyes of the Nation, from those <HI>birds of prey,</HI> foraign and domestick vultures, which hope when these are pulled out, to seize upon the <HI>blind</HI> and <HI>deformed Nation,</HI> with greater freedom of <HI>Ro∣mish superstition,</HI> and <HI>fanatick Vsurpation,</HI> who gape to devour all that is lest of the civil or sacred <HI>patrimony,</HI> of Gods, or the Kings, the Churches or the Crowns portion.</P>
<P>§. We have once again (by Gods wonderful mercy, and his blessing upon <HI>one great heroick</HI> and <HI>steady soul</HI>) got the <HI>wind of the Jesuitick, Anabap∣tistick</HI> and <HI>fanatick designs,</HI> who have abused us with their long wiles; O lose not the advantages which God hath given you to bring your Church and Country into a fair and <HI>happy haven,</HI> after so many tempests <HI>and agitations</HI> of <HI>infinite loss and haz∣zard.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="63" REF="37"/>§. There are many holy Duties, and <HI>Christian Rites</HI> which call for your Justice and Mercy; the two blessed <HI>Sacraments</HI> which have a long time been either wholly despised, or prophanely abused, or very partially used; The <HI>Lords Prayer</HI> also, the <HI>Ten Commandments</HI> and the <HI>Creed,</HI> all sacred and wholesom forms, of excellent use to the people of <HI>Christs flock,</HI> but despised and neglected by some of their <HI>supercilious Pastors,</HI> to the great detri∣ment of true Religion and abatement of piety; these expect your exemplary Justice, to restore them to their primitive <HI>and Catholick honor,</HI> which will be a mercy to the whole <HI>Nation,</HI> which by extem∣porary <HI>novelties</HI> and <HI>crude varieties</HI> in Religion, hath been wholly deprived of all those pristine forms of <HI>liturgical devotions</HI> by which the generality of Christians were best informed and most affected, as to the grand <HI>fundamentals</HI> of <HI>Religion</HI>; Sure it is but the effect of crafty or crazy brains, to deny us all use of <HI>Our Father</HI> in English, because we gave over the <HI>Pater nosters,</HI> the <HI>Ave Maries,</HI> and other prayers which were in Latin, and so of little use to the vulgar. It was once thought a blessing to have prayers and holy duties in a language which people understood; Now tis a <HI>seraphick stratagem</HI> of Sa∣tan to make people forget those things which they could easiest remember and best understand.</P>
<P>§. Lastly, There are many prevalent and <HI>epide∣mical sins</HI> of <HI>Sacriledge, Prophaness, irreverence, Perjury, rash swearing, Duelling, Ʋncleanness</HI> and all <HI>manner</HI> of <HI>licentious</HI> discoveries of <HI>Atheism</HI> and <HI>irreli∣gion</HI> which call for your Justice to suppress them, for they are the cruellest enemies of Church and State.</P>
<P><PB N="64" REF="38"/><NOTE PLACE="marg">Conclusion.</NOTE>If you will (indeed) <HI>do Justice, love Mercy, and walk humbly with your God</HI>; if you will shew <HI>loving kindness</HI> and <HI>sense</HI> of <HI>honor</HI> to your <HI>Country,</HI> resolve upon all those <HI>dispensations, restitutions,</HI> and <HI>exer∣citations</HI> of Justice and Mercy, which are before you: Which you will best do if you</P>
<P N="1">1. Be pleased so to fix our Laws, yea our <HI>legisla∣tive</HI> and <HI>Soveraign authority,</HI> so that we may be no more <HI>tossed too and fro with every wind</HI> of <HI>mens am∣bitious fancies; qui malunt leges quam mores mutare,</HI> who had rather change our <HI>good laws,</HI> than mend their own <HI>ill manners.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. To remove all <HI>obstructions</HI> which are inward in your own souls, and outward in other <HI>mens pas∣sions</HI> or actions, by which either Justice or Mercy are most hindred of their free course.</P>
<P N="3">3. If you listen not to that wicked maxim of the Devils politicks, <HI>Fieri non debuit, factum valet,</HI> as if evil actions did call for perseverance not re∣pentance. <HI>Nullum tempus</HI> occurit <HI>Justitiae,</HI> no time or fact must prescribe against justice, truth, God and the Church.</P>
<P N="4">4. When you have undone by justice what hath been done by injustice, to the undoing of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> Prince and People; Then will mercy be seasonable, by acts of such <HI>amnesty, pardon,</HI> and <HI>oblivion,</HI> as may rather compose than irritate the spirits of men; <HI>praestat motos componere fluct∣us.</HI></P>
<P N="5">5. If you needed (which I hope you do not) any motives to these great indeavours and discoveries of justice and mercy, it is no small one which the <HI>Platonists</HI> observe, as to the difference between just
<PB N="65" REF="38"/>
and unjust, the good and evil men, which is as great as between light and darkness, order and confu∣sion, men and beasts, good and bad Angels, as between a King and a Tyrant, God and the Devil. God is the first <HI>fountain</HI> and grand <HI>example</HI> of justice and mercy, as the Devil is of injuriousness and cruelty.</P>
<P N="6">6. If you inquire <HI>Cui bono?</HI> what their reward shall be? First the conscience of well doing, and this to your Country and in its greatest <HI>distresses</HI>; Next, you shall have that reward of <HI>lasting honour,</HI> and <HI>renown,</HI> by which your names, as repairers of our breaches, shall be <HI>embalmed</HI> in the love of their Country, and <HI>transmitted</HI> with a sweet <HI>resentment</HI> to all posterity; where as the names of proud and cruel <HI>oppressors,</HI> shall rot and perish like their <HI>own dung</HI>; the blood thirsty and deceitful men shall not live out half their dayes; not only, as to those <HI>dies naturales</HI>; but as to those <HI>dies civiles,</HI> which pre∣serve the living fame of worthy men to many ge∣nerations as blessed; he is but short-lived whose <HI>infamy</HI> only survives; as the <HI>damned</HI> in hell, are counted <HI>dead,</HI> because they only live to shame and <HI>torment.</HI></P>
<P>§. As for your <HI>direction</HI> what and how <HI>to do ex∣cellent</HI> things, you need not search <HI>Achitophels</HI> braines, or rake the skull of <HI>Matchiavel</HI>; you need not call up the <HI>Ghost</HI> of <HI>Richelieu,</HI> or conjure up those subtil spirits of <HI>Government,</HI> which may tell you the <HI>Adyta imperii, &amp; arcana principum,</HI> the depths, mysteries, intrigoes, and riddles of States; you need not listen any longer to those Seraphick <HI>Syrens,</HI> and Phanatick Counsellors, who under
<PB N="66" REF="39"/>
the title of Gods cause and the Saints interest, which I know not what blessed <HI>projects</HI> or gainful godli∣ness, had made a <HI>shift to undo</HI> all, but themselves, yea and themselves too, as to all sence of justice, or mercy, or honor, or conscience of modesty or humility; You need not advise with <HI>flesh</HI> and <HI>blood,</HI> with humane passions and lusts (<HI>facilis &amp; parata est ad virtutem via,</HI>) the <HI>counsel of God is at hand,</HI> (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) you cannot easily miscarry by fol∣lowing his <HI>wisdome</HI> in justice, mercy and humility; however, you had better perish in Gods <HI>way,</HI> as to <HI>temporal</HI> effects, then prosper for a season in the Devils, which must end in <HI>endlesse infelicities.</HI></P>
<P>§. There can no better course be followed in ci∣vil justice, than that which was given by the <HI>Oracle</HI> to the <HI>Sicilian Pyrates,</HI> when afflicted by the plague, after they had gotten much booty, they enquired What they should do to be releived? Answer was given in these letters; <HI>R. A. S. P. P.</HI> which some cunning man <HI>interpreted,</HI> to import by the <HI>Acrostick</HI> letters thus much, <HI>Reddite Aliena, S'ultis Possi∣dere Propria,</HI> Restore to others what is theirs, if you hope to preserve to your selves your <HI>own</HI>; else your common weal will be but a common wo.</P>
<P>§. There is neither darkness in your way of ju∣stice and mercy, nor will there be much <HI>difficulty.</HI> God hath and will remove mountains of malice, hypocrisie and injustice before you, yea he hath prepared the vvay for you by levelling the leve∣lers, and confounding the confounders of all things civil and sacred. His vvord and the lavvs of the Land vvill tell you vvhat is to be done, <HI>State super vias autiquas &amp; bonas,</HI> stand <HI>and enquire for the good
<PB REF="39"/>
old ways</HI> and <HI>walk</HI> therein, <HI>that you and we may</HI> find that rest, vvhich hath been a long time and ever vvill be denyed us, in any of those <HI>fanta∣stick</HI> and novel models vvhich make religion a <HI>nurse</HI> of <HI>rebellion,</HI> pretend that the Kingdome of <HI>Jesus Christ</HI> vvill indure no temporal Christi∣an Kingdome except such as they may rule and raign in.</P>
<P>§. But you have not so <HI>learned Christ</HI>; neither his <HI>law,</HI> nor his <HI>Gospel</HI> suggest any such unjust and cruel <HI>counsels,</HI> nor do they favour any violent and rebel∣lious designes. Do (as I believe you will) what be∣comes your duty to God and man, your love to your <HI>Country,</HI> your respect to true Religion, and your care of your posterity, and no doubt God will be with you, both to strengthen your hands, and to make your faces to shine with that glory in this life, which is the first, but least recompense of just and honorable actions, and also with that eternal glory, which is the purchase of Christs blood, and the <HI>honorary</HI> recompense of God, to all that in the way of well doing seek for honor and immortality; to which the Lord bring you and all his Church, for Jesus Christ his sake, to whom with the Father and the blessed Spirit be all glory and honour now and ever, <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

