<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Kakourgoi, sive Medicastri slight healings of publique hurts. Set forth in a sermon preached in St. Pauls Church, London, before the Right Honorable the Lord Mayor, Lord General, aldermen, Common Council, and companies of the honorable City of London. February 28. 1659. Being a day of solemn thanksgiving unto God, for restoring the secluded Members of Parliament to the House of Commons: (and for preserving the city) as a door of hope thereby opened to the fulness and freedom of future Parliaments: the most probable means under God for healing the hurts, and recovering the health of these three Brittish kingdomes. By John Gauden, D.D.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A42487</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing G361A</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R215531</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99827385</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99827385</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">31803</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42487)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31803)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1908:15)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Kakourgoi, sive Medicastri slight healings of publique hurts. Set forth in a sermon preached in St. Pauls Church, London, before the Right Honorable the Lord Mayor, Lord General, aldermen, Common Council, and companies of the honorable City of London. February 28. 1659. Being a day of solemn thanksgiving unto God, for restoring the secluded Members of Parliament to the House of Commons: (and for preserving the city) as a door of hope thereby opened to the fulness and freedom of future Parliaments: the most probable means under God for healing the hurts, and recovering the health of these three Brittish kingdomes. By John Gauden, D.D.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 112 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>printed for Andrew Crook, at the Green Dragon in Pauls Church-yard,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1660.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>First word of title in Greek characters.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York, New York.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A42487">
<STC T="W">G361A</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99827385</BIBNO>
<VID>31803</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>sive MEDICASTRI: SLIGHT HEALINGS</HI> OF PUBLIQUE HURTS.</P>
<P>Set forth in a SERMON PREACHED In St. <HI>Pauls</HI> Church, <HI>London,</HI> before the Right Honourable the Lord Major, Lord Ge∣neral, Aldermen, Common Council, and Companies of the Honourable City of <HI>London February</HI> 28. 1659.</P>
<P>Being a day of solemn Thanksgiving unto God, for Restoring the Secluded Members of Parlia∣ment to the House of Commons: (And for preserving the City) as a Door of Hope thereby opened to the fulness and freedom of future Par∣liaments: The most probable means under God for healing the hurts, and recovering the health of these three <HI>Brit∣tish</HI> Kingdomes.</P>
<P>By <HI>JOHN GAUDEN,</HI> D.D.</P>
<BIBL>Ezek. 21. 26, 27.</BIBL>
<Q>Thus saith the Lord, Remove the Diadem, and take off the Crown: this shall not be the same, exalt him that is low, and abase him that is high. I will overturn, overturn, over∣turn it, and it shall be no more, untill be come whose it is, and I will give it him.</Q>
<P><HI>Restat ut <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ciores pluribus ce<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>: hoc uno <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ta<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t popularia imperia, abter cas<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ra.</HI> H. Gro. Hist. Bar. 1. 17. pag. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>0.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed for <HI>Andrew Crook,</HI> at the <HI>Green Dragon</HI> in <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard, 1660.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="imprimatur">
<PB REF="2"/>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Aleyn Major.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>A <HI>Common Council</HI> holden the 29. of <HI>Febru∣ary</HI> 1659.</P>
<P>Ordered that the thanks of this <HI>Court be</HI> gi∣ven to Dr. <HI>Gauden,</HI> who preached <HI>Yester∣day</HI> before them at St. <HI>Pauls</HI> Church. And that he from this Court be desired to print his Sermon.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>SADLER.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the right Honourable <HI>THOMAS ALEYN</HI> Lord Mayor of the City OF London. THE Court of Aldermen and Common-Counsel.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>S by your <HI>Desire</HI> I was induced to preach the following Sermon; so by your <HI>Order</HI> in <HI>Common Council</HI> I was re∣quested to print what I preached; I have obeyed you in both, and su∣pererogated in the later: adding something prepared, but omitted for want of time, and a respect due to your expectation of a second and better course <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n that Festival. This I have done not only as <HI>compliant</HI> with your Christian
<PB REF="3"/>
Commands, but as solicitous to <HI>conform</HI> all my endea∣vours to the publick Good of your City, and our com∣mon Countrey. In w<SUP>ch.</SUP> a great part of the <HI>Church of Christ,</HI> and many precious souls, as well as mens bodies, Lives, Liberties, Honours and Estates are embarqued: All which have for our sins been long engaged in a tempest of <HI>War</HI> and sea of <HI>Blood;</HI> nor have they been able to make any fair <HI>Port</HI> or happy <HI>Haven</HI> these many years, since they lost their Pilots and Compass, their Kings and Par∣liaments, by the various <HI>Euroclydons</HI> of mens passions, Lusts and Interests; which have tossed them to and fro with every wind; &amp; made great waste of all that is pre∣cious for Religion, Justice and Honour, besides Estates and Lives of men in the three Kingdomes; threatning all either with speedy and utter <HI>Shipwrack</HI> by forreign In∣vasion, or an everlasting storm by domestick confusions; untill the unexpected and undescerned providence of God began to open to your and the Countryes prayers <HI>some door of hope,</HI> by the prudent, valiant and succesfull Conduct of the present Lord General <HI>Monck:</HI> from whom all good men expect all good things: nor can he deceive them without deceiving and destroying himself and his Countrie.</P>
<P>Your gratitude to God for this seasonable dawning of Mercy (which seems to bespeak a great calm) oc∣casion'd your solemn Convention that day; and my preaching to you. In which work you cannot wonder if I endeavoured to shew my self a <HI>Work-man</HI> that needed not to be <HI>afraid</HI> or <HI>ashamed;</HI> being very sensi∣ble with you of the great, many and long hurts of the <HI>daughter of my people,</HI> both in Church and State: I then declared them to you: I deplored them
<PB REF="3"/>
with you; I proposed the methods of cure to you, as fully as the time would permit; and as freely as became my duty to my God and my conscience. As I would not injure any man, or fester the times: so I abhor to flatter them, which is the greatest injury a Preacher can do to Church and State.</P>
<P>Some <HI>I</HI> hear were offended (the fate of Christs, of <HI>John</HI> Baptists, and of Saint <HI>Pauls</HI> preaching) at the plain dealing I used (which possibly was from their own rawness and soreness, more then from my roughness or sharpness) As I aim to do things faithfully &amp; seasonably, so decently and discreetly: Nor do I think I am to learn those <HI>Censorious Catos</HI> how to preach, any more than they will learn of me how to buy and sell; or how to fight and war. No man may wonder if I dare to reprove those sins which some dare to do, or approve, but dare not hear of, or repent.</P>
<P>The parrhesie or freedom of my speech as a man, a Christian, and a Preacher was such, as became my feeling of the publick miseries; my desire of the pub∣lick tranquility, and my sense of that fidelity I ow to God, to my Countrey, to you, and to my own soul.</P>
<P>Thest are not times to palliate and speak smooth or soft things: Never age had fouler humours or prou∣der tumours; more felt and more painfull; more hard, and less mollified; These I would help to cure, that so we might recover publick health, together with out wits, and reason; our Laws and Religion, our good Conscience and Government: our Peace and Unani∣mity: all which we have lost, since we lost our heads in Church and State. Our full and free Parliaments, consisting of King, Lords and Commons; in which
<PB REF="4"/>
the soule and life, the honour and happiness of these Nations are bound up.</P>
<P>And no part of it is more concerned then your fa∣mous sometime flourishing, and still populous City; in whose happiness the whole Nation will be happy, and in its misery all must be miserable. Since <HI>Lon∣don</HI> is not only as a ponderous <HI>Byas</HI> to the great bowl, (which draws all parts towards it) But it is as the <HI>Mis∣tresse, Lady</HI> or <HI>Queen,</HI> to which every <HI>Village, City</HI> and <HI>Countrey</HI> of the Nation (as officious <HI>Hand-maids</HI>) stu∣dy to present all manner of costly comlyness; not only feminine, as the superfluity of peace and plenty; but also masculine; for <HI>London</HI> is (like <HI>Pallas</HI> furnished as with men of Counsel and Conduct; so with Treasure and Strength, with all sorts of Armes and Aminition; Be∣ing <HI>Camera Imperii Britanici,</HI> The Metropolis of the <HI>Brit∣tish</HI> Empire, a vast Magazine of men &amp; money, a nursery of all Arts, Mechanick, Ingenuous and Military: a great entertainer of Learning; and a noble encourager of Re∣ligion, wanting nothing to make it self and the Nation happy, if it have such heroick minds and honest hearts, as become so rich, so great, and so Christian a City.</P>
<P>'Tis true, like pl<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>thorick bodies, great care must be had how ill humours, yea and good ones too, are put in∣to motion; since the first cannot well be long kept in, nor may the second be purged out: The first threat∣ning dangerous inflamations; the second no less dange∣rous Eva<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uations. Here Prudence, Order, Moderation, Conscience and Unanimity are required; besides Zeal and Courage, in order to recover your and our former health in Church and State; which was made up of an admirable temper &amp; constitution; untill sins, tumults, vi∣olence,
<PB REF="4"/>
and warre, cast us into these <HI>Feavers, Convul∣sions</HI> and <HI>Confusions,</HI> with which we have wrestled for ma∣ny years. Indeed your City ows some Reparation (and now payes it) to the whole Nation: not only for the ad∣vantages it hath from all parts; but for the disadvanta∣ges which all have suffered: not from the ill intentions, but from some tumultuating dispositions, which (as Por∣pusses) were pregnant in your <HI>sea of people,</HI> when our troubles first began.</P>
<P>I hope God hath prepared blessings for you, and by you for the whole Nation; by opening your eyes, humbling your hearts, disposing your minds, and exci∣ting your spirits to thoughts of Justice and Piety; of Re∣pentance, Restitution and Peace: We have had <HI>wounds</HI> and <HI>hurts</HI> enough; <HI>slight healings,</HI> and <HI>strong Delusions</HI> too many. It is high time (if it be Gods time) to speak comfortably to <HI>Zion,</HI> to tell her, <HI>Her Warfare is ac∣complished;</HI> to pour in the Balm of <HI>Gilead</HI> by sober and equanimious Counsels; to bind up by orderly &amp; just <HI>pow∣er,</HI> what hath been long broken; to make up the grand <HI>defects</HI> in our Government, and to lay foundations of fu∣ture peace and happiness in <HI>Righteousness</HI> and <HI>Truth:</HI> That the enemies of our <HI>reformed</HI> Religion, and this <HI>re∣nowned</HI> Nation, may not rejoyce in our continued mise∣ries, and say, <HI>So would we have it.</HI></P>
<P>I have sought to do my duty: if some think I have overdone it; I must crave your patrociny to assert that, which by your acceptance seemed to be your sense, as well as mine; and is, as I hope, the sense of all honest and judicious men: For men that are fanciful &amp; fanatick, we need them not, to make us happy: I am sure they have made a shift to make us very <HI>miserable.</HI> And
<PB REF="5"/>
if God had not in mercy set bounds to the rage of that <HI>sea,</HI> and the madness of that people, they would have made your <HI>City</HI> an heap of <HI>ashes,</HI> and our Countrey a field of <HI>Blood;</HI> It will be your Wisdom, Honour and Happiness to keep in the bounds of just, moderate, re∣ligious and sober <HI>Counsels;</HI> to aim at legal, honest and tried wayes of settlement: to chuse and use such Physici∣ans as you find most able and faithfull; so will health and salvation break forth upon you, and the three Nations, which is the earnest prayer</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Of your humble servant in <HI>Christ,</HI>
J. GAUDEN.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<HEAD>Books written by Dr. <HI>Gauden,</HI> and sold by <HI>An∣drew Crook</HI> at the <HI>Green-Dragon</HI> in <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. <HI>HIeraspistes,</HI> A Defence for the <HI>Ministry</HI> and <HI>Ministers</HI> of the Church of <HI>England.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Three Sermons preached on publick occasions.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. <HI>Funerals</HI> made <HI>Cordials,</HI> in a Sermon preached at the In∣terment of the Corpse of <HI>Robert Rich,</HI> Heir apparent to the Earldom of <HI>Warwick.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>4. A Sermon preached at the Funeral of Dr. <HI>Ralph Broun∣rig</HI> Bishop of <HI>Excester</HI> (<HI>Decemb.</HI> 17. 1659.) with an account of his <HI>Life</HI> and <HI>Death.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>5. A <HI>Petitionary Remonstrance</HI> in the behalf of many thou∣sand Ministers and Scholers.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB N="1" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>A SERMON PREACHED Before the Lord Mayor, Alder∣men, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> of <HI>London.</HI></HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>IER. 8. 11.</BIBL>
<Q>For they have healed the hurt of the Daughter of my people slightly, saying, Peace, peace, when there is no peace.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">B</SEG>Eing called to this publick service by<NOTE PLACE="marg">The preface or address.</NOTE> the piety and civility of this <HI>great City</HI> (Right honorable and worthy Auditors) I could not well tell how to avoid it, because it seemed so <HI>good a work;</HI> nor yet (upon so short warning) how to accept of it, being so <HI>great a work,</HI> if either I re∣gard
<PB N="2" REF="6"/>
the importance of the <HI>occasion,</HI> which looks like a <HI>door of hope</HI> opened to the healing of these <HI>Nations,</HI> and composing of their sad distractions, by the counsels of a <HI>full and free Parliament,</HI> and by the assistance of regular and orderly power.</P>
<P>§. Or if I consider (as I ought in prudence)<NOTE PLACE="marg">The difficulty and danger of the work.</NOTE> the <HI>difficulty</HI> and <HI>danger</HI> of touching, though in order to <HI>heal</HI> the <HI>old sor<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> and <HI>sistulating ulcers</HI> of this <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> which are now (<HI>vetustesceu∣tia mala, &amp; annosi morbi</HI>) inveterate <HI>dolors,</HI> obstinate <HI>evils</HI> and pertinacious <HI>maladies;</HI> not onely impati∣ent to be <HI>touched freely,</HI> and <HI>searched throughly,</HI> but are prone to plead as the <HI>Divels</HI> in the Gospel (who had possessed the poor man now <HI>a long time</HI>) against <HI>all health</HI> and recovery. Many men like <HI>Canters</HI> and <HI>Lazars</HI> are in love with their wounds and ulcers, getting their living more easily by keeping their sores open, raw and running, than if they should quite heal them up.</P>
<P>§. I am further conscious not only to the <HI>touchi∣ness</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Touchiness of times.</NOTE> of the times, and the tenderness of many mens minds, who are onely for <HI>lenitives</HI> and <HI>oyles,</HI> for soft, smooth and <HI>supple applications,</HI> even to their most desperate hurts; but also that my own native <HI>parrhesia,</HI> or <HI>freedom of speaking,</HI> which is both customary and consciencious; not that I af∣fect unseasonable <HI>severities</HI> of speech, and such rudeness under the pretence of freedom, as ra∣ther exasperates the wound, and inflames the humor, than purgeth, <HI>allays,</HI> or easeth them.</P>
<P>§. But I profess to chuse not to preach at all, rather<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ossre<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> speak∣ing in preach∣ing.</NOTE> than to preach <HI>timorously</HI> or <HI>precariously</HI> (<HI>Ut Lug∣dunensem</HI>
<PB N="3" REF="6"/>
<HI>Rhetor dicturus ad aram</HI>) as if I should ask men leave to be honest, or were afraid to speak the <HI>Word of God</HI> to them.</P>
<P>§. When I am called <HI>to speak in Gods name,</HI> I must be <HI>Parrhesiastes</HI> as <HI>well as Ecclessiastes;</HI> I am to do it as a workman that needs not to be ashamed, either for his ignorance, or cowardise, or indiscre∣tion; whether men <HI>will hear, or forbear,</HI> the <HI>whole counsel of God</HI> must be delivered in its season, so as becomes the words of <HI>soberness and truth,</HI> for the Church or Pulpit must not be a sanctuary for insolency, or a burrow or a retreat for rudeness: No, however men may become our <HI>enemies for speaking the truth,</HI> yet it is better so than to have God our <HI>enemy for smothering it,</HI> when it is just and seasonable; and such it is when <HI>necessary</HI> and <HI>sove∣raign</HI> to heal the hurt of a Church and State.</P>
<P>§. It hath been my <HI>fate</HI> frequently to offend<NOTE PLACE="marg">Offence easily taken from free preaching</NOTE> some men, when I have been most intent to serve them, by Texts and Sermons, which I thought most apt, <HI>useful</HI> and <HI>innocent.</HI> When I preached at the Court <HI>Anno.</HI> 1640. upon that <HI>Heb.</HI> 12. 14. <HI>Follow peace with all men, and holiness, without which no man shall see God:</HI> When before the <HI>long Parli∣ament,</HI> at its first convening, upon <HI>Zach.</HI> 8. 19. <HI>Therefore love the truth and peace:</HI> When at ano∣ther great and <HI>epidemick Assembly,</HI> upon 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 3. 19. <HI>For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God:</HI> Of <HI>all three,</HI> though wholsom and <HI>innocent Texts, and</HI> (I hope) <HI>accordingly handled,</HI> yet I heard some unpleasing Ecchoes and reflexi∣ons;<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Tim. 4. 2.</NOTE> the sore and <HI>itching</HI> ears of some men in all
<PB N="4" REF="7"/>
ages are such, that they will not endure (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) <HI>healing</HI> or <HI>sound</HI> and <HI>wholesome Doctrine,</HI> though the pain riseth from the soreness and in∣flamation in themselves, and not from the <HI>plaister</HI> or hand which honestly applies it; yet they are prone as in <HI>fell boles,</HI> and <HI>acute tumors,</HI> when touched, though but gently, to fly upon those that are next them, and cry <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>loud <HI>O you hurt me,</HI> when the hurt is within and from themselves.</P>
<P>§. <HI>Sound parts</HI> will endure free and rough healing; such as are unsound, do most want it; and therefore if we will be faithful to God, to our own souls, and to our hearers, we must not <HI>flatter their sores to their ruine;</HI> but rather <HI>chuse</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 36. 28</NOTE> to heal them, though at present we be thought to hurt them; nor shall our <HI>labor of love</HI> be in vain either in the <HI>Lord,</HI> or before <HI>good</HI> men; who<NOTE PLACE="marg">H<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t free∣dom is best.</NOTE> at length will find by experience, that the wounds <HI>of a friend</HI> (which let out the putrified matter of <HI>painfull tumors</HI>) <HI>are better than the kisses of an ene∣my,</HI> which do (<HI>insides cicatricibus cuticulam obdu∣cere</HI>) skin over with <HI>unfaithful scars,</HI> the <HI>ill search∣ed</HI> and <HI>ill purged vnlcers</HI> of mens hearts and lives, saying <HI>peace, peace,</HI> all is, all will, all must be well in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> when (<HI>bona fide,</HI> or <HI>mala &amp; misera experientia</HI>) in true, but sad <HI>trial</HI> and sence of things, there is no <HI>peace, inward,</HI> or <HI>out∣ward,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Ci. ron. 15. 5.</NOTE> <HI>to him</HI> that <HI>goes out,</HI> or <HI>him that comes in;</HI> no <HI>peace religious</HI> or <HI>politick, civil or ecclessiastial, foraign</HI> or <HI>domestick,</HI> either to the <HI>Estates, Liber∣ties, Laws, honors</HI> or <HI>lives</HI> of men; nor yet to their <HI>opinions, doctrines, devotions</HI> and <HI>consciences,</HI>
<PB N="5" REF="7"/>
in any rank or degree; but as the Prophet <HI>Isaiah</HI> complains, <HI>The whole head</HI> (if we have any head) <HI>i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 1. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></NOTE> <HI>sick, and the whole heart is faint; from the sole of the foot to the crown of the head, there is no sound∣ness in it, but wounds and bruises and pu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rifying sores;</HI> they have not been <HI>closed, nor bound up, nor mollified with ointments.</HI></P>
<P>§. Yet there are that have cryed amain <HI>Peace,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Pre<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en l<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s to pe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>al<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</NOTE> <HI>peace;</HI> men that are either so merry or so mad in our common <HI>calamities,</HI> as to command us to call our sicknesses health; our <HI>wounds salves;</HI> our <HI>slavery, liberty;</HI> our <HI>divisions, union;</HI> our <HI>deformities reformings;</HI> our <HI>unset<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ledness, settling;</HI> our <HI>sands</HI> and <HI>quag<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, rockie foundations;</HI> our <HI>wars, peace,</HI> our <HI>oppressions, ease;</HI> our <HI>Commonwo, a Common∣weal.</HI> The Prophet seems thus to complain, That either <HI>Physitians</HI> of no <HI>value</HI> (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) many and <HI>unskilful Empiricks</HI> have un∣faithfully tampered with us, and (<HI>dum vulnera publica in lucra privata vertunt</HI>) while they make <HI>private gain</HI> by our <HI>publique pains;</HI> they have tur∣ned (<HI>ipsa remedia in morbos</HI>) our very <HI>remedies</HI> to <HI>new diseases,</HI> and have kept us long <HI>uncured,</HI> under pretence of <HI>cure;</HI> or else we are by the venome of our own inbred and <HI>malignant humors,</HI> become <HI>incurable;</HI> as (<HI>immedieabile vulnus, ense recidendum</HI>) a gangreen only fit for the saw and sword: and such indeed do our proud and dead <HI>flesh</HI> (or proud <HI>minds</HI> and dead <HI>hearts</HI> rather) portend our case to be, whilst so many tough obstructions, so many high inflammations, such new tumors and cruel biles daily arise of <HI>various</HI>
<PB N="6" REF="8"/>
<HI>interests;</HI> such a constant fall of <HI>ill humours,</HI> sharp and undigested, not onely upon the outward and grosser or more Mechanick parts of of the body Politick, but also upon the most vital and noble, the <HI>head</HI> and <HI>heart;</HI> where the <HI>counsel</HI> and <HI>cou∣rage,</HI> the <HI>strength</HI> and <HI>wisdom,</HI> the best <HI>blood</HI> and <HI>spirits</HI> of the Nation are or ought to be <HI>contained</HI> and exserted to the publick welfare.</P>
<P>Although, as the <HI>woman</HI> in the <HI>Gospel,</HI> we have<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mark. 5. 26.</NOTE> spent all, or most, or <HI>much</HI> of our <HI>substance</HI> on <HI>Physitians,</HI> and their attending <HI>Chyrurgeons,</HI> on <HI>Counsellors</HI> and <HI>Soldiers,</HI> yet we do not find our selves any whit the better; still we are scared and threatned by our sins, which are Gods discon∣tents; and our <HI>utsettlednesses</HI> (which are the <HI>Na∣tions discontent</HI> and <HI>sufferings</HI>) with daily break∣ings out and angry <HI>tumors,</HI> with new <HI>purgings</HI> and loathsome <HI>potions,</HI> with <HI>lancings</HI> and <HI>blood∣lettings,</HI> with <HI>cutting off</HI> and <HI>cauterisings,</HI> which will not <HI>heal, restore, close</HI> and <HI>redintigrate</HI> the body, but <HI>maime</HI> and <HI>defame,</HI> and <HI>cripple it</HI> for ever.</P>
<P>§. To prevent which <HI>successive miseries</HI> (or the<NOTE PLACE="marg">The scope or design of the Text.</NOTE> like) from the <HI>daughter of my people</HI> here in <HI>Eng∣land</HI> (as much as in me lies) I have sought to improve the sanctity and solemnity of this occa∣sion, this thankful and hopeful <HI>opportunity</HI> of future <HI>mercies,</HI> be presenting you with my <HI>meditations</HI> on this <HI>Text;</HI> because it is not onely (<HI>querela defalla∣cia medieorum, &amp; medelae mendacio</HI>) a just com∣plaint of the <HI>falsity</HI> of <HI>Physitians,</HI> and <HI>inefficacy</HI> of the past <HI>applications,</HI> which some <HI>Medicasters</HI> had
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
with great vapour and confidence <HI>applied,</HI> as bold <HI>Mountebaks</HI> are wont to do, when they wound their slaves to shew their skill in healing them.</P>
<P>§. But farther, the text is <HI>monitio de vera me∣dendi methodo</HI>) a dirction for the right method and an honest way of curing an afflicted Nation; It doth not only deplore the publique <HI>maladies,</HI> but denotes their right <HI>remedies,</HI> which may easily be <HI>known,</HI> and <HI>followed,</HI> if the healers were but honest; For the hurts are not so <HI>fatal, necessary</HI> and <HI>un∣avoidable,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Hurt of a Na∣tion not fatal and incurable.</NOTE> that men should <HI>despaire,</HI> and sink under them, Saying, There is no hope, it is in vaine to wait on the Lord any longer; God hath <HI>condemned</HI> and decreed us, as poor diseased, and <HI>desperate creatures,</HI> to lie always in the <HI>Hospital</HI> under <HI>sores</HI> and <HI>pains,</HI> expecting no cure but that of death, and utter dissolution; If it were<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er. 6. 14.</NOTE> so, God would not here and elsewhere grei∣vously <HI>reproach</HI> and <HI>perstring</HI> those cheating <HI>under∣takers,</HI> those false▪ <HI>Quacksalvers,</HI> these wanton and <HI>cruel Leeches;</HI> who did not want, skill, and know∣ledg, of what would heal <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> in Law and Government, in true Religion and Ju∣stice, in Mercy and Humility, Which are the <HI>best balsoms of both,</HI> and clearly revealed to them by the Lord; but they wanted honesty and fidelity; therefore God pleads against them; <HI>is there no</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 9. 22.</NOTE> <HI>balme in</HI> Gilead? <HI>is there no Physitian? &amp;c. Why then is not the hurt of the daughter of my people re<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o∣vered?</HI> The question (<HI>Is there no Balm?</HI>) is a <HI>ve<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e∣ment affirmation,</HI> a <HI>Satyrick <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; There</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
<HI>are ways</HI> and <HI>means</HI> (<HI>parabiles &amp; ad manum</HI>) suf∣ficient, easy, apt, obvious and at hand to cure the <HI>wounds,</HI> or <HI>bruises,</HI> or <HI>tumors,</HI> or <HI>hurts of any Nati∣on;</HI> if men did not either wilfully shut their eyes against them, and refuse to use them, or if God had not for their hypocrisie, fraud &amp; baseness, just∣ly blinded their eyes, and hid from them the things belonging to their own and the Nations peace, by leaving them to the mists and clouds of their own partial, <HI>covetous</HI> and ambitious <HI>lusts;</HI> Then (indeed) nothing is to be expected, but dayly (<HI>recrudescentia ulcera</HI>) <HI>relapses</HI> and <HI>recruitings</HI> of our wounds, until God gives us Physitians of better eyes and hearts, that may both wisely discern our maladies, and both speedily and faithfully incounter them with seasonable and fit remedies.</P>
<P>§. To which posture of providence we are<NOTE PLACE="marg">The hope and expectation of this day for our healing.</NOTE> prone to hope that we are this day <HI>restored</HI> by the valour, honour and integrity of those who now have the conduct of power and counsel; I pray God we may have cause (<HI>seri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> gaudere</HI>) to re∣joyce long and in good earnest; for every days delay of our oure is a chargeable, uncharitable, and painful <HI>delusion</HI> to the Nation, threatning such a consumption of Spirits, and such <HI>debilitati∣on</HI> of the Nations <HI>strength</HI> and estate (besides the debasing of its honor and reputation) as must necessarily (at Kast) betray us with our poste∣rity, with our <HI>Estates, Laws, Liberties</HI> and <HI>Lives,</HI> yea and with our <HI>Reformed Religion</HI> (which ought to be dearer to us, as it was to our forefathers, than our <HI>live<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> and <HI>estates</HI>) to that <HI>f<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>raign inva∣sion,</HI>
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
and <HI>Romish superstition,</HI> which is the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) the great design of the <HI>Jesuitick agitation,</HI> whereto are subservient all the <HI>fanatick facti∣ons</HI> of those who are such enemies to the just and legal closing, or <HI>composing</HI> of our hurts in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State.</HI></P>
<P>§. It will be found true by us at last (as well as hitherto some others have felt it to their smart) That a Commonwealth as well as <HI>King∣dom</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">M rk. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 25.</NOTE> <HI>divided against it self</HI> cannot long stand; <HI>Et sero medicina paratur, Cum mala per longas in∣valuere moras;</HI> In vain shall we at last cry out, <HI>How have we been deluded? how have we despised counsel, and neglected such plain and safe reme∣dies, as would have cured us long ago?</HI> There want not <HI>birds of prey</HI> (<HI>Eagles, Ravens</HI> and <HI>Vul∣tures</HI>) that wait for the feebleness and fall of this Church and State; that they may pick out its eyes of Religion and Learning, of Law and Justice, the Universities and Inns of Court, that the life and soul of Christian and humane So∣cieties, <HI>Equity</HI> and <HI>Charity, Reason</HI> and true <HI>Re∣ligion</HI> being departed, the (<HI>cadavarosa Patria &amp; Ecclesia</HI>) carkass of our Church and Country may be their spoil and booty, which God of his mercy forbid.</P>
<P>§. In the Text there are six things to be en∣quired.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Division in six parts.</NOTE></P>
<P>1. <HI>Persona laesa, icta, afflicta,</HI> the <HI>Patient</HI> or <HI>af∣flicted;</HI> whom the Prophet, yea God himself <HI>de∣plores</HI> and owns; she is called the <HI>daughter of my people.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="10"/>2. <HI>Plaga</HI> or <HI>laesio;</HI> the <HI>grief</HI> or <HI>malady,</HI> her <HI>hurt</HI> or <HI>lesure.</HI></P>
<P>3. <HI>Ficta medela,</HI> or <HI>insana sanatio,</HI> the pre∣tended cure or verbal <HI>healing;</HI> they have <HI>healed, with saying Peace, peace,</HI> slightly and superfici∣ally.</P>
<P>4. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or <HI>mendacium;</HI> the fallacy and cheat, when there is <HI>no peace.</HI></P>
<P>5. <HI>Medicorum turba;</HI> the <HI>Physitians</HI> or <HI>Empe∣ricks; They,</HI> great Statists, grave Polititians, for∣mal pretenders to do great feats, and miraculous cures in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> when really they are no other than <HI>imperious Hypocrites, magniloquent Montebanks,</HI> cruel and covetous, confident and careless <HI>Boasters</HI> of their skill; but no way <HI>Effecters</HI> of a real cure.</P>
<P>6. <HI>Vera medendi methodus;</HI> the true way of <HI>curing a diseased Nation</HI> a distressed Country, a sick and languishing Church, which is implied and supposed to be</P>
<P>First, As evident in <HI>it self.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, As easie and as <HI>feasible</HI> by these <HI>Pre∣tenders,</HI> if honest.</P>
<P>Thirdly, As it necessary, apt and seasonable for the poor Patient; hence the great blame and reproach imputed to these <HI>Tamperers</HI> or <HI>Medica∣sters; They,</HI> to their sin and shame; <HI>They</HI> with their pride and pollicy; <HI>Thy</HI> with their cunning and cruelty; <HI>They,</HI> more for want of honesty than ability, have thus superficially skinned over, and perfunctorily healed the <HI>hurt of the dauhhter of my people; saying, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="10"/>§. Of these I intend by Gods blessings to speak, not as a <HI>Ruler</HI> or <HI>Magistrate,</HI> nor as a <HI>Statist</HI> and <HI>Politian,</HI> nor as a <HI>Soldier</HI> and <HI>Commander,</HI> nor as a <HI>Citizen</HI> and <HI>Trader,</HI> but as a <HI>Preacher</HI> or <HI>Minister</HI> of God to his Church: And since we are exclu∣ded beyond all men in the Nation, from being chosen to meet or advise in any other ways of publick Counsels, Civil or Ecclesiastical; you may not think much if as men and Christians, no less than <HI>Divines,</HI> we use the freedom of this place to acquaint you with the sence and sympathy of our souls; yea of <HI>Gods Spirit,</HI> in and by the <HI>Pro∣phet;</HI> when he was not a Spectator only, but a joynt suffer (as we Ministers have been more than any order of men) in the common hurts and mise∣ries of Church and State.</P>
<P>1. I begin with the <HI>Patient,</HI> who is called here<NOTE PLACE="marg">The Patient or diseased and hurt daughter of my people.</NOTE> both by God and the Prophet, <HI>The daughter of my people,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, That is <HI>gens mea,</HI> or <HI>populus meus.</HI></P>
<P>First, In relation to God, the people that I<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 As related to God.</NOTE> have bred up with so much care and tenderness; the Nation that hath been to me as a <HI>Son</HI> or <HI>Daughter;</HI> the <HI>Vine</HI> that I have planted, watered and fenced for my self; That Polity of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State</HI> to which I was <HI>Lawgiver,</HI> the chief Counsellor and Constitutor, the supream Head and Governor; the Captain, Shepherd and Bishop; their great King and Protector: <HI>My peculiar people,</HI> whom had preferred <HI>beyond all Nations,</HI> as a <HI>Theocracy</HI> or holy <HI>Monarchy,</HI> or royal <HI>Priest∣hood;</HI> This is the <HI>Patient</HI> with whose <HI>hurts,</HI> sores,
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
<HI>bruises, wounds</HI> and <HI>sorrows,</HI> these <HI>practicants</HI> have most impudently <HI>padled,</HI> and cruelly pleased them∣selves, in turning <HI>publique miseries</HI> of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State</HI> to their private <HI>advantages.</HI></P>
<P>2. In relation to the <HI>Prophet;</HI> the <HI>daughter of</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 As related and indeared to the Prophet</NOTE> <HI>my people,</HI> which are of the same <HI>linage</HI> and <HI>de∣rivation;</HI> of the same <HI>Father</HI> and <HI>Family;</HI> of the nearest blood, both by <HI>parentage</HI> and <HI>alliance;</HI> with whom I have the same Laws and <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ivil im∣munities;</HI> also the same <HI>Religion</HI> and <HI>sacred com∣munion;</HI> Natural, Civil, Ecclesiastical kindred endears me to them; they are <HI>as flesh of my flesh and bone of my bone;</HI> yea we are, or ought to be of the same spirit and soul, as having the same <HI>God and Saviour,</HI> the same <HI>holy duties</HI> or <HI>solemni∣ties,</HI> to engage us in love and <HI>dearness</HI> as well as <HI>nearness</HI> to each other, so as the publick and com∣mon good should be the supream good of every particular: We cannot be happy or miserable alone; as members in one body, all our enjoy∣ments are <HI>social,</HI> and all our sufferings are <HI>sympa∣thetick;</HI> This is the <HI>daughter of my people,</HI> for whom I am so concerned and afflicted, that I <HI>preach</HI> and <HI>pray,</HI> I <HI>write</HI> and <HI>weep,</HI> I <HI>wake</HI> and <HI>dream, lamentations</HI> and <HI>tears</HI> for her a man, as a Citizen, as a true Israelite, or Jew, as a Christian, as a Protestant or reformed Pro∣fessor.</P>
<P>This Tittle of the <HI>Daughter of my people,</HI> is so<NOTE PLACE="marg">The impor∣tance of the Title. The Daughter of my people.</NOTE> frequent in Scripture, that it seems to importune the Reader to consider the importance of it; <HI>Isa.</HI> 1. 8. and 22. 4. <HI>Jer.</HI> 4. 12. and 9. 1. and 6. 14, 19.
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
<HI>Lam. 2. 11. Zach.</HI> 9. 9. So <HI>Daughter of Sion,</HI> and of <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> or the like expressions.</P>
<P>First, To shew, not so much the <HI>fruitfulness</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Fertility.</NOTE> of a Nation, whom God so blesseth, that they in∣crease and multiply, as that softer and procreative or mother sex doth, to great numbers, which are as the off-sets or fruit of a pregnant womb; as the people of God are sometimes called his <HI>first born,</HI> and his <HI>sons,</HI> in respect of that masculine<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 19.</NOTE> vigor and valor which was among them while God with them; so the <HI>daughter of his people,</HI> as apt to bring forth.</P>
<P>Secondly, But further to express the tender<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Tenderness and indul∣gence▪</NOTE> care, and fatherly indulgence that God hath to∣ward such a people as are called by <HI>his name,</HI> who have had the special signets and bracelets, the Jewels and Ornaments of his favor, the glory of his Ordinances and presence among them: God himself is afflicted in her afflictions; such as tor∣ment her torment him; he feels her <HI>wounds,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">3 Sympathy in God and the Prophet.</NOTE> and faints as it were to see her <HI>blood</HI> prodigally shed as water on the ground, either by open ene∣mies, or <HI>fallacious Physitians,</HI> and cruel Phleboto∣mists; who under pretence of healing the hurts they have made, or <HI>festred,</HI> venomed and <HI>in∣flamed</HI>) do cut, and lance, and sear, and lop, and purge, and let blood, to such <HI>evacuation,</HI> and <HI>super∣fluity,</HI> as quite exhaust the best and <HI>vital spirits</HI> of a Nation; bringing it to fainting fits and <HI>con∣<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ulsions,</HI> to weakness and <HI>consumption.</HI> As a Fa∣ther would be affected to see his <HI>tender daugh∣ter</HI> thus used and abused (which cannot endure
<PB N="14" REF="12"/>
<HI>pains</HI> like the hardier and rougher sex of <HI>Sons</HI>) so is God and so is his Prophet; and so is every good man and woman to the Church and Countrey whereto they are so nearly rela∣ted.</P>
<P>§. God is so concerned and touched to the<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier 31. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>0</NOTE> quick, that his <HI>bowels are turned within him;</HI> he deplores himself as if he were a <HI>miserable God,</HI> while his people, his <HI>sons</HI> and <HI>daughters</HI> are mise∣rable, either by their <HI>sins</HI> or <HI>sufferings;</HI> God hath his <HI>sympathies</HI> with them, his reputings toward them, his returns with tears and kisses for them, as a compassionate and good natured parent hath toward his <HI>daughter</HI> when he hath been forced to use her hardly; and hath in his anger either wounded, or bruised, and hurt her.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>kindnesses</HI> that in mankind are <HI>humane affections,</HI> in God are <HI>Divine perfections:</HI> None can be so good natured, so <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, as the good God is; if we were not cruel to him and our own souls, he could never be other than most kind to us; for he doth not afflict us willingly; We compel him to be <HI>froward</HI> by our <HI>froward∣ness,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 22. 17</NOTE> and to break upon us by rebelling against him; we bruise our selves by dashing against that <HI>rock</HI> which would be our <HI>refuge</HI> and shelter; <HI>we wound our selves</HI> by running upon that <HI>sword which would only be our defence:</HI> God never ceaseth to be our <HI>father,</HI> till we cease to behave our selves as his <HI>children.</HI></P>
<P>§. From the blessed God, the best men learn
<PB N="15" REF="12"/>
and derive this tender love, care compassion and<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of the love due to our Countrey.</NOTE> indulgence towards the <HI>Daughter of their people,</HI> both in civil and sacred relations; the concern∣ments or <HI>interests</HI> of both are great endearments to gracious souls: hence as other Prophets so spe∣cially <HI>Jeremiah,</HI> becomes a man of <HI>sorrows;</HI> his eyes <HI>run down night and day with rivers of tears,</HI> nor can he be comforted while <HI>Sion</HI> is afflicted; Though he be <HI>wel-nigh drowned</HI> in his own tears, yet he wisheth, <HI>Jer.</HI> 9. 1. <HI>O that my head were a fountain of tears.</HI></P>
<P><HI>His bowels, his bowels are pained within him</HI> (by<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 4. 19</NOTE> that coarctation or compression, which great grief, fear and horror makes upon (by the retirings of spirit and blood) the <HI>lactes</HI> and smaller bowels, which are near the heart;) he is <HI>weary of life,</HI> which doth but daily torment him with so many <HI>sad spectacles,</HI> such dreadful diurnals, such <HI>un∣welcome news,</HI> of breach upon breach; such a dying and self-destroying Church and State; all things growing worse and worse and no <HI>remedy:</HI> Still the <HI>alarm of war,</HI> and sound of the <HI>Trumpet:</HI> The Church and State Physitians are wholly for <HI>corrosives</HI> and no <HI>lenitives;</HI> for fraud and force, not for Reason and Law; they pretend necessi∣ty, and pursue providences till they are in wil∣derness of woe and confusion; far from peace,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lam, 3. 17</NOTE> <HI>health,</HI> salvation and <HI>establishment;</HI> which are the effects and fruits only of <HI>Righteousness</HI> and <HI>Ju∣stice,</HI> of <HI>Reason</HI> and <HI>Religion.</HI> Hence the Pro∣phet with vehemency demands, and demanding he deplores, and deploring he reproacheth the
<PB N="16" REF="13"/>
folly and defect, the stupidity and cruelty of those in power; <HI>Is there no balm in Gilead? is there no</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 8. 22.</NOTE> <HI>Physitian? Why then is not the health of the daugh∣ter of my people recovered.</HI></P>
<P>The best of the Heathens had very quick stroaks<NOTE PLACE="marg">The heathens compassion &amp; courage for their Country.</NOTE> upon their <HI>heart strings,</HI> by the love and care they had of their Countries; they thought it (<HI>dulce &amp; decorum pro patria mori</HI>) most worthy of a good man not onely to live, but also to die for his Countries <HI>safety</HI> and <HI>honor.</HI></P>
<P>§. It argues mindes without natural affection not to have <HI>compassion for their Country,</HI> and more for their <HI>Church;</HI> They must be <HI>Cyclopick monsters</HI> of <HI>brutish Barbarity,</HI> who can like <HI>Can∣nibals</HI> feed on the <HI>flesh</HI> and drink the <HI>blood</HI> of their Country and <HI>neighbors,</HI> of their kindred, of their <HI>parents</HI> and of their children; yea of their very <HI>daughters,</HI> who have a priviledge and plea from their sex for greatest tender∣ness.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>daughter of our people</HI> in respect of our<NOTE PLACE="marg">Our Country is both our Mother and Daughter.</NOTE> posterity and descendents from us, whom we leave to succeed after us, in our <HI>lands,</HI> houses, and <HI>estates;</HI> is also our <HI>Mother</HI> and <HI>Parent, com∣munis parens,</HI> if we look backward, as we are derived from our <HI>Forefathers; Patria est &amp; mater &amp; silia;</HI> our Country is our parent or mother, also our childe or daughter, in different aspects, and so requires different respects:</P>
<P>First, Of reverence, as to our <HI>majores, pro∣genitores</HI>) Father or Mother, that begat and bare us.</P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="13"/>Secondly, of <HI>Indulgence,</HI> as to our <HI>Daughter</HI> or <HI>posteri,</HI> which derive from us: In both, that love and kindness is expected, and by the <HI>Law of Nature</HI> (which is Gods Law) so commanded; that they <HI>sin highly</HI> who are so cruel, as either to sacrifice their <HI>Sons</HI> and <HI>daughters,</HI> or their <HI>Fa∣thers</HI> and <HI>Mothers,</HI> their Church and Country, root and branch to the <HI>fires</HI> and flames of <HI>civil Wars</HI> and <HI>dissentions,</HI> begun and continued by their sinful cruelty, and tyrannous hypocri∣sie.</P>
<P>§. <HI>Can a Mother forget her childe,</HI> or a <HI>Father</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 9 15</NOTE> <HI>cast off his Son,</HI> or sheath his sword in the <HI>bowels</HI> of his <HI>daughter,</HI> without the just imputation of <HI>madniss</HI> and <HI>inhumanity?</HI> Judge then, what men, yea what <HI>Sea-monsters</HI> they are, that can be stu∣diously, designedly and industriously cruel to that Country wherein they were bred; and to that Church in which they were baptized, to deform the beauty and destroy the blessings of peace, plenty, order, good government; and true Religion left them by their <HI>Progenitors,</HI> and to leave to posterity nothing but <HI>poverty</HI> and <HI>pain, terrors</HI> and <HI>Wars, blood</HI> and <HI>confusion, hypocrisie</HI> and <HI>cruelty, fanatick fury</HI> and <HI>military insolency;</HI> nothing but either <HI>oppression</HI> or <HI>Anarchy;</HI> either the crys of the oppressors threatning, pillaging and exacting as grievous <HI>tax-masters,</HI> or of the oppressed, mourning and deploring their sad con∣dition in vain, while either the cords of un∣righteous decrees do binde a Nation captive to
<PB N="18" REF="14"/>
the lusts of unreasonable and merciless men, as to the rack and torture, or such daily executi∣ons of violence, exasperation and rigor, as fills the land with discontent, blood and tumult; the <HI>daughter of his people,</HI> daily appearing as the <HI>slain wallowing</HI> in their own blood; and her voyce<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezek. 3<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 14</NOTE> is as the <HI>groans of a deadly wounded and dying man.</HI></P>
<P>Fourthly and lastly, this denomination or title<NOTE PLACE="marg">The dange∣rous and deso∣late estate of a Nation depri∣ved of her true Fathers.</NOTE> of <HI>the daughter of my people,</HI> imports, as the happy estate of any Nation, that is thus under Gods eye and tender care; also under the pro∣tection, or guardianship of <HI>wise Governors,</HI> of just and lawful Magistrates, who carry themselves as <HI>Nursing-fathers</HI> and <HI>Nursing-mothers</HI> to Church<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 43. 23.</NOTE> and State; yea as kind Husbands, and indul∣gent Spouses to their beloved Brides or Wives: So it shews how sad, <HI>desolate</HI> and helpless, yea how <HI>dangerous</HI> and exposed to <HI>miseries,</HI> both of <HI>dishonour</HI> and death, and all manner of hurts, incident to any Church and State, the conditi∣on of any people is, that is not under Gods care, or is deprived by their sin and madness, of good Governors, of lawful <HI>Magistrates,</HI> of able <HI>Mini∣sters,</HI> and Pastors; such a Nation or Church is as a poor, weak, helpless <HI>daughter,</HI> that is an Or∣phan or <HI>fatherless,</HI> without any friend, father or husband to defend and take care of her; she be∣comes as a <HI>forsaken virgin,</HI> subject to all those inso∣lencies and indignities, to which her own weak∣ness; and the power of others lusts may expose her; nor can she have any safety, health, honor
<PB N="19" REF="14"/>
security, or handsom subsistance and defence untill she be restored to the care and protection of those who under God deserve to be, and by law are <HI>Patres patriae,</HI> the true <HI>Fathers of the daughter of their people;</HI> All others that usurp on a <HI>Nation</HI> are, as unjust, so hard <HI>Fathers, Fathers in law,</HI> because without and against law, having neither the Law of God nor man for their <HI>usurped authority,</HI> nor the <HI>Law</HI> of love and tenderness in their stony hearts; but as <HI>Physitians</HI> (who unsent for, obtrude their <HI>visits</HI> and <HI>practice,</HI> more for their <HI>fee</HI> and <HI>gains</HI> than for any <HI>love</HI> to their <HI>Pa∣tients welfare</HI>) are most welcome when the Pati∣ent is <HI>soonest rid of them,</HI> whose <HI>project</HI> is rather to <HI>protract</HI> and perpetuate their <HI>Patients Afflictions,</HI> than to cover them; nor are they afraid of kill∣ling them, further than their gain may dye with them, and their <HI>pragmatick</HI> humor have less <HI>mis∣chief to do.</HI></P>
<P>§. But I have <HI>done</HI> with the first particular, the<NOTE PLACE="marg">Conclusion of the first part of the Text.</NOTE> import of this <HI>stile,</HI> and <HI>compellation,</HI> the <HI>daughter of my people;</HI> thus <HI>God,</HI> and thus the <HI>Prophet,</HI> thus all good men, and all good Christians are wonted to <HI>speak,</HI> and <HI>think,</HI> and <HI>act,</HI> to love, to pitty, and to pray for their country, both-<HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State.</HI> What I beseech you must they be, who wound her with the <HI>wounds</HI> of an <HI>Enimy,</HI> and smite her with the strokes of a <HI>cruel one,</HI> as if all their <HI>policy,</HI> and <HI>power,</HI> served to no other use, but to <HI>execute ani∣mosities,</HI> and <HI>exercise antipathies,</HI> against <HI>their country,</HI> to eat out (as the generation of vipers are vulgarly said do) the bowels of their <HI>mother,</HI> who
<PB N="20" REF="15"/>
<HI>pray</HI> not for the <HI>peace</HI> of <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> but seek to make a <HI>prey</HI> of her, both in <HI>peace</HI> and <HI>war,</HI> in things <HI>sacred</HI> and <HI>civil,</HI> condemning her to everlasting enmities, wars, divisions, confusions, taxes and ex∣actions, which cannot be removed, till <HI>health is re∣stored;</HI> nor can this be, till the great <HI>wounds</HI> and wide <HI>breaches</HI> made and continued, yea <HI>enlarged</HI> by some, are <HI>closed and drawn together;</HI> till there be a (<HI>redintegratio continui, et reparatio disjuncti,</HI>) restitution of all noble parts that are necessary for the publique integrality and unity; its order and beauty, its honour and safety; Which what they are, and how to be done, I leave it to wise, <HI>honest</HI> and <HI>impartial</HI> men, who have <HI>counsel</HI> to <HI>guide</HI> their <HI>power,</HI> and <HI>power</HI> to executeor <HI>put in practice their good and healing counsels,</HI> in spight of all the Leeches <HI>and Empiricks,</HI> that would hinder pub∣lique health, that they might from the open <HI>Orifi∣ces</HI> of their bleeding <HI>Country,</HI> suck more <HI>advan∣tages</HI> for <HI>themselves</HI> and their parties to the <HI>ruine of the whole.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, Having visited the <HI>Patient,</HI> and find∣ing it to be our <HI>near Relation,</HI> as a <HI>Sister,</HI> or <HI>Daughter,</HI> or <HI>Mother,</HI> even our Country and Church; It is time for us to consider its <HI>hurt or affliction,</HI> to see what it ails; what that <HI>plaga,</HI> or <HI>vulnus,</HI> or <HI>laesio,</HI> or <HI>morbus</HI> is, wherewith it is so pained that it cannot rest night nor day: Our work is not onely to <HI>behold her a far off</HI> with si∣lence <HI>and stupor</HI> (as <HI>Jobs</HI> friends) in her grief and anguish, but either apply suitable <HI>reme∣dies,</HI> or at least such <HI>prayers and words of com∣fort</HI>
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
(<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> to her heart) as may show our pitty and <HI>compassion,</HI> which is some <HI>relief</HI> to those that are in bitterness of <HI>soul.</HI></P>
<P>The Hebrew word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> (whence our English <HI>shiver</HI> may well be derived) is rendred by the LXX. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, and by the Latin <HI>contritio,</HI> which properly <HI>imports</HI> some injury or <HI>hurt</HI> inflicted (<HI>ab extra</HI>) from an outward aget, by violence, so as to <HI>wound</HI> or <HI>bruise,</HI> or <HI>batter,</HI> or <HI>break,</HI> or <HI>tear;</HI> any thing that causeth (<HI>solutionem continui</HI>) <HI>separation</HI> or <HI>dissipation</HI> of parts which should be united, and in whose right union is ease, as in their dissolution or dislocation is pain.</P>
<P>§. But the latitude of the word may well ex∣tent to the larger scope and intent of the place and <HI>complaint;</HI> which is not onely upon the ac∣count of outward force and violent <HI>impression,</HI> made upon <HI>Church and State,</HI> against all <HI>Reason, Justice</HI> and <HI>Religion;</HI> but as in bodies <HI>natural,</HI> so in these <HI>politique</HI> (both civil and <HI>Ecclestastical</HI>) there are many kinds of <HI>hurts or maladis</HI> incident to them, both from <HI>within</HI> and from <HI>with∣out.</HI></P>
<P>§. There are besides (<HI>v<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lnera</HI>) or flesh wounds,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>bred hur<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s or di∣stempers.</NOTE> and (<HI>ulcera</HI>). which are <HI>inveterate sores;</HI> and (<HI>gangrenae</HI>) gangreens which are deadly; if not speedily cured or cut off, their are <HI>pustuli,</HI> ve∣nemous tumors, or <HI>angry biles,</HI> which arise from some putid or <HI>corrupt humors</HI> in the body, also running <HI>issues</HI> and <HI>sistulas,</HI> which are most at ease when they have some vent, and most dan∣gerous, when suddenly and indisretly <HI>stopped;</HI>
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
these are <HI>hurts</HI> too, and very grievous ones, when times are such, by the discontent of mens minds, by the dissolution of their licentious man∣ners, by weakning the <HI>authoritie</HI> of <HI>Laws,</HI> and overturning the course of <HI>Government</HI> in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> (<HI>ut nec morbos, necremedia ferre pos∣sint;</HI>) that either the pertinacy of <HI>customary dis∣orders</HI> and prevalent mischiefs, or the <HI>petulancy of people overgrown</HI> with <HI>epidemical</HI> and <HI>tolerated diseases,</HI> will not endure fit <HI>remedies,</HI> yet are un∣done if they linger under their distempers un∣cured.</P>
<P>§. Sometimes a body grows plethorick, and is<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hurts by <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e∣duudancy of humors</NOTE> hurt by its excess of humors, crude and indigest∣ed, which are prone to gather together and fall on any weak disaffected part; there to fer∣ment and inflame, to high feavors and verry great anguish of the whole; so is it in a Nation when either <HI>over-peopled</HI> to an indigence and idleness, through want of work; or when grown luxuri∣ant by long peace and plenty, which runs to <HI>sot∣tery</HI> in many, and at last to the <HI>armed man po∣verty;</HI> whose <HI>free quarter</HI> pressing on people pro∣vokes them to discontents, and so to design pub∣liqe troubles (<HI>quia multis utile bellum</HI>) because they have nothing left them but their carkasses, and their swords; dig they cannot, to beg they are ashamed, <HI>fighting</HI> is their only fortune.</P>
<P>§. Other while a Nation may be too much <HI>ex∣hausted</HI> by war, by exactions and oppressions, by decay and want of trade, so as it becomes <HI>con∣sumptive, weak</HI> and <HI>languishing,</HI> either the (<HI>humi∣dum</HI>
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
<HI>radicale</HI>) native moisture, <HI>oyl</HI> and <HI>balm</HI> of competency is wasted for want of encouraged <HI>industry</HI> and commerce; or the <HI>calor nuturalis,</HI> the <HI>spirits activity,</HI> and generosity of a people are (as the <HI>Moderne Egiptians,</HI>) quite extinct; being either <HI>sottishly idle,</HI> or so cowed and over-awed, that they are <HI>crestfallen,</HI> and below any gallant <HI>actions</HI> and <HI>designs;</HI> living more like slaves under hard Ma∣sters, than like the <HI>Sons</HI> and <HI>Daughters</HI> of a <HI>Father∣ly Prince,</HI> or a free and legal <HI>Polity;</HI> much as poor <HI>Hospital wretches,</HI> who are condemned to live aways under the hands of <HI>Physitians,</HI> and <HI>Chy∣rurgeons,</HI> kept down by Janisaries, and daily ter∣rified with either taxes, or instruments of pain, or menaces of death. Certainly, as <HI>qui medicae,</HI> so <HI>qui militariter vivit, misere vivit.</HI> It is a kil∣ing and dying life, to live always under the <HI>Chy∣rurgeons</HI> lance, or the <HI>Souldiers</HI> sword.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>Hurts</HI> of a <HI>Nation</HI> may be distinguished<NOTE PLACE="marg">3 Civil hur<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s or bod<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly di∣ste<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pets by in∣justice.</NOTE> into those that either disaffect the body and outward man, by <HI>Tyranny, Injustice</HI> and <HI>oppression,</HI> contrary to the known laws, good constitutions and venerable customs of a people (which are the <HI>native and self-healing balsom</HI> of those great bo∣dies) pressing upon the estates, propertys, liber∣ties, limbs, lives and hourrs of mankind; When either <HI>Superiors,</HI> like the <HI>disaffected head,</HI> distil too sharp and corrosive humors upon <HI>inferior parts,</HI> or these send up (by a kind of circulation, or <HI>exhal∣tation</HI>) pestilent fumes and vapors of mutiny and <HI>rebellion</HI> against their Heads and Superiors, jealous of, and envying each others welfare, also
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
withdrawing that natural assistance from each other, which is indeed the support and health of the whole.</P>
<P>§. These <HI>hurts</HI> are very <HI>dangerous,</HI> and ought to be speedily composed to such an harmony as is a tolerable state of <HI>health,</HI> by adjusting every one their rights assigned to them by that Law, which so takes care and provides for the publick order, beauty, and welfare of all, that it per∣mits no one private <HI>interest,</HI> like a <HI>wen</HI> or <HI>leech,</HI> or <HI>Incubus</HI> to oppress, <HI>drein</HI> and destroy anothers, for as in <HI>Nature</HI> so in <HI>States,</HI> the whole cannot be well at ease, if one part be grievously pained or pierced.</P>
<P>§. There are sometimes <HI>horrible rapes</HI> com∣mitted<NOTE PLACE="marg">4 Of violent rapes commit∣ted on the Daughter of my people.</NOTE> upon the <HI>daughter of my people,</HI> while <HI>vile</HI> and <HI>violent men</HI> (<HI>sons of Belial</HI>) to satisfie their own <HI>inordinate lusts</HI> of <HI>revenge, covetousness, pride</HI> or <HI>ambition,</HI> apply by <HI>force</HI> or <HI>fraud,</HI> or both, to obtain that <HI>power</HI> and <HI>place,</HI> that <HI>favor</HI> and <HI>preferment</HI> in the publick, which they dis∣pair to get in fair and honest ways of worthy <HI>industry</HI> and <HI>merit.</HI> These are like the <HI>incestuou<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ravishers</HI> of their own <HI>Sisters,</HI> or <HI>Daughters,</HI> or <HI>Mothers;</HI> men that have much of <HI>Cateline</HI> in them; nothing of the true Christian; nor are they to be envied, if they prosper for a time in their <HI>wicked devices</HI> and <HI>endeavours,</HI> since this is all the <HI>shadow of greatness</HI> they shall ever en∣joy; while for a moments <HI>glory</HI> among a com∣pany of <HI>poor mortals</HI> they venture eternal <HI>debase∣ment</HI> among the Devils; where such great sin∣ners
<PB N="25" REF="17"/>
shall be <HI>greatly tormented;</HI> nor will their <HI>pro∣sperity</HI> procure their <HI>impunity;</HI> though they dye in <HI>peace,</HI> yet they descend to an <HI>eternall war,</HI> which is (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) never to be ended by peace or truce, nor yet by <HI>annihilation</HI> or <HI>ex∣tinction.</HI></P>
<P>§. There are als<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>grievous hurts,</HI> which may be∣fall<NOTE PLACE="marg">5. Spiritual hurt<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 1. As to Religion.</NOTE> a Nation as to its very <HI>soul</HI> and <HI>better spirits,</HI> that is, its <HI>intellectuall powers</HI> and <HI>excellencies</HI> of <HI>Religion</HI> and <HI>Learning,</HI> of <HI>rationall</HI> and <HI>ingenuous</HI> improvements, most worthy of <HI>men,</HI> of <HI>Gentle∣men,</HI> and <HI>Christians.</HI></P>
<P>These <HI>hurts</HI> are when <HI>true Religion,</HI> which is founded on Gods word, confirmed by the te∣stimony of the Church of God in all ages, <HI>forti∣fied</HI> by good Laws; <HI>regulated</HI> by good Discipline or Government, and <HI>supported</HI> by <HI>honourable en∣couragements;</HI> when this is either corrupted in its soundness of doctrine, or overgrown (as the head with a scald) by superstition, or broken by facti∣on, or bafled by vulgar insolency, or persecuted by misguided zeal, or oppressed by <HI>inordinate power,</HI> or robbed of its just <HI>maintenance,</HI> or dis∣composed in its due order and government, or despised in its <HI>best Preachers</HI> and <HI>Professors,</HI> or run out to the <HI>itch</HI> and <HI>s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ratch</HI> (the <HI>soabies &amp; pruritus disputandi,</HI> as Sir <HI>Henry Watton</HI> calls it) of disputing and jangling, which breeds uncha∣ritable and empty formalities; tending and end∣ing in <HI>prophaness</HI> and <HI>Atheism,</HI> extinguishing truth and love, sound faith, and sincere chari∣ty, which are as the oyle and flame of the lamp
<PB N="26" REF="18"/>
of Religion in any Church and heart; these are most dangerous distempers, and hardly to be <HI>cu∣red</HI> or <HI>recovered,</HI> unless such speedy <HI>cordials</HI> and <HI>antidotes</HI> be applied by wise <HI>Magistrates,</HI> sober <HI>Ministers,</HI> and sincere <HI>Christian people,</HI> as may <HI>recollect, refocillate</HI> and <HI>restore</HI> the power of god∣liness, and spirits of true Religion, by <HI>dissipating</HI> and expelling those noxious and <HI>pestilent oppres∣sions,</HI> with which either <HI>Princes,</HI> or <HI>Peers,</HI> or <HI>People,</HI> or <HI>Preachers</HI> have pressed upon <HI>true Reli∣gion,</HI> by <HI>Covetousnesse,</HI> or <HI>Ambition,</HI> or <HI>Sacriledge,</HI> or <HI>Schism,</HI> or <HI>Popularity,</HI> or love of <HI>Novelty,</HI> or <HI>Sedition,</HI> to the great disgrace of <HI>true Religion,</HI> and the best Ministers of it, both Fathers and Sons.</P>
<P>§. It is observed by <HI>Guildas</HI> and others, who give account of our English subversions by <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xons</HI> and <HI>Danes</HI> (when we were Christian and civili∣zed, but they Heathens and barbarous) that no∣thing more <HI>presaged</HI> the deluge of those <HI>miseries,</HI> which followed such <HI>invasions,</HI> than the great contempt and <HI>oppression</HI> to which the <HI>Clergie</HI> and <HI>Religious Orders</HI> were brought; partly it may be by their own sloth and <HI>luxury;</HI> but chiefly by the prophane insolency of all sorts of people; who were content to have all <HI>Religious cords</HI> broke asunder, that they might enjoy the full sway of their <HI>licentious humors.</HI></P>
<P>§. Again when <HI>good learning</HI> (which is a most<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. Hurts as <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o good Learning</NOTE> officious, useful and comely <HI>handmaid</HI> to <HI>Religi∣on</HI>) when <HI>humane Arts</HI> and <HI>Sciences</HI> (which are beams or structures of <HI>divine wisdom</HI>) when <HI>studies</HI>
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
of <HI>good Laws,</HI> and due administration of <HI>Justice</HI> accordingly, (which are the vital spirits of a Na∣tion) when these are <HI>villified</HI> and outraged by the vilest people, by <HI>Jack-Straws</HI> and <HI>Wat-Tilers,</HI> whose ignorance makes them enemies to <HI>know∣ledge,</HI> as darknesse is to <HI>light</HI> (being like Mastiffs, the feircer for those <HI>dark kennels</HI> in which they are bred and kept up.) When this ill kind of men cry down (like the <HI>Ephesine</HI> rabble) with<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts. 15. 28.</NOTE> dust and clamor, more then any shew of reason, all <HI>Scoholes</HI> of <HI>Learning</HI> and <HI>Universities,</HI> that they may run after <HI>false Prophets</HI> and <HI>Dreamers,</HI> whose simplicity is so impudent to pretend <HI>inspirations</HI> and <HI>new lights,</HI> to so eagle-eyed and quick sight∣ed a people as the English are, till their <HI>delusions and folly are manifested.</HI></P>
<P>§. These are as rough <HI>Satyrs,</HI> a kind of robust <HI>wilde men,</HI> who trust more either to their <HI>limbs</HI> and <HI>sinews,</HI> or to their <HI>wit</HI> and <HI>cunning,</HI> than to their consciences, or our Laws for the getting of their Living; aiming to live more like <HI>beasts</HI> by rapine, then like civil men and good Chri∣stians, by honest labour and ingenuous in∣dustry.</P>
<P>§. Nor are they small <HI>hurts</HI> which the teeth of such <HI>Foxes,</HI> and tuskes of such <HI>Boars</HI> have given to any Church or State, where they have for a while <HI>prevailed;</HI> being much fitter for <HI>Ma∣hometan conversation</HI> than <HI>Christian profession;</HI> for there (among Turks) only force or fury makes men <HI>considerable;</HI> for they think that their Prin∣ces and their mad-men are highly favoured and
<PB N="28" REF="19"/>
most familiar with God and his Angels.</P>
<P>§. These <HI>hurts</HI> on the <HI>mental spirits,</HI> or <HI>intel∣lectuall powers</HI> of a Nation, are more dangerous than those that are incident by <HI>grosser wounds</HI> of <HI>outward immortalities,</HI> which the <HI>Physick</HI> or <HI>dicticks</HI> of <HI>good Laws</HI> well executed, will easily keep from <HI>predominating;</HI> but the <HI>hurts</HI> which fall on <HI>Religion</HI> and <HI>Learning,</HI> on the <HI>Reason</HI> and <HI>Conscience</HI> of a Nation, are like frenetick <HI>distem∣pers,</HI> long a <HI>growing,</HI> and long a <HI>going,</HI> like the <HI>wounds</HI> on the <HI>head,</HI> or <HI>cracks,</HI> as we say, of the <HI>brain,</HI> hardly ever throughly cured; when <HI>Here∣sie</HI> or <HI>Schism,</HI> like a <HI>spirituall frenzy</HI> hath <HI>seised</HI> on <HI>any people;</HI> as was evident in the <HI>Manachies, Novations, Arians, Donatists, Nestorians, Euty∣chians</HI> and others, of ancient and modern ages.</P>
<P>§. There are further, <HI>plagae per peccatum,</HI> and<NOTE PLACE="marg">Publick hurts from sins pre∣dominant and unpunished.</NOTE> <HI>propter peccatum;</HI> hurts from sin, and for sin; the first <HI>hurts</HI> are by our own evill <HI>meritings,</HI> as the self wounds of a <HI>drunkard;</HI> the second by <HI>Gods just inflictings</HI> upon malefactors; for he will not always leave the publick sins of a Nation, without visiting with sore and publike punishments.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>first hurts</HI> are those from <HI>sins,</HI> when they <HI>grow great</HI> and <HI>masterly, boysterous</HI> and <HI>impe∣rious,</HI> either <HI>countenanced</HI> in <HI>Court,</HI> or <HI>indulged</HI> in City, or <HI>prevalent</HI> and neglected in Countries; when <HI>prophanenesse,</HI> and <HI>lying and swearing,</HI> and<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 27. 10. Isa. 59. 3: Hos. 4. 2.</NOTE> <HI>drunkennesse,</HI> and <HI>vncleannesse,</HI> and <HI>murthers</HI> or the like <HI>faedities</HI> come to pollute a great or a consi∣derable part of a Nation, so as men make a
<PB N="29" REF="19"/>
mock of sin, and <HI>glory in their shame;</HI> when <HI>Re∣bellion, Perjury, Innocent-blood-shed</HI> and <HI>Sacri∣ledge</HI> are drawn on) like strait and pinching shooes at first) with the <HI>shooing horne</HI> of <HI>Religion</HI> and <HI>Refor∣mation,</HI> of publick necessity, thrift and good Hus∣bandry, with antipathies against <HI>Idolatry,</HI> and abhorrencies of <HI>superstitions;</HI> when <HI>Prince</HI> is bad and <HI>people</HI> worse, and <HI>Priest</HI> or <HI>Prophet</HI> worst of all: When from the <HI>Rulers</HI> or <HI>Teachers</HI> of a Nation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 5 31. and 6. 13.</NOTE> wickednesse as a <HI>plague of leprosie,</HI> is spread over all the Land: When there is a loathing of the <HI>heavenly Manna,</HI> a contempt of <HI>Word</HI> and <HI>Sacraments,</HI> an <HI>indifferency</HI> to all Religion, as little <HI>reverence</HI> in a <HI>Church at holy duties,</HI> as in a <HI>Play-house,</HI> and fat less than in a <HI>Shire-house;</HI> these <HI>fiery darts</HI> of mens own wanton lusts and the devils tempta∣tions do wound very deep; they at once <HI>pierce</HI> and <HI>sear,</HI> they <HI>hurt</HI> and <HI>stupifie,</HI> they make men past feeling at length, and only fit them for vengeance.</P>
<P>§. The <HI>second hurts</HI> are <HI>propter peccatum;</HI> those<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hurts f<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> sin by Gods in∣flicting.</NOTE> which the just and <HI>angry God</HI> in his sore <HI>judge∣ments inflicts</HI> on a people now incorrigible in or∣dinary ways and; most severely on those that<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 25. 29.</NOTE> are <HI>called by his name,</HI> and owned as <HI>the daughter of his people;</HI> so the Jews by various hurts and healings were objects of Gods wrath and mercy, till they had filled up the measure of sin. See the <HI>Eastern, Asiatick, Greek, Egyptick</HI> and <HI>African</HI> Churches; how famous, how fruitfull, how flou∣rishing, till wounded with sins, over-grown with gross heresies and schisins, noisom lusts, base opi∣nions
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
and bad actions: the sword of Gods ven∣geance by the barbarous <HI>inundations</HI> of <HI>Scythians, Sacracens, Turks,</HI> and other <HI>Colluvies</HI> or scum of people at last so divided them, that they are at this day almost utterly destroyed.</P>
<P>§. The arrows of presumptuous sins shot up against heaven, fall on the heads of the shooters to their own hurt (as <HI>Lamech</HI> speaks) And as <HI>Solomon</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 6. 32.</NOTE> tells us, <HI>wicked men sin against their own souls,</HI> and so against the peace, plenty, honor, health and wel∣fare of their Nation and posterity: sin (as <HI>Pliny</HI> says of Quick-silver) is (<HI>venenum omnium</HI>) the pest and poison of all <HI>things;</HI> it urgeth God to be as a <HI>cruel one,</HI> it <HI>provokes</HI> till there be no <HI>mediation,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Chron. 36. 16</NOTE> <HI>intercession</HI> or <HI>Remedy:</HI> when men proudly and im∣penitently treasure up sin, they treasure up with∣al <HI>wrath against the day of wrath,</HI> till judge∣ment break in like the flood on the old world, or fall like <HI>fire from heaven</HI> without any to help, or the earth open and <HI>swallow men</HI> up quick, as <HI>Korah</HI> and his complices.</P>
<P>§. Here God is in Justice and Honor <HI>concerned</HI> to arise, to <HI>bend his bow,</HI> to <HI>whet his sword,</HI> to be avenged on such a <HI>nation,</HI> which is <HI>grown wanton∣ly</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 5. 9. and 9. 9.</NOTE> <HI>wicked,</HI> which dares <HI>fight against God,</HI> yea and <HI>challenge</HI> him, whether he regard <HI>iniquity or no,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psalm. 6. 11.</NOTE> whether he be not such an <HI>one as themselves;</HI> the <HI>wounds</HI> which men inflict on the <HI>Spirit, Grace</HI> and <HI>Glory of God,</HI> force him to wound them; when there is no <HI>fear of God,</HI> no <HI>shame,</HI> or <HI>remorse,</HI> or <HI>repentance</HI> for sin (<HI>ideo conterimur quia non conte∣rimur; ideo vulneramur quia non vulneramur,</HI> as St.
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
<HI>Bernard</HI>) because our hearts are not <HI>broken,</HI> nor our <HI>spirits contrite</HI> with in us for sin, therefore the Lord of hosts <HI>breaks</HI> in upon us, with one<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 27. 1.</NOTE> <HI>breach</HI> in the neck of another, with <HI>famine, plague,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">and 9. 21.</NOTE> <HI>sickness,</HI> and <HI>death,</HI> with <HI>intestine war, divisions</HI> and <HI>endless distractions,</HI> till <HI>Ephraim</HI> rise against <HI>Manasseh,</HI> and <HI>Manasseh</HI> against <HI>Ephraim,</HI> and <HI>Judah</HI> against both; to eat as Canibals one anothers flesh, and drink each others blood, and thereby break the <HI>arm</HI> or strength of the <HI>whole Nation;</HI> yea the very bones will be broken, as when one choppeth wood; when the <HI>sinews</HI> are cut in sunder, all <HI>bonds</HI> of <HI>Law</HI> and <HI>Conscience,</HI> of Reason and Reli∣gion, of Justice and Charity, of Unanimity and Unity, are (like <HI>Sampsons</HI> withs) snapped in pei∣ces. All these hurts mens <HI>own ways</HI> procure to<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 4. 18.</NOTE> them, so that God appears either as a <HI>stranger</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">and 30. 14.</NOTE> and <HI>waifering man,</HI> or an enemy, yea as a <HI>cruel one</HI> in his sore <HI>judgements,</HI> which like <HI>waves</HI> of the sea pursue one another.</P>
<P>§. Yet there was some mercy in this <HI>severity</HI> as to<NOTE PLACE="marg">There is good in the evil of punishment out-wards.</NOTE> <HI>Israel</HI> and <HI>Judah</HI> a long time, while God <HI>cut them short only,</HI> but did not utterly forsake them, or cast them out of his sight: it may argue some hope, that a <HI>Physician</HI> yet vouchsafes to mind and visit his <HI>Patient,</HI> to apply any <HI>causticks</HI> or <HI>scarify∣ings,</HI> which by <HI>pain</HI> may bring to <HI>sense,</HI> and so to healing.</P>
<P>But there are (<HI>coeca &amp; surda vulnera</HI>) silent,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The worst hurts are un∣seen and unfelt.</NOTE> and <HI>unseen,</HI> and at present unfelt, yet very sore hurts and deep <HI>wounds</HI> bleeding inwardly, which God may inflict, as upon a particular soul, so up∣on
<PB N="32" REF="21"/>
the <HI>spirit</HI> and <HI>genius</HI> of a <HI>whole Nation,</HI> as to<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hos. 14. 17.</NOTE> the generality of the people, by giving them over, by letting them alone; <HI>why should they be</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 2. 30.</NOTE> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mitten any more, being a rebellious, stif-necked and back-sliding people! profound to revolt, bold Apo∣states,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Hos. 5. 2.</NOTE> falling from their duty to God and man,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 7. 9, 10.</NOTE> yet glorying as if they <HI>were delivered to do all this wickedness,</HI> by the test and approbation of <HI>pro∣vidence,</HI> discovered as they fancy in the prosperity of their impiety for a season.</P>
<P>§. Whereas indeed as St. <HI>Anstin</HI> observes, <HI>Seve∣rissim<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nit Deus, cum poenalis nutritur impunitas;</HI> There need no greater punishment of a <HI>gangrene,</HI> than to <HI>let it alone,</HI> to <HI>leave it to it</HI> self; This (<HI>crude∣lis misericordia,</HI>) severe mercy St. <HI>Bernard</HI> passio∣nately and wisely <HI>deprecates,</HI> (<HI>po<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iws u<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, seca, percute, domine, ne parcas, ut parcas,</HI>) Rather lance (O Lord) and cut and burn, by a merciful cruelty, than so spare me by a cruel clemency, as to spoil and damn me for ever, saith the <HI>devout man.</HI></P>
<P>§. There are <HI>spirituall maladies,</HI> and <HI>miseries too,</HI> which give a people over to <HI>Dementation,</HI> and <HI>asto∣nishment,</HI> to <HI>blindnesse</HI> and <HI>madnesse,</HI> to seek after and trust in <HI>Lying va<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ities</HI> and desperate hypocri∣sies,<NOTE PLACE="marg">D<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut 28. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>4 a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> 64.</NOTE> to rest in the <HI>flatteries</HI> of <HI>successes,</HI> or the <HI>ap∣plauses</HI> of the <HI>vulgar,</HI> who think every one th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ospe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> to be a <HI>God</HI> or a <HI>good Angel;</HI> and every one that is unfortunate to be a <HI>Devil,</HI> or a great offendor, as the <HI>Barbarians</HI> did St. <HI>Paul</HI> when the Viper seised on his hand, and he shaked it off<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts 18. 3.</NOTE> unhurt.</P>
<P>§. Hence any <HI>Idol of superstition,</HI> any <HI>meteor</HI>
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
of <HI>Enthusiasm,</HI> any <HI>glow-worm</HI> of <HI>sanatick fancy</HI> and <HI>Fury</HI> serves the turn, and instead of Gods Candles and Lampes of <HI>pure Religion</HI> in well∣ordered Churches, as golden Candlesticks. God takes away these burning and <HI>shining Lights,</HI> and leaves a people to the <HI>Sparks</HI> they have <HI>kindled,</HI> to be <HI>satisfied with their own delusions,</HI> to <HI>believe</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 50. 11.</NOTE> <HI>Lyes,</HI> to rejoyce and glory in their evil and per∣verse<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 16. 5.</NOTE> wayes; and when God hath taken away his <HI>Peace</HI> and <HI>Truth</HI> from them both in Church and State, they will fall under grievous <HI>violences,</HI> oppressions, and exa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tions of men, whose Mer∣cies are cruel, and their <HI>healings</HI> further hurts, which shall make their very souls <HI>bow down</HI> to the ground, that proud <HI>men</HI> may passe over them;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isai. 51. 2<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> when nothing but Fury and Sedition at home; nothing but <HI>Warre</HI> and <HI>Invasion</HI> from abroad is in reason to be expected; yet then some people will easily <HI>smile</HI> and <HI>fawn</HI> on their <HI>Oppresso<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</HI> they (poor Wretches) being prone to believe (as <HI>Countrey-fellowes</HI> doe the <HI>Mountebancks</HI>) that all is <HI>well</HI> and <HI>whole</HI> which powerfull hands undertake to touch; they will eccho <HI>Peace, Peace</HI> in Church and State, and cry up a <HI>Common-wealth,</HI> when in∣dead it is a <HI>Common <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e,</HI> as to the grand <HI>Interests</HI> of the Nation, i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the best and noblest, yea, in the most of its parts and members, which can never be fully happy, unless they be of one heart and mind, of one Law and Religion as to the main.</P>
<P>§. Which leads me to the <HI>Third Particular,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">3. part. The pretended Healing</NOTE> The <HI>Medela</HI> or <HI>Sanatio;</HI> the seeming and preten∣ded,
<PB N="28" REF="22"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="29" REF="22"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="30" REF="23"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="31" REF="23"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="32" REF="24"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="33" REF="24"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="34" REF="25"/>
yea professed and boasted <HI>Healing</HI> of the Nations <HI>Hurts;</HI> They have healed with saying, <HI>Peace, Peace,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; <HI>repetita, duplicata, firma &amp; certa pax;</HI> nothing but <HI>Peace</HI> enjoyed, and <HI>Peace</HI> to be expected, sayes <HI>Zedekiah</HI> and <HI>Hananiah</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 King. 22. 11 Ier. 28. 15.</NOTE> the false Prophets, who lied in the name of the Lord.</P>
<P>§. We may observe the cunning <HI>of those Empinicks,</HI> those false <HI>Physitians,</HI> who are of no <HI>value;</HI> they use<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 The craft of these Empi¦rick.</NOTE> this sweet welcome word of <HI>Peace</HI> to the peo∣ple, which is a <HI>Catholicon, comprehensive</HI> of all <HI>enjoy∣ments</HI> (for every <HI>want</HI> is a kind of <HI>Waree</HI>) when they cry <HI>peace,</HI> and repeat the <HI>crambe</HI> of <HI>peace, peace,</HI> and sing this song (or <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) over and over again; they hope, (as <HI>Demetrius</HI> and his fellow-craftsmen)<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts 19. 35.</NOTE> by crying <HI>Great is Diana of the Ephesians,</HI> even to a <HI>raving</HI> and <HI>hoarsenesss,</HI> to make the people be∣lieve that the <HI>Image</HI> which came down from hea∣ven, was certainly a <HI>goddesse;</HI> with this <HI>lullaby</HI> of <HI>peace, peace,</HI> do the <HI>Polititians</HI> and <HI>Oppressors</HI> of a Nation seek to quiet the <HI>Trefe</HI> and <HI>Wayward people,</HI> when they cry out of their <HI>Ails</HI> and <HI>Oppressions,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Jud. 17. 13.</NOTE> as poor <HI>Micah</HI> did, when the <HI>churlish Danites</HI> took away his <HI>gods</HI> and his <HI>Priests,</HI> yet was he de∣manded <HI>what he ailed so to cry after them.</HI></P>
<P>§. So the great <HI>Artists of State,</HI> that they may the better set off their skill, make (as Mounte∣banks) l<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rg Haranges, specious and popular ora∣tions, like <HI>Herod,</HI> most <HI>artificial speeches,</HI> mixed with preaching and praying, and sprincklings of Scripture, and Gods cause, as gilded or syrupped
<PB N="35" REF="25"/>
bitter pils, to give the better <HI>gusto;</HI> still conclu∣ding with the <HI>Epiphonema</HI> of <HI>peace, peace;</HI> when be∣hold nothing but <HI>usurpation</HI> and <HI>oppression,</HI> grie∣vous <HI>exactions,</HI> and heavy <HI>loads, bonds,</HI> and <HI>chains</HI> and <HI>prisous</HI> are every where prepared for those that dare <HI>cry,</HI> or <HI>complain,</HI> or call for <HI>remedy; Pes∣sime medicastry impensus ostentant artem:</HI> None make ampler <HI>prefaces</HI> brags and <HI>spreadings</HI> of their <HI>skill,</HI> and <HI>salves</HI> and rare <HI>feats</HI> than the most <HI>arrant Quaks</HI> and <HI>Cheats.</HI></P>
<P>§. These, as the <HI>Magicians</HI> of <HI>Egypt,</HI> some times so enchant poor people, that they believe all to be miraculous, at least innoxious, which comes from the <HI>tongues</HI> and <HI>hands</HI> of those who possess them; as Heathens ascribed all blessings to their Idols; the most <HI>crying Injustice</HI> must be thought the <HI>highest Justice;</HI> the greatest con∣tempt and Curb, the strongest <HI>oppression</HI> and <HI>de∣lusion</HI> of a <HI>Nation,</HI> the wildest and most partial toleration must be voiced for liberties, yea, for <HI>precious Christian Liberty,</HI> purchased with much blood and treasure; the grossest <HI>Anarchles,</HI> and most snarled <HI>misgovernment,</HI> whose <HI>wheels</HI> are oft taken off, and whose weight drivces heavily over the very heads and bellies, Laws and Liberties of the Nation (as that <HI>Romane Virago, Tullia Hosti∣lia</HI> did her chariot over her Fathers corps) to the depression of the honor and freedome of <HI>Princes Peers,</HI> and best of the people, this is voyced <HI>peace, peace;</HI> the most irreligious <HI>licentiousnesse</HI> in <HI>doctrine opinion, speech</HI> and <HI>manners,</HI> must be re∣puted freedom of spirit; the most novel and un∣just
<PB N="36" REF="26"/>
<HI>cause</HI> that ever was on foot, must needs be cry∣ed up for the <HI>Good old Cause;</HI> when 'tis indeed quite contrary to the goodnesse of Equity, and the anti∣quity of truth.</P>
<P>§. Such <HI>monstrous soloecisms</HI> there are in the<NOTE PLACE="marg">The confi∣dence and cruelty of false hearers.</NOTE> world between some mens <HI>words</HI> and <HI>actions,</HI> be∣tween the credulity of cowardly people, and the reallity of their enjoyments: This is the <HI>cunning,</HI> this the <HI>confidence,</HI> and this the <HI>cruelty</HI> of some <HI>State Juglers,</HI> and their <HI>Plebeian Parasites,</HI> to boast of all they do or say, is in order to <HI>peace, peace;</HI> when by <HI>Peace</HI> they mean (as <HI>Salust</HI> expresseth it) nothing but the <HI>servility</HI> or the <HI>solitude</HI> of a Nati∣on, that all interests, sacred, civil and military, may <HI>truckle</HI> under their <HI>high</HI> and <HI>mighty power,</HI> their <HI>tripple crowns; &amp; submissis faucibus deferre imperium:</HI> All that search and try their <HI>wayes,</HI> or<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 29. 21.</NOTE> <HI>wounds</HI> rather, are <HI>offendors,</HI> even for a word, if they dare speak, <HI>whisper,</HI> think or <HI>weep</HI> ought but <HI>peace, peace;</HI> When such <HI>valiant,</HI> such <HI>succes∣full,</HI> such <HI>holy,</HI> such <HI>praying,</HI> such <HI>preaching,</HI> such <HI>Saintly,</HI> such <HI>Seraphick</HI> men, have gotten <HI>power,</HI> and <HI>place,</HI> and <HI>plenty,</HI> and <HI>palaces,</HI> O now all is <HI>peace, peace.</HI></P>
<P>§. And the better to colour over the overthrow of three flourishing Nations (which from the pile of three <HI>united Kingdoms</HI> are fillipped to the cross of an ill <HI>sodered Common-wealth</HI>) some men must by all means pretend to set up (as <HI>John</HI> of <HI>Leyden</HI> and his Complices did) the Kingdom of Righteousness, the <HI>Throne</HI> and <HI>Scepter</HI> of <HI>King Jesus;</HI> Which is justly esteemed a <HI>Kingdom of</HI>
<PB N="37" REF="26"/>
<HI>peace,</HI> being seldom or never advanced by an <HI>active war,</HI> but only by a <HI>passive;</HI> yet is this a principall decoy to impose upon <HI>vulgar people;</HI> for who will not seem willing and forward to submit to Christs Kingdom; that he may rule and reign? But we are not such children, nor have so <HI>learned Christ,</HI> as to expect his <HI>Kingdom to be of this world;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ioh. 18. 16.</NOTE> though in it, yet not after its <HI>methods of the sword,</HI> but by the <HI>word of Truth</HI> and <HI>spirit of Patience;</HI> thus came the King of <HI>Sion;</HI> the other by the sword of blood, is a rare project for <HI>Muncer</HI> and <HI>Knipperdolling,</HI> for <HI>Hacket</HI> and <HI>Arthington,</HI> when they can be merry in <HI>peoples miseries,</HI> with (<HI>po∣pulus vult decipi, decipiatur</HI>) people have a mind to be deluded, and tis fit they should be so, when credulous people will believe in <HI>any spirit,</HI> an hun∣dred to one but some <HI>lying spirits</HI> and <HI>deceivers,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Ioh. 4. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Mat. 24. 23.</NOTE> false Christs, and false Apostles will come among them, who shall make them believe <HI>light</HI> is <HI>dark∣nesse,</HI> and <HI>darknesse light?</HI> that <HI>good is evill</HI> and <HI>evill</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 5. 20. Rev. 3. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>good;</HI> that their <HI>iron Chains</HI> are <HI>Bracelets</HI> of <HI>gold;</HI> that factious Conventicles are purest Churches; that Synagogues of Satan are the truest Jews, or children of <HI>Abraham;</HI> that partiall <HI>Conventions,</HI> and <HI>Senates,</HI> sifted, and purged, affronted and bafled by tumultuary or armed force are <HI>full</HI> and <HI>free Parliaments.</HI></P>
<P>§. Which name and thing of Parliament<NOTE PLACE="marg">The honour of Parlia∣ments when full and free.</NOTE> every sober and understanding <HI>English man</HI> just∣ly <HI>venerates</HI> and highly esteems in their due and only true constitution; so Parliaments are justly honoured, as <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>os &amp; corona gentis,</HI> the cream,
<PB N="38" REF="27"/>
flower and crown of a Nation, the anchor and center (under God) of Laws, Liberties, Lives and honours of all that is dear to us in this <HI>world,</HI> yea, of our Religion too: A Free and full Par∣liament is the very <HI>Pall<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dium pacis publicae,</HI> the best <HI>preserver and restorer</HI> of our <HI>peace,</HI> publick <HI>health,</HI> and all honest <HI>interests;</HI> the most <HI>august</HI> and <HI>honourable Assemblie</HI> in the world (<HI>Quo s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l il∣lustriorem non aspicit,</HI> as Bishop <HI>Andrews</HI> calls it, in his <HI>Tortura Torti, pag.</HI> 291.) the best temper∣ed <HI>constitutions</HI> of <HI>spirits</HI> and <HI>humors,</HI> of <HI>power</HI> and <HI>counsel</HI> in a Nation; the <HI>oracle</HI> of <HI>publick wis∣dom,</HI> the <HI>magazine</HI> of <HI>publick strength,</HI> the <HI>source</HI> and <HI>fountain</HI> of <HI>publick order</HI> and <HI>Authority;</HI> the treasure of our <HI>Riches,</HI> the sanctuary of true <HI>Re∣ligion,</HI> the ark in which the Church of <HI>England</HI> is embarqued; the Conservatory of both <HI>sanctity</HI> and <HI>civility,</HI> the best Umpire of our civill <HI>diffe∣rences,</HI> the most <HI>equanimous Censor</HI> and reformer of manners; the grand <HI>Trustees</HI> of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> when so full and free as becomes men of conscience and honor; Who would not submit their honor, estate, liberty, life, all things temporal to such a Judicature of his Coun∣try-men, such Arbitrators of the publique choise?</P>
<P>§. But to cry <HI>peace, peace;</HI> to the body, when<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 1 5.</NOTE> the whole heart is <HI>faint,</HI> when the whole head is <HI>sick,</HI> when the very <HI>brains are <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaten out,</HI> when the vital and best spirits of a Nation, are almost expired and exhausted, of when the military and pretorian insolence shall stand over the Senate
<PB N="39" REF="27"/>
or Parliament, as <HI>Hercules</HI> with his clud over <HI>Hydra</HI>'s many heads; This Partiality is such a <HI>tyrannous Imposition</HI> on reasonable men, as if they were commanded to believe and declare that a part is equal to, or more than the whole; that <HI>glow-worms</HI> are brighter than the <HI>Stars,</HI> and <HI>Meteors</HI> or <HI>Comets</HI> more benign than the <HI>Sun</HI> and <HI>Moon;</HI> that all the wisdom and piety of a Nation, were contained in a Knapsack, as the holy Ghost was carried in a Cloak bag from <HI>Rome</HI> to <HI>Tre<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t:</HI> Men need but count the pole or tell noses, to tell what a <HI>Free and full Parliament means,</HI> which comprehends all the Representatives and Trustees chosen by the Nation, besides the <HI>Peers,</HI> who were the great coun∣cil to the Prince.</P>
<P>§. Peace, as health, <HI>includes</HI> the good <HI>constitution</HI> of the <HI>whole,</HI> but chiefly of the most noble <HI>principal parts;</HI> peace of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> at home and a∣broad, will be far from that <HI>Nation,</HI> whose pub∣lick counsels are at <HI>variance,</HI> and their chief <HI>Councellors</HI> are either <HI>Fighters</HI> against themselves, or <HI>Oppressors</HI> of <HI>one another,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o serve some <HI>partial</HI> (which must needs be a) <HI>Sinister base and bad inte∣rest;</HI> for no counsel is good, in or out of <HI>Parlia∣ment,</HI> which is not for the <HI>publicks</HI> good, in which every legal and just interest is contained; Indeed its a meer <HI>cheat,</HI> put on the poor <HI>patient</HI> the <HI>daugh∣ter of my people,</HI> when <HI>vain</HI> and empty words of <HI>peace, peace</HI> are used; and yet either the <HI>sword</HI> or the exactor, or the <HI>oppressor</HI> devoureth every way, and every day, when God and man, his <HI>word</HI> and the violated <HI>Laws,</HI> peoples sad <HI>experience,</HI> and tired
<PB N="40" REF="28"/>
patience, their exhausted Estates, and daily A∣larms proclaime, there is no true Peace, no <HI>honest</HI> and <HI>just;</HI> no <HI>safe</HI> and <HI>secure Peace,</HI> which indeed is not to be expected, while such Witch-crafts are imposed, and such wicked purposes partially and violently promoted, utterly to deceive, undo, and destroy a people; which brings me to the fourth particular.</P>
<P>§. Fourthly, The <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Lye</HI> or <HI>Fallacy,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">4. The lye or fallacy of hea∣ling slightly.</NOTE> which the Spirit of God by way of <HI>Irony</HI> expres∣seth, they have healed, thus they pretend and brag: but (<HI>lightly</HI> (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>super leve, ut leviculum, tan∣quam rem ni<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ili,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, LXX. <HI>despicientes, vili∣pedentes: cum illusione,</HI> Syr. <HI>cum ignominia, verbis mendaciorum suorum,</HI> Chald.) Thus <HI>Translators</HI> and <HI>Interpreters</HI> render the word variously, but to the same sence, arguing the little respect of <HI>Piety, Ho∣nesty, Equity</HI> and <HI>Charity,</HI> or <HI>Humanity,</HI> which was in these vain-glorious and ungracious <HI>Healers,</HI> who either wanted <HI>Skill</HI> or <HI>Will,</HI> or <HI>Power,</HI> and <HI>In∣fluence,</HI> or due <HI>Authority,</HI> or they were <HI>slighters▪</HI> and <HI>Contemners</HI> of the publiques <HI>Health,</HI> only intent to their private <HI>Wealth</HI> and advantages.</P>
<P>§. They never searched the bottom of the Na∣tions<NOTE PLACE="marg">The <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ud of su<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h.</NOTE> great crying sins, Disorders and Sufferings, nor applied seasonable, just and <HI>meet Remedies</HI> to either; yea, they <HI>festred</HI> and enflamed the <HI>Lighter hurts,</HI> to <HI>grievous Ulcers,</HI> small <HI>Faults, Offences, mi∣stakes, Differences</HI> and <HI>Jealousies,</HI> which did arise in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> they either dressed these scratches
<PB N="41" REF="28"/>
with <HI>Vinegar</HI> and <HI>gall</HI> only, with <HI>sharp and pic∣quent corrasives,</HI> without any <HI>lenitive</HI> or <HI>moderation;</HI> or else by a <HI>dilatory negligence,</HI> and supercilious carelesness, they let <HI>publick distempers</HI> and <HI>hurts</HI> run on, till they were less capable of any cure, or pa∣tient of good applications; Yea, and by a <HI>super∣fluity</HI> of wanton <HI>cruelty,</HI> they either widened the <HI>wounds,</HI> and made their <HI>probes</HI> their <HI>punniards;</HI> or else dressed them with poysoned spunges, while they seem to purg them, as one that is killed by a glyster or potion. And at best by a most <HI>impu∣dent hypocrisie,</HI> they have skinned over the <HI>hurts,</HI> with some shew of <HI>setling</HI> what <HI>was sha∣ken,</HI> and of reforming what was amiss; when indeed no men did more deform the <HI>beauty,</HI> or <HI>ruine</HI> the welfare and hinder the <HI>healing</HI> of the publique, than these <HI>Healers,</HI> by their enormious sins, and <HI>outra∣gious lusts,</HI> by their <HI>unjust</HI> and <HI>violent</HI> actions, by their <HI>partiality,</HI> and <HI>impotency</HI> of their <HI>passions,</HI> by their <HI>evil eyes,</HI> their <HI>fowle breath,</HI> and their <HI>rough hands;</HI> which are the instruments of <HI>bad hearts,</HI> and <HI>base minds.</HI></P>
<P>§. Little or no publique healing is expectable<NOTE PLACE="marg">Their Cha∣racter.</NOTE> from men that are inordinate <HI>self-lovers, covetous,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Tim. 3. 2, 3.</NOTE> <HI>boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient</HI> to <HI>parents, (natural, civil, ecclesiastical) unthankeful, unholy, without natural affection, truce-breakers, false-ac∣cusers, incontinent; fierce despisers of those that are solidly, sincerely and constantly good, Traytors, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleasures more then of God, ha∣ving a form of godliness, but denying the power of it,</HI> as the Apostle gives their character by an holy <HI>Satyr.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="42" REF="29"/>§. And can any thing, that is good for the<NOTE PLACE="marg">Despair of cure by them.</NOTE> <HI>health</HI> of the <HI>daughter of my people,</HI> proceed from such <HI>Galileans,</HI> such evil men, who meditate mis∣chief night and day, who decree unrighteous de∣crees, and act wickedness with both hands, greedi∣ly? Who think themselves most <HI>hurt,</HI> if the <HI>State</HI> and <HI>Church</HI> should be <HI>throughly</HI> and <HI>speedily healed;</HI> they fancy themselves undone, if any publick good be honestly done; 'tis pain and death to them to have the bones well set, which by them have been broken; to see the (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> rather than the <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) gaping wounds or gulphs ra∣ther closed up, which they have either made or widened, and kept so open, that they threaten in a few years to <HI>swallow up</HI> all the wealth, and <HI>pea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</HI> and honour, and <HI>strength,</HI> and <HI>happinesse</HI> of the <HI>Nation</HI> and <HI>Church.</HI></P>
<P>§. Yet these are the men that say <HI>peace, peace;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Their Mono∣poly of heal∣ing.</NOTE> that would be thought the only <HI>blessed Peace∣makers,</HI> the <HI>soveraign healers</HI> of the hurts of the <HI>daughter of my people;</HI> such <HI>Monopolisers</HI> of all Medicines and healing Drugs, that they are im∣patient any others should take the <HI>cure</HI> in <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and, or have any thing to do in <HI>Church</HI> or <HI>State,</HI> be∣side themselves and their Applauders. They tell the poor Patient which is <HI>full of wounds</HI> and <HI>pu∣tre<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ied sores,</HI> that they will do her more good with their <HI>tongues</HI> and <HI>lips,</HI> added to their <HI>Laun∣cets</HI> and <HI>Swords,</HI> than the <HI>best Physicians</HI> can do by their best <HI>unguents</HI> and soveraign <HI>balsoms;</HI> while the poor sick, wounded and languishing Creature cries out for some ease, and pity; yea
<PB N="43" REF="29"/>
<HI>roars for the very disquietnesse of its soul,</HI> and con∣tinued<NOTE PLACE="marg">Jer. 8. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</NOTE> pains; yet without any shame or blush∣ing, these <HI>Physicians</HI> of no value, these miserable <HI>Mountebanks,</HI> affecting a supercilious shew of so∣veraign Majesty, severely <HI>frown</HI> on the <HI>pitifull looks</HI> and tears of the <HI>daughter of my people;</HI> with <HI>terror threatning her</HI> to hold her peace, to believe she <HI>hath peace,</HI> nay to <HI>say and swear</HI> it is <HI>peace, peace;</HI> yea and to <HI>abjure</HI> the use of any <HI>other men</HI> or <HI>better means,</HI> which have been for∣merly very <HI>effectual for her healing</HI> and <HI>reco∣very.</HI></P>
<P>§. <HI>Quis Coelum terrae non misceat &amp; mare</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Impo. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> pro¦voke to just impatience.</NOTE> <HI>c<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lo▪</HI> Here Patience it self is a sin, and Im∣patience a vertue: Who, not stupid, can for∣bear<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 1. 2.</NOTE> with the Prophet to cry out, <HI>Hear O hea∣ven, and give ear O earth?</HI> Was ever any Na∣tion so tampered with, so pestered by a company of <HI>fallacious Physicians; pretenders to heal, su∣perficial skinners, dilatory Empiricks,</HI> and <HI>misera∣ble Medicasters</HI> who resolve <HI>small hurts</HI> into <HI>grie∣vous Ulcers;</HI> and <HI>green wounds</HI> into <HI>virulent gan∣greens,</HI> and <HI>little braises</HI> into fell and <HI>inflamed tu∣mors,</HI> yet cry <HI>peace, peace;</HI> and we <HI>have healed</HI> you; why do you yet complain?</P>
<P>§. As if the Prophet should say, it is high time (indeed) after so many years of wasting and wounding, of <HI>war</HI> and <HI>trouble,</HI> of <HI>death</HI> and <HI>blood∣shed,</HI> of <HI>undoing</HI> and <HI>destroying,</HI> of <HI>cutting</HI> and <HI>dividing</HI> the <HI>Body Politique,</HI> turning the <HI>daughter of my people</HI> (as on the Gridiron) from one side to the other, by <HI>vicissitudes</HI> of <HI>burning Fea∣vers,</HI>
<PB N="44" REF="30"/>
by continual <HI>tossings,</HI> and fits of high <HI>diste<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣pers</HI> (between the wrath of God and heavy hand upon her, beside the fury of men against her) yet to cry <HI>peace, peace to her; when, as the Lord lives, there is no peace;</HI> nor many steps between the pa∣tient and death; or at best such a sorry peace as is no less chargeable, <HI>terrible</HI> and <HI>oppressive,</HI> than an open <HI>war; Pax omni bello tristior,</HI> a peace patched up with popular pretentions, and impi∣ous injuries; as the body of <HI>Lazars;</HI> whose <HI>plaisters</HI> rather <HI>hide</HI> than <HI>heal</HI> their sores: What true peace can that be which is founded one∣ly on sands and quagmires, on violence and ex∣action, daubed over with the untempered mo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣tar of policy and hypocrisie, which holds not one winter; built up <HI>with cries,</HI> begun with <HI>vio∣lence,</HI> carryed on with <HI>oppression,</HI> and ending in <HI>desolation?</HI></P>
<P>§. <HI>Peace,</HI> or <HI>health,</HI> and <HI>salvation</HI> are far from<NOTE PLACE="marg">Character of true healers.</NOTE> the ungodly; What peace can there be to the <HI>wicked</HI> Princes or People, Senators or Souldiers,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 119. 155. Isa. 57. 22.</NOTE> <HI>whose feet are swift to shed innocent bloud?</HI> whose hands are <HI>full of bribes,</HI> whose hearts are <HI>hollow</HI> and <HI>double minded,</HI> whose power is <HI>usurped,</HI> whose decrees are <HI>unrighteous,</HI> whose mouths are <HI>full of</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 32. 17.</NOTE> <HI>fraud</HI> and <HI>flattery? Peace</HI> and <HI>Establishment</HI> in <HI>Church and State</HI> with God and Men, are the fruits of <HI>Justice</HI> and <HI>Righteousness,</HI> of <HI>true Religion</HI> and <HI>good Laws,</HI> of <HI>just Magistracy</HI> and <HI>legal Sove∣raignty,</HI> of <HI>fixed, free</HI> and <HI>united Councils,</HI> of <HI>wise and honest Valour,</HI> the study, prayer and en∣deavour of men <HI>fearing God</HI> and <HI>hating covetous∣ness,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 18. 21.</NOTE>
<PB N="45" REF="30"/>
men of <HI>true publique Spirits,</HI> who are not swayed by private interests and passions to any no∣vel designs and factious <HI>adherencies.</HI></P>
<P>§. Men of wisdome and honor fortified with just Authority, are only apt to make a Nation happy by healing her, in those ways of honest decrees and impartial dealing, which are legal and regular, not fanatick and extravagant, which every night dream, and in the morning propose <HI>new receits, Seraphick projects,</HI> and <HI>untryed medi∣caments,</HI> which sufficiently shew, that such <HI>Chy∣rurgeons</HI> and <HI>Physitians,</HI> are either ignorant or <HI>pragmatick</HI> or <HI>impertinent;</HI> either not <HI>knowing</HI> what to <HI>do,</HI> or not <HI>willing</HI> to do what they <HI>know,</HI> but are resolved to do any thing, never so foolish and pernicious, rather than sit still and do nothing, or give way to better heads and hands, who have more authority from God and man, and so may better expect a blessing.</P>
<P>§. What <HI>peace</HI> can there be or true healing, while the most crying sins that mankind are ca∣pable to commit or conceive, the deepest <HI>wounds</HI> and sorest <HI>hurts</HI> from the hand of man that a Na∣tion can receive are unpunished and unrepented; yea unconsidered, yea <HI>incouraged,</HI> yea cryed up by some for rare <HI>examples of Justice,</HI> of <HI>Liberty,</HI> of <HI>Piety,</HI> of <HI>Sanctity?</HI> when neither the holy God ever commanded, or holy men ever practised any such thing?</P>
<P>§. What <HI>peace</HI> can there be while fleshly lusts, and all manner of evil concupiscence in Rulers and ruled, fight against mens own souls, against
<PB N="42" REF="31"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="43" REF="31"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="44" REF="32"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="45" REF="32"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="46" REF="33"/>
Gods Spirit, and against the publique welfare? while <HI>worldly lusts</HI> of pride, <HI>envy, covetousness, am∣bition</HI> and <HI>Sacriledge</HI> daily supply matter for ge∣neral<NOTE PLACE="marg">James 4. 1</NOTE> discontents, publique <HI>wars,</HI> and perpetual <HI>woes?</HI></P>
<P>§. What <HI>peace</HI> or <HI>healing</HI> can there be in Church and State, while men of the same polity are like Pikes in a pond, or fish in the sea, or <HI>beasts</HI> of prey in a <HI>wilderness,</HI> pursuing and devouring one another? while neither the bonds of the same <HI>Laws,</HI> nor the same Oathes, nor the same Cove∣nants, nor the same Religion can hold them? while they will not indure the same Magistrates, nor the same Ministers, nor the same form of Church and State? while they have so little equi∣ty, so no piety or charity to each other? while every petty person among the Prophets and peo∣ple aims to set up a party of faction, and every par∣ty designs to subdue others, to set up it self, and to oppress the common liberty and publick wel∣fare, which are only contained in those <HI>Laws,</HI> that are made by the consent of all Estates in the Na∣tion.</P>
<P>§. What peace can there be where there are so many <HI>tumults</HI> and <HI>strifes,</HI> so many <HI>whispers</HI> and <HI>jealousies;</HI> so many <HI>fewds</HI> and <HI>animosities</HI> in the brest and <HI>bowels</HI> of the <HI>same Nation?</HI> for want of that rare <HI>Elixir</HI> of <HI>lawful</HI> and just <HI>government</HI> which only is able to compose the distracted spi∣rits, to give a just allay and temperament to all <HI>hu∣mors</HI> and parts in their due places and proporti∣ons, except they be such as are indigestable to any
<PB N="47" REF="33"/>
good order, and are better purged out, than kept in the body?</P>
<P>§. Alas these pitiful <HI>partial applications,</HI> these <HI>diurnal doses,</HI> these <HI>borary medicaments,</HI> these <HI>slight</HI> and <HI>superficial plaisters;</HI> these <HI>verbal</HI> and <HI>decretal healings</HI> which some men have so gloried in, and vapoured of, are as <HI>ridiculous</HI> as they have been <HI>inefficacious;</HI> unless these <HI>great Masters</HI> of their <HI>new arts;</HI> these <HI>Galens</HI> and <HI>Hypocrates</HI> of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State</HI> were so in favour with some <HI>Esculapius,</HI> as to partake of his <HI>Diety;</HI> and so by the <HI>words of their mouths,</HI> or <HI>shadows of their bodies,</HI> or <HI>touch of their garments,</HI> to rebuke the <HI>Feavers</HI> of the <HI>body politick,</HI> and immediately to cure, as by <HI>miracle,</HI> what they have so long tampered about to very ill purpose.</P>
<P>§. But as an illfavored <HI>Physitian</HI> is an ill <HI>omen</HI> to his patient, especially if he look ill from his be∣ing ill; therebeing no great hope that the <HI>Phy∣sitian</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 4. 23.</NOTE> should cure others, who doth not, or cannot cure himself; so the busie <HI>Practitioners</HI> on the <HI>Daughter of their people,</HI> should do well, first to commend their skill to the <HI>publique,</HI> by giving some good <HI>experiments</HI> on their selves, by curing their own corrupt hearts, or crazy heads; by recovering themselves from those <HI>vertigo's, me∣grims,</HI> and falling <HI>sicknesses,</HI> with which they have been so oft afflicted; let them wash their own <HI>foul hands,</HI> and cleanse <HI>their double minds,</HI> let<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 1. 16, 17.</NOTE> them cease to do <HI>evil,</HI> and learn to do good;<NOTE PLACE="marg">James 4. 8.</NOTE> Let them do all things not arbitrary (<HI>ad libitum, &amp; libidi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI>) but as exact Physitians and Apothecaries
<PB N="48" REF="34"/>
<HI>per pondus &amp; mensuram,</HI> by weight and measure; by the <HI>rule</HI> and <HI>standard</HI> of the Laws of <HI>God</HI> and <HI>man;</HI> which give, or restore, or preserve to every one what is their own, by such purchase, donation, descent and honest industry; wherein their rights are made good by Law; and which they have no way forfeited by any injury to the publique, of which the <HI>Laws</HI> of the Land and <HI>lawfull Magi∣strates,</HI> are the only lawful Judges.</P>
<P>§. Let them not think by a little <HI>Fasting-spittle</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 58. 6, 7, 8.</NOTE> to cure the hurts of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> nor yet by their <HI>solemne feasts;</HI> This is the <HI>fast,</HI> and this the <HI>feast,</HI> the Lord hath chosen, comely for true reli∣gion, and wholsome for the Nation, <HI>To loose the bands of wickedness, to undo heavy burthens, to break every yoak of unrighteous decrees</HI> and acts; to <HI>restore</HI> what is unjustly, that is without law, ta∣ken away from <HI>any man,</HI> to do as they would be done unto, to <HI>deal justly to all men,</HI> to shew<NOTE PLACE="marg">Micah 6. 8.</NOTE> <HI>mercy,</HI> even in deserved Justice; and (after all) to <HI>walk humbly with God,</HI> This do, (O ye Phy∣sitians of my people) and you shall live; This do, and the <HI>daughter of my people shall live; being through∣ly</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Zach. 13. 6.</NOTE> <HI>healed of the wounds she hath received in the house of her seeming friends;</HI> (For it was <HI>not an open Enemy</HI> of the heathens round about, which hath done her <HI>all this hurt:</HI> But her own Children,)<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 1. 23.</NOTE> Let them cease from being <HI>Rebellious</HI> Children, companions of Adulterers, Robbers, and Mur∣therers, return to that duty, they owe to their God and their civil Parents, to their <HI>Country,</HI> and their <HI>Church,</HI> or to that pity and compassion,
<PB N="49" REF="34"/>
they owe to their <HI>Children</HI> and <HI>Posterity,</HI> whose teeth will certainly be set on edge by the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ower grapes their Fathers have eaten, <HI>Jer.</HI> 31. 29. Then shall <HI>health spring forth speedily, righteousness shall go</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 58. 8.</NOTE> <HI>before, and the glory of the Lord be thy rearward.</HI> Then shall they be as Fathers and Sons too, of the Nation; who shall <HI>build the old wast places,</HI> repair the <HI>breaches,</HI> and raise <HI>up the foundations</HI> of <HI>many</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezek. 21. 27.</NOTE> <HI>generations,</HI> which have been <HI>overthrown, over∣thrown, overthrown,</HI> after they had continued firm for many Ages, as to the <HI>stability of Church and State,</HI> under Gods indulgence and the care of good Magistrates.</P>
<P>§. But since these <HI>Tamperers</HI> are so justly and<NOTE PLACE="marg">Particular in∣stances of slight healing.</NOTE> severely reproached by <HI>God</HI> and the <HI>Prophet,</HI> for their <HI>slight healing,</HI> which was indeed none at all; the more <HI>cruel,</HI> by how much they were more <HI>cunning,</HI> to <HI>keep the daughter of my people in continual pain,</HI> and themselves in <HI>constant practice</HI> and <HI>pay;</HI> It will not be amiss <HI>more particularly</HI> to ex∣amine in the sence of Gods Spirit and his Prophet, whence this malice or mistake had its rise; how this <HI>slight healing</HI> did befall the daughter of his people; and how it is to be avoided as much as Death, and Hell, and Devil.</P>
<P>First, it comes by unskilfull <HI>Empiricks,</HI> such as<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. By unskil∣full underta∣kers to heal.</NOTE> neither understand the Science of <HI>Physick,</HI> nor the Art of <HI>Chirurgery;</HI> neither the <HI>cause,</HI> nor the <HI>symptoms,</HI> nor the proper and specifick <HI>medicines</HI> for such hurts and diseases as Church and State may <HI>labour under;</HI> which possibly may be as many as the natural bodies of men are subject to; if a
<PB N="50" REF="35"/>
man had a true <HI>Anatomy</HI> of the parts and <HI>consti∣tution,</HI> with all accidentall distempers incident to the body Politick, from within or without: When men of little or no <HI>literature,</HI> of as little <HI>experience</HI> in <HI>matters</HI> of <HI>policy</HI> and <HI>prudence,</HI> of <HI>mean capacity</HI> and <HI>education,</HI> of <HI>small minds</HI> and <HI>narrow souls,</HI> do undertake the cure, who are easily <HI>deluded</HI> and <HI>gulled,</HI> byassed and swerved with <HI>fair words,</HI> spe∣cious pretenses, and partial, yea <HI>pivate interests;</HI> (especially if these novel interests have any <HI>smack</HI> or <HI>tincture, fucus</HI> or <HI>form</HI> of more than <HI>ordinary god∣liness</HI>)<NOTE PLACE="marg">4 Tim. 3. 5.</NOTE> when these <HI>easie, shallow</HI> and <HI>inconsultive men,</HI> of <HI>giddy heads</HI> and <HI>rash hands,</HI> full of childish <HI>credulity,</HI> and popular <HI>formalty,</HI> come to the <HI>helm of Church and State,</HI> to rule and <HI>steer</HI> all, they look more to the spreading of their <HI>sails,</HI> then to that due <HI>balast and lading,</HI> or to that right <HI>cynosure and com∣pass of Law</HI> and <HI>Justice which God</HI> and their Coun∣trey have prescribed.</P>
<P>§. <HI>Gonsalvo,</HI> whom <HI>Guicciardine</HI> calls the <HI>great Captain of his time,</HI> was wont to say, that a Ge∣neral, or chief commander of an Army, had need have <HI>thirty years</HI> experience, to breed him <HI>accomplished</HI> to all the abilities, requisite to such a place; on whose prudent conduct the lives of so many men depend; Yea, and whole Nati∣ons too; truly no less time is needfull to train up a <HI>compleat Counsellor</HI> of <HI>State,</HI> a meet <HI>Phy∣sician</HI> for the <HI>daughter of my people;</HI> It is not a pragmatique <HI>forwardnesse,</HI> a <HI>bustling activity,</HI> or a <HI>projecting impudence,</HI> or an <HI>unblushing igno∣rance,</HI> or a <HI>voluble impertinence</HI> of tongue, or a
<PB N="51" REF="35"/>
<HI>military strength</HI> of hand, and <HI>Robustnesse</HI> of body, which makes men fit to undertake the <HI>healing of a Nation;</HI> every Fool and evil doer, is capable to be <HI>medling,</HI> and to do <HI>mischief,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 20. 3.</NOTE> onely the work of closing and healing, is ex∣pectable from <HI>wise</HI> and good <HI>men,</HI> of ingenuous and learned educations, and of exemplary lives; and adorned with competent estates, men who know how to temper their <HI>Physick</HI> and <HI>Plaisters,</HI> so as are commensurate to the <HI>nature</HI> and <HI>degree of the disease,</HI> to the spirits and <HI>strength of the Patient,</HI> neither <HI>over-doing</HI> by <HI>precipitancy,</HI> nor <HI>under-doing</HI> by <HI>presumption;</HI> neither fearfull to use tried and fit <HI>medicines,</HI> nor rash to tamper with every <HI>new receipt</HI> propounded.</P>
<P>2. By <HI>unfaithfull Empiricks,</HI> such as are crafty<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. By unfaith¦full.</NOTE> enough to do <HI>evil, but to do good they have no</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 5. 13.</NOTE> <HI>knowledge</HI> or honesty; they have <HI>heads able</HI> e∣nough, and <HI>hands active</HI> enough, but they have <HI>corrupt hearts</HI> and <HI>base ends;</HI> they can boast, as<NOTE PLACE="marg">Jer. 42. 22.</NOTE> much as any of a <HI>publick spirit,</HI> and the <HI>common∣weal,</HI> or <HI>bonum publicum;</HI> but while they look one way, they <HI>row</HI> another; the <HI>tide</HI> of <HI>private bene∣nefit</HI> secretly carries them contray to the sail and winde, with which they <HI>clamor</HI> amain for the <HI>publick good;</HI> full of <HI>pretended necessities,</HI> and impatience for an <HI>hudling</HI> and <HI>preposterous Reformation</HI> in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State;</HI> and the <HI>work is well done,</HI> if their <HI>crasie estates,</HI> and <HI>waining Fortunes,</HI> or <HI>crackt credits</HI> be once <HI>well recruited;</HI> if they find no <HI>gain in true godlinesse,</HI> yet they make good <HI>gains of the form of it,</HI> having the <HI>Cre∣tian</HI>
<PB N="52" REF="36"/>
faculty to <HI>speak lies in hypocrisie for filthy</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Tit. 1. 11.</NOTE> <HI>lucre sake;</HI> every one looks to the profit which is to be <HI>made from their quarters;</HI> if their Purse<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 56. 11.</NOTE> prosper, all is <HI>peace</HI> and <HI>prosperity;</HI> though all things publick are <HI>worse and worse,</HI> as to <HI>Religion, Laws, Liberties,</HI> as to freedome and honour of <HI>publick Councels,</HI> as to trade and commerce, as to peace and concord in Church and State; they care not how snarled the skain of things be, so as they can draw some good threads out of it to stitch up their affairs, and mend their <HI>rents.</HI></P>
<P>§. Though the <HI>daughter of their people</HI> have scarce <HI>rags</HI> to hide her <HI>sores</HI> of sin and shame, to dry up her tears or dress her <HI>wounds</HI> by reason of oppression and anguish; yet these <HI>grand Ge∣niusses</HI> of <HI>State</HI> (whose gracious nods are <HI>sana∣tive,</HI> and their <HI>touch</HI> or <HI>presence</HI> must be thought <HI>soveraign</HI>) must be cloathed in <HI>scarlet</HI> and <HI>fine¦linnen;</HI> in robes of silk and embroidery, and fare deliciously every day; that they may appear ra∣ther as <HI>Princes</HI> in splendor and <HI>majesty,</HI> than as <HI>Mountebanks</HI> and <HI>Quacks;</HI> who care not how little they <HI>heal</HI> their <HI>Patients,</HI> nor how much they help their own <HI>purses;</HI> yea some of them are so false that they conspire the total subversion and de∣struction of all the health and wealth of the <HI>daugh∣ter of their people,</HI> which sate as a Queen among the Nations in former ages; that they may either <HI>keep</HI> or <HI>increase</HI> the spoyls they have already got, and further hope for, from her final expiration and dissolutions; where from an ancient, united and flourishing <HI>Kingdom,</HI> to a puny, peeled and
<PB N="53" REF="36"/>
divided <HI>Commonwealth,</HI> the change is not like to be<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 15.</NOTE> (as that of our vile bodies at the <HI>resurrection</HI>) from <HI>dishonour</HI> to <HI>honour,</HI> from <HI>corruption to incorruption;</HI> but from <HI>peace, glory, plenty</HI> and <HI>Renown, to e∣verlasting war, dishonour, beggery</HI> and <HI>cont<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mely;</HI> the <HI>fruit</HI> and <HI>fate</HI> attending the silly or subtile tamperings of false more then foolish Physicians, who are neither good for others bodies, nor for their own souls; for while they <HI>through ambition, covetuousness</HI> and <HI>unfaithfulness</HI> neglect to heal the one, they damnably hurt the other. Certainly no want of honesty or charity is more damning than that which is due to the publick, but denyed or withdrawn, when it is in the <HI>power of our hand to do a Nation</HI> or <HI>a Church good:</HI> Nor are any <HI>Trai∣tors</HI> more <HI>dangerous</HI> and <HI>detestable,</HI> than those<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Lopes</HI> was Phi∣sitian to Q. <HI>E∣lizabeth</HI> and suborned to poi∣son her. <HI>Cambden.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Lopesses,</HI> who are rather <HI>carnifices</HI> than <HI>medici; empoysoners, torinentors,</HI> and <HI>executioners,</HI> more than <HI>healers</HI> or <HI>Physitians;</HI> then most <HI>betraying</HI> their <HI>trust,</HI> when most <HI>trusted,</HI> for the publique <HI>wel∣fare</HI> of a Church and nation, on which not only many thousand bodies but souls do depend.</P>
<P>3. When the <HI>pretending healers</HI> are either tain∣ted<NOTE PLACE="marg">When trans∣ported with passion and o∣pinion.</NOTE> with the contagion, and <HI>leavened</HI> with the <HI>sowreness</HI> of other mens odd opinions and <HI>passions,</HI> or transported with their own; sometimes Phy∣sicians are such <HI>Gentle Sirs,</HI> that they symbolize too much with the <HI>humors</HI> of their <HI>Patients,</HI> and are so indulgent to their diseases, or <HI>compliant</HI> with their <HI>ulcers,</HI> that they dare not tell the people their real dangers, and the <HI>tendency</HI> of their un∣reasonable <HI>distempers,</HI> if not <HI>prevented</HI> and <HI>mode∣rated;</HI>
<PB N="54" REF="37"/>
sometimes <HI>people</HI> love to have such <HI>Phy∣sicians,</HI> such <HI>Magistrates,</HI> such <HI>Parliament-men,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Jer. 3. 31.</NOTE> and such <HI>Preachers</HI> too, who shall speak soft and <HI>smooth things, sow pillows under their broken bones,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 3. 9.</NOTE> and bind up the <HI>unsearched sores with silken bands;</HI> This is the way (<HI>non sanare sed palpare morbos &amp; vulnera; &amp; ipsa remedia in morbos vertere</HI>) not to <HI>heal</HI> but to <HI>humor an hurt;</HI> not to mend it to the <HI>better,</HI> but to change it to <HI>worse;</HI> for an <HI>im∣patient Patient</HI> many times needs a plaister of <HI>moral Philosophy,</HI> and <HI>Divinity,</HI> more then of <HI>Phy∣sick</HI> or <HI>Chirurgery,</HI> and stands more in need to have his <HI>passion</HI> than his <HI>sore</HI> cured; which (as in bodies full of <HI>sharp humors</HI>) is worse by their <HI>fret∣ting</HI> than by the <HI>first wounding.</HI></P>
<P>§. Hence <HI>Patients</HI> and <HI>Physitians,</HI> like <HI>Ideots</HI> and <HI>Simpletons</HI> very gravely conspire to lay aside all use of <HI>what things</HI> are known to be good in or∣der to health? out of a great zeal against the <HI>abuses</HI> some have formerly made of them, and a like jea∣lousie for hereafter.</P>
<P>§. Thus they transfer by an (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) <HI>impati∣ence</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">The <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> or transport.</NOTE> <HI>of prejudice, and transport</HI> of their <HI>own</HI> or <HI>others passions,</HI> the <HI>faults</HI> and <HI>frailties</HI> of <HI>persons</HI> to <HI>things,</HI> condemning with the <HI>Turks</HI> all <HI>wine,</HI> because some men are <HI>drunk with its excess;</HI> and all good <HI>chear,</HI> because some are apt to <HI>surfeit,</HI> blaming the meat, when the fault is in their ill stomach or digestion; hence they study so to dry up <HI>Hydro∣pick bodies,</HI> till they kindle in them <HI>calentures,</HI> and make them as tindar, apt <HI>fewel</HI> for a <HI>Feaver;</HI> they draw <HI>away</HI> so much <HI>blood</HI> pretending it is <HI>bad,</HI>
<PB N="55" REF="37"/>
till the <HI>Patient (Church</HI> and <HI>State)</HI> loseth, withal, much <HI>of its best blood</HI> and <HI>purest spirits;</HI> so falling at last into fits of <HI>convulsion,</HI> and such <HI>emaciatings</HI> as betray to desperate consumptions: Thus they are prone totally to abandon a good, an excel∣lent, a long tried, yea and the only adequate <HI>way</HI> of <HI>Government,</HI> that can be adapted to all just <HI>in∣terests</HI> in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> out of a popular <HI>preju∣dice,</HI> against some <HI>misgovernments</HI> incident to the Governors, and to the best Governments; <HI>which are sooner remedied,</HI> then a <HI>new one modelled</HI> and fitted; as a crackt <HI>silver vessell,</HI> is sooner <HI>sodered</HI> and <HI>new burnished,</HI> then a <HI>new one malleated</HI> out of the <HI>rough m<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss</HI> or <HI>wedge</HI> of <HI>metal.</HI></P>
<P>§. Thus (<HI>Dum vitant stulti vitia in contraria currunt</HI>) for want of wise, honest and steady <HI>Phy∣sicians</HI>) <HI>remedies</HI> over-driven prove <HI>worse</HI> than the <HI>diseases;</HI> and a <HI>Nation</HI> is further off from cure after <HI>twenty years</HI> passionate practice, than it was at the first cause of complaint.</P>
<P>§. This fals out, when <HI>Physicians,</HI> grow so <HI>sympathysing,</HI> or <HI>symbolising,</HI> with their <HI>petients pevish passions</HI> and humors, that they flatter their diseases, and fear nothing so much, as to <HI>cure them,</HI> with that discreet <HI>severity</HI> and <HI>moderati∣on</HI> which permits not the <HI>outcry▪</HI> (when great∣er, than the grief) nor the importune <HI>clamor of the patient,</HI> either to keep him <HI>short,</HI> or carry him beyond the reality of the <HI>disease;</HI> Since <HI>health</HI> of the body, as vertue which is the health <HI>of the mind,</HI> consists (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) in the <HI>mean</HI> between <HI>extreames.</HI> Tis too
<PB N="56" REF="38"/>
true, as in Patients, and Physicians, so in people, and Parliaments <HI>(perit judicium, quum res transit in effectum)</HI> when Physicians so much mind their patients <HI>distemper</HI> and <HI>clamor,</HI> that their minds contract a disease that sets them next dore to a kind of <HI>raving</HI> or <HI>madness,</HI> or <HI>dotage,</HI> of which all men are thought in some <HI>degree guilty,</HI> who either much over-do or underdo, what they <HI>undertake to do;</HI> as he that <HI>broke</HI> the pitcher which he was to <HI>wash;</HI> and <HI>burnt</HI> or pulled <HI>down</HI> that house, which he had commission only to <HI>sweep</HI> or <HI>repair;</HI> and cut off that head for <HI>aking,</HI> which was only to be <HI>shaved,</HI> and forrified with some <HI>defensive plaister,</HI> against the rheume; To these transports of some men, who were much swayed by the passionate outcries of some people, we owe the loss of our antient Government, and have run the sad ventures, yea shipwracks, of <HI>Anarchy</HI> so long in both <HI>Church and State.</HI></P>
<P>4. When these <HI>pretended healers</HI> look more<NOTE PLACE="marg">4. When they too much in∣tend petty sym∣ptomes, and neglect the main distem∣pers.</NOTE> at the lesser <HI>symptoms of the diseases,</HI> or at the <HI>putid excrescencies of the sore,</HI> than at the <HI>ro<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</HI> and <HI>fountaine</HI> of the <HI>malady;</HI> when they re∣gard more the <HI>sufferings of a Nation,</HI> then their own or other mens gross sins, and are more sensible of mans prejudices and <HI>displeasures,</HI> than Gods.</P>
<P>It is a rule in <HI>Physick,</HI> (In <HI>complicatis morbis acutiori attendendum</HI>) In <HI>complicated</HI> diseases the maine care must be to give check to that, which is most accute, malignant and predatori∣ous of the <HI>spirits;</HI> for if these <HI>faile,</HI> or be not <HI>refocillated,</HI> both <HI>nature</HI> and <HI>art,</HI> (as <HI>Hippocrates</HI>
<PB N="57" REF="38"/>
says) must needs fail; they are then very <HI>im∣pertinent Physitians,</HI> who seeing a <HI>Patient</HI> in an high <HI>feavour,</HI> are more <HI>solicitous</HI> to take away some <HI>cloths</HI> or <HI>covering,</HI> which seems too hot on them, then to <HI>mitigate</HI> the <HI>flames</HI> of that fevo∣rish <HI>furnace</HI> which <HI>boyles within them.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> Here, by grosse mistakes, some <HI>Physitians</HI> take (<HI>non causam pro cause;</HI>) angry at some <HI>Ceremo∣nies,</HI> and scared with meer <HI>shadows,</HI> more than with grosse sins, that are most <HI>immoral</HI> and <HI>sub∣stantially</HI> evil (as I may say:) This <HI>runs</HI> even <HI>Re∣formation</HI> it selfe many times to a <HI>Deformity,</HI> while <HI>Physitians</HI> look so much to some <HI>appearances</HI> of <HI>evil,</HI> that they neglect what is most <HI>apparent evil.</HI> Thus men quarelled (in their little <HI>cavils,</HI> at<NOTE PLACE="marg">The slight healing by ta∣king away the Liturgy.</NOTE> the <HI>Liturgy</HI>) so <HI>much about some</HI> things they lesse fancyed, or <HI>understood,</HI> as to the Antiquity, and Innocency of their <HI>sence</HI> and <HI>use,</HI> that they never <HI>regarded</HI> either the <HI>excellent matter</HI> and <HI>forme</HI> of the <HI>Prayers</HI> and <HI>Administrations</HI> in it, or their own dull, <HI>cold,</HI> and formal application to them, when indeed they deserved for their Divine Truth to be believed, and for their <HI>pub∣lique</HI> use and <HI>charity</HI> to be <HI>entertained</HI> with hum∣ble, intentive, fervent and devout affections; the fault was not in the holy formes, but the unholy formality; Nor (lastly) did they <HI>bethink them∣selves</HI> of the great want which <HI>plainer people have</HI> of such <HI>wholesome, compleat, wonted formes</HI> of <HI>Publique Prayers,</HI> and administrations, which they can best <HI>learn</HI> and <HI>understand,</HI> and <HI>intend;</HI> For daily <HI>variety</HI> in Religion, (such as some
<PB N="58" REF="39"/>
men affect) is almost as <HI>inedifying</HI> to poor <HI>countrey people</HI> as <HI>Latin service;</HI> nor is any <HI>Sym∣bol of Christian union</HI> more <HI>proper</HI> in any Church (and if it could be in all the Churches,) then to have where ever they come, the same Summary <HI>sence</HI> and <HI>solemnity</HI> of holy mysteries; and such duties are ill left to all private mens fancys, yea or to all <HI>Ministers</HI> suddain and <HI>extemparary abilities,</HI> though they be able men.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> If lying and swearing, and riot, and luxury,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Grand neg∣lects, and pet∣ty severity.</NOTE> if <HI>Schisme</HI> and <HI>perjury,</HI> and <HI>sacriledge,</HI> and <HI>Hy∣pocrisie,</HI> and <HI>bloodguiltinesse,</HI> if <HI>covetousnesse</HI> and <HI>ambition,</HI> and <HI>immoderate revenge,</HI> if <HI>discontent</HI> and impatience against God and Superiours, if malice and high uncharitableness, if bribery and corruption, if popularity, <HI>formality, idlenesse,</HI> and <HI>debauchery</HI> in Ministers, if peoples immora∣lities, and prophanesse, factiousnesse, <HI>Atheistical indifferency,</HI> and rude insolencies; if these and the like great hurts <HI>of the daughter of my people</HI> had been <HI>cordially</HI> reformed, and by <HI>reinforced</HI> Lawes with due execution of both <HI>Civil</HI> and <HI>Ecclesiastical discipline</HI> had been so purged out, or curbed and abated that the <HI>flagrancy</HI> and <HI>predominancy</HI> of them had been generally <HI>allayed;</HI> doubtlesse the <HI>publique welfare</HI> might have con∣sisted with those <HI>other things</HI> of convenient and comely use, in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> at which some mens zeal did so rise and over-boyle, that it almost <HI>quenched</HI> all Religion and Civility to <HI>sor∣did confusions.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="59" REF="39"/><HI>Sect.</HI> 5. When these <HI>pretended healers,</HI> do either by immoderate tampering and <HI>dilatoriness,</HI> mul∣tiply<NOTE PLACE="marg">5. By immode∣rate and dila∣tory tamper∣ings.</NOTE> diseases, or by stopping one <HI>orifice</HI> indiscreet∣ly make a <HI>score,</HI> or force ill Humors to shift their seat, and transfer Diseases (alike the <HI>running gout</HI>) from <HI>one part to another,</HI> from the <HI>head</HI> to the <HI>hands,</HI> thence to the <HI>feet,</HI> and at last to the <HI>heart;</HI> still the <HI>inward malady</HI> remains <HI>unpurged,</HI> the daugh∣ter<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of curing the hurt of Monar∣chy by Demo∣cracy, and E∣piscopacy by Presbytery.</NOTE> of my people as to the main is not <HI>healed;</HI> so to <HI>rectifie</HI> the more feared than felt excesses of <HI>Mo∣narchy</HI> and <HI>Episcopacy,</HI> a greater <HI>Tyranny</HI> may be easily raised, not only in a downright <HI>Anarchy,</HI> but there are tyrannous and tedious burthens to be feared even in the best <HI>Democracy</HI> or <HI>Aristo∣cracy</HI> that can be <HI>modelled</HI> for Church or State: where, as the teeth of <HI>harrows</HI> are worse than the point of one <HI>sword,</HI> so many <HI>Reguli</HI> or <HI>Masters</HI> are like to be more <HI>inaccessible,</HI> more <HI>untractable,</HI> more <HI>intollerable,</HI> more <HI>chargeable</HI> to the people than any one can be; and no less both severe and supercilious, besides less <HI>satisfactory</HI> and <HI>honorable;</HI> For it is more ingenuous to be a Subject under some person of ancient <HI>honor</HI> and <HI>eminency,</HI> then to have a <HI>snip of Soveraignty</HI> among others that are but <HI>upstarts</HI> and <HI>equals.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> I believe the <HI>Peers</HI> and <HI>Gentry</HI> of <HI>England</HI> lived much more freely, amply and magnificent∣ly, though <HI>Subjects</HI> under one <HI>Soveraign,</HI> than the best <HI>Heres</HI> or <HI>Burgomasters</HI> do among the Low∣country-men o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Swisses▪</HI> And so did the Clergy of <HI>England</HI> under <HI>excellent Bishops,</HI> beyond what they ever will under the rigor of others who have
<PB N="60" REF="40"/>
their horns, though they endure no head; The little finger of rigid <HI>Presbytery,</HI> hath been heavier than the loins of moderate <HI>Episcopacy.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> It is a <HI>Monstrous</HI> either want of <HI>skill,</HI> or<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of Medicines become Ma∣ladies.</NOTE> of <HI>conduct,</HI> or constancy, for publique <HI>Physicians</HI> to let things run to such impolitick <HI>lapses,</HI> (under the pretence of <HI>curing the hurts of the Daughter of their People</HI>) as while they sought to <HI>recover</HI> the <HI>frequency</HI> of <HI>Parliaments,</HI> (thereby to mode∣rate all enormities, and remedy all burthens in∣convenient in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI>) that (at last) the publique welfare should come to that sad pass or ill fare, that some things called Parliaments, should be thought the greatest publick grievance (and what convention is there so illegal and <HI>con∣temptible,</HI> which some flatterers of times and <HI>powers</HI> will not <HI>christen</HI> and <HI>consecrate</HI> with the ve∣nerable name of that almost sacred Senate?) How desparate and sad a State is it when any grievance should be called a Parliament, or any Parliament prove a publick grievance! as that <HI>Parliament</HI> had the name from (<HI>Parium &amp; Populi &amp; Principis lamentum;</HI>) The <HI>lamentation</HI> or <HI>complaint</HI> of <HI>Prince, Peers,</HI> and of <HI>People,</HI> or their contempt till at length even <HI>military insolency</HI> dared to ad∣venture (as the requital of the long and great pay, which they as Soldiers had received from their dear Country-men) to <HI>garble</HI> and <HI>purge,</HI> to <HI>shufle</HI> and <HI>cut,</HI> to lay out and take in <HI>Parliaments</HI> at their pleasure, like a Stock at <HI>Gleek,</HI> yea and not only to act against them, and without them, but <HI>above</HI> them, in a game of Government, wholly
<PB N="61" REF="40"/>
new to <HI>England,</HI> called <HI>Stratocracy.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> Mean while (<HI>good God!</HI>) what became of the wits of some of our wise <HI>Physitians,</HI> and our confident <HI>Surgeons!</HI> Could they not have fore∣seen and prevented (by discreet counsels and mo∣derate methods of seasonable applying <HI>State Phy∣sick</HI>) those swoonings, and heart-faintings; those convulsions, and dyings; those groans and bleed∣ings of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> of <HI>Kingdoms</HI> and <HI>Com∣mon-wealth,</HI> of <HI>Laws</HI> and <HI>Religion,</HI> of <HI>Magistracy</HI> and <HI>Ministry,</HI> which have all suffered in twenty years of tedious attending their cure, more hurts than they ever did for an hundred years by all the diseases that were pretended so necessary to be cured, that rather than fail, all, even head and members, limb and life it self must be ventured! Where was the vertue of former Oathes, of late Protestations, of all their Covenants and Vows, the Antidotes which they had taken or given a∣gainst Anarchy and Apostacy!</P>
<P>Sect. <HI>Sage and well-advised Physitians</HI> must still<NOTE PLACE="marg">The lubricity and subtilty of ill humors.</NOTE> consider, how <HI>subtil</HI> and <HI>Proteus</HI>-like distempered humors and spirits are in a body that is foul; they instantly, being moved but not removed, slide as from one part, so from one disease to another; as easily transmuting <HI>interests</HI> and <HI>dangers,</HI> as the scales of a ballance go up and down when more weight is cast into one than the other, it presently follows the preponderancy, and grows <HI>lower</HI> when heavier, which was before <HI>higher,</HI> because lighter.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> So in publick or <HI>epidemick distempers,</HI> pre∣ventive
<PB N="62" REF="41"/>
and <HI>prophylactick medicines</HI> must be used as well as <HI>Cathartick</HI> and <HI>purgative;</HI> else things will by <HI>secret</HI> and <HI>insensible steps,</HI> suddenly vary from one extream: and oppression to another, as the cold and hot Fits of a Quartane, especially if the grievances of sharp and unseasonable reme∣dies (like some <HI>corroding plaisters</HI>) follow the <HI>grievances</HI> of the sore and disease, so either <HI>stupi∣fying</HI> instead of <HI>suppling;</HI> or <HI>exasperating</HI> instead of <HI>mollifying;</HI> or cutting <HI>noble parts quite off</HI> in∣stead of <HI>reducing</HI> them to <HI>due temper</HI> and <HI>propor¦tion:</HI> State Physitians must be as wary of using too much of the <HI>salt</HI> of <HI>popular Proposals,</HI> and the <HI>niter</HI> of <HI>levelling principles,</HI> as other Physitians are of using <HI>Quick-silver</HI> uncorrected, or un∣mortified; for they are both most acute poysons if not well prepared and aptly applied; by which either <HI>unfit,</HI> or <HI>unseasonable,</HI> or <HI>immoderate,</HI> or <HI>rude,</HI> or <HI>forcible applications,</HI> men are quickly carried beyond their own duties, and others <HI>de∣serts,</HI> for want of that <HI>Caution, Conscience, Chari∣ty</HI> and <HI>Discretion,</HI> which is necessary for all those who meddle in matters of life and death; in pri∣vate, much more publick <HI>healing</HI> and <HI>welfare;</HI> else the <HI>quick</HI> as well as the <HI>dead flesh</HI> may be cut off and consumed; the <HI>vital</HI> as well us <HI>vitiated spirits</HI> and humors may be exhausted. The very <HI>Arteries</HI> and <HI>Sinews</HI> of Government are prone to be rotted, and the whole fabrick of the Body will fall one limb from another.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> Especially when by the fury or fear of<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of violent wayes of Healing.</NOTE> <HI>Prince,</HI> or <HI>People,</HI> things are brought to that
<PB N="63" REF="41"/>
pass, that all other <HI>medicines</HI> being laid aside, nothing is made use of but the <HI>weapon-salve,</HI> that <HI>unguentum armarium,</HI> the Sword of War, which hath seldome the vertue of <HI>Achilles his Sword,</HI> which was to <HI>heal</HI> as well as to Wound; hence follow those <HI>horrible healings,</HI> which (like<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 34. 25.</NOTE> <HI>Simeons</HI> and <HI>Levi's</HI> cure of the <HI>Sichemites</HI> when they <HI>were sore,</HI>) destroy both <HI>Prince and People,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov, 14. 28.</NOTE> either <HI>lopping off the armes</HI> and <HI>legs of the body</HI> Politick, the strength and <HI>multitude</HI> of the <HI>Nobi∣lity, Gentry,</HI> and <HI>Communalty,</HI> which is the <HI>glory</HI> of a King and Kingdome, or else by a <HI>dreadful abscission,</HI> cropping off the very <HI>head</HI> of <HI>So∣veraignty,</HI> from the <HI>body</HI> of the <HI>polity;</HI> the first reduceth a <HI>Nation</HI> to its <HI>stumps,</HI> and makes it a cripple <HI>a long time;</HI> the <HI>other makes</HI> both its <HI>ap∣pearance,</HI> and its <HI>motions,</HI> as <HI>monstrous</HI> and <HI>desor∣med,</HI> as if a <HI>body</HI> should move without an head, (as it was in those dayes when there <HI>was no King in Israel.</HI>) or as the Giant <HI>Polyphemus</HI> did;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Judg. 21. 25.</NOTE> when <HI>blind,</HI> he <HI>gropeth</HI> for <HI>Ulysses;</HI> so are a great <HI>people,</HI> when in the <HI>darknesse</HI> and <HI>confusion</HI> of <HI>Anarchy,</HI> they seek in vain <HI>for</HI> that <HI>order, Wis∣dome,</HI> and <HI>authority,</HI> which are the <HI>Body, Soul,</HI> and <HI>spirit</HI> of <HI>Government,</HI> and are eminently <HI>comprehended</HI> in the <HI>head,</HI> with which the whole body best corresponds, when happily compacted together. This principal part once taken away by violence, the body (like fouls, whose heads are wrong off) may <HI>flutter</HI> for a while, with blind inordinate and dying <HI>motions;</HI> but no better can be expected, unless (as in <HI>Hydra</HI>) many heads
<PB N="64" REF="42"/>
could presently spring up in stead of one, which is neither easily nor suddenly done in Nations, whose native courage, emulation, spirit and metal raiseth up many <HI>rivals</HI> for <HI>soveraignty,</HI> and as many disdainful enemies against all that either <HI>obstruct</HI> their pretended power, or affect to enjoy it themselves.</P>
<P>6. When these <HI>pretending healers</HI> are much<NOTE PLACE="marg">Slight healers by new inven∣tions and un∣experienced applications.</NOTE> for a new <HI>Paracelsian</HI> practice, for unexperi∣mented applications or <HI>medicaments</HI> of their own inventions, which are <HI>occasionally</HI> extracted and <HI>Chimically</HI> made (with sin and force) by <HI>them∣selves,</HI> and such as are of their faction; but they do not natively flow as the <HI>balme</HI> of <HI>Gilead</HI> doth from the Tree of good Government and polity, that is from those <HI>Laws</HI> and <HI>Constitutions,</HI> which <HI>have been</HI> long approved as most proper for the Nations Welfare, which (without doubt) are best able and most apt, both to preserve and re∣store the health of the <HI>Daughter of my people;</HI> no <HI>counsel, practice,</HI> or <HI>power</HI> of <HI>Prince</HI> or <HI>Potentate,</HI> or <HI>Parliament,</HI> that are <HI>praeter,</HI> or <HI>contra legal,</HI> can be for long or sound healing, but rather proves more <HI>noxious</HI> and <HI>infestive</HI> at last to the publique <HI>peace:</HI> For the <HI>Law</HI> (which is power regulated by <HI>Wisdome,</HI> and <HI>Wisdome</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Law the most healing.</NOTE> <HI>asserted</HI> by just power, and both <HI>confirmed</HI> by the <HI>Parliamentary</HI> consent of all estates concerned) this is the <HI>Radical moysture</HI> or <HI>native balsome,</HI> by which the <HI>lamp of life</HI> is preserved in the body <HI>politique;</HI> as this decayes, so <HI>spirit</HI> and <HI>vigor,</HI>
<PB N="65" REF="42"/>
<HI>health,</HI> and <HI>harmony, peace</HI> and <HI>protection,</HI> love and life decays.</P>
<P>§. Yea, where <HI>force</HI> is <HI>necessary</HI> to be used, yet it must be <HI>limited,</HI> and <HI>commissionated</HI> by law; else it is but a <HI>Lion broke loose,</HI> or a <HI>ranging Bear,</HI> or a <HI>ravening Wolf,</HI> or as a <HI>mutinied Army,</HI> no better then a <HI>tumultuary riot,</HI> and <HI>violence,</HI> like the fighting of a body with it self in fits of the falling sickness, such new <HI>pits</HI> and <HI>cisternes</HI> will not hold any water; for they are not onely crackt in the making, and marred upon the wheels, but they presently dash against one another, as earthen pitchers; they are <HI>by-paths</HI> of <HI>extravagant power,</HI> and fallacious pretentions,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 6. 16.</NOTE> but not comparable, in <HI>point of health</HI> and <HI>safety,</HI> to the good old way, (<HI>&amp; bona, &amp; antiqua, &amp; probata</HI>) which long time had liked and <HI>attested</HI> to be <HI>very good.</HI></P>
<P>Such as put on in all haste <HI>Sauls Armour</HI> of Soveraignty, which they never before <HI>essayed</HI> to <HI>wear,</HI> nor have <HI>shoulders fit for it,</HI> will soon find it not onely <HI>inconvenient</HI> for them, but com∣bersom, dangerous, and in the end pernicious; if they mean indeed to kill those <HI>Gyants,</HI> those <HI>Goliahs</HI> of <HI>uncircumcised enormities,</HI> which defie God and Law, it is better to take those smooth stones, and that <HI>sling,</HI> to which as Masters of assemblies, or Magistrates, or Parliament men, or Justices, they are <HI>wonted,</HI> according to the Law, and the duty of their place, than to <HI>cumber</HI> and <HI>engage themselves</HI> in such uncoth▪ high and heavy <HI>undertakings,</HI> which are seldome other
<PB N="66" REF="43"/>
than <HI>disadvantagious,</HI> and <HI>destructive,</HI> as al∣ways dangerous to the <HI>counsellors</HI> and <HI>actors,</HI> no less than to the publick peace and welfare; for as <HI>Tacitus</HI> well observes, (<HI>Consilia callida &amp; inhonesta, prima fronte laeta, tractatu dura, eventu tristia</HI>) new and illegal projects, are commonly pernicious, and crying at last, however they smile and flatter at first; nor can any violence or success heal a Nation or a conscience, where the Law smites by accusing, and the conscience by <HI>con∣demning</HI> men for their wicked principles and unjust proceedings.</P>
<P>7. When these <HI>pretended Healers,</HI> leaving all<NOTE PLACE="marg">7 Healing by charmes and Parliaments.</NOTE> <HI>wonted</HI> and <HI>approved medicines,</HI> which Gods word and the <HI>laws</HI> of the land, right reason and true religion do <HI>warrant</HI> or allow, fly to their <HI>inchantments,</HI> as if they would heal by <HI>charmes,</HI> and cure by <HI>Philters</HI> or <HI>amulets,</HI> as by <HI>carrying Bibles</HI> in their hands, by using much Scripture phrase and expression, by following <HI>sermons</HI> and <HI>fasts</HI> and <HI>prayers,</HI> by affecting an odd kind of <HI>canting way</HI> of <HI>writing</HI> and <HI>speaking,</HI> by zealous pretending of <HI>sanctity</HI> and <HI>Christian liberty,</HI> or through <HI>reformations</HI> of <HI>advancing</HI> the cause of God, and Kingdome of Jesus Christ, by cry∣ing up <HI>providences,</HI> and successes, by <HI>conjuring</HI> up strange <HI>fears</HI> and hopes, <HI>jealousies</HI> and <HI>expecta∣tions,</HI> like so many <HI>Ghosts</HI> and <HI>Goblins,</HI> to scare and amuse the common people: Lastly by flying to <HI>raptures, inspirations, enthusiasms, holy con∣vulsions, and such like quaking and quacking tricks</HI> as pretend no less to the skill of <HI>healing</HI> all the
<PB N="67" REF="43"/>
<HI>hurts of the daughter of my people,</HI> than <HI>Wizards</HI> and cunning men do to cure <HI>all diseases of man and beast.</HI></P>
<P>§. Thus the <HI>Temple</HI> of the <HI>Lord,</HI> the <HI>Temple</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier 7. 4.</NOTE> <HI>of the Lord</HI> is urged, when they intend to de∣stroy <HI>Church and State;</HI> it is superciliously yea very surlily spoken, to <HI>persons</HI> much better every way then themselves, Stand by, we are holier<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 65. 5.</NOTE> <HI>than you,</HI> we are <HI>Abrahams</HI> seed, and the true <HI>Israel of God.</HI> The work of healing <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> is the work <HI>of Saints;</HI> as soone as they can agree what way to take, <HI>what plaisters</HI> to make, and what <HI>power</HI> to get into their hands, that they may apply their rare <HI>Cataplasmes</HI> or <HI>Empla∣sters.</HI></P>
<P>Thus some tell us there must be no <HI>King</HI> but<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>0. 21.</NOTE> <HI>King Jesus,</HI> and themselves sitting <HI>on his right</HI> and <HI>left hand,</HI> in all <HI>power, Ecclesiastical, Civil,</HI> and <HI>Military,</HI> judging the <HI>twelve tribes of Israel;</HI> for they strongly fancy <HI>England</HI> to be <HI>Judea,</HI> or the <HI>holy land,</HI> and most of the <HI>people</HI> to be of late turned <HI>Jews;</HI> Others will have <HI>no Bishops,</HI> nor<NOTE PLACE="marg">The spo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les of those Egypti∣ans.</NOTE> <HI>any thing that belonged to Bishops,</HI> but onely <HI>their good lands</HI> and <HI>houses,</HI> the spoiles of those <HI>Egyptians;</HI> others will have no <HI>presbyters, nor tythes, nor Temples,</HI> but <HI>arbitrary,</HI> and <HI>unmerci∣nary Preachers,</HI> in occasional <HI>Barnes</HI> and <HI>Stables,</HI> or (<HI>sub dio</HI>) in open fields, who will do the <HI>work of Christ without mans wages.</HI> It were well if their Souldiers would do so too, in their <HI>holy wars,</HI> which are voted by some to be the <HI>work of Jesus Christ;</HI> some would have they
<PB N="68" REF="44"/>
know not <HI>what themselves,</HI> but they attend fur∣ther light, by which they may better <HI>discerne</HI> the way of <HI>healing</HI> the <HI>Nations, and their</HI> own hurts.</P>
<P>§. Mean time they look neither to the <HI>Law</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Is<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 5. 2<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> nor the <HI>Testimony,</HI> neither to the rule of <HI>piety, equity,</HI> nor <HI>charity,</HI> as if a little <HI>chattering</HI> of pious, or rather impious <HI>nonsence,</HI> were suffici∣ent to cast out the <HI>legions of Divels,</HI> or the clay and spittle of their lips were able to cure the ma∣ny <HI>distempers</HI> of these Nations, especially when the blindness, boldness and folly of such Operators and Circulators, is so manifest to all men that have eyes inlightned by reason or religion, by Laws of God or man, that I hope it shall <HI>pro∣ceed no further.</HI> Have we need of <HI>mad men,</HI> as <HI>Achish</HI> King of <HI>Gath, speaks</HI> of <HI>David,</HI> disfigu∣red<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 2<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 15.</NOTE> to a frenzy! Are they likely to be <HI>healers of others,</HI> whose diseases are so got into their <HI>crowns,</HI> that they are not onely <HI>fantastick</HI> but <HI>fanatick,</HI> to the tune of the <HI>Maniches</HI> and <HI>Cir∣cumcellians;</HI> that is, people of no <HI>just</HI> and <HI>honest,</HI> of no settled or constant, no rational or religious principles (<HI>morbus destruit artem</HI>) a good Physi∣tian is not fit to be his own or others Physitian, if he be distempered; much less these men, than who no men have discovered more craziness of mind, and crookedness of manners, having little fear <HI>of God,</HI> and less <HI>reverence of men;</HI> either their <HI>ambition,</HI> or their <HI>indigence,</HI> or their <HI>idleness,</HI> or their <HI>Jesuitick juglings,</HI> or their desperate de∣signs to turn all into rapine, blood and confusion,
<PB N="69" REF="44"/>
makes them impatient that any men of <HI>better skill,</HI> and <HI>honester wills</HI> than themselves should come nigh the <HI>Patient,</HI> or apply those <HI>All-heals,</HI> or <HI>Pa∣naces</HI> and <HI>Catholicons,</HI> which are no where to be found in their Pedlars packs or Apothecaries shops (where poisons are set off with the specious titles and inscriptions of sanctity, and liberty and light) but in the known Laws of God and man rightly in∣terpreted and impartially executed according to <HI>Equity, Order▪</HI> and <HI>Charity;</HI> not in those <HI>godly forma∣lities,</HI> or <HI>gracious extravagancies,</HI> or <HI>illegal irregu∣larities,</HI> with which some vaporers have made so great flourishes for some years, and so long afflict∣ed the <HI>daughter of my people;</HI> and would for ever have done so (according to the method of those rare cures they sometimes wrought in <HI>Germany</HI> a∣bout the 1530. by the seduction and slaughter of an hundred thousand people in the Anabaptistick and fanatick waies of mutiny and rebellion) if God in his mercy (as we hope) had not prepared to put the <HI>Patient</HI> into <HI>better hands,</HI> which may be guided by wiser heads and honester hearts, who will not so cry up <HI>Religion</HI> and <HI>Reformation,</HI> as to<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 3. 8.</NOTE> run out to horrid violence and crying injustice; nor fancy and teach that <HI>any evil of sin and in∣justice</HI> may be done that a <HI>publick good</HI> may come thereby: One may as well expect to <HI>heal wounds</HI> by <HI>poysoned plaisters</HI> or venemous instruments: Men must not <HI>lye for God,</HI> nor <HI>commit robbery for</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 61. 8.</NOTE> <HI>burnt offering,</HI> nor do things unwarrantable or unjust by mans Law, in order to magnifie Gods cause, much less their own, though just; and may
<PB N="70" REF="45"/>
they do it for causes wholly unjust? this is only to dash the two Tables against each other at best, or to break them both in pieces against the rocks of hard hearts, as is usually done when <HI>fantastick heads,</HI> and <HI>foul hands</HI> dare without authority from God or man, to set up the golden Calves which they list to Idolize, and which all men must presently fall <HI>down and worship;</HI> such was that popular and plau∣sible <HI>invention</HI> of the Jews at first, but it cost the wickedly wanton people dear at last, when their<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 32. 28. 35</NOTE> <HI>new Diety</HI> &amp; <HI>rare invention</HI> was consecrated by the blood and death of many thousand of the people; Nor was that fire of <HI>mutiny</HI> and <HI>rebellion</HI> with <HI>Ko∣rah</HI> and his faction raised against <HI>Moses</HI> and <HI>Aaron,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Numb. 16. 7.</NOTE> quenched at a <HI>cheaper rate,</HI> whatever they pre∣tend of holiness. Yea St. <HI>Austin</HI> observes in his 162 <HI>Epistle</HI> (<HI>ex poenae differentia peccatum censeri</HI>) by the honor of that new punishment which fell on them one may easily see how the sins of <HI>mutiny Rebellion</HI> and <HI>Hypocrisie</HI> being twisted together do outweigh any other sins.</P>
<P>Lastly, Then they <HI>heal slightly,</HI> 1. When Phy∣sitians<NOTE PLACE="marg">8. Slight hea∣ling <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r want of constant<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ap∣plication of good prescrip∣tions.</NOTE> either give <HI>good words,</HI> or make good <HI>salves,</HI> and spread good <HI>plaisters,</HI> but never ef∣fectually <HI>apply</HI> them to the <HI>Patient,</HI> or suffer them to be pulled off as their impatience listeth: When bones are broken, as well as the flesh deeply wounded, the <HI>ligatures</HI> and <HI>splinters</HI> must be good as well as the <HI>plaisters:</HI> There must be no <HI>dislocation</HI> where we expect a perfect cure; <HI>Parts</HI> must be set and kept in their proper pla∣ces;
<PB N="71" REF="45"/>
else they either <HI>heal not at all,</HI> or to a great <HI>deformity</HI> and continued infirmity.</P>
<P>Or 2. When both <HI>Healers</HI> and <HI>Patient,</HI> like<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Chron. 16. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> For too much trusting to Physitians.</NOTE> <HI>King Uzziah,</HI> trust so much to themselves, to the skill of the <HI>Physicians</HI> and <HI>Chrurgeons,</HI> that they less look up to God, and lean to their own un∣derstanding: They will find the <HI>wisdom of the world foolishness,</HI> and the <HI>arm</HI> of <HI>flesh an Egyptian</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 17. 5,</NOTE> <HI>reed;</HI> to lean so much on them as to <HI>neglect God,</HI> is not only a vain but a <HI>noxious</HI> and cursed thing; for God will bring to naught the counsels of Princes, who begin not their wisdom and end it in the fear of God; as the most pious and learned <HI>Primate</HI> Bishop <HI>Usher,</HI> in the begin∣ning<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of Patients idolizing their Physitian.</NOTE> of the <HI>long Parliament</HI> would oft with <HI>ear∣nestness foretel,</HI> That God would confute and pu∣nish the too great <HI>glory</HI> and <HI>confidence</HI> which people generally had in <HI>Parliaments,</HI> as if the sins of the Nation could not out-vie all the care, skill and power of Parliaments; who may have their infection and diseases too, if they do not exact∣ly look to God and their consciences, to <HI>Religion</HI> and <HI>Justice</HI> both; to duty more than <HI>applause</HI> or reward, or <HI>success;</HI> which can never be good or comfortable, unless it be First the fruit and effect of <HI>good counsel,</HI> (that is <HI>religious</HI> and <HI>legal;</HI>) Se∣condly, of <HI>humble prayer</HI> to God; Thirdly, of a gracious submission to his will, when we have done our duty; men lose themselves when they <HI>seek not God</HI> first in all their publick counsels. For<NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccles. 9. 11. Psa. 3. 8▪ and 29. 11: Psa. 147. 14.</NOTE> <HI>the race is not to the swift, nor the battel to the strong, but the Lord gives the blessing of peace, and</HI>
<PB N="72" REF="46"/>
<HI>health, and salvation to his people;</HI> He, as the so∣veraign Physitian can best, and only heal our <HI>pub∣lick wounds,</HI> by making men to be of <HI>one mind in the Lord,</HI> by <HI>pouring</HI> out his <HI>spirit</HI> of <HI>wisdome</HI> and <HI>moderation,</HI> of <HI>repentance</HI> and <HI>compensati∣on,</HI> of <HI>mutuall pitty</HI> and <HI>compassion,</HI> of <HI>Ju∣stice</HI> and <HI>judgment,</HI> of an <HI>holy</HI> and <HI>happy refor∣mation,</HI> which heals the hurts of mens hearts, and the wounds of their consciences, and the <HI>running issues</HI> of their <HI>evil lives;</HI> these are the happiest and surest methods of a Nations heal∣ing. We see in the <HI>oft relapses</HI> of the <HI>Jews,</HI> no sooner had they by sins of publique scandal and notorious contagion hurt themselves, but Gods hand smites them by <HI>famine</HI> or <HI>plague,</HI> or<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 2. 30.</NOTE> <HI>sword, or war</HI> and <HI>oppression;</HI> no sooner had they <HI>repented</HI> and <HI>turned</HI> solemnly from their sins to him that smote them, but God <HI>turned from his wrath and healed the Land.</HI></P>
<P>§. We have had in <HI>England</HI> many <HI>days of hu∣miliation,</HI> in order to our humbling and heal∣ing, but hitherto we have been more and more hurt; because we fasted not for sin, but to sin, as God reproacheth the <HI>Jews; for strife, and</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa 58.</NOTE> <HI>debate, and oppression, to smite with the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ist of vio∣lence, &amp;c.</HI> We laid on a formal <HI>plaister of Refor∣mation,</HI> but we never throughly searched the wound, nor purged out the <HI>putid matter;</HI> yea we multiplied the <HI>corruption,</HI> and added <HI>hypocri∣sie</HI> to former <HI>iniquity;</HI> the sins of War and vio∣lence, of inordinate revenge and cruelty to those of peace and luxury.</P>
<P><PB N="73" REF="46"/>I finde, the Parliaments of England never<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. Parliament Prayers, in a Book called <HI>The Ancient<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Prayers of the Church.</HI></NOTE> thrived better, nor kept the publick in better health, than when those two excellent <HI>Prayers</HI> (lately reprinted) which very <HI>gravely</HI> and <HI>plainly</HI> minded them of their <HI>duty</HI> in that <HI>place,</HI> were daily used among them; which were much more <HI>significant, grave</HI> and <HI>pertinent,</HI> than such Sera∣phick or <HI>rambling,</HI> and loose or odd <HI>Expressions,</HI> as some men are prone to use either in their affected <HI>varieties,</HI> or in their tedious <HI>Tautologies;</HI> which have oft more in them of Invention than Judgment, and stick more upon fancy and faction, than conscience and the common good. Certainly, where men are solemnly and jointly to ask of God the same proper <HI>blessings</HI> every day, they may very well use the same words, and <HI>petitionary Formes,</HI> as Christ did thrice in his Agony; For Gods <HI>immutability</HI> is not weary of any holy <HI>constancy,</HI> nor delighted with any <HI>novelty,</HI> but that of a <HI>new heart,</HI> and <HI>new spirit,</HI> which I hope and pray he would give both the <HI>Physicians</HI> and to the <HI>Daughter</HI> of my people: That neither the later may be miserable, by not being well healed, nor the second blameable for <HI>healing</HI> onely <HI>slightly,</HI> and <HI>superficially;</HI> which is the fault here laid to the charge of some persons, and leads me to the fi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Particular proposed; namely,</P>
<P>5. They: that is, <HI>Those publick</HI> persons, who of<NOTE PLACE="marg">5. The per∣sons charged for slight healing.</NOTE> right <HI>ought,</HI> or <HI>in fact</HI> do, or in their action may manage the Affairs of the <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State;</HI> who have <HI>Councels, power, and Authority,</HI> interest, and influence, fit to advance the <HI>publick welfare;</HI> by
<PB N="74" REF="47"/>
<HI>correcting</HI> the distempers, and reducing all to a due constitution of health.</P>
<P>They: that is, 1. Those <HI>Princes</HI> or <HI>Kings,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Kings and soveraign Princes slight heaven.</NOTE> <HI>Judges</HI> and <HI>Chief</HI> Magistrates; who being them∣selves vicious, or <HI>Idolatrous,</HI> or Hypocrites, or vain, (turning Piety into Policy, and Religion into <HI>reason of State</HI>) not onely infect the people by the contagion of an <HI>impious example;</HI> but are willing the people should be as bad as them∣selves; That, for their enormities being followed by their Subjects, they may seem less by the Imitation; and, as it were, Approbation: <HI>Kings</HI> that rule their people not by Law and Justice, but<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ep<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ 22. 26, 27.</NOTE> by will, and Passion, more for their own <HI>pleasure,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Pro. 28. 15, 16.</NOTE> than the Publick Wellfare; that are great <HI>Op∣pressors, staying</HI> as well as <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lee<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing</HI> their people; yea, <HI>breaking their bones,</HI> and <HI>eating their flesh:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mic<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪ 3. 2, 3.</NOTE> Ruling men, not as <HI>rational creatures,</HI> of the same <HI>Creator,</HI> nor as brethren in the same Saviour, Sons to the same <HI>Father of their Country;</HI> but as meer <HI>Slaves</HI> and <HI>Vassals,</HI> forgetting, that every <HI>King</HI> hath a <HI>King</HI> in heaven above him, to whom he is <HI>subject,</HI> and must give account, not onely of the <HI>hurt</HI> he hath done, and the <HI>wounds</HI> he hath made, on the soules and bodies, the estates and consciences of his people, but also of their Health, and good he hath left undone, when it was in his place, and power, like the <HI>Sun</HI> in the <HI>firmament:</HI> or as a little God among men, to have been (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) a Catholick good to Church and State, that thousands might have been blessed by them in this world, and
<PB N="75" REF="47"/>
to <HI>eternity</HI> blessed God for them. Not only the hands, but the mouths &amp; eyes of Princes are <HI>heal∣ing</HI> of their peoples evils, if they will but rebuke and reprove, frown upon, and discountenance evil doers. Mens sins and Accounts enlarge ac∣cording as their <HI>influence</HI> and <HI>relations</HI> ampliate; which carry their obligations with them, to God and man. Great place and power are of all things most to be avoided, if they onely serve to <HI>aggrendise</HI> a man<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sins, either of <HI>omission,</HI> or <HI>commission,</HI> for to augment his Judgement, and Eternal torment.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Those subordinate <HI>Counsellors,</HI> and inserior<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Counsellors and subordi∣nate Magi∣strates slight Healers.</NOTE> <HI>Magistrates</HI> who are under the command of <HI>man,</HI> and more of God, these heal <HI>slightly,</HI> when they are not men of <HI>Integrity, fearing</HI> God, and <HI>hating</HI> Covetousnesse, but orafty <HI>Complyers</HI> with<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 18. 21.</NOTE> the inordinate lusts and passions, with the illegal commands of either▪ Princes or people, contrary to their oaths: so by flattery, or faction, to make way for their <HI>Ambition,</HI> and gain, by the unde∣served favour of either, or dividing one from the other, by a most unnatural <HI>wa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> and <HI>jealousle;</HI> such as please man rather then God, and love<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Gal.</HI> 1. 10▪</NOTE> themselves more then their <HI>Country,</HI> or▪ the <HI>Church;</HI> such as prefer their bodies and Est<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es before their <HI>Souls;</HI> and put the <HI>healing<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> of the Church, and true Religion in the last place, or Rear of affairs: and when they professe to heal the Irreligion of others by severe <HI>Acts</HI> and <HI>Ordi∣nances</HI> against <HI>Adultery, S<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>earing, Proph<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nes<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, debauch<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry, drunkennesse, corruption, injustice,</HI>
<PB N="76" REF="48"/>
&amp;c. yet themselves are higher by the <HI>shoulders,</HI> than the most of the people in these and other <HI>enormaties:</HI> As if <HI>Peers,</HI> or privy-<HI>Counsellors,</HI> or <HI>Counsellors</HI> of <HI>State,</HI> or <HI>Parliament-men,</HI> had a Priviledge to sin more, or to repent, and suffer lesse than other men.</P>
<P>Nothing weakens the credit and Authority of any publick Lawes so much as when the <HI>Law∣givers</HI> least observe them, or are the first that break them; like <HI>Physitians</HI> that prescribe strict <HI>diet</HI> to their <HI>Patients,</HI> but themselves indulge all manner of <HI>Epicurisme:</HI> Here every one is prone to retort; <HI>Physician heal thy self:</HI> The<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 4. 23.</NOTE> best things are commonly done by the <HI>best hands; Religio Medici,</HI> Conscience is here required as well as his <HI>Science:</HI> They will hardly do their Country good, who care not, either to <HI>serve</HI> God, or to save their own souls.</P>
<P>Men should make conscience of private actions, much more of publique adventures, which are of grand consequence (as the undertakings in war) and not to be done <HI>rashly, slovenly, slightly,</HI> and <HI>indifferently.</HI> Nor may publick <HI>Counsellors,</HI> or <HI>Ministers</HI> of State like <HI>Achitophel</HI> think they do wisely, or safely, because they go with the <HI>vogue</HI> and <HI>stream</HI> of times, with the winde, and tide, or humor of some people, in their prevalent <HI>Factions, discontents,</HI> and <HI>clamors,</HI> by which vote Christ himself was crucified, <HI>Mark</HI> 15. 13.</P>
<P>Common people in their <HI>Paroxismes,</HI> or fits of discontent, like sick and <HI>pained patients,</HI> are ill <HI>Dictators</HI> to their <HI>Physitians;</HI> who must advise
<PB N="77" REF="48"/>
better for them than they would for themselves; else they will heal their hurts very slovingly, slowly, and ill-favouredly, to their own sin and reproach as well as others pain and charge; Nor is it enough for <HI>Aarons</HI> excuse to say, <HI>The people are set upon mischief;</HI> when they would needs<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 32. 22.</NOTE> have him make them visible <HI>Egyptian</HI> Gods, to <HI>go</HI> before them, under the figure of a <HI>golden calf,</HI> to be instead of their true and invisible God: publick Persons, and Honorable Counsellors, (as <HI>Joseph of Ari<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>thea</HI>) must not go (<HI>quâ <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tur,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 93. 53.</NOTE> <HI>sed qua eundum</HI>) as peoples fury, or the prevalent Factions drives them: but as the <HI>Word</HI> of God, and the Lawes of the Land <HI>direct</HI> them; else they shall beare not onely their one, but the <HI>iniquity of their people,</HI> who sin and suffer un∣warned and naked, hurt and unhealed, upon<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezekiel 33.</NOTE> the account of such <HI>cowardly Counsellors,</HI> and <HI>corrupt Magistrates,</HI> or <HI>Ministers</HI> of <HI>State;</HI> all whose wisdomes will come to nought; and they<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 2. 6.</NOTE> will at length (like <HI>Achitophel</HI>) be snared in<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 17. 23</NOTE> the halters of their own twisting.</P>
<P>3. Those <HI>Priests</HI> and <HI>Prophets;</HI> those <HI>Pastors</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">3 Priests and Prophets, Pa∣stors and Mi∣nisters slight Healers.</NOTE> and <HI>Teachers,</HI> those <HI>Bishops</HI> and <HI>Presbyters,</HI> who are in <HI>Publick Place,</HI> and sacred <HI>Authority,</HI> as to the <HI>things</HI> of God; the matters of <HI>Religion,</HI> and mens <HI>souls</HI> good: These <HI>heal slightly,</HI> when they do the Work of God negligently; when they skin<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 2. 22.</NOTE> over scandalous publique sins, (as <HI>Ely</HI> to his Sons, with soft reproof; when they sow pillows under <HI>Princes, Parliaments,</HI> and <HI>peoples</HI> elbowes, when<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezek. 13. 18.</NOTE> they fear the <HI>face</HI> and <HI>offence of men,</HI> more than
<PB N="78" REF="49"/>
<HI>of God;</HI> when they are <HI>workmen</HI> that need to be <HI>ashamed,</HI> their Lives and Actions confuting their Instructions; and their doing, making their <HI>Doctrine</HI> to blush; when they heal publick <HI>Enormities</HI> or <HI>calamities</HI> by I know not what novel <HI>Inventions,</HI> and <HI>magick spels</HI> of fine words: which are no better than the <HI>powder</HI> of a <HI>post;</HI> compared to the approved <HI>Catholick prescriptions</HI> of 1600 years, which were <HI>sove∣raign</HI> for <HI>Clergy</HI> and <HI>Laity;</HI> to preserve <HI>order</HI> and <HI>unity; soundnesse of doctrine,</HI> and <HI>ins<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an∣dalousness</HI> of <HI>manners</HI> in the Church of Christ, under Christian Kings and Queens (who were bountiful <HI>nursing Fathers,</HI> and <HI>Mothers,</HI> to the Church of Christ, and the Clergy): yet not by the <HI>Dominion</HI> and <HI>pomp, luxury</HI> and <HI>tyranny</HI> of <HI>Bishops,</HI> nor yet by the <HI>Factious</HI> and <HI>refractory humours</HI> of <HI>Presbyters;</HI> much less by the <HI>schismatick saucinesse</HI> of people, who cast off both <HI>Bishops</HI> and <HI>Presbyters;</HI> but by the <HI>fatherly gravity,</HI> prudence, and Eminence of godly and Reverend <HI>Bishops;</HI> by the brotherly <HI>assistance,</HI> and <HI>son-like subordination</HI> of sober and <HI>orderly</HI> Presbyters, by the <HI>service</HI> and <HI>obsequiousness</HI> of <HI>humble</HI> and <HI>diligent Deac<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>;</HI> and by the meek submission of Christian people to the Care, Monition, Councel, and respective <HI>Superiority</HI> of every order; as sheep to their Chief <HI>Shepherds,</HI> and their <HI>Assistants,</HI> o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/><NOTE PLACE="marg">The Har∣mony which ought to be in the Church, in or∣der to Hea∣ling.</NOTE> <HI>Attendants.</HI></P>
<P>Divide this chain <HI>of Church-Union,</HI> Order and Communion, in vain shall we talk of <HI>beal∣ing</HI>
<PB N="79" REF="49"/>
the Flock of its <HI>scabs</HI> and <HI>scratches,</HI> or <HI>hurts;</HI> I confess, that I own, and ever shall do, Primitive Episcopacy with Presbitery; so that as St. <HI>Paul</HI> speaks in another case, Neither of them should be without the other in the Lord; Neither of them oppressed or extirpated, but so regulated and incouraged, as I believe, all <HI>moderate</HI> and <HI>learned</HI> men desire; if it be my fault and Errour, that I prefer this Holy and Catholick Composition before any other late simple receipts of Church <HI>Government,</HI> by which to <HI>heal</HI> any <HI>Church;</HI> Truly I ow this my <HI>Judgment</HI> to all the Councils, to all the Fathers, to all the Church-Historians, to be best <HI>witnesses of truth in all times,</HI> who have unanimously <HI>conspired</HI> to lead me into this Opinion; agreeable to the word of God, the Example of Christ, the practice of the Apostles, and the parallel Customes of all Churches▪ which is, besides, mightily <HI>confirmed</HI> in me by the <HI>misdom, Piety,</HI> and <HI>Prosperity</HI> of this Church under good Bishops, since its. Reformation, which none in the world exceeded, for <HI>health</HI> and <HI>happiness,</HI> for sound and sincere Christians, till some mens <HI>itching</HI> and <HI>scratching</HI> too much (even till the bloud came)▪ and others, either not applying <HI>seasonable</HI> Salves, or else <HI>sharper Remedies</HI> than perhaps were <HI>necessary</HI> (or pre∣scribed by the <HI>wisdom of our</HI> Church and Laws) have festred the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urts</HI> and <HI>sores</HI> of Religion, that they now feem almost incurable, till such <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nds are by Gods goodness applyed, and such
<PB N="80" REF="50"/>
Medicines used, as are most proper for a <HI>sick▪</HI> and <HI>diseased Church:</HI> which hands and Medicines I cannot think ought to be <HI>Secular,</HI> but rather <HI>Ecclesiastick.</HI></P>
<P>Such in a free <HI>Synod of learned Divines</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Of Ecclesiasti∣cal Council, or Free Synods.</NOTE> should, as a Colledge of spiritual Physicians, <HI>advise</HI> and <HI>prepare;</HI> (for there is as much need of calling for free <HI>Synods,</HI> as <HI>Free Parliaments</HI>) The want of the former <HI>G. Naz.</HI> deplores as the occasion of so much Faction and Vexation in the Church in his times. <HI>Lay-men,</HI> though learned, able and honest, have enough to do in <HI>Lay-matters. Churchmen</HI> have nothing left them to do, as to <HI>Secular Councels,</HI> or <HI>State Concernments,</HI> and therefore ought not to be <HI>excluded</HI> from their proper sphere, <HI>Church</HI> affairs; being the <HI>best skilled</HI> of any <HI>men</HI> (else they are ill imployed in the things of God) for the <HI>searching, supplying,</HI> and <HI>healing</HI> the <HI>hurts</HI> of the <HI>Church,</HI> and <HI>true Religion,</HI> in its <HI>Doctrine, Discipline, Order, Unity</HI> and <HI>Authority;</HI> That <HI>maxime</HI> is true of the <HI>Clergy,</HI> as well as of other <HI>Orders</HI> of men, <HI>Unicuique credendum est in sua arte,</HI> Every man is most to be credited in what he is most skilled. I am sure (as to the <HI>point</HI> of <HI>Physitians</HI>) no people that are wise, and would be <HI>healed</HI> in good earnest, but are carefull to get the <HI>best</HI> and <HI>ablest,</HI> unless they <HI>undervalue</HI> their <HI>health</HI> and <HI>lives,</HI> and to save <HI>charges will venture</HI> to <HI>dye.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Fourthly,</HI> They; that is, Those <HI>Souldiers</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Souldiers and Commanders slight healers.</NOTE> and <HI>Military</HI> men, Chief <HI>Commanders</HI> and
<PB N="81" REF="50"/>
<HI>Others</HI> under them; these <HI>heal</HI> but <HI>sleightly,</HI> when either they will be (as the Clowns all-heal) the onely Professors of State Physick, and under∣take all cures in Church and State, or else they think and act, as if there is no such way to <HI>heal</HI> soundly, as to make greater <HI>wounds</HI> and <HI>bruises,</HI> by <HI>irreconcilable distance, prepo∣sterous</HI> power, and violent <HI>impressions,</HI> even on those that both <HI>commissionate</HI> them, and re∣compence them.</P>
<P>They are Iron Heads, Brazen Faces, and Stony Hearts, who crye, that <HI>Might</HI> gives <HI>Right;</HI> And all <HI>power is of God,</HI> (though un∣justly gotten, and so used <HI>against the Word of God,</HI> and the <HI>Laws of the Land:</HI> such a <HI>com∣mission</HI> the <HI>Devil</HI> may <HI>boast of,</HI> as well as any evil <HI>doers,</HI> but little to the comfort of either: when mens <HI>will</HI> is their onely <HI>warrant</HI> in Law, and sad <HI>successes</HI> their onely <HI>security</HI> in <HI>Con∣science;</HI> when Souldiers make <HI>their backs</HI> and <HI>bellies</HI> the <HI>Commonwealth,</HI> putting their <HI>Interest</HI> of <HI>pay</HI> and <HI>power</HI> into the ballance against all others, when they are but as the <HI>dust</HI> of the <HI>ballance</HI> to the weight of the Nation, for numberand estates. When men of War know not the way of <HI>peace,</HI> but onely to avoid it, seeking to make themselves <HI>necessary</HI> by keep∣ing the <HI>wounds</HI> open, and the sores <HI>raw</HI> of a <HI>Nation;</HI> pleading <HI>necessity</HI> and native Liberty, and I know not what <HI>Good Old Cause,</HI> or <HI>Meta∣physical</HI> godly interests, unknown <HI>to our Lawer</HI> or <HI>fore-fathers;</HI> and it had been happy if we
<PB N="82" REF="51"/>
never had known them.</P>
<P><HI>Lastly,</HI> When Military men are <HI>injurious,</HI> ra∣pacious, and <HI>insolent, lovers</HI> of <HI>themselves more</HI> than of God or the <HI>Church</HI> or their <HI>Countrey;</HI> when they look more to their Guns, and Pistols than <HI>to God</HI> or godliness, to their swords than to his Word, and to the Riddles of <HI>Pro∣vidence</HI> more than the Rules of <HI>conscience:</HI> resolved to sacrifice the daughter of their peo∣ple, as <HI>Agamemnon</HI> did <HI>Iphigenia,</HI> or <HI>Jephta</HI> his, on the Altar of the Military interest.</P>
<P>These will be <HI>smart</HI> and <HI>chargeable beatens</HI> of the hurts <HI>of the</HI> daughter <HI>of their</HI> peo∣ple, when they shall be such as prepare <HI>Wan<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> against any that speak of Peace, when such as e∣steem the speedy <HI>healing</HI> of their Countrey, to the publick <HI>peace,</HI> to be their <HI>greatest hurt,</HI> when they grow so desperate, as they had as <HI>live be damned</HI> as fairly <HI>disbanded,</HI> though in order to the publick ease and tranquillity.</P>
<P>When as no good <HI>Souldier</HI> that either <HI>fears God</HI> or loves <HI>his Countrey,</HI> or reverences the <HI>Church,</HI> or hopes to save his own Soul, but will most seriously strive to <HI>avoid</HI> the latter, and most willingly submit to the former▪ without the sin of <HI>Rebellion</HI> or <HI>Mutiny,</HI> being content with his wages; and more, that his <HI>sharp work</HI> is at an end, and no more need of cutting and lancing, remembring that it is not mul∣titude, or <HI>Power,</HI> or <HI>Armies,</HI> or <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> that shall keep injurious and <HI>dissolute Souldier<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> from the vengeance of God, when they have deser∣ved
<PB N="83" REF="51"/>
it by such wicked Counsels and <HI>Actions,</HI> as cannot be carried on but with the Devils <HI>maxime</HI> (<HI>Scelera sceleribus tuenda</HI>) continued injuries and cruelties to the <HI>daughter of their people,</HI> to <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> to their <HI>brethren</HI> and <HI>Countrey</HI> men; yea, to their <HI>fathers</HI> and <HI>posterity.</HI></P>
<P>But our hope is, that <HI>God hath</HI> by his sore <HI>rebukes</HI> and <HI>defeats</HI> of some (who trusted too<NOTE PLACE="marg">The pre∣sent hope of better things from Soul∣diers.</NOTE> much in their <HI>swords</HI> &amp; <HI>spears,</HI> in <HI>their</HI> own <HI>Armes</HI> &amp; <HI>their horses legs</HI>) taught others more <HI>wisdome, justice</HI> and <HI>modesty;</HI> yea, and stirred up such a spirit of Christian <HI>valour, moderation</HI> and <HI>ho∣nour</HI> in some gallant Souldiers of more just Principles and nobler Spirits, that they will not rest till they have put <HI>the hurts</HI> of the <HI>daughter of their people</HI> (which are now <HI>chronick</HI> or <HI>inveterate,</HI> of many years <HI>conti∣nuance,</HI> and very <HI>deep,</HI> reaching from <HI>head</HI> to <HI>feet</HI>) into such a posture of <HI>healing,</HI> and into such <HI>healers</HI> hands as may be best <HI>able</HI> and <HI>ho∣nest;</HI> on which account as these <HI>Souldiers</HI> (who can do nothing against <HI>the truth</HI> and <HI>Law,</HI> a∣gainst <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State</HI> but for <HI>them</HI>) will de∣serve<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Cor. 13. 6<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></NOTE> great honour and <HI>rewards from the Na∣tion,</HI> and its Parliaments full and free: So people must <HI>blame themselves,</HI> if they chase for <HI>Healers</HI> or <HI>Physitians</HI> such men as are nei∣ther for <HI>wisdom</HI> and <HI>skill,</HI> nor for <HI>courage</HI> or <HI>conscience,</HI> nor for <HI>honesty</HI> or <HI>vertue,</HI> nor for good <HI>example</HI> or <HI>reputation,</HI> or yet for well∣<HI>gotten</HI> estates of any <HI>value,</HI> or <HI>publique interest;</HI> nor ever probable to heal others, since <HI>them∣selves</HI>
<PB N="84" REF="52"/>
are <HI>sick</HI> and <HI>sore</HI> either of <HI>fear</HI> and <HI>guilt,</HI> or of <HI>Schism</HI> and <HI>Faction,</HI> or of <HI>superstition</HI> and <HI>sacriledge,</HI> or of <HI>Rebellion</HI> and <HI>Anarchy,</HI> or of the itch of novelty, and <HI>mange</HI> of <HI>popula∣rity,</HI> or of the plague, of <HI>immorality</HI> and <HI>de∣bauchery:</HI> From such <HI>Healers,</HI> both Civil, Sacred, and Military, so <HI>unhealed,</HI> so <HI>unwholesome,</HI> so <HI>infectious,</HI> so destructive to Church and State, to Law and Gospel, to Justice and Religion, good <HI>Lord deliver the daughter of my people.</HI></P>
<P>5 <HI>Lastly,</HI> Not only these <HI>unskilful,</HI> or <HI>unfaith∣ful,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">5 The patient blamable for its own slight healing.</NOTE> or unwilling persons of <HI>publique influence,</HI> are blamable for <HI>not healing</HI> the <HI>hurts</HI> of a <HI>Na∣tion,</HI> when they have <HI>authority</HI> and <HI>opportunity</HI> as well as <HI>power:</HI> or for <HI>healing so slightly,</HI> that things are never the better, nay <HI>worse</HI> and <HI>worse.</HI> But further, there lyes no small <HI>sin</HI> and <HI>blame</HI> upon the Patient, the people or <HI>community;</HI> First, when they are not <HI>conscienciously careful,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 By not▪ carefully ap∣plying to good Physi∣tians.</NOTE> what <HI>Physitians</HI> or <HI>Surgeons</HI> they make choice of, and put themselves with their <HI>lives</HI> &amp; <HI>estates, liberties</HI> and <HI>lawes, bodies</HI> and <HI>souls</HI> into their hands, but adventure upon every pragmatique Emperick, and confident Undertaker.</P>
<P>Next, when this is done commendably (as truly I am prone to believe it was in the first <HI>Ele∣ctions</HI> of the long Parliament, if they could have quietly kept tog<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ther without tumul∣tuating factions, and fatal divisions) for people then not to <HI>acquiesce</HI> (as they ought under God) in their skill and honesty, onely following them with such modest
<PB N="85" REF="52"/>
<HI>Petitions,</HI> as are necessary, and such complaints as are comely: also with their prayers to <HI>God</HI> for a <HI>blessing.</HI> But for the populacy, then to <HI>cluck</HI> into <HI>parties</HI> and conspiracies, according<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 By popu∣lar conspira∣cies against them.</NOTE> to the cunning of some Agitators for novelty, and factors for troubles, then to break out into <HI>tu∣multuary rudenesses</HI> and <HI>seditious menaces,</HI> and at last to become dictators to their Physitians, and like <HI>gonty feet</HI> to <HI>threaten</HI> the <HI>head</HI> and <HI>shoul∣ders</HI> and <HI>hands,</HI> if they be not cured of their an∣guish after their own fancy, not after the <HI>Rules</HI> of <HI>Art</HI> and <HI>Law</HI> of <HI>Health:</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> These are so far from being Healers, that they are the greatest hinderers of their own and others publique health in the world; yea, the venome and acrimony of these <HI>fretting</HI> and <HI>turbulent humors,</HI> sub<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>idy <HI>diffused</HI> among the divided <HI>vulgar,</HI> and by their means re-infused into the <HI>publique hurts</HI> and real grievances, cannot but strangly increase the <HI>malignity</HI> of distempers throughout the<NOTE PLACE="marg">The danger of popular distempers.</NOTE> <HI>whole habit of the body;</HI> which <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>pesti∣lent</HI> and <HI>depraved</HI> state of the <HI>generality</HI> of the <HI>people,</HI> divided and distracted (like <HI>Demoni∣acks,</HI> or possessed) with <HI>fears</HI> and jealousies, with envies and hatred, with hopes, and other <HI>unreasonable passions,</HI> is much harde<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o be <HI>c<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣red,</HI> and more dangerous to the publique than the <HI>disaffection</HI> or <HI>inflammation;</HI> the <HI>discontent</HI> or <HI>ambition</HI> of any one part <HI>of the body,</HI> which is easily corrected or counter-ballanced with the <HI>Antid<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te,</HI> as it were of all <HI>other sound parts,</HI> which are far <HI>the major number.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="86" REF="53"/>When therefore a <HI>s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ok Nation</HI> hath done<NOTE PLACE="marg">Peoples due regard and submission to their right Physicians, full and free Parliaments.</NOTE> its <HI>duty</HI> in the choice of its <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ealers▪</HI> The way is to ass<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> the <HI>Honor</HI> and <HI>Authority</HI> of those orderly Physicians, not to suffer any intruding <HI>Empyricks,</HI> or extruding <HI>Mounte∣banks,</HI> by fraud or force to drive these away, that <HI>way</HI> may be made for their <HI>cruel activity</HI> and <HI>unsatiable gain;</HI> It will prove an <HI>endless</HI> and <HI>costly cure,</HI> which permits it self to every one that hath a minde to be tampering? The best way is, <HI>patiently</HI> to <HI>submit</HI> to their own Parliamentary choice, and to Gods dispen∣sation by their means: In this way there is hope, if people can be still, they may see the <HI>Salvation</HI> of God: <HI>Patients</HI> will make mad work if they may controle and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>dgel their <HI>Physitians.</HI></P>
<P>Although, it is possible that the crying sins<NOTE PLACE="marg">Some sins may keep the hurts of a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣cur<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>.</NOTE> committed in a Nation may be such that no <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> means can cure its sores, and ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ms; especially, if the <HI>noblest,</HI> and most <HI>vital</HI> parts of the body being cut off, or grievously w<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ded, there be a clamor of blood un∣justly <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ied, crying to heaven for vengeance; which vengeance if a <HI>Nation</HI> will hope to <HI>escape,</HI> and be healed, they must be sure not to <HI>ad<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pt</HI> the sin by <HI>after <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> or <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>;</HI> But rather so publickly to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> in <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pentance,</HI> as it may not be imputed to the whole Nation, and then Posterity▪ As the desp<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> His <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lood be upon<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> 27. 25.</NOTE> us and our childre<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, in the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> christs being
<PB N="87" REF="53"/>
put to death, by envy and faction; by popular clamors, &amp; State policies, when against all <HI>justice of God and man,</HI> yea, against the <HI>s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce</HI> and consci∣ence of <HI>Pilate,</HI> none of the <HI>juste<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> judges,</HI> he was condemned to dye, to gratifie a <HI>popular</HI> and <HI>military importunity;</HI> to which some <HI>Scribe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> and <HI>Pharises, Hypocrites,</HI> together with some cove∣tous and ambitious Priests, had exalted the cre∣du<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s and cruel <HI>common people,</HI> who are pron<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> in the Tragick executions, and <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> of their <HI>betters</HI> and <HI>Superiours;</HI> a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a kinde of victory over the others greatness, and a levelling of eminent honor to their own meanuess and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eness.</P>
<P>6. But, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t is now time for me, in order, to give way<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Part.</HI> 6. The true method of sound <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ealing.</HI></NOTE> to the pains of my <HI>learn'd,</HI> and <HI>reverend Success<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</HI> and to avoid the <HI>tyring</HI> of your patience, at the <HI>first Stage,</HI> when you are to g<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a <HI>second▪</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> is time (I say) for me to bring up the <HI>Ro<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</HI> and to present you in the <HI>Sixth particular,</HI> with the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>andi methodus,</HI> the <HI>true method of publick</HI> cures, of healing the <HI>hurts</HI> of the <HI>Da<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ghte<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of my people,</HI> in <HI>Church or State.</HI></P>
<P>For the <HI>precipitan<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, preposterous,</HI> or <HI>presumpte∣ous</HI> neglect of which, these <HI>Medieasters</HI> are here blamed, reproached, and threatned by the <HI>Spir<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> of God;</HI> with whose <HI>Phila<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>thropy</HI> (as with <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> good man) that <HI>politick</HI> and indeed pio<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> (be∣cause <HI>charitable maxime</HI> beares s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y; <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>suprem<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> l<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>x,</HI> The <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="88" REF="54"/>
in all its integral members, and essential parts, as compacted by the <HI>constitution</HI> and order of the publick <HI>polity,</HI> is the <HI>supream Law,</HI> rule, measure, and end of all just <HI>Councels</HI> and honest <HI>actions,</HI> which aym at the health or healing of a <HI>Nation.</HI></P>
<P>As <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Beauty is the due <HI>proportion of parts,</HI> with <HI>decent colour;</HI> So <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>Health</HI> cousists (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> in the <HI>harmony, and orderly constitution of all the humors,</HI> and <HI>parts</HI> of the <HI>body;</HI> That nothing necessary for the well being of the <HI>whole</HI> be wanting; That all grand <HI>defects</HI> be supplyed: That what is weak be <HI>strengthened,</HI> what is <HI>dislocated</HI> be restored to its place; That there be no <HI>dividing</HI> of what should be <HI>united:</HI> That, what is divided be gently <HI>closed,</HI> and <HI>composed;</HI> That there be no such <HI>redundancy,</HI> or overgrowing of any humor or tumor in any <HI>p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>,</HI> as to <HI>rob</HI> and <HI>weaken</HI> others; or to swell and exceed in themselves; or to deform and inflame the <HI>whole.</HI></P>
<P>In brief, the true and safe method of healing effectually the hurt of the daughter of my people, is,</P>
<P>1. <HI>Medicos optimos accersendo,</HI> By calling to her<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 By putting themselves into the hands of good Physicians, able and honest.</NOTE> help wise and worthy <HI>Physicians,</HI> (as I have formerly touched); men of skill and experience, of Honesty and Ability, of honor and conscience, who prize a publick <HI>Good Work</HI> above any <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>;</HI> and think it the highest <HI>temporal reward,</HI> to do their country <HI>good,</HI> in which they serve their <HI>God,</HI> and their <HI>Saviour,</HI> the Church and State.
<PB N="89" REF="54"/>
they must be Physitians that are not by much <HI>study and practice</HI> run out to <HI>Atheism</HI> (as some corn in <HI>lasty ground</HI> doth to straw and halm) but such as know what belongs to (<HI>Religio medici</HI>) the piety of a Christian, as well as the mystery of a Physitian; my meaning is, people must take special care in their <HI>choice of Parliament-men,</HI> that they be not <HI>Mechanick,</HI> or <HI>Mercenary,</HI> or <HI>Military</HI> ob∣truders of themselves, who have much to get and l<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tle to lose <HI>by troubles,</HI> whose fortunes and estates must be vampt and mended by their practice upon the Church and State; But such Gentlemen of quality and repute, for <HI>wel-gotten and wel-used estates,</HI> that they may deserve to be esteemed <HI>Heads and Fathers of their Tribes,</HI> and not the Tails or <HI>Posteriors,</HI> as the Scripture speaks to the reproach of some publick persons; Such in whom the Country may have sufficient caution and se∣curity for their love of Justice, Order, and Peace, by what they have to venture and lose in tumults, wars and oppressions: Commonly desperate minds attend desperate fortunes; and the motto of such is <HI>Quocunque modo rem,</HI> and <HI>oportet ha∣bere.</HI> The (<HI>multis utile bellum</HI>) hoped advanta∣ges, (as <HI>Lucan</HI> observes in the <HI>Cesaria<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> and <HI>Salust</HI> in the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> and <HI>Appian</HI> in the other Civil Wars) is the spark, fewel and bellows for the most part to civil perturbations; private not publique interests are usually looked at. For how can it be that the full and sound parts of the body Poli∣tique should hope to mend their condition by war, any more than men that are well, and not de<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣rant
<PB N="90" REF="55"/>
or <HI>raving in a Feavor</HI> and <HI>madness</HI> should by bruising, and beating, and cutting, and wound∣ing themselves and all that are near them, ex∣pect to make themselves more strong, or more comely.</P>
<P>§. 2. When the Patient hath done himself so much right as to get good <HI>Physitians,</HI> able and honest, for the publique care:</P>
<P>Their work is, First, <HI>Morbum decernere, &amp;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">The Physitians right discern∣ing the disease and throughly searching the wounds.</NOTE> <HI>vulnera, perserutari,</HI> to find out the true disease▪ to <HI>search</HI> the wounds througly, and impartially, yet with as little <HI>pain and disorder to the Patient</HI> as may be, with a clear and judicious eye, with a gentle but faithful hand, with a tender, but honest <HI>heart;</HI> neither Physitians <HI>passion,</HI> nor <HI>com∣passion,</HI> must divert them from doing their duty.</P>
<P>§. It is the first step, and a good advance to health, to know truly what the hurts and disease is; herein to be only <HI>conjectural, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> over-confident,</HI> or <HI>fearful,</HI> or <HI>perfunctory,</HI> or <HI>palliating,</HI> or complying, not daring to search and <HI>discover</HI> the (<HI>pudenda vulne∣ra</HI>) shameful wounds, and (<HI>lethales morbos</HI>) <HI>deadly diseases,</HI> which are discerned in the Pati∣ent, but with <HI>smiles,</HI> and fair <HI>words,</HI> with heal∣ing questions, with <HI>Physical</HI> or <HI>Anatomical lect∣ures</HI> about <HI>Government,</HI> as with lingering <HI>leni∣tives,</HI> and petty <HI>cordials,</HI> to supple and skin <HI>them over,</HI> to silence and smother them, with crying <HI>peace, peace,</HI> till we have done our work, which is to undo you and all men but our selves; or for State Physitians, so to regard by a super∣politick
<PB N="91" REF="55"/>
<HI>policy,</HI> the several partial novel and <HI>pre∣tended interests,</HI> that have been or are on foot, as to take in among others, even that of the very <HI>disease,</HI> as if it were to be <HI>considered</HI> other ways than to be cured, as if it must be continued, tolerated and indulged, yea and fed as a Wolf or Cancer, in the body or brest, with good nourishment, least it <HI>prey upon the whole body.</HI></P>
<P>§. This is for <HI>Physitians</HI> to be <HI>afraid,</HI> and<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of faintheart∣ed, foolish, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alse and flat∣tering Physiti∣ans.</NOTE> <HI>overawed</HI> by the <HI>Malignancy,</HI> and <HI>predominancy</HI> of the disease; at this rate, (<HI>Grex totus in agris, Unius scabie perit &amp; porrigine porci</HI>) the whole herd, or flock must be <HI>infected;</HI> the <HI>patient</HI> will be like <HI>Gehazi,</HI> condemned to an eternal <HI>plague</HI> and <HI>Leprosie</HI> of civil dissentions and oppessions, of war, and its black consequences. Physitians after this course must turn very fools, and become <HI>parasites</HI> to <HI>putrefactions;</HI> if they dare not own, or cannot attaque either the sourse and head of the disease, or the streams and potency of it, what do they meet and sit and consult (or rather <HI>constult</HI>) toge∣ther? they had as good cast their caps, as thus lay their heads together, when they have no mind to do the work, nor courage to go through with the cure.</P>
<P>§. Not but that all great and noble cures (not miraculous) are the children of time and discretion; for a while the sons of <HI>Zerviah</HI> were too hard for <HI>David;</HI> and <HI>Solomon</HI> did not those acts of <HI>remarka∣ble Justice</HI> against <HI>Joabs,</HI> and <HI>Shi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eis,</HI> and <HI>Abiathars</HI> factious Priests, insolent Soldiers, and cursed cur∣sers,
<PB N="92" REF="56"/>
until the Kingdom was strengthned in his hand; but this is certain, as Christ did not raise to life <HI>Jarus</HI> his daughter <HI>till the Minstrils were all</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth. 9. 23.</NOTE> <HI>turned out;</HI> So nor can <HI>the daughter of my people</HI> be <HI>recovered to firm and sure health,</HI> till all pre∣tended <HI>Civil Interests</HI> are by degrees, either <HI>satisfi∣ed, if just,</HI> or <HI>crushed, quashed</HI> and <HI>removed,</HI> if not <HI>consistent with our Reformed Religion,</HI> also with the <HI>Laws of the Land,</HI> and the <HI>fundamentals of our excellent Government,</HI> which are the true <HI>princi∣ples of publique health;</HI> and till all Religious or Ecclesiastical pretended <HI>Interests</HI> are so tried and <HI>examined (for many say they are Jews that are not,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 2. 9.</NOTE> and cry up their new <HI>Church ways;</HI> when they may be but <HI>factors for the Synagogue of Satan;</HI> vapor∣ing of <HI>Christ,</HI> and the <HI>Spirit,</HI> when they are <HI>Anti∣christs,</HI> and full of <HI>unclean spirits</HI>) till I say, all these, on all hands be faithfully reduced and sub∣jected to the grand <HI>interest of God, and of our Lord Jesus Christ,</HI> which consists in Justice and true Religion: The measure of the first is our Laws enacted in <HI>full and free Parliaments:</HI> The rule of the second are clear truths of Scripture, which set forth the (<HI>facienda</HI>) morals necessary to be <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>one by all to all men; the (<HI>credenda</HI>) myste∣ries of Faith necessary to be believed, also the spe∣cial practiques of Christian Piety and Charity, of Worship and good works, which are to be exer∣cised decently and in order by all Christians in publick as well as private: Till these be setled<NOTE PLACE="marg">Healing of the Church and Religion.</NOTE> there is no hope of soundness or health in Church or State.</P>
<P><PB N="93" REF="56"/>§. Now of these things which properly tend<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lev. 13, &amp; 14.</NOTE> to the <HI>health of the Church,</HI> and the right consti∣tution of Religion in piety and polity, for Do∣ctrine, Worship, Discipline and Government, I humbly conceive (as the Priests of old were by God appointed to be Judge and Physitian of the plague of <HI>Leprofie</HI>) the <HI>Clergie</HI> or <HI>Evangelical Mi∣nistry</HI> are fittest men to discern the distempers, and to <HI>prepare</HI> those <HI>plaisters</HI> or <HI>applications,</HI> which by the <HI>sanction</HI> of the civil <HI>Magistrate,</HI> may best be laid to the <HI>Patient,</HI> or the <HI>parts affected.</HI></P>
<P>§. And here for any part to plead that it may<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of scandalous toleration in matter<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of Re∣ligion.</NOTE> have liberty or toleration for that, which by pub∣lique advice, and upon due search is found to be such as is prone to endanger, or disorder, and in∣fect the <HI>whole body</HI> with that itch, and scab, or scalling humor, which that part pleaseth it self to scratch and scatter, this is such a <HI>presumptuous mo∣tion</HI> as ought not to be made by any Patient, nor granted by any Physitians, who have either justice or charity for the (<HI>salus publica</HI>) common welfare▪ none inclining to those sad indulgences but they who have neither <HI>ability</HI> nor <HI>authority</HI> to cure the hurt and disease; but must to their shame cry out (<HI>Morbus superat artem, &amp; Chyr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rg<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> vulnus</HI>) the ill humors are too <HI>strong</HI> for the best <HI>Physiti∣ans,</HI> and the ulcers conquer the <HI>Chyrurgeons▪</HI> Truly in such deplorable cases, where not the disease, but the Physitians are desperate, as in the raging plague, the way is to shut up the doors of the Physitians Colledge, and the Chyrurgeons Hall, and write upon them in behalf of Church and State (<HI>Miserere Domine</HI>) <HI>Lord have merey <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> and
<PB N="94" REF="57"/>
for nothing remains in so deplored and desperate cases, where Healers cannot or will not do their work; but the <HI>prayers</HI> and <HI>patience</HI> of the poor <HI>Patient, the miserable daughter of my people;</HI> as in a State where either the disease is (<HI>contemptor ar∣tis</HI>) a <HI>despiser of all remedies;</HI> or the <HI>Patient</HI> is of nothing more impatient than to be well cured; or the Physitians are of nothing more afraid than to make too speedy and sincere a cure.</P>
<P>Thirdly, But if <HI>Physitians</HI> of the <HI>daughter of</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">The practice o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sincere and speedy healing</NOTE> <HI>my people</HI> are so <HI>blessed of God,</HI> and <HI>encouraged</HI> by the Patient, that they may <HI>freely</HI> and do <HI>se∣riously</HI> apply to their <HI>work of publique healing;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. To purge a. way what is noysom.</NOTE> they have but these main things to do. 1. <HI>Noxia &amp; morbifica purgare;</HI> discreetly to facilitate, and constantly to follow the purging away of the most <HI>peccant</HI> and pestilent humors, which either are the main cause, occasion, or increase and conti∣nuers of the hurt and disease: Here every pre∣sumptuous and <HI>prevalent sin,</HI> which is most <HI>spread among the people,</HI> is to be <HI>repressed by good Laws,</HI> and the <HI>due execution</HI> of them; when sins grow <HI>epidemical,</HI> and by the <HI>multitude of com∣miters</HI> either threaten or plead their <HI>impunity,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psa. 119 126</NOTE> they <HI>provoke God to punish</HI> what <HI>man does not;</HI> he takes the matter into his own hand, when his <HI>Laws Moral</HI> and <HI>Evangelical</HI> are openly and impu∣dently broken.</P>
<P>§. Here it were good for <HI>Physitians</HI> of Church and State, in extraordinary diseases, <HI>long distem∣pers,</HI> and obstinate <HI>hurts,</HI> admitting no cure, such (as those of the <HI>daughter of our people</HI>) are to make accurate search (as <HI>Joshua,</HI> and <HI>David,</HI> and
<PB N="95" REF="57"/>
the <HI>Mariners</HI> in <HI>Jonah</HI> did) for what special cur∣sed thing, or <HI>crying sins</HI> sake all this evill, this long storm is come on us, and still so continues for <HI>many years,</HI> as if there were no peace or calm to be expected; no effectual Physician or cure to be had, till those Vipers teeth, or Serpents stings be pulled out; till then no <HI>balm in Gilead</HI> will do us good.</P>
<P>§. Doubtless every honest <HI>Englishman</HI> and <HI>good Christian</HI> would be glad of <HI>health</HI> and <HI>peace to Church</HI> and <HI>State;</HI> whence then are our so dread∣ful wounds, so raging humors, and our so <HI>dila∣tory healing?</HI> We must needs conclude (as he did<NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth 13. 28.</NOTE> of the <HI>Tares</HI> (<HI>inimicus homo fecit</HI>) an enemy hath done, begun, or augmented this evil: Some whose bloody designs, and sacrilegious interests (as <HI>Achans</HI> and <HI>Sauls</HI>) are contrary to the Word of God among us, and the vows or oathes of God upon us; contrary to the principles of the Prote∣stant and Reformed Religion, which once so <HI>flourished in England,</HI> and contrary to the peace, honor and freedom of this Nation, which some foraign and domestick Policies would <HI>bring down</HI> as a <HI>Dromedary</HI> on <HI>its knees,</HI> that it might at length, take upon his back the <HI>burthen</HI> of foraign tyranny and usurpation, of <HI>Romish Trumpery and superstition.</HI></P>
<P>§. Hence no doubt are our distempers so hor∣ribly inflamed, our <HI>healing</HI> so cruelly protracted, our Physitians so shamefully baffled, our body so wofully maimed; Hence our wounds are made so <HI>deep,</HI> and our abscissions so <HI>desperate,</HI> that (ac∣cording to <HI>Achitophels</HI> counsel, to make the <HI>breach irreconcilable</HI> between <HI>Absolom</HI> and <HI>David</HI>) some things have been done to so high a rage
<PB N="90" REF="58"/>
and <HI>exorbitant indignities,</HI> and so <HI>intolerable in∣juries,</HI> without any authority from God or man, that they are not capable of full reparation, nor yet patient (hitherto) to bear such a measure of publick repentance or reparation, as are not on∣ly most just but most necessary for the appeasing Gods wrath, and for the perfect healing of the Nation, without which there can be no soundness of <HI>constitution,</HI> no <HI>compleatness of parts,</HI> no <HI>decen∣cy of motion</HI> in the <HI>Body Politick</HI> or <HI>Ecclesi∣astick. Nor will the wrath of God be turned away, but his hand stretched out still.</HI></P>
<P>§. Here not only Justice must be so done, to take away the <HI>guilt</HI> and curse from the Nation of crying and notorious sins; but also such <HI>penitent deprecations,</HI> and <HI>compensations</HI> as (are possible, and) may best expiate those horrid sins, which are and ever will be (while unrepented, uncorrected, and uncured) the <HI>maim</HI> and <HI>ulcer,</HI> the <HI>sin</HI> and <HI>shame,</HI> the <HI>defect</HI> and <HI>deformity;</HI> yea, the <HI>con∣sumption</HI> and <HI>death</HI> at last of the <HI>daughter of my people:</HI> For tragical Judgements sooner or later follow tragical sins; and <HI>presumptions</HI> bring a a Nation to <HI>consumptions; England</HI> will never be it self, till it doth it self this right, both in <HI>ho∣nor</HI> and <HI>conscience,</HI> in <HI>Reason of State,</HI> and for the repute of the <HI>Reformed Religion;</HI> from whose face such black and bloody <HI>stains</HI> must be washed if ever she will appear lovely to the world, and not as the Whore of <HI>Babylon,</HI> who was drunk as well as besmeared with blood. All the inventi∣ons and projects of making supplies and amends by some other Commonwealth way, is no better
<PB N="97" REF="58"/>
than getting a wooden leg, or hands of clouts, instead of such as are <HI>natural;</HI> or as <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bolster of g<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ats hair</HI> instead of <HI>David:</HI> The body cannot have ease or orderly <HI>motion,</HI> or <HI>beauty</HI> and <HI>com∣plexion,</HI> till every part is restored to its <HI>place, of∣fice</HI> and <HI>proportion.</HI></P>
<P>2. When the <HI>venom</HI> and core of the <HI>main di∣stempers</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2. To apply such who e<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om medicines as are tried and p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oper.</NOTE> is removed, the next work of a wise Physitian and Chyrurgeon, is, <HI>Sana Medicamina applicare,</HI> to follow the Patient with wholesom <HI>me∣dicaments,</HI> as are (1) <HI>probata,</HI> approved upon the file of long experience, (2) <HI>propria &amp; specifica,</HI> as <HI>apt, proper,</HI> and <HI>specifick,</HI> as can be had, con∣sidering the <HI>genius</HI> and <HI>constitution</HI> of the Patient; also the original, continuance and progress of the disease; cures are by contraries; those medi∣cines<NOTE PLACE="marg">M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dels of new Govern∣ments <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>heal not.</NOTE> will most certainly help, which most encounter the <HI>principal causes</HI> of our maine dis∣ease; and are proper antidotes, against the malignity of our sores.</P>
<P>§. It is but the capricious and <HI>ridiculous conceit</HI> of some fine men who want employment, to send this now languishing <HI>State of England,</HI> and the other two adjacent, antient and united King∣domes, to <HI>Mars his hill</HI> in <HI>Athens,</HI> or to the <HI>Lacedemonian Sparta,</HI> or to the Roman <HI>Capitol,</HI> or to the <HI>Venetian Arsenal,</HI> or to the <HI>State-house</HI> of the <HI>low Countries,</HI> and so to send the Church to <HI>Geneva, Edinbrough,</HI> or <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> as if we were Churches or Nations of yesterday, in our bibs and swadling clouts, to be dandled in the laps of such dry nurses, and this in order (for sooth) to learn some unwonted models of <HI>civil</HI>
<PB N="98" REF="59"/>
and <HI>Ecclesiastical Government,</HI> which like new <HI>garments</HI> will hardly fit, for they will be either uneasie because too <HI>straight,</HI> or <HI>unhansome</HI> be∣cause too <HI>loose.</HI></P>
<P>§. Doubtless in Governments, that Scripture Proverb of <HI>Wine</HI> holds true, <HI>the elder is the bet∣ter,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 29.</NOTE> if it have <HI>not lost its spirits,</HI> especially when not onely time and use, but great wisdome had proportioned it to the true interests of the Nati∣on, and of all estates in it, which follow much the <HI>genius</HI> of the people, if they be either <HI>soft, slavish</HI> and <HI>pesantly,</HI> as in some countrys,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Government must fit the genius of peo∣ple.</NOTE> or robust, manly, and generous, as in <HI>England;</HI> the first will easily <HI>croutch</HI> under any burthen, and <HI>truckle</HI> under any prevalent power; the second is hardly contained in <HI>any bounds</HI> but those that are <HI>Soveragine,</HI> and <HI>Imperial,</HI> by way of <HI>monar∣chical,</HI> yet <HI>legal Majesty,</HI> which having something in it neerer the <HI>Divine Idea,</HI> than any other way of Government, by the perfection of wis∣dome guiding power, and power assisting wis∣dome, is onely fit to govern those <HI>Nations,</HI> whose <HI>high spirits</HI> are impatient to be <HI>ridden</HI> by their <HI>equals,</HI> much more▪to have their <HI>inferi∣ours</HI> to <HI>become</HI> not only their rivals, but superi∣ours. When the <HI>Cappadocians</HI> had leave to be a <HI>Province,</HI> or popular <HI>State, under</HI> the <HI>Roman Empire,</HI> they refused the <HI>freedome,</HI> and <HI>craved</HI> the favour of having a <HI>King to rule them,</HI> as they ever had, <HI>time out of mind,</HI> professing the temper of the people was such, that they would not be subject to any, but those in whom <HI>Majesty</HI> was so <HI>concentred, by the Laws</HI> and <HI>customs of the</HI>
<PB N="99" REF="59"/>
<HI>Nation,</HI> that they could without shame and <HI>dis∣dain,</HI> pay an <HI>homage</HI> as subjects to them.</P>
<P>§. Herein experience hath been, and will be<NOTE PLACE="marg">Novel essays of Gōvern∣ment dange∣rous.</NOTE> our teacher; but then it will be and hath been as <HI>Hippocrates</HI> begins his <HI>Aphorisms,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, a costly, painful difficult and dangerous expe∣riment, and if at last it do not fit the Genius temper and desire of these <HI>Nations,</HI> so as to ease them of their <HI>terrors</HI> and vast charges of civil War, to <HI>free</HI> them of the <HI>fear of Enemies</HI> at home, and abroad, to settle them in such <HI>peace</HI> and <HI>plen∣ty,</HI> as many yet remember they injoyed before the <HI>flood</HI> of our civil wars, to open the obstructions of <HI>trade,</HI> and those veins of industry, by which the body is <HI>maintained,</HI> by the secret <HI>circulation of commerce,</HI> as of the blood; if all these <HI>Symp∣tomes, Concomitants,</HI> or effects of <HI>health,</HI> do not follow the <HI>essayes</HI> of <HI>new formes</HI> of <HI>Govern∣ment,</HI> alas what do we all the while, but keep the <HI>daughter of our people upon the rack of paine and expence,</HI> using a kind of a <HI>State Strappado,</HI> by which to bring the armes to hang <HI>backwards,</HI> rather than forwards, so as they can neither lift up themselves to <HI>their head,</HI> nor yet <HI>defend</HI> and help the body or <HI>themselves,</HI> so by a <HI>dread∣ful convulsion,</HI> to bring all things of antient <HI>order, honor,</HI> and <HI>beauty</HI> in the nation, to the <HI>distractions</HI> and <HI>deformities,</HI> which must needs attend such <HI>novel∣ties</HI> as are not proper for the <HI>publique,</HI> nor <HI>practica∣ble</HI> without <HI>continued force,</HI> and <HI>endless charge.</HI></P>
<P>3. Their healing medicines must be <HI>plenaria, &amp;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">To apply Ca∣tholic<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d compleating medicines.</NOTE> <HI>Catholica,</HI> such as may in time do the work <HI>com∣pleatly,</HI> yet with <HI>leisure</HI> and discretion (For
<PB N="100" REF="60"/>
<HI>momentary cures,</HI> are onely <HI>miraculous,</HI>) So as carefully to preserve the good <HI>spirits</HI> und <HI>humors,</HI> to strengthen the sound parts yet remaining, to follow the grand crises of the disease, and the <HI>indications</HI> of <HI>health,</HI> which way evil humors are easiest discussed; breathed out, or purged, still conserving the two main <HI>principles, pillars,</HI> and <HI>supports</HI> of <HI>health, life</HI> and <HI>subsistence</HI> in the body politique, the <HI>radicale humidum</HI> (as I call it)<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 144. 14</NOTE> which is <HI>plenty,</HI> by <HI>trade and industry,</HI> that there be no crying out, nor <HI>complaining,</HI> by those whose mouths cannot <HI>eat if their hands be idle.</HI> 2. That <HI>calidum radicale,</HI> the sacred fire, or celestial flame, which <HI>Prometheus</HI> is said to have kindled in <HI>mankind,</HI> which shines in reason and religion, in Justice by good <HI>Laws</HI> well execu∣ted by Magistrates, and in <HI>devotion</HI> by the holy publique worship of God, solemnly dis∣charged by able and autoritative Ministers; both which are the grand designes of good <HI>learning,</HI> which is the <HI>souls school</HI> for <HI>improvement</HI> and education, during its minority or absence from its <HI>Fathers house,</HI> till it comes to vision and frui∣tion, which sets it beyond all learning, but that of the <HI>Fathers</HI> glorious example.</P>
<P>§. No civil laws can be <HI>wholesome</HI> for the pub∣lique which do <HI>enterfeer</HI> with true <HI>Religion;</HI> which either <HI>rob God,</HI> or his <HI>Church,</HI> or his <HI>Vice∣gerents,</HI> and <HI>Ministers,</HI> or his <HI>poor,</HI> of what is <HI>their due;</HI> nor can any <HI>Ecclesiastical laws</HI> be <HI>healthful,</HI> which cross the civil <HI>laws,</HI> and authority, so, as to bring in <HI>licentionsness, injuriousness, rebel∣lion,</HI> or any thing that is for <HI>Doctrine</HI> fanatick,
<PB N="101" REF="60"/>
or for <HI>practice</HI> injust and <HI>immoral,</HI> all which like <HI>poysonons</HI> touchings, or <HI>unwholesome feedings,</HI> are destructive to the <HI>publique health.</HI></P>
<P>§. The perfect healing of the <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>Reli∣gion,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Of Ecclesiasti∣cal Synods to heal a Church.</NOTE> as <HI>Christian</HI> and <HI>reformed</HI> (whose divisions, hurts and deformities are many) will hardly be done without <HI>calling</HI> those <HI>spiritual Physitians</HI> to∣gether, after the primitive pattern in <HI>Ecclesiasti∣cal Synods</HI> or <HI>National Councils,</HI> who are best skil∣led<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts 15. 6</NOTE> in the true state of health, in the nature of the diseases, and in the <HI>aptest remedies,</HI> which in Re∣ligion ought to be very <HI>humane</HI> and <HI>charitable,</HI> convincing with <HI>meekness of wisdom,</HI> and <HI>healing</HI> as much by <HI>prayers</HI> and <HI>tears</HI> as by <HI>reasonings</HI> and <HI>perswasions.</HI> I confess I cannot see how a Com∣mittee of Parliament for <HI>Religion</HI> is proper for this work, further than to be <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; the promo∣ters of it, when put into fit hands of able Ministers.</P>
<P>§. Herein, the first grand work is to bring us to be again one National Church; from which ho∣nor and happiness we fell as <HI>Lucifer</HI> from heaven, when some mens <HI>ambition</HI> affected to make the chief Magistrate of a <HI>Commonwealth</HI> to be <HI>simi∣lis al<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>issimo,</HI> as high as the <HI>highest</HI> in three King∣doms, which unity of this Church, those have sought most subtilly to divide, whose <HI>interests</HI> and <HI>purposes</HI> was to destroy it; that by balancing of parties they might better keep up themselves, as dancers on the rope are wont to do. This re∣storing of the Church to its <HI>pristine unity,</HI> is to be done by such an <HI>harmony of Doctrine,</HI> as may be publickly owned and confessed, by such an <HI>uni∣form way of worship,</HI> as shall be publickly <HI>recom∣comended</HI>
<PB N="102" REF="61"/>
and <HI>eneouraged;</HI> by such an <HI>authoritative</HI> and <HI>orderly Church Government</HI> among <HI>Bishops, Presbyters</HI> and <HI>People,</HI> as may carry on the <HI>Discipline of the Church,</HI> for <HI>Ordination</HI> and <HI>Censure,</HI> with <HI>gravity</HI> and <HI>honor,</HI> with <HI>piety</HI> and <HI>charity,</HI> redee∣ming both <HI>holy things,</HI> and the <HI>Ministers</HI> of them, from that vulgar insolency and <HI>Plebeian contempt,</HI> under which they are fallen and have long lain, ei∣ther by their own <HI>indiscretion,</HI> levity and divisi∣ons; or by the <HI>petulaney, force,</HI> or <HI>fraud</HI> of o∣thers, whose aim is to have no <HI>Presbyters</HI> as well as no <HI>Bishops,</HI> yea and no <HI>Churches</HI> of the Reformed <HI>Religion.</HI></P>
<P>§. That lenitive of <HI>equanimity, forbearance,</HI> and <HI>moderation,</HI> in respect of consciencious <HI>Dissenters</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">charitable ration.</NOTE> from the <HI>publique consent, customs</HI> and <HI>constitutions</HI> in the <HI>Church</HI> (which <HI>Christian charity</HI> requires, and <HI>publique peace</HI> with safety may bear) will best be <HI>prepared</HI> and <HI>applied,</HI> when we fully see what is <HI>noxious, malicious</HI> and <HI>intolerable;</HI> what is only <HI>inconvenient,</HI> and <HI>imprudent,</HI> or <HI>infirm,</HI> and <HI>venial</HI> in mens opinions and pretensions; to be sure such a wise method may be used, and such a course taken, to have able <HI>Ministers,</HI> and <HI>honest Magistrates</HI> concur in their judgement and <HI>joynt endeavors,</HI> that the Justice of the one, and the gentleness of the other; the <HI>ability</HI> and <HI>sanctity</HI> of both in their places and performances, may be such, as shall render the <HI>established Religion</HI> so venerable and conspicuous as will in a few years draw all <HI>sober men</HI> to it, when they shall see no∣thing in it, but what is for the <HI>main conformable</HI> to <HI>Gods Word,</HI> and necessary either for the <HI>being</HI>
<PB N="103" REF="61"/>
or <HI>wel-being</HI> of Humane and Christian Societies.</P>
<P>§. As Civil, so Ecclesiastical hurts are best (that is,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Civil hurts healed by re∣course to the Laws.</NOTE> soonest, easiest &amp; surest healed) <HI>revertendo ad leges bonas &amp; antiquas</HI>) by returning (as the wounded Hart to <HI>Dictamnum</HI>) to those <HI>Laws</HI> and <HI>Canons</HI> w<SUP>ch</SUP> are not therefore (<HI>bonae quia antiquae;</HI> but therefore <HI>antiquae, quia bonae▪</HI> in which the <HI>aequum, &amp; unum, &amp; bonum</HI> make the <HI>vetustum</HI>) Their <HI>verity, equity and piety</HI> gave rise to their <HI>antiquity;</HI> and their <HI>anti∣quity</HI> gave <HI>reverence and solemnity</HI> to their <HI>equity</HI> or <HI>goodness;</HI> Tis certain, there can be no com∣pleat <HI>health</HI> in the body till every part, every <HI>limb,</HI> every <HI>vein,</HI> every <HI>vessel</HI> doth its <HI>Office</HI> in due time and place; irregularities must be <HI>recti∣fied, defects supplied,</HI> excesses repressed, <HI>ill humors purged,</HI> and all reduced by Law to good order.</P>
<P>§. A blessed work, and to be done with as<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of I ni ives and moderati∣n in healing</NOTE> much <HI>Moderation and gentleness</HI> as the <HI>fidelity</HI> of the cure will permit, and the <HI>spreading of the dis∣ease doth require;</HI> wherein many parts may by <HI>weakness</HI> or by <HI>nearness</HI> to the (<HI>fons morbi</HI>) the first peccant or ill <HI>affected part,</HI> have contracted sad <HI>distempers;</HI> which will easily be cured of their anguish if the <HI>evil neighborhood be mended:</HI> Here generous and gracious <HI>remissions</HI> are just and Christian, to <HI>misled multitudes,</HI> and to such whose <HI>penitent errors</HI> shew they were not of malice, but credulity and <HI>mistake,</HI> who are more zealous now <HI>for health,</HI> than ever they were to be de∣bauched and disordered, so much to their own and the publique <HI>affliction.</HI></P>
<P>§. Acts of pardon, <HI>Amnesty,</HI> or <HI>Oblivion,</HI> are<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts of Obli¦vion.</NOTE> excellent <HI>lenitives, (Publico bonotam publicae quam</HI>
<PB N="104" REF="62"/>
<HI>privatae simultates &amp; injuriae sunt condonandae,</HI> to pardon as well publique as private <HI>losses</HI> and <HI>inju∣ries</HI> to the publique peace, to interpret the in∣tent and meaning of either side to have been good, who persist <HI>not in evil;</HI> the <HI>zeal</HI> of some to maintain their <HI>Loyalty</HI> to the King, for which they thought they had the clearest <HI>commands of Gods Laws and mans;</HI> The <HI>zeal of others,</HI> to pre∣serve the <HI>lawful priviledges,</HI> and fixed authority <HI>of Parliaments,</HI> against any thing, that by violent overthrowing of those, must needs hazard the overthrow of all; possibly neither of these par∣ties might be so bad or blameable, as to the first intentions, but that they may easily be reconciled in the medium which both first professed to in∣tend, namely King and Parliament, setled laws and established Religion; if this had been kept to, the quarel had been soon ended in <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State;</HI> the misery was that by jealousies and misunderstandings, the passions and transports of both sides, might so overbear them, as to <HI>occasion</HI> those sad <HI>conflicts</HI> and <HI>consequences</HI> upon both, which neither of them at first intended, but <HI>deprecated</HI> and detested; mean <HI>time</HI> while humors were in <HI>motion,</HI> new and unexpected <HI>dis∣eases</HI> got head, under the name of interest of State, of liberty and common equity, which had no law, little reason or Religion.</P>
<P>§. So, between the <HI>Episcopal, Presbyterian,</HI> and <HI>Independent Parties,</HI> much of the <HI>acidness</HI> and <HI>sharpness</HI> of the <HI>humor</HI> would be allayed, if this <HI>Poltice</HI> of <HI>charitable</HI> censure and interpreta∣tion were applyed one all sides that the first
<PB N="105" REF="62"/>
did but aim to <HI>maintaine</HI> the order and <HI>eminency</HI> of presidential <HI>Episcopacy,</HI> which was so <HI>univer∣sal,</HI> so <HI>antient,</HI> so <HI>primitive,</HI> so <HI>apostolical,</HI> and so <HI>prosperous</HI> in the Church of Christ; the second designed onely to bring <HI>Episcopacy</HI> to such a pater∣nal <HI>temperament</HI> with <HI>Presbytery,</HI> that the whole <HI>Clergie of a Diocess,</HI> and the concerns <HI>of Religion,</HI> might not be exposed to one mans <HI>sole jurisdiction,</HI> without the such joynt <HI>counsel, consent</HI> and <HI>assistance</HI> of <HI>Ministers,</HI> as is safest for Bishops <HI>Presbyters,</HI> and <HI>People;</HI> the third of <HI>Independents'</HI> or <HI>Congregationists,</HI> which seemed to <HI>stickle</HI> for' the <HI>iuterests of people</HI> in <HI>religious transactions,</HI> where their <HI>souls</HI> are so much concerned, what <HI>Minister</HI> they have, and how both he and others of their <HI>congregation</HI> behave themselves, either to the edification and comfort, or the <HI>scandal</HI> and <HI>grief</HI> of that <HI>part</HI> or <HI>members</HI> of the <HI>Church,</HI> with which they actually <HI>congregate</HI> and <HI>communi∣cate.</HI> It seems but <HI>agreable</HI> to the <HI>ancient usage</HI> of the <HI>Churches of Christ,</HI> in St. <HI>Cyprians, Ter∣tullians,</HI> and <HI>Ireuaeus</HI> his time, that no publique <HI>transactions,</HI> much less <HI>impositions,</HI> touching <HI>Re∣ligion,</HI> should be made, without fairly aquain∣ting the Clergy and Christian people too with the <HI>grounds</HI> and <HI>reasons</HI> of <HI>them,</HI> that Church-govern∣ment, might not seem to be a <HI>tyranny,</HI> or an<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Pet. 53.</NOTE> <HI>arbitrary</HI> and <HI>absolute domineering</HI> over the faith and consciences of Christs flock, but a mutual and sweet <HI>conspiring</HI> of the <HI>Shepherds</HI> with the <HI>sheep,</HI> to make each other happy▪ in truth and love, by <HI>orderly authority,</HI> and due subordination.</P>
<P>§. I should be glad to see the <HI>beams of this can∣dor,</HI>
<PB N="106" REF="63"/>
this kindness, this charity, <HI>shine in all faces</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Charity and candor among Christians.</NOTE> from all sides, that the <HI>Shiboleths</HI> of different dialects and designes, the carnal and unhappy dis∣criminations of <HI>I am of Paul, I of Apollos,</HI> and <HI>I of Cephas,</HI> might be laid aside, by being all for and of Christ, who <HI>is not,</HI> and <HI>ought not,</HI> and<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 1. 12 and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, 3</NOTE> <HI>cannot, ether truly</HI> in <HI>himself, or comfortably</HI> as <HI>to any Christians and churches be divided;</HI> let all, like <HI>straight lines</HI> from the several points of the <HI>circumference,</HI> be drawn <HI>true</HI> to the <HI>centre</HI> of Gods <HI>glory,</HI> the <HI>publique peace,</HI> and the <HI>good of souls;</HI> no doubt we shall by meeting <HI>in those,</HI> come so nigh <HI>to each other,</HI> that all will rejoyce in the <HI>harmony</HI> and <HI>concurrence,</HI> who do not seek the <HI>ruine of this Church,</HI> and the <HI>reformed Religion;</HI> and indeed the <HI>differences</HI> of honest <HI>Protestants</HI> are but <HI>small,</HI> compared to the <HI>bonds</HI> of union in which they <HI>do agree,</HI> as to <HI>doctrinals, morals,</HI> and <HI>essentials;</HI> nor are we hard I hope to be <HI>recon∣ciled</HI> as to prudentials, if we could meet freely, debate soberly, and submit humbly to the pub∣lique votes and results of the Major part of <HI>Parliaments</HI> and <HI>Synods,</HI> without which submission, all <HI>counsels,</HI> and all government, depending upon <HI>suffrages,</HI> must needs be vaine, and <HI>dissolved</HI> either into Tyranny or Ataxy, as the learned <HI>Grotius</HI> observes, in his <HI>Batavick history, (Restat ut pauciores pluribus cedant; hoc uno stant populorum</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Lib. 17. p, 115▪</NOTE> <HI>imperia, aliter casura.)</HI></P>
<P>§. To conclude, let every one keep <HI>in Gods</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Follow holi∣ness, and peace will follow.</NOTE> <HI>way,</HI> which is the way of <HI>peace</HI> and <HI>holiness,</HI> of duty <HI>to God and man</HI> let good Christians en∣tertain good thoughts, and give good words to
<PB N="107" REF="63"/>
each other; good ayre conduceh much to <HI>reco∣very;</HI> uncharitable speeches, and sinful courses (which are but <HI>halitus Diaboli,</HI> the breath of the Divil, or the exhaltation of our own <HI>foul</HI> hearts, or the <HI>eructations</HI> of hell) render the very <HI>aire,</HI> in which men live <HI>unwholesome,</HI> and the very <HI>Se∣nates</HI> or <HI>Synods,</HI> where such men meet, grow infective by foul lungs and putid breaths.</P>
<P>§. Let us privately mourn over the <HI>daughter of</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mourn for sins</NOTE> <HI>our people</HI> for the hurts, which our sins have either first inflicted on her, or deserved for her, or <HI>festred</HI> and <HI>inflamed,</HI> or at least <HI>hindred</HI> from <HI>healing,</HI> by childish peevishness, or popular <HI>per∣tinacies,</HI> or <HI>Sinister designs,</HI> or <HI>politique jealou∣sies;</HI> lay these aside, the work of <HI>healing</HI> will go on; for not outward applications so much, as inward sound principles and honest perswasions do heal; as the outward <HI>plaisters</HI> and <HI>unguents</HI> or <HI>balsoms</HI> do not heal <HI>wounds</HI> by adding any matter to the <HI>part,</HI> or the <HI>whole,</HI> but <HI>healing</HI> flows from an <HI>internal native principle,</HI> so soon as the noxi∣ous <HI>humours</HI> are <HI>purged,</HI> and the <HI>proud</HI> or <HI>dead flesh removed,</HI> which hinder the closure of parts, and the <HI>digesture</HI> of good supplies.</P>
<P>§. Lastly let us in <HI>patience</HI> and <HI>prayers</HI> possess<NOTE PLACE="marg">Pray with pa∣tience.</NOTE> our <HI>souls,</HI> and wait for the <HI>saving health of Gods salvation,</HI> who can best <HI>ordain peace for us,</HI> who<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 2<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ 12 Isa. 19. 20</NOTE> hath <HI>smittenus,</HI> and only <HI>can heal us,</HI> by allaying and composing, the spirits of honest-meaning men, by making them to be of one <HI>mind,</HI> by <HI>suggesting</HI> good <HI>counsels,</HI> which no passions shall stop, or private interests <HI>prevent,</HI> by shewing us the way of peace, and <HI>guiding us in it.</HI> It is time for us to ac∣cept
<PB N="108" REF="64"/>
of the <HI>long punishment God hath inflicted on us;</HI> take heed (like King <HI>Ahaz</HI>) of sinning more and<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lev. 26. 41</NOTE> more in our <HI>affliction,</HI> by adding <HI>drunkeness</HI> to <HI>thirst,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Chron. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>8. 22</NOTE> confusion to <HI>rebellion,</HI> and desolation to division.</P>
<P>§. Do not listen to those <HI>charmers</HI> and <HI>cheaters</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Beware of false healers.</NOTE> who will pretend you are <HI>healed,</HI> or the <HI>daugh∣ter of your people is not hurt,</HI> or she is much men∣ded, or she is <HI>not to be cured</HI> but only in those ways which their <HI>popular, partial, tumultuary, bloody</HI> and <HI>violent heads</HI> have <HI>invented, practised,</HI> &amp; <HI>pursued</HI> to the into lerable charge &amp; anguish of the Nation.</P>
<P>§. If it be publique, perfect <HI>peace; peace</HI> (as some have pretended) if <HI>she be indeed healed,</HI> whence are those (<HI>moribundae palpitationes</HI>) dead∣ly pantings and <HI>fainting fits</HI> into which she falls so oft? What means the running Issues, the <HI>putid sores</HI> and <HI>purulent matter</HI> which daily is vented in such pamphlets of scurrility, and papers of discontent as shew the <HI>fedity, pain</HI> and <HI>shame</HI> of our times and Nation? what a scorn and derision, what a hissing and ashonish∣ment is she become at home and abroad, by the impatience and contempt of those useless, yea hurtful means which some Empiricks have rude∣ly applied, and variously tampered with!</P>
<P>§. Ask all parts of the <HI>body politick</HI> if they<NOTE PLACE="marg">Appeal to all esteats whe∣ther healed.</NOTE> be yet <HI>healed;</HI> what an <HI>Asthma</HI> or difficulty of breathing have we had since the breath of our nostrils hath been oppressed as to that order and government, that <HI>soveraign publique honor</HI> and highest <HI>authority</HI> which belongs to the Na∣tion, as its crown and glory, no less than those properties, Liberties and Laws, or that industry,
<PB N="109" REF="64"/>
peace, and security, which are due to every pri∣vate honest man!</P>
<P>§. Ask the <HI>Nobility,</HI> and <HI>Peers</HI> if they think themselves yet healed of the wounds which some of their <HI>honor's</HI> received in <HI>Iezreel,</HI> when they gave themselves the first great blow by separating their <HI>Spirituals</HI> from their <HI>Temporals,</HI> and instead of <HI>grave, venerable Bishops</HI> (who had for many hundred years sate in <HI>Parliament</HI> as <HI>Patres &amp; Pares</HI> to counsel with them) they submitted their honors to such Presbyters as affected to be not only their Confessors but their Dictators!</P>
<P>§, Ask the <HI>Gentry</HI> and <HI>Commons</HI> in <HI>Parlia∣ment,</HI> if they are yet fully healed of the hurts which first <HI>tumults</HI> and afterward <HI>mutinies</HI> with armed force have made on them.</P>
<P>§. Ask the generality of the <HI>Clergie</HI> or <HI>Mini∣sters</HI> (that are truly such) if they are healed <HI>of the hurts</HI> which <HI>Schism</HI> and <HI>Heresie, prophaness</HI> and <HI>licenciousness, Sacriledge</HI> and <HI>Ataxy, contempt</HI> and <HI>confusion, inordination</HI> and <HI>new Ordinations</HI> have made upon all holy <HI>Orders</HI> and <HI>Offices,</HI> upon all pub∣lick <HI>duties</HI> of Religion and devotion: Particularly, Ask those poor, but worthy Ministers (who <HI>fla∣grante bello, &amp; in cautelam</HI>) were by way of <HI>cau∣tion (ne noceant)</HI> or by way of <HI>castigation (quia nocuerunt)</HI> for some light offences sequestred from their Livings, and after silenced from all Offici∣ating; whether their punishment which was grea∣ter than their sin be yet taken off? whether their first <HI>sequestration</HI> be not made a <HI>total</HI> and <HI>final de∣privation</HI> of all livelihood; and their <HI>Purgatory</HI> become an <HI>Hell,</HI> out of which is no redemption
<PB N="110" REF="65"/>
by a <HI>summa justitia,</HI> which looks like <HI>summa injuria.</HI></P>
<P>§. Ask the <HI>whole People,</HI> when their <HI>Represen∣tatives</HI> or <HI>Deputies</HI> meet, as their mouthes, whe∣ther they are <HI>healed,</HI> or have any hope to be healed of those <HI>stabs</HI> and <HI>wounds</HI> which <HI>Oaths</HI> and <HI>Covenants,</HI> and cross <HI>Engagements</HI> have made upon their <HI>souls;</HI> by either ill taking the latter, or ill keeping the former▪ which were thefirst just and lawful ones, which no <HI>Pope</HI> or <HI>People</HI> can dispense withal.</P>
<P>Ask all degrees of men whether they are heal∣ed as to their <HI>Laws, Liberties, Properties, Peace, Plenty, Estates</HI> and <HI>Trade,</HI> except it be very slightly, or whether they expect to be <HI>soundly healed</HI> till such methods of <HI>healing</HI> are taken by <HI>wise, honest, impartial, authoritative, free</HI> and <HI>unanimous Phy∣sicians,</HI> as may bring them to those <HI>tried and good applications,</HI> both for <HI>diet and physick</HI> (both repenting what hath been done amiss, and retur∣ning to do what is just) by which they enjoyed <HI>health</HI> so many years, without any considerable <HI>aches</HI> or <HI>pains,</HI> which was easily and speedily re∣medied, by the justice and discretion of <HI>honest Physitians,</HI> compleat and conscientious Parlia∣ments, with a learned and godly Synod.</P>
<P>§. You know the <HI>unanimous cry and vote</HI> of<NOTE PLACE="marg">The sence of the Nation.</NOTE> far the most and best people of the <HI>Nation</HI> is for <HI>healing,</HI> which shews that they do not yet finde themselves <HI>healed;</HI> the <HI>cries</HI> and <HI>complaints</HI> of <HI>poor</HI> and <HI>rich,</HI> of <HI>great and small</HI> witness, We are not yet <HI>healed:</HI> All testifie this so <HI>loudly</HI> in <HI>Cities</HI> and <HI>Country,</HI> that none <HI>contradict it,</HI> but those who (as <HI>Sylla's</HI> lice, or <HI>Herods worms</HI>) feed on our
<PB N="111" REF="65"/>
soars, and hope to make a prey of <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State,</HI> of our <HI>Bodies, Estates</HI> and <HI>Souls</HI> by <HI>conti∣nuing</HI> the hurts, putrefactions and miseries of both.</P>
<P>§. Whose cruel <HI>policies</HI> and <HI>impressions</HI> I hope the mercy of God by the <HI>valour</HI> and <HI>wisdom</HI> of <HI>godly men,</HI> will speedily (if our sins hinder not) <HI>frustrate</HI> and <HI>defeat,</HI> when they see, that next our <HI>sins,</HI> the <HI>instruments of all our miseries</HI> have been <HI>Fanaticorum spicula, Jesuitarum venen<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tincta: Fanatick darts and arrows, dipt in the Jesuites poison.</HI></P>
<P>§. My only <HI>ambition</HI> and design in this <HI>freedom</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Necessary freedome to speak of our hurts▪</NOTE> of my speaking to you, is, to help to heal and close hurts, and to arm you against them for the time to come. Tis high time for every <HI>honest heart</HI> to make use of a <HI>discreet tongue,</HI> pathetically to set forth with the <HI>Prophet</HI> the <HI>hurts of the daughter of his people,</HI> to cry mightily to heaven and earth, to God and man, to <HI>honest Counsellors</HI> and <HI>just Commanders,</HI> to give us leave to use, or in pity to put us into <HI>such hands,</HI> and such <HI>ways</HI> as may <HI>effectually</HI> and <HI>speedily heal us,</HI> and not by a <HI>su∣pine silence</HI> and <HI>sottish slavery</HI> suffer our selves, and our posterity to <HI>wallow in our sanies</HI> or <HI>putid effluxions,</HI> or to sit for ever on <HI>a dunghil,</HI> like <HI>Job,</HI> scraping our sores with <HI>potsheards,</HI> and there is <HI>none to help us.</HI></P>
<P>§. We do <HI>not desire</HI> to be happier than our <HI>religion</HI> and <HI>laws</HI> would make us, and did so<NOTE PLACE="marg">Pristine health was best.</NOTE> before <HI>might affronted right,</HI> and <HI>force</HI> cut the sinews of <HI>Justice,</HI> to put us off <HI>with fine words,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Good words <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eal not.</NOTE> (godly phrases) and <HI>Saraphick</HI> fancys of cures,
<PB N="112" REF="66"/>
beyond the <HI>proportions</HI> of this mortal condition, as if we must all be <HI>healed</HI> to <HI>Angelick perfections,</HI> and setledby <HI>Mathematical ballancing of a Common∣wealth,</HI> or a Church, beyond all <HI>humane infirmi∣ties,</HI> or worldly <HI>vicissitudes;</HI> these are but the <HI>phil<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers</HI> and delusions of those who meditate no∣thing less <HI>than a</HI> speedy and honest <HI>healing;</HI> to which if my <HI>freedome</HI> used this <HI>day</HI> may any way <HI>contribute,</HI> who am (I thank God) exempted from <HI>base fe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s</HI> or <HI>flatteries of any man,</HI> I may hope that it will not onely be <HI>pardonable</HI> but <HI>acceptable to you,</HI> as from one that hath no designe so upon his <HI>heart</HI> (next the saving of his soul,) as to see, <HI>before I dye,</HI> the <HI>salvation of God</HI> in the right <HI>healing of the hurts of the daughter of my people,</HI> both in <HI>Church and State</HI> (whose <HI>welfares</HI> are <HI>unseparable.</HI>) For this <HI>end</HI> I have now preached to you <HI>upon your desire,</HI> and shall ever <HI>pray to God,</HI> the father of our <HI>Lord Jesus Christ,</HI> and Saviour of his Church, that after the many publique <HI>troubles</HI> we have for our <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ins seen and suffered to our sorrows, at length the waters may be so moved, by some good Angel, that the <HI>daughter of my people may be effectually healed,</HI> (by a soveraign and celestial influence) of what ever <HI>disease</HI> or <HI>hurt</HI> she hath, either in <HI>Church</HI> or <HI>State;</HI> and this for <HI>Jesus Christs sake,</HI> to whom with the <HI>Father</HI> and blessed <HI>Spirit, be everlasting glory.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="66"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

