<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A censure upon Lilly's Grammar wherein, besides a discourse on the reason of education, are shewn : the contradictions, falsities and false words, omissions, repetitions, superfluous rules, and misplaced words in our grammar / by R.G., formerly of the Free-School in New-Castle.</TITLE><AUTHOR>R. G. (Richard Gower)</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A42610</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing G51</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R18350</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13044916</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13044916</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">96905</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42610)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96905)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 739:8)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A censure upon Lilly's Grammar wherein, besides a discourse on the reason of education, are shewn : the contradictions, falsities and false words, omissions, repetitions, superfluous rules, and misplaced words in our grammar / by R.G., formerly of the Free-School in New-Castle.</TITLE><AUTHOR>R. G. (Richard Gower)</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Garthwaite, Richard, 1621 or 2-1690.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[16], 96 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by B.W. for George Downs ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1684.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Attributed to Richard Gower. Cf. BM.</NOTE><NOTE>Sometimes attributed to Richard Garthwaite.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Lily, William, 1468?-1522.</TERM><TERM>English language --  Grammar --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A42610">
<STC T="W">G51</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13044916</BIBNO>
<VID>96905</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
A CENSURE UPON Lilly's Grammar: Wherein, besides a DISCOURSE Of the Reason of EDUCATION; ARE SHEWN, The Contradictions, Falsities and false words, Omissions, Re∣petitions, superfluous Rules, and misplaced words in our <HI>Gram∣mar.</HI></P>
<P>By <HI>R. G.</HI> formerly of the Free-School in <HI>New-Castle.</HI></P>
<Q><P>Obest plerumque iis qui discere volunt, autoritas eorum qui se docere profitentur. <BIBL>Cic.</BIBL></P></Q>
<Q><P>Sapientiam sibi adimunt, qui sine ullo judicio inven∣ta majorum probant. <BIBL>Lactant.</BIBL></P></Q>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed by <HI>B. W.</HI> for <HI>George▪ Downs,</HI> at the three <HI>Flower de Luces</HI> over against S. <HI>Dun∣stan</HI>'s Church, in <HI>Fleet-Street.</HI> 1684.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="list of authors cited">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A Catalogue of those <HI>Au∣thors</HI> and <HI>Grammarians</HI> which I have perused for compo∣sing this <HI>Censure</HI> and <HI>Epitome</HI> of <HI>Lilly.</HI></HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>AUTHORS.</HEAD>
<ITEM>ANgelus Politianus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ausonius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aurelius Victor.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Boëthius de Consolatione.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cato de▪ re rusticâ.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Catullus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Caesar, <HI>with</HI> A. Hirtius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cicero.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="3"/>
Claudian's Epig.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Columella.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cornelius Celsus de Medicinâ.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cornelius Nepos.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cornelius Tacitus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Curtius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Eutropius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Florus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fulgentius de prisco Sermone.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gellius Noct. Attic.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Horace.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jornandus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Isidorus Originum.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Julius Exuper.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Justin.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Juvenal.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lactantii Instit.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lipsius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Livy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lucan.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="3"/>
Lucretius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Macrobius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Martial's Epig.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Marcellus de propriet. Serm.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Osorius de gloriâ, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Ovid.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Paterculus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Palladius de re rust.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pompeius Festus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Petrarcha de remed. fortunae.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Plautus. Persius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pliny's Nat. Hist.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pliny's Ep.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Propertius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Quintilian.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rufus Festus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Salust. Suetonius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seneca <HI>the Philosopher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Seneca <HI>the Poet.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Terence.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Tibullus.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="4"/>
Valerius Flaccus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Valerius Maximus</ITEM>
<ITEM>Valerius Probus de notis Rom.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Varro de linguâ lat.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Varro de re rusticâ.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vitruvius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Virgil.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>GRAMMARIANS.</HEAD>
<ITEM>ALvarus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Despauterius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Farnaby.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Johnson's Sciagraphia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Linacrus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Oxon. Notes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vossius; <HI>and several others.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To the Right Worshipful and Worshipful Aldermen
<LIST>
<ITEM>Nicholas Fenwick, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> May.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir Rob. Shaftoe, <HI>Kt. Record.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir Ralph Carr, <HI>Kt.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir Ralph Jennison, <HI>Kt.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir Nathanae Johnson, <HI>Kt.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry Brabant, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR></HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Timothy Davison, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR></HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Matthew Jeffreyson, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR></HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>George Morton, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR></HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Timothy Robson, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR></HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>William Blacket, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR></HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>William Aubonee, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR></HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Nicholas Ridley, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR></HI> Sheriff.</ITEM>
</LIST> 
And to the rest of the Common Council of the Town and County of <HI>New-Castle</HI> upon <HI>Tine.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIRS,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>THE deep obligation you hav laid me under, in the time of my sickness, does not a little move me, to take the first occasion wherein
<PB REF="5"/>
to acknowledge my self indebted un∣to you.</P>
<P>What I present to your Worships, is a strict survey of <HI>Lilly's Gram∣mar,</HI> which has bin view'd by several judicious persons and <HI>Masters</HI> of <HI>Free-Schools;</HI> and not without their good liking: And I doubt not, but it will giv satisfaction also to you my Worthy and learned Patrons, who are able to judge in the matter, and of competency to put a decision to the point: for, did <HI>Athens</HI> flourish more with men of learning, than does <HI>New-Castle?</HI> what City in the Land givs like incouragement thereto, and carries on her affairs with such unanimity and prudence.</P>
<P><PB REF="5"/>
I beseech you then allow it the shadow of your wing, and accept this acknowledgement of my gratitude, as a testimony how great my desires are, to manifest that I am unfeign∣edly,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>SIRS,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>Your most obliged, humble and very grateful Servant, R. G.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><DATE>Aug. 4. 83.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prefatory letter">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>A Copy of a Letter written to a Ma∣ster of a <HI>Free-School,</HI> and of thirty six years standing.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>HAving finished my <HI>Censure</HI> and <HI>Epitome</HI> of <HI>Lilly,</HI> which I told you of som time since: I now send them you, desiring that what over∣sights you meet with there∣in, may be impartially corre∣cted.</P>
<P>None can say, I have bin severe upon him; having used
<PB REF="6"/>
less <HI>aloes</HI> than <HI>hony;</HI> and don but as others be∣fore me: <HI>Strabo</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Nulla salis mica est, nec guttula fel∣lis in illa.</NOTE> found fault with <HI>Eratosthenes; Ga∣len</HI> with <HI>Thessalus;</HI> and what School of Philosophy, is not at daggers-drawing with those who went before? yea, <HI>Horace</HI> sais, <HI>Grammatici certant</HI>—and why not I with <HI>Lilly?</HI> so with <HI>Hera∣clitus</HI> we may say, <HI>Omnia secun∣dum litem fieri;</HI> and as <HI>Seneca</HI> ob∣serves; <HI>Tota hujus mundi concordia, ex discordibus con∣stat.</HI> This then <NOTE PLACE="marg">Nat. quaest. l. 7.</NOTE> was my task, by the help of those Authors pre∣fix'd, to expunge what has not bin of use among the Ancients,
<PB REF="7"/>
or rather contrary thereunto: and to shew what latitude the <HI>Romans</HI> took in writing: for <HI>Apud nos nulla magis haberi verba &amp; usit ata debent, &amp; recepta; quam quae de veteribus illis magnorum Autho∣rum thesauris proferantur.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Macrobius</HI> tels us plainly, <HI>Ve∣teres indulsisse copiae per varietatem:</HI> as when they said, <HI>Exanimos &amp; exanimes; Saturnalium &amp; Sa∣turnaliorum:</HI> and that <HI>Homo mag∣nâ eloquentiâ</HI> is neither full nor perfect, but so taken: <HI>Quae custo∣diam attinent. Val. Max. Quod ad sor∣des attinuerat, id. Inter coenam. id. In∣ter coenandum. M. Sen. Hortor amare. Cic.</HI> for <HI>ut ament. Consilium coepisse hominum fortunas evertere. id.</HI> for <HI>e∣vertendi. It visere. Ter.</HI> for <HI>visita∣tum.
<PB REF="7"/>
Charidemum dicere audistis. Cic:</HI> for <HI>dicentem. Viginti millium, &amp; centum millia. Corn. Nepos.</HI></P>
<P>After perusal, I pray return them stamped with your learn∣ed pen, which will, not a lit∣tle, add credit and authority to them, and oblige me to be,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>Your real Friend and Servant.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="answer to letter">
<PB REF="8"/>
<HEAD>The Answer.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I <HI>Hav perus'd your</HI> Censure <HI>and</HI> Grammar, <HI>and cannot but ap∣prov of that undertaking, which tends both to a quicker acquiring all neces∣sary</HI> Grammar-<HI>rules, and givs us an account of that liberty the</HI> Ro∣mans <HI>did, and therfore we may use.</HI></P>
<P><HI>As for the first, experience shews that too many years are spent in learning</HI> Lilly; <HI>even though the Master be industrious and skilful; and the Scholar apt and teachable: which puts me in mind of the com∣plaints of many bemoaning, that by
<PB REF="8"/>
neglect, after leaving the School, they had almost lost all their Latin: whom I advis'd to begin with their</HI> Grammar <HI>and get it by heart; but they reply'd it was a task insuperable: and doubtless the repeted necessary rules, with others, wholly useless, greatly burdens the Scholars memory, which your Epitome has cur'd.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Now as for the second, even mo∣dern Writers, do not confine them∣selves to</HI> Lilly'<HI>s rules; but take a greater latitude, as the old hav don; of which you hav giv'n account at large, and that, out of the Authors them∣selvs: so that the case is clear: for, came not rules at first from reading?</HI></P>
<P><HI>One thing I cannot approv,</HI> name∣ly, <HI>that</HI> Laus &amp; Vituperium—<HI>should be expung'd; for the</HI> Genitiv
<PB REF="9"/>
<HI>case, the latter of two Substantivs, is, as it were, possessor of the former: thus,</HI> Facundia Ciceronis, <HI>shews that</HI> Cicero <HI>possesses his Eloquence; but</HI> Puer boni ingenii, <HI>notes that the child possesses the wit. So that in this I cannot accord with you.</HI></P>
<P><HI>As for your</HI> Grammar, <HI>the un∣dertaking is ingenious, and stored with many right good observations; as the Learned at</HI> Cambridge <HI>hav Characteriz'd it to you: and sure it is the most useful way in writing, to comprehend</HI> multum <HI>in</HI> parvo, <HI>and most helpful to the learn∣er. Thus you hav the opinion of,</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>Your Friend and Servant.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="critique">
<PB N="1" REF="9"/>
<HEAD>A CENSURE UPON LILLY'S Grammar.</HEAD>
<P N="1">1. LET it not seem strange to any that I pass a <HI>Censure</HI> upon <HI>Lilly,</HI> while I teach him; his method, indeed, is more distinct than others: but the world knows, his rules are faulty: and I cannot conceiv it in∣justice, either to examin or refute, the doctrin, of our predecessors: for <HI>pecudum more non ducimur,</HI> sais <HI>Lactantius.</HI> And thus in our own profession, did <HI>Hippocrates,</HI> above
<PB N="2" REF="10"/>
2000 years ago; and <HI>Galen</HI> no less the like, who yet were as little infallible as they. Which seeing it falls in my way, take this following § for a di∣gression.</P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>Celsus</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">De Med. l. 3. c. 4.</NOTE> telling that <HI>Hippo∣crates</HI> accounts, if a Fever abate on an o∣ther day than Cri∣tical, a relapse was wont to return: sais, <HI>Asclepiades</HI> did justly repudiate it as vain, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> and a little below, adds that he keeps not to his pur∣pose: thus gravely reproving him for his fancied critical days. After the same manner <HI>Helmont</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Tract. de Temp.</NOTE> speaks plainly, that he al∣wais observ'd with diligence, that there is never any <HI>crisis</HI> at all, where the Physician being Master of his Art knows how to take away the dis∣eas before the usual time: and else∣where <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">De Feb. c. 11.</NOTE> sais; It is the part of a good
<PB N="3" REF="10"/>
and faithful Physician not to giv any regard to <HI>crises:</HI> but rather to pre∣vent them: For nature never intends a <HI>crisis,</HI> but when she is left to shift for her self. Shall I tell you how his 24 <HI>Aph.</HI> is contradicted in the second Book <HI>Aph.</HI> 29. The <HI>23d</HI> in the se∣cond Book by the <HI>19th.</HI> And see how little truth is in <HI>Aph.</HI> 31. <HI>l.</HI> 5. Thus with <HI>Sanctorius</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Method. vitand. error.</NOTE> I do not account them of such verity as men cry them up to be: but many of them rather, as <HI>Cicero</HI> expresses it, <HI>Vix d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gna lucubratione anicularum:</HI> than to be of the monument of Phy∣sick: How are they then <HI>aeternae veri∣tatis?</HI> Yea <HI>Galen</HI> himself, sticks not to contradict <HI>Hippocrates</HI> about <HI>Eu∣nuchs</HI> having the Gout, and growing bald: Whereat <HI>Sen. Ep.</HI> 95. breaks forth, saying; What a wonder is it, that the greatest of Physicians should be taken in a lie? Nor is <HI>Galen</HI> less without his failings; whose 2000
<PB N="4" REF="11"/>
pulses (as Dr. <HI>Primrose</HI> computes them) are more intelligibly known by their strength, greatness, fre∣quence; with the contraries, and means of those ex∣treems <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Sylvii prax. med. l. 1, c. 26.</NOTE>. And were it not too tedi∣ous, I could shew ten of his for one of <HI>Lillies</HI> contradictions. Then they who deify either, must needs be but children in the art: And if, as for certain they hav erred, and speak contrary to our senses, why should we not reject them? and so we may do with <HI>Lilly;</HI> for the way to redeem our art is (as my L. <HI>Bacon</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Novum Organ. Aph. 31.</NOTE> has it) to attempt an in∣stauration <HI>ab imis fundamentis,</HI> from the very foundation: and first to take of that superstitious reverence, which has bin so long paid to the antiqua∣ted Masters of the profession. In which undertaking, if I happen to mistake, consider, that even the <HI>Ro∣man</HI>
<PB N="5" REF="11"/>
Orator confesses himself inci∣dent <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Difficile est, in longa oratione non a∣liquando it a dicere, ut sibi ipse non conve∣niat. <HI>Brutus.</HI></NOTE> thereun∣to: and as <HI>Lactanti∣us</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Institut. l. 1. c. 5.</NOTE> observes, <HI>Ari∣stotle</HI> though styled the Prince of Phi∣losophers, yet saves others the pains to refute him, and contradicts himself: <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">l. 2. c. 9.</NOTE> <HI>Nec enim ab ul∣lo poterit Cicero, quam à Cicerone vehementius refutari.</HI> But to return.</P>
<P N="3">3. The complaint of our Countreys slow instructing Youth, in the Latin tongue, is not without cause: which though it be a great orna∣ment in a Gent. and such an accom∣plishment, as alone will man him a∣broad; yet is, I confess, purchased at an over high rate. But the fault may be as well in the Scholar, as in the Master: the duty of the latter, is easi∣ly discharg'd, seing advice and in∣struction, may sooner be given and
<PB N="6" REF="12"/>
enjoind, than followd and obeyd: the work and task of the former (I mean of the Scholar) may be retarded, and like <HI>Aristotl's pons asinorum,</HI> made unattainable; I mean where the Boy has a genial indisposition, and weak capacity; and withall affects not his Book: It is as hard a matter for a Master to penetrate that thick skull, as for a Boat to row against tide: If he com to som smatterings, they shall be as imper∣tinent <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Laudamus verba benè rebus accommo∣data. <HI>Quintil.</HI></NOTE> as <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Plin. Ep. 14. l. 2.</NOTE> <HI>Pliny</HI>'s <HI>Attilius;</HI> or as hald as an <HI>Augean</HI> stable is impure. We need not revive <HI>Origen</HI>'s or <HI>Phi∣lo</HI>'s allegory, of singeing his tongues∣end, with an hot Iron, <HI>Moses</HI> like, to make him a stammerer: <HI>Ex quovis ligna non fit Mercu∣rius;</HI> he is not fit <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> timber for polish∣ing: such should be remanded to the place from whence they came,
<PB N="7" REF="12"/>
with a true account of their dulness, ere they be besotted by severe cor∣rection <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Caedi discentes minime velim, quia deforme at{que} servile est: quod si cui tam est mens illiberalis, ut objurgatione non corri∣gatur, is etiam ad plag as, ut. pessima quae∣que mancipia dura∣bitur. <HI>Quintil. Insti∣tut. l. 1. c.</HI> 3.</NOTE>. For there are, not only, particular Boys; but whole Nations in∣disposed for learn∣ing, whereunto is required, not only education, but a pregnant <HI>Minerva,</HI> and teeming consti∣tution. For the wisdom of God, hath divided the genius of men, ac∣cording to the different affairs of the world: and varied their inclinations, according to the variety of actions, to be performed therein; which they who consider not; rudely rushing, upon professions and ways of life, unequal to their natures; dishonour not only themselves, and their suncti∣ons; but pervert the harmony of the whole world. <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Brown</HI>'s Enquiry in∣to vulgar errors.</NOTE> For if the world
<PB N="8" REF="13"/>
went on, as God hath ordained it; and were every one employed, in points concordant to their natures; Professions, arts and Kingdoms would rise up of themselvs; nor needed we a lanthorn to find a man in <HI>A∣thens.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4. Others ther are, I confess, whose wits, like wax, will take a full impression, and be cultivated by their Masters daily instruction; upon such has nature bestow'd a good memory, the chief fign of wit in a Boy (as <HI>Quintilian</HI> observes) adorned with those excellent properties, to appre∣hend the Masters dictates, with faci∣lity, and keep them with fidelity. Now these although by a long am∣bages and many weary paces, yet at last shew the true and genuin stamp of the Muses: and even such, you will say, make a tedious work of it; and scarce compass that part of their education, in less time than a seven years apprentice-ship: If they
<PB N="9" REF="13"/>
were to learn the <HI>China</HI> language, which consists of 50000▪ words; or <HI>Mithridates</HI> his 22, <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Valer. Max. l. 8. c. 7.</NOTE> sure they would need <HI>Methu∣salems</HI> years to acquire them in, al∣though it were their only work, being freed of State affairs, wher∣with he was incumbred. We like∣wise find, that a year or two, is time enough, to acquire the <HI>French</HI> or a∣ny forrein language: all which I must confess is true, and seems not strange to me, while we are such strangers to the thing we pretend un∣to, and never practice what we teach, I mean, speaking of Latin. As if with <HI>Aristotle</HI> in his <HI>Physics,</HI> we affirm <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, we taught and did not teach: whereas we know all things are per∣fected by practice <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Quarum omne o∣pus est in faciendo, at{que} agendo. <HI>Cic. Ac. quaest. l.</HI> 4. Rerum om∣nium magister est usus. <HI>Caes. de bello civ. l.</HI> 2.</NOTE>. Thus if I see a Surgion open a
<PB N="10" REF="14"/>
vein, it will instruct me better how to do the same, than the reading in Books, where the arm should be strait bound, how the lance is held and guided in the breathing <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>So,</HI> Quantitatem syllabarum Poetarum tectio multo faciliùs quàm regularum mul∣titudo suppeditabit. <HI>Saisour Greek Gram∣mar.</HI></NOTE>, and thus it is in every thing, Practice is the only Mistress, and want of use will caus our Mother tongue to rust. Thus <HI>Montaign</HI> af∣firms of himself <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Essais l. 1. c. 25.</NOTE>, that hé learnt Latin from his infancy, without any rules of <HI>Grammar,</HI> and only by discours with his Master; the servants and others being all forbid to talk, unless som Latin words, un∣to him; and when he was six years old, he had got as pure a Latin tongue, as his Master could express; being then able to reduce bad La∣tin into good. So much does the life of every Study, Art, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> depend
<PB N="11" REF="14"/>
upon use, that by practice, it becoms habitual; which ceasing, it is sub∣ject to decay, although it were at∣tain'd before, unto perfection: What being is it likely then to hav, where it has never bin put into practice? Skill in Physic, cannot be attain'd un∣to, without an Hospital of sick people, wherby to give the Students insight into practice: for those <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Arist. Eth. l. 2. c. 1.</NOTE> things, which they who learn ought to pra∣ctice, while they practice they will best learn. Even thus, if our Scholars were to board with us <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Plus viva vox &amp; convictus, quàm oratio, proderit Quia longum iter est per praecepta, breve &amp; effir ax per exempla. <HI>Sen. Ep.</HI> 6.</NOTE>, or we with them, and in∣stead of gabling <HI>En∣glish,</HI> all their dis¦cours were turned into Latin, in a year or two they would be expert, if follow'd closely, and corrected wherin their speech is in∣congruous;
<PB N="12" REF="15"/>
which would no less tend to the advantage of Masters, and breed a race, that could readily entertain any Forreiner with discours in Latin; and shake off that opprobri∣um of the <HI>British</HI> Ile.</P>
<P N="5">5. Another impediment, no less than the former; and therfor not to be passed over slightly, is the long journey from <HI>In Speech</HI> to <HI>Prosodia;</HI> a greater Task than learning Latin (as a Reverend Dr. of the Church did lately tell me) and too much toil for a generous mind to be enslaved with; which makes so many of our Youth to nauseat School learning; being as glad to be taken from School; as a Prisoner to be set at liber∣ty from a Gaol; rather choosing to be branded with the name of a dunce, than to be so enslav'd with daily re∣petitions of parts, and making of Themes and Verses, all which must be drawn out of another Fountain; and this must surely dull and confuse
<PB N="13" REF="15"/>
their young and tender wits; the ra∣ther seing as <HI>Montaign</HI> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Essais l. 1. c. 25.</NOTE> remarks, half our age is con∣sum'd that way. Many years being spent in learning bare words; I mean more, than an illiterat Nurs will be in teaching a child the <HI>English</HI> tongue, and as many years after, ere they can succinctly know, how to mingle and join them handsomly into one co∣herent orb: Much of which must be trifled in their learning without book every thing, while within Book they understand very little, as <HI>As∣cham</HI> observes.</P>
<P N="6">6. Now in detecting those repeti∣tions, omissions, contradictions, and fals Latin, I meet with in <HI>Lilly,</HI> I shall offer such things, as upon reading La∣tin Au∣thors <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><LG>
<L>Grammaticas rectè si vis cognoscere leges.</L>
<L>Discere si cupias cultius ore loqui;</L>
<L>Addiscas veterum clarissima scripta virorum:</L>
<L>Et quos Authores turba latina docet—</L>
<L>Quos qui non didicit, nil praeter somnia vidit,</L>
<L>Certat &amp; in tenebris vivere Cimmeriis.</L>
<L><HI>Lill. de moribus.</HI></L>
</LG></NOTE>
<PB N="14" REF="16"/>
and perusing other <HI>Grammars</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><LG>
<L>Sed tu nec stolidos imitabere Grammaticastros,</L>
<L>Ingens Romani dedecus eloquii.</L>
<L><HI>id. ioidem.</HI></L>
</LG></NOTE> I hav collected, which I judgemay somewhat satisfie the curious: For <HI>Magna pars studiorum amoenitates quaerimus,</HI> sais <HI>Pliny,</HI> leaving cavillers to abound in their own sens; who, <HI>quia ipsi errant, irascuntur iis, qui veram viam sequun∣tur, Lact. Inst. l. 5. c.</HI> 1. To my King, and Parliament, it does belong to new model, to rescind or alter for publick use, what by their authority, has been, for so many years establisht. And this perhaps with my <HI>Grammar,</HI> may make way thereunto.</P>
<P N="7">7. <HI>First,</HI> Then I hav observ'd se∣veral repetitions; som only of which I shall here name, and add the rest to the following Sections.</P>
<P>Those Figures <HI>Appositio, Syllepsis, Zeugma, Synthesis</HI> and <HI>Synecdoche</HI> are
<PB N="15" REF="16"/>
made rules in the <HI>Syntax,</HI> and yet set down at large after it; both of which the Boys are enjoin'd to learn.</P>
<P>The rule, <HI>Praepositiones cum casum amittunt</HI>—is thrice in the <HI>Accidence,</HI> and once in the <HI>Syntax;</HI> although ther be one that might serv for all in the Adverb: Moreover he givs it a plain contradiction by <HI>pòst</HI> in <HI>Longo post tempore venit,</HI> under <HI>adverbia di∣versitatis</HI>—where <HI>post</HI> which go∣verns only an <HI>Accusativ,</HI> must there be∣ing an <HI>Adverb,</HI> govern an <HI>Ablativ:</HI> al∣though the same words be under <HI>Prae∣positiones cum casum</HI>—to shew that <HI>pòst</HI> governs not <HI>tempore. Quorum parti∣cipia frequentius dativo gaudent,</HI> is in∣cluded in <HI>Verbalia in bilis</HI>—and <HI>Quam∣vis in his usitatior est dativus.</HI></P>
<P N="8">8. Again, there are sevral omissi∣ons, contradictions, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> of which as they lie</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="16" REF="17"/>
<HEAD>In the Accidence.</HEAD>
<P>IMuch question <HI>filia</HI> and <HI>nata</HI> end∣ing in <HI>is:</HI> and <HI>as</HI> much <HI>agnus, lu∣cus, populus,</HI>—being Vocativs. I read often <HI>Dei</HI> and <HI>Deis</HI> in <HI>Sen. Tra∣goed. Ovid, Livy, Martials epig. Au∣sonius, Tacitus, Lucan,</HI> &amp;c. Yea <HI>Ter. Varro</HI> sais <HI>hi Dei. &amp; l. 7. Ʋt hic Deus, sic hi Dei.</HI> Thus <HI>Dugard</HI> ren∣ders <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. in <HI>Lucian,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> 4. <HI>hominesve deive. Genius</HI> though no proper name has its Voc. in <HI>i</HI> sais <HI>Ti∣bullus,</HI> and so <HI>Mercurius,</HI> if you dare credit <HI>Hor.</HI> and <HI>Cic.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Meridies</HI> an example for the 5th. decl. is said, not to hav the Plu∣ral.</P>
<P><HI>Ʋnus</HI> is join'd to words of the sin∣gular; as <HI>Satis una superque vidimus excidia. Vir. Tabulae testamenti, unae
<PB N="17" REF="17"/>
erant allatae, alterae relictae. Caes.</HI> which <HI>tabulae</HI> for a will, <HI>Cic.</HI> has in the sing. as <HI>Tabulam ceratam dari, ce∣râ legitimâ:</HI> and a little after, he sais <HI>Tabulae unae.</HI> So <HI>duplices loci; uni è rebus ipsis. Cic. Or. Ʋnae literae,</HI> but som will say it is in the sing. on∣ly <HI>poëticè</HI> as with <HI>Ovid</HI> often. <HI>Ʋnae decumae. Cic.</HI> and <HI>ad unas unius agri decumas;</HI> and <HI>plus decumâ. id. Ʋnis moribus vivunt. id. Ʋnis vestimentis lautus es. id. Ʋnis vinculis duos alli∣gat. Sen. controv. 19. l.</HI> 3. So that it seems to be a piece of elegancy, and as <HI>Priscian</HI> terms it, a peculiar property in <HI>unus,</HI> to be in the plural, with words taken as if in the singu∣lar: Thus in <HI>English</HI> we say, They are good ones: <HI>Lillies</HI> rule must then be inconsistent with Latin.</P>
<P>Som question <HI>nostrate</HI> in the Nom. seing <HI>Cic.</HI> sais, <HI>Iter Arpinas:</HI> and <HI>Livy, bellum Privernas:</HI> for after words in <HI>atis</HI> were contracted into <HI>as, as</HI> kept all genders: and it
<PB N="18" REF="18"/>
was <HI>hic &amp; haec nostratis &amp; hoc nostrate</HI> of old; as <HI>Lilly</HI> in <HI>Prosodia</HI> clears.</P>
<P>We may either use the Future <NOTE N="w" PLACE="marg">Se Gell. noct. Att. l. 1. c. 7.</NOTE> Infinitiv; or Participle in <HI>rus;</HI> as, <HI>Hanc sibi rem prae∣sidio sperant futurum. Cic.</HI> or <HI>futur am.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Cum</HI> with <HI>amarem</HI> he calls a con∣junction, and in the <HI>Syntax</HI> he would hav it an Adverb, but without any reason.</P>
<P>We may as well say, there are <HI>Jurativ, dubitativ, permissiv</HI>—Moods as Optativ and Potential, which two in Latin with the Subjunctiv hav but one termination; different from the <HI>Greeks,</HI> which therfor must not be a precedent.</P>
<P>The present, preterperfect and fu∣ture subjunctiv, may at any time sup∣ply the Imperativ: why then are they not set therin? or an hortativ and permissiv Mood annext? seing <HI>Lilly</HI> sais it is called so then: and why
<PB N="19" REF="18"/>
want we the first person sing. (for <HI>peream</HI> commands as much as <HI>amemus)</HI> seing we hav the first plu∣ral? or rather why hav we any of the Subjunctiv Mood therin? and <HI>ero</HI> an Indicativ, put to <HI>amatus</HI> in the Fut. Subj.</P>
<P>The same is in <HI>fiamus, fer at</HI>—all which want authority and reason for their place: Thus <HI>Gellius</HI> sais, <HI>Exul esto;</HI> not <HI>sit. Fortunis careto;</HI> not <HI>ca∣reat:</HI> and <HI>Cic.</HI> about the end of his works has Verbs in <HI>nto</HI> near 100 times; as <HI>Pietatem adhibento: opes amòven∣to</HI>—</P>
<P>The signs of the Pot. Mood, and Fut. tens Indic. must be us'd with discretion: for <HI>Cic.</HI> yea all Authors frequently make use of <HI>possum, volo</HI>—beyond what is allow'd in Schools, where they are generally taken for signs: although <HI>volo</HI> should be us'd when one is purpos'd to do a thing: A Fut. tens notes what is like to com to pass. <HI>Possum</HI> shews power in the
<PB N="20" REF="19"/>
person: the sign <HI>may,</HI> the lawfulness of the thing, or if the party hav got leav, that then he may do it. But <HI>can</HI> is exprest by <HI>possum;</HI> as you may see below: and <HI>ought</HI> by <HI>debeo;</HI> so <HI>would</HI> by <HI>volo;</HI> as, <HI>Pompeius muniti∣ones Caesaris prohibere non poterat, nisi praelio decertare vellet</HI>—and a little after, <HI>Caes.</HI> sais, <HI>Si acrius insequi volu∣isset, bellum eo die potuisse finiri.</HI> So <HI>Juv. Omnia ferre si potes &amp; debes. Il∣lud debes cogitare. Cic. Haec nota es∣se debebunt. id. Vult emere agellum. Plin.</HI> in <HI>ep. Nihil volo de amico arro∣gantius dicere. id. Habere amicum volo. Sen. ep. 35. Ego volo discere. ep.</HI> 121. You shall find <HI>Cicero</HI> in his <HI>Off.</HI> full of such expressions thus, <HI>Quid habes dicere?</HI> and <HI>Sen. Non ha∣beo tempus.</HI> Thus also the <HI>Greeks,</HI> S. <HI>Luke</HI> 13. 31. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, so S. <HI>John</HI> 8. 44. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</P>
<P><PB N="21" REF="19"/>
I could never learn the difference between <HI>multum</HI> the Adjectiv and Adverb, in that repeted sentence <HI>Multum lucri</HI> in the <HI>English Rules:</HI></P>
<P>Nor can I distinguish between <HI>est;</HI> in <HI>Orantis est,</HI> a personal in the <HI>English Rules;</HI> and <HI>est</HI> in <HI>Prudentis est,</HI> call'd an Impersonal under <HI>Haec tria Imper∣sonalia</HI>—</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="22" REF="20"/>
<HEAD>In Orthographia, and those By-Rules.</HEAD>
<P N="9">9. Safter <HI>x</HI> must needs be ill o∣mitted, becaus it obscures the simple word: as, in <HI>expes, exanguis:</HI> who knows whether they com of <HI>pes</HI> or <HI>spes; anguis</HI> or <HI>sanguis?</HI> wherfor it were better us'd, as it is in forrein prints.</P>
<P><HI>Ctesiphon</HI> a <HI>Greek</HI> name, is a far fetch to prov the spelling of <HI>do-ctus; do</HI> having the sound of broad <HI>Scotch,</HI> a shame for <HI>English</HI> men to teach: so it were better spelt <HI>doc-tus</HI> and more naturally, being the true division of the word by its sound.</P>
<P><PB N="23" REF="20"/>
So <HI>A-bdomen</HI> is not a simple word as <HI>Lilly</HI> would have it, but coms of <HI>abdo,</HI> and should be spelt <HI>ab-dòmen.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sisenna</HI> bids write <HI>patres fami∣liarum:</HI> yet <HI>Caes. Cic. Livy, A. Hirt. Sen.</HI> in his <HI>Ep. Macrob. Festus,</HI> alwais write <HI>patribus familiâs, pa∣trum</HI> or <HI>matrum familiae</HI> or <HI>famili∣âs.</HI></P>
<P>We read <HI>Quinquatruum, Tac. Quinquatribus, Juv.</HI> and <HI>Cic. Quin∣quatriis, Cic.</HI> and <HI>ad Att. 17. l. 9. Pridie quinquatrûs:</HI> and <HI>per Quin∣quatrus serere. Plin. Nat. Hist.</HI> which <HI>Cal.</HI> tels us is of the second and third dec. and I think of the fourth also: though <HI>Lilly</HI> confine it to the second. <HI>Cic.</HI> and others say <HI>iens,</HI> and why may not we?</P>
<P><HI>Animans,</HI> which he declines with <HI>haec</HI> or <HI>hoc,</HI> is also <HI>masc.</HI> by <HI>Hor. Quen∣quam animantem. Ser.</HI> 2. so by <HI>Cic. A quo animante reliquos contineri vel∣let animantes. de Ʋniv.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="24" REF="21"/>
He sets <HI>abundans lactis</HI> for an ex∣ample of Participls made Nouns when they govern another case than their Verb; and in <HI>Syntax</HI> he makes the Verb govern a Gen. in the same words. The rest you may expect in my <HI>Grammar.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="25" REF="21"/>
<HEAD>In Propria quae maribus.</HEAD>
<P N="10">10. <HI>ALbula, Garumna, Lethe, Ma∣trona, Sequana, Vistula</HI> ri∣vers are Fem. so <HI>latae Garumnae. Auson. Jader</HI> is Neuter. <HI>Subur</HI> is a river and a town. <HI>Plin. Daphnus</HI> a city is <HI>masc.</HI> so <HI>Croto, Narbo: Pessinus</HI> is only <HI>masc.</HI> in <HI>Cic. Pliny</HI> sais, <HI>Hippo regius; utraque Hippo:</HI> and <HI>Hippo, quod Vibanus appellamus. Pontus</HI> the country is <HI>masc. Argos</HI> a country is <HI>neuter.</HI></P>
<P>I find no need of <HI>Sunt etiam volu∣crum</HI>—for though <HI>mus, elephas, pas∣ser, anser</HI>—are <HI>Epicens,</HI> as are all beasts, birds and fishes specified by one word in both Sexes, as is told in the Genders; yet are declined with <HI>hic,</HI> by other rules: so <HI>hirundo, tigris,
<PB N="26" REF="22"/>
vulpes, cetus, ostrea</HI> (or <HI>ostreum)</HI> hav other rules for their articls.</P>
<P><HI>Natalis</HI> is call'd an Adjectiv by <HI>Cal.</HI> having <HI>dies</HI> alwais either exprest or understood.</P>
<P><HI>Virus</HI> is an <HI>Aptôte.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Penis</HI> and <HI>menses</HI> words seldom us'd, might with modesty be left out; as the <HI>Lacedemonians</HI> exported <HI>Archilocus</HI> his Books, being account∣ed immodest: not willing their children should be corrupted by them, lest their manners might be more depraved, than their wits im∣proved.</P>
<P><HI>Pelagus</HI> is also <HI>masc.</HI> by <HI>Val. Flacc.</HI> I read not <HI>halcionis</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Tanquam scopu∣lum sic fugias inau∣ditum, at{que} insolens verbum. <HI>Gel. noct. Att.</HI> l. 1. c. 10.</NOTE> but <HI>haec alcion;</HI> so that he has chang'd both the word and special rule to save his vers.</P>
<P><HI>Ficus</HI> a <HI>fig. Lilly</HI> sais is of the fourth dec. and in <HI>Quae genus</HI>—the fig and its tree are of the second and fourth:
<PB N="27" REF="22"/>
and so <HI>Cic.</HI> has it; <HI>Qui arborem fici nunquam vidisset, fiscinam ficorum ob∣jecisti,</HI> and <HI>suspendisse se de ficu.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ficus</HI> an ulcer is of the second dec.</P>
<P><HI>Lar</HI> is <HI>masc.</HI> by <HI>Cic.</HI> and should be among the monosyllables.</P>
<P><HI>Mulier</HI> is confest by <HI>Lilly</HI> to belong to the third special rule, though set under the second.</P>
<P>In <HI>o, signantia corpus</HI>—is obscure, for <HI>corpus</HI> there is <HI>physicum,</HI> to differ them from words of passion, or acti∣on, as <HI>lectio, corruptio.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ausonius</HI> makes <HI>sal</HI> Neuter, <HI>Quibus additur aequoreum sal:</HI> so <HI>Donatus</HI> would have it <HI>n.</HI> as it is us'd by Physicians at this day, to distinguish it from <HI>hic sal</HI> a jeast: so <HI>sal nemo exigat. Vopiscus</HI> in <HI>Aur. Idsal. Varro</HI> in <HI>Fab.</HI> yet <HI>Celsus</HI> uses <HI>hic sal</HI> salt.</P>
<P>I find <HI>Python</HI> to be <HI>hic vel haec,</HI> though som deny it.</P>
<P><HI>Cupido</HI> is often <HI>masc.</HI> by <HI>Hor.</HI> so <HI>Sen. Tragoed. Nullus hic auri caecus cupido:</HI> yet it is commonly Fem.</P>
<P><PB N="28" REF="23"/>
<HI>Plin. l. 2. c.</HI> 5. sais <HI>tres siseres.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Lilly</HI> givs <HI>hic &amp; haec,</HI> only, to <HI>di∣ves</HI>—and yet <HI>ingenium dives. Ov. Opus superstes. Lucan. oppidum locuples. Cic.</HI> why then not <HI>hoc</HI> also? <HI>degener</HI> ends in <HI>e</HI> or <HI>i,</HI> in the Abl. as Adje∣ctivs of the third dec. <HI>Degeneri sub hoste. Lucan. Comes</HI> I find alwais us'd as a Substantiv, and <HI>Lilly</HI> has it under <HI>Communis generis—Statius</HI> sais also <HI>de paupere regno.</HI> and <HI>Sen. uberi solo.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="29" REF="23"/>
<HEAD>In Quae Genus.</HEAD>
<P N="11">11. <HI>PErgama</HI> coms of <HI>Pergamum</HI> us'd by <HI>Sen.</HI> and <HI>Pliny.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Supellectilia</HI> is of old <HI>supellectile</HI> us'd by <HI>Ter. Varro.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Gargarus</HI> and <HI>Taenara</HI> sais <HI>Alvarus,</HI> were never red: but <HI>Gargarum Ma∣crob. Sibila</HI> coms of <HI>sibilum</HI> in <HI>Se∣ren.</HI></P>
<P>I would gladly know the diffe∣rence between <HI>instar</HI> the <HI>aptôte</HI> and Adverb. We read <HI>hic astus, ûs: &amp; hi astus, astibus, Cic. Astu</HI> is a ci∣ty.</P>
<P><HI>Nil</HI> is by <HI>Syncope</HI> for <HI>nihil,</HI> which by <HI>Apocope</HI> is for <HI>nihilum,</HI> which <HI>Lilly</HI> affirms.</P>
<P>I am at a stand, whether to teach <HI>hoc verber</HI> in <HI>Propria quae maribus;</HI> or the <HI>diptôte.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="30" REF="24"/>
<HI>Angelus Pol.</HI> sais <HI>meae preci:</HI> so <HI>Ter.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Frugi</HI> and <HI>opus</HI> are of both num∣bers.</P>
<P><HI>Ausonius</HI> has <HI>frux,</HI> and <HI>Ter. Varro</HI> sais <HI>frugi rectus est natura frux.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Mille</HI> an Adjectiv wants the sing. but when a Substantiv, it has both numbers; we read also <HI>millia</HI> an Ad∣jectiv pl. <HI>aptôte.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Centum</HI> is an <HI>aptôte,</HI> but its com∣pounds are declin'd, <HI>ducenti, tae, ta; quingenti,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Ditio</HI> is in <HI>Dictionaries.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Lac</HI> being moist, and <HI>gluten</HI> sold by weight, should not be in <HI>Nec licet his neutris</HI>—</P>
<P><HI>Hesperos</HI> is a proper name with <HI>Cic.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Pliny</HI> sais <HI>Conjectare crassitudinem gelûs,</HI> so <HI>gelu</HI> is no <HI>aptôte;</HI> and if the <HI>Romans</HI> had needed its other cases, no doubt we had had them.</P>
<P><HI>Tacitus</HI> has <HI>gratibus.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Cicero</HI> sais <HI>effatum.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="31" REF="24"/>
I am to seek for his <HI>flexile cornum;</HI> yet read <HI>cornus</HI> and <HI>cornu;</HI> so <HI>cornûs Cervini. Plin. nat. hist.</HI></P>
<P>I find no <HI>plebis,</HI> but only <HI>plebs &amp; plebes; plebes jejuna. Lucan,</HI> so <HI>Cic.</HI> often, and <HI>Tac.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Pulver</HI> is old. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Verborum delectus o∣rigo est eloquentiae. <HI>Cic. in Bruto.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P><HI>Sen. nat. quaest. l.</HI> 2. has <HI>manubium.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ausonius mapale.</HI></P>
<P>We read <HI>tapetium,</HI> and <HI>tapetus</HI> as well as <HI>tapes.</HI></P>
<P>So <HI>hoc sinapi, is: haec sinapis,</HI> and <HI>si∣napi,</HI> the <HI>aptôte.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Lacus, ci;</HI> is denied.</P>
<P><HI>Fores</HI> said to want the sing. is us'd by <HI>Hor. Exclusus fore,</HI> shut out of doors. <HI>Forem cubiculi. Val. Max.</HI></P>
<P>It is an abuse to say <HI>nemo</HI> wants the Gen. <HI>Lilly</HI> notes it not, and <HI>Plaut.</HI> sais <HI>neminis misereri;</HI> thus also the Translators of the Minor Poets, <HI>Ne∣minis ô Conjux.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="32" REF="25"/>
<HEAD>In As in praesenti.</HEAD>
<P N="12">12. <HI>PLevi</HI> is <HI>obsolete.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Delevi</HI> is by <HI>Praet. dat. idem</HI>—which rule would make <HI>elicui</HI> to be <HI>elexi.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Levi</HI> seems to be of old <HI>leo,</HI> rather than of <HI>lino.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Cumbo, is,</HI> is not red; nor <HI>pegi,</HI> its compounds belong to <HI>Haec si compo∣nas</HI>—</P>
<P><HI>Psalli</HI> I read not, nor <HI>nexo, is:</HI> nor <HI>crepo, is.</HI> So <HI>Cello</HI> is only in the com∣pounds; and if so, what need <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Grammatica re∣cte loqui docet; nec insuetas loquendi re∣gulas commiaiscitur; sed quae plurimum in loquendo videt observari, eorum loquendi rudes, ne contra morem loquantur, admo∣net—si sana est. <HI>Morus.</HI></NOTE> we them?</P>
<P><PB N="33" REF="25"/>
<HI>Sapui</HI> is by <HI>syncope,</HI> so <HI>sapisti</HI> oft us'd in <HI>Mart. Epig. Capessi</HI> is by <HI>Apocope,</HI> as <HI>lacessi,</HI> so <HI>incessi</HI> or <HI>sivi.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Tacitus</HI> has <HI>Accucurrit.</HI> and <HI>Sen. de ben. l.</HI> 4. So <HI>A. Hirt.</HI> annext to <HI>Cae∣sar</HI> has <HI>adcucurrisse</HI> and <HI>accurrit; Con∣cucurrissent,</HI> and <HI>concurrissent. A. Hirt. Liv. L. Florus, Vell. Paterc. Val. Max. Decucurri. Liv. Suet. A. Hirt. Sen. ad Marc. Plin. Tacit. decurrerit. Sex. Aur. Vict. &amp; Val. Max. Curt. Ex∣cucurrerunt Liv. A. Hirt. excurrissem. Plin. l. 3. Ep. 4. Liv. l. 2. Praecucur∣ri. A. Hirt. Plaut. Liv. Sen.</HI> and <HI>Caes∣praecurri. Plaut. Cic. Val. Max. Procu∣curri &amp; procurri. Caes. Plaut. Florus. Transcucurrit. Sen. controv. 2. l. 1. transcurrerat. id. controv.</HI> 6.</P>
<P>Except <HI>retracto, pertracto, ablacto,</HI> becaus they change no vowel in∣to <HI>e.</HI></P>
<P>Also <HI>supersedeo</HI> and <HI>circumago</HI> from that of <HI>ago, emo</HI>—</P>
<P><PB N="34" REF="26"/>
Compounds of <HI>sto</HI> make <HI>stitum</HI> and <HI>statum; praestiti</HI> and <HI>praestavi. Am. Marc. praestitum, &amp; statum, stiturum, Sen. de ben.</HI> and <HI>staturum. id.</HI> and also <HI>Quinti∣lian.</HI> So <HI>constitum, constatum &amp; con∣staturus, Sen. l. 1. de Clem. Martial</HI> and <HI>Plin. extatura. id. obstatum, obsta∣tura.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Linquo</HI> he sais, makes <HI>lictum;</HI> and had he said only in the compound, he had not said amiss; for it wants the Sup. as in <HI>Haec raro aut nunquam</HI>—Thus we learn dreams; and must teach them by authority.</P>
<P><HI>Pinso</HI> has <HI>pinsum, pistum</HI> and <HI>pin∣situm.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Exculpo</HI> seems to be of <HI>sculpo,</HI> for <HI>scalpo</HI> forms <HI>excalpo</HI> in the compound.</P>
<P><HI>Merui</HI> coms of <HI>mereo; Quid mere∣as? Cic. meritus sum</HI> of <HI>mereor,</HI> as may be seen in <HI>Mereor cum adverbiis</HI>—</P>
<P><HI>Quod dat ui</HI>—omits <HI>intona∣tum.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Passus</HI> coms not of <HI>pateo</HI> a neuter, but of <HI>pandor</HI> a passiv; so <HI>Passis velis
<PB N="35" REF="26"/>
provehi. Cic.</HI> which <HI>Vir.</HI> renders <HI>Velo∣rum pan dimus alas.</HI></P>
<P>We want authority for <HI>titubatus,</HI> which is but a participle.</P>
<P>So for <HI>suetus, venditus, vidi</HI> of <HI>cer∣no,</HI> which yet he sais has <HI>crevi,</HI> and is us'd in the compound.</P>
<P>So for <HI>percussi</HI> of <HI>ferio;</HI> for <HI>minxi</HI> of <HI>meio;</HI> though <HI>Martial</HI> say <HI>Meiêre pe∣des, l.</HI> 11 and <HI>meibat. id.</HI></P>
<P>And were it not better to say, <HI>qua∣tio</HI> wants the praet.? for <HI>percussi</HI> coms of <HI>percutio:</HI> and that <HI>Fe∣rio</HI> wants both praet. and sup. than to go beyond the Moon for <HI>per∣cussi,</HI> which none can prov who use it?</P>
<P><HI>Sido</HI> has <HI>sedi</HI> and <HI>sidi</HI> among Au∣thors.</P>
<P><HI>Sisto</HI> makes <HI>stiti</HI> not <HI>steti,</HI> sais <HI>Cal.</HI> and wants <HI>sup.</HI> for <HI>statum</HI> sais he is of <HI>sto;</HI> and he reasons the case at large.</P>
<P><PB N="36" REF="27"/>
<HI>Taedet</HI> forms <HI>taesum est,</HI> and <HI>pertae∣sum est</HI> must com from <HI>pertaedet;</HI> thus <HI>Gell.</HI> has <HI>pertaedebat.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Furo, vescor, liquor, medeor</HI>—want the praet. for <HI>insanivi, pastus sum</HI>—are too far fetcht.</P>
<P><HI>Potus, tutus &amp; tutum, fessus defes∣sus,</HI> are nouns: and <HI>fatiscor</HI> is old. <HI>Cal.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Antecello, pateo,</HI> and <HI>viso</HI> want sup.</P>
<P><HI>Resputum, Cal. Suctum,</HI> whence <HI>suc∣tus, ûs, Plin. Nat. Hist.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Renutum, luitum,</HI> in. <HI>Dictionaries.</HI> So <HI>satactum. Cal.</HI></P>
<P>I never knew the difference be∣tween <HI>Cedo, cedite</HI> the Verb and Ad∣verb, nay hav grounds to think it can∣not be an Adverb, seing it has both numbers, a thing to which Adverbs are strangers; it must then be only a defectiv Verb; the like I judge of <HI>age, agite:</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</P>
<P>Som think <HI>inquio</HI> no Latin word and those places in <HI>Cic.</HI> and <HI>Catull</HI> corrupted.</P>
<P><PB N="37" REF="27"/>
<HI>Fer,</HI> he sais, is by <HI>Apocope</HI> for <HI>fere;</HI> and why then does he teach <HI>fer ferto?</HI> There he tels us <HI>furo</HI> is not red, and yet he has it in <HI>As in praesenti,</HI> but pass it, he sais <HI>insanivi</HI> after it.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="38" REF="28"/>
<HEAD>In Syntaxis.</HEAD>
<P N="13">13. THe second and third rule were fully exprest by <HI>Re∣ctus saepe subauditur.</HI></P>
<P>In <HI>Aliquando Oratio supplet locum sub∣stantivi, audito</HI> seems to be absolute, and set for <HI>re audita;</HI> and who can shew me any difference between it, and <HI>Audito Christum venisse,</HI> under <HI>Ablativus absolute sumptus?</HI> I confess it answers to <HI>What;</HI> but what is that to the purpos, seing it is without con∣cord, and as little needed.</P>
<P><HI>Rerum</HI> in <HI>Quod omnium rerum est primum;</HI> breaks that claus in <HI>Nomi∣na part. genito à quo &amp; genus mutuan∣tur, gaudent;</HI> which sais the Gen. <HI>re∣rum</HI> will make <HI>primum</HI> to be of the
<PB N="39" REF="28"/>
same gender: Now this claus fails also in heteroclits, collectivs, and when an Adjectiv regards a preced∣ing Substantiv.</P>
<P><HI>Aliquando relativum</HI> is difficult, and needless; its latter example be∣longs to <HI>Haec possessiva</HI>—.</P>
<P><HI>Res</HI> is somtimes us'd; <HI>Tres sunt res. Cic.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Laus &amp; vituperium</HI>—when in a Gen. is by <HI>Quum duo substanti∣va</HI>—when in an Abl. then <HI>praeditus, ornatus, perfectus</HI> or such a like word, is either understood by <HI>Ellipsis;</HI> or ex∣prest by <HI>Dignus, indignus</HI>—or <HI>Forma vel modus.</HI>—So we have it in our chois to express or omit them, and that with elegancy; yet <HI>Cic.</HI> in <HI>Verr.</HI> and indeed all over more frequently ex∣presses them; <HI>Adolescentibus bonâ in∣dole praeditis, sapientes senes delectan∣tur:</HI> which <HI>Lilly</HI> in the <HI>English Rules</HI> has without <HI>praeditis.</HI> And whether makes the better autho∣rity? without doubt the <HI>Roman.</HI>
<PB N="40" REF="29"/>
Orator <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Ille se profecisse sciat, cui Cicero val∣de placebit—Qui non bominis, sed elo∣quentiae nomen habet. <HI>Quintil.</HI></NOTE>: for the Broad Seal was never intended to countenance Errors. We may also use the Nom. <HI>Rufus homo doctus,</HI> (and Da∣tiv) <HI>&amp; philosophiae deditus.</HI></P>
<P>We say <HI>Similis tui,</HI> like thee in manners: <HI>similis tibi,</HI> like thee in per∣son.</P>
<P><HI>Caesar</HI> sais <HI>Proxime Rhenum inco∣lunt;</HI> and <HI>Proximi Rheno.</HI> and <HI>Curt. Proximi Aethiopum:</HI> and <HI>Ovid, Proxi∣mus ad dominam—sedeto.</HI> the first as it coms of the Preposition <HI>prope:</HI> the second by <HI>Adjectiva quibus commo∣dum</HI>—the third, by <HI>Quaedam ex his</HI>—the fourth, by <HI>Natus, commodus</HI>—and <HI>Sen.</HI> sais, <HI>Proxima ab his sunt.</HI> l. 1. <HI>de benef. &amp; Prope ab ultimo est. id. Ep.</HI> 15.</P>
<P>We may use or want <HI>quam</HI> with a Comparativ; <HI>Tu eruditior quam Piso, prudentior quam Cotta, abundantior consilio quam Crassus.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="41" REF="29"/>
<HI>Cic.</HI> so <HI>unam moestiorem, quam caeteras. Curt.</HI> or <HI>caeteris</HI> without <HI>quam.</HI> Yea <HI>Virgil</HI> for <HI>quam,</HI> has <HI>ante</HI> with its case; <HI>Scelere ante alios im∣manior omnes,</HI> for <HI>aliis omnibus:</HI> which I find also in the Superlativ; <HI>Ei unus ante alios fuerit charissimus. Corn. Ne∣pos.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Nomina ex Con</HI>—as <HI>Commilito Pompeio. Cic</HI> is fully comprehended in <HI>Est ubi in dat. vertitur,</HI> being gene∣ral.</P>
<P><HI>Quaedam ex his</HI>—hav also their contraries; <HI>Sectani dissimilis es. Hor.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Interrogativum &amp; ejus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>redd.</HI> so <HI>Mei, tui, sui—Meus, tuus—Sui &amp; suus—Ipse &amp; idem</HI>—are guides in making, not in parsing Latin: for there are other rules which teach them in parsing: thus <HI>Mei, tui</HI>—is by <HI>Quam duo subst. Meus, tuus</HI>—by <HI>Ad eundem modum</HI>—Again <HI>ille</HI> is often us'd for <HI>se</HI> the reciprocal: <HI>Pos∣sessivs</HI> for <HI>primitivs; Mea causa fecit. Cic. Nostra causa faceremus. Ter. Odi∣um
<PB N="42" REF="30"/>
tuum. id. Invidia mei. Cic. sc. de qua mihi invidetur. Linacrus</HI> will shew you that one Case, Number, Mood, Tens and part of Speech is of∣ten put for another: and by <HI>Ellipsis</HI> that any of the parts of Speech are understood in Authors.</P>
<P><HI>Haec possessiva</HI>—makes <HI>sui</HI> have a Gen. after it; and yet he writes <HI>Suo sibi jugulo gladio;</HI> so <HI>Cic. suo sibi victi∣tant succo:</HI> now in both, <HI>ipsius</HI> were Grammatical and also <HI>Roman:</HI> so we se that rule <HI>Haec possessiva</HI>—does not alwais hold; and those Genitivs <HI>ip∣sius, solius</HI>—are seldom us'd, and then only ad <HI>pompam.</HI></P>
<P>The rules would then bin more teaching, if they had shewn the li∣berty of a <HI>Roman</HI> in this and others: for as <HI>Alv.</HI> the <HI>Jesuit</HI> in his <HI>Grammar</HI> remarks; We must observ the right use of Authors, which supplies, yea exceeds all <HI>Grammar</HI> rules.</P>
<P><HI>Iste</HI> I find us'd in prais; and <HI>ille</HI> in contempt. <HI>Istum pene solum lego
<PB N="43" REF="30"/>
Cic. Adulter ille. Sen.</HI> in <HI>Trigoed. Fin∣gite aliquem, qui isti par ad nefarias libidines esse possit. Is erat Apollonius ille. Cic. Ridiculum est illud Neronia∣num vetus in furace servo. id. Ridentur imagines quae in deformitatem ducun∣tur, ut meum illud in Helmium, id.</HI> so you may se <HI>ille</HI> is only us'd to point at one <HI>remote,</HI> and <HI>iste</HI> at one <HI>near</HI> him I speak to: as is most plain in those Orations of <HI>Cic. in Catil.</HI> who being in the Senat, <HI>Cic.</HI> sais, <HI>si iste u∣nus tolletur.</HI> And in the next, being banished <HI>Rome,</HI> he alwais stiles him <HI>ille;</HI> though no less notorious, than when pointed at <HI>iste; Vicimus cum illum ex occultis insidiis conjecimus:</HI> and a little after, <HI>Nec ego sum ferreus ille.</HI></P>
<P>Instead of <HI>hic</HI> and <HI>ille,</HI> we may use <HI>alter &amp; alter; Praeter Aeduos &amp; Rhe∣mos, quos honore habuit, alteros pro ve∣tere fide; alteros pro belli officiis, nul∣la fere fuerit civitas non suspecta nobis. Caes.</HI> or <HI>ille</HI> and <HI>ille; Credc cum vidisset
<PB N="44" REF="31"/>
qui homines in hisce subselliis sede∣rent, quaesisse, num ille, aut ille defen∣surus esset. Cic.</HI> Or, <HI>unus</HI> and <HI>al∣ter; Elis duas familias habet, Jami∣darum unam, alteram Clutidarum. id.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Infinitum utrinque</HI>—is fals: for although it will admit of a Nom. after it, yet never before it; but when it is put for an Indicativ by <HI>Enallage modi:</HI> and the Nominativs in its examples com before the principal Verb, and not before the Infinitiv; which often has an Acc. before and after it.</P>
<P>The three last examples are con∣trary to the Rule; and patched by the next.</P>
<P><HI>Sum</HI> with a Gen. has <HI>officium, pro∣prium,</HI> or such a word understood; which <HI>Cicero</HI> more frequently expres∣ses than omits; <HI>Proprium est stulti∣tiae. Oratoris est officium,</HI> so <HI>Pecus est Meliboei, sc. pecus.</HI> which is as plain an <HI>Ellipsis</HI> as any examples he has in
<PB N="45" REF="31"/>
<HI>Ponitur genitivus tantum</HI>—the former Substantiv being under∣stood.</P>
<P>The next Rule, <HI>Meum, tuum,</HI>—is only <HI>adjectivum in neutro genere</HI>—neither did any ever read <HI>est,</HI> with <HI>meâ, tuâ</HI>—or with a Genitiv, o∣therwise than is here set down: so that <HI>Haec tria impersonalia</HI>—must be but <HI>duo,</HI> or else it is fals.</P>
<P><HI>Ʋterque, nullus</HI>—wants good authority; for <HI>Grammarians</HI> (as <HI>Laurentius</HI> who is said to hav made this Rule) are invalid without the concurrence of <HI>Roman</HI> Authors.</P>
<P><HI>Misereor</HI> with a Dativ, I judge, not to be imitated; seing the best Copies hav <HI>hujus,</HI> not <HI>huic misereor,</HI> his only example, which is in <HI>Sen. de vi∣tâ beatâ, c.</HI> 24.</P>
<P>In <HI>Ex his quaedam efferuntur</HI>—he has <HI>juvat,</HI> as if it were commonly red with a Dativ; wheras <HI>juvat</HI> whether personal, or impersonal has only an Acc. according to him: in∣deed
<PB N="46" REF="32"/>
<HI>Plautus</HI> givs it a Dativ, but that is <HI>obsolete.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Do tibi literas,</HI> is said to a Messen∣ger: <HI>Do ad te,</HI> is said to him they are sent to: yet <HI>Ovid</HI> sais, <HI>Hanc—ti∣bi mittit Ʋlysses,</HI> which to salv, you must call <HI>poëticé.</HI> So <HI>Martial, Mira∣ris docto quod carmina mitto Severo:</HI> the title being <HI>ad Severum.</HI></P>
<P>Under <HI>Verba obsequendi</HI>—are three examples, which belong to <HI>Dat. po∣stulant</HI>—</P>
<P>The like in the next Rule, which besides, has one belonging to <HI>In Dat. feruntur</HI>—viz. <HI>Saevis inter se convenit ursis;</HI> also its first, <HI>Ad∣amorem nihil potuit accedere,</HI> owns <HI>Verba composita cum à, ab, ad</HI>—</P>
<P>Thus few Rules between <HI>Omnia verba</HI>—and <HI>Verba transitiva</HI>—hav all their examples suitable; and were more intelligible if drawn into two Rules.</P>
<P><PB N="47" REF="32"/>
Verbs compounded with <HI>benè satis</HI> and <HI>malè,</HI> are plainly Verbs of profit, or disprofit.</P>
<P><HI>Praeiret exercitui. Ter. Varro.</HI> and <HI>Ʋt mihi praeeatis,</HI> sais <HI>Cic.</HI> though <HI>Lilly</HI> confine <HI>praeeo</HI> to an Acc.</P>
<P>We may use <HI>habeo</HI> as well as <HI>est</HI> for <HI>habeo,</HI> which is frequent with <HI>Cic. Quintil.—Habeo opus magnum in manibus. Cic. Haec fere dicere habui de natura deorum. id. De nostris somniis quid habemus dicere? id.</HI></P>
<P>Two negativs in Latin do affirm; <HI>nemo non eadem volet. sc. omnes vo∣lant.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sum</HI> in Comp. either has a Dativ by <HI>Dat. postulant</HI>—or which is as common, has its Preposition repe∣ted by <HI>Verba composita—Inerant in ur∣be. Cic.</HI></P>
<P>A Verb transitiv is such, as passeth into an Acc. of the person suffer∣ing.</P>
<P><HI>Vestiendi verba</HI>—with a Dativ, is acquisitiv; with an Ablativ, is by <HI>Quodvis verbum</HI>—</P>
<P><PB N="48" REF="33"/>
<HI>Per</HI> with his Case, is us'd for the Ablativ of the instrument, and of the caus, <HI>&amp;c. Id facinus auctum per stu∣prum. Cic. Per vim expulso socio. id.</HI> So the agent with a passiv, <HI>Ab impru∣dente, aut per imprudentem interfectus. Quintil. Judicium per eum corruptum putabatur.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Delector</HI> I find only once with a Prep. <HI>ab altero delectêre. Cic.</HI></P>
<P>If there be no Preposition with Verbs specified under <HI>Quaedam acci∣piendi,</HI> as <HI>Abstinuit Venere. Hor.</HI> say <HI>Praepositio subauditur:</HI> which <HI>Lilly</HI> might hav noted, seing <HI>abstinuit</HI> with a Prep. is set under the former Rule.</P>
<P>Som question his examples in <HI>Ver∣titur hic abl.</HI>—and call them old Ablativs: but for <HI>aliquando</HI> he might hav said <HI>saepe;</HI> thus <HI>Claud. Abest urbi.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Eripiamus huic aegritudinem. Cic. Abstulit urbi. Juv.</HI> And indeed <HI>Quaedam accipiendi</HI>—is of little use, only as it founds <HI>Vertitur hic abl.</HI>—for the Verbs there noted, common∣ly
<PB N="49" REF="33"/>
belong to <HI>Verba composita cum à, ab</HI>—or (as before) the Preposition is left out, by <HI>Praepositio subaudita—A∣quâ prohibet. Caes. Abstinet concubitu Juv.</HI></P>
<P>The Ablativ <HI>absolute</HI> commonly has a word in <HI>ing</HI> with <HI>it.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Cic.</HI> uses Adjectiv <HI>verbals</HI> in <HI>bilis,</HI> as Verbs Passivs; <HI>Separabilem à cor∣pore esse.</HI></P>
<P>His first Supines <HI>absolute,</HI> are Im∣personals.</P>
<P>Part or Continuance of Time, is in∣differently us'd in the Acc. or Abl. Case by Authors.</P>
<P>Time answering to <HI>quamdiu</HI> sel∣dom has an Abl. but an Acc. <HI>Septem regnavit annos. Liv.</HI> Yet <HI>Sexaginta an∣nis regnasse. Plin. Vixit annis 29. Suet.</HI></P>
<P>Time answering to <HI>quando,</HI> has an Abl. <HI>Datum est anno superiore. Cic.</HI> This by many is thought the best and surest Rule.</P>
<P><HI>Omne verbum admittit gen.</HI> is often broke: <HI>Habitaturum putas fuisse in Ʋ∣ticâ.
<PB N="50" REF="34"/>
Sen. Ep. 51. In Cajetâ est parata. Cic. Ad Corfinium gestae. Caes.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Humi, domi</HI>—fail as much; <HI>Rese∣dit humo, Ov. Corpora devolvunt in hu∣mum. id. Maneant in domo. id. Neque ducem in bello, nec principem domi res magnas gerere potuisse. Cic.</HI> Thus <HI>Sen. In bello meas, in domo etiam filii manus perdidi. l. 1. controv.</HI> 4. and relating the same story again he has <HI>domi per∣didi;</HI> which if <HI>Roman,</HI> why not re∣gular? <HI>Livy</HI> also writes <HI>domi, bello{que}. Nequam esse in domo. Plin. Nat. Hist. In domo clari hominis adhibenda est cu∣ra laxitatis. id. Domo moestus. Cic. Sa∣lust</HI> who was <HI>Cicero</HI>'s contemporary, uses <HI>humi,</HI> for in the ground; <HI>Duode∣cim pedes humi depressus.</HI> and <HI>Quae hu∣mi gignuntur. sc. arbores. id.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Domi non alios</HI>—is as little kept as either; <HI>Vix credens potuisse illum in domo suâ nasci. Sen. de benef. l. 3. Ʋt in suâ domo duae partes essent. id. l. 5. Si modo nostrâ in domo unquam fuisti. Sen.</HI> in his <HI>Tragedies. In suis domibus ser∣vat.
<PB N="51" REF="34"/>
Val. Max. In domo suâ haerentem. Suet. In domo meâ convaluit. Cic.</HI> and <HI>Pliny l. 7. Ep.</HI> 16. has the same words. <HI>Erat in domo nostrâ locus. Quintil. Non licuit in domo suâ spiritum effun∣dere. id. In domo meâ ageretur. id.</HI> This <HI>Quintilian</HI> was Master to <HI>Pliny</HI> the younger, and taught School 20 years; yet se how little he observs this Rule: sure his <HI>Grammar</HI> had it not. Nay where he once observs one of these three last Rules, he breaks them thrice; and very seldom sais <HI>domi,</HI> but <HI>in domo.</HI> The like does <HI>Seneca, Nero</HI>'s Tutor: and so do all I hav seen greatly neglect them, as al∣so those following Rules of To, and From a place.</P>
<P>The meaning of <HI>Domi non alios</HI>—is, that with other Adjectivs than <HI>meae, tuae</HI>—it is never a Gen. but commonly an Abl. <HI>Sola domo moeret vacuâ. Vir.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Priscian, Alvarus,</HI> and others, will have the Dativs in <HI>Verum si propri∣um—</HI>
<PB N="52" REF="35"/>
to be old Ablativs, and account it safest to speak in the Abl.</P>
<P><HI>Verbis significantibus motum ad lo∣cum</HI>—have the proper name often us'd with a Preposition, and so <HI>domus: Profectus sum ad Capuam. Cic. In do∣mum multiplicatam non repulsam solum retulit. id. Inque patris duxêre domum,</HI> whether the place be exprest with∣out a Preposition, or with <HI>in, apud, ad,</HI> Authors oft-times mean the same; <HI>Haec non in tuam domum, sed Romam in publicum deportasses. Cic. Apud Isson superfuerunt. Caes. Ad domum praecu∣currisse, &amp; dominam suam ante se egis∣se. Sen. de ben. l. 3. Reliquit me ad pa∣ternam domum. id. Proficisci ad doctas Athenas. Propert.</HI> which cannot stand for <HI>ante</HI> or <HI>prope,</HI> as <HI>Vossius</HI> confesses. And although Historians use <HI>ad</HI> for <HI>ante,</HI> yet <HI>Caesar</HI> has <HI>Ante Ʋticam mi∣serat;</HI> and without <HI>ad,</HI> makes <HI>Ʋti∣cam</HI> to mean before the place; <HI>Ʋticam exercitum ducit, &amp; pro∣pe opidum castra ponit:</HI> so <HI>A.
<PB N="53" REF="35"/>
Hirt. de bello Alex.</HI> sais, <HI>Alexandri∣am ad Caesarem contendit.</HI> When <HI>Caes∣ar</HI> besieged it, and <HI>Pompey</HI> was in it: <HI>Brundisium veni; ad murum castra posui. Cic. l. 9. Ep. ad Att. 16. Ʋticam pervenit, atque extra opidum ea nocte mansit. A. Hirt. de bello Afr. Oricum proficiscitur—portis clausis. Caes. de Bello Civ. l.</HI> 3.</P>
<P>Thus you may se these rules are not to be taken exclusivly, and what liberty the <HI>Romans</HI> took, often putting the Noun into what case best suited the matter, or Verb; <HI>Vectus esset Alexandriae. C. Vell. Paterc. Productus Romae. Macrob. Ʋticae appropinquare. Cic. &amp; Caes. Ʋticae subduxerat. A. Hirt.</HI></P>
<P>From a City or place, has a Prep. as frequently; <HI>Ab Româ venerunt. Liv. Ab Româ profectus. id. Ab Ʋticâ venire. Sall. A Brundusio.</HI> and <HI>Ab A∣thenis ire. Cic. Ab Alexandriâ profe∣ctus. Curt. Ab domo venerunt.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Liv. Profectum ab domo. id. Abesset
<PB N="54" REF="36"/>
à domo. Cic. Abesse ab domo maluit. id. A rure profectus. id. Ex domo prodire. id.</HI></P>
<P>Now seing cu∣stom <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Consuetudo certis∣sima loquendi magi∣stra. <HI>Quintil.</HI></NOTE> is the best guide, why may we not say as <HI>Quintili∣an</HI> did? Whom should I imitate but <HI>Cicero?</HI> Whom should we follow but these famous Authors, before <HI>Grammarians?</HI></P>
<P>What need we <HI>Nonnulla imper∣sonalia</HI>—seing it contradicts in <HI>terminis</HI> his rule, in the leaf after <HI>As in praesenti</HI>—where <HI>pudet</HI> is exprest in both: and first said to be alwais an Impersonal; and in the latter, som∣times a Personal.</P>
<P><HI>Coepit, incipit</HI>—is as needless; it being a standing Rule in Latin, that a Nom. Case makes a Verb to be a personal, and without one it becoms an Impersonal: besides his Infinitivs in the examples are no Impersonals, as the Rule would hav, which to me seems impertinent.</P>
<P><PB N="55" REF="36"/>
<HI>Natus, prognatus</HI>—are as often us'd with a Prep. as without; <HI>A te pro∣gnatum. Hor. E centurionibus orti. id.</HI></P>
<P><HI>En &amp; ecce exprobrantis</HI>—are red with a Nom. <HI>En causa, cur regem fugi∣tivus, dominum servus, accuset! Cic. En memoria mortui sodalis! id.</HI> Som think they govern no Case, but by <HI>Ellipsis</HI> hav a Verb understood: and <HI>Cicero</HI> often has them with a Dat. <HI>Ecce tibi.</HI> So <HI>Pliny</HI> in his <HI>Ep. Ecce tibi Regulus!</HI> where <HI>advenit,</HI> or such a Verb is understood.</P>
<P><HI>Instar</HI> is no Adverb, but governs a Gen. by <HI>Adjectivum</HI> in <HI>neutrogen.</HI> and is an Acc. when it has <HI>ad.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Tempori, luci, vesperi</HI> are old Ab∣lativs; <HI>Abii mane cum luci, Plaut. Lu∣ci claro. Varro Epheb.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Cedo</HI> I shew'd to be no Adverb in <HI>As in praesenti.</HI></P>
<P>How <HI>Plus</HI> can be an Adverb I ad∣mire; and as much how it should go∣vern those Cases given it in <HI>Plus
<PB N="56" REF="37"/>
Nom. genitivo</HI>—seing the Verbs there do it: or if <HI>plus,</HI> then you must borrow <HI>quam,</HI> and so make them Ab∣lativs, by <HI>Comparativa per quam</HI>—thus <HI>Hor.</HI> uses it as an Adjectiv, <HI>Plus aequo liber;</HI> and when it has a Gen. as <HI>Auxilii latura plus. id.</HI> it is by <HI>Com∣parativa &amp; superlativa accepta parti∣tivè—</HI>The first <HI>hominum</HI> in his ex∣amples depends on <HI>millia;</HI> the latter on <HI>quinquaginta,</HI> by <HI>Nomina partiti∣va—Passus</HI> in the next example fol∣lows the Verb <HI>abierat:</HI> In that and the first example it governs no word: In the last, <HI>Plus eo,</HI> is plainly by <HI>Comp. per quam</HI>—which <HI>quam</HI> is exprest in the third; and by <HI>Conjunctiones co∣pulativae cum quam</HI>—is of the same Case with <HI>quinquaginta.</HI></P>
<P>Som reject the four first Rules of Conjunctions, as really making no Cases, or Moods alike; but where they are, there is <HI>Syllepsis</HI> or <HI>Zeugma;</HI> as, <HI>Docuit Xenophontem,</HI> and <HI>docuit Platonem. Vixi Romae</HI> by <HI>Omne ver∣bum—</HI>
<PB N="57" REF="37"/>
and <HI>vixi Venetiis,</HI> by <HI>Verum si proprium—</HI></P>
<P>The like may be said of the questi∣on, and its answer; for if I ask <HI>Quis est?</HI> and answer <HI>Petrus, est</HI> is under∣stood to make <HI>Petrus</HI> a Nom. and no otherwise depends it on <HI>quis</HI> the In∣terrogativ.</P>
<P>Besides those Prepositions no∣ted by <HI>Lilly</HI> to be set after their Case I hav red these, <HI>Micenum apud. Tac. Quos advorsum ier at. Sall. Ri∣pam ad. Tac. Hanc circa. Sen.</HI> in his <HI>Trag. Ovilia circum. Vir. Quem con∣tra veneris. Cic. Eo coram. Tac. Quo de ambigitur Cic. Vertice in. Sen.</HI> in his <HI>Trag. Quos inter controversia est. Caes. Metum juxta. Tac. Hamum in∣fra. id. Transtra per. Vir. Te propter. Cic. Te sine. Vir. Thalamo sub fluminis alti. id. Hunc subter. Plin. Ep. Quos super. Tac. Dubium ultra. id.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Lilly</HI> writes <HI>Interseritur inter rel. &amp; verbum:</HI> and yet omits <HI>inter</HI> in <HI>Verba comp. cum à, ab</HI>—though
<PB N="58" REF="38"/>
<HI>inter, per, sub</HI> and <HI>trans</HI> be so in use a∣mong the <HI>Romans: Inter horum aeta∣tes interjectus. Cic. Vide quid inter te &amp; hunc interest. id. Inter eos atque Ariovistum intercederent. Caes. Per ea permeat. Cic. Per haec perventum est. Plin. Ep. Per nos percipere. Cic. Per∣nassia laurus Parva sub ingenti matris se subjicit umbra. Vir. Sub acumen sty∣li subeant. Cic. Cum bonis omnibus sub praecone subjiceretur. id. Trans Taurum arma transmissa sunt. Fest. Rufus. Trans Euphraten trajectos vastavit. id.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sub</HI> for <HI>ante,</HI> we find has an Abl. <HI>Sub oculis domini suam probare ope∣rain studebant. Caes. de Bello Civ. l. 1. Sub oculis accepto detrimento.</HI> ibid. <HI>Sub ipsa die invia petunt. Plin. Nat. Hist.</HI> And for <HI>post</HI> an Acc. <HI>Ille sub haec. Vir. Aen. 5. Sub haec, non ut ante. Hor. Sub hoc tempus. id.</HI> which <HI>Bond</HI> renders <HI>paulo post.</HI></P>
<P>So <HI>super</HI> for <HI>ultra</HI> an Abl. <HI>Et pau∣lum sylvae super his forent. Hor. sc.
<PB N="59" REF="38"/>
ultra:</HI> Bond. <HI>Nocte super mediâ. Vir. sc. ultra.</HI></P>
<P><HI>In</HI> I find variously us'd; and servs to both Cases somtimes: without <HI>to; Esse in amicitiam P. Rom. Cic. In te.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>inter; Reponere in Deos. Cic. In adversariis relinquebas. id.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>contra; In eam invehi solent. Cic. Ostendi disparem fortunam negotio∣rum in Muraena, at{que} in Sulpitio fuisse. id. In matre peccas. Sen. Tragoed.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>ante,</HI> or <HI>ad; Vereor coram in os te laudare. Ter. In oculis summersa. Curt. In anchoris constiterunt. Caes. Viam in Suevos monstrat. id.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>erga</HI> and <HI>contra; Accipit in Teu∣cros animum. Vir. Lapsa est libido in muliere ignota. Cic. sc. erga. In hoc reo finem accusandi facere. id. sc. contra.</HI></P>
<P>To an Acc. only, if it note passing into a place; <HI>Via ducit in urbem. Vir.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>pro; Multis parcit in poenam Plin.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>apud; Non probantur in vulgus. Cic.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="60" REF="39"/>
For <HI>vice; In praesidem esse jussit. Curt.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>formam; Curvatus in antrum. Vir. se. in formam antri.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>usque; In decem annos pariunt. Varro.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>super; Oner a in jumenta extolle∣re. id.</HI></P>
<P>For interpretation; <HI>Servius in Vir∣gilium;</HI> which I think is not among the Ancients.</P>
<P>To an Abl. only; for <HI>cum; Quid inter est in matrona, ancilla peccesve to∣gata. Hor. In puellis urere. id.</HI></P>
<P>For action in a place; <HI>Lucus in urbe fuit. Vir. Spectatur in ignibus aurum. Ov.</HI> And <HI>In tempore veni.</HI></P>
<P><HI>In</HI> with <HI>to,</HI> serves to an Acc. <HI>In</HI> without <HI>to,</HI> to an Abl. is the only short Rule for a Boy.</P>
<P><HI>Horace</HI> has <HI>heu</HI> with a Voc. <HI>Heu posteri negabitis!</HI> and <HI>Ovid,</HI> with a Da∣tiv, <HI>Heu mihi! Amor. l. 2. Eleg.</HI> 19. and <HI>de Ponto l. 4. Eleg.</HI> 6.</P>
<P><PB N="61" REF="39"/>
<HI>Seneca controv. l.</HI> 3. has <HI>prô</HI> with a Voc. <HI>Prô bone Jupiter!</HI> yea, <HI>Lilly</HI> has the like in his examples of <HI>Proh,</HI> while he forgets it in the Rule.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>In Figura.</HEAD>
<P N="14">14. I Take <HI>Apposition</HI> to be no <HI>figure,</HI> and so place it in <HI>Quum duo subst</HI>—</P>
<P><HI>Evocation</HI> is either a Substantiv put in the same Case, with the first, or second person exprest, or under∣stood; or an Adjectiv agreeing with it; or else is implied in <HI>Synthesis,</HI> and so is expunged.</P>
<P>By <HI>Syllepsis</HI> we are taught to make the Verb a Plural, where <HI>&amp;</HI> is be∣tween two Nominativs: yet <HI>Cic.</HI> sais, <HI>Vos &amp; Senatus restitit. Odium &amp; mo∣lestia est perferenda. id.</HI> which are by <HI>Zeugma,</HI> and though <HI>Lilly</HI> say it not;
<PB N="62" REF="40"/>
yet we may turn a sentence spoken by <HI>Zeugma</HI> into <HI>Syllepsis,</HI> and on the contrary: For <HI>Zeugma</HI> regards the word; but <HI>Syllepsis</HI> the sens. Thus, we may say, <HI>Rex &amp; regina beati; sc. sunt;</HI> by <HI>Syll. Rex &amp; regina beata;</HI> or <HI>Rex beatus &amp; regina; sc. est:</HI> by <HI>Zeugma.</HI></P>
<P>And thus you may se the liberty of the Latin tongue.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>In Prosodia.</HEAD>
<P N="15">15. LEt me now tell you, what an excellent salvo <HI>Caesura</HI> is, making a short syllable long after a due foot, if the Poet need it; other∣wise he may giv it a go by.</P>
<P><HI>Ovid</HI> can break <HI>Vocalis ante duas consonantes</HI>—if it were then inven∣ted.</P>
<Q><PB N="63" REF="40"/>
<L>Vadit ad artificem dirae Polymnestora caedis.</L></Q>
<P><HI>Hor.</HI> can make a <HI>dactyl</HI> of an <HI>anapaest,</HI></P>
<Q><L>Militat in sylvis catulus nunc ādhī∣bē puro.</L></Q>
<P>Also <HI>Virgil</HI> can omit <HI>synaloepha</HI> twice in a Vers.</P>
<Q><L><HI>Ter sunt conati imponere</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Pelio</HI> So</NOTE> Ossam.</L>
<L>Et succus pecori, &amp; lac subducitur agnis. id.</L>
<L>Et longum formose vale, vale, inquit Iola. id.</L>
<L>Arctius at{que} haedera procera astringi∣tur ilex. Hor.</L></Q>
<P>Which three last make good the tradition in Schools; that when <HI>Sy∣naloepha</HI> is omitted, the former vowel is common, as here.</P>
<P>Thus <HI>Lilly</HI> uses a <HI>Proceleusmatic</HI> foot (that is four short syllables) in one vers.</P>
<P><HI>Pro salto salio salui, ēt āmīcīō āmīcūi dat. &amp; with spōspondi</HI> breaks <HI>Vocalis ante duas consonantes:</HI> for <HI>Primam
<PB N="64" REF="41"/>
praet. geminantia,</HI> cannot alter Posi∣tion.</P>
<P><HI>Ta</HI> in <HI>occulta spolia</HI>—is long by <HI>Cae∣sura.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Systole</HI> makes a long syllable short; <HI>Tu cavè defendas quamvis mordebere dictis. Ov.</HI></P>
<P>The last syllable of a vers, ending with a vowel, or <HI>m</HI> and his vowel, if the next begin with a vowel, it may be cut off, which is call'd an <HI>Hyper∣meter,</HI> having a syllable too many:</P>
<P><HI>Nilus &amp; antiquo sua flumina reddi∣dit alveo Aethereoque—Vir.</HI></P>
<P>Poets oft make the <HI>5th</HI> foot a <HI>spon∣de; Cecropiumque thymum &amp; gravè olentia centaurea. id.</HI></P>
<P>The last syllable of any vers is common. If a vers end with a vow∣el, and the next begin with one, you may use or leav the former, but scars use <HI>Synaloepha</HI> four times in one line;</P>
<P><HI>At{que} Ephyre, at{que} Opis, at{que} Asia Deï∣opea Et tandem—Vir.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="65" REF="41"/>
Thus also the <HI>Greeks</HI> take a like li∣berty with the Latins, whether neces∣sitated or not; which is <HI>quodam∣modo infinita</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Se the <HI>Greek Grammar.</HI></NOTE> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>Hesiod.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Solon.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Apostrophe</HI> they value not, and cut off Vowels and Diphthongs, before Consonants at pleasure—for all which, Figures and Poets licens were devi∣sed: And what greater liberty, could a Boy desire? but alas! he must only know it and be Tantalized.</P>
<P>Thus <HI>Hor.</HI> further takes his liber∣ty; saying, <HI>tondentes</HI> for <HI>contendentes. Moenia Catili,</HI> for his Brother <HI>Tiberis. Ʋnde domo;</HI> from what hous. So <HI>Mar∣tial, Leporem rumpes equo,</HI> for <HI>delassabis.</HI></P>
<P>The third foot of an Heroic, should not end with a word.</P>
<P N="16">16. Had Books bin exactly Printed, I had saved my self much toil in com∣paring Editions; for errors of the
<PB N="66" REF="42"/>
Press are grown so common, that it puzzles the best of wits somtimes to make sens of Print; thus <HI>In oleastro quadam,</HI> for <HI>quodam Cic.</HI> has deceiv'd many; and from these words in <HI>Cic. Verr. 4. Quid ego injurias colligo? quae in furtis istius, versata esse videantur?</HI> a fam'd Critick, whom I name not for shame, made this Rule; that Som∣times one single antecedent is follow'd by a Neuter relativ: wheras <HI>versata</HI> is <HI>versatae</HI> in good Copies. <HI>Hor.</HI> in <HI>pag.</HI> 232 published by <HI>Macock</HI> 1660, has <HI>damnos ebibimus:</HI> for <HI>damnosè.</HI> So S. <HI>Mat.</HI> 11. 7. <HI>Arundinem qui agitetur:</HI> sais our little <HI>Latin Test.</HI> Now <HI>qui</HI> say som must be an Adverb, and yet spoils the sens: and forrein Editions have <HI>quae.</HI> So S. <HI>Luke</HI> 6. 38. has <HI>metietur</HI> a Passiv, which opposes <HI>Lilly</HI>'s Rule; for <HI>metimini</HI> in the same Vers is Dep. and Deponents admit only an activ or neuter signifi∣cation. Not much unlike to these, is the denying those Books of <HI>Rhet. ad Heren.</HI> to be <HI>Cicero</HI>'s, though <HI>Quinti∣lian</HI>
<PB N="67" REF="42"/>
call him the Author. <HI>Inst. Or. l. 2. c.</HI> 17. It were tedious to insert more testimonies, only that School Books do groan for good Correctors of the Press. It were then to be wished, that they whose right it is, would settle exact Correctors, men of known parts, for every Press; seing publick good, not privat gain, is the design thereof. This would prevent the reception of runa∣gates, and other ignoramuses, who are better at a full Table, than with the Correctors pen; and do wors be∣com the Pulpit. But these are chie∣pest, and will play at small game. What need is there then of a wary admission!</P>
<P N="17">17. I know, many, at first, will say, this savours too much of novelty; and as the <HI>Roman</HI> Emperour <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Quae volumus, &amp; credimuslibenter, &amp;, quae sentimus ipsi, reliquos sentire speramus. <HI>Caes. de bello Civ. l.</HI> 2.</NOTE> said; Men fancy others think, what they would hav be so: yet hav I rather affected to speak the
<PB N="68" REF="43"/>
truth, though with a <HI>Pythagorean;</HI> than be in an error with <HI>Plato</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Cic. Tuse. quaest. 1.</NOTE>; looking upon it a foul crime, that <HI>Grammar</HI> should authorize falsities <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Si Grammaticum se professus quispiam bar∣barè loquatur, hoc turpi∣or sit, quod in eo ipso pec∣cet, cujus profit etur Sci∣entiam. <HI>Cic.</HI></NOTE> and coin new words: to prevent which I hope this Essay will contribute not a little.</P>
<P N="18">18. And thus I hav giv'n a survey of <HI>Lilly,</HI> which will be more satisfacto∣ry, when he shall be view'd as Epito∣miz'd in my <HI>Grammar;</HI> which to be complete, the Reader will perhaps find shorter, than he could hav expe∣cted: for I hav abridg'd from <HI>In Speech,</HI> to the end of <HI>Prosodia,</HI> into less than this, with all those By Rules at <HI>Or∣thographia,</HI> which lock nothing that can be call'd Instructing, and hav large Notes added.</P>
<P N="19">19. Yet is Antiquity, the mortalest enemy unto truth and knowledge; having don its greatest execution, by establishing our belief on its dictates:
<PB N="69" REF="43"/>
as though the authority of the one, should exceed the reason of the other; even when it has deviated from the track of truth. So prevalent is per∣swasion, that <HI>Lilly</HI> allow'd must be like the Pope, <HI>sine crimine;</HI> and we may not detect him, as though it were beyond amendment, or all its errors authoriz'd. Sure his Champions can∣not make it a point of Faith. Ought not the Boys then rather save them∣selvs, <HI>cum bonâ veniâ Praeceptoris,</HI> than defend old <HI>Priscians</HI> head? For as you hav seen, our Rules com short of what they pretend unto: and although there be as many <HI>Grammars</HI> as <HI>Gram∣marians,</HI> yea, more; for <HI>Aldus</HI> set forth abov five, <HI>Moria</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Erasmus in Moriae encomio.</NOTE> calling him Son for his pains; and al∣though likewise ours hav bin compo∣sed since, and had the help of all before, yet is it thus faul∣ty <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Quot enim Grama∣ticorum nugae asperna∣biles?</NOTE>: and hence <HI>puerorum lacrymae.</HI></P>
<P N="20"><PB N="70" REF="44"/>
20. Now if this charge be true, as, true it is, how does Youth spend, or rather mispend their time? and what need is there of altering our Rules, both for their length, and also over∣sights? <HI>Lilly</HI> then thus purg'd <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Addiscend a est (sc. lingua lat.) &amp; facile potest, si Praeceptor adsit judicio probus, qui non circumducat pervaria &amp; supervacua praecepta. Pauca haec, &amp; lectio, in brevi eam dabunt. <HI>Lips. no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ae ad l. 1. Pol.</HI></NOTE> and abreviated, as that an ordinary capa∣city may learn it in about four Months; and understand it so much the bet∣ter <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Brevitas est amica memoriae. <HI>Petrarc.</HI> Si causa permittat, nihil aeque ut brevitas placet. <HI>Plin. Ep.</HI></NOTE>, as it is the shorter: whereas the common <HI>Gram∣mar</HI> is near three years a learning. I say it must needs greatly conduce to the breeding of Youth, and credit of our learned Ma∣sters. For then might they proceed to the Volumes of Classick Authors, a while after they hav begun the <HI>Acci∣dence:</HI> whereas now, they are one day after another toiled with repetitions,
<PB N="71" REF="44"/>
of this and that part of their <HI>Grammar,</HI> and whipt for not understanding and believing superfluities and falsities: and indeed to confine it within so nar∣row a compas, as the Rules of <HI>Gram∣mar,</HI> were both to bereav it of its ex∣cellency, and as <HI>E∣rasmus</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">In Moriae Encomio.</NOTE> sais, is enough to make a man spend his life∣time, in tortures, and be a cross to his ingenuity; not but that the Rules are good, and must be had and taught, yet rather by practice, without such toilsom drudgery, of learning them from end to end: For as <HI>Cicero</HI> per∣swades <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Or. l. 1.</NOTE> us, the common sens of cu∣stom and usual form of speech, heed∣ing the sound of words in sentences, is to be our guide, which would faci∣litate the study, and make it delight∣som; the reasonableness of which I shall now subjoin.</P>
<P N="21">21. If a sentence of bad Latin be uttered, it is first observed to be faul∣ty
<PB N="72" REF="45"/>
by its ill sounding <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Voluptate aurium judicatur Oratio. <HI>Cic. Or.</HI> Mihi placet Latinā rationem sequi quous{que} pa∣titur decor. <HI>Quint. l.</HI> 5. c. 5.</NOTE>, which grates harshly in the ear; and if you require a reason for it, the answer must be, that it is against the usual way or idiom of speaking; against which excursions we are now fenced with Rules; not that they were <HI>ab origine,</HI> for as <HI>Eras∣mus</HI> <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">In Moriae Encomio.</NOTE> sais wit∣tily, what need was there of <HI>Grammar,</HI> when all spake the same language, and nothing was more desired, than to be understood? And where Rules are not particular, and cannot reach the matter, there is no other test, than custom and use: for Rules were borrowed from them, and invented out of a proportionable correspondency to Art; not it guided by Rules, which som as <HI>Lud. Vives</HI> <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">De corr. Art. l. 2.</NOTE> sais, by doing would draw the un∣bounded stream, of Use and Practice,
<PB N="73" REF="45"/>
through; and so pollute the Latin tongue, with foul enormities, by fol∣lowing Art, which cannot compre∣hend use, as is sufficiently shown in those oversights of the <HI>Grammar;</HI> wherby we se that he who follows Authority runs oft against rule, and he who observs rule, disturbs Authori∣ty <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><LG>
<L>Si bene discutias docto∣rum scripta virorum,</L>
<L>Multa seus cernes, quam lex vult Grammaticorum.</L>
</LG></NOTE>, without whose Hand and Seal, the best of Rules is but irre∣gular, hence <HI>Aliud Grammaticè, aliud Latinè loqui.</HI></P>
<P N="22">22. Yet this, as <HI>Suetonius</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">de claris Gram.</NOTE> ob∣servs, drew many after it, through the novelty therof, having an appearing likelihood of reason: wherto it is ve∣ry remarkable, what <HI>Cominius</HI> as∣serts <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">In Ep. Rest.</NOTE>, that who∣so observs the dia∣lect of ancient Writers, shall find that the most learned of them, did ne∣ver concern themselvs with <HI>Grammar,</HI>
<PB N="74" REF="46"/>
so as to approv it, by following its Rules: for neither did <HI>Quintilian</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">l. 1. Inst.</NOTE> undertake to compose an art therof: Art being found out, at first, as is a∣bovsaid, after men spake, and as well, as could be, reduced into Rules, which as they com short of their purpos, did only shew that S. <HI>Peter</HI>'s Successor was not Prime in the consult; else would a Bull bin publish'd against <HI>Priscian,</HI> for condemning his Prede∣cessors (for <HI>Tacitus</HI> sais, he kept a fear∣ful stir) another would bin sent a∣gainst <HI>Valla,</HI> and those after him; <HI>Stoa, Phineas</HI>—as also against <HI>Alvarus,</HI> who is said to hav inveigh'd against <HI>Lilly:</HI> and seing all are so full of mistakes, who but the blind would follow such guides?</P>
<P N="23">23. For, it is evident, that the <HI>Ro∣man</HI> tongue was well pen'd, before the invention of <HI>Grammar;</HI> yea, that the excellency of its speakers gave it a midwifry, such are <HI>Plautus, Naevius,
<PB N="75" REF="46"/>
Livius, Lucretius</HI>—Writers of el∣der date than <HI>Grammar,</HI> which own∣ing its birth to forreiners, becoms a suspected off-spring; and so as to the rigour of it, might be laid aside: the tongue being still attainable by cu∣stom, authority, and exercise <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Ʋsus optimus dicen∣di magister. <HI>Plin. Ep.</HI> &amp; magistorum praecepta superat. <HI>Cic.</HI> Assiduus ingenium &amp; artem saepe vincit. <HI>id.</HI></NOTE>; all which are govern'd by the ear, which is in this kind pleas'd or displeas'd by an inbred, secret and impenetrable har∣mony in nature. I confess it may be nourish'd by Art, but in its infancy.</P>
<P N="24">24. In vain it is then, to say, that we must speak and write by <HI>Grammar,</HI> not by those Classick Authors, for so they confute themselvs, seing it was in∣vented out of a correspondency to their writings; and so, if not them, we must follow none at all; for their wa∣ters came from the others fountain. Let them trifle in Rules, we hav som∣what else of greater import, to speak
<PB N="76" REF="47"/>
<HI>latinè</HI> as a <HI>Roman,</HI> not as a <HI>Grammari∣an,</HI> sais <HI>Montagin</HI> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Essais l. 1. c. 25.</NOTE>, and find there are som who know neither <HI>Case, Tens,</HI> nor <HI>part of Speech,</HI> and yet can entertain you in elegant Latin; and defend <HI>Pri∣scians</HI> head from a blow, as well as those, who hav for many years bin train'd up in that Fencing-school. Af∣ter which said, he puts an opprobrium, upon such Bragadocians of their <HI>Gram∣mar,</HI> who yet, can neither write nor speak the Latin tongue: making it his observation; that he found those the choisest men, who least used it: and these were most accurate in Speech, and the most eloquent Orators, who no doubt would hav recommended it to posterity, had they looked upon it with another eye, than as milk for a Babe, or as spelling for a Reader.</P>
<P N="25">25. Thus <HI>Ascham</HI> sais plainly of Q. <HI>Eliz.</HI> who though she borrowed no∣thing of <HI>Grammar,</HI> but Declension and Conjugation, yet had a most rea∣dy
<PB N="77" REF="47"/>
way of expressing her self; and that both smooth and elegant; so that, he must be more than ordinary, who could do the like. <HI>Scaliger</HI> also, is said, without <HI>Grammar</HI> to hav attain'd the <HI>Greek:</HI> and so, for many thousand years, were all languages learnt, and still may be, with greater expedition and less toil, where <HI>Grammar</HI> is less, and Authors more us'd.</P>
<P N="26">26. Thus <HI>Schorus</HI> sais also, that Children may by imitation, example and custom, (not only come to speak, but) be made better linguists, than by Precepts: and if so, what need this toil upon <HI>Grammar?</HI> this <HI>Cicero</HI> <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">De Or. l. 1.</NOTE> sets his hand unto; and <HI>Quintilian</HI> <NOTE N="w" PLACE="marg">Or. l. 1. c. 10.</NOTE> tels us, it has no ground or foundation other than custom: to which <HI>Gellius</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Noct. Att.</NOTE> givs his suffrage, saying, that among the best of Wri∣ters, the sweet sound of words <HI>(Eu∣phonia)</HI>
<PB N="78" REF="48"/>
was more observ'd, than <HI>Grammar</HI> Rules. And lastly, <HI>Cor∣derius</HI> <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">l. 3. Coll. 34.</NOTE> affirms, that Latin con∣sists, rather in Use and Authority, than in Reason or Rule. Say not then, that Latin differs from all Languages, becaus of Conjugations and Declensi∣ons; as if others wanted them; or they could not be better kept by use, when once, they are got without Book. It is also frivolous to say, that use may do much in others, but Latin being mainly founded in the works of ancient Authors, no expedient can be deviz'd like to <HI>Grammar;</HI> as though it did not rather follow, that those Au∣thors are the fitter for us to learn by; for it is best drinking at the Fountain Head, as the Poet has it, <HI>Dulcius ex ip∣so fonte</HI>—but this is like the <HI>Papists</HI> locking up the Bible: Wheras prac∣tice makes the impression, when Rules are not so effectual: and sure it were more tolerable, as <HI>Fabius</HI> sais, to
<PB N="79" REF="48"/>
speak after the example of <HI>Cic.</HI> or <HI>Caes.</HI> or <HI>Virgil</HI>—though we com short in imi∣tating them. For any by a secret feel∣ing, may discern without art, what is right or wrong by art, and so in Latin.</P>
<P N="27">27. Thus I hav set down the reason of our Youths slow proficiency; and ignorance even in the <HI>idiom</HI> of Latin. Let me now chalk out that way which is as ready, as easy and delightful: in which one years recreation will re∣compens the toil of many; without preposterous task∣ing the Boys <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Inopes rerum nugae{que} canorae.</NOTE> to compose Themes, Orations, or Verses: acts of ripest judgment, and the product of an head well stored, with great reading <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Ex rerum cognitio∣ne efflorescat oportet, &amp; redundet Oratio; quae nisi subest, res ab Orato∣re percepta &amp; cognita inanem quandam habet elocutionem, &amp; p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nè puerilem. <HI>Cle. de Or. l.</HI> 1. Quin∣que faciunt quasi membra eloquentiae; invenire quod dicas; inventa disponere; deinde ornare verbis; post, memo∣riae mandare; tum ad extremum agere ac pronunciare. <HI>Id.</HI></NOTE>, and diligent obser∣vance of elegant Maxims digested in∣to
<PB N="80" REF="49"/>
common places <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Verbaque provisam rem non invitasequentur.</NOTE>: Which alone, can make a copious invention; and without which they cannot be squeez'd out of raw Youth: For <HI>Nemo potest de eâ re, quam non no∣vit, non turpissime dicere. Cic. de Or.</HI> 2. and neither are Boys so confident as to think with the Poets, <HI>Ad rem non pertinere, verum dicere;</HI> who being ei∣ther straitned of necessity, or by grace in speaking corrupted, <HI>id quaeque vocari jubent, quod belle facit ad versum. Sen. de ben.</HI> and hence it was called <HI>Ineptia poëtandi,</HI> by <HI>Ausonius:</HI> so <HI>Angelus Pol.</HI> sais, <HI>scribat Joan. Scotus, &amp; quidem carmine ut sit ineptior:</HI> so <HI>Ter. Varro, Poëtae transilire lineas impune possunt.</HI></P>
<P N="28">28. Were a Child to take it in, as his Mother tongue, from his infancy; the only way to make him prompt, were to follow <HI>Montaign</HI>'s, whose Fa∣ther took in a Master into his Hous, of which se §. 4. and experience tels us, a Nativ tongue is soon attain'd, and if
<PB N="81" REF="49"/>
we follow the same Method, we shal no question accomplish our purpose.</P>
<P N="29">29. But where a Boy can read <HI>En∣glish</HI> well, he may learn to decline Nouns, and conjugate Verbs; with the <HI>Syntax:</HI> which are not taught for lov of themselvs <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">In. Gram. sufficit, eas observationes didi∣cisse, quibus possis &amp; ipse latinè loqui, &amp; quae ab iis latine scripta sunt, intelligere non du∣tem anxiè innumeras lo∣quendi regulas aucupa∣ri, literas{que} inter &amp; syl∣labas insenescere. <HI>Morus.</HI></NOTE>, but to be our guides in Construing, and so will better be ta∣ken in, by use, than by so frequent repe∣titions: the Master may then use him to talk in the same language, having a well composed <HI>Pueriles Sententiae,</HI> the way I learned <HI>French.</HI></P>
<P N="30">30. It were not amiss, if at the same time he carried about him, a <HI>Vocabu∣lary,</HI> with the Latin of the most usual words, we frame our discours in: for with <HI>Erasmus</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Ep. de utilitate Coll.</NOTE>, I know not whether any thing be better learnt, than what
<PB N="82" REF="50"/>
is learnt by play: not that I would hav it got off Book, as now at Schools; for that is like to making a rope of sand; words being wing'd, if unchain'd by a sentence <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Erasmus de Arte No∣toriâ.</NOTE>: but to look a word upon occasion, as discours brings it in. By this means, having learnt his <HI>Grammar,</HI> which is but a few months task, I would enter him upon som good Latin Author, the matter of which should be suited to the Scholars capacity; still the longer, he should procede to the more sub∣lime, and so, Latin would be as ready as English; for, <HI>Ʋsus promptos facit.</HI></P>
<P N="31">31. Let no man laugh at this, and call it a difficult work, or impossible; while I am ready to demonstrate the truth; as I think I hav in a pretty good measure som years before I taught in a Free School; upon a Youth, who had bin three years from School, in all which time he had laid aside his La∣tin: whom, notwithstanding, in four
<PB N="83" REF="50"/>
months time, with only one hours in∣struction daily, I led to the reading of a Physick Book, needing the <HI>Dictionary</HI> (and that but in som words) more than my help; and in the <HI>Greek</HI> to an handsom improvment, so as he could Construe me six or eight verses in the <HI>New Testament</HI> in a morning: should any question the truth hereof, the young Gentleman is not far remote. While I write this, I am credibly in∣form'd, that in the late times, Dr. <HI>Tul∣ly</HI> taught School in <HI>Glocestershire</HI> after this method; and did far outstrip other Masters. Neither know I any diffi∣culty, in practising this method, even in a Free School, were there autho∣rity for it: I am sure, they would have like benefit, if not with advan∣tage to what a private Master can make; for good Masters <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Magni interest quos quis{que} audiat quo tidie domi, quibuscun loquatur à puero. <HI>Cic.</HI></NOTE> like a rich soil, will make the plant of a taller growth.</P>
<P N="32"><PB N="84" REF="51"/>
32. And as we hav so many famous Schools in our Land, I wonder, how it is, that runagate rabble, <HI>suoque simil∣lima coelo</HI> <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">At Emollit gentes elementia coeli.</NOTE>, com so thick in among us? having more need, themselvs, to be taught <HI>English,</HI> and our <HI>Royal Grammar,</HI> than to be Ma∣sters: these are the pest of our Coun∣try: by these have our Boys their learning so mangled, that in Free-Schools we are forc'd to make a seat of every one, sent from those petty pla∣ces.</P>
<P N="33">33. By the former method, a Child might be taught, almost without a Book, in one year, playing: which noble things, if we made our aim, and brought to pass; we should leav no room for those pedling merchants, to possess or insinuate into the heart of an <HI>English</HI> man; but rather if they will, like <HI>Hornets,</HI> swarm in among us; we should imploy them as <HI>Gibeonites.</HI></P>
<P N="34">34. When Latin were thus understood,
<PB N="85" REF="51"/>
they might procede in their Studies; and in a little time, it would appear what peculiar gifts of nature they were endued with: and if there were any secret excellen∣cy <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">A puero adamaram, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Cic. ad Fr. Q. l. 3. Ep.</HI> 5.</NOTE> among them, it would be fetch∣ed out; and a fair opportunity be gi∣ven, to advance it self by; which must greatly redound to the good of this Nation; and bring, even into fashion, the old admired vertues, with much improv∣ment <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><LG>
<L>Sic honor &amp; nomen di∣vinis vatibus a que</L>
<L>Carminibus venit: post hos in∣signis Homerus,</L>
<L>Tyrtaeusqut mares animos in Martià bella,</L>
<L>Versibus exacuit—<HI>Hor.</HI></L>
</LG></NOTE>, now in this purity of Christian know∣ledge.</P>
<P N="35">35. Neither should we need the <HI>Mounsieurs</HI> of <HI>Paris,</HI> to take those flowrs of our Country, into their sleight and prodigal keeping; and send them back again, transform'd only into <HI>Mimics</HI>
<PB N="86" REF="52"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd <HI>Apes:</HI> but other Nations then, would be glad to visit us, for their breeding; or at least would imitate us, in their own Countreys.</P>
<P N="36">36. I do not say, they will in this time, com to an excellent well com∣posed style, in speaking or writing; for with <HI>Plutarch</HI> <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> As natural disposition, without insti∣tution, is blind; so instruction, with∣out a genius and disposition, is defe∣ctiv; and exercise without both, is lame and imperfect. Without which three things, a man cannot be accu∣rat, in any art or discipline: And sure I am, the readiest way to attain it, is by being well verst in those Authors; to which, if the Mother hav luckily contributed store of her wit, they may in time imitate <HI>Tertullian,</HI> for his sen∣tentiousness; <HI>Cyprian</HI> for his gravity; <HI>Jerom</HI> for his resoluteness; <HI>Chrysostom</HI>'s mellifluous flowing; Divine <HI>Ambrose;</HI> devout <HI>Bernard;</HI> Heavenly <HI>Augustin,</HI>
<PB N="87" REF="52"/>
who alone is all the former; Courtly <HI>Esay;</HI> learned <HI>Paul;</HI> elegant <HI>Luke;</HI> fa∣cetious <HI>Erasmus;</HI> pitthy and concise Bishop <HI>Hall,</HI> like a second <HI>Seneca.</HI></P>
<P N="37">37. Or to com to our School Au∣thors; it is a commendable part in Scholars, to be grave as <HI>Cato</HI> Senior was in his praises, sharp in his re∣proofs, witty in discours, subtil in teaching, illustrious both in words and matter; eloquent as <HI>Laelius</HI> and <HI>P. Africanus;</HI> majestical as <HI>Scipio;</HI> of a flagrant wit as <HI>C. Gracchus,</HI> and learn∣ed from a Child; and with <HI>M. Antho∣ny,</HI> relate things to best advantage; with <HI>M. Crassus,</HI> to be accurat in the Latin tongue, and copious in discours; with <HI>Hortensius</HI> to hav a vast memory; studious as <HI>Piso, Tully</HI>'s Son in Law; and with <HI>Julius Caesar,</HI> to take the ad∣vantage of a good light, for well drawn Pictures; by these they may in time be admired with <HI>Salust,</HI> a Prince among the <HI>Latins,</HI> for his ner∣vous brevity; and could they com to
<PB N="88" REF="53"/>
thē height of eloquence with <HI>Cicero,</HI> they might be compared to the <HI>Roman</HI> Empire, and run style it self, unto the uttermost very perfection of Elo∣quence: Their prudence and judg∣ment, with <HI>Corn. Tacitus</HI>'s, would be in esteem; their great eloquence like <HI>Livy</HI>'s in discours, would not be con∣ceal'd, whom though <HI>Lipsius</HI> call <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, and frigid in som places, yet is he copious for the grandure and majesty of his Work before others. <HI>Curtius</HI> for his admired plainness in speech, and grace in discours, subtil and clear, without care most accurat; <HI>Thucydides</HI> almost divine in his speech, grave and brief in elocution; and <HI>Poly∣bius</HI> not much unlike him, were sit ex∣amples for them. I were injurious should I pass over <HI>Homers</HI> excellency, giv'n him by the best of Writers; <HI>So∣lon</HI>'s great liberty in speaking; <HI>Pisistra∣tus</HI> his golden Fishing Net; the palms of <HI>Themistocles</HI> his eloquence, and lau∣rels of Victory: <HI>Herodotus</HI> in History,
<PB N="89" REF="53"/>
compared to a Garden full of trees; whose walks are decked with flowers, casting forth perpetual odors; or <HI>Theo∣pompus</HI> his perspicuity; <HI>Plato</HI>'s elo∣quence abov what is human; whom <HI>Jove</HI> would imitate, were he to speak unto us; <HI>Aristotle</HI> so neat a flower of eloquence, in <HI>Isocrates</HI> his style; whose glory none could equal; <HI>Lycurgus</HI> his prudence; <HI>Demosthenes</HI> as bright as the <HI>Sun;</HI> polite <HI>Phalereus;</HI> heroic <HI>Virgil;</HI> smooth <HI>Ovid;</HI> great <HI>Theophrastus;</HI> sweet <HI>Xenophon,</HI> whose praises none can sing, without his Muse.</P>
<P N="38">38. And whoso can equal any of these, were he born a Prince; then <HI>Brutus</HI> like, would grace the Crown; for as all hav an inbred propensity, to this or that strain; so might our Youth be improv'd, beyond what is ordinary, would but the Masters shorten the way, and release the prisoners, from such drudgery, as <HI>Erasmus</HI> terms it.</P>
<P N="39">39. And thus, I hav presented the Reader with what I had to say, con∣cerning
<PB N="90" REF="54"/>
this Subject. Overlook the mistakes with candour, and account me not imperfect <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Neque est omnino ars ulla, in qua omnia illa, quae ar te effici possunt, à doctore traduntur. <HI>Cic. de Or. 2. For</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Arist. 2. Pol. c.</HI> 6.</NOTE> or deficient, becaus I hav left him work who shall com af∣ter: And seing I know there are ma∣ny who will be dis∣pleas'd hereat; I hav therfor chosen, to bring in the learned speaking, and tell mine opinion in their words: And if, as I confess <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Est enim plenum in∣genui pudoris, fateri per quos profecer is, non ut ple∣ri{que} ex iis, quos atti∣g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, secerunt. <HI>Plin. ad vesp:</HI></NOTE>, I hav transscrib'd most of what is written; I do but as the <HI>Latins</HI> did with the <HI>Greeks;</HI> and the <HI>Greeks</HI> with the <HI>Latins;</HI> Thus <HI>Justin</HI> borrow'd all from <HI>Trogus Pompeius:</HI> and <HI>Julius Solinus,</HI> much of <HI>Pliny. Era∣tosthenes</HI> wholly translated <HI>Timotheus de Insulis,</HI> not reserving the very Preface. The wittiest piece of <HI>Ovid</HI> is beholden to <HI>Parthenius Chius:</HI> yea èven the
<PB N="91" REF="54"/>
magnified <HI>Virgil</HI> hath borrow'd in all his works, his <HI>Eclogs,</HI> from <HI>Theocri∣tus;</HI> his <HI>Georgics,</HI> from <HI>Hesiod,</HI> and <HI>A∣ratus;</HI> his <HI>Aeneids,</HI> from <HI>Homer;</HI> the ex∣ploit of <HI>Sinon</HI> and the <HI>Trojan</HI> Hors, as <HI>Macrobius (x)</HI> notes, he hath <HI>verbatim</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">(n) <HI>Saturnal. l. 5. c.</HI> 2. Se him compar'd in <HI>c.</HI> 3, 4, 5, 6—</NOTE> deriv'd into his se∣cond Book, from <HI>Pisander.</HI> Our own Profession is not excusable herein; Thus <HI>Oribasius</HI> and others, hav greatly transcribed <HI>Galen. Marcellus Empyr.</HI> hath word for word, transcrib'd all <HI>Scribonius Largus, de comp. med.</HI> with his very peroration. Thus <HI>Lucian</HI> and <HI>Apuleius,</HI> served <HI>Lucius Pratensis,</HI> in those Books entitled <HI>Lucius,</HI> by the one; and <HI>Aureus Asinus</HI> by the other. <HI>Clemens Alexandrinus</HI> hath observ'd many ex∣amples hereof, among the <HI>Greeks;</HI> and <HI>Pliny</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">In praef. ad Vesp.</NOTE> sais, that conferring his Au∣thors, he generally found those that went before, <HI>verba∣tim</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Transcriptos ad ver∣bum.</NOTE> transcrib'd,
<PB N="92" REF="55"/>
by those who came after, and their o∣riginals never so much as mention'd; which I hav not thought shame to do; Getting stone and timber of others, yet hav I contriv'd and shap'd the edi∣fice my self: I hav been the Builder, while I sought matter in every place; neither is it the wors, because like the <HI>Bee,</HI> we hav gather'd <HI>ex alienis hortulis.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Contenti simus inventis: aliquid veri∣tati &amp; posteri conferant.</HI> Sen. nat. quaest.</P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="appendix">
<PB N="93" REF="55"/>
<HEAD>APPENDIX.</HEAD>
<P><HI>MƲla</HI> and <HI>equa,</HI> hav the Dat. and Abl. pl. in <HI>is,</HI> as well as <HI>abus: Ex his equis pulli. Varro de re rust. De∣me his mulis parturam. id.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Propert.</HI> sais, <HI>Deis. Val. Flacc. Dei &amp; Deis.</HI> so <HI>manibus ab unis,</HI> and <HI>Lucret. Moribus unit.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Cato de re rust.</HI> and <HI>Lucret.</HI> hav <HI>sal</HI> in the Neuter.</P>
<P><HI>Garumna</HI> is also Masc. <HI>Magnus Garumna. Tibull.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Varro de re rust.</HI> writes, <HI>verris,</HI> not <HI>verres</HI> in the Nom. which also would sound bet∣ter in <HI>Lilly,</HI> being set with <HI>natalis</HI> and <HI>aqua∣lis. Verris octo mensium incipit salire.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Calepine</HI> sais <HI>Pelagus,</HI> is as much Masc. as Neuter, and quotes <HI>Flaccus</HI> lin. 169—<HI>pe∣lagum quantos aperimus in usus:</HI> yet the <HI>Dutch</HI> Ed. writes <HI>pelagus</HI> however,</P>
<P><HI>Divitis ad mensam pelagi sylvae{que} feruntur.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="94" REF="56"/>
The Ancients from <HI>Buceriae{que} greges</HI> in <HI>Lucr.</HI> say <HI>hic &amp; haec grex.</HI></P>
<P>Although <HI>Dictionaries</HI> afford us not <HI>Cures, etis:</HI> yet <HI>Propertius</HI> sais <HI>Jovis Curetis.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Tibullus</HI> and <HI>Varro de re rust.</HI> hav <HI>gelum, li: Cato</HI> also sais <HI>nè gelus noceat,</HI> and I do not remember that I hav red <HI>gelu</HI> in the Nom.</P>
<P><HI>Suet.</HI> sais, <HI>discucurri; Livy discurri. Suet.</HI> and <HI>A. Hirt.</HI> say <HI>percucurri:</HI> and <HI>Pliny</HI> in <HI>Ep. percurri.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Suet.</HI> sais <HI>lacessi</HI> against <HI>Lilly.</HI></P>
<P>Many think <HI>Gerunds</HI> in <HI>di,</HI> hav a Gen. sing. as well as pl. so <HI>Lipsius</HI> in <HI>ep. Ʋt otium sit Italiae ipsius &amp; amicorum videndi.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Lucret.</HI> makes <HI>luci</HI> an Abl.—<HI>in luci quae poterit res Accedere:</HI> and <HI>Varro, vesperi: Far∣ciunt meridie, vesperi:</HI> so <HI>Columella, Se vesperi celant;</HI> and <HI>se vespere celat: vesperi</HI> and <HI>ves∣pere exoritur: vesperi</HI> and <HI>vespere occidit:</HI> they are then far from being Dativ <HI>adverbials.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Suet.</HI> givs an Abl. to <HI>sub</HI> for <HI>ante; Sub exi∣tu vitae voverat:</HI> and an Acc. to <HI>super</HI> for <HI>at; Non amplius ter bibere eum solitum super coe∣nam,</HI> which <HI>Curtius</HI> uses often.</P>
<P>These Prepositions also are red after their Case.</P>
<P><PB N="95" REF="56"/>
<HI>Quibus è Lucr. Te praeter. Tibull. Te supra. Lucr. Aequora longè Trans abeunt. Flacc.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Circum</HI> I read in Comp. and Apposition.</P>
<P><HI>Circumponito circum radices. Cato.</HI></P>
<P>The Ancients us'd to cut off <HI>s,</HI> ending a word, if a consonant follow'd; <HI>Fontibu' mag∣nis, Lucr.</HI> And <HI>s,</HI> with its vowel before a vowel; <HI>Success' indignos noli tu ferre molesté. Cato.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Lu</HI> in <HI>Luceo</HI> is long, yet <HI>Vivaeque producent lūcernae. Hor.</HI></P>
<P>Among the <HI>Comics,</HI> we read <HI>venūstas</HI> and <HI>volūptas:</HI> and <HI>smarāgdos</HI> in <HI>Mart. Sardonichas, smarāgdos, adamantas, iaspidas, uno Portat in articulo.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Lucret.</HI> (like the <HI>Greeks,</HI> with <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>—<HI>quibus nihil est negatum)</HI> makes syl∣lables long and short at pleasure;</P>
<P><HI>Crassa{que} pugnabant liquidis &amp; liquida crassis.</HI> and <HI>Hor.</HI> takes the same liberty: but with <HI>Mart.</HI></P>
<Q><L>Nobis non licet esse tam disertis</L>
<L>Qui musas colimus severiores.</L></Q>
<P><HI>Taliambics</HI> are often us'd, as by <HI>Liv. Andro∣nic.</HI></P>
<Q><L>Dirige odorisequos, ad certa cubilia cānes:</L></Q>
<P><HI>so</HI> Virg.</P>
<Q><L><PB N="96" REF="57"/>
Quanquam animus, meminisse horret, luctu∣que refūgit.</L></Q>
<P>which <HI>refugit</HI> cannot be of the Preter tens, as <HI>Servius</HI> would hav it. Thus he also givs us a dactyl in the sixth foot;</P>
<P><HI>Et spumas miscent argenti, viva{que} sulphura.</HI> In all which cases the <HI>Greeks</HI> go beyond the <HI>Latins.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="57"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

