<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Healing queries for sick churches that is, some seasonable thing begun, whereby the present breaches in churches may be repaired, future rents and divisions prevented, and so all the Lords people have communion not in darknesse but light / published, by a friend to the virgin daughter of Zion.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Friend to the virgin daughter of Zion.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A43196</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H1303</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R12197</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13016561</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13016561</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">96550</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A43196)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96550)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 741:25)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Healing queries for sick churches that is, some seasonable thing begun, whereby the present breaches in churches may be repaired, future rents and divisions prevented, and so all the Lords people have communion not in darknesse but light / published, by a friend to the virgin daughter of Zion.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Friend to the virgin daughter of Zion.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 8 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>[s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1658.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Schism.</TERM><TERM>Concord.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A43196">
<STC T="W">H1303</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13016561</BIBNO>
<VID>96550</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>HEALING QVERIES
FOR
SICK CHVRCHES.</P>
<P>That is,
Some seasonable thing begun, whereby
the Present Breaches in Churches may
be Repaired: Future Rents and Divisions prevented;
and so all the Lords People have <HI>Communion</HI> not in
darknesse but <HI>LIGHT.</HI></P>
<P>PUBLISHED,
<HI>By a</HI> FRIEND <HI>to the</HI> Virgin Daughter
of Zion.</P>
<Q><BIBL>Jer. 8. 22.</BIBL>
<P>Is there no Balm in Gilead? Is there no Physitian there?
Why then is not the health of the daughter of my people
recovered?</P></Q>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed in the Year, 1658.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<OPENER><SALUTE>To all the
GATHERED CHVRCHES
in England, Scotland and Ireland,
PEACE with HOLINES be wished.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Men, Fathers and Brethren,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I May say in <HI>Jacobs</HI> words: <HI>Why do ye look one upon ano∣ther?
Behold I have heard that there is Corn in Aegypt,</HI> Gen.
42. 12. Parents as they are deeply affected with their Childrens
afflictions: so they are carefull to use what means they can for
their recovery. It is very pious and Christian, <HI>for the divisions of</HI>
Reuben <HI>there be great thoughts of heart.</HI> Indeed our eyes cannot
weep enough for the breaches among brethren: yet this is but part of
our duty. <HI>Get thee up</HI> (saith God to <HI>Joshua) wherefore lyest thou
upon thy face?</HI> Josh. 7. 10. Not blaming him for his mourning, but
telling him there was more work to be done. There are three Reasons
(which I shall name) why I have published these Queries. First, that
they may be of some use to <HI>Pastours</HI> and <HI>Teachers of Churches:</HI> who
are most concerned in seeking to <HI>heale</HI> the <HI>breaches</HI> among them. Now
I do not see away more probable for <HI>healing,</HI> than to look into the
Cause of their differences.</P>
<P>As for example, when some Brethren are not satisfied about the
place of <HI>TRIERS;</HI> cannot comfortably joyn in communion with
<HI>Souldiers:</HI> Nor with such as have civill Offices under the present Go∣vernment:
think it a <HI>PUBLIKC SCANDALL</HI> to Religion, that
Church-members should be <HI>Jaylors</HI> and <HI>Judges</HI> of the Saints; and
<PB REF="3"/>
shew no cause why they persecute them: Here it is the Ministers duty
in a speciall manner to appear, where such offences are taken. And by
sound Doctrine prove (if he can) that these scruples and questions do
arise through the ignorance, and weaknes of the Brethren, and that
they are offences taken, but not given.</P>
<P>Secondly, Of some use to such Brethren as desire to keep themselves
pure, and not be partakers of other mens sins: I hope without any fur∣ther
enlargment, those who know what it is <HI>not to defile their gar∣ments,</HI>
God will inable them to make a fruitfull improvement of these
<HI>Queries.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, Because I do intend to prosecute this subject about Chur∣ches
a little further; These <HI>Queries</HI> concern Churches already con∣stituted:
But I have something to publish for their sakes, who are not
yet in Church fellowship. <HI>Lift up your eyes and look on the fields;
for they are white already to Harvest,</HI> Joh. 4. 35. Here I shall shew
(so far as may be hinted by Queries:) first, what things are necessary
that Saints agree upon as <HI>uniting principles:</HI> secondly, what things
(as differences) may be born with: thirdly, what Opinions and pra∣ctises
are destructive to the peace and growth of Churches, which here∣after
shall be constituted. <HI>Because of the house of Jehovah our God,
I will seek good for thee,</HI> Psal. 122. 9.</P>
<P>But in the queries one thing I forgot; Whereas some <HI>Church Offi∣cers</HI>
a while since took great liberty and boldness to write against the
misdemeanour of the late <HI>King,</HI> and in their Sermons, had often that
Text, <HI>Judg. 5. 23. Curse ye Meroh, &amp;c.</HI> What is the reason that Do∣ctrine
is now laid aside? I move this question, to the end that such
who are herein concerned may vindicate themselves: For it is gene∣rally
said, if that which they wrote and preacht against the <HI>King,</HI> had
been done sincerely, and in the fear of God, they would now by Preach∣ing
and Writing, as earnestly perswade people to lcome forth <HI>to the
help of the Lord against the mighty,</HI> as they did then.</P>
<P>The close is thus, so that I may be any way usefull for the overthrow∣ing
of Iniquity, in Church and State, and the advancement of righte∣ousness
in both, I have my end: With me it is a very small thing to
be judged of mans judgment: my judgment is with the Lord,
and my work with my God.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Healing Queries for sick Churches.</HEAD>
<P N="1"><HI>Question</HI> I. WHether in a Church rightly constituted, every member
is not alike under the power of Christ, given to the
Church; that is, whosoever breaks the known laws of
Christ, ought to be admonished and dealt with according to <HI>Mat.
18. 15, 16, 17, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blurred" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 16. 17. 1 Thess. 3. 14. Levit. 19. 17. Gal. 5. 12. 1 Tim.</HI> 1. 20.</P>
<P N="2"><HI>Quest.</HI> II. Whether such Church Members as know any of their
Brethren (in the same fellowship with them) walk disorderly to
the dishonour of God, the scandal of Religion, and hardning wic∣ked
men in their sins; do not wrap themselves in the sin and
guilt of their Brethren; yea, and are murderers before God, if they
seek not to reclaim them, according to the Rules of the Gospel,
<HI>Lev.</HI> 19. 17. with 1 <HI>Joh. 3. 15. Ezec. 3. 18. Jam. 5. 19. 20. Gal.</HI> 6. 1.</P>
<P N="3"><HI>Quest.</HI> III. If a Brother or Brethren sin openly, and the same is
known to the whol Church, but the Church useth not the means
and way, which Christ hath appointed for the humbling and re∣covering
of such scandalous members: The question is, whether
the whole Church be not leavened, and her holy things polluted?
yea, further, it may be queried by what Gospel promise such a
People can expect the presence of Christ in the midst of them, so
long as they remain thus rebellious against the Lord, and the whol
lump leavened: 1 <HI>Tim. 5. 20. Hag. 2. 12, 13, &amp;c.</HI> 1 Cor. 5. 6. <HI>Isa. 1. 11.
to 17. Josh. 7. 12. Hab. 1. 13. Jer. 7. 8, 9. Gen 35. 2, 3, 4. Amos</HI> 3. 3.</P>
<P N="4"><HI>Quest.</HI> IV. Whether Churches are to take Cognizance of the
Sins mentioned by <HI>Paul</HI> in 2 <HI>Tim. 3. 2, 3, &amp;c.</HI> and more particular∣ly,
whether it be their duty to enquire and judge, who are the
<HI>Traitours and Covenant breakers,</HI> there foretold to be in the last
dayes; briefly, whether Churches, (as Churches) ought to judge
the Actions of their members in civill things, that is, about the
lawfulness of mens Callings, Places, Offices, Administrations,
<PB N="2" REF="4"/>
Maintenance? suppose it be State Affairs, (as they call it) what
hath the Church to do with her members in such a case? 1 <HI>Cor. 6.
2. 1 Thes. 4 6. Phil. 4. 8. 1 Cor. 10. 32. 33. 2 Tim. 4. 5. Rev. 2. 2. Heb.</HI> 10. 24.</P>
<P N="5"><HI>Quest.</HI> V. Whether such Church members walk not scanda∣lously
and bring a publick dishonour to the Name of God, who
joyn and act with the open Enemies of the Gospel against the
Saints; that is, persecute their Brethren, apprehend them, and cast
them into prison, will be their <HI>Judges and Jaylors,</HI> and yet have no
matter of Crime to lay to their charge? If so, whether then it be
not a great sin and shame to that Church, who keeps in her bosom
any open persecutors of the Lords people, <HI>Psal. 50. 18. Obe. v. 11, 12,
13, &amp;c. Mat. 24. 48, 49, 50. Act. 9. 4, 5, Mat. 25. 39, 40 43, 45. Ps, 93. 5 1 Pet.</HI> 2. 12</P>
<P N="6"><HI>Quest.</HI> VI. In case the greater number of a Church shall tolerate
and allow apparent sin, in some members, and not deal with them
for the same? what is the duty of the other part (howsoever the
lesser) knowing the walking of such members to be very scanda∣lous
and sinfull (and yet born with by the greater number) that
they may keep themselves pure, and not be partakers of others
mens sin. 2 <HI>Cor. 6. 17. 2 Tim. 3. 2. 3. 5. Hos. 11. 12. 1. Tim. 5. 22. Hos. 2. 2.
Rev.</HI> 3. 4. Or thus, If known scandalous persons are in a Church,
and the Church is dealt with for suffering the same? whether that
Church may lawfully be left and separated from, by Brethren
(many or few, yet so as the lesser number) who have used all due
means and wayes (so far as their duty is) to have the Church pur∣ged
of such defilements? but the <HI>Major part</HI> will not heare, but
rather abets the sinners and justifies the wicked? Again, if the
greater number in such a case may be left, the question is whether
as a true Church, or a company of Rebels, and the visible Church.
State remain with the better part, though fewer in number, <HI>Rev. 2.
5. Jer. 7. 11, 12. Mat. 21. 13 Eccles. 9. 18. 2 Chro. 15. 2. Prov. 17. 15. Jer.</HI> 28. 16.</P>
<P N="7"><HI>Quest.</HI> VII. Whether a Church lying under the guilt of much
sin should not please God far more to execute justice and judge∣ment,
that is, <HI>purge out the old leaven,</HI> and destroy the accursed from
among them, than to pray, preach, fast, break bread, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Yea more,
so long as judgment is neglected, and nothing done against scan∣dalous
walkers? where is there any promise that the Lord will
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
accept of their sacrifices, as Prayer, Preaching, Fasting, <HI>&amp;c. Prov.
21. 3. 1 Sam. 15. 22. &amp;c. Isa. 1. 11 Hos. 6. 6. Mic. 6. 6, 7, 8. Isa. 33. 5. Mic. 3. 10, 11,
12. Jer. 7. 21. 23. Mat. 23. 23, 24. Mat. 5. 23, 2<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Rev. 2. 12. Jam. 4. 8. 1 Pet.</HI> 2. 1, 2.</P>
<P N="8"><HI>Quest.</HI> VIII. Seeing it is well known how the Churches have
been charged with Apostacy publickly to the world, and in them
(as it is asserted) the second Apostacy is fulfilled, set down in 2 <HI>Tim.</HI>
3. 1, 2, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> It is queried, why some thing is not published for their
vindication; Besides it is desired that they will declare, 1. What
Apostacy that is of which <HI>Paul</HI> there speaks, 2. To what time it is
to be applied, 3. How it doth appear that such Churches as are fal∣len
in with the present Government, have not by it made that A∣postacy.
4. What is meant by these words in the Text <HI>from such
turn a side, 2 Pet. 3. 15. Josh. 22. 10, 11. Tit. 1. 9. Act. 11. 2, 3, 4. &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P N="9"><HI>Quest.</HI> IX. Whether such Pastors and Teachers of Churches, as
joyn with this present Government, and have much worldly ad∣vantage
by it; do not by their silence shew either great ingrati∣tude
to their Lord Protector, being as they say a <HI>nursing Father</HI> to
them (if they can justifie the Power and Government which he
hath taken up:) or otherwise, whether they give not just occasion
unto People to think they cannot justifie him, by Law, Reason,
Religion, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> and so it is rather of coveteousness than Consci∣ence,
that they are faln in with him; besides by their silence, whe∣ther
they deal not the more unworthily with their <HI>Nursing father,</HI>
(if they can defend him) considering they well know, how the
most conscientious Christians in the Nation are altogether dissa∣tisfied
about the present Government. <HI>Prov. 27. 10. &amp;</HI> 22. 1.</P>
<P N="10"><HI>Quest.</HI> X. Whereas that place <HI>Rom. 13. 1, 2, &amp;c.</HI> is by our Bre∣thren
often brought against us (as they know it was once the spe∣ciall
objection of Royalists against them and us,) <HI>Let every soule be
subject to the higher powers, &amp;c.</HI> Here we shall propose a few things,
1. If the higher powers must be submitted too, because <HI>they are or∣dained
of God, and are Gods Ordnanceiv.</HI> whether it be not meant,
so far as they are lawfully constituted, &amp; do govern according to
reason and just laws, preserve their peoples Liberties, Persons and
Estates; Again, when they prove Traitors to the Nation, and are
the Devils Agents, whether they may not be severely punished
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
for it. 2. Because <HI>these who resist lawfull authority and just commands
receive to themselves condemnation;</HI> it be not a <HI>non sequitur; Ergo,</HI>
Usurpers must be submitted too, and unjust commands obeyed.
3. Rulers must be obeyed, because <HI>they are not a terror to good
works but to evill, v.</HI> 3. Whether this be a good consequence,
when they are profest enemies to good works, and do evill
continually with both hands; therefore they must be obeyed. 4.
Seeing the Magistrate is to be obeyed, because <HI>he bears not the sword
in vain, he is the Minister of God, a revenger to execute wrath on him
that doth evill, v.</HI> 4. Here the query may be, if he seek to ruin, spoil,
and enslave the people, gives liberty to all manner of unrighte∣ousnes,
bears the sword not onely in vain, in reference to the pub∣lick
good, but draws it forth upon those that are good, and be∣cause
they are good, whither it be the intendment of this text,
<HI>therefore he must be obeyed.</HI> 5. Whither that which is not the Ordi∣nance
of God, but rather of the Devill, and the meer sin, and pre∣sumption
of men, is within the compasse of this Text. 6. Whe∣ther
that which is no point or part of the Magistrates lawfull po∣wer
ordained of God, but <HI>Diametrically</HI> repugnant to it, as Tyran∣ny,
Oppression, Violence, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> is within the Verge of this Text,
and to be obeyed for conscience fake. 7. Whether all the powers
intended in the text, said <HI>to be ordained of God,</HI> are not circumscri∣bed
and bounded with certain rules of Law, Justice, and Honesty,
within which they must contain themselves, and if they passe be∣yond
those limits, they are none of Gods Ordinances; <HI>Consider of
it, take advise and speak your mindes. Judg. 19. 30. Prov.</HI> 22. 21.</P>
<P N="11"><HI>Quest.</HI> XI. Whereas one special cause of the present differences
divisions, and rents in Churches, is this; namely, <HI>That souldiers and
others, who have places under the present Government (being Church
members) are not called to an account as evill doers:</HI> The question is,
whether it be not the duty of Churches, (especially the Officers)
for the satisfaction of their offended Brethren, to give some rea∣sons,
that howsoever there is offence taken at Souldiers and o∣ther
State <HI>Officers,</HI> yet they have the word of God to warrant their
practise in holding communion with them, <HI>Isa. 8. 20. 2 Tim. 3. 16, 17
Tit. 1. 9. 2 Tim. 2. 24, 25. Acts 20 2<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="smudged" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 2 Cor. 1. <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="smudged" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>4. 1 Thess. 2. 7, 8, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P N="12"><PB N="5" REF="5"/>
<HI>Quest.</HI> XII. In like manner, where as it is well known that the
place of <HI>Tryers.</HI> (as it is commonly called) hath given offence to
many pretious Christians, and occasioned much trouble in some
Churches, no lesse than division; the query is, whether it be not
the Duty of such TRIERS as are Church-members to prove (if
they can) what they act in that particular business to be lawfull
by the Word of God, 1 <HI>Cor. 10. 32, 33. 1 Pet. 5. 2, 3. 1 Cor. 8. 12,
13. &amp; 9. 22, 23. 1 Thess. 5. 22. 1 Joh. 2. 10. Isa. 57. 14. 2 Cor. 8. 21 &amp;</HI> 13. 7.</P>
<P N="13"><HI>Quest.</HI> XIII. Whereas in the dayes of the late King, many ho∣nest
men for refusing to submit to an Arbitrary Power, and Ille∣gall
Taxes, and standing for the Rights and Liberties of the Peo∣ple,
suffered very much in their Liberties and Estates, and were
counted for it, <HI>Good Patriots to their Country:</HI> The question is, if
in Churches there are some Persons, who shall promote an Arbi∣trary
Power, and seek to destroy the civill Rights and Liberties of
the People? whether this be not a <HI>Scandall</HI> to Religion, and a
matter which the Church is to take notice off, and to deal with
such members as offenders, 1 <HI>Cor. 6. 8, 9. 1 Tim. 1. 13. Job 24. 2.
Psal. 50. 18. Deut. 19. 14. &amp; 27 17. Prov. 22. 28. Phil. 4 8. 1 Thess,</HI> 4. 12.</P>
<P N="14"><HI>Quest.</HI> XIV. Whether in all Ages the Lord hath not had some
glorious work proper to every Generation;<NOTE PLACE="marg">* Whereas Mr. <HI>William Bridge,</HI> preaching lately at the <HI>Charterhouse, May</HI> 23. 1658. Told his Hearers, That there is now <HI>a Gene∣ration work, a generation Truth, and generation Sins.</HI> Whether it be not the du∣ty of all <HI>Pastors</HI> and <HI>Tea∣chers,</HI> clearly to declare unto their people, when the proper <HI>Work, Truth</HI> &amp; <HI>Sins</HI> are of this generation. <HI>Psal. 40. 10. Jer. 23. 28. Rom.</HI> 1. 18.</NOTE>
if so, what is the Work now, as most proper
to the Saints of this Generation; <HI>Acts 13. 36.
2 Tim.</HI> 3. 1. 5. Or thus, whether to bear wit∣ness
to and for the glorious and visible King∣dome
of <HI>Jesus Christ,</HI> and to hold forth a pub∣lick
Testimony against the present Powers
of the World, that they shall be all broken to
pieces, and <HI>the Lord alone exalted as King of
Saints and Nations;</HI> be not now a Work
more proper to the Churches and People of
God than it was to Saints in former Ages;
<HI>Dan. 2. 44 &amp; 7. 13, 14. &amp; 12. 8, 9, 10. Rev. 22. 10. Act. 1. 6, 7. Isa.</HI> 35. 5.</P>
<P N="15"><HI>Quest.</HI> XV. Whereas <HI>Rev.</HI> 11. 16. There is mention made of
the <HI>twenty foure Elders,</HI> but the <HI>foure living Creatures,</HI> are left out
of the Text; The question is, whether it may not probably be
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
concluded from the place, (comparing our present experience
with it) that neer or about the expiration of the <HI>Fourth Monarchy,</HI>
when <HI>the Kingdoms of this world, are to become the kingdomes of our
Lord and his Christ;</HI> there will be a generall declining of <HI>Church-Officers</HI>
from the work of that Generation, and the Brethren,
(not in Office) more faithfull than their Pastors and Teachers, in
holding forth a publick Testimony to the glorious Kingdom and
and Reign of Christ, <HI>Psal. 8. 2. Isa. 26. 2. Jer. 50. 45. 1 Cor. 1. 26, 27.
Isa. 29. 9. 10, 11, 12. 18. &amp; 43. 27. Rev. 12. 4. Joel</HI> 3. 15, 16.</P>
<P N="16"><HI>Quest.</HI> XVI. Whereas the late divisions and rents in many
Churches have <HI>risen from Souldiers and others, who have places un∣der
the present Government;</HI> It be not necessary that all Churches
(as yet free from the occasion of such trouble) do well consider
what they do, before they admit Souldiers and others (so much
excepted against) into Church Fellowship? Again, for others who
either intend to joyn to some Church already gathered, or to
constitute themselves a Church? Whether it do not likewise ve∣ry
much concern them to avoid that thing which others have
been so much prejudiced by: As a wise man will not run his Ship
upon that rock, on which he sees another Vessel is split before his
eyes. <HI>Prov. 22. 3. Ezra 4. 1, 2, 3. 1 Cor.</HI> 5. 6.</P>
<P N="17"><HI>Quest.</HI> XVII. Whether Churches in such a day as this is, should
not make diligent enquiry, what it is that hinders their glory and
growth? What it is that keeps the bad in, and the good out?
whence it is that they do not experience so much life, sweetnesse,
and divine Presence in Church Ordinances as formerly they did?
Again, would they be conscientious, and sincere in searching for
the cause? then, whether it would not be found: First, <HI>Negli∣gence</HI>
in some Officers, who look more after the world than after
the walking of their Flock, and seek to keep up state and pompe
in their own Family, more than purity and holines in the house of
God. Secondly, <HI>Arrogancy</HI> and Pride in some Members who be∣ing
<HI>Statesmen,</HI> are like the <HI>Sons of Zerviah, too hard for the rest:</HI>
For through fear some dare not speak to them of their scandalous
walking; others by gifts and preferment have their mouths stopt,
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
though not their consciences, others care not for it, as if (<HI>Caa<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blurred" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣like</HI>)
they were <HI>not their brothers keeper,</HI> Thus though the wicked∣nes
of some Church members be like <HI>Gehazis leprosie upon the fore
head of the Church;</HI> and the world cryes shame on it; yet the
Church hath neither an ear to hear, nor an ey to see, <HI>Lam. 3. 40.
Josh. 7. 5, 6. 2 Cor. 7. 9, 10, 11. Ezec. 3. 4, 5, &amp;c. Mat.</HI> 18 7.</P>
<P N="18"><HI>Quest.</HI> XVIII. Whether unfaithfulness among Churches in
neglecting their Christian Duty each to other, that is, not admo∣nishing
one another of the great corruption, which they see crept
into Churches (especially the deceitfull walking of some <HI>Church-Officers,</HI>
who were winked at, when they openly sought by LET∣TERS
and other wayes to corrupt the Churches) hath not (by
the just hand of God) brought many troubles and divisions upon
them: Again, if a Church be corrupted by suffering scandalous
persons in it, what is the Duty of a <HI>Sister Church</HI> knowing the
same to, be true? And how far, and how long may a Church
hold communion with any Church, which keeps scandalous per∣sons
in communion howsoever admonished of it.</P>
<P N="19"><HI>Quest.</HI> XIX. Whether the <HI>stop,</HI> that hath been put to the Lords
work, and the <HI>good old Cause</HI> once famous in the <HI>three Nations,</HI> with
what present oppression and persecution is amongst us: hath not
been raised and continued in a speciall manner, by some <HI>Church-members;</HI>
And whether such Church members have not been
more false to the Interest of Christ and his People, then any o∣ther
people, and betrayed the most glorious Cause that ever was
in the world. <HI>Jer.</HI> 11. 15.</P>
<P N="20"><HI>Quest.</HI> XX. Whether <HI>Pride</HI> and <HI>Covetousness</HI> (so much con∣demned
in holy Scripture) are sins to be born with in Churches?
If not, what is the reason that few (if any) Church members,
though never so apparently <HI>proud</HI> and <HI>Coveteous</HI> are called to an
account for such sins. Besides, whether for <HI>Pride</HI> and <HI>Coveteous∣nesse,</HI>
some <HI>WITHIN</HI> do not far exceed most <HI>WITHOƲT; Prov. 8. 13
Hos. 5. 5. 1 Joh. 2. 16. Isa. 2. 12. Mal. 3. 15. 2 Tim. 3. 2. Jam. 4. 6. Psal. 10. 3.
1 Cor. 6 10. Ephes 5. 5. Luk. 12. 15. Col 3. 5. Isa. 5<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 11. Ezec. 16. 48. 51. 1 Cor. 5. 4
Thou canst not bear them that do evill,</HI> Rev. 2. 2.</P>
<P N="21"><HI>Quest.</HI> XXI. Whereas the <HI>Name of God and Religion,</HI> lies under
so much reproach everywhere, by reason of the Apostacy, Hypo-
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blurred" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>hood of Professors; for many hereby are hindred from joyn∣ing
to Churches: Others hardned in errour and sin; yea, many
by this occasion are become Libertines, Blasphemers, Atheists, and
what not? Query is, How far it is the duty of Churches, publick∣ly
to appear in vindicating the <HI>great name of God,</HI> and wiping off
that scandal and reproach which lies upon the truth &amp; them too.
<HI>Exo. 32. 32. Josh. 7. 9. &amp; Psa. 122. 9. &amp; 137. 5, 6. Numb. 25. 13. Joh. 2. 17.
Neh. 2. 3. Prov.</HI> 22. 1.</P>
<P N="22"><HI>Quest.</HI> XXII. That some Brethren at this time not holding
forth a faithfull Testimony, against the corruptions crept into the
Churches, and shewing the Churches their evill and sin: so far as
their light and duty is: whether this be not one great cause, that
the abuses and corruptions now in Churches are not reformed?
Further the Query is, In what <HI>souldanger</HI> that member is, who hath
made a solemn Covenant before the Lord with his Brethren to
practise all known <HI>Gospel order, Christian <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> &amp; duties,</HI> both to the
Church and every individuall member, shall notwithstanding
(contrary to the light of his own conscience) break that Cove∣nant
so solemnly made in the principall part of it. <HI>Prov. 14. 25.
Ezek. 2. 7. Isa. 58. 1. Jer. 23. 22. Ephe. 17. 15, 16, 17, 18. Rom. 1. 31. Psal.</HI> 15. 4.
Rom. 21. 27. and 22. 15. 1 <HI>Joh. 3. 20. Ruth. 3. 18. Isa. 30. 9. and</HI> 63. 8.</P>
<P N="23"><HI>Quest.</HI> XXIII. Our last Query shall be; first, Whether there be
not good ground to think, when the Lord shall bring forth his
judgements against the Nations of the world, he will <HI>begin at his
own house; Jer. 25. 18. 29. Eze. 9. 6. Amo. 3. 2. 1 Pet.</HI> 4. 17.</P>
<P>Secondly, Whether the Lords controversie at this time against
Churches, be not their neglect of judgement? <HI>Isa.</HI> 59. 4. 9. 14, 15.</P>
<P>Thirdly, Whether there be any way (following the Word of
God) for Churches to escape publique judgments, than to purge
out unclean persons and things? <HI>Josh. 7. 13. 26. 2 Sam. 21. 14. Rev. 2.
5. 16. J<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="smudged" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI> 1. 15.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="7"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

