<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached in the collegiate church of St. Peter in Westminster, on Wednesday May 29th, 1661 being the anniversary of His Majesties most joyful restitution to the crown of England / by Peter Heylyn ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Heylyn, Peter, 1600-1662.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A43551</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H1734</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R12653</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13016933</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13016933</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">96577</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A43551)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96577)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 741:40)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached in the collegiate church of St. Peter in Westminster, on Wednesday May 29th, 1661 being the anniversary of His Majesties most joyful restitution to the crown of England / by Peter Heylyn ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Heylyn, Peter, 1600-1662.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 44 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by E.C. for A. Seile,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1661.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Includes bibliographical references.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXI, 21 --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2002-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A43551">
<STC T="W">H1734</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13016933</BIBNO>
<VID>96577</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A
SERMON
Preached in the
Collegiate Church
OF
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>PETER</HI> in <HI>WESTMINSTER,</HI>
On Wednesday <HI>May</HI> 29<SUP>th.</SUP> 1661. Being the Anniversary of his <HI>Majesties</HI> most joyful
Restitution to the Crown of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>By <HI>PETER HEYLYN,</HI> D. D.
Chaplain in Ordinary to his Majesty, and one of
the <HI>Prebendaries</HI> of that Church.</P>
<Q><BIBL>2 Sam. 19. 14.</BIBL>
<P>And he bowed the heart of all the men of <HI>Judah,</HI> even as the heart of one
man; so that they sent this word unto the King, <HI>Return thou and all
thy servants.</HI></P></Q>
<Q><BIBL>August. de Civit. Dei. lib. 1. cap. 7.</BIBL>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>squis non videt, caecus: quisquis videt nec laudat, ingratus: quisquis
laudanti reluctatur, insanus est.</P></Q>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI>
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>inted by <HI>E. C.</HI> for <HI>A. Seile</HI> over against St. <HI>Dunstans</HI> Church
in <HI>Fleetstreet.</HI> M.DC.LXI.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the READER.</HEAD>
<P>THis <HI>Sermon</HI> gods not to the <HI>Press</HI> for want of <HI>Hearers,</HI>
for seldom hath been seen a more numerous <HI>Auditory</HI>
then was assembled in this <HI>Church</HI> at the Preaching of
it. Nor doth it go into the world to seek for <HI>Readers;</HI> who should
not be sollicited to the losse both of time and patience, if nothing
more than <HI>ordinary</HI> did present it to them, and perhaps not that.
Some <HI>Guests</HI> are commonly best pleased when they are least
<HI>courted,</HI> and think themselves most welcome when they are not
looked for. And yet the <HI>Master of the feast</HI> in our Saviours <HI>Pa∣rable,</HI>
when the invited <HI>Guests</HI> neglected or refused to come,
sent forth his Servants into all the <HI>streets</HI> and <HI>lanes</HI> of the <HI>City,</HI> to
bring in all that could be found, whether <HI>good</HI> or <HI>bad,</HI> till he had
filled his <HI>Table,</HI> and made up his company▪ And 'twas a <HI>wedding
dinner</HI> too, which our Saviour speaks of. A <HI>feast</HI> prepared for
celebrating the most joyful <HI>Marriage</HI> betwixt <HI>Christ</HI> and his
<HI>Church;</HI> or (as this was) betwixt a <HI>Mighty Prince,</HI> and a
<HI>loving People.</HI> But so it is in all great Meetings of this nature,
that many come not to the <HI>feast,</HI> though they are expected; and
many come not time enough to enter when the <HI>Bridegrome</HI> doth;
some cannot reach to that which is set before them, and others
have received no <HI>invitation</HI> to attend the <HI>Nuptials.</HI> Who not∣withstanding
would not easily be contented with the <HI>fragments
of it,</HI> though they should possibly amount to as many <HI>baskets full,</HI>
as the first provision. And therefore▪ that the honest desires of some,
and even the curiosity of others, may not rest unsatisfied, it is now
served in <HI>cold</HI> but <HI>whole;</HI> with <HI>grace</HI> before it, and <HI>grace</HI> after
it, lest otherwise there might be some defect in the <HI>entertain∣ment.</HI>
Nothing remains, but that the <HI>Guests</HI> fall to, and much
good may it do them.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Westminster, <DATE>Iune
8▪ 1661.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epigraph">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>PSALM XXXI. ver. 21.</HEAD>
<Q><BIBL>Versio Septuagint. Interpret.</BIBL> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></Q>
<Q><BIBL>Versio Vulgaris.</BIBL> Benedictus Dominus, quoniam mirificavit misericordi∣am
suam mihi in Civitate munita.</Q>
<Q><BIBL>Versio Sancti Hieron.</BIBL> Benedictus Dominus, quoniam mirabilem fecit miseri∣cordiam
suam mihi, in Civitate munita.</Q>
<Q><BIBL>Versio Tremelii.</BIBL> Benedictus sit Iehova; quia mirificam reddit benigni∣tatem
suam erga me, ut in Civitate munita collo∣cans
me.</Q>
<Q><BIBL>The Old English Translation.</BIBL> Thanks be to the Lord: for he hath shewed me mar∣vellous
great kindness in a strong City.</Q>
<Q><BIBL>The New English Translation.</BIBL> Blessed be the Lord: for he hath shewed me his marvel∣lous
kindness, in a strong City.</Q>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>A
SERMON
Preached at the
Collegiate Church
OF
S<SUP>t</SUP> PETER in WESTMINSTER,
On Wednesday May 29<SUP>th.</SUP> 1661.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>PSALM XXXI. 21.</BIBL>
<Q>Blessed be the Lord, for he hath shewed me his
marvellous kindness, in a strong City.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>1. <HI><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>ERMO opportunus est optimus.</HI> It is
affirmed by <HI>Solomon,</HI> amongst his
Proverbs,<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Prov. 15. 23</NOTE> that <HI>a word spoken in
due season,</HI> is like to <HI>apples of gold in
pictures of silver;</HI> that is to say, as
pleasing to the ear and understanding of judicious men,
as Jewels made like <HI>apples of gold</HI> in nets <HI>of silver,</HI>
are in the eyes of curious and magnificent persons.
And of this nature is the Text now read unto you, ac∣commodated
to the time, to the present Solemnity. A
Text of Thankfulness, and a Time of Thankfulness:
A Time of great deliverance, and a Text of great de∣liverance.
And as the Text, such also is the Psalm
out of which it is taken; A Psalm of Consolation,
and a Text of Comfort; a Psalm of Confidence, and
a Text of Confidence. A Psalm of Confidence, <HI>In
<PB N="2" REF="4"/>
te Domine speravi, In thee, O Lord, do I put my trust,</HI>
so it begins. A Psalm of Consolation, <HI>Viriliter agite,
Be of good courage, and you shall be strengthned in the
Lord,</HI> with which words it ends. From the begin∣ning
to the end, it speaks Gods infinite mercies unto
his Anointed, and in him to us. As for the form, it is
like many of the rest, Plaints mixt with Prayers, things
present mingled with things past; the sad remem∣brance
of his former troubles, indeared and sweetned
by the consideration of some marvellous mercies which
God had shewed unto him after all his troubles. But
what this kindness was, how <HI>great,</HI> how <HI>marvellous;</HI>
how <HI>David blessed</HI> the name of God for so great a
mercy, and what we are to do upon the sense and ap∣prehension
of the like felicity; we shall the better see,
if you shall please to joyn with me in humble and
hearty Prayer to Almighty God, <HI>&amp;c. Our Father
which art in Heaven,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>2. <HI>Victori Psalmus David.</HI> The Title of this Psalm
(as St. <HI>Hierom</HI> reads it) makes it to be composed in
memory of some great deliverance, which God, the
giver of all victory had <HI>marvellously</HI> wrought for his
servant <HI>David.</HI> But what particular deliverance it
was, which is herein celebrated, hath been made a
question. <HI>Lyra,</HI> a natural <HI>Iew</HI> by birth, affirmes upon
the credit and authority of <HI>Rabbi Solomon,</HI> that <HI>David</HI>
framed this Psalm, <HI>existens in persecutione Saulis;</HI>
when he was under those calamities which were for∣ced
upon him by the house of <HI>Saul;</HI> or rather, On
the sense and remembrance of them, as from the com∣position
of the Psalm may be easily gathered. <HI>The∣odoret,</HI>
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
an old <HI>Greek</HI> writer, thinks rather, that it was
composed by the Royal Pen-man, <HI>Cum ab Absolome
persecutionem pateretur,</HI> when he was outed of his
Kingdom by the arts of <HI>Absalom.</HI> Which difference,
how great so ever it appears, may be soon agreed.
For, even the Treason of <HI>Achitophel,</HI> and the Rebel∣lion
of <HI>Absolom,</HI> were cherished and fomented by some
Grandees of the house of <HI>Saul,</HI> as we may be clearly
evidenced by some passages of the Sacred Story, in
which it is affirmed, that <HI>Shimei who threw stones</HI> at him,
and reviled him for a man of bloud, when he was
forced to quit <HI>Hierusalem</HI> to the party of <HI>Absolom;</HI>
was <HI>of the family</HI> or kindred of the house of <HI>Saul;</HI>
And <HI>Sheba</HI> who revived the War,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 20. 1.</NOTE> and <HI>blew the
Trumpet</HI> of Sedition, when all the people were re∣turning
to their old obedience, is plainly said to be
<HI>a man</HI> of the <HI>Tribe</HI> of <HI>Benjamin,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 16. 5.</NOTE> (which was <HI>Sauls</HI>
own <HI>Tribe</HI>) and generally believed to be of <HI>Sauls</HI> kin∣dred
also, who could not easily lay aside their hopes
of the Crown of <HI>Israel,</HI> till all <HI>Sauls</HI> sons were hang∣ed
in <HI>Gibeah</HI> before the Lord, of which the Scripture
speaks in the second of <HI>Samuel,</HI> chap. 22. So that
we may declare in favour of the first opinion, that the
great kindness, so much magnified by the Royal Psal∣mist,
relates to his deliverance from the house of <HI>Saul,</HI>
when he was setled in <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> and reigned in
peace and glory over all the <HI>Tribes.</HI> In which estate
he sung this <HI>Benedictus</HI> to the Lord his God, that is
to say, <HI>Benedictus Dominus, Blessed be the Lord, for
he hath shewed me his marvellous kindness in a strong
City.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="5"/>3. The Text it self contains in it these two gene∣ral
Parts, God's Mercy, <HI>David</HI>'s Thankfulness; God's
mercy unto <HI>David</HI> in that great deliverance, and
<HI>David</HI>'s thankfulness unto God for so great a Mercy.
In the first General, God's Mercy, we have these par∣ticulars;
The Subject of it first, and that was <HI>David, Da∣vid
the King,</HI> the Lord's Anointed, one chosen by the
Lord out of all his Family, to be the blessing of his
Tribe, and the Prince of his People; <HI>Mirificavit mihi,
He hath shewed to me.</HI> 2<SUP>ly</SUP> The condition &amp; extent there∣of,
as being not only called a kindness, a great <HI>kindness</HI>
too, in our old Translation; but, <HI>misericordia mirabi∣lis,</HI>
a marvellous <HI>great kindness;</HI> a <HI>kindness</HI> which
had very much of a Miracle in it. 3<SUP>ly;</SUP> The Author,
or the Donor of it, <HI>Misericordia sua;</HI> His kindness, or
the Lord's own <HI>kindness.</HI> And lastly, On what Thea∣tre,
or Stage, this marvellous kindness of the Lord
was acted, <HI>in Civitate munita,</HI> in a strong City.
Over all which, I mean to draw so thin a veil, that
under it we may behold the face of our own affairs,
but helped by some reflections from the <HI>Glass</HI> of Scri∣pture,
and some comparisons of the <HI>Copy</HI> with the old
<HI>Original.</HI> In the next General, <HI>David</HI>'s Thankfulness,
we shall observe the Retribution which he made to
the Lord his God for such multiplyed mercies, whe∣ther
it were expressed in his words, or actions. And
then the duties of the Day will come in of course, as
the Conclusion followeth on the Premises in a well∣formed
Syllogism. I begin therefore with the first
General, God's mercy unto <HI>David</HI> in that great de∣liverance,
and therein first of all with the Subject of
it, <HI>David the King,</HI> the Lord's Anointed, the Author
of this Psalm, and the argument of it.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="5"/>4. <HI>Expertâ morbi molestiâ, evidentior fit jucun∣ditas
Sanitatis,</HI> as St. <HI>Austin</HI> hath it. None can so
rightly estimate the benefit of a perfect health, as he
who hath been long oppressed with a languishing
sickness. Contraries set together, do most perfectly
illustrate and express each other. If therefore we
would know, how great God's kindness was to <HI>Da∣vid</HI>
in the time of his Glories, we must a little look
upon him in his fall, in his lowest fortunes, his wan∣derings
in the vale of misery, or rather, in the <HI>Val∣ley
of the shadow of Death,</HI> as his own words are.
A misery which fell upon him when he least looked
for it, when he conceived himself most happy, and
on the steps of his Ascendent to the <HI>Throne of Israel;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 16. 13.</NOTE>
Anointed privately by <HI>Samuel</HI> in his Father's House,
and by that art designed for the next <HI>King</HI> of the House
of <HI>Iacob:</HI> Of great esteem amongst the people,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 17. 24.</NOTE> for
taking up their quarrel against <HI>Goliah,</HI> when all men
else fell off, and refused the combate; Amongst the
Priests, as men that had some secret notice of the
designation, or otherwise, beheld him as a man re∣plenished
with the Spirit of God; Amongst the Cour∣tiers
as a <HI>Prince</HI> of the <HI>Royal Family,</HI> in being mar∣ried
unto <HI>Mich<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l</HI> his Master's Daughter;<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 28. 28.</NOTE> Amongst the
Military men for his singular valour made known in
many fortunate skirmishes against the <HI>Philistims,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 18. 27.</NOTE> two
hundred of whose fore-skins he brought back with
him for a sign of his Victory; And, finally, amongst
the <HI>Damosels</HI> or Ladyes of <HI>Israel,</HI> for his personal
gallantry, who <HI>playing</HI> on <HI>their Musical</HI> Instruments,
did use to answer one another, saying, That <HI>Saul
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
had slain his Thousands,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 18.</NOTE> <HI>and</HI> David <HI>his Ten Thou∣sands.</HI></P>
<P>5. But, <HI>Eminentis fortunae comes est invidia,</HI> said
the Court-Historian. This general applause and those
publique honours, made him a fit subject for as great
an envy; and drew upon him the displeasure of that
mighty Tyrant, who looked not only on him as his Ri∣val
in pursuit of glory, but a competitor with the
Princes of the house of <HI>Kish</HI> for the Regal Diadem.
And being once possessed with these <HI>fears</HI> and <HI>jea∣lousies,</HI>
he thinks of nothing but to bring him to a swift
destruction;<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 19.</NOTE> and to that end incenseth all his servants
to conspire against him,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 19. 1.</NOTE> reproves his daughter for
not betraying her husband to his rage and fury, and
darts a Javelin at his own son <HI>Ionathan</HI> for daring
to affect the man whom his father hated.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 20. 33.</NOTE> No safety
being to be found for <HI>David</HI> in or neer the Court,
he must be take himself to places more remote and pri∣vate;
and in his flight obtains both Arms and Victuals
from <HI>Abimelech,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 21. 6, 9.</NOTE> being at that time the <HI>High Priest</HI> of
the <HI>Iewish</HI> Nation. For which small courtesie <HI>Abimelech</HI>
himself, and more then fourscore of the Priests, such
as <HI>did wear a linnen Ephod,</HI> as the Text informs us,
were miserably slaughtered by the hands of <HI>Doeg</HI> a ma∣litious
<HI>Sycophant;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 22. 18, &amp;c.</NOTE> their City sacked, their Wives and
Children smitten with the edge of the Sword; <HI>their
Sheep, their Oxen, and their Asses,</HI> together with the
rest of their goods and substance,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1</NOTE> given over for a
prey to their Barbarous Enemies. Poor <HI>David</HI> in the
mean time had retired to <HI>Akish</HI> the <HI>King of Gath,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 21. 10.</NOTE> and
consequently the old Enemy of his native Countrey,
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
where he could promise to himself no great hopes
of safety, considering those many sorrows and that
foul dishonour he had wrought unto them in the death
of their Champion.</P>
<P>6. I should both tire my self and afflict your pa∣tience,
if I should lead him back again to the land
of <HI>Iudah,</HI> follow him there in all his wanderings,
from thence wait upon him to the Court of <HI>Moab,</HI>
where he was forced to leave his Parents, that he
might save them from the fury of the present Army.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 22. 3.</NOTE>
And he might rather choose to leave them in that
Countrey then in any other, by reason of his Descent
from <HI>Ruth,</HI> a <HI>Moabitish</HI> woman, as the Scripture tells
us; and therefore like to find some favour amongst
those of her kindred. But look upon him where
we will, either in the cave of <HI>Adullam,</HI> the wilder∣ness
of <HI>Ziph,</HI> the Desarts of <HI>Mahum,</HI> or the Rocks and
Mountains of <HI>Engeddi, (Inter Serpentes aprosque avi∣d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sque
Leones),</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 23.</NOTE> and we shall find him no where
safe from the hand of his Enemies as long as he conti∣nued
in the Realm of <HI>Israel.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 23. 20.</NOTE> The <HI>Keylites,</HI> whom he
had redeemed from the power of the <HI>Philistims,</HI> re∣solved
to have betrayed him to the malice of <HI>Saul,</HI>
had he not been fore-warned by God of their ill in∣tentions.
The men of <HI>Ziph,</HI> more savage then the wild
Beasts in all those Desarts, had entertained the like de∣sign,
but were as happily prevented as the treacherous
<HI>Keylites. Nabal</HI> the churl, whose flocks had been pro∣tected
by him from all Thieves and Robbers refused to
gratifie him with some part of that superfluity which
was provided for his Sheerers.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 25. 11.</NOTE> And though his Bre∣thren,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 22. 1.</NOTE>
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
and some few of his next Relations had re∣paired
unto him; yet, generally, his friends and kin∣dred
look upon him as a man forlorn, whom they
could neither privately supply without manifest dan∣ger,
nor openly relieve without certain ruine.</P>
<P>7. And yet he was not so deserted,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 27. 2.</NOTE> but,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam.
22. 2.</NOTE> that some
companies resorted to him from all parts of the
Realm, either to mend their own condition, or to
sweeten his. Not altogether men of such desperate
fortunes as <HI>Nabal</HI> the old churl reported, and per∣haps
believed. Some of them, questionless, might be
persons no less eminent both for place and quality, as
for their good affections to him; though generally
they were (as the Scripture telleth us) either is <HI>debt</HI>
or <HI>discontent,</HI> or some great <HI>distress;</HI> that is to say,
such as were either <HI>discontented</HI> with the Tyranny of
the present Government, or were <HI>indebted</HI> to some
cruel and unmerciful creditors, from whom they could
expect no favour, and as little Justice; or, in a word,
were otherwise <HI>distressed</HI> upon some suspition, that
they were wedded to the Interest of the son of <HI>Iess.</HI>
The taking of these few <HI>Volunteers for a guard to
his person,</HI> is publiquely declared to be the <HI>Levying
of a War</HI> against the King;<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 29. 8.</NOTE> and all the Forces of the
Realm must be forthwith armed to suppress those
men, who were not able to withstand the twelfth part
of a Tribe.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 27. 2.</NOTE> This drives him once again to the Court
of <HI>Akish,</HI> where he found better entertainment then
he did before, because he came accompanyed with
a Train of couragious followers; from whom the Bar∣barous
King assured himself of no mean assistance
<PB N="9" REF="7"/>
in his next Wars against his Neighbours, without
excepting those of the house of <HI>Israel.</HI></P>
<P>8. But now the Tide begins to turn, and a strong
floud of mercies of flow in upon him. As there is
no deep Valley, but neer some high Mountain; so,
neer unto this Vale of Misery was a Hill of Mercy,
and we shall see him climb the top of it without any
great difficulty. <HI>Akish</HI> beholds him as a person
so depressed and injured by the power of <HI>Saul,</HI> that
no reconciliation could be made between them;
and thereupon bestows upon him the strong Town
of <HI>Ziglag,</HI> to serve for him and his adherents as a
<HI>City of Refuge,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 27. 6.</NOTE> to which his party might resort upon
all occasions. And for his better welcome thither,
the news of <HI>Saul's</HI> uncomfortable, but unpittied death,
is swiftly posted to him on the wing of Fame; which
opened the first passage to him for the Crown of <HI>Is∣rael.</HI>
For now there dayly came unto him many men
of note and merit, whose names are on record in the
Book of <HI>Chronicles,</HI> affirmed there <HI>to be mighty men,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Chr. 12. 1, &amp;c.</NOTE>
experienced in the use of Arms, Captains of Hun∣dreds
and of Thousands, and such as seemed to carry
Victory in their very countenances.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Chr. 12. 22.</NOTE> And they came
thither in such numbers as they made up a <HI>great
Host like the Host of God,</HI> (as the Scripture calls it)
that is to say, a puissant and mighty Army, fit for
the undertaking of the noblest actions. By whose
incouragement, but chiefly at the instigation of the
men of <HI>Iudah,</HI> who had repaired to <HI>Ziglag,</HI> amongst
the rest; he goes up to <HI>Hebron,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 2. 1, 4.</NOTE> the Principal City of that
Tribe, having first taken Gods direction &amp; commission
<PB N="10" REF="8"/>
with him. There he is cheerfully received, and
<HI>anointed</HI> King, King only over <HI>Iudah,</HI> his own native
<HI>Tribe,</HI> the rest of <HI>Israel</HI> still adhering to the house of
<HI>Saul.</HI> For, <HI>Abner</HI> Captain of <HI>Saul</HI>'s Host, and one
as neer to him in bloud, as in place and power, had
gained so far upon the Military men,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 14. 50.</NOTE> that they agreed
to set the Crown upon the head of <HI>Ishbosheth,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 2. 8, 9.</NOTE> the
eldest of <HI>Saul</HI>'s Sons which survived his Father: And
this he did, not on design to divide the Kingdom, to
break it into two, and set up Scepter against Scepter,
as <HI>Ieroboam</HI> and on the death of <HI>Solomon;</HI> but, with
a purpose to compel the men of <HI>Iudah</HI> by force of
Arms to cast off <HI>David,</HI> to unite themselves to the
rest of <HI>Israel,</HI> and all together to be subject to a
Prince of the house of <HI>Saul.</HI> A Prince indeed of no
great parts, affirmed to be a person of a dull and un∣active
spirit, more given to ease and pleasures, then
to deeds of Arms, <HI>&amp; magis extra vitia quam cum vir∣tutibus,</HI>
in the words of <HI>Tacitus:</HI> but fit enough to
bear the Title of a King, whilest <HI>Abner</HI> and the Soul∣diers
managed all affairs as to them seems best.</P>
<P>9. This brings new troubles upon <HI>David,</HI> though
they held not long. A breach is made between the
new King, and that great Commander; Who being impatient of rebuke, and netled with some words
which escaped his Master,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 3. 8.</NOTE> resolves upon delivering
the whose Kingdom to the hands of <HI>David:</HI> to which
end he maintains a Treaty with him, and concludes
the business. But, before all things could be setled,
the <HI>Titulary</HI> King is murthered by the two sons of
<HI>Rimmon,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 4. 2.</NOTE> both of them Captains in his Army, both</P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="8"/>Natives of the <HI>Tribe</HI> of <HI>Benjamin</HI> (his Fathers Tribe)
and possibly both of them of some kindred and rela∣tion
to him. This puts an end unto the war; the west
of <HI>Israel</HI> seconding the Tribe of <HI>Iudah,</HI> and altogether
calling upon <HI>David</HI> to accept the Government. To
which end they <HI>annoynt</HI> him the third time, and own
him by that Sacred Ceremony for their Soveraign
Prince. And such as Prince as must have somewhat in
him of the Priest, and the Prophet also. For, <HI>Rex est
mixta persona cum Sacerdote,</HI> as our Lawyers tels us,
and capable on that account of the <HI>Sacred Unction</HI>
(if some of our <HI>Masters of the Ceremonies</HI> have not been
mistaken). But so it was, that those of <HI>Benjamin</HI> could
not so easily forget their late pretentions to the Crown
of <HI>Israel,</HI> which they had held successively under two
great Princes, and therefore came not up to <HI>Hebron</HI>
with the rest of the Tribes, to confer the Kingdom
upon <HI>David,</HI> but to obtain it for themselves (as <HI>Iose∣phus</HI>
telleth us).<NOTE PLACE="marg">Antiq. Iud. lib. 7. cap. 2.</NOTE> A secret not to be concealed from
<HI>David</HI> a discerning Prince, and one that was well
studied in his own concernments. Who therefore to
cut off their hopes, and prevent their practises, re∣solves
to get into his hands the strong City of <HI>Sion.</HI>
Which standing in a corner of the <HI>Tribe</HI> of <HI>Benja∣min,</HI>
might serve for a sufficient bridle to hold them
in, if they should practise any thing against his quiet
for the time to come. And being afterward inlarged
at the charge of <HI>David,</HI> by taking in the City of <HI>Sa∣lim,</HI>
and building all from <HI>Millo</HI> inward (as the Scri∣pture
telleth us) he caused it to be called <HI>Hierusalem,</HI>
peopled it with such Families as he might confide in,
and made it from thenceforth the chief seat of his <HI>Royal
<PB N="12" REF="9"/>
Residence.</HI> Never till now was <HI>David</HI> setled in the
<HI>Kingdom,</HI> and now he growes considerable in the eyes
of all forain <HI>Princes,</HI> who <HI>court</HI> him, and send <HI>presents</HI>
to him, and trie all means imaginable to obtain his
favour.</P>
<P>10. And thus the <HI>Scepter</HI> promised to the Tribe of
<HI>Iudah</HI> is put into the hands of <HI>David</HI> the Son of <HI>Iesse,</HI>
one of the chief Princes of that Tribe. And all this
done at such a time, when they had all the reason in
the world to fear the contrary. The Government
having passed through many Tribes, from <HI>Moses</HI> of the
race of <HI>Levi,</HI> to <HI>Ioshua</HI> the Son of <HI>Nun</HI> of the seed of
<HI>Ephraim,</HI> and so from one Tribe to another, until
it came to <HI>Saul</HI> of the stock of <HI>Benjamin.</HI> And this
may seem to have been done for these reasons chiefly:
First, That the Tribe of <HI>Iudah</HI> might not claim the
Kingdom otherwise then by Gods donation, as possibly
they might have done, if they had entred on the Go∣vernment,
upon the death of <HI>Moses,</HI> by any Military
Vote, or Popular election, or in relation to that <HI>Pri∣mogeniture,</HI>
which was vested in them by the last Will
and Testament of their Father <HI>Iacob.</HI> And 2<SUP>ly</SUP>, It
was so done, that the people being sensible of the in∣conveniences
of the former Government, the miseries
which they had indured in the times of <HI>Anarchie,</HI> and
the extremities which they had been reduced to, in the
Reign of <HI>Saul;</HI> might with a greater cheerfulness im∣brace
a Prince of the Royal Family, whom God
had so miraculously preserved, and commended to
them.</P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="9"/>11. And it may seem to have been kept so long
from <HI>David,</HI> for two Reasons also: First, that he be∣ing
trained up in the School of experience, and ham∣mered
on the Anvile of Affliction, might be the bet∣ter
qualified for mannaging all affairs of State, then
if he had been educated in the pride and pleasures of a
Princes Court. And, Secondly, it was so disposed
of, that, being to be married to the Realm of <HI>Israel;</HI> he
might more passionately long to in<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oy his Spouse, then
if she had cast her self into his imbraces at the first
making of the Contract. And this was done accor∣ding
to the custome of the <HI>Iewish</HI> Nation, who use
to place some fitting and convenient interval, be∣twixt
the Espousal and the Wedding, for which
St. <HI>Austin</HI> gives this reason,<NOTE PLACE="marg">August. in Con∣fes. lib. 8. cap. 2.</NOTE> <HI>Ne vilem habeat maritus
datam, quam non suspiravit sponsus dilatam;</HI> for fear
(saith he) lest otherwise the Bridegroom might despise
her in the first fruition, for whom he had not longed
with some vehement passion. But being longed for,
and long looked for, they are met at last, to the full
comfort of both parties, the pleasure of Almighty
God, and the joy of the Nation.</P>
<P>12. Such was Gods kindness unto <HI>David,</HI> expressed
in his marvellous <HI>preservation,</HI> when he was com∣passed
round about with invincible dangers; his <HI>ex∣altation</HI>
to the Throne, from keeping sheep, <HI>to be the
Shepherd of his people;</HI> and therefore not a <HI>kindeness,</HI>
a <HI>great kindeness,</HI> only; but, <HI>misericordia mirabilis</HI> (in
St. <HI>Hieroms</HI> reading) a <HI>marvellous great kindeness,</HI> as
my Text assures me. For, what particular is there in
<PB N="14" REF="10"/>
all this kindeness which is not marvellous, <HI>mirabile in oculis nostris,</HI>
as marvellous in our eyes as it was
in his ? And not a <HI>marvellous kindeness</HI> only; but, <HI>mi∣serecordia
mirifica,</HI> a <HI>kindness which wrought wonders,</HI>
as <HI>Tremelius</HI> reads it. What can it else be thought,
but a singular miracle that God should for so many
years preserve this poor fugitive Prince, both from
the treachery of his friends, and the power of his
enemies; that he should finde more favour in the
Land of <HI>Moab,</HI> then he durst hope for in the place of
his birth and breeding; that men from all parts of
the Kingdom should resort unto him, when he had
neither Town of War to secure their persons, nor any
stock of money and provisions to maintain their Fa∣milies;
That <HI>Akish</HI> and the men of <HI>Gath,</HI> should lay
aside their animosities against him for the death of
<HI>Goliah,</HI> and put into his hands a piece of such strength
and consequence, as might inable him to create unto
them a far greater mischief?</P>
<P>13. And was it not as great a miracle, if it were
not greater, that <HI>Saul</HI> should come to such a miserable
and calamitous end, without ingaging <HI>David</HI> in a rui∣nous
and destructive War, against those men which
were designed to be his Subjects? That God should
so incline the hearts of the men of <HI>Iudah,</HI> as to ac∣cept
him for their King, and thereby to involve them∣selves
in a tedious War; when all the rest of the
Tribes adhered still to <HI>Abner,</HI> and the Sons of <HI>Saul:</HI>
That God was pleased to make to use of any of
<HI>Davids</HI> party for the destruction of <HI>Sauls</HI> house, but
acted that great work by <HI>Abner</HI> and the Sons of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI></P>
<P><PB N="15" REF="10"/>being the Kings near kinsmen and his chief Com∣manders:
That all the Tribes of <HI>Israel</HI> should unite
together to set and Crown upon his head, whom they
had formerly pursued from one place to another, till
they had forced him to take Sanctuary in a forain Nati∣on:
That all this should be done without noyse or
trouble; more then the noyse of joyful shouts and
acclamations, and the short trouble of an easie, though
a martial, progress: That there should be so few men
killed on either side, between the death of <HI>Saul,</HI> and
the Crowning of <HI>David;</HI> and, that God should put
into his hands the strong, Fort of <HI>Sion,</HI> which neither
<HI>Saul,</HI> nor any of the Judges, nor <HI>Ioshua</HI> himself, nor
<HI>Gideon,</HI> nor <HI>Ieptha, Duo Fulmina belli,</HI> the veriest
Thunder-bolts of War, had before attempted.</P>
<P>14. And yet the <HI>kindeness</HI> was the greater, and
the more miraculous, considering that it was exten∣ded
to spiritual mercies, and not confined to tem∣poral
preservations, and external benefits. For not∣withstanding
the horrid murther of <HI>Abimelech,</HI> the
terrible massacre of so many Priests, and the unmerci∣ful
sacking of the City of <HI>Nob; Abiathar</HI> the next
High-priest, and many others doubtless, of that Sacred
Order, joyned themselves unto him. <HI>Abiathar</HI> was
too great a person, and too well beloved, not to
bring some attendants with him; and, who more like
to bear him company then the <HI>Priests</HI> and <HI>Levites?</HI>
Not so much out of care to preserve themselves, as
to do service unto him whom the Lord had chosen.
By means whereof, not only he; but, all his followers,
were instructed in the things of God: and thereby kept
<PB N="16" REF="11"/>
from-being any way infected with those gross Idola∣tries,
which were predominant in <HI>Moab</HI> and the Court
of <HI>Gath.</HI> Than which there could be nothing more
conducible to his future advancement, or which
could more indear him to the <HI>Iewish</HI> Nation; when
they came once to be assured, that neither flatteries
could intice him, nor great threats affright him, nor
hope of promised aid allure him, from standing fast
to the Religion of his Fathers, to the Law of <HI>Moses.</HI>
And more then so,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 23 6.</NOTE> <HI>Abiathar</HI> brought along with
him the <HI>sacred Ephod,</HI> by which the High-priest used
to consult with God, and to enquire his will and
pleasure in all difficult cases. The want whereof,
necessitated the unhappy Tyrant to have recourse for
counsel to the Witch of <HI>Endor,</HI> as if he had been
forced upon that desperate resolution in the antient
Poet, (<HI>Flectere si nequeo superos, Acheronta movebo</HI>)
that since he could not move the Gods, he would trie
the Devil.</P>
<P>15. Nor was all this a <HI>kindeness</HI> only, or a <HI>great
kindeness,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">☞</NOTE> as the old Translation, and <HI>misericordia mi∣rabilis,</HI>
a <HI>marvellous great kindeness,</HI> in the eyes of all
men; but, it was <HI>misericordia sua,</HI> the Lords own
kindeness, &amp; <HI>factum Domini,</HI> the Lords own doing; to
which, no humane prudence could pretend a title. This
<HI>David</HI> understood, none better. And therefore at∣tributes
his safety and deliverance to the Lord alone,
<HI>Ipse sit licèt magna unique cura &amp; industria usus,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Muscul. in Psal. 31.</NOTE>
(as <HI>Musculus</HI> hath night-well observed), though he
himself had used all possible industry and care▪ for
his own preservation. He had his <HI>agents</HI> and <HI>intel∣ligeneers</HI>
<PB N="17" REF="11"/>
in the Court of <HI>Saul,</HI> to give him notice of
the secret purposes of his mortal enemy; He enter∣tained
<HI>Abiathar</HI> in a place both of trust and nearness,
that by his means he might maintain a correspon∣dence
with the rest of that Order. And when neces∣sity
compelled him to ingage in battail, he sent out
<HI>Ioab,</HI> (a man of most undaunted courage) to incoun∣ter
<HI>Abner,</HI> with whom he was competitor for the Palm
of victory. More providence and care could no man
use then <HI>David</HI> did; and yet, he calleth it, <HI>misericor∣diam
Domini,</HI> only Gods mercy, and his <HI>marvellous
kindeness,</HI> by which he was preserved in the day of
trouble.</P>
<P>16. And so indeed it was; meerly Gods mercy,
and his marvellous great kindness, by which he was
preserved in the dayes of <HI>Saul,</HI> and raised to the Throne
of <HI>Israel</HI> on the death of <HI>Ishbosheth.</HI> For what could
<HI>David</HI> have effected with all his diligence, had not
God secretly forwarned him of those dangers which
were near at hand; or what advantage could <HI>Abia∣thars</HI>
discoveries have procured unto him, had not God
sent the spirit of <HI>infatuation</HI> amongst the Princes of
<HI>Sauls</HI> house; supplanted their designes, and turned
<HI>their wisdom into foolishness?</HI> Or, what could <HI>Ioab</HI>
with all his valour have atchieved against so many
enemies, had not God broken them in pieces, had not
God throwen amongst them such a Ball of discord,
such a <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, as made them turn their Swords
upon one another. In which dissention the <HI>Royal No∣thing</HI>
is dispatched on his bed of ease, and dispossessed
at once both of Crown and Life, before he had served
<PB N="18" REF="12"/>
out his Indentures in the Trade of Government;
which also must be <HI>factum Domini,</HI> the Lord's doing
only, as to the ordering, permitting, and disposing of
it; though <HI>Abner</HI> and the sons of <HI>Ri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mon</HI> had their
own vile ends. For, who but God could turn his own
Sword upon him, and so <HI>infatuate</HI> the Counsels of
his chief Commanders, as to contrive the ruines of
their nearest kinsman, by whose sole power they stood,
and might have longer stood (in all apparent probabili∣ty)
in their former greatness.</P>
<P>17.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 127. 1.</NOTE> <HI>Except the Lord doth keep the City</HI> (saith the
Royal Psalmist) <HI>the watchman watcheth but in vain.
Except the Lord doth build the house, their labour is but
lost that build it.</HI> What then? Shall then the Workman
play,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Origen. in Rom▪ cap. 9.</NOTE> and the Watchman sleep? Not so, saith <HI>Origen,
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mpendant ipsi, quantum in se est, laboris et sollicitudi∣nis,
&amp;c.</HI> Let them continue their indevours in the name
of God, and let the Watchman watch, and the Work∣man
labour. Though God be all, and that our safety
is from him, and from him alone; yet, he hath told us,
that <HI>the lazie person shall not eat;</HI> and, <HI>the careless
person shall not prosper: It is the hand of the diligent
which maketh rich; and he becometh poor that dealeth
with a slack hand,</HI> (faith the wiseman <HI>Solomon</HI>). God
in the ordering and disposing of humane affairs, is
like the Pilot in a Ship; It is the Pilot only which
doth steer and guid the Vessel, and bringeth it safe into
the Haven; yet, it is expected that every several Ma∣riner
do discharge his duty, and yield obedience to the
whistle of the Boat-swain.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="12"/>18. But on the other side, it is not therefore to
be thought, that we may warrantably intitle either
our industry, or strength, or wisdom to the rights of
God. <HI>The wisdom of the wise (saith Paul)</HI> is it not
foolishness with the Lord? <HI>What Man is there</HI> (saith
<HI>David) that can save himself by his much strength;
Yea, or by taking thought</HI> (saith the Son of <HI>David) can
add one cubit to his stature.</HI> Man purposeth, but God
disposeth: And, when we have most spent our spirits,
and consumed our bodies in the well ordering of our
fortunes; yet, it is all in vain, and fruitless, and of no
effect <HI>except the Lord, even our own God, doth give us
his blessing.</HI> Ascribe we therefore to the Lord, the
glory of his own exployts; and let us not presume to
say in any of our prosperous actions, that, This my
own right hand hath done, or my wit effected. Though
<HI>David</HI> did as much as care and wisdom could per∣form
for his own security; yet he refers it all to God,
and reckons it His mercy only, and his marvellous
kindeness whereby he was preserved from danger,
made Master of <HI>Hierusalem,</HI> and setled, after all his
troubles, in so strong a City.</P>
<P>19. <HI>In a strong City.</HI> That's the next. <HI>In civitate
munita,</HI> In a fenced City, saith the Latin. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,
a City walled and ditched about, as the Greek
Text reads it. <HI>In civitate robusta &amp; firmata,</HI> A City
strong in men, and as strongly fortified, in St. <HI>Hierom's</HI>
Gloss. Only <HI>Tremelius,</HI> with some notable difference
from all men else, doth translate it thus: <HI>Benedictus
Dominus,</HI> Blessed be the Lord for she hath shewed his
<PB N="20" REF="13"/>
marvellous kindeness to me in as great a measure, <HI>ut in
civitate munita collocans me,</HI> as if he had inclosed and
kept me safe in a Town of War, as if I had been bil∣lited
and strongly garrison'd in a Fort and City. Tis
true indeed, Gods mercy is the surest Hold, to which we
may commit our safety; the strongest <HI>Castle of defence,</HI>
to which we may intrust our persons. A fortress against
all our foes; an <HI>Antidote</HI> against all Plagues; a Remedy
against all Diseases. He that is so defended, need no
other Arms.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Horat.</NOTE> <HI>Non eget Mauri Iaoulis, nec arcu;</HI> Not
shield, nor bow, nor poysoned arrows. Gods mercy
is all kinde of weapons to him, both for annoyance and
defence. No armour is so sure of proof, but it may
be broken; nor Town so strong, but may be taken;
nor wals so high and close, to keep our contagion.
Put if Gods mercy doth protect us, and his power
defend us; if we be compassed round about with
his deliverance, as with a wall; we will not be affraid
through war, and poverty, and sickness, do conspire
against us. For we are sure that then we are in such
a City, which neither enemy can force, nor want of
trade impoverish, nor disease infect. <HI>Deus meus &amp;
omnia.</HI> Let God be mine, and I am strong enough
against all the world, against all violence, against all
practices, against all misfortunes. I could inlarge my
self on this general <HI>Topick</HI> as to the moral of my Text,
but that I am to keep my self to the <HI>literal sense,</HI>
to the <HI>strong City</HI> herein meant by the <HI>Royal Psal∣mist.</HI></P>
<P>20. And if I keep my self to the <HI>literal sense,</HI> we
must inquire what City is here meant by <HI>David.</HI> And
<PB N="21" REF="13"/>
we shall finde upon a very short inquiry, that it was
either <HI>Ziglag, Hebron,</HI> or <HI>Hierusalem,</HI> and the last
most likely. St. <HI>Austin,</HI> and St. <HI>Hierome,</HI> so resolve
for certain, with whom the Moderns do agree, as to
that particular; all telling us, That God declared his
<HI>marvellous</HI> mercies unto <HI>David,</HI> by setling his affairs,
<HI>in Civitate Ierusalem,</HI> in the <HI>strong City</HI> of <HI>Hierusa∣lem,</HI>
in the Fort of <HI>Sion.</HI> For there he found an end
of his former sorrows, thither he brought the <HI>Ark,</HI>
to that place he removed the <HI>Trabernacle,</HI> and there
did he fix his <HI>Royal Palace,</HI> with the <HI>Courts of Iustice,</HI>
and thereby drew unto it, by degrees, all the wealth
of the <HI>Kingdom;</HI> and there he reigned in greater glo∣ry
and renown, then any of the Kings and Princes
which were round about him.</P>
<P>21. Now Cities are accounted strong in two re∣spects:
first, in the strength of situation, or of art;
and next in the multitudes and natural courage of the
people: and in both these <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> as it flourished
in the time of <HI>David,</HI> might worthily be called a
<HI>strong City,</HI> (as indeed it was) <HI>Civitas munitissima,</HI>
as my Author hath it. For first, it was well situated
and strongly fortified, three Towns in one of them
seated on steep Hills, and all of them invironed with
high Walls, strong Bullwarks, and unpassable Ditches:
But none to be compared with the City of <HI>Sion,</HI> which
made the <HI>Iebusites</HI> presume so far upon the strength
of the place, that, in contempt of <HI>Davids</HI> Forces, they
mann'd their walls with none but their <HI>blind</HI> and <HI>lame,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">A<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iq. Iud ic. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 7. chap 3.</NOTE>
as <HI>Iosephus</HI> tells us▪ and then sent word, (whether with
greater pride or folly, it is hard to say) that except
<PB N="22" REF="14"/>
he took away the blind and the lame, he could not
come thither. Which was to tell him in effect, that
those poor wretches were sufficient to make good
the Fort against all his Army, and therefore must be
first removed, before he could expect to be Master of it.
<Q>Such confidence, saith he, they had in their Walls and
Trenches, that they conceived them able, without
further help to keep out the Enemy.</Q></P>
<P>22. But Walls, we see by this example, are but
simple strengths, if there be any want of people, or
in the people any want of <HI>courage</HI> to make good the
place. The honour of a King consists not in the
strength of Towns, and frequency of Garrisons; but
in the multitude, and courage, and good affection of
his Subjects. Kings are then safest, when they trust
rather to their <HI>Castles of bones,</HI> then <HI>their Castles of
stones;</HI> according to the <HI>Aphorism</HI> of Sir <HI>Henry Sa∣vage,</HI>
an old <HI>English</HI> Souldier. <HI>Lycurgus</HI> also seemed
to be of the same opinion, when he prohibited the
<HI>Spartans</HI> to immure their City, or to use any of the
Arts of Fortification. And in this sense <HI>lerusalem</HI> was
strong; because it was as populous, and no less ca∣pacious,
then either <HI>Nineveh,</HI> or <HI>Babylon,</HI> or <HI>Eckba∣tana,</HI>
or any other Cities in the Eastern Countries.
So populous, that at the siege thereof by <HI>Titus,</HI> there
perished by the Sword and Famine of all sorts and
sexes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">loseph. de <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ello. Iud. lib. 7. c. 17.</NOTE> 1100000. and above, as <HI>Iosephus</HI> telleth us.
And so prodigiously capacious, that once the High-Priest
(at the request of <HI>Cestius</HI> a <HI>Roman</HI> President)
numbering the people which came thither to observe
the Passover,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Id. ibid.</NOTE> found them to be <HI>two millions and se∣ven
<PB N="23" REF="14"/>
hundred thousand</HI> men (besides women and chil∣dren)
all sound and purified, and fitted by the Law for
that Sacred Ceremony. A number numberless, and
not indeed to be believed, were not <HI>Iosephus</HI> gene∣rally
reckoned for a true Historian, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,
as the good Father, <HI>Iustin Martyr,</HI> hath assured us
of him. And though these numberings of the peo∣ple
in that mighty City happened long after <HI>David</HI>'s
time; yet the City after <HI>David</HI>'s time received small
inlargements. Ten of the Tribes revolting on the death
of <HI>Solomon,</HI> and never afterwards returning to the
Kings of <HI>Iudah.</HI></P>
<P>23. As for the courage of the People, and Inha∣bitants
of it, in the time of <HI>David;</HI> we may conceive
it equal at the least, if it were not greater, then
that of their posterity in the times succeeding. Which
was so eminent, that he which reads the Story of their
final ruine, when besieged by <HI>Titus,</HI> will find the
<HI>Romans</HI> so put to it, that they never purchased any <HI>Ci∣ty</HI>
at a dearer rate. And hereupon may say in the word
of <HI>Iustin, Et tanta animorum virtus fuit, &amp;c.</HI> That
though they had just cause at all times to despair of
safety; yet, for the most part, they presumed, and
came off with safety, till God was pleased to give
them over for a prey to the Sword of their Ene∣mies.</P>
<P>24. And yet there might be somewhat in it, which
more assured <HI>David</HI> of his peace and happiness, than
either the Courage of the people, or the Strength of
the place; which was their good Affection and fide∣lity
<PB N="24" REF="15"/>
to him. And this appears plainly by their car∣riage
towards him, when he was forced to give way
to the Treason of <HI>Absolom.</HI> For, when he left them
to the power of the Enemy, the people followed
him in great <HI>numbers,</HI> to express their loyalty; and
followed him in tears, to express their affection. So,
as it cannot be affirmed, that either they betrayed,
or forsook their King: but, that the King rather in a
Royal pity did withdraw from them; left otherwise
he might have brought some evil on the City, as the
Text informs us. Lay all that hath been said, toge∣ther,
of the strength of this City, and we shall find,
that <HI>David</HI> had good reason to extol Gods Name for
giving him possession of a place so strong, so popu∣lous,
and so replenished with a loyal and couragi∣ous
people.</P>
<P>25. And thus I have run over all the parts of my
Text, as they declare God's <HI>marvellous</HI> kindness unto
<HI>David;</HI> so, that it can be no hard matter to remove
the <HI>vail,</HI> and to behold the face of our own affairs,
the mercies of this day, and the glories of it. A day
in which we solemnize the memory of as great a
kindness; a kindness as remarkable in respect of the
Person, as marvellous in its own condition, no less
peculiar to the Lord as the Author of it, and in a
place as notable, our Principal City, our strongest
City of descence. To which, by Gods assistance, and
your Christian Patience, I shall now proceed, and
then descend unto the duties of the dayes, where we
shall meet with <HI>David</HI>'s thankfulness, and our own to boot.</P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="15"/>26. <HI>Et, De quo loquitur Propheta, vel populus fidelis?</HI>
And in this place may be asked in the <HI>Eunuch</HI>'s words,
<HI>Of whom here speaks the Prophet, either of himself, or of
some other?</HI> Not of himself alone saith <HI>Cassianus,</HI> an old
Christian Writer, but in behalf of all Gods children, of
his faithful servants. The Books of <HI>Psalms</HI> is so compo∣sed
saith <HI>Athanasius,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Athanas. in E∣pist. ad Mar. in Tom. 3.</NOTE> that every man may read his own
Story in them, and find therein his own particular
concernments; and that as punctually, as if the pur∣pose
of the Psalm had been addressed and fitted on∣ly
unto his occasions. Let it be so, and then, Who may
not find the quality of our late afflictions, and our
deliverance together in this present Psalm, and read
the state of our affairs in the Story of <HI>David;</HI> and
then draw down an easie and familiar parallel be∣twixt
the Persons, and the mercies, and the places
too? A parallel, right worthy of the pen of <HI>Plutarch,</HI>
if any such were found amongst us; but, such as
seems to have been done in part already, by laying
before you <HI>David</HI>'s troubles and his great deliver∣ance.
And therefore passing by those things which
apply themselves, and those in which the Story of
both Princes seems to make but one; we will observe
the method which is used by <HI>Plutarch,</HI> in laying down
the points in which they differ, or, those wherein
one party seems to have preheminence above the
other.</P>
<P>27. First then, It may be truly said of our <HI>English
David,</HI> as <HI>Commodus,</HI> not without vain-glory, did af∣firm
of himself, <HI>Quem Primum Sol &amp; Principem &amp;
<PB N="26" REF="16"/>
hominem vidit,</HI> that he was born a Prince, and that
the Sun did never otherwise behold him then as Heir
to a Kingdom. Which cannot be affirmed of <HI>David,</HI>
nor of <HI>David</HI>'s Ancestors; though all of them might
live in expectation of obtaining that Scepter, which
had been promised to that <HI>Tribe,</HI> in the person of
<HI>Iudah.</HI> And as his Birth was higher, so his Fall was
lower, and his afflictions so much greater; and the
more insupportable, because he was more tenderly
bred, and less able to bear them. Nay, they were
greater in themselves then the heavyest sorrows that
ever fell upon <HI>David</HI> in the time of his troubles; who
kept himself most commonly unto those retreats
which his own Countrey did afford him, and when
he was compelled to retire to <HI>Moab,</HI> or to sojourn in
the Realm of <HI>Gath,</HI> neither <HI>Saul</HI>'s malice, nor his
power did pursue him there. But so it was not in the
case of our <HI>Royal Exile;</HI> Driven out of all the Forts and
Cities of his own Dominions, by the <HI>power</HI> of his
Enemies; and, by their <HI>practises,</HI> not suffered to re∣main
in <HI>France;</HI> nor to be entertained in <HI>Holland;</HI>
compelled to shift from one Imperial City to another;
from the <HI>Higher, to the Lower Germany;</HI> but, pursued
in all, seldom nor never free from their trains and
treacheries, who would not think themselves secure
but in his destruction. <HI>Sic aquilam fugiunt trepi∣dae
Columbae;</HI> Never was Patridge flown at with
a swifter wing by a well-train'd Falcon, nor game
more hotly followed, by the fiercest Hounds; than
this poor Prince was chased by those <HI>mighty Hunters,</HI>
those <HI>Nimrods,</HI> those <HI>Robusti Venatores,</HI> as the Scri∣pture
calls them: who had the building of that <HI>Babel</HI>
<PB N="27" REF="16"/>
which they raised amongst us. They had their cun∣ning
<HI>Lime-hounds</HI> to draw <HI>Dry-foot</HI> after him, and
plyed the chase with all the <HI>Kennil</HI> at his Heels,
when the Hunt was up: not with a purpose to <HI>call off</HI>
when they had breathed their Horses or tryed their
Dogs; but with a <HI>merciless retreat</HI> to <HI>hunt him</HI> down,
and then to wash their cruel and accursed hands in his
precious bloud, as is accustomed in the fall of a Buck
of Stagg.</P>
<P>28. And as the dangers which accompanyed our
English <HI>David,</HI> were more transcendent in respect of
his Sacred Person; so, were they far more grievous
to him in respect of his party: whose <HI>tears</HI> he put
into his <HI>bottles,</HI> whose <HI>stripes</HI> he bare on his own <HI>body,</HI>
and whose calamities did more afflict his <HI>righteous
Soul,</HI> then his own misfortunes. And, if we look up∣on
his Party with an equal eye, we shall soon find
them to have suffered more and far heavier pressures in
his cause and quarrel, then all the <HI>Hebrew Nations</HI> did
for the sake of <HI>David.</HI> We read indeed of 85. Priests
slaughtered by the cruelty and command of <HI>Saul;</HI> But
we may read of more than twenty times that number
of our <HI>Regular Clergy;</HI> all the Bishops, Deans, and Dig∣nitaries,
and almost all the <HI>Heads of Houses</HI> impri∣soned,
plundered, sequestred, ejected; their wives
and children miserably turn'd out of doors, some of
them left for dead in the open streets. And why all
this? but for adhering to his Majesty, and his Fa∣thers
house, and to the Laws, and the Religion here
established, and for no crime else. But then again, we do
not read of any man of quality in the Tribes of <HI>Israel,</HI>
<PB N="28" REF="17"/>
condemned and executed, or otherwise deprived of
Lands and Liberties, for his well wishing unto
<HI>David.</HI> Amongst us, nothing was more common
than the imprisoning of our choisest and most able
Gentry, selling the Goods, confiscating the Lands,
and calling those in question for their very lives,
whose known fidelity was imputed to them for their
only crime. For, now we had attained to that height
of wretchedness, that Loyalty must pass for Trea∣son,
and Treason must be <HI>Unicum eorum crimen qui∣vacabant
crimine,</HI> as in the worst and most de∣plorable
condition of the <HI>Roman</HI> Empire. And
thereupon it was concluded in the School of <HI>Tyran∣nus,</HI>
that they who were so prodigal of their Mo∣ney,
Arms and Victuals to another man, especia∣lly,
to one marked out for ruine by their mighty
Masters, should have no bread to feed their Fa∣milies,
or money to maintain themselves; or o∣ther
Arms, but Prayers, and Tears, to save them from
the violence of unjust Oppression, even from Death
it self.</P>
<P>29. Besides, it might be some alleviation unto <HI>Da∣vid</HI>'s
followers, to suffer by the hands of a lawful
King, a King set over them by God, by the Lord
himself; whose Power they were not to resist, whose
Person was too Sacred, and his Authority too transcen∣dent
to be called in question. But it must be a tor∣ment
unexpressible to a generous spirit, to be trode
underfoot by an <HI>Adoni-bezek;</HI> to have their lives and
Vineyards taken from them, at the will of an <HI>Ahab;</HI>
to see the <HI>Bramble</HI> Reign as King over all the Trees
<PB N="29" REF="17"/>
our tallest Oakes felled down by a shrub of yester∣day;
and all the <HI>goodly Cedars</HI> of the Church, grubbed
up, to make room for a stinking <HI>Elder.</HI></P>
<P>30. In the next place, as the calamities which fell
upon <HI>our English David,</HI> and his faithful followers,
were more in number and more grievous, then all
those which had been suffered by the other; so was
the kindness of the Lord more marvellous in his pre∣servation,
the hand of God more visible in his Resti∣tution.
And first, the kindness was more marvellous
in his <HI>Preservation,</HI> because we do not find that <HI>David</HI>
ever hazarded his own person in the day of Battail, but
managed all his Wars with <HI>Abner, Absolom,</HI> and <HI>Sheba,</HI>
by the hand of <HI>Ioab.</HI> Which gave him means and
opportunity to provide for himself, though all his For∣ces
had been routed, and their General taken. But our
great Master put himself into the head of his Army,
ventured his life for the Redemption of his people,
charged and recharged through the thickest of his
enemies, the first that came into the field, and the
last that left it; and thereby gained the honour, though
he lost the victory of the day. By what miraculous
means he was preserved from death in that fatal
Overthrow, and with what Loyal secrecy conveyed
from one place to another, is not so clearly and di∣stinctly
known as the cause deserves; &amp; therefore to be
wished that it may publickly be declared by his Sacred
Majesty; that God might have the glory of his own
great Mercies, and all good men the honour of their
brave fidelity. In the mean time, we may with piety
believe, that he was either carryed off by God on the
<PB N="30" REF="18"/>
wings of Angels, so that none could reach him; or
else inveloped round about with a cloud of darkness,
so that none could see him,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Virgil. Aencid.</NOTE> <HI>Cernere ne quis eum,
ne quis contingere poss it,</HI> as <HI>Virgil</HI> telleth us of <HI>Aeneas</HI> in
the last condition.</P>
<P>31. And then again, the hand of God was far
more visible in his <HI>Restitution.</HI> For, was it not a <HI>mar∣vellous
kindness,</HI> that God was pleased to preserve a
strong party for him, which had not been infected with
the <HI>errors</HI> and <HI>corruptions,</HI> which then reigned amongst
us; that in a time of such a general defection from
the rules of the Church, so many thousands should
be found of all sorts and sexes, which <HI>had not bowed
the knee to Baal,</HI> nor to the <HI>golden Calves</HI> of <HI>Dan</HI>
and <HI>Bethel,</HI> nor the more <HI>guilded Calves</HI> that grazed
and bleated upon these mountains of the Lord. And
that far more should keep their hearts intire and
loyal in those times of danger, when they could find
no means to signifie it by their tongues and hands.
And this not only was a <HI>kindness,</HI> and a <HI>marvellous
kindness;</HI> but, <HI>misericordia sua,</HI> the Lords <HI>kindness</HI>
also, most properly to be called the work of God, who
did both bow their Hearts, and advance their Hands,
and use them both, for the facilitating of the Kings
<HI>Reduction.</HI></P>
<P>32.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 King. 18. 44.</NOTE> In which conjuncture of affairs, a little cloud
ariseth from the Northern Sea, after the heavens had
been shut up for some years together. Which though
it were no bigger then a mans hand in the first appea∣rance,
yet brought along with it such <HI>abundance of
<PB N="31" REF="18"/>
rain,</HI> as did not only comfort and refresh the
afflicted
Land, but forced our politick <HI>Ahabs,</HI> and their fol∣lowers
too, to take their Chariots and make haste away
to some other place, before the storm should over∣take
them. And certainly this must needs be <HI>miseri∣cordia
sua,</HI> as well Gods mercy in it self, as to be
reckoned for a <HI>mavellous mercy</HI> in the eyes of men.
For neither the Party was so weak, nor the Cause so
desperate, as to be broken by the coming of so small
a power, as rather seemed to be a Guard to their
<HI>Generals</HI> person, then of sufficient force to oppose that
Army, before which <HI>two great Kings were not able to
stand.</HI> And then it is to be observed, that such as
draw their Swords upon God's Anointed, use com∣monly
to throw away the scabbards also; and find no
way of doing better, but by doing worse.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Tacit. Hist li. 2.</NOTE> <HI>Nil me∣dium
inter summa &amp;. praecipitia.</HI> No middle way for
them to walke in, but either to bear up like Princes,
or to die like Traytors. But it was otherwise in the
case which we have before us. God so prevailing on
the hearts of the men of war, that they became no less
ready to receive their King, then his own party to
invite him; And they which first ingaged in the War
against him, expulsed him hence, and voted him un∣capable
of the Regal Dignity, are now as zealous as
the best to advance him to it. Nay, they contended
eagerly with the rest of the Subjects (as once the men
of <HI>Israel</HI> did with the men of <HI>Iudah</HI>) which of the two
should shew most zeal for his Restitution; and did
not only send word to him that he should <HI>return,
both he and his servants</HI> with him; but, some of them
passed over the Flood, that they might bring him
<PB N="32" REF="19"/>
back unto his Countrey with the greater glory. <HI>Et
certant ipsi secum, utrùm contumeliosius eum expulerint,
an honorabilius revocaverint;</HI> as in the case of <HI>Alci∣biades</HI>
is observed by <HI>Iustin.</HI></P>
<P>33. But possibly our <HI>Gideon</HI> with such a handful of
men, might not have been of power sufficient to ef∣fect
the enterprise, if our great City had not openly
appeared in favour of it, and thereby given en∣couragement
to the rest of the Subjects, whose hearts
stood firm unto the King. A treble City of three
Towns together, but all of them united in one com∣mon
name, as <HI>Ierusalem</HI> was; and no less strong
then that, in regard on the multitude; but stronger,
in respect of the power and riches of the people of
it. For here it was, in this <HI>strong City,</HI> the principal
City of our Nation, the <HI>abstract</HI> or <HI>Epitomie</HI> of all
<HI>Britain (In Britanniarum compendio)</HI> as my Author
cals it, that the design was most advanced, though
not there contrived. And here it was in this <HI>strong City</HI>
that this great miracle of mercy did receive accom∣plishment,
by opening both their Gates, and Hearts, and
Hands, to receive their Soveraign. Let them continue in
that obedience to our Lord the King, &amp; they shal wipe
away the memory of their former Errors. Nay, our
Posterity shall behold them with a cheerful gratitude,
as the restorers and preservers of our common happi∣ness,
by giving good example to the rest of the King∣dom.
For certainly the practice of great Cities, is
exemplary, not only in their Morals; but, their
Politicks too. According to the motion of the <HI>Pri∣mum
mobile,</HI> the lower Stars and Planets move in
<PB N="33" REF="19"/>
their several <HI>Spheres,</HI> and think it no disgrace
to be sometimes <HI>retrograde,</HI> or in their <HI>motus tre∣pidationis;</HI>
when the first Orbe begins to be <HI>irregu∣lar,</HI>
or seems to be left destitute of those <HI>Intelligences</HI>
which are said to move it.</P>
<P>34. And therefore it concerns great Towns and
populous Cities, upon whose actions all mens eyes
are fixed and busied, to be a pattern of good works, of
Loyalty, and of due obedience to the rest of the peo∣ple.
Faction, and Opposition to Authority, are two
dangerous plagues, more fatal and destructive to the
greatest Empire, than the Sword, Pestilence, or Fa∣mine.
Which if they get into a City or a Town of
note, <HI>Non ibi consistunt ubi caeperunt,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Vellei. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Hist. l. 2.</NOTE> infect not there
alone where they first brake out; but, as the nature of
the Plague is observed to be, from thence it springs into
the Villages adjoyning, and in the end to all the quar∣ters
of the Kingdom. It cannot be denied, but that we
found it to be so in the first revolt; but then it must
be granted also, that the Tide never turned in the lesser
Rivers, until the <HI>Thames</HI> had made a stand under <HI>Lon∣don-Bridge.</HI>
The noise of which great miracle (as it
was no other) made all the waters clap their hands,
and the floods rejoyce, and even the <HI>Ocean</HI> to be proud
of so rich a burthen, as was committed to its trust by
the heavenly Pilot.</P>
<P>35. For now the King prepares for his return to the
Royal City, not with an Army to besiege it, to smite
it with the edge of the sword, and to root out the
<HI>Iebusites,</HI> which were planted in it, as <HI>David</HI> did when
he first brought <HI>Hierusalem</HI> under his command. Not
so; but, as a Prince of peace, as the Son of <HI>David,</HI> to
<PB N="34" REF="20"/>
bring the glad tidings of salvation to all his Subjects,
to put an end to all the miseries of his People, and to
restore them to that peace and happiness, which they
had forfeited by pride and wantonness, by disobedience
to his Person, and distrust to his Promises; and, in a
word, by doing more then is to be repeated, since it hath
been pardoned. And to this <HI>City</HI> came the <HI>Tribes</HI> to
receive their <HI>King;</HI> whether, in greater numbers, or
with greedier eyes, or with more joyful hearts, it is hard
to say. Of which, I shall speak little now, because
more anon. This was the blessing of the day, and this
conducts me next to the duties of it, which we shall
take from <HI>David</HI>'s Doctrine and example, <HI>Benedictus
Dominus, Blessed be the Lord.</HI></P>
<P>36. <HI>Et quemodo dicit, Benedictus Dominus? Num illi
opus est benedictione nostra?</HI> What means the Prophet
(saith St. <HI>Hierom</HI>) by this form of speech? Hath the
Lord need of us that we should bless him? No, but
we say, with <HI>Vatablus,</HI> that it is an <HI>Hebraism,</HI> a garb
of speech peculiar to the <HI>Hebrew</HI> Language; the mea∣ning
this, <HI>Dignus est omni laude Dominus,</HI> The Lord
is worthy to be praised, His mighty Acts to be pre∣served
in perpetual memory. What <HI>David</HI>'s practice
was, we need make no question; or, if we did, we have
sufficient evidence for it in the Book of Psalms. Most
of which were composed to no other purpose, but to
extol Gods name, and set forth his prayses for all the
blessings which he had bestowed upon him in his soul
and body. Among which last, there was none more
<HI>great,</HI> more <HI>marvellous,</HI> more fit to be ascribed to the
Lord alone, then the preserving of his Person, the rai∣sing
of him to his Throne, and the establishing of that
<PB N="35" REF="20"/>
Throne in so <HI>strong a City.</HI> And therefore, <HI>Benedictus
Dominus, Let thanks be given unto the Lord,</HI> saith our
old Translation.</P>
<P>37. But more particularly we may behold the thank∣fulness
of <HI>David,</HI> in his Works and Actions. We may
behold it in his Works, if we consult that notable pas∣sage
of <HI>Iosephus,</HI> where it is said, that <HI>David</HI> being de∣livered
from his Wars and troubles <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Antiq. Iudaic. lib. 7. chap. 10.</NOTE>
indited Anthems, Psams, and Hymnes in the
praise of God; calling to minde those manifold and
great occasions which might induce him to a pious
and religious gratitude; and more then so, he procu∣red
many Instruments to be made for God's publick
service, Organs, and Psalteries, and Harps, and taught
the <HI>Levites</HI> how to praise Gods name upon them (saith
the same <HI>Iosephus</HI>) not only on the <HI>Sabbath,</HI> but the
other <HI>Festivals.</HI> For doing which, he had no precept
from above, or any warrant that we read of, but his
own authority, and that he thought it fit and decent.</P>
<P>38. <HI>David,</HI> no question, knew as perfectly Gods na∣ture
and the true nature of his service, as any other man
whatsoever he was: Yet thought he not that either of
them was prophaned or made lesse edifying by the oc∣casion
of sweet Musick &amp; melodious Harmony. Which
made him call so often upon all his people, not only
to set forth Gods praises in their Songs and Hymns,
but to extol and celebrate his Name, with <HI>Trumpets</HI> and
<HI>loud sounding Cymbals,</HI> with <HI>Psalteries</HI> and <HI>Harps, Strin∣ged
instruments,</HI> and <HI>Organs</HI> also; and that not in their
houses only, but in the blessed <HI>Sanctuary,</HI> as appears
plainly in the last of the Book of <HI>Psal.</HI> And he appoin∣ted
also that the singers, and such as played upon the
<PB N="36" REF="21"/>
Musical instruments, in the performance of this ser∣vice,
should be cloathed in white, or rather with a
linnen vesture over the rest of their garments, as it is
said expresly in the 1 <HI>Chro.</HI> ch. 15. From whence (or
from the <HI>linnen ephod</HI> which was worn by the Priests)
we have derived the <HI>Surplisse</HI> now in use amongst us, and
not from any garment used by the <HI>Priests</HI> of <HI>Isis,</HI> as
some of the preciser sort have most idely fancyed.</P>
<P>39. But <HI>David</HI> was as excellent in paying his thank∣fulnesse
to God in the acts of piety, as praising him with
songs and hymns, and musical Instruments. The <HI>Ark
of God</HI> which had been taken by the <HI>Philist ms</HI> in the
time of <HI>Eli,</HI> and kept at <HI>Keriath-jearim</HI> all the Raign of
<HI>Saul;</HI> is now brought back▪ and setled in <HI>Hierusalem</HI>
by the care of <HI>David,</HI> who gave not only order for
the doing of it, but saw it done and was himself a prin∣cipal
actor in that sacred Ceremony. He thought it
no way mis-becomming any earthly Majesty, to look
to all such matters as concerned Religion and apper∣tained
unto the service of the most high God; Nor
is there any thing which makes a King more esteema∣ble
in the eies of his subjects, then to be active and in∣dustrious
in the restoring of Gods worship to it's anti∣ent
purity. <HI>Ille diis proximus habetur, per quem deorum
majestas vindicatur,</HI> are the words of an Heathen, yet
such as may become the most sober Christian.</P>
<P>40. Follow him yet a little further, and we shall
see him putting the whole service of God into a better
frame and order, then it had been formerly. To which
end he appointed to the priests their several tunes, that
every man might know the course of his ministrati∣on;
and so distributed and disposed them under seve∣ral
<PB N="37" REF="21"/>
<HI>heads,</HI> that all things might be acted by them with∣out
confusion. Which <HI>Heads</HI> or <HI>Rulers,</HI> or <HI>chief Cap∣tains,</HI>
as the gospel calls them, being in number twen∣ty
fowr, besides the <HI>High-priest,</HI> and his <HI>Sagan</HI> or the
second <HI>High-priest,</HI> twenty six in all, make up the just
tale of our <HI>English</HI> Bishops. And in regard the <HI>Tribe of
Levi</HI> had remained so faithful to him, and done and
suffered so much for him, in the time of his troubles,
he is resolved to make a retribution worthy of a Roy∣al
spirit. Some of them therefore he sets over the
<HI>treasures of the house</HI> of God, that is to say, such
treasures as were dedicated and laied up in the <HI>Holy
Temple,</HI> or otherwise offered and designed for Religi∣ous
uses. Others he made <HI>officers</HI> and <HI>Iudges</HI> in the
Tribes of <HI>Israel,</HI> and that not only in all <HI>businesses of
the Lord,</HI> in all sacred matters, but in the businesse
<HI>of the King,</HI> even in civill concernments, as is expres∣sed
most plainly in the first of Chro. ch. 26. So far
was <HI>David</HI> from conceiving, that <HI>sacred Orders</HI> were a
<HI>super-sedeas</HI> to all civill prudence; and that he might
not lawfully make use of the abilities of any of his
Subjects, of what sort soever, as <HI>Councellours, Iud∣ges,
Officers,</HI> or what else he pleased.</P>
<P>41. Thus <HI>David</HI> did, and thus our <HI>David</HI> hath
done also. He made it his first act to close the brea∣ches
in this Church, both in Doctrine and Discipline,
and to restore the antient government of Bishops, ac∣cording
to Gods words and the primitive practice. He
takes care that <HI>Divine service</HI> be officiated with
as much solemnity, as in the best and happiest times
of his predecessors, adorns his Chappel in a costly
and magnificent manner, gathereth together the best
<PB N="38" REF="22"/>
voices in his whole dominions, and intermingleth
them with Musical Instruments, which seem to carry
a resemblance to that heavenly Harmony which some
ascribe unto the <HI>Spheres.</HI> A form of service highly
magnyfied by the primitive <HI>Christian,</HI> and such as
gained exceedingly upon mens affections. St. <HI>Austin,</HI>
when an <HI>Heathen</HI> or at best a <HI>Manich<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</HI> found two temp∣tations
to invite him to the Christian Churches; that
is to say, to hear the <HI>eloquence</HI> of St. <HI>Ambrose</HI> when
he was in the Pulpit, and the <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rmonious Melody</HI> which
was made in the <HI>Quire.</HI> And it is hard to say, which
of the two prevailed most towards his Conversion.
The musick of the Church so mollified his stony heart
that it drew tears from his eys (<HI>ut flevi ad cantus Ec∣clesiae
tuae</HI>)<NOTE PLACE="marg">Aug Conf. lib. 10. ch. 23.</NOTE> and thereby made him apter for all such
impressions of the <HI>Holy Spirit,</HI> as afterwards advan∣ced
him highly in the favour both of God and Men,
Retained on this account, (as he after tells us) in all
the Churches of those times, both <HI>Greek</HI> and <HI>Latin, Ut
per oblectamenta aurium,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Id. ibid.</NOTE> <HI>in firmior assurgat animus in pie∣tatis
affectum;</HI> because it did compose mens thoughts,
and calm their passions, and fit them to the serious and
the grave performance of religious Offices: Which
makes it seem the greater wonder, that any man, prefer∣red
and dignified in the Church of <HI>England,</HI> should in a
Sermon preached, and printed, and exposed to sale;
compare the <HI>heavenly musick</HI> in Cathedral Churches to
that confused medley of the <HI>Flute,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Dan. 3. 5.</NOTE> the <HI>Sackbut,</HI> and the
<HI>Harp,</HI> the <HI>Psaltery,</HI> the <HI>Cornet,</HI> and the <HI>Dulcimer,</HI> which
played before the <HI>Golden Image,</HI> advanced by <HI>Nebucad∣nezzar</HI>
in the fields of <HI>Babylon.</HI> But he hath-long since
<HI>smarted</HI> for his folly, and so let him go.</P>
<P><PB N="39" REF="22"/>42. Our <HI>English David</HI> stays not here, but looks up∣on
the services and the sufferings of the <HI>Regular</HI> Cler∣gy;
some of which he restoreth to their former
fortunes, and raises others unto greater then they
had before. All the <HI>Episcopal Sees,</HI> but one, are
filled with Learned and Religious Prelates, of
whom the tongue of envy, hatred, malice and uncha∣ritableness
can speak no reproach. And as the Sees are
filled with <HI>Learned</HI> and <HI>Religious</HI> Prelates; so is it to
be hoped that by the <HI>Piety of these times,</HI> those Prelates
shall be re-established in those Powers and Priviledges,
which <HI>the Iniquity of the last Times</HI> hath taken from
them. Without which they must pass for <HI>Cyphers</HI> in the
Church-Arithmetick, disabled from proceeding in the
work of God; of less esteem amongst their friends, and
a scorn to their adversaries. The <HI>State</HI> was never bet∣ter
served, then when the <HI>Messengers</HI> of Peace were the
<HI>Ministers</HI> of it: when Kings asked Counsel of the
Priests, and that the Priests were Counsellors, Officers,
and Judges in their several times. Which <HI>David</HI> must
needs know as well as any (being a Prince replenished
with the Spirit of God) or else he had not called them
to those imployments which the Scripture speaks of.</P>
<P>43. Thus hath the King performed his duty, we
must next do ours; and pay our thankfulness to God
on the <HI>knees of our hearts,</HI> for the advancement of our
<HI>David</HI> to the Throne of his Fathers; and, thereby
giving us such a fair and blessed Sun-shine after a
long <HI>Egyptian</HI> darkness, and so miraculous a calm up∣on
the back of that most dreadful intermixture of
Thunder and Lightning (the roaring of the Can∣nons,
and the burning of Towns), which was never
<PB N="40" REF="23"/>
equalled in this Nation. Which as it ought to
be our duty to the last day of our lives; so, more
particularly of this day, which by the Piety of the
State hath been set apart for the Celebration, for the
commemorating, of that kindness, that <HI>marvellous great</HI>
kindness which he hath shewed to us, and to his A∣nointed,
in the chief City of our Nation, the <HI>abstract</HI>
or <HI>Epitomie</HI> of the whole, as before was said. Such <HI>Fe∣stivals</HI>
as these come not within the censure of our ni∣cer
<HI>spirits:</HI> Those which have quarrelled at the rest, the
<HI>Festivals</HI> of <HI>Christ,</HI> and his Apostles, and his Virgin
Mother; do yet allow of <HI>Feriae repentinae, &amp; ex re nata
institutae,</HI> as they please to phrase it: Such as are institu∣ted
and ordained upon new Emergencies. If any thing
displease them in it, it is the setling of it by a Law
to be made perpetual; to be a day of Thankfulness
and Commemoration to succeeding Ages. Which be∣ing
the adding of a new to the ancient Festivals, may
spur on those which are in eminent place and power,
to rejoyn the old Festivals to the new, and cause them
both to be observed with such Christian Piety, that all
men laying aside their Trades and profane Imploy∣ments,
may diligently repair to their Parish Churches,
to set forth <HI>God's most worthy praise, to hear his most
holy Word, and to ask those things which be requisite
and necessary both for the body and the Soul,</HI> according
to the Laws and Statutes in that case provided. But,
as for this particular day, it is to be observed as our
Feast of <HI>Purim,</HI> in memory of our deliverance from
the hands of <HI>Haman,</HI> and <HI>Haman</HI>'s being hanged up∣on
the Gallouse of his own preparing, together with
his <HI>ten sons</HI> (mark the number well) all executed by
<PB N="41" REF="23"/>
the Common Hang-man on the same account. A day
of praising God in our Publique Churches, of Feast∣ing
and Rejoycing in our private Houses, of Joy and
Triumphs in our Streets; A day to be observed with
all due Solemnity, as being the Birth-day of the King
and the Kingdom too.</P>
<P>44. And so it cannot choose but do, if we look back
upon the miseries of the former Tyranny, as well in our
Spiritual Concernments as our Civil Rights. And then
reflect upon this Day as it was celebrated by all sorts
of People at the King's Reduction. And first, if we
take notice of the miseries of the times preceding in
reference to <HI>Spiritual matters,</HI> we may observe our
Publique Liturgie disgraced, and at last discharged,
to make way for the rash, seditious, and inconside∣rate
evaporations of those turbulent spirits, whose ve∣ry
Prayers, in fine, were turned into Sin: The Pulpits
every where left open to all sorts of <HI>Mechanicks;</HI> and
either no Priests made at all, or, none but such as were
of <HI>Ieroboam</HI>'s making, <HI>Priests of the lowest of the Peo∣ple;</HI>
abhorring <HI>Idols</HI> made a colour for committing
<HI>Sacriledge,</HI> such <HI>Sacriledges</HI> too as seldom or never
had been heard of amongst the <HI>Gentiles; Pictures</HI> and
<HI>Images</HI> in Church-windows (retained for Ornaments
till this day in the <HI>Lutheran</HI> Churches) defaced on pur∣pose,
for the ostentation of a swifter <HI>Zeal,</HI> than <HI>could
keep company</HI> with <HI>Knowledge.</HI> But, in the mean time,
such a <HI>worshipping of Imaginations</HI> advanced and coun∣tenanced
as seemed no less destructive to all <HI>Christian
Piety,</HI> than the <HI>worship of Images;</HI> and, in a word, all
the exploded Heresies of the <HI>elder times</HI> revived, and
justified, without reproach to them that did it; to the
<PB N="42" REF="24"/>
displeasure of Almighty God, the dishonour of the
Church, the grief of all good men, and the shame of
the Nation. Nor did we speed much better in our <HI>Ci∣vil
Rights,</HI> in reference to that <HI>liberty</HI> and <HI>property,</HI>
which seems peculiar in a manner to the <HI>English</HI> Sub∣jects.
<HI>Quocunque aspiceres, luctus gemitus que sonabant,</HI>
in the Poets language. No news in any of our Streets,
but that of leading men into fresh captivity; nor
Musick to be heard in our private Houses, but the
sighs, groans, and cries of afflicted people, who either
suffered in themselves, or their friends and kindred.
Our persons haled unto the prisons, and our heads
to the block▪ our children born to bondage, and brought
up to servitude, our goods taken from us, and exposed
to sale; all our Lands either held in <HI>villenage;</HI> or, which
was worse, <HI>ad voluntatem Domini,</HI> during the will and
pleasure only of our mighty Landlords. Such a confusi∣on
in the City, such spoils and rapines in the Countrey,
and such oppressions in all places under their com∣mand;
that greater miseries never fell upon God's
own people in those wretched times, in which there
was <HI>no King in Israel.</HI></P>
<P>46. To put an end to which misfortunes, God brings
the King unto his Throne, as upon this day; and brings
him to his Throne after such a manner, as makes it
seem all-miracle in the eyes of Christendom. When
first, like <HI>Noah</HI>'s <HI>Dove</HI> in the book of <HI>Genesis,</HI> he left the
<HI>Ark</HI> of his retreat and preservation, that he might trie
whether the <HI>waters were asswaged from the face of the
earth,</HI> he found no resting place for the <HI>soles of his feet;</HI>
but when he took his second flight, and came next a∣mongst
us, and brought an <HI>Olive leaf</HI> in his mouth, to
<PB N="43" REF="24"/>
be a Pledge of Peace and Reconciliation betwixt him
and his people, he made his coming most agreeable to
those very men, who before most feared it. A coming
so agreeable to all sorts of people, that never King was
entertained with more signs of joy, or welcomed with
a greater concourse of his faithful Subjects; all of them
with <HI>Te Deum</HI> in their mouths, and the <HI>Magnificat</HI> in
their hearts; old women being as busie at their <HI>Bene∣dicite</HI>'s,
in their dark retreats, as Children were at <HI>Ho∣sanna's</HI>
in the wayes and fields. <HI>The mountains skippe
like Raws, and the little hils like young Sheep,</HI> as he
passed along; the Trees bowed down their heads to
salute their King; and the glad earth, rejoyced to be∣come
his footstool. But when he came within the view
of the <HI>Royal City,</HI> Good God! what infinite throngs of
people did run out to see him? With what a gallant
equipage did the Nobility and Gentry set forth to
meet him. Never did <HI>England</HI> see it self so glorious
as upon that day, nor <HI>old Rome</HI> so magnificent in her
stateliest Triumphs, as our great City then appeared
in the eyes of those, who flocked from all parts of the
Kingdom in such infinite numbers, that <HI>London</HI> could
no more be called the <HI>abstract</HI> or <HI>epitome</HI> of the Realm
of <HI>England,</HI> but the Realm it self.</P>
<P>47. Incouraged with which general Welcome, he
hath received here (here in this Church, he hath recei∣ved)
his last <HI>Anoynting,</HI> to the great joy of all his true
and faithful Subjects; who once again repaired to our
Capital City, but in greater multitudes, that by their
quality, numbers, and external Gallantry, they might
express their good affections, and add some new
Lustre to the accustomed Pomp and Splendour of the
<PB N="44" REF="25"/>
<HI>Coronation.</HI> The Pomp and Splendour of which day, is
not to be described by a readier pen than I am able to
pretend to; nor to be equalled by any other in the
times preceding, but only by the glorious day of the
Kings <HI>Reduction;</HI> of which we may affirm with the
Court Historian, though with no such flattery, <HI>La<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i∣tiam
illius diei, consursum totius civitatis, &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
pene inferenti<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m coelo m<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>is, &amp;c.</HI> What pen is able to
express the Triumphs of those two great dayes, when
all the bravery of the Nation seemed to be powred
into the City, and the whole City emptied into some
few streets, the windows in those streets to be glased
with eyes, the houses in a maner to be tyled with men;
and all the people in the streets, the windowes and the
house tops also, ingeminating and regeminating this
most joyful acclamation, <HI>God save the King.</HI></P>
<P>48. For which great mercies, and the rest of this
glorious day, let us sing our <HI>Benedictus</HI> also, to the
Lord our God: <HI>Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, for he
hath visited and redeemed his people, and hath raised
up a mighty salvation for us in the house of his servant
David.</HI> To which Immortal and Invisible God, the
Almighty Father; and to the Honorable, true and only
Son, the Lamb that sits upon the Throne; and to the
Holy Ghost the Comforter; Let us ascribe, as we are
bound, all Majesty, Might, Praise, Power, and Glory,
from this time forth for ever more. And let all the
people say, <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="25"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

