<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A plain and true relation of a very extraordinary cure of Marianne Maillard in a letter to a friend.</TITLE><AUTHOR>E. H.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A43793</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H20</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R29466</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">11147120</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 11147120</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">46414</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A43793)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46414)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1424:15)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A plain and true relation of a very extraordinary cure of Marianne Maillard in a letter to a friend.</TITLE><AUTHOR>E. H.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 14 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Randal Taylor,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1693.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Signed: E.H.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Maillard, Marianne.</TERM><TERM>Hip joint --  Dislocation.</TERM><TERM>Dislocations.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Celeste Ng</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Celeste Ng</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A43793">
<STC T="W">H20</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">11147120</BIBNO>
<VID>46414</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A
PLAIN and TRUE
RELATION
Of a Very
Extraordinary CURE
OF
<HI>Mariane Maillard.</HI></P>
<P>In a LETTER to a Friend.</P>
<P><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="license">
<P>Licensed,</P>
<CLOSER><DATE><HI>December</HI> 21. 1693.</DATE>
<SIGNED>Dan. Popler.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI>
Printed for <HI>Randal Taylor,</HI> near <HI>Stationers-Hall▪</HI>
1693.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A
PLAIN and TRUE
RELATION
Of a very Extraordinary Cure
OF
Mariane Maillard.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="letter">
<HEAD>In a Letter to a Friend.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Dear Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><HI>I</HI> Received yours of the <HI>20th</HI> Instant, in which you
desire to be Inform'd of the Truth of a Story, which
you say, you have seen in a small Printed Paper,
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
called, <HI>The Happy Virgin,</HI> of a <HI>French</HI> Girl late∣ly
Cured after an extraordinary manner in a moment
of time of an old inveterate Lameness, which hath
been always thought Incurable by any Art of Man;
as she was Reading the Story of our Saviours Healing
and Pardoning of the Paralitic; being therefore always
ready to serve you in what I may, and being my
self also much affected with the thing, I have enquir∣ed
fully into the Matter, and do not in the least doubt
of its Truth and Certainty; though I am very much
concern'd and scandalized at that Relation, which you
have seen in that Printed Paper, because it is not on∣ly
untrue in many things, and particularly in what it
says of an unhappy Fall from a Table, which bruised
and broke the Childs Hip and other Bones; which are
nothing so, but do very much disparage the Story it self
in the Account it pretends to give of it; and there∣fore
having Inform'd my self sufficiently (as I think)
about it, I shall give you a Plain and True Relati∣on
of the matter of Fact, without any Remarks, or
Observations of my own, for the thing being undoubt∣edly
true, needs nothing to set it off, or recommend it
to the World, there being no Parties of Men that I
know of that endeavour to serve themselves by it any
further than to be satisfied of its Truth, and give
Glory to God for the things that he hath done; and in∣deed
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
you are your self too great a Judg of such
watters, for me to Attempt any thing more than the
Relation it self, which in Obedience to your Commands,
for such all your Requests are with me, I here withal
send you, and give you free leave to impart it to as ma∣ny
of your Friends as you think fit.</P>
<P><HI>MAriane Maillard,</HI> the Person of whom you
desire an Acconnt, is the Daughter of
one Mr. <HI>John Maillard</HI> a French Protestant, of the
Town of <HI>Cognar,</HI> in <HI>Saintonge,</HI> where he Lived
in good repute, being a Sword-Cutler by Trade,
and a very Honest Man, and had four Children,
of which this <HI>Mariane</HI> was the Eldest, who when
she was Six Months Old, became Lame by an
accidental Fall out of her Fathers Arms, who
being very fond of her, would be frequently
playing with her, tossing her up, and catching
her again, till at last he very unhapyily let her
fall to the Ground, where she received, as it ap∣pear'd
afterwards, a very considerable hurt in her
left side; which he not then apprehending any
danger from, thinking that it might be only a
little Bruise that would be soon well again; and
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
being unwilling to tell his Wife of it, for fear of
frighting, or troubling of her, took no further
care about it, till at last perceiving that her Hip
was out, by the wryness of the Leg and Foot,
and very distorted motion when the Child began
to go, the Heel turning almost quite forward, he
became extreamly concern'd at it, and desir'd the
help of several Surgeons, who after they had
seen it, declar'd it to be incurable, as did also di∣vers
other Surgeons, both in <HI>Switzerland</HI> and <HI>Lon∣don;</HI>
and particularly Mr. <HI>Dubatt,</HI> a very Emi∣nent
Surgeon in <HI>Green-Street</HI> near <HI>Leister-Fields,</HI>
to whom it was shewn by her Parents afterwards,
and that the Cure of it could not be attempted
without endangering the Life of the Child, and
exposing it to the most exquisite Pain and Tor∣ture,
which the Parents by no means consenting
to, chose rather to submit to the Will of God,
than try so cruel and desperate an Experiment:
And by this means the Child continued Lame,
growing still more and more crooked and defor∣med
as it grew up, being always ready to fall as
she went along; and thus she continued till she
was 6 or 7 years old, when her Father was forc'd
to fly out of <HI>France,</HI> upon the Dragooning part
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
of the <HI>French</HI> Persecution, chusing rather to do so
than change his Religion; and so taking his Wife
and Four Children with him, of which this was
the Eldest, he fled first into <HI>Switzerland,</HI> traveling
only by Night, enduring great hardships, and es∣caping
many dangers; where having staid some
time, he came from thence through <HI>Germany</HI> into
<HI>Holland;</HI> and at last came over into <HI>England</HI> about
the time of the late Revolution; but being ex∣tream
poor, and not able to maintain his Wife
and Children, he obtain'd to be made a Serjeant
in one of the <HI>French</HI> Regiments that went over in∣to
<HI>Ireland,</HI> under the Command of Capt. <HI>De La∣sherosi,</HI>
in Col. <HI>Corbon</HI>'s Regiment, where he served
the Regiment Two Years, but the Pay not an∣swering
his Expectation and Necessities, he was
forc'd to quit that Imployment, and return to his
Trade, and went over every year with the Ar∣my
into <HI>Flanders,</HI> there to mend and sell Swords.
His Wife also being an Industrious and Skillful
Woman, went amongst the <HI>French</HI> Refugees, to
make the Beds, and clean the Rooms of those
that were sick, by which means she got a small
subsistence for her self and Children, being paid
an half penny for each Room. And in this sort
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
of Service she continued for some time, taking
this Girl, for the most part, along with her,
who us'd, as far as she was able, to assist her
Mother, and soon became very serviceable to
her, till one day as she was attending thus upon
one Madam <HI>Laulan,</HI> who fled hither from the
<HI>French</HI> Persecution, and formerly, for about 12
or 13 years together had been a Domestick of
Marshal <HI>Turene;</HI> during his being a Protestant,
waiting upon his Lady (a Person of Eminent Pi∣ety,
Charity and Wisdom, and a great Patro∣ness
of all of the Reform'd Religion in <HI>France</HI> that
needed her Countenance and Assistance) in the
Quality of her Woman, who perceiving the Girl
very towardly, and willing to do any thing she
could for her Mother, was so pleas'd with her,
(being then very ill her self, and having a Son
also sick at the same time, who is since dead) that
she took her to look to them both, and to go a∣bout
upon Errands as she had occasion, instead of
a Nurse, or other Servant, which she was not
able to maintain; And with her she lived Three
Years, doing all things with greater care and har∣diness
than could have been expected from her
Years and Condition, being then but a little a∣bove
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
nine years old, and withal so much afflicted
with extream Pains by reason of her Lameness,
that she rather seem'd to need one to attend upon
her, than to be put to attend upon an other;
and indeed if meer poverty had not forced her
to it, she might well have been excused from
that sort of Service; but her Parents not being
able to maintain her better, were glad of the
opportunity to dispose of her so well, knowing
Madam <HI>Laulan</HI> to be a very pious and good tem∣pered
Woman, and indeed the Girl was so pleas∣ed
with her New Service, and took such a liking
to her Mistress, that she seem'd well contented
with her Condition, and bore her Affliction with
the greatest patience (tho she often felt great
pain in her Hip and Leg on that side on which
she was Lame, especially in Foggy Misty Wea∣ther.)</P>
<P>The only thing that most sensibly Afflicted her,
was the scoffing persecution which she daily met
with from the Boys in the Streets; who seeing her
strange distorted manner of goiug (which was in∣deed
very unusual) were wont to follow her, and
pull her with great Rudeness, calling her <HI>Crooked
Monster,</HI> &amp;c. of which she frequently complain'd
to her Mrs. who being a very good Christian, gave
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>
her still the best Advice and Comfort that she
could, telling her, that there was no help for her.
and therefore she must bear it with patience; which
indeed she did for a long time.</P>
<P>But on <HI>Sunday,</HI> the 26th of <HI>November,</HI> last past,
as she return'd home in the Evening from Church,
she was much concern'd to see a Man, as she judg∣ed,
about Forty years of Age, joyn with the
Boys in abusing and tormenting of her, telling
her Mistress when she came home, with many
Tears, that she thought he might have been
better Imployed than to Laugh at her, who had
already but too much Sorrow and Affliction from
her Condition; her Mistress endeavoured to
Comfort her again, as she used to do, and told
her, That if she would thus trouble her self
every time she was so used, she would have e∣uough
to do, and never want for Vexation,
since her Lameness was Incurable, and would
remain so all her Life long, and that therefore
she must resolve to be Patient, and to Commit
her Cause to God, using several other Argu∣ments
with her to the same purpose, to pacify
her Mind, and allay her Trouble, and the more
to put these thoughts out of her head, having
eaten a little Supper, she bid her take her Bible
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
and Read a Chapter to her, as she used to do
every day in the <HI>New Testament.</HI> The place that
she was then to Read, in the course of her daily
Reading, was the 2d of St. <HI>Mark;</HI> but opening
the Bible, she hapned to meet with that place of
St. <HI>Matt.</HI> where the <HI>Evangelist</HI> speaks of St▪ <HI>Peter's</HI>
Mother, who lay sick of a Fever, and was by our
Saviour's touching of her immediately cur'd.</P>
<P>Her Mrs. liking that place, because it had some re∣lation
to her present distemper, which was an inter∣mitting
Fever, and r<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>turn'd every day, and continu'd
for a long time, bid her read that out before she
turn'd to her own Chapt. Which she did, and when
she had done they had some discourse upon it, the
Mrs. saying, <HI>Oh▪ how happy should I be if I were thus deli∣ver'd
from my Fever: And I</HI> (adding the maid) <HI>if I were
Cur'd of my Lameness.</HI> After this she turn'd to her own
Chapter, which hepned to be the 2<HI>d</HI> of St. <HI>Mark;</HI>
where upon reading the Story of the man that was
sick of the <HI>Palsie,</HI> whose Faith our Saviour there
commends; amongst the rest that assisted in letting
him down thro' the Roof into his presence, and
whom he not only cures, but grants besides the for∣giveness
of his sins too: She made a stop, and began
to exclaim against the <HI>Scribes,</HI> not only for persist∣ing
in their incredulity, but for accusing our Savi∣our
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
also of Blasphemy, saying to her <HI>Mrs. Oh how wic∣ked
were these unbelieving</HI> Scribes <HI>to speak so of our Savi∣our,
when he had done so many Miraeles; I am sure I should
have done quite otherwise; and if I should hear of such a thing
I should immediately run to him and believe.</HI> And whilst
she was thus speaking, she had her leg stretch'd out
towards her <HI>Mrs.</HI> who bid her pull it back, telling
her it was not decent to put it so near her; to whom
the maid reply'd, <HI>Mrs. I did not complain much to day be∣cause
you forbad me, but I do assure you I have felt a great
deal of pain, as I use to do in all misty weather.</HI> And at the
same time as they were thus talking together, they
heard suddenly a great snap, which they both per∣ceived
very plain, the <HI>Mrs.</HI> thinking it had been som∣thing
in the fire that made that noise; but the maid
rising up very hastily, crys Out, <HI>Mrs. Did you hear the
noise? It was my Hip-bone that is certainly restored to its place;</HI>
and throwing her self upon her mrs. with such
transports of Joy, as if she had been beside her self;
she embrac'd her knees about so fast, that she could
not get her off, saying, <HI>my dear mistriss,</HI> I <HI>am well, my pain
is all gone, and</HI> I <HI>hear something that says, thou art cured, my
joy is so great that</HI> I <HI>cannot tell where</HI> I <HI>am, nor what</HI> I <HI>do:
pray feel your self and see here the hollow place is filled up, and
the swelling quite gone; Oh God be thanked; pray let me go
and shew it the Landlord and Landlady, and the Maid below</HI>
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
<HI>Stairs;</HI> and so walkt several turns about the Room
without any pain at all, her foot being now strait as
the other. And thus she has continu'd ever since, on∣ly
that leg being a little shorter than the other (per∣haps
through the long continuance out of its place
which hindred its due growth, and the necessary ex∣tension
of the Nerves and Sinews; She therefore halts
a little still, but has nothing at all of that monstrous
distorted lameness which she had before, and which
all that knew her then, and have seen her now, can∣not
but extreamly wonder at, and praise God for.</P>
<P>Her Mrs. seeing her in these transports of joy, was
afraid at first that she was or would be quite beside
her self; but considering the matter well, and seeing
with her own Eyes the wonderful change that was
made in her condition, the hollow place which she
had often, and but that very day seen and felt, per∣fectly
fill'd up, the bone in its proper place, and her
leg and foot now strait and right as it should be;
She bid her not think of going down stairs that
night, but rather fall upon her <HI>knees,</HI> and give God
his due praise, who had done so much for her, and
who in a minutes time had cur'd a pain and lame∣ness
that had been of 12 years continuance, which
no Art of man could do; aud so they accordingly
did, it being then late, went both to bed, vvhere the
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
poor Girl could hardly rest or sleep for Joy. The
next morning she shew'd it to as many of her ac∣quaintance
as she could meet with, who could not
but wonder at so strange and unlook'd for a thing.
Her Parents savv it vvith tears of Joy, and have, as
they ought, sent Bills into the Churches, that God
might be the more glorified, and his praises be set
forth the better by vvhole Congregations.</P>
<P>Thus, Sir, I have given you a plain, but very
true and exact Account of this Matter, in com∣pliance
with your earnest and well intended en∣quiry
after it, to which I might indeed add, for
the full Confirmation of it, a great number of
Certificates and Affidavits (having some by me)
from many hundreds of Persons that have seen
and known this Girl both before and since her
Cure, and are able to give a full and satisfactory
Account of her, to all that shall be desirous more
particularly to be Inform'd about her; but to
what purpose should I give my self and you that
Trouble, since the same enquiry into the Truth
of those Certificates and Affidavits, which is ne∣cessary
for the confirmatiod of them, would be
sufficient to satisfy any body of the Truth of the
thing; let it suffice therefore to shew you that
she was Personally known to Mr. <HI>Du Batt,</HI> whom
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
I mention'd before; to the Lady <HI>Sunderland,</HI> and
her Family, whether she often resorted, and
where she was always well accepted, and receiv'd
many Charitable Kindnesses, both in Meat and
Mony, and who will all Testify to the Truth of
her Lameness; as will also most of Mr. <HI>Hamp∣den</HI>'s
Family, whither she also went very frequent∣ly
to sell some little things for her Mrs. which
they used in Charity and Compassion to Buy of
her; to these I might add above 100 persons more
of this Nation, besides an innumerable company
of her own, who all knew and pittied her sad con∣dition,
and who now rejoyce and wonder to see
her so perfectly Cur'd in so short a time. One thing
indeed will be necessary for me to give you a lit∣tle
account concernidg the place of her abode,
and where she may be found, that so all doubting
persons may be fully satisfied in the Truth of this
matter that are any ways desirous to be inform'd
of it, and when this strange and amazing Cure was
Wrought, she liv'd with her Mrs. who Lodg'd at
an <HI>Apothecary</HI>'s House whose Name is <HI>Tent,</HI> in an
Ally at the <HI>East</HI> end of S. <HI>James</HI>'s Church, that goes
up from <HI>Germain-Street</HI> into <HI>Pickadilly;</HI> but <HI>Tent</HI>
being behind hand with his Rent, went away pri∣vately
with his Goods on <HI>Sunday</HI> Night, the 17th
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
instant, which the Landlord hearing of, came the
next day to the House, and finding Mrs. <HI>Laulan</HI> in it,
Seiz'd her Goods, supposing them to be <HI>Tents,</HI> and
turns her and the Girl out of doors; upon vvhich
they were forc'd to part, till Mrs▪ <HI>Laulan</HI> can get her
Goods again. In the mean time she lodges among
some of her acquaintance, but as yet at no certain
place. The Girl is now vvith her Father, at the cor∣ner
of <HI>Newport-Ally</HI> near <HI>Soho,</HI> and may be seen and
spoken vvith at any time by any that desire it. Her
Father is a Sensible Good Man, and no vvays exal∣ted
above vvhat is fitting for a Good Christian up∣on
such an Extraordinary Occasion, being more
Glad and Thankful in the Mercy, than any ways of∣ficiously
concern'd to have any body believe it;
whicb does indeed seem to me to Give no little
Credit to the truth of the story it self.</P>
<P>I shall now conclude, Sir, in the <HI>words</HI> of the <HI>Pa∣rents</HI>
of the man that vvas born blind, vvho told the
inquisitive and unhelieving <HI>Pharisee, That he was their
Son, and was born blind, but they could not tell how he came
to see.</HI> The same, in a manner, may hundreds say a∣bout
this Child, <HI>That they knew her to be lame, and now
see her cur'd, but how she came to be so they know not, and
can believe it to be no other than a very extraordinary and
amazing thing.</HI> Which is all at present from,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>Your humble servant,
E. H.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
<PB REF="9"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

