<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A tract concerning schism and schismatiqves wherein is briefly discovered the originall causes of all schisme / written by a learned and judicious divine ; together with certain animadversions upon some passages thereof.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Hales, John, 1584-1656.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A44476</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H278</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R2860</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12630457</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12630457</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">64736</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A44476)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64736)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 251:E143, no 22)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A tract concerning schism and schismatiqves wherein is briefly discovered the originall causes of all schisme / written by a learned and judicious divine ; together with certain animadversions upon some passages thereof.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Hales, John, 1584-1656.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Page, William, 1590-1663.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 33 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>Oxford :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Leonard Lichfield for Edward Forrest,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1642.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>"The Animadversions which are the raison d'être of this issue were, according to Wood, by Dr. William Page."  Cf. Madan, Oxford books.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Church of England --  History --  Sources.</TERM><TERM>Heresy --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Schism --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ben Griffin</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ben Griffin</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A44476">
<STC T="W">H278</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12630457</BIBNO>
<VID>64736</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A TRACT
CONCERNING
SCHISME
AND
SCHISMATIQVES. WHEREIN,
Is briefly discovered the originall causes
of all Schisme.</P>
<P>Written by a Learned and Judicious Divine.</P>
<P>TOGETHER,
With certain Animadversions upon some
Passages thereof.</P>
<P>OXFORD,
Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD for
<HI>Edward Forrest.</HI> 1642.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A
TRACT CONCERNING
SCHISME.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>Eresie and <HI>Schisme</HI> as they are commonly used,
are two Theologicall scar crows, with which
they, who uphold a party in Religion, vse to
fright away such, as making enquiry into it, are
ready to relinquish and oppose it, if it appeare
either erronious or suspitious; for as <HI>Plutarch</HI> re∣ports
of a Painter, who having unskilfully painted a Cock, chased
away all Cocks and Hens, that so the imperfection of his Art
might not appeare by comparison with Nature; so men, willing
for ends to admit of no fancy but their own, endeavour to hinder
all enquiry into it, by way of comparison of somewhat with it,
peradventure truer, that so the deformity of their own, might
not appeare: but howsoever in the common manage, <HI>Heresie</HI> and
<HI>Schisme</HI> are but ridiculous tearmes, yet the things in themselves
are of very considerable moment, the one offending against
Truth, the other against Charity, and therefore both deadly,
when they are not by imputation, but in deed.</P>
<P>It is then a matter of no small importance, truely to descry the
nature of them, that so they may feare who are guilty of them, and
they on the contrary strengthen themselves, who, through the
iniquity of men and times, are injuriously charged with them.</P>
<P><HI>Schisme</HI> (for of <HI>Heresie</HI> we shall not now treat, except it be
by accident, and that by occasion of a generall mistake, spread
through all the writings of the Ancients, in which their names
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
are familiarly confounded) <HI>Schisme,</HI> I say, upon the very sound
of the word imports division, <HI>Division</HI> is not but where <HI>Com∣munion</HI>
is or ought to be: now <HI>Communion</HI> is the strength and
ground of all Society, whether <HI>Sacred</HI> or <HI>Civill;</HI> whosoever
therefore they be, that offend against this Common society and
friendlinesse of men, if it be in civill occasions, are guilty of Sedi∣tion
or Rebellion; if it be by reason of <HI>Ecclesiasticall</HI> difference,
they are guilty of <HI>Schisme:</HI> So that <HI>Schisme</HI> is an <HI>Ecclesiasticall
sedition,</HI> as <HI>Sedition</HI> is a <HI>lay Schisme,</HI> yet the great benefit of Com∣munion
notwithstanding, in regard of divers distempers men
are subject to, Dissention and Disunion are often necessary; For
when either false or uncertain Conclusions are obtruded for
truth, and Acts either unlawfull, or ministring just scruple are
required of us to be perform'd, in these cases, consent were con∣spiracy,
and open contestation is not faction or <HI>Schisme,</HI> but due
Christian animosity.</P>
<P>For the opening therefore of the nature of <HI>Schisme,</HI> some∣thing
must be added by way of difference, to distinguish it from
necessary separation, and that is, that the cause upon which divi∣sion
is attempted, proceed not from Passion, or from Distemper,
or from Ambition, or Avatice, or such other ends, as humane
folly is apt to pursue, but from well weighed and necessary rea∣sons,
and that when all other means having been tryed, nothing
will serve to save us from guilt of Conscience, but open separa∣tion;
so that <HI>Schisme,</HI> if we would define it, is nothing else but
an unnecessary separation of Christians from that part of the visi∣ble
Church, of which they were once members; now as in mu∣tinies
and civill dissentions, there are two attendants in ordinary
belonging unto them: one, the Choyse of an Elector or Guide,
in place of the Generall or Ordinary Governor, to rule and
guide, the other the appointing of some publique place, or Ran∣devous,
where publike meetings must be celebrated. So in
Church dissentions and quarrells, two appurtenances there are,
which serve to make <HI>Schisme</HI> compleat.</P>
<P>First, in the choyce of a <HI>Bishop,</HI> in opposition to the former,
(a thing very frequent amongst the Ancients, and which many
times was the cause and effect of <HI>Schisme.</HI>)</P>
<P>Secondly, the erecting of a new Church and Oratory, for the
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
dividing parts to meet in publiquely. For till this be done, the
<HI>Schisme</HI> is but yet in the wombe.</P>
<P>In that late famous Controversy in <HI>Holland, De Pradestina∣tione
&amp; auxiliis,</HI> as long as the disagreeing parties went no far∣ther
then Disputes and Pen-Combats, the <HI>Schisme</HI> was all that
while unhatched; but as soon as one party swept an old Cloyster,
and by a pretty Art suddenly made it a Church, by putting a new
Pulpit in it, for the separating party there to meet; now what be∣fore
was a Controversy, became a formall <HI>Schisme.</HI> To know
no more then this, if you take it to be true, had been enough to
direct how you are to judge, and what to think of <HI>Schisme</HI> and
<HI>Schismatiques,</HI> yet because of the <HI>Ancients,</HI> (by whom many
are more affrighted then hurt) much is said and many fearefull
doomes are pronounced in this case, we will descend a little to
consider of <HI>Schisme,</HI> as it were by way of story, and that partly
farther to open that, which we have said in generall by instancing
in particulars, and partly to disabuse those, who reverencing
Antiquity more then needs, have suffered themselves to be sca∣red
with imputation of <HI>Schisme</HI> above due measure, for what the
Ancients speake by way of censure of <HI>Schisme</HI> in generall is most
true, for they saw (and it is no great matter to see so much) that
unadvised and open fancy to break the knot of union, betwixt
man and man (especially amongst Christians, upon whom above
all other kind of men, the tye of love and communion doth most
especially rest) was a crime hardly pardonable, and that nothing
absolves men from the guilt of it, but true and unpretended
Conscience, yet when they came to pronounce of <HI>Schisme</HI> in
particular, (whether it was because of their own interest, or that
they saw not the truth, or for what other cause God only doth
know) their judgements many times (to speak most gently) are
justly to be suspected, which that you may see, we will range all
<HI>Schisme</HI> into two rankes.</P>
<P>First, there is a <HI>Schisme,</HI> in which only one party is the <HI>Schis∣matique:</HI>
for where cause of <HI>Schisme</HI> is necessary, there not he
that separates, but he that is the cause of separation is the <HI>Schis∣matique.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, there is a <HI>Schisme</HI> in which both parties are the
<HI>Schismatiques,</HI> for where the occasion of separation is unnecessa∣ry,
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
neither side can be excused from guilt of <HI>Schisme.</HI></P>
<P>But you will aske, who shall be judge, what is necessary? In∣deed
it is a question which hath been often made, but I think
scarcely ever truly answered, not because it is a point of great
depth or difficulty truly to assoyle it, but because the true soluti∣on
of it, carries fire in the taile of it (for it bringeth with it a piece
of doctrine, which is seldome pleasing to Superiors) To you for
the present, this shall suffice,</P>
<P>If so be you be <HI>animo defaecato,</HI> if you have cleared your selfe
from froath and grownes, if neither sloath nor feare, nor ambi∣tion,
nor any tempting spirit of that nature abuse you (for these
and such as these are the true impediments, why both that and
other questions of the like danger are not truly answered) if
all this be, and yet you know not how to frame your resolution,
and settle your selfe for that doubt; I will say no more of you,
then was said of <HI>Papias</HI> S. <HI>Iohns</HI> own schollar, your abilities are
not so good as I presumed.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="comment">
<HEAD>ANIMADVERSION.</HEAD>
<P>THIS tract, I must confesse, is handsomly and acute∣ly
penned, and many things in it well worthy our
observation. Yet because I greatly honour antiquity,
and highly reverence the holy Fathers of the Church, I
must crave pardon, if I deale plainly, and roundly with
the Author thereof, who in some passages (as I con∣ceive)
doth two much neglect antiquity, and indeed all
authority.</P>
<P>For first, in that he saith, <HI>the Fathers generally mistake
in confounding these names of Heresies and Schisme,</HI> they
doe not mistake them, but commonly distinguish them,
or it is no great matter if they doe, they are so neerly
linked together, that they are seldome seperated, you
shall hardly find any one guilty of Schisme, but he doth
easily and very often fall into Heresie.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="4"/>
<HI>Schisme,</HI> say you, <HI>is an unnecessary seperation of Christi∣ans
from that part of the visible Church, of which they
were once members.</HI> But as you will put the question
afterwards, <HI>who shall be judge what is necessary? and you
are loath to assoile this question because the solution there∣of
carryeth fire in the taile of it, for it bringeth with it a
peice of doctrine, seldome pleasing to superiors.</HI></P>
<P>Is this doctrine, let me aske you, good or bad? If
good, then it should, then I hope it will be pleasing to su∣periours;
If bad, then should it displease superiours and
inferiours too. But the truth is, the doctrine is most per∣nicious
to government, and therefore to all sorts of
people, to wit, in plaine termes, it is this, that every one
must judge for himself with this proviso, so he be <HI>animo
defaecato,</HI> And I pray who shall judge of this? Even
your selfe also. So that if you be perswaded that you are
<HI>animo defaecato,</HI> and if you thinke <HI>you have cleared your
selfe from the froath and grownes of feare, sloath, and ambi∣tion,</HI>
then it must needs be so, whereas the heart of man
being deceitfull above all things, there is nothing more
usuall then for a man to deceive himselfe, and think he
is thus and thus, when he is nothing so. And seeing the
best of us all have <HI>faces</HI> enough in us, why may not su∣periors
have as few of these dreggs in them as inferiors,
and so as well able, at the least, to judge a right, as they.
And you may talke what you will of being clear from
the froath of ambition, I know not what greater pride
and ambition there can be then thus to pull downe all
authority and jurisdiction, and erect a tribunall in euery
mans brest; And yet he that goeth about it, will think
him selfe to be <HI>animo defaecato:</HI> And you may well say
<HI>it carrieth fire in the taile of it.</HI> For thus to trample un∣der
foot all power and authority, by making every one
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
his own judge, must needs raise a great combustion and
a strange confusion in the world.</P>
<P>Secondly, you cannot endure that they should be tru∣ly
Hereticks and Schismaticks which were anciently so
esteemed. For say you, <HI>men are more affrighted then
hurt by the Auncients, and that many reverence antiquity
more then need,</HI> and after tell us in plain tearmes, <HI>that
when they came to pronounce of Schismes in particular,
whether it were because of their own interests, or that they
saw not the truth, or for what other cause God only doth
know, their judgements many times to (speak most gently)
are justly to be suspected.</HI></P>
<P>Where I will not goe about to defend all the particu∣lar
tenents of every Father, for questionlesse, being men,
they had their passions and perturbations as well as wee,
so that take them singly, wee shall find in many of them
such private conceits of their owne, which cannot be so
well excused: Yet for all this, when all, or most of them
agree together in any point, we are not to question or
doubt of the truth of it, according to that ancient and
hitherto well approved rule of <HI>Vincentius Lirinensis,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Lib. ad Her. cap. 39.</NOTE>
<HI>Whatsoever all of them, or most of them, in one and the
same sense shall plainly frequently and constantly deliver
and confirme, let that be esteemed as a ratified, certaine,
and undoubted truth.</HI></P>
<P>So then, though one or two of them may be mista∣ken,
yet that all or the greatest part should agree toge∣ther
in a falsehood, I cannot easily believe. And there∣fore
I cannot think that the current of the Fathers
should thus be mistaken, and that they should generally
account them for Hereticks and Schismaticks, which
were not so indeed; I shall not so much suspect their
<HI>judgements,</HI> as his that thinks so. But all this I perceive
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
is, that there might be some opinions favoured now,
which were commonly condemned by them, as we shall
see afterward.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="text">
<HEAD>TRACT.</HEAD>
<P>But to goe on with what I intended, and from that that diver∣ted
me, that you may the better judge of the nature of <HI>Schismes</HI>
by their occasions, you shall find that all <HI>Schismes</HI> have crept into
the Church by one of these three waies, either upon matter of
fact, or upon matter of opinion, or point of ambition: for the
first, I call that matter of fact, when something is required to be
done by us, which either we know, or strongly suspect to be un∣lawfull;
so the first notable <HI>Schisme,</HI> of which we read in the
Church, contained in it matter of fact, for it being upon error
taken for necessary, that an <HI>Easter</HI> must be kept, and upon worse
then error (if I may so speak) for it was no lesse then a point of
Iudaisme forced upon the Church, upon worse then error, I say,
thought further necessary that the ground of the time, for keep∣ing
of that Feast must be the rule left by <HI>Moses</HI> to the <HI>Iewes,</HI>
there arose a stout Question, whether we were to celebrate with
the <HI>Iewes</HI> on the fourteenth <HI>Moon,</HI> or the <HI>Sunday</HI> following?
This matter though most unnecessary, most vaine, yet caused as
great a combustion as ever was in the Church, the <HI>West</HI> separat∣ing
and refusing Communion with the <HI>East,</HI> for many years to∣gether:
In this fantasticall hurry I cannot see but all the world
were <HI>Schismatiques,</HI> neither can any thing excuse them from
that imputation, excepting only this, that we charitably suppose
that all parties did what they did out of Conseience, a thing
which befell them through the ignorance of their guides, (for I
will not say through their malice) and that through the just
judgement of God. because through sloath and blind obedience
men examined not the things which they were taught, but like
beasts of burthen, patiently couched downe, and indifferently
underwent whatsoever their Superiours laid upon them: by the
way, by this we may plainly see the danger of our appeale to
Antiquity, for resolution in controverted points of Faith, and
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>
how small reliefe we are to expect from thence; for if the dis∣cretion
of the chiefest Guides, &amp; Directors of the Church, did in
a point so triviall, so inconsiderable, so mainely faile them, as not
to see the truth in a subject, wherein it is the greatest marvaile,
how they could avoide the sight of it, can we without the im∣putation
of great grossenesse and folly, think so poore spirited
persons, competent Iudges of the questions now on foot betwixt
the Churches; pardon me, I know not what Temptation drew
that note from me.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="comment">
<HEAD>ANIMADVERSION.</HEAD>
<P>Thirdly, about keeping of Easter, say you, <HI>anciently
all the world were Schismaticks.</HI></P>
<P>A strange assertion, to lay such an heavy imputation
upon all those auncient worthies. Had they been thus
guilty, it had been the part of a dutifull sonne to have
made some apology for them, and to have covered his
Fathers nakednesse. But a farre greater crime it is, thus to
accuse them without a cause. The best of it is, I shall not
haue occasion here to excuse their error, but to defend
their innocencie. For first, their difference is not about a
point that concerneth <HI>Faith</HI> or <HI>Good manners,</HI> but only
the outward discipline and government of the Church:
about the keeping of a solemne feast. And that not, whe∣ther
we should keep it or no, (for all agreed well enough
that it ought to be kept) but about the time of keeping it,
whether at this or that time, which is a matter of farre
lesse moment.</P>
<P>The occasion of this difference briefly was thus, S<SUP>t</SUP>
<HI>Peter</HI> and his successors at Rome kept Easter the Sunday
after the foureteenth Moon. But S. <HI>Iames</HI> and many of
his successors at <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> being all of them Ministers
of the circumcision, the sooner to win their brethren the
Iewes, condescended to keep their Easter, as the Iewes
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
did, <HI>14<SUP>o</SUP> Lunae.</HI> Which diversity of observation conti∣nued
for the space of 200. years, neither Church cen∣suring
or condemning one another for it. Till at the
length <HI>Victor</HI> Pope of Rome would needs take upon him
to bring all those Easterne Churches to his custome, and
excommunicate them for not yeelding, whereupon
grew the Schisme. So that although at the first they
kept Easter diversly for a long time together, yet so
long as there was no breach of charity between them,
there was no Schisme, by your own confession, who tell
us, <HI>that Schisme offends against charity, as Heresy against
truth.</HI></P>
<P>So then, whiles they were charitable one to ano∣ther,
all the world were so farre from being Schisma∣ticks,
that no part of it could be justly thus branded.
The Schisme indeed began, when the Pope would needs
rashly and unadvisedly excommunicate those Easterne
Churches, with whom he had nothing to doe. But then
was not the whole world, but only <HI>Victor</HI> and his parti∣zans
the Schismaticks according to you, who unjustly
divided themselves from the other side, the East Chur∣ches
continuing their old custome without any Schisme
at all, yet some of them not forbearing to tell <HI>Victor</HI> of
his unadvised and unjustifiable action.</P>
<P>For shall we not allow to severall Churches (especial∣ly
when they have no dependency one upon another)
their severall rites and observations, but they must be
all Schismatick for it? You may as well call both these
Churches Schismaticks for this also, because the one
Church fasts on Saturday, the other fasts not; the one
administers the Eucharist in unleavened, the other in lea∣vened
bread. These and such like points concerne not
the body of the Church, but her garments: now al∣though
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
her body must be but one, yet her garments are
of divers colours. Nay, as one saith very well, <HI>diversi∣tas
rituum commendat unitatem fidei.</HI> The unity of faith
doth more gloriously appeare amidst the diversity of ce∣remonies
and rituall observations.</P>
<P>I wonder if one of our refined spirits now a daies,
who is <HI>animo defaecato,</HI> had lived in those times, what
could he have done to avoid this Schisme? how could
he have chosen but be a Schismatick on one side or ano∣ther?
I conceive how he should have escaped by you,
to wit, to joyne with neither side by keeping no Easter
at all: for with you <HI>it is an error to think that an Easter
must be kept:</HI> which position being put in practise will
prove the greatest Schime of all, thus to divide ones
selfe from all the Christian world. For although these
holy Fathers differed for a while amongst themselves
about the time, yet they all agreed against you about the
thing it selfe, and not only the Orthodoxe but the very
Hereticks of those times kept an Easter. Not so much
as the Novatians (who called themselves <HI>Cathari</HI> the
Puritans of the Primitive Church) but an Easter they
had, though they were very indifferent about the time
of keeping it. And the whole Christian world ever
since hath duely observed the keeping of Easter. But
you take no notice of this, only your eare is to excuse
those Fathers the best you can. And you can find but
this one way to doe it, <HI>That we charitably suppose that all
parties did what they did out of conscience, a thing which
befell them through the ignorance of their guides, for I will
not say through their malice, and that through the just
judgement of God, because through sloath and blind obedi∣ence,
men examined not the things which they were taught,
but like beasts of burthen patiently couched downe, and in∣differently
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
underwent whatsoever their superiors laid upon
them.</HI></P>
<P>Doe you call this an excusation, and not rather an hea∣vy
censure and accusation both of <HI>Priest</HI> and <HI>People</HI> in
those purer times: For what a dishonour is this to the
Pastors and Prelates then, that they who lived so neare
the Apostles should be such ignorant guides? Nay what
a disparagement is it to the very Apostles themselves,
that they should choose such ignorant guides, that could
instruct the people no better. For some of these you
speak of, certainly were the immediate successors of the
Apostles themselves. They have been accounted hi∣therto
men, not only of conscience but of learning, know∣ing
and understanding, pious and devout men, in many
of them the gift of doing miracles still remained. I can∣not
with patience speak against this imputation.</P>
<P>But you are as bold with the people, by accusing <HI>them
of sloath and blind obedience, and to be beasts of burthen, be∣cause
they did not examine what they were taught.</HI></P>
<P>Whereas this good people had well learned, that they
should not, they could not be wiser then their teachers;
and they had been newly taught from S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Pauls</HI> own
mouth, that they <HI>were to obey those that had the rule over
them, and submit themselves.</HI> Which was not a blind
but a wise discreet holy and dutifull obedience.</P>
<P>But you it seems will teach the people another lesson,
to wit, to guide their guides. And they are now apt e∣nough
to learne it. For they begin to practise it apace.</P>
<P>But you inferre upon these weak premises. <HI>By this you
may plainly see the danger of our appeale to antiquity for
resolution in coutroversed points of faith, and how small
reliefe we are to expect from thence; For if the discretion
of the chiefest guides of the Church, did in a point so trivi∣all,
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
so inconsiderable, so mainely faile them as not to see the
truth, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>But you build too large a structure upon such a sandy
foundation. For here the discretion of the chiefest
guides of the Church did not faile them, as you imagine:
but they constantly kept their own severall customes in
love and charity, and therefore without Schisme, till
<HI>Victor</HI> would needs take too much upon him, whereas
the whole businesse was afterwards setled in that famous
Councell of <HI>Nice.</HI></P>
<P>So that here is no oversight of any truth, as I con∣ceive,
unlesse, as you intimate before, the truth is, they
should have kept no Easter at all: and then as you say, it
was most unnecessary and most vaine to strive about the
time of keeping it. But such a truth as this, the Christi∣an
world hath not yet embraced, neither doe I know
when it will. So that for ought yet appeares, (unlesse
you bring better reason against them) we may take good
directions from antiquity in the resolution of our mo∣derne
controversies: and we may for all this examine the
question on foot, by the doctrine of those purer times,
and Heroick spirits, although you are pleased to terme
them <HI>poore spirited persons.</HI> Which to mee seemeth a very
strange appellation, was S. <HI>Ambrose</HI> a poore spirited per∣son,
who durst excommunicate that great Emperour
<HI>Theodosius,</HI> and forbid him to enter into the Church?
Was S. <HI>Chrisostome</HI> a poor spirited person, who did
preach against <HI>Eudoxia</HI> the Empresse, and valiantly suffe∣red
banishment for it? Was S. <HI>Athanasius</HI> either, a poor
spirited person who durst stand out even against all the
World, as it is storied of him, <HI>Athanasius against the
world, and the world against Athanasius?</HI> Or were any of
those Fathers poor spirited persons, who did couragi∣ously
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
suffer martyrdome for the testimony of Christ?
Can you name any one author auncient or moderne, that
hath so called or esteemed of them? If not, then it is but
thus with you. <HI>The Fathers are poor spirited persons, be∣cause
I say so, who am animo defaecato.</HI></P>
<P>Neither are you yet constant to your selfe in this as∣sertion,
for although here you call them poor spirited
persons, yet afterwards you doe in effect unsay it, where
you so much approve of what <HI>Socrates</HI> observeth of
them, that they were the great disturbers of the Christi∣an
world. Doe poore spirited persons use to make such
hurly burlies? <HI>Pardon me,</HI> say you, <HI>I know not what temp∣tation
drew this note from me.</HI></P>
<P>And if you would pardon me, I could give a great
guesse at the temptation. I feare it is a temptation of
pride and singularity, thus to trample upon those aunci∣ent
worthies, the better to make way for some kind of
novelty. And I would it were no worse then this, of
not keeping Easter.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="text">
<HEAD>TRACT.</HEAD>
<P>The next <HI>Schisme</HI> which had in it matter of fact, is that of the
<HI>Donatist,</HI> who was perswaded (at least pretended so) that it was
unlawfull to converse or communicate in holy duties with men
stained with any notorious sinne, for howsoever, that <HI>Austen</HI> doe
specifie only the <HI>Thurificati</HI> and <HI>Traditores</HI> and <HI>Libellatici, &amp;c.</HI>
as if he separated only from those, whom he found to be such,
yet by necessary proportion, he must referre to all notorious sin∣ners,
upon this he taught that in all places, where good and bad
were mixt together, there could be no Church by reason of Pol∣lution,
evaporating as it were from sinners, which blasted righ∣teous
persons, who conversed with them, and made all unclean
on this ground, separating himselfe from all that he list to suspect,
he gave out, that the Church was no where to be found but in
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
him, and his Associates, as being the only men among whom
wicked persons found no shelter, and by consequence the only
cleare and unpolluted company, and therefore the only Church.
Against this Saint <HI>Augustine</HI> laid downe this Conclusion, <HI>Vnita∣tem
Ecclesiae per totum Mundum dispersae propter nonnullorum pec∣cata
non esse deserendam,</HI> which is indeed the whole summe of
that Fathers disputation against the <HI>Donatists.</HI> Now in one part
of this Controversy, one thing is very remarkable. The truth
was there, where it was, by meer chance, and might have been
on either side, the reason brought by either party notwithstand∣ing,
for though it were <HI>Defacto false,</HI> that <HI>pars Donati</HI> shut up
in <HI>Africke</HI> was the only Othodox party, yet it might be true, not∣withstanding
any thing Saint <HI>Augustine</HI> brings to confute it; and
on the contrary, though it were <HI>de facto</HI> true, that the part of
Christians dispersed over the whole Earth were Orthodox, yet
it might have been false, notwithstanding any thing Saint <HI>Augu∣stine</HI>
brings to confirme it. For where, or amongst whom, or
how many the Church shall be, or is, is a thing indifferent, it may
be in any number more or lesse, it may be in any Place, Country
or Nation, it may be in all, and for ought I know, it may be
in none, without any prejudice to the definition of a Church, or
the truth of the Gospell, <HI>North</HI> or <HI>South,</HI> many or few, di∣spersed
in many places, or confined to one: None of these doe
either prove or disprove a Church.</P>
<P>Now this <HI>Schisme,</HI> and likewise that former, to a wise man
that well understands the matter in Controversie, may afford
perchance matter of pitty, to see men so strangely distracted up∣on
fancy, but of doubt or trouble what to doe, it can yeeld none;
for though in this <HI>Schisme</HI> the <HI>Donatist</HI> be the <HI>Schismatick,</HI> and
in the former, both parties be equally ingaged in the <HI>Schisme;</HI> yet
you may safely upon your occasions communicate with either,
if so be you slatter neither in their <HI>Schisme:</HI> For why might not
it be lawfull to goe to Church with the <HI>Donatist,</HI> or to cele∣brate
<HI>Easter</HI> with the <HI>Quartodeciman,</HI> if occasion so require?
since neither Nature, nor Religion, nor Reason doth suggest any
thing of moment to the contrary? For in all publique meetings
pretending holinesse, so there be nothing done, but what true
Devotion and piety brooke; why may not I be present in them,
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>
and use communication with them; Nay, what if those to whom
the execution of the publique service is committed, doe some∣thing
either unseemly or suspitious, or peradventure unlawfull?
what if the garments they weare be censured, nay indeed be su∣perstitious?
what if the gesture of adoration be used to the Altars,
as now we have learn'd to speak? what if the Homilist have
preached, or delivered any doctrine of the truth, of the which
we are not well perswaded? a thing which very often falls out:
yet for all this we may not separate, except we be constrained
personally to beare a part in them our selves; The Priests under
<HI>Ely</HI> had so ill demeaned themselves about the daily sacrifice, that
the Scripture tells us, they made them to stink, yet the People
refused not to come to the Tabernacle, nor to bring their Sacri∣fice
to the Priest, for in those <HI>Schismes</HI> which concerne fact, no∣thing
can be a just cause of refusing of Communion, but only to
require the execution of some unlawfull or suspected act; for not
only in reason, but in religion too, that maxime admits of no re∣lease,
<HI>cautissimicuius{que} Praeceptum quod dubitas ne feceris;</HI> long it
was ere the Church fell upō <HI>Schisme,</HI> upō this occasion, though of
late it hath had very many, for until the second Councell of <HI>Nice,</HI>
in which concileable, Superstition and Ignorance did conspire, I
say, untill the Rout did set up Image-worship, there was not any
remarkable <HI>Schisme</HI> upon just occasion of fact, all the rest of
<HI>Schismes</HI> of that kinde were but wantons, this was truly serious;
in this the <HI>Schismaticall</HI> party was the Synod it selfe, and such as
conspired with it; for concerning the use of Images in sacris,</P>
<P>First, it is acknowledged by all that it is a thing unnecessary.</P>
<P>Secondly, it is by most suspected.</P>
<P>Thirdly, it is by many held utterly unlawfull, can then the en∣joyning
of such a thing be ought else but abuse? or can the refu∣sall
of Communion here be thought any other thing then duety?
Here or upon the like occasion to separate, may peradventure
bring personall trouble or danger, (against which it concernes a∣ny
honest man, to have <HI>pectus bene Praeparatum)</HI> further harme it
cannot doe, so that in these cases you cannot be to seek what to
think, or what you have to doe.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="comment">
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>ANIMADVERSION.</HEAD>
<P>Fourthly, you fall foule upon S. <HI>Austin</HI> in particular,
who, I may boldly say, hath deserved as well of the
Christian world as any one man since the Apostles
times. And if this were my opinion alone, I should
suspect it, but I appeale herein to the generall applause
the learned have of him.</P>
<P><HI>The truth was,</HI> say you, <HI>on S. Austins side against the
Donatist, but by meer chance. For the Donatist might
have been the only Orthodoxe party, for any thing</HI> S. Au∣stin <HI>brings to confute it, and the other party might not
have been Orthodoxe, for any thing</HI> S. Austin <HI>brings to
confirme it.</HI></P>
<P>Then which, what could have been spoken more de∣rogatory
to so famous, learned and renowned a Father?
As if his arguments were so slight and silly, both to de∣fend
himselfe and offend his adversary, that they are
not worth the reading or regarding, but are as much, as
if he had said nothing at all. Whereas it is well known
and confessed, that although this good father was re∣nowned
for many things, yet his master peece doth ap∣peare
in his Polemicks, who, to the admiration of the
World hitherto, is accounted to have acutely subtly, &amp;
soundly confuted all those Hereticks and Schismaticks
he wrote against; and therefore deservedly stiled <HI>Mal∣leus
haereticorum, the mauler of the hereticks.</HI></P>
<P>Now he must be esteemed a silly man, and to have
said nothing against them. You should doe well, now
you have thus accused him, to set downe and make it
appeare unto the world, that his arguments both offen∣sive
and defensive against the Donatist, are so slight and
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
weake as you would make us believe. There be some
that will defend him, and maintaine that this Father
hath proved against the Donatist by irrefragable argu∣ments
drawn out of Scripture, that the Church of Christ
neither then was, nor ever shall be, drawn into such a
narrow compasse, as you and they imagine.</P>
<P>I would aske you this question. If S. <HI>Austin</HI> hath gi∣ven
you so little satisfaction against the Donatist, how
doe you know, but that the Donatist may be <HI>defacto</HI> in
the right, and S. <HI>Austin</HI> in the wrong; for it seems by
you, it was but hap hazard, which way it would goe. I
would therefore willingly learne the way you take to
discerne which of these two waies is the right, for it
seems you have learnt nothing by S. <HI>Austin.</HI></P>
<P>But me thinks you goe a strange way to worke to say
the <HI>Church may be in none, without any prejudice to the
definition of the Church or the truth of the Gospell.</HI></P>
<P>I would willingly know how you define a Church,
which shall consist of none, and whether this be not
most derogatory to the truth of the Gospell, that Christ
should have a Church which is in none, that is, as I con∣ceive
it, should have no Church at all. For although it
pleaseth God to remove his Candlestick from one
Country to another, and that his Church should be like
the Moon, sometimes in the full, and sometimes in the
waine; yet that it should be utterly eclipsed, and quite
vanish away, directly crosseth the prophesies of the old
Testament, and the promises of the new.</P>
<P><HI>But you will pitty S. Austin and those Fathers before
him, that were thus distracted upon fancy.</HI></P>
<P>And me thinks the greatest pitty of all is, that some of
<HI>our wise men that so well now understand the matters in
controversy,</HI> had not lived in their times, to have recti∣fied
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>
them, and put these fancies out of their heads. But
I know not, whether it be not the greatest fancy of all,
to think our selves so wise, and them so phantasticall.</P>
<P><HI>But you easily resolve the doubt, and think it lawfull to
goe to Church with the Donatist, or to celebrate Easter
with the Quartodeciman, so you flatter neither in their
Schisme, and there be nothing done but what true devoti∣on
and piety will brooks.</HI></P>
<P>But how can this be? for your joyning with them in
their custome and communion, must needs, if not flatter,
yet much harten and encourage them in their Schisme.
Besides you give a great scandall and offence to the Or∣thodox
party, and make them justly so suspect, that be∣cause
you thus joyne with them in their publique com∣munion,
that you favour, at the least dislike not, their
private opinion. Thus then to scandalize your brethren,
can never stand with true piety and devotion.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="text">
<HEAD>TRACT.</HEAD>
<P>Come we then to consider a little of the second sort of <HI>Schisme,</HI>
arising upon occasion of variety of opinion: It hath been the
common disease of Christians from the beginning, not to content
themselves, with that measure of Faith, which God and Scrip∣tures
have expresly afforded us, but out of a vaine desire to know
more then is revealed, they have attempted to devise things,
of which we have no light, neither from Reason nor Revelati∣on,
neither have they rested here, but upon pretence of Church
authority (which is none) or Tradition (which for the most
part is but fained) they have peremptorily concluded, and con∣fidently
imposed upon other a necessity of entertayning conclu∣sions
of taht nature, &amp; to strengthen themselves have broken out
into divisions and factions, opposing man to man, Synod to Sy∣nod,
till the peace of the Church vanished, without all possibi∣ity
of recall: hence arose those ancient, and many seperations
<PB N="19" REF="11"/>
amongst Christians, occasioned by <HI>Arianisme, Eutychianisme,
Nestorianisme, Photinianisme, Sabellianisme,</HI> and many more
both ancients, and in our owue time, all which indeed are but
names of <HI>Schisme;</HI> howsoever in the common language of the Fa∣thers,
they were called <HI>Heresies,</HI> for <HI>Heresie</HI> is an act of the will,
not of thereason, and is indeed a lye and not a mistake, else how
could that of <HI>Austen</HI> go for true, <HI>Errare possum, Hareticus esse
nolo:</HI> indeed <HI>Manichanisme, Valentinianisme, Macedonianisme,
Mahometisme,</HI> are truly and properly <HI>Herises:</HI> For wee know
that the Authors of them received them not, but invented them
themselves, and so knew what they taught to be a lye: but can
any man avouch that <HI>Arius</HI> and <HI>Nestorius,</HI> and others that taught
erroniously concerning the Trinity, and the person of our SA∣VIOUR,
did maliciously invent what they taught, and not ra∣ther
fall upon it by error and mistake? till that be done, and up∣on
good evidence, we will thinke no worse of all parties than
needs we must, and take these Rents in the Church to be at the
worst but <HI>Schismes,</HI> upon matter of opinion, in which case what
we are to do, is not a point of any great depth of understanding
to discover, if so be distemper and partiality do not intervene: I
do not see that <HI>opinionum varictas &amp; opinantium unitas,</HI> are
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or that men of different opinions in Christian Religion,
may not hold communion in <HI>Sacris,</HI> and both go to one Church,
why may I not go▪ If occasion require, to an <HI>Arian</HI> Church, so
there be no <HI>Arianisme</HI> exprest in their Liturgy, and were Litur∣gies
and publique formes of Service so framed, as that they ad∣mitted
not of particular and private fancies, but contained onely
such things, as in which all Christians do agree; <HI>Schismes</HI> on opi∣nion
were utterly vanished: for consider of all the Liturgies that
are and ever have beene, and remove from them whatsoever is
scandalous to any party, and leave nothing but what all agree
on, and the event shall be, that the publique Service and Honour
of God shall no wayes suffer. Whereas to load our publique
formes, with the private fancies upon which we differ, is the
most soveraigne way to perpetuate <HI>Schisme</HI> unto the worlds end;
Prayer, Confession, Thanksgiving, Reading of Scriptures, Ad∣ministration
of Sacriments, in the plainest and the simplest man∣ner,
were matter enough to furnish out a sufficient Liturgy,
<PB N="20" REF="12"/>
though nothing either of private opinion, or of Church Pomp,
of Garments, or prescribed Gestures, of Imagery, of musike, of
matter concerning the Dead, of many superfluities which creep
into the Church, under the name of Order, and Decency, did in∣terpose
it selfe.</P>
<P>To charge Churches and Liturgies, with things unnecessary
was first the beginning of all superstition, and when scruple of
Conscience began to be made or pretended, there <HI>Schisme</HI> began
to breake in; if the speciall Guides and Fathers of the Church
would be a little sparing of incumbring Churches with superflu∣ities,
or not over-rigid either in reviving obsolete Customes, or
imposing new, there would be farre lesse cause of <HI>Schisme</HI> or <HI>Su∣perstition,</HI>
and all the inconveniance likely to ensue, would be
but this, they should in so doing yeeld a little to the imbecillity
of their Inferiors, a thing which S. <HI>Paul</HI> would never haue re∣fused
to do; meane while wheresoever false or suspected opini∣ons
are made a peice of Church Liturgy, he that seperates is not
the <HI>Schismatique,</HI> for it is alike unlawfull to make profession of
known or suspected falsehood, as to put in practise unlawfull or
suspected actions.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="comment">
<HEAD>ANIMADVERSION.</HEAD>
<P>Fiftly, having trampled upon the Auncients, you
come now to the Church, and levell that also with the
ground. <HI>It hath been,</HI> say you, <HI>the common disease of
Christians from the beginning, not to content themselves
with that measure of faith which God and Scriptures have
expressely afforded us, but out of a vaine desire to know
more then is revealed, they have attempted to devise things
of which we have no light from reason nor revelation.
Neither have they rested here, but upon pretence of Church
authority (which is none) or Tradition (which for the
most part is but fained. &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>I, hath the Church no authority? did not our Saviour
giue power to the Church to punish &amp; excommunicate a
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>
notorious offendor? when he saith, <HI>goe tell the Church,
and if he heare not the Church, let him be to thee a heathen
or a Publican.</HI> And did not his S. <HI>Paul</HI> give great power
to the Church when he calleth <HI>it the Pillar and fortresse
of truth.</HI> It were easy here to enlarge my selfe, and prove
out of the Ancient Fathers did you not reject them, that
they attributed great powre &amp; authority to the Church.
But the Church of England (whose sonne suppose you
are, and therefore cannot so well neglect her autho∣rity)
will tell you,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Artic. 20.</NOTE> that <HI>the Church hath powre to decree
rites or ceremonyes, and authority in controversies of
faith.</HI> But here you would cry up the authority of the
Scriptures, that thereby you might decry the authority
of the Church, whereas these two are not opposite, but
subordinate one to another; I meane the Church to the
Scripture; If therefore you will commend unto us the
authority of Scripture, you must also uphold the autho∣rity
of the Church, which is founded in Scripture, but
if you nullify the authority of the Church, you must al∣so
neglect the authority of the Scripture, which giveth
the Church such power. And let no man think the Ro∣man
Church will here break in upon mee, for by
Church, I meane the <HI>truly auncient Catholick and Aposto∣licke
Church,</HI> from which the Roman Church is farre e∣nough.</P>
<P>And as by Church, so I meane by Tradition, for
where Tradition is fained, none are to esteem of it, but
when it doth appeare unto us to be <HI>truly auncient Catho∣lick
and Apostolick,</HI> it is not a little to be regarded. Here∣upon
<HI>Vincentius</HI> would have us <HI>duplici modo munire fi∣dem,</HI>
to fortify our faith two manner of waies,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Cap. 1. &amp; 2.</NOTE> <HI>primò, di∣vinae
legis authoritate, deinde Ecclesiae Catholicae traditio∣ne,</HI>
first, by the authority of divine law, then by the tra∣dition
<PB N="22" REF="13"/>
of the Catholick Church. Then he putteth that
objection, which you here, and many others are used to
make; <HI>seeing that the canon of Scripture is perfect enough
and more then enough sufficient in it selfe to all things,
what need is there that wee should joyne unto it the autho∣rity
of Ecclesiasticall exposition.</HI> Unto which me thinks
he giveth a very satisfying answere, <HI>Because all doe not
understand the holy Scriptures, by reason of the height
thereof, in one and the same sense: but one interprets it
one way, and another a severall way. So that there be as ma∣ny
minds and meanings about it, almost as there be men.
For</HI> Novatus <HI>expounds it one way,</HI> Donatus <HI>another,</HI>
Arius <HI>another,</HI> Pelagius <HI>another, &amp;c. Therefore it is ve∣ry
needfull, by reason of so great and diverse errors, that the
line of Propheticall and Apostolicall interpretation, be di∣rected
according to the rule of Ecclesiasticall and Catho∣lick
meaning.</HI></P>
<P>So that true and Catholick Tradition, is like unto a
strong wall about the garden of holy Scripture, which
keeps it from the incursion of Hereticks, or if they
chance to get in, it is a soveraine antidote to preserve us
from the poison they suck out of these sweet flowers.</P>
<P>So that take the Church and Tradition in a right
sense, there is much to be attributed to them, but I entend
brevity. Only I cannot omit, how you would make
us believe, that this authority of the Church hath cau∣sed
those seperations which <HI>Arius, Nestorius,</HI> and other
Hereticks have raised, when you say, <HI>hence arose those
auncient and many separations amongst Christians. &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>Whereas indeed it was the authority of the Church
and Catholick Fathers which hath quelled, confuted,
and silenced all those Heresies, and Hereticks which it
seems you have a mind to revive, for you will not have
<PB N="23" REF="13"/>
them called Heresies, but Schismes, <HI>for indeed,</HI> say you,
<HI>they are but names of Schisme, howsoever in the common
language of the Fathers they were called Heresies.</HI></P>
<P>But you must pardon those who thinke it safer and
sounder to follow the common language of the Fathers,
then your own private assertion.</P>
<P>But you have a reason for it. <HI>For Heresie,</HI> say you, <HI>is an
act of the will not of reason,</HI> whereas indeed it is both. For
doth not the hereticke first fasten upon a false opinion,
which is an act of the understanding and corrupted rea∣son,
and this is the materiall part of heresie. And then
doth wilfully and stubbornely▪ being convinced of it,
maintaine the same, which is an act of the will and for∣malizeth
heresie. And in this sense, not in yours, is that
knowne speech of S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>Austine</HI> true, <HI>errare possum, haereti∣cus
esse nolo,</HI> that is, I may erre and so fall into the mate∣riall
part of heresie, by apprehending and iudging that to
be a good doctrine which is false and erroneous, but <HI>hae∣reticus
esse nolo, I will not be an hereticke,</HI> that is, I will
not persist in this opinion, being lawfully convicted and
condemned for it by the Church and governours there∣of.
For then I should be formally and properly an here∣ticke.
For howsoever you slight and nullify the autho∣rity
of the Church, yet in the primitive times when the
Church was at unity, when there was not <HI>altare contra
altare,</HI> it was then esteemed to be of great power and au∣thority,
which authority of that Church hath justly de∣clared
not only the <HI>Manichees, Valentinians</HI> and <HI>Marci∣onites,</HI>
but also the <HI>Arians, Nestorians,</HI> and <HI>Pelagians</HI> to
be hereticks. Howsoever you are willing to distinguish
them, and make these latter scarce <HI>Schismaticks,</HI> for <HI>you
will take these rents in the Church to be at the worst but
Schismes.</HI> Then at the best it seemes they are not so much
as <HI>Schismes.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="24" REF="14"/>
Yet I cannot be perswaded so ill of the former; as to
thinke they knew what they taught, was a lye, and so
went directly against their owne consciences: nor yet so
well of the latter to excuse them with you, from heresie,
for I am yet to learne, that <HI>heresie is nothing els, but to
know that a lye is taught,</HI> such kinde of wickednesse I shall
rather terme open blasphemy then heresie, when men go
against the light of their owne consciences.</P>
<P>Sixtly, you chalke us out a way, wherein we may
safely walke, not only with the <HI>Donatists,</HI> But with the <HI>Arian</HI> and all other hereticks. And that is <HI>to have Litur∣gies
and publique formes of service so framed, as that
they admitted not of particular and private fancyes, but con∣tained
onely such things, as in which all Christians do agree;
and then, Schismes on opinion were vtterly vanished, and
thus, say you, I may go to an Arian Church.</HI></P>
<P>A pretty fancy indeede. But first I thinke you could
not prevaile with the <HI>Arian</HI> party to frame their Creede
so, as might not give offence to the orthodoxe side, for
in all Liturgies they use to have a confession of their
faith.</P>
<P>And secondly, if you could prevaile with them, how
could you perswade all our Churches, to put that
clause out of our Creede. [<HI>I believe in Christ the only
begotten sonne of God, begotten of his father before all
worlds, God of God, light of light, very God of very God,
begotten, not made, being of one substance with the father
by whome all things were made.</HI>] which was a good illust∣ration
of our Creed joyned to it, and made a part of it by
the fathers of the <HI>Nicene</HI> Councell against the <HI>Arians</HI>
then, and will serve as a sufficient bulwarke against our
<HI>Sosinians</HI> now: which Creed hath had the generall
applause of the Christian Churches since, and hath the
<PB N="25" REF="14"/>
honour to be one of the Creeds of the Catholicke
Church.</P>
<P>You must prevaile with them likewise to blot out of
<HI>Athanasius</HI> Creed (which though it were made but by
one man, yet by generall approbation is now also be∣come
the Creed of all our Churches,) I say you must
put out of it, these clauses. [<HI>there is one person of the Fa∣ther,
another of the sonne, another of the Holy Ghost, but the
Godhead of the Father &amp; of the sonne and of the Holy Ghost
is all one, the glory equall, the majesty coeternall, the Father
eternall, the sonne eternall, and the Holy Ghost eternall: the
Father is God, the sonne is God, and the Holy Ghost is God.</HI>]
All which do directly overthrow these heresies. And
do not call these clauses, <HI>particular and private fancies,</HI>
for they are part of the universall and publique faith of
the Church, which all the East and West, all Popish
and Reformed Churches doe unanimously professe and
believe. It is not a time now to add, much lesse to de∣tract,
from our publique Confessions of faith.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="text">
<HEAD>TRACT.</HEAD>
<P>The third thing I named for matter of <HI>Schisme</HI> was <HI>Ambiti∣on,</HI>
I meane <HI>Episcopall Ambition,</HI> shewing it selfe especially in
two heads, one concerning Pluralities of <HI>Bishops</HI> in the same Sea.
Another concerning the superiority of <HI>Bishops</HI> in diverse Seas.
<HI>Aristotle</HI> tels us that necessity causeth but small faults, but A∣varice
and Ambition were the mother of great Crimes; <HI>Episco∣pall
Ambition</HI> hath made this true, for no occasion hath produ∣ced
more frequent, more continuous, more sanguineous
<HI>Schismes,</HI> than this hath done; the Seas of <HI>Alexandria,</HI> of <HI>Con∣stantinople,</HI>
of <HI>Antioch,</HI> and above all of <HI>Rome,</HI> doe abundant∣ly
shew thus much, and all Ecclesiasticall stories witnesse no
lesse, of which the greatest part consists of factionating and tu∣multuating
of great and potent <HI>Bishops.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="26" REF="15"/>
<HI>Socrates</HI> Apologizing for himselfe, that professing to write an
Ecclesiasticall story, he did oft-times interlace the actions of se∣cular
Princes and other Civill businesse, tels us that he did this
to refresh his reader, who otherwise were in danger to be cloyd
by reading so much of the Acts of unquiet and unruly Bishops,
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, in which as a man may say, they made
butter and cheese one of another, for <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, that I may shew
you a cast of my old office and open you a mystery in Gram∣mer,
properly signifies to make butter and cheese, and because
these are not made without much agitation of the milk, hence
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, by a borrowed and translated signification, signifies
to do things with much agitation and tumult.</P>
<P>But that I may a little consider of the two heads, I but now
specified, the first I mentioned was the plurality of <HI>Bishops</HI> in
one Sea. For the generall practise of the Church, since the be∣ginning,
at least since the originall of Episcopacy, as now it is,
was never to admit at once more than one Bishop in one Sea,
and so far in this point have they been carefull to preserve unity,
that they would not have a Bishop in his Sea to have two Cathe∣drall
Churches, which thing lately brought us a book out of
<HI>France De monogamia Episcoporum,</HI> written by occasion of the
Bishop of <HI>La<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gres:</HI> who, I know not upon what fancy, could not
be content with one Cathedrall Church in his Diocesse but
would needs have two, which to the Author of that Work
seeme, to be a kind of Spirituall Polygamy; it fell out amongst
the Ancients very often, sometimes upon occasion of difference
in opinions, sometimes because of those who were interessed in
the choice of Bishops; that two and sometimes more were set
up, and all parties striving to maintaine their owne Bishop,
made themselves severall Churches, severall Congregations,
each refusing to participate with others, &amp; many times proceed∣ing
to mutuall excommunications; that is that which <HI>Cyprian</HI>
cals <HI>Erigere Altare contra Altare,</HI> to this doth he impute the
originall of all Church disorders, and if you read him, you world
thinke he thought no other Church tumult to be <HI>Schisme</HI> but
this. This perchance may plead some excuse, for though in re∣gard
of Religion it selfe, it matters not whether there be one or
more Bishops in one Diocesse, and sometimes two are knowne
<PB N="27" REF="15"/>
to have set at once; for <HI>Epiphanius</HI> reckoning up the Bishops of
<HI>Rome,</HI> makes <HI>Peter</HI> and <HI>Paul</HI> the first: and Saint <HI>Augustin</HI> ac∣knowledgeth
for a time he sate fellow Bishop with his prede∣cessor,
though he excused it, that he did so by being ignorant that
the contrary had been decreed by the Councell of <HI>Nice,</HI> yet it
being a thing very convenient for the peace of the Church to
have it so, neither doth it any whit savour of vice or misde∣meanor,
their punishments sleeps not who unnecessarily and
wantonly goe about to infring it.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="comment">
<HEAD>ANIMADVERSION.</HEAD>
<P>Seventhly, you come to <HI>Episcopall Ambition, then
which you say none hath caused more frequent, more conti∣nuous,
more sanguineous Schismes.</HI></P>
<P>It is very true indeed, we shall read of many uproares
and much bloudshed about the election of some Bish∣ops,
for which you cannot so much accuse the Bishops
as the factious, furious, and unruly multitude, who ea∣gerly
pursue their severall humors, and are violently
carryed into extreames. And therefore for the cure of
this mischiefe, the order and power of Bishops was not
taken away, but the choice of them, you know, was taken
from the giddy multitude and translated unto the nomi∣nation
and election of temporall Princes.</P>
<P>As for your story out of <HI>Socrates,</HI> you should have
done well to have put downe the place, that your reader
might have seene, you have urged it to your owne ad∣vantage.
I shall set it downe plainly as I finde it in his
proeme to his fift booke: where <HI>Socrates</HI> intending to
write an ecclesiasticall history, and yet withall is will∣ing
to mingle amongst it temporall affaires, makes three
apologies for it. First, saith he, that these warlike affaires
might not be forgotten, but come unto posterity, for it
seemes there were few or no historians in his time. The
<PB N="28" REF="16"/>
second excuse is (which you alledge) for variety sake,
least the reader should be cloyed with perusing only
Church affaires, which is no more then if a man writing
a story of a common-wealth, should for variety and de∣light,
intermixe here and there businesses of the Church.
Not that the common-wealth was then more quiet then
the Church, but there were full as many troubles and tu∣mults
in that as in this. Nay which may serve somewhat
to excuse the unquietnesse of the Clergy, it was caused
through the disturbance of the common-wealth. For
that is <HI>Socrates</HI> his thirde and chiefest reason, because by
setting downe the affaires of the temporall estate, we may
knowe from whence these tumults amongst Bishops a∣rose.
For when, saith he, the common-wealth was thus
tossed up and downe with troubles and seditions with fa∣ctions
and divisions: the estate of the Church and chief∣est
Church-men <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>as it were by a certaine
kinde of Sympathy,</HI> could not chuse but be infected with
the same disease.</P>
<P>Besides, suppose some Bishops then were factious
and ambitious, you should consider that this concern∣eth
the persons of Bishops, not their calling, though
I thinke you might have spared both. Now what a vul∣gar
and illogicall way is this, through the sides of any
mans person to wound his very calling. And had our
great writer of Bishops lives been as carefull to lay toge∣ther
all that makes for them, as he hath been industrious
to rake together all that makes against them, he might
have made his volumes swell twise as bigg.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="text">
<HEAD>TRACT.</HEAD>
<P>But that other head of <HI>Episcopall Ambition,</HI> concerning <HI>Supre∣macy
<PB N="29" REF="16"/>
of Bishops</HI> in divers Seas, one clayming <HI>Supremacy</HI> over
another, as it hath been from time to time, a great trespasse a∣gainst
the Churches Peace, so it is now the finall ruine of it. The
<HI>East</HI> &amp; <HI>West</HI> through the fury of the two prime Bishops being irre∣mediably
separated without all hope of Reconcilement. And be∣sides
all this mischiefe, it is founded on a vice contrary to all
Christian humility, without which no man shall see his SAVI∣OUR;
for they do but abuse themselues and others, that would
perswade us, that Bishops by CHRISTS Institution haue any
superiority over other men further then of Reverence, or that
any Bishop is Superior to another further than Positive order a∣greed
upon amongst Christians hath prescribed: for we have be∣leived
him that hath told us that in IESVS CHRIST
there is neither high nor low, and that in giving honour, every
man should be ready to preferre another before himselfe, which
saying cuts of all clayme certainly of superiority, by title of
Christianity, except men thinke that these things were spoken
only to poore and private men. Nature and Religion agree in
this, that neither of them hath an hand in this heraldry of <HI>Secun∣dum
sub &amp; supra,</HI> all this comes from Composition and agree∣ment
of men amongst themselves, wherefore this abuse of
Christianity to make it Lacquey to Ambition, is a vice for which
I have no extraordinary name of Ignominy, and an ordinary I
will not give it, least you should take so transcendent a vice to
be but triviall.</P>
<P>Now concerning <HI>Schisme</HI> arising upon these heads, you can∣not
be for behaviour much to seek, for you may safely communi∣cate
with all parties as occasion shall call you, and the <HI>Schisma∣tiques</HI>
here are all those who are heads of the faction, together
with all those who foment it: for private and indifferent persons,
they may be spectators of these contentions as securely in regard
of any perill of Conscience, (for of danger in purse or person, I
keepe no account) as at a Cock fight where serpents fight, who
cares who hath the better? the best wish is that both may perish
in the fight.</P>
<P>And for conventicles, of the nature of which you desire to be
informed, thus much in generall evidently appeares, that all
meetings upon an unnecessary seperation are to be so stiled, so
<PB N="30" REF="17"/>
that in sense a Conventicle is nothing else but a Congregation of
<HI>Schismatiques,</HI> yet Time hath taken leave sometimes to fix this
name upon good and honest meetings, and that perchance not
altogether without good reason, for with publique religious
meetings thus it fares. First, it hath been at all times confessed
necessary, that God requires not only inward and private devoti∣on,
when men either in their hearts and Closets or within their
privaet walls, pray, prayse, confesse and acknowledg; but he fur∣ther
requires all those things to be done in publique, by troupes
and shoales of men, and from hence have proceeded publique
Temples, Altars, formes of Service, appoynted times, and the
like, which are required for open Assemblies, yet whilst men
are truely pious, all meetings of men for mutuall help of piety &amp;
devotion wheresoever and by whomsoever celebrated, were
permitted without exception.</P>
<P>But when it was espyed that ill affected persons abused pri∣vate
meetings, whether Religious or Civill to evill ends; Re∣ligiousnesse
to crosse Impiety, as appeares in the Ethnick Elusi∣nia,
and Bacchanalia, and Christian meetings under the Pagan
Princes, when for feare they durst not come together in open
view, were charged with foule imputations, as by the report of
Christians themselves plainely appeares, and Civill meetings
many times, under pretence of friendly and neighbourly visites,
sheltred treasonable attempts against Princes and Common-weales,</P>
<P>Hence both Church and State joyned, and joyntly gave order
for Formes, Times, Places of Publique meetings, whether for
Religious or Civill ends, and all other meetings whatsoever, be∣sides
those of which both time and Place, are limited, they
censured for Routs and Riots, and unlawfull Assemblies in the
State, and in the Church, for Conventicles.</P>
<P>So that it is not lawfull, no not for prayer, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>earing, for Con∣ference,
for any other Religious office whatsoever, for people
to Assemble otherwise, then by publique order is allowed, nei∣ther
may wee complaine of this in times of incorruption, for
why should men desire to do that suspitiously in private which
warrantably may be performed in publique.</P>
<P>But in times of manifest Corruptions and persecutions,
<PB N="31" REF="17"/>
wherein Religious Assembling is dangerous, private meetings
howsoever, besides publique order, are not only lawfull, but
they are of necessity and duty, else how shall we excuse Mee∣tings
of Christians for publique Service, in time of danger and
persecutions, and of our selues in Queene <HI>Maries</HI> dayes? and
how will those of the Romane Church amongst us, put off the im∣putation
of Conventicling, who are knowne amongst us private∣ly
to assemble for Religious exercise against all established or∣der,
both in State and Church? For indeed all pious Assemblies
in times of persecution and corruption howsoever practised, are
indeed or rather alone the lawfull Congregations, and Publique
Assemblies though according to forme of Law, are indeed no∣thing
else but Riots and Conventicles, if they be stayned with
corruption and superstition.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="comment">
<HEAD>ANIMADVERSION.</HEAD>
<P>Eightly and lastly, you take away all superiority from
Bishop's when you say, <HI>they doe but abuse themselves and
others, that would perswade us, that Bishops by Christs insti∣tution
have any superiority over other men, further then
of reverence.</HI></P>
<P>Where (although you intended onely to speake a∣gainst
the superiority of one Bishop over another) yet
you seeme to take away, not only all power of one
Bishop over another, but of a Bishop over a Presbyter,
yea of a Bishop over any other private man. I cannot here
(intending brevity) enter upō the dispute about the power
of one Bishop ouer another, or of the power of a Bishop
over a Presbyter. The former of which is no doubt con∣firmed
by a long continued Ecclesiasticall power, the
latter by an Apostolicall. But that a Bishop should not
have any superiority over an ordinary lay-man, seemes
strange to mee. Certainely our Saviour intended some
power and authority unto <HI>Peter</HI> and the rest of the <HI>A∣postles,</HI>
<PB N="32" REF="18"/>
when he gave them the keyes and wisht them to
open and shut, to binde and loose, whose successors Bi∣shops
are, and though some make question whether they
succeede them as Bishops, yet none doubt but they suc∣ceede
them as Pastors of the Church, and thus have they
power over lay-men. S. <HI>Paul</HI> wills Timothy <HI>to com∣mand
and teach,</HI> 1. Tim. 4. 11. and in another place will∣eth
others <HI>to obey those who had the oversight of them,</HI>
Heb. 13. 17.</P>
<P>Now where there is commanding on the one side and
obeying on the other, there must needs be superiority.</P>
<P>But I could not have imagined this had been your
meaning, but for your proofes which followe. <HI>For we
have believed him that hath told us, that in Christ Iesus
there is neither high nor low, and that in giving honour e∣very
man should be ready to preferre another before him∣selfe,
which saying cuts of all claime certainly of superiority,
by title of Christianity, except men thinke that these things
were spoken only to poore and private men.</HI></P>
<P>Where, you consider not, that you run into an Ana∣baptisticall
humor, and take away all superiority in the
common-wealth, as well as in the Church, and entrench
upon the Scepter of the King as well as upon the Miter
of the Bishop. But your proofes are easily satisfied. For
the first, though we finde not those very words in Scrip∣ture,
yet I suppose you aime at that place wherein it is
said, <HI>Wee are all one in Christ Iesus,</HI> Gal. 3. 28. where
the true meaning of the place is, that as wee are Christi∣ans
we are all one, that is, wee have all equally, and alike
beene partakers of Christ by baptisme, as he saith, <HI>vers.
27. as many of you as have beene baptized into Christ, have
put on Christ.</HI> So that as members of Christ we are all
one, &amp; all make but one body of Christ. Yet as amongst
<PB N="33" REF="18"/>
the naturall members of our bodies, so amongst the
mysticall members of Christ, though they be all one as
members, being compared with the head: yet being
compared one with another, S. <HI>Paul</HI> tels us, there are
<HI>more honourable and lesse honourable members,</HI> 1. Cor. 12.
23.</P>
<P>Your other place, that we should in giving honour
preferre one another, teacheth humility, but taketh not a∣way
superiority.</P>
<P><HI>But you go on and tell us, that nature and religion
agree in this, that neither of them hath an hand in this
heraldry of Secundum sub &amp; supra:</HI> whereas in it
they both joyne hand in hand. Nature acknowledgeth
this heraldry, that shee may avoyd ataxie and confusi∣on:
And religion also, for did not our Lord and Master
acknowledge a <HI>Caesar,</HI> and commanded us to give unto
him that which belonged unto him, to wit, obedience &amp;
subjection. And doth not his Apostle S. <HI>Paul</HI> command
that <HI>every soule should be subject to the higher power.
Rom.</HI> 13. 1. where you see this heraldry of <HI>sub &amp; supra,</HI>
is put downe in expresse tearmes: and pray let us observe
the Apostles reason why wee should thus be subject to
the higher powers, for, saith he, <HI>there is no power but of
God, &amp; the powers that be are ordained of God.</HI> How heare I
then, <HI>that all this comes from composition and agreement
of men amongst themselves.</HI></P>
<P>But I spare to prosecute this doctrine any further, least
I should discover in it a very transcendent crime.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

