<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Dr. Hammond's brief resolution of that grand case of conscience (necessary for these times) concerning the allegiance due to a prince ejected by force out of his kingdoms; and how far the subjects may comply with a present usurped power.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Brief resolution of that grand case of conscience.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Hammond, Henry, 1605-1660.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A45399</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H517</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R218875</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99830429</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99830429</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">34880</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A45399)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34880)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2091:13)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Dr. Hammond's brief resolution of that grand case of conscience (necessary for these times) concerning the allegiance due to a prince ejected by force out of his kingdoms; and how far the subjects may comply with a present usurped power.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Brief resolution of that grand case of conscience.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Hammond, Henry, 1605-1660.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>4 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1689?]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Caption title.</NOTE><NOTE>Place and date of publication from Wing.</NOTE><NOTE>Attributed by Wing to Henry Hammond, however the text apparently refers to King James II and King William III, while Henry Hammond, D.D., died in 1660.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the John Rylands University Library, Manchester University, Manchester, England.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Allegiance --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1680-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A45399">
<STC T="W">H517</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99830429</BIBNO>
<VID>34880</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="question and answer">
<PB N="1" REF="1" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>Dr. <HI>Hammond</HI>'s brief Resolution of that Grand Case of Conscience, (necessary for these Times) concerning the Allegiance due to a Prince ejected by Force out of his Kingdoms; and how far the Subjects may comply with a pre∣sent Usurped Power.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="question">
<HEAD>Question.</HEAD>
<P><HI>DOth not Victory give a Right to the Conquercur?</HI></P>
<P><HI>And doth it not thence follow, that he which is ejected out of his Kingdom, by Force of a prevailing Party, hath thereby lost his Right of</HI> Allegiance <HI>from his former Subjects?</HI></P>
<P><HI>And is not then that Right devolved on the</HI> Conquerour, <HI>by the force of these words of</HI> God, <HI>when he saith, Dan. 4. 17. and 25. 32. That</HI> he ru∣leth in the Kingdoms of Men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will, and setteth up over it the basest of Men? <HI>And of</HI> Ecclus. 10. 8. be∣cause of Unrighteousness the Kingdom is translated from one People to another?</P>
<P><HI>And when he doth so, are not all Members of such a Kingdom obliged (as the</HI> Israelites <HI>in their Deportation to</HI> Babylon) <HI>to yield Obedience to the</HI> Con∣querour?</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="answer">
<HEAD>Answer.</HEAD>
<P>This Objection consists of divers Branches, and I shall answer it by degr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</P>
<P N="1">1. That all Victory doth not give a Right to the <HI>Conquerour,</HI> but onely when the War being founded on a just Cause, that just Cause hath <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> with Victory. And when that is, depends wholly on the truth of that Quetion, concerning the Lawfulness of any War.</P>
<P>Now <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> there can never be just War on the <HI>Subjects</HI> part against their <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> they want the Warrart of Supr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me Authori∣ty, without which (though the Cause should be never so just, and the
<PB N="2" REF="2"/>
End never so good,) all the Blood that is shed, is no better than Mur∣ther: Therefore though the <HI>Subjects</HI> in such a War should prevail against their <HI>Sovereign,</HI> yet neither is he hereby divested of his just Right, nor they invested therewith, because the War was wholly un∣just on their part, for want of Authority.</P>
<P N="2">2. Therefore if that Party whose Cause is Unjust, shall yet prevail, and prove successfull, then in answer to the second Branch, I say, that there is no Right acquired by this: For, 'tis a mistake to think that this is the meaning of <HI>Jus Victoriae, the Right of Victory,</HI> which the <HI>Civil Law∣yers</HI> speak of, as if <HI>God</HI> had by this <HI>lottery</HI> testified his Judgment of the Right, and pronounced that Just now, which was Unjust before; or that the present Force is always to be looked on as the <HI>Higher Powers,</HI> and allowed the Obedience required by the <HI>Apostle,</HI> as due to them, which is the mistaking of <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Power,</HI> for <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Authority,</HI> and agrees with that speech of the <HI>Atheists, Wis. 2. Our strength is the Law of Justice, and that which is feeble is found to be nothing worth.</HI> And we know 'tis Gods ordinary dispensation now under the <HI>Gospel</HI> to permit Violence to oppress the Godly, which sure is no Argument that those prosperous Ungodly, have the sole Right to the Possessions of the World, or that the opprest Godly Man, shall no longer be thought to be op∣prest, when the prosperous Oppressour, is arrived at the height of his oppression.</P>
<P N="3">3. The Question then being removed from the Title of <HI>Force,</HI> (which being itself unjust, cannot confer Right on any,) It must next be con∣sider'd, what <HI>Dedition</HI> (that is, <HI>yielding or resigning up of one's Right)</HI> can doe. That will be of two sorts; either of the <HI>Prince,</HI> or the <HI>People;</HI> and again, either <HI>Voluntary</HI> or <HI>Involuntary.</HI></P>
<P>A <HI>Voluntary Dedition,</HI> or <HI>yielding up,</HI> of the rightfull Possessor, if he be a private Man, transfers a Right: But a <HI>Prince,</HI> being a publick Person, and having an obligation of Protection to his Subjects, cannot without some breach of that Obligation, abdicate his <HI>Kingdom,</HI> nor consequently voluntarily yield up his Power; or if he do, he cannot transfer the Right to any, (save to the lawful Heir or Successor,) with∣out the tacit or express Consent of the People also.</P>
<P>But in case they consent also, then will his Right <HI>(in Kingdoms Elec∣tive)</HI> be transferred by the joint yielding of the King and his Subjects. As for Kingdoms hereditary, the Subjects Consent is not necessary; but the King's yielding up of his Right alone, is sufficient to transfer the Right to the next Heir. Neither can the joint Act both of King
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
and People, transfer this Right, from the next Heir, to any other. The King's yielding is an Absolution of the Subjects from the Allegi∣ance formerly due to him by them, and so makes it lawfull for them to yield the same to another; and when 'tis thus free and lawfull to them, the Intervention of their own Act also becomes Obligation on them to submit to that Person so yielded to. And when this is done (in <HI>Kingdoms Elective)</HI> and withall when no Heir is left to make Claim, or the Claim is relinquish'd by the right Heir, <HI>(in Kingdoms hereditary,)</HI> then is the Kingdom removed, (and given by God, who now rules not immediately among us, as he did in the time of the <HI>Theocracy</HI> among the <HI>Jews,</HI> but is then said to remove a Kingdom, when his Providence so disposes, that by the Laws, and Right among Men, it is removed,) to another.</P>
<P>But till this be done, <HI>i. e.</HI> till <HI>He,</HI> or <HI>They,</HI> in whom the Right both of <HI>present Possession,</HI> and <HI>future Claim by Inheritance,</HI> is truly vested, do voluntarily yield up that Right, and when that is done, till they which by their yielding, are freed from their former Bands, do now by their own Act enter, into new, what Force soever there be, and how suc∣cessfull soever the Force be, there is not thereby any such Victory com∣pleated, as shall be able to confer Right on the Victor, nor remove it from him that hath, and still protests his <HI>Right,</HI> though as yet he be not strong enough to vindicate it.</P>
<P N="4">4. But then in the next place, if there be a Dedition, or yielding up by the King, and that Dedition involuntary; that is, such as no∣thing but the present Success of the Force hath inclined him to, then certainly doth it not so divest him of his <HI>Right,</HI> as that it shall be un∣lawfull for him when he can, to make Claim, and recover it again. As he that by a violent Invader is made to swear to pay such a Summ of Money, it is acknowledged lawfull for him to implead that Thief, and recover from him, what in performance of that involuntary Oath he hath paid him.</P>
<P>In this case the difficulty is, What Condition those <HI>Subjects</HI> are lest in for that time, betwixt the <HI>involuntary Dedition</HI> of the <HI>King,</HI> and his <HI>re∣newing</HI> of his <HI>Claim;</HI> and the Solution must be, That a Proportion be observed between the Act of the King, and the Subjects consequent Act: The Act of the King is but a <HI>present Dedition,</HI> and doth not ob∣lige him never to make any farther Claim again; and consequently this gives not any such Absolution to the <HI>Subjects,</HI> as that they may doe any thing which shall prejudice that After-Claim, or blemish his <HI>Roy∣alty,</HI>
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
such as are taking new Oaths of <HI>Allegiance, Abjurations</HI> of him and his Issue, <HI>Engagements</HI> to the <HI>Usurped Power,</HI> &amp;c. All that it can doe, is to make it free for them to submit to such other things, of an infe∣riour nature, (which includes not any such blemishment of <HI>Rights</HI> of the lawfull Prince,) provided that they acknowledge not the lawfulness of the present usurped Power, nor act as Ministers or Instruments there∣of. This is the utmost that seems possible to determine in this matter.</P>
<P N="5">5. As for that Power which <HI>Tract of Time</HI> may be thought to have in this business, that is not considerable, where the Claim is continued, (for that argues the Dedition involuntary,) and much less, when there is no Dedition at all; for there 'twas before supposed, that Force can∣not conser Right.</P>
<P N="6">6. And if by this stating of the Case it follow, that the Lot of the faithfull Subjects must be very unhappy at this time, and that great Disorder must necessarily continue in such a broken Kingdom, as long as the Contention between the violent <HI>Usurper</HI> and the just <HI>Owner</HI> thus remains undecided. I answer: That this is oft the Lot of the most pious Men under the Gospel, <HI>who have their good things here mixt with Tribulations,</HI> and must content themselves in the solaces of a good Con∣cience, in performing those Duties which cost them dearest, and ex∣pect their full payment of joys without hardships, to be paid them in another World.</P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="3"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

