<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached at Mercers-Chappel, on the 13th of January, 1688/9 by Timothy lord bishop of Oxford.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Hall, Timothy, 1637?-1690.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A45344</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H444</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R42065</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">23361298</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 23361298</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">109548</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A45344)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109548)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1701:29)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A sermon preached at Mercers-Chappel, on the 13th of January, 1688/9 by Timothy lord bishop of Oxford.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Hall, Timothy, 1637?-1690.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 43 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Tho. Cockerill ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>MDCLXXXIX [1689]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Bible. --  O.T. --  Leviticus XIX, 17 --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2008-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Pas</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Pas</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A45344">
<STC T="W">H444</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">23361298</BIBNO>
<VID>109548</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A SERMON PREACHED at Mercers-Chappel, On the 13<HI>th</HI> of JANUARY, 1688/9.</P>
<P>BY TIMOTHY <HI>Lord Bishop of <HI>OXFORD.</HI></HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI> Printed for <HI>Tho. Cockerill,</HI> at the <HI>Three Legs</HI> in the <HI>Poultry,</HI> over-against <HI>Stocks-Market.</HI> MDCLXXXIX.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><BIBL><HI>LEVITICUS XIX. 17.</HI></BIBL>
<P>Thou shalt not hate thy brother in thine heart; thou shalt in any wise rebuke thy neighbour, and not suffer sin upon him.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>THAT we love the Brotherhood, and be kindly affectioned to one another, is the joint and concurrent Language both of Law and Gospel; It is one of those com∣mon Principles which are naturally en∣graven on the tables of the hearts of all men. The ways and methods of discharging our duty, and ex∣pressing our good will to Mankind, are various and dif∣ferent, they run in several channels; one is mentioned in my Text, <HI>viz.</HI> by fraternal correption; a necessary, but a much neglected Duty. We are very prone and forward to reproach our Brethren for their infirmities, and to make a mock at their sins; instead of going back, and throwing a Mantle over them, to hide and cover their nakedness; we rather draw the Curtain open, and with a secret titillation and pleasure expose them to the observation and contempt of the most scornful <HI>Michal:</HI> Instead of burying, and Christianly interring in silence, some of their slips and failures, men rather rake in the Grave, and tear up the Earth to give them an inglorious resurrection.</P>
<P>When we should privately address to our Brother with all imaginable Meekness, Pity, and Sobriety, to restore and recover him after some irregular step, or
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
unwary fall, men rather publickly proclaim and di∣vulge on the House-top their Neigbours failing; and set it in such a light where it may most eminently be seen.</P>
<P>With what bitter taunts and cruel mockings, with what slanderous aspersions and defamations do men prosecute one another? Yea, to that height of wick∣edness have some advanced in these low-running dregs of time, that instead of being grieved that their Bro∣ther has done amiss, they could be glad if he had done much worse. My Friends, is not this a great fault? have we thus learned either of <HI>Moses,</HI> or Christ? This way of treating thy Brother will appear to be collate∣ral Blasphemy, and virtual Murther: Let me shew you a more excellent way, by learning your Duty to him in the words of my Text:</P>
<P>Which Duty is expressed,</P>
<P N="1">1. Negatively, <HI>Thou shalt not hate thy brother in thine heart.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. Affirmatively, <HI>Thou shalt in any wise rebuke thy neighbour.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. With an Argument and Motive persuading us to it; <HI>And not suffer sin upon him.</HI></P>
<P>I shall not wear out my little time in accurate and Logical Analysing of the words, but shall consider them as an entire Doctrinal Proposition.</P>
<P N="1">1. Neg. <HI>Thou shalt not hate thy brother in thine heart.</HI></P>
<P>A <HI>Meiosis:</HI> Thou shalt heartily love him, and do all good Offices to him, relating both to his Soul and Body.</P>
<P>This is to resemble God, who is always doing of good, and showring down his Blessings and Mercies on our Heads; nay, in this work of Brotherly Reprehension we resemble our Heavenly Father, who is said to <HI>rebuke and reprove whomsoever he Loves,</HI> Rev. 3.19.
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
And if thou makest not Conscience thus to Love and affect him, thou art guilty of his Blood, and wilt be esteem'd, in God's account, his Murtherer; for he that <HI>hates his Brother</HI> is so, 1 <HI>John</HI> 3.15. And the Con∣nexion of the Text to the former Verse, gives us full proof of it. Verse 16. <HI>Thou shalt not stand against the blood of thy neighbour;</HI> and this is one way of doing of it, by omitting rebuke. Well then, love thy Brother, get admission into his heart and bowels; not by the point of a Baionet, or the force of a Bullet, that is a very strange demonstration of our affection to him (which by some has been practised); but get into him by mild and soft counsels, by wholesom advice.</P>
<P N="2">2<HI>dly, Thou shalt in any wise rebuke thy neighbour.</HI></P>
<P>Fail not at your peril; here's a plain injunction, no Man exempted, no corner to creep out at. It is not left to your will and pleasure; no Pleas and Excuses will serve your turn to justify your omission. Necessity is laid on thee, <HI>Thou</HI> shalt <HI>in any wise</HI> do it: <HI>Thou</HI> shalt do it, Thou thy self, not by thy Deputy or Substitute. Reproof is like the Peace-offering made by Fire, thine own hand must bring it, <HI>Lev.</HI> 1.17.</P>
<P>Rebuke thy <HI>Neighbour.</HI></P>
<P>Who is this Neighbour? It was a Question pro∣pounded to Christ himself, <HI>Luke</HI> 10.29. The Solution may be gathered out of Christ's Answer.</P>
<P N="1">1. In the General. Every Man to whom I may be helpful. Our Lord proves a Stranger may be a Neigh∣bour, <HI>Luke</HI> 10.36.</P>
<P>All people that have the face of Man are called our flesh, <HI>Isa.</HI> 58. And our blood, <HI>Acts</HI> 17.26. <HI>One blood;</HI> Cousins at a remoter distance. Any Man is our Neigh∣bour, in regard of the nearness of our first Original;
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
nay, not only a <HI>Stranger,</HI> but an <HI>Enemy</HI> may thus be our Neighbour.</P>
<P>'Tis true indeed, that the Precept of <HI>Moses,</HI> con∣cerning the kind dealing of the <HI>Jews</HI> with other men, extended not universally to all,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Dr.</HI> Ham∣mond.</NOTE> but peculiarly to their Country-men or Fellow-<HI>Jews;</HI> as for Aliens and Enemies they were not bound to be kind to them; nay, against some, <HI>viz. the Seven Nations,</HI> they were commanded to proceed in an hostile manner. <HI>Matt.</HI> 5.43. But our Saviour teacheth us to extend our kindness as the Blessings of Heaven, even to enemies and injurious provokers: In the same manner and measure as they do ill to you, do ye good to them, blessing, obliging, admonishing, reproving, praying for them, and making them no other returns for all their virulencies, and malicious behaviour toward you, but those of kind∣ness and love, that so you may approve your selves to be the Servants and Children of the Most high God, and your Heavenly Father.</P>
<P N="2">2<HI>dly,</HI> There are more especially Neighbours, who dwell near us, with whom we frequently converse, and have repeated opportunities of shewing our love in this kind to them. There are also,</P>
<P N="3">3<HI>dly,</HI> Spiritual Neighbours, begotten by the same spirit, to the same hopes; these are to have a special preferment in our affections: They have the same God to their Father, the same Church for their Mother, the same House for their dwelling, and the same Inheritance for their portion.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>And not suffer sin upon him.</HI></P>
<P>There are various Readings of these words; some thus, <HI>Do not burthen thy self with sin for him,</HI> Non susci∣pies propter illum peccatum, <HI>i. e.</HI> Poenam peccati.
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
Take heed lest by thy silence thou bringest the guilt of his sin upon thee.</P>
<P>Through the silence of one, we often suffer two to dye, our selves and our erring brother. Sure I am, he that said, <HI>If thy brother repent, forgive him,</HI> said also before that, <HI>If thy brother offend, admonish him:</HI> And it is as great a sin, not to reprove our brother when he hath trans∣gressed, as not to forgive him, when he hath repented. If we suffer sin upon him, we our selves may suffer for his sin. We neglect to do good, and so great evil comes of it.</P>
<P>But the most general and proper reading of the words is, as in our ordinary Translation, Thou shalt not connive at him, and thereo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> embolden him to continue in his sin, augmenting the heap and number of his Transgressions, but shalt put a stop to him by seasonable and timely Re∣prehension. Let no man tell me this is meer Morality, and prejudice himself against the benefit he should reap. As God in his Law, so Christ in his Gospel doth peremptorily exact and call for our compliance with this Precept in several places: <HI>If thy brother shall trespass against thee, go and tell him his fault,</HI> Mat. 18.15. <HI>Warn them that are unruly,</HI> 1 Thes. 5.14. They are said to be full of Good∣ness, who have <HI>the ability to admonish one another, Rom.</HI> 15.14. Ye count him as an enemy, whom you will not admonish as a <HI>brother.</HI> 2 <HI>Thes.</HI> 3.15. <HI>Reprove the unfruitful works of darkness, Eph.</HI> 5.11. It was a Law in <HI>Israel, That a man should not see his Brothers Ox or Ass fall down by the way, and hide himself from them. Doth God take care for Oxen? nay, for us are these things written.</HI> But alas! we are fallen into those latter days spoken of by our Blessed Saviour, wherein <HI>iniquity should increase, and the love of many wax cold.</HI>
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
What a sinful bashfulness doth attend us, sneaking shame∣fully from our work and duty of Reproof, when an hellish impudence is in some profligate Wretches, that with open face, and brazen brow daily make breaches on God's Royal Law! How quietly and unconcerned∣ly can we see some violent sinners upon a full career in the broad way of Destruction, and never attempt to stop them, or throw in a bar or block to abate the swiftness of their feet, tho it be to the shedding of their own blood? Is this consistent with the Love of God? with the love of thy brother's invaluable soul? or the happiness and security of thine own?</P>
<P>Having by this short Paraphrase taken off what of mist and darkness might surround the Words, I should descend to an Enquiry into several Particulars, each of which would require more time to discourse of, than usually is allotted to Exercises of this nature; yet I shall not totally omit them.</P>
<P>As 1. I should state the nature of this Duty, and shew you wherein it doth consist.</P>
<P N="2">2. On whom this Duty is most principally incum∣bent.</P>
<P N="3">3. I shall demonstrate the great Necessity and Reaso∣nableness of it.</P>
<P N="4">4. I shall lay down some Rules and Directions how to manage it successfully.</P>
<P N="5">5. I shall, lastly, Apply it.</P>
<P>In short, for the First Particular, I shall only take no∣tice of Three Words in the Scripture, which suffici∣ently express the nature of Reprehension.</P>
<P N="1"><PB N="7" REF="5"/>1. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. A striking and beating of one. It de∣notes the vehemency and earnestness of Reproof.</P>
<P>The Gravity of some mens Persons, and the Emi∣nency of their Station, do exempt them from blows of this nature; you may read the <HI>Supersedeas</HI> which some men have, 1 Tim. 5.1. <HI>Rebuke not an Elder, but intreat him as a father;</HI> have respect to his Office, and deal not rigidly with him.</P>
<P N="2">2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, a more mild and gentle kind of increpa∣tion, yet join'd with some Acrimony, and tartness of Speech, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 2.6. Thus <HI>Peter</HI> rebuked Christ, <HI>Mark</HI> 8.32.</P>
<P N="3">3. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, a bare minding and remembring, a put∣ting of the Mind in order by Advertisement and Ad∣monition. This is the most fair and favourable course, the most likely to prove successful, that which primarily is to be used, the other only in extremities.</P>
<P>The Schoolmen give many definitions of it, and the Ancient Fathers abound with variety of Illustrations, telling us, that great is the Affinity between Soul and Body, both as to their Diseases and Remedies: That which Physick is to the Body, Reprehension is to the Soul, and the same rule and method must be observed in the application of the means of Cure. They reckon up three Parts of Physick, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, by Diet, Medicines, and Chyrurgery, all which by way of Analogy and Proportion, are to be used in the Cure of Spiritual Distempers. <HI>Clemens Alexandrinus</HI> com∣pares them together.</P>
<P N="1">1. <HI>Admonition</HI> (he says) is the <HI>Diet</HI> of the Soul, forbidding that which is simply hurtful, or contrary to the disposition of the Patient, and affording strong and wholesome nourishment.</P>
<P N="2"><PB N="8" REF="6"/>2. <HI>Reproof</HI> is a <HI>Medicinal</HI> Potion, that hath always attending of it a tang of bitterness, which purgeth out the Morbifick Matter, and all peccant Humors and Corruptions of the Soul, and is a great Restorative.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>Rebuke,</HI> if sharp and keen, is the spiritual <HI>Chyrurge∣ry,</HI> which sometimes is to be used cuttingly, with a sharp Point and Edge. <HI>Intemperans aeger crudelem facit Medicum.</HI> Salt upon some occasions must be rubb'd and chaf'd into some sores and wounds.</P>
<P>In short, Brotherly correption consists in giving our Brethren necessary instructions in matters they are ig∣norant of; in letting them have timely notice of their sinful Affections, and Inclinations; and in a total break∣ing off our intimacy of conversation, and society with them, if they prove stubborn and incorrigible, stopping their ears against all wise Charms.</P>
<P>I proceed now to the</P>
<P N="2">II. Particular, To shew <HI>who are the Persons mostly concerned in the discharge of this Duty.</HI></P>
<P>The better to understand this, you must know that Divines generally distinguish Reproof into <HI>Ministerial,</HI> and by way of Authority; and <HI>Fraternal,</HI> by way of Charity.</P>
<P N="1">1. <HI>Ministers admonish by way of Office.</HI> The truth is, the work of Reproof belongs in some sort to all men who have the use of Reason, because it is a natural Precept, and a work of Mercy, a general Of∣fice due from one neighbour to another. Hence Infi∣dels may reprove Believers; so <HI>Abimelech</HI> reproved <HI>Sa∣rah,</HI> Gen. 20.15. Thus Inferiors may reprove their Superiors, provided it be done with Modesty and Re∣verence. But principally this Duty is incumbent on three sorts of Persons.</P>
<P N="1"><PB N="9" REF="6"/>1. On such who in regard of <HI>Office</HI> are obliged to take the charge and care of others, as Ministers and Dispensers of the Divine Oracles are.</P>
<P N="2">2. On such who are engaged by bonds of <HI>Nature,</HI> and their Relative Stations and Capacities; thus Pa∣tents and Masters stand more especially concerned.</P>
<P N="3">3. On such who are <HI>qualified and fitted with Parts and Gifts</HI> to perform this Office with success.</P>
<P N="1">1. It is a principal part of our Ministry to rebuke. Among Christ's Disciples one was stiled a <HI>Son of Thunder;</HI> and what was said of St. <HI>Basil,</HI> ought to be the Cha∣racter of every faithful Steward in God's House, That he thunder'd in his Doctrine, and lighten'd in his Life. If we look through all the Old Testament, you will find that most of the Prophets Messages were severe Rebukes and Threatnings. The <HI>Jews</HI> call the Book of <HI>Deuteronomy,</HI> the <HI>Book of Objurgations;</HI> and that Section which beginneth <HI>Deut.</HI> 28.15. they call the <HI>Section of Objurgations.</HI> The necessity of this Duty is such to us, that God will require the blood of the People at the hands of their Pastor, if he reprove not. The Shepherd was bound to make good that which was stollen, as <HI>Jacob</HI> did to <HI>Laban, Cry aloud, spare not,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 31.19. Isa. 58.1.</NOTE> <HI>lift up thy voice like a trumpet, and shew my people their Transgressi∣on, and the house of Jacob their sins.</HI> 'Tis the Spiritual Father's charge to his own Son in the Faith, <HI>That he re∣buke them that sin, before all, that others may fear:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Tim. 5.20.</NOTE> And this he must do without Partiality, not fearing the Emi∣nency, nor being deterr'd at the Greatness or any bold and open Transgressor.</P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="7"/>As this is required of Ministers chiefly, so it is ex∣pected and demanded of <HI>Parents and Masters;</HI> God hath made them Guardians of their Children and Servants. It is an idle conceit to think that we only are intrusted with the Cure of Souls; you will find it no excuse for your negligence and omission in the great day of giving up your Accounts at God's Tribunal; you are obliged to be keepers of their Souls, as well as we; nay, every man, in this sense, ought to be his Brother's Keeper. As God hath set Conscience to watch over the inward man, so for the conversation he hath set Christians to watch over one another. Suffer me before I proceed any further, to improve this.</P>
<P N="1">1. It should teach all Ministers to be faithful in their places, and to take care that no man muzzle up their mouths.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 2.2.</NOTE> See how the Holy Ghost commends the An∣gel of the Church of <HI>Ephesus; I know thy works, and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canst not bear them which are evil.</HI> Wicked men are sometimes intolerable, not to be endured or bore with. It is no breach of Pa∣tience to be impatient against sin and sinners.</P>
<P>It is said of <HI>Suetonius,</HI> that he took the same liberty in writing the Emperors lives, that they took in lead∣ing them. Wicked men take liberty to licentiousness in committing sin, let us take as great a liberty in repro∣ving it, and let nothing either affright or allure us to a sinful connivance at their bold violations of God's Law. We must not be dumb, tho they should use us as the thief doth a dog, hold out a piece of bread to bribe us not to bark.</P>
<P N="2">2. This should teach the Great ones of the world to bear with Patience, and to receive with Meekness the word of Reproof. None are so high exalted as to be out of the reach of that Word which God speaks.</P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="7"/>None are more our friends than they are, who can∣not stand by, and see us offer violence to our selves with∣out holding of our hands, <HI>Let the righteous smite me, it shall be a kindness; and let him reprove me, it shall be an excellent oyl, which shall not break my head.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 141.5.</NOTE> There may be smiting without violation of Friendship; and his wise Son <HI>Solomon</HI> preferr'd <HI>the wounds of a friend, be∣fore the kisses of an enemy.</HI> These may be pleasanter,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 27.6.</NOTE> but those will prove wholesomer; there is Treachery in these kisses, but in those wounds faithfulness. The Mo∣ther of <HI>Cyrus</HI> charged him who was to speak to the King, to express himself <HI>verbis byssinis,</HI> in soft and silk∣en terms. 'Tis true, sometimes we must come in the Spirit and Language of Love; but 'tis as true, there is oftentimes as great need of coming with a Rod in our hands, as a soft word in our mouths.</P>
<P>Bad men love not a Correcting Ministry; like them, Amos 7.10. <HI>The land is not able to bear all his words;</HI> and ver. 13. <HI>prophesie not again any more at Bethel, for it is the King's chappel, and it is the King's court. They hate him that rebuketh in the gate, (i. e.</HI> the Judg that punished sin) <HI>they abhor him that speaketh uprightly.</HI></P>
<P>Men will endure to hear new Notions and contro∣verted Points; any Satyrical Reflections, and bitter In∣vectives against their brethren; but cannot brook to have their own Personal sins roughly handled. Be care∣ful you do not <HI>Galatizare</HI> (as <HI>Tertullian</HI> phrases it) <HI>hate him who tells you the truth;</HI> nor be like those hearers mentioned <HI>Luke</HI> 4.19, 21, 22, 28. While our Saviour preached the acceptable and glad tidings of Salvation, the good news contained in the Gospel, all the Congre∣gation of <HI>Nazareth</HI> applauded his Doctrine, and ad∣mired
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
at the blessed words which proceeded out of his mouth; but when he came to apply the word unto themselves, they were filled with wrath against him, thrust him out of the City, and would have broke his neck, by attempting to cast him down headlong from the brow of the Hill, <HI>v.</HI> 29.</P>
<P>Have a care you resist not such a Ministry, which awakens the Conscience, and sets the worm on gnawing, altho it should provoke thee to cry out with a loud voice, as he did who was possessed with an unclean Spi∣rit,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 4.33, 34.</NOTE> <HI>Let us alone, art thou come to destroy us?</HI> God doth manifest his Presence and mighty Power in such a sift∣ing Ministry; and the nature of Sin is to make men afraid of God's Appearance, and foolishly with <HI>Adam</HI> to attempt the secreting of themselves from his All-seeing Eye.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Tit. 2.15.</NOTE> We are commanded <HI>to exhort and rebuke with all authority;</HI> and you are enjoined not to despise and fret against the Doctrine we deliver, and that on pain of Everlasting Damnation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 15.10.</NOTE> <HI>for he that hateth re∣proof, shall dye.</HI></P>
<P>I proceed to the 2<HI>d</HI> Branch of Reproof, that which is <HI>Fraternal,</HI> and done in <HI>Brotherly Charity.</HI> Every Pri∣vate Christian may bear the <HI>Person,</HI> tho not the <HI>Office</HI> of a Reprover; and this is founded upon undeniable Grounds, too large to be insisted on at this time, in one single Sermon.</P>
<P>Whether we consult the Honour of God, or the necessity of a punctual conformity to his Will, not di∣stinguishing his Commands, but obeying all equally; it nor disputing any of them, but obeying all readily; it will appear to be our interest as well as our duty, pre∣sently to comply with God's Will and Pleasure: Or if
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
we respect the happiness and welfare of our Brother, exercising in this work the highest acts of charity and benevolence; for if he hear us, then we have <HI>gained our brother.</HI> When thou hearest thy Neighbour swear, lye, slander, deride holiness, persecute with his Tongue the Man who is more righteous than himself, intreat him then to bethink himself what will be the end of such Devilish practices; shew him his danger, and snatch him, if it be possible, out of the fire he is hast∣ning into. Thou hast a heart of Stone, if thou art not concerned, and industrious to prevent his everlast∣ing ruine; for he is riding post to the Devil, if a stop be not put in his way. It is no privilege to any Man to be out of the way of a Reprover; but a severe judg∣ment to be told they shall no more be smitten with this Rod. God, to punish <HI>Judah</HI> for their Rebellion, threatneth to impose silence on his Prophet.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezek. 3.26</NOTE> Let us make much of a blow and stroke of this nature, it car∣rieth healing with it.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lib. 6. Conf. c. 9.</NOTE> St. <HI>Austin</HI> gives two instances of the happy success of Admonition, the one given by himself to his Friend <HI>Alipius,</HI> who was there∣by reclaimed from the Theatre and Stage-plays; the other by a taunt and check given to his Mother <HI>Monica,</HI> who was thereby reclaimed from her Tippling.</P>
<P>If we consult in the next place our own private weal and happiness, it will appear to be highly reason∣able. Hereby we prevent our being <HI>partakers of other mens sins;</HI> so that if our Brother perish, he perisheth to himself. This is the way to keep our selves <HI>pure from the blood of all men,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts 20.26.</NOTE> by declaring to them the whole coun∣sel of God.</HI> This is the way to entail, God's Blessing on us: <HI>To them that rebuke,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 24.25.</NOTE> <HI>a good blessing shall come upon them.</HI> Nay, it is not only the way to procure God's
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
favour, but Man's too. A well-given reproof will in∣gratiate the Reprover with the Reproved. <HI>He that re∣buketh a man,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 28.23.</NOTE> <HI>afterwards shall find more favour, than he that flattereth with the tongue.</HI> This is according to the former Observation, <HI>Rebuke a wise man, and he will love thee.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prov. 9.8.</NOTE> If we hereby be so <HI>wise</HI> as to <HI>turne many to righ∣teousness,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Dan. 12.3.</NOTE> <HI>we shall be so happy as to shine as the bright∣ness of the firmament, and as the stars for ever and ever.</HI> And one advantage more we shall gain, we hereby take a prudent course to provide for our selves a faithful Friend to perform the same kind office as occasion serves. There is no member in the mystical body of Christ, that may not need the assistance of another The eye hath need of the hand, the hand of the feet. We were sometimes foolish and disobedient; And had not we Preachers and Friends to admonish us? Freely you have received, freely give. Thy heart is not right, if thou who wast a Stranger, cannot pity Strangers. Hereby also we should countermine the Devil in two grand methods of his deceit, <HI>viz. The multitude of sinners,</HI> and <HI>the Impunity of sin.</HI> Reproof will abate the number of offenders, and shew the ap∣parent hazard and danger men run by continuing in their sins. That impediment to the discharge of this Duty, <HI>viz. Singularity,</HI> would be taken off; weak Chri∣stians would be kept from being scandalized, and strong ones from being grieved. If these Considerations are not sufficient to shew us the necessity of taking up vigorous and speedy resolutions to live no longer in the neglect and sinful omission of fraternal Repre∣hension, I know not what to add more that may pre∣vail; But must leave such to some other, and I fear, more dreadful way of conviction, when it will be too
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>
late to retrieve the loss, either of their Brother or themselves. I am forced to wave my Answer to the particular Cavils and Excuses which many alledge for their discharge from this work. I therefore must come to the last particular propounded to be spoken to, which was,</P>
<P>The giving some <HI>Directions and Rules</HI> how to man∣age Reproof in such a manner, as that we rationally may expect we shall see it turn to account.</P>
<P>It is a great Art to do it aright, <HI>like the Husband-man's skill which his God doth teach him.</HI> Every one can find fault and chide; but to reprove discreetly and effectually, requires much wisdom:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccles. 12.11.</NOTE> <HI>The words of the wise are as goads, and as nails fastned by the Masters of Assem∣blies.</HI></P>
<P>And here I shall not multiply <HI>Rules;</HI> but among the great throng of them, which by many have been produced, shall select these few following:</P>
<P><HI>Rule</HI> 1. Let the Rebuker look to it, that he be free from that Sin which he condemns in another. <HI>He∣rod</HI>'s Conscience was pricked to the quick, from the consideration of the holiness and justness of the Baptist. Thus did <HI>Samuel</HI> deal with the people;<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 12.3.</NOTE> first he clears his own Innocence, and then charges them with their Sin. God Honours his Servants in the Consciences of their greatest Enemies. To accuse a Man for Drunken∣ness, Covetousness, or any other sin, and yet to live in it thy self, What is this, but with <HI>David</HI> in <HI>Nathan</HI>'s Parable, to pronounce the sentence of condemnation on thy self? With what a controuling, over-powering force did our Saviour tax the sins of the <HI>Jews,</HI> when he prefaced his Discourse with that bold Challenge, <HI>Who
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>
is there amongst you that convinces me of sin?</HI> He that lives in the commission of that sin he condemns in another, must expect that his words will recoyl upon himself, as a foul Gun doth in discharging. Let us so walk that our feet cast not dirt into our mouths. Ma∣ny a savoury truth is hindred in its operation, by the stinking breath of him that delivers it. Every one desires, if he must be stricken, that it be by the hand of the Righteous. To see a <HI>Judas</HI> cast a Stone at a Co∣vetous Man, a <HI>Pharisee</HI> at an Hypocrite, an <HI>Herod</HI> at an Adulterer, is a sight that creates laughter and contempt. None speak at so great an advantage, as they whose <HI>Hands</HI> are lifted up to God's Command∣ments, whilst their <HI>Tongues</HI> are rebuking the transgres∣sors. of them.</P>
<P><HI>Rule</HI> 2. As the Reprover must look to it that he be <HI>faultless,</HI> so he must be sure that his Brother be <HI>faulty;</HI> for otherwise thou dost not reprove, but reproach him; and instead of being a Wise Admonisher, thou art an Hellish Accuser of the Brethren; thou dost not per∣form the Duty of a Christian, but dost execute the Of∣fice of the Devil. Two things must here be re∣garded:</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. That it be a <HI>sin</HI> thou reprovest him for.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. That it be <HI>His sin</HI> thou reprovest him for.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P N="1">1. That it be a <HI>sin;</HI> Be sure he be a transgressor of the Law, before thou smite him with this rod. There must be a breach of some Command, Affirmative or Nega∣tive; directly, or by consequence; either the doing what he ought not, or the not doing of what he ought. To judge a Man for an Hatband or Cuffs, for a Lace
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
or piece of Ribbon, for a Knot or a Feather, (as un∣couth sort of men have of late done) smells rank of pride, censoriousness and uncharitableness. But alas! In what an Age do we live, where mens quarrels against one another shall take their rise from such minute and inconsiderable beginnings, that a wise Man is ashamed to name them, being as insignificant and unedifying, as he who studied Thirty years, whither <HI>Virgil</HI>'s name should be written with an <HI>I,</HI> or an <HI>E.</HI></P>
<P>Reprove not therefore thy Brother for things law∣ful or indifferent, for trivial and undecided matters. Be sure you have good ground to proceed on. Beware of severe censures, and contentious debates. Many a matter that kindles unnatural heart-burnings between Professors of Religion, when it comes to be scann'd, and fully understood, proves either nothing at all, or at most, nothing to the purpose. It was the case of the <HI>Reubenites,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Josh. 22.12.</NOTE> The Army of <HI>Israel</HI> was raised against them, nothing but War, Fire and Sword were threat∣ned for their building an <HI>Altar of Testimony</HI> in their journey; when they met together, and had discoursed the matter, and came to a right understanding of their Brethrens end and intentions,<NOTE PLACE="marg">V. 35.</NOTE> they were presently re∣conciled. Thus our Brethren suffer often through our ignorance; to such Reprovers we may say, what <HI>Job</HI> did to his mistaken friends, who upbraided him with hypocrisy; <HI>How forcible are right words!</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Job 6.25.</NOTE> <HI>but what doth your arguing reprove?</HI> Some conceive that <HI>Jacob</HI> un∣derstood not the mystery of his Son <HI>Soseph</HI>'s Dream (concerning the <HI>Sun, Moon and Stars making obeisance to him)</HI> whence it came, and how it should be ac∣complished, when, he read his chiding Lecture a∣bout it.</P>
<P N="2"><PB N="18" REF="11"/>2. Look to it carefully that the thing be not only a <HI>sin</HI> you reprove him about, but that it be <HI>his</HI> sin. It was foretold of <HI>Christ,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isa. 11.3.</NOTE> that <HI>he shall not judge after the sight of his eyes, neither reprove after the hearing of his ears.</HI> Jealousies and conjectures, hear says, fancies and re∣ports, are not sufficient grounds for reproof. The Rule of Charity is, <HI>Quisque presumitur quod bonus est, nisi constat de malo.</HI> Thus we read, neither <HI>John</HI>'s <HI>mourning,</HI> nor Christ's <HI>piping</HI> could pass their hard censures; but the one has a <HI>Devil,</HI> and the other is a <HI>Glutton, and Wine-bibber.</HI></P>
<P>Tho Christ came to fulfil the Law, yet there were that accused him as a destroyer of it. Tho he decided the Question fairly on <HI>Caesars</HI> side, in the grand Case of Tribute and Custom, yet there wanted not those who charged him with disloyalty. How were the Apostles slandered as Seducers and Sectaries, Vain Bablers, and Hereticks, Broachers of new, false, and pestilent Do∣ctrines, Presumptuous and Heady, Despisers of Digni∣ties, and Promoters of Uproars, Riots and Routs, and Unlawful Assemblies. In succeeding times, if we read the Apologies of <HI>Athenagoras, Tertullian</HI> and others, it will amaze you to see with what vilainous practices, and unnatural impieties they are charged; and no won∣der, for if they called the Master of the House <HI>Beelzebub,</HI> how much more those of his houshold?</P>
<P>Because it was against Law to have Virgins strangled, <HI>Tiberius</HI> would have them first deflour'd, and then ac∣cording to Law, (alias <HI>humour, will and pleasure)</HI> they must dye that death.</P>
<P>It is too much to abuse a good Man, <HI>as</HI> such; but first commit a rape on his Name, and your way is open to his Life and Fortune.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="11"/>The poor <HI>Protestants</HI> of <HI>Paris</HI> must first be accused of a Conspiracy against the King, and then thousands together must be Butcher'd without mercy.</P>
<P>So Men, by misrepresenting, dress up their Brethren in the monstrous shapes of <HI>Vultures</HI> and <HI>Harpies,</HI> with Claws and Talons, as being well armed for Prey and Rapine; and then afterwards fall foul on them. Thus was <HI>Hannah</HI> reproved for Drunkenness, which she no ways could be guilty of, except large draughts of her own Tears should intoxicate her: She was far enough from a merry heart; her grief and sorrow did even break her heart, and she was overwhelmed with her di∣stress.</P>
<P>Mistake not therefore thy Man and Mark, and <HI>bear not false witness against thy brother.</HI> Tho <HI>David</HI> will ever be registred in the <HI>Albo Justorum,</HI> and reckoned in the number of good men, yet his act of censuring un∣heard <HI>Mephibosheth,</HI> will ever be reckoned amongst his unjust Actions.</P>
<P><HI>Potiphar</HI> was guilty of this injustice, by an over∣hasty crediting his Wifes forged Tale against <HI>Joseph.</HI> A better course is prescribed. <HI>Inquire and make search,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 13.14.</NOTE> <HI>and ask diligently,</HI> if it be Truth that is told.</P>
<P>Rule 3. <HI>Take care thy ends and intentions be sincere and upright in this work:</HI> For if they are not right, it will vitiate all thou dost in this or any other Duty of Religion, either to thy God, or thy Neighbour. Let nothing be done out of vain-glory, and a secret ambitious desire of observation and raising up a great name for thy self. Purge out that evil proud humour of contradicting and controuling others; avoid every thing that may be interpreted to be a design to dis∣grace
<PB N="20" REF="12"/>
and render thy Brother mean and contemptible in the eyes and apprehensions of his Neighbourhood and acquaintance. Look to it that all be directed to those glorious ends of God's Glory, the recovery of thine erring Brother, the satisfying thine own Con∣science in the necessary discharge of thy Duty, out of hatred to sin, and a desire to suppress that in this un∣toward and evil Generation, and to promote universal Holiness throughout the World.</P>
<P>Rule 4. <HI>Let all Reproofs be managed with the great∣est demonstrations and expressions of Charity and Love to their persons that may be.</HI> When you express your warmest zeal against their sins, be sure you usher in all your advice with soft Prefaces of good-will, pity, and real affections to them. The Text tells us, Re∣proofs must not be given <HI>in hatred;</HI> they are bitter Pills, and should be wrapt up in Honey, that they may slip down the better. Many therefore have well advi∣sed it as a prudent course, to intermix their due Com∣mendations with our Admonitions, whereby the re∣ception of our Advice would be much facilitated. The dreadfullest and most solemn Censures of the Church of God, are not <HI>Mortal</HI> but <HI>Medicinal,</HI> and are appointed not for <HI>Killing,</HI> but for <HI>Cure.</HI> Our reproofs being thus temper'd with Love, will be like a Sword dipt in Bal∣som, that woundeth and healeth at the same time. It was said long since by an Ancient Father, <HI>Admonitio misericordia carens tortura est.</HI> Do not put thy Bro∣ther on a Rack, and torture him with violent and con∣tinual repetitions of his guilt.</P>
<P N="5"><PB N="21" REF="12"/>5. Rule, <HI>Avoid all extravagancies of rage and passi∣on, and let all be done meekness and humility of mind.</HI> Reproof, tho it ought to be warm, yet it must not be scalding hot. <HI>The wrath of man worketh not the righte∣ousness of God. Michael</HI> the Arch-Angel when contro∣verting with the Devil, shewed himself to be a pure Spirit, by the calmness of the debate, which was not managed with any <HI>excess</HI> of Passion. <HI>Hard</HI> Argu∣ments and <HI>Soft</HI> Words should be yoked together.</P>
<P>Play not the part of an enemy under the mask of a friend, which is done by pretending to heal a wound in the <HI>Conscience</HI> of our brother, or to wash him clean from some blots and stains in his <HI>Conversation,</HI> but thou dost set and imprint some mark or brand of shame and ignominy on his <HI>name.</HI> This is the direction of the Apostle, <HI>Restore such an one in the spirit of meekness;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gal. 6.1.</NOTE> <HI>q. d.</HI> Deal as gently with a fallen brother, as thou would'st with a man whose bones are dislocated; for so much, say <HI>Criticks,</HI> the Metaphor in that place im∣ports. <HI>Elisha</HI> did more with a <HI>kiss,</HI> than his man with a <HI>staff.</HI></P>
<P>Consider not so much what you are able to <HI>say,</HI> as what your brother is able to <HI>bear.</HI> Use the Christian Art to suit and proportion your <HI>Wine</HI> to your <HI>Bottles;</HI> let not children have <HI>strong meat,</HI> nor grown persons <HI>milk;</HI> be sure it be what is most proper for their health and nourishment, what the stomach can well digest, and will not throw up again. Yet withal, remember to reprove with all <HI>seriousness,</HI> that they may know thou art in earnest. A trifling slight reprehension, like old <HI>Eli</HI>'s to his profligate Sons, (who only shaked his head at them, when their heads rather should have been
<PB N="22" REF="13"/>
stricken off) What doth it signifie or avail? Often∣times it doth more harm than good, and rather em∣boldens than reforms the Offender.</P>
<P>It is a piece of great Wisdom and Skill to commen∣surate our rebukes to the temper of the offender, and to the nature of his offence. Commonly we are either <HI>too remiss</HI> if we endeavour <HI>Moderation,</HI> or <HI>too austere and rough</HI> if we design <HI>faithfulness:</HI> But I think there is little need to caution any persons against overdoing in this kind, it is an Extreme few fall into, there being more danger in our <HI>oyl,</HI> than in our <HI>salt,</HI> i, e. as one ex∣presses it, in our <HI>smooth words,</HI> than in our <HI>sharp rebukes.</HI> I fear the greatest work that is done in this matter, is sowing of pillows under sinners elbows, when our duty should be quilting of thorns to lay under their backs, that when the bold and contumacious sinner retires to his Chamber, he may also retire within himself, and be kept awake in his bed here, that so his sleeping an everlasting sleep of death, and making his bed in un∣quenchable flames may be prevented. Command then thy brother in the name of God to be think himself, to repent and reform, to read what the God of Truth and Justice has threatned against him if he do not amend and turn; fight him with this glittering Sword of God's Word, and 'tis the likeliest way to make his sins fall before thee, and to give up the Ghost.</P>
<P>There are several other weighty Directions relating to the prudent management of this important duty of Fraternal Rebuke, which I must pass by with a very little reference to them; that so as we ought to pray read, sing, and perform all Christian Offices with the Spirit, and with our Understandings also; so we may perform this in that manner, that it may not be a <HI>sacri∣fice
<PB N="23" REF="13"/>
of fools.</HI> Let us apply our selves to learn that Wis∣dom which is from above, so as to take the Sinner <HI>by a holy craft and guile;</HI> as the Apostle expresses it.</P>
<P>And here distinction should be made between the Persons and Crimes of Offenders, the proper Seasons, and the particular Ways and Methods of Reproof.</P>
<P N="1">1. We must distinguish between <HI>the Persons.</HI> Of some we are <HI>to have compassion, making a difference.</HI> Ma∣king a difference between men in publick and private capacities; <HI>Thou shalt not revile the gods,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 22.18.</NOTE> <HI>nor curse the ruler of thy people.</HI> Rough and unhewn language is not to be used to them. <HI>Shimei</HI> said nothing more in substance to <HI>David,</HI> than <HI>Nathan</HI> did, but it was in a very scurrilous and railing manner. Tho we may <HI>rebuke,</HI> we must not <HI>revile:</HI> Difference must be made between the <HI>tempers</HI> of sinners. There cannot be an uniform proceeding with all, but we must vary according to their dispositions. Some men are like Thorns, which if gently touched, hurt not; but if you grasp them with an hard and unwary hand, they will fetch blood: Others are like Nettles, which if they are nicely and delicately handled, sting and prick, but if closely and roughly press'd and grasp'd, you may pull them up without pain or harm.</P>
<P>Before therefore you reprove a sinner, know whe∣ther he be a <HI>Thorn</HI> or <HI>Nettle.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. Difference is to be made betwixt their <HI>Crimes.</HI> As the Offence is great or small, so should the reproof be <HI>sharp</HI> or <HI>mild.</HI> There are Beams and Motes, Pimples and Plague-sores, Scratches and Ulcers. We must not hang a man for filching a pin or a rattle, and whip him gently and tenderly for Murther and Treason. As
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>
the Offence is more secretly, or more impudently com∣mitted, whether drunk in the Night in his Chamber, or at noon-day in the <HI>Exchange:</HI> Some sin publickly, the greater is their sin, and so should their shame, be∣cause they give the greater scandal; others sin more privately; our Reprehension in this case ought to be auricular, and there is no better Sepulchre than that of secresie, wherein to bury his more hidden failings. There is no need of going to the House-top, when a Closet would be more proper. Thus we see, that tho all sins want an equal Price and Merit for Atonement and Satisfaction, yet they require not equal severity in our Rebukes and Admonitions. Some must have Le∣nitives, others Corrosives. Superiors may be reformed by Exhortation, Equals by Friendly Admonition; and Inferiors (if in the highest form and chair of Scorners) by severe Reprehension. We must not indeed be fiery-hot in terrifying the meaner sort, and look upon the rich as that Mount which must not be touched. We must not talk one half in the language of <HI>Canaan,</HI> and the other in that of <HI>Ashdod;</HI> but let us go to work impar∣tially, not executing the command, as <HI>Saul</HI> did against <HI>Amalek,</HI> when he spared the fat and chief, and destroy∣ed only the poor and refuse. This made that excellent Emperor <HI>Theodosius</HI> have so great a value for St. <HI>Ambrose,</HI> because he was not affrighted with the huffing of the Proudest, and had great compassion to the souls of the poorest.</P>
<P N="3">3. We must make a difference in the <HI>seasons</HI> of Re∣proof; <HI>There is a time to speak, and a time to be silent.</HI> It is difficult here to assign the <HI>mollia fandi tempora,</HI> the soft Articles and Opportunities wherein we are to speak, because variety of Circumstances may alter
<PB N="25" REF="14"/>
the case; only all must agree to do it as soon as con∣veniently we may. Delays harden. As we must <HI>ex∣hort,</HI> so we must <HI>rebuke</HI> daily, <HI>Heb.</HI> 3.13. Suffer not sin <HI>to lye upon him,</HI> nor he in his sin one day longer, if it be in your power to help it. But especially avoid thy rebuking of him, when he is like the wild Ass, with whom there is no medling while she is in the heat and fervour of her lust, <HI>Jer.</HI> 2.24. but she hath her parti∣cular month to be taken in. <HI>Abigal</HI> deferred to reprove <HI>Nabal</HI> in his Wine; she let him sleep it out, thinking the best time to give him this Physick, would be when he was fasting in the Morning. Good Physicians eva∣cuate not the body in extremity either of heat or cold. Watch when thy Brother is <HI>himself,</HI> nay, <HI>more than himself,</HI> humble, tender, and pliable, then he is indeed a qualified recipient. Such are times of Affliction and Fear, Sickness and impending Chastisements. But do not under pretence of a more convenient season, total∣ly neglect and shift off thy Duty.</P>
<P N="4">4. We are to make difference in the ways and me∣thods of reproving; sometimes <HI>plainly and directly,</HI> as <HI>Nathan</HI> to <HI>David, Thou art the man;</HI> at other times more <HI>covertly,</HI> by intimation and circumlocution. The Sun keeps the world in good temper, by moving in an oblique Circle; and Ships (Mariners say) sail best, and make the greatest way with side-winds.</P>
<P>I crave leave only to Apply what has been said in these following ways, when I have laid down this sin∣gle Caution, <HI>viz.</HI> That tho Reproof is then best taken, when it is best given, (according to those Directions now given) yet no man must reject it, because the Re∣prover wants those due Qualifications to render him every way meet for his work. Good Counsel from a bad
<PB N="26" REF="15"/>
man must not be slighted; <HI>Balaam</HI> was a bad man, yet he had a good wish, and uttered a most excellent Pro∣phesie. A diseased Physician may prescribe good Me∣dicines; a lame Steward may distribute his Masters Alms: Ungrounded is that Doctrine both of the <HI>Ro∣manists</HI> and several others, who tell us, That the Bene∣fit of God's Ordinances depends upon the goodness and <HI>right intentions</HI> of the Priest and Minister. What, shall I not be saved by hearing, unless the Preacher be saved, whom I hear? Is the Grace of God tied to the Ministry of man? Shall the Servant share the Honour, and part stakes with his Master? Our Lord and Great Prophet taught the people to observe their Doctrines that sate in <HI>Moses</HI> Chair; tho without breach of Cha∣rity he called them Serpents and Hypocrites. <HI>Sampson</HI> did not disdain the Sweets, because he found them un∣cleanly laid in the Lions Carkass. His diet was strict enough, he might not eat that which savoured of Le∣gal Impurity, yet refused not a Honey-comb, because found in the belly of a dead Beast. Honey is Honey, tho in a dead Lyon.</P>
<P>Having inserted this necessary <HI>Caution,</HI> I shall in the Close, subjoin Two or Three Things by way of <HI>Infe∣rence, Reproof,</HI> and <HI>Advice,</HI> by way of more parti∣cular</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="application of sermon">
<HEAD>Application.</HEAD>
<P N="1">1. I hence <HI>infer,</HI> That if it be the Duty of Mini∣sters, Parents and Governors of Families to <HI>give</HI> Re∣proof, then it is the Duty of People, Children, and Servants to <HI>take</HI> it. You are as much obliged to have a willing <HI>Ear,</HI> as we are to use a faithful <HI>Tongue.</HI> But
<PB N="27" REF="15"/>
woe unto us! we have stopped our ears against the loud and reiterated Rebukes of Heaven. God at sun∣dry times, and divers manners hath both in times past spoken, and still doth speak in very Reprehensory Lan∣guage, and has let us know his mind in very broad and legible Characters; so that if we were upon the wing, flying, or on our feet running, we may plainly read it. There are four ways, in a more singular and eminent manner, by which God has reprehended us.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. By his Word.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. By our Consciences.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. By the Examples of Good Men.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. By his Judgments on Bad Men.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P N="1">1. By his <HI>Word;</HI> That is profitable for <HI>reproof;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Tim. 3.16.</NOTE> for reproof of Errors and false Doctrines; for <HI>correction</HI> of sin and evil manners. Every one that doth evil, hates this sacred Torch, <HI>neither cometh to this light,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Joh. 3.20.</NOTE> <HI>lest his deeds should be reproved. Moreover by them</HI> (i. e. by thy Statutes) <HI>is thy servant warned.</HI> But men seal up this Book to themselves, and spend more time in Ro∣mantick Discourses, than in these Sacred Oracles.</P>
<P N="2">2. He reproves by our own Consciences. How often do they check and chide us? 'Tis said of <HI>David,</HI> as soon as he had cut off the lap of <HI>Saul</HI>'s Garment <HI>(his heart smote him)</HI> that is, his Conscience recoil'd upon him. Conscience is the great <HI>Register</HI> and <HI>Recorder of</HI> the World; it hath the Pen of a ready writer; not a word or thought escapes its swift Pencil. It is God's <HI>Hi∣storiographer,</HI> which writes not only <HI>Anuals,</HI> but <HI>Diaries;</HI> it hath its Book and Table, wherein it indelibly writes mens Transgressions and Swervings. It is man's
<PB N="28" REF="16"/>
<HI>private Notary; his Bailiff</HI> to arrest him, and seize up∣on every miscarrying habit and act. It is his <HI>Judg,</HI> sifts and scrutinizes the Offender, convicts and then con∣demns the Malefactor; <HI>Their consciences also bearing witness,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 2.15.</NOTE> <HI>and their thoughts</HI> the mean while <HI>accusing, or else excusing one another.</HI> And how many secret Lectures hath this read to us? What Artifices have we used to rock it to sleep? Play and Gaming, Musick and Feast∣ing, Company and many diversions of the same nature, have been cast in to still this importunate and offensive babler, whose tongue will never lye still.</P>
<P N="3">3. God reproves by the <HI>Examples of Good Men. Noah condemned</HI> the old world for their security, by his prepa∣ring an Ark.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Heb. 11.7.</NOTE> A good man leads a <HI>convincing life,</HI> and there is an <HI>Elenctical</HI> Power in his holy deportment. Those that stood with the Lamb,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rev. 14.1.</NOTE> had the <HI>Father's</HI> name in their foreheads, as <HI>Holiness to the Lord</HI> was upon the High Priest's. We must answer not only for sinning against the Light of God's <HI>Word,</HI> and our own <HI>Conscien∣ces,</HI> but the light of good <HI>example</HI> also. The faithful are called <HI>Witnesse;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Heb. 12.1.</NOTE> so <HI>Lot</HI> witnessed against the sin∣ners of his age. A Good Man's life is the best Scripture-Commentary, and hath a Magnetical Virtue, a hidden Excellency to allure to Goodness.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Phil. 2.15.</NOTE> The Godly shine like <HI>Lights</HI> in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation.</P>
<P N="4">4. God reproves by his <HI>Judgments on bad men;</HI> he reproves both by his <HI>Word</HI> and <HI>Rod,</HI> as by the <HI>testimo∣ny of his mouth,</HI> so by the <HI>works of his hands. Thou hast rebuked the heathen,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 9.3.</NOTE> <HI>thou hast destroyed the wicked.</HI> That act of destruction was a smart Reprehensory Lecture to them; they were taught with Briars and Thorns. God will get his lessons in at mens backs, if they will not kindly receive them at their ears; he will whip
<PB N="29" REF="16"/>
them into better manners, and shew them their faults by their stripes.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Chron. 16.21. Psal. 16.21. Psal. 39.11.</NOTE> Reproof is frequently in Scripture put for chastisement.</P>
<P><HI>Lot</HI>'s Wife was turned into a Pillar of Salt, looking back contrary to God's command; and that this <HI>Pil∣lar of Salt</HI> was for the seasoning of all that would cast an eye behind to <HI>Sodom,</HI> appears by our <HI>Saviour</HI>'s ge∣neral application of it, <HI>Remember Lot's wife.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 17.32.</NOTE></P>
<P><HI>Remember,</HI> What? Not so much the <HI>Miracle,</HI> which every cursory Reader of the Scripture has at his fingers ends; and poor Children, like Parrots, can recite to you; but Remember the <HI>Moral,</HI> the <HI>Doctrine,</HI> and <HI>In∣struction</HI> which lies more covertly under it.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Jer. 7.12.</NOTE> <HI>But go ye now unto my place which was in Shiloh, where I set my name at the first, an see what I did to it, for the wick∣edness of my people Israel.</HI></P>
<P>The Ancient Philosophers (as <HI>Gellius</HI> noteth) as∣signed Three Grounds for punishment of offenders:</P>
<P N="1">1. That which is called <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, when punishment was inflicted for amending of the party punished, and to put him in mind of the committed offence.</P>
<P N="2">2. The second they called <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, for preservation of the honour of him against whom the offence was committed, lest indulgence should occasion contempt of his figure and dignity.</P>
<P N="3">3. They call'd <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, when an Offender was punished for Example sake, to deter others from the like offence. Some notorious Malefactors are hang∣ed up in Chains to warn and affright others. This was the aggravation of <HI>Belshazzar</HI>'s Pride,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Dan. 5 22.</NOTE> that he <HI>humbled not his heart,</HI> tho he knew the judgment inflicted on his Father for the same sin.</P>
<P><PB N="30" REF="17"/><NOTE PLACE="marg">Zeph. 3.6, 7.</NOTE>Mark God's own method of Arguing. <HI>I have cut off the nations: their towers are desolate, I made their streets waste, that none passeth by: their cities are de∣stroyed, so that there is no man, that there is none in∣habitant. I said, Surely thou wilt fear me: thou wilt re∣ceive instruction: so their dwelling should not be cut off, howsoever I punished them: but they rose early, and cor∣rupted all their doings.</HI></P>
<P>The ordinary word the <HI>Greeks</HI> used for punishment was <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, which signifies Example, because there is not a punishment on one, but it should be an ex∣ample to all; so the publick putting away a Wife that was found faulty, is called, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, to make her a publick example.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Matt. 1.19.</NOTE><HI>Cambyses</HI> fley'd off the skin of a corrupt and warp∣ing Judge, and spread it over the Seat of Judgment for his Successors to tread on, that so it might be a continual Monitor to them to avoid injustice.</P>
<P>God will not endure a succession in wickedness; and to prevent exemplarity, reproves many in this way, to give a check to the boldness of others in sin.</P>
<P>How often his methods in all these ways of Repre∣hension have been used with us, I leave it to your selves to judge; and how often we have defeated them, God well knows, and will judge us for them: which leads me to a second branch of my Application, I mean, from a <HI>Doctrine</HI> of Reproof, to descend to a <HI>Second Ʋse</HI> of Reproof.</P>
<P N="2">2. When we compare God's Precept with our Practise, What bad Comments are they on so blessed a Text? We may well cry out with our Country-man <HI>Linacre, Aut hoc non est Evangelium, aut nos man sumus Evange∣lici:</HI> Either: this is not <HI>Gospel,</HI> or we are not <HI>Gospellers.</HI>
<PB N="31" REF="17"/>
We ramble dreadfully from the Text; the meanest Preacher may easily keep closer to the <HI>Sense</HI> of it, than the generality of Professors do to the <HI>Practise</HI> of it.</P>
<P>Instead of taking this wise and honest course of <HI>fra∣ternal correption,</HI> we have used our selves to an ac∣cursed and odious way of <HI>fraternal defamation.</HI></P>
<P>Two Beasts walk much up and down (which <HI>Dio∣genes</HI> advised the <HI>Emperor</HI> to avoid, being malignant biters) the <HI>tame beast</HI> the <HI>Flatterer,</HI> and the <HI>wild beast</HI> the <HI>Slanderer:</HI> As the <HI>Jews</HI> conspired against <HI>Jeremiah,</HI> so do many against their Brethren and Neighbours, saying as they, <HI>Let us smite them with the tongue,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Jer. 18.18.</NOTE> <HI>let us devise devices against them.</HI></P>
<P>If to Rail and Lye, Censure and Revile, to Misre∣port and Misrepresent, were fulfilling the Commands of God, and paying our Duty to our Brother; if they were Rules of Behaviour and Conversation, the gene∣rality of men might chime in with that young Gentle∣man in the Gospel, and say after him, <HI>All these have I kept from my youth upward.</HI></P>
<P><HI>They hate their brother in their heart,</HI> and shew it in these following ways:</P>
<P N="1">1. By industriously searching out what is culpable and blame worthy in them, on purpose to disgrace and reproach them. Of this the <HI>Psalmist</HI> complains,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 64.6.</NOTE> <HI>They search out iniquities, they accomplish a diligent search.</HI> It is a sad sign and indication, that malice is boyl'd up to a great height in mens hearts, when they are so in∣quisitive and studious to find out articles of impeach∣ment against their Brother, and proud <HI>(as they who have obtained great spoil)</HI> when they have made a fresh discovery of some crime in him.</P>
<P N="2"><PB N="32" REF="18"/>2. Men discover their <HI>hatred of their brother,</HI> by tempting him to the <HI>commission</HI> of that sin which they design to make matter of <HI>objection</HI> against him. Thus the malicious <HI>Pharisees</HI> did their utmost to cause Christ to offend <HI>(if it had been possible) urging him vehement∣ly,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 11.53.</NOTE> <HI>and provoking him with</HI> all their little artifices, <HI>to speak of many things, that they might accuse him.</HI> They asked him many a captious question to make him an of∣fender for a word.</P>
<P N="3">3. Their hatred is manifested by magnifying and aggrandizing their Brethrens faults, swelling and im∣proving every Mole hill to the size and bulk of a Moun∣tain. With their viperous and poysonous breath, they blow up every bubble (which at first was but a drop of Water stuft with a small vapour) to the dimensions of a large Globe. Some think themselves excusable herein (if not commendable) as thereby discovering their zeal against sin, which never can be made to ap∣pear sufficiently <HI>sinful:</HI> But let such beware, lest upon scrutiny it should be found a <HI>bitter zeal,</HI> having more of malice at the bottom, than any true concern for God's Glory, or their Brethrens good.</P>
<P N="4">4. And <HI>Lastly,</HI> Men discover their hatred of their Brother, by mentioning their failures and infirmities with some secret kind of rejoycing and pleasure. What self-satisfaction do many take, and without any uneasi∣ness, can hear a discourse of twice the length of any Sermon, if the subject affect the reputation and good name of their nearest Neighbours? A sad sin, tho little laid to heart.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 27.24.</NOTE> <HI>Cursed be he that smiteth his neighbour secretly.</HI></P>
<P>This renders a Man like the Devil himself, and transforms him into an <HI>Angel of darkness;</HI> this involves
<PB N="33" REF="18"/>
us in the guilt and breach of many a Commandment; Five of the second Table are often at once violated: That <HI>Honour</HI> we should give to our <HI>Fathers,</HI> our Gover∣nours, and Superiours, is with-held. We are also dipt in Blood, and guilty of <HI>Murther;</HI> for he that hates his Brother, wishes he were not; Hatred extends it self to the extirpation and non-existence of the thing hated, and therefore it is <HI>Heart-Murther;</HI> thou dost kill him in thy thoughts, tho for many external considerations thou art restrained from padling in his Blood with thy hands; thou art loth to be hang'd for thy Fact. A <HI>Rape</HI> also is committed on his Name, and thou canst not excuse thy self from a reductive breach of the <HI>seventh Commandment.</HI> As for the <HI>eighth</HI> and <HI>ninth,</HI> they are apparently broke. Thou art a notorious <HI>Thief</HI> and <HI>Robber.</HI> Your Brother's good name is by <HI>Solomon</HI> pre∣ferr'd before <HI>precious Oyntments.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Eccl. 7.1.</NOTE> Oyntments in anci∣ent times were a special part of the Royal Treasure of Princes. When <HI>Hezekias,</HI> in ostentation of his Royal Wealth, and the Magnificence of his Treasures, would shew the <HI>Babylonish Ambassadors</HI> his choicest Col∣lections, among the chiefest things there are reckon∣ed in the Inventory, the <HI>precious Oyntments.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Kings 20.13.</NOTE> Some tell us out of <HI>Pliny,</HI> That there were Oyntments in the Apothecaries Shops of that value, (so great was the Riot and Luxury of those times!) that every Pound amounted to more than Twelve Pounds of our Money, if they rightly compute the value of the <HI>Roman</HI> Peny. A great rate surely, if we consider the time wherein he lived, about 1500 years since. He had been a notorious Robber, who should steal any considerable quantity of such costly Ware. And is not He a worser Thief,
<GAP DESC="missing" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page missing〉"/>
<PB N="34" REF="19"/>
injuriously and feloniously takes his Neighbour's good Name from him, which is by the <HI>Wise Man</HI> adjudged to be <HI>better than any Oyntment,</HI> consisting of the most costly Ingredients? Let us have no fellowship with these Slanderers, Tale-bearers, and Whisperers, but rather re∣prove them; which we then effectually shall do, when we will not allow our selves to be <HI>Receivers</HI> to these <HI>Thieves,</HI> nor <HI>Abbettors</HI> of these <HI>Murtherers,</HI> by setting our Ears open to these Calumniators and Detractors. The <HI>Tale-hearer</HI> is the great Patron and Encourager of the <HI>Tale-bearer.</HI> Receive not stoll'n Goods, and you'll spoil the Thiefs Trade. What great difference is there to be found betwixt him who has the <HI>Devil in his Tongue,</HI> and the other who has the <HI>Devil in his Ear?</HI></P>
<P>A <HI>venomous Tongue,</HI> if it be not match'd with an <HI>easie, credulous,</HI> and <HI>itching Ear,</HI> can never make any conside∣rable earnings of it. Beware therefore of this Snare of the Devil, of reporting with some kind of delight the worst thou canst find in thy Brother, overseeing wilfully the many commendable qualifications he is endowed with. We are too like the old <HI>Criticks,</HI> who had all <HI>Homer</HI>'s imperfect Verses in memory, but could not repeat any of those Excellent in their kind. My Friends, are we not here highly concerned? With what a <HI>gusto</HI> and re∣lish do many report (if not raise) Stories and Fables that may any ways derogate from the good Name and Reputation of those who dissent from them? What (say they) do you not hear what such an one hath said; or what the other hath done? We tell smiling, what St. <HI>Paul,</HI> or any other right-complexion'd Christian, could tell no otherwise than weeping. They would mix tears with their words. Is this to be rightly affected
<PB N="35" REF="19"/>
with other Mens breaches of God's Statutes? Is this the right method of conquering your otherwise-minded Brethren? <HI>Is this your rejoicing in good?</HI> It was a great fault among some of the <HI>Corinthians,</HI> that when they heard of the scandalous sin of the <HI>Incestuous person,</HI> they were <HI>puffed up,</HI> when they should rather have <HI>mourned.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 5.2.</NOTE> There were great Divisions and Parties amongst them at that time when the Incest was committed, and the con∣trary Faction thought they had an advantage against the whole Party, and this puffed them up, and they started the discourse of it in all Companies they came into. Verily this is a great fault amongst us; to throw thy Brother into the Dirt, and then stand strutting up∣on him, and crowing on his back while he is wallowing in the Mire; This is a posture fitter for a <HI>Devil</HI> than a <HI>Christian:</HI> For, I beseech you, in what one thing can a Man approach nearer to the similitude and likeness of that Evil Spirit, than in the rejoicing at that Wicked∣ness which is committed in the World; especially for them to be guilty of it, who by their <HI>Holy Office and Calling</HI> are more particularly obliged to the observation of the aforementioned Rules of Reprehension? It is a Crime inexcusable. It is no wonder to see wicked and profligate Wretches priding themselves in their proseli∣ting others to their own practise, when they <HI>make</HI> or <HI>find</HI> some in their own likeness; but yet in them it is the height of Wickedness to glory either in their own, or other Mens shame. <HI>Lamech</HI> indeed did thus.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 4.</NOTE> Thus did <HI>Alexander Pharoeus,</HI> who consecrated that Javelin wherewith he had slain <HI>Polyphron;</HI> and <HI>Protagoras,</HI> who boasted he had spent forty years in corrupting of Youth. Thus <HI>Mark Anthony</HI> disgorged a Book concerning his
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
own abilities in Gluttony and Drunkenness. <HI>Johannes a Casa</HI> wrote a Poem in commendation of those <HI>Spanish Virtues</HI> (as one stiles them) <HI>Whoredom, Sodomy,</HI> and <HI>In∣cest.</HI> But for men making a more strict Profession of their subjection to <HI>Divine Revelations,</HI> and all <HI>Moral Principles;</HI> for such whose Character loudly calls on them, as the more immediate Servants of the Lord, <HI>not to strive, but be gentle to all men, in meekness instruct∣ing those that oppose themselves,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Tim. 2.22, 23, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> <HI>avoiding all things that do gender strifes, to follow Righteousness, Faith, Charity, Peace.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Tim. 5.</NOTE> <HI>To reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long-suffering, thereby giving proof of their Ministry.</HI> For these to be found deficient, is a doubled and multiplied Iniquity.</P>
<P>Give me leave to be plain, and a little more particu∣lar. I am sorry to see men of this Rank so to unhallow and profane their own venerable Office, that one would think in their Orders they received an <HI>unholy Spirit,</HI> and <HI>Fire,</HI> in the very literal sense of the words, with∣out the relief of Figure or Metaphor. But it spreads far∣ther abroad. The Mouths of most stand half-cock'd, ready to discharge at their Brethren in loud Vollies of Contumelies, and false Reports; nay, some there are, who, if they were <HI>Basilisks,</HI> as they are <HI>Vipers,</HI> would stab their Brother to death with their <HI>Eyes. Father, for∣give them, though they know what they say and do!</HI> What strange Accusations of late have been charged on such whose Souls abhorred to enter into any such Se∣cresies! <HI>viz. That they are Popishly inclined, Promoters of Addresses of Abhorrence; that they have covenanted to pull down all Bulwarks that have been erected for the De∣fence and Safeguard of the Protestant Religion!</HI></P>
<P><PB N="37" REF="20"/>In Defence of several within the compass of mine own knowledge, I will adventure to say thus much: These Evidences might with as much Reason and Ho∣nesty have sworn them to have been nurs'd up with the Milk of a Tygress or Bear; that they came into the World vested with the Skins of <HI>Porcupines,</HI> full of Darts and Spikes, to squirt out at pleasure at Mankind; That for their Religion they are <HI>Turks</HI> and <HI>Jews, Pagans</HI> and <HI>Idolaters,</HI> yea and that of the worst sort also; that they are <HI>Canibals,</HI> and eat nothing but Mans Flesh, and that their drink is a warm draught of Human Gore; That they were in a Plot to cut the Throats of their nearest Relations, and had signed an Obligation to the Devil, written with their own Blood, That after a small space of time, wherein they were to accomplish the aforesaid Designs, they should tamely surrender themselves to that <HI>Evil One</HI>'s disposal and mercy. If this be thought to be spoken with too keen an edge, I have only this to add in justification of it: Those I speak of were never such Admirers of the Doctrine of <HI>Passive Obedience</HI> and <HI>Non-Resistance,</HI> as to suffer all the Dirt and Offal that could be raked out of Kennels and Common-shoars to be plaistered on their Faces, without lifting up of a hand to wipe it off. <HI>Their rejoicing is this, the testi∣mony of their Consciences,</HI> that they have had their Con∣versation in the World with more Integrity and Godly Sincerity than these men will allow them; and can say that humbly and thankfully, which the <HI>Pharisee</HI> said falsly and haughtily, <HI>God we thank thee, we are not the Men as such report us to be.</HI></P>
<P N="3"><PB N="38" REF="21"/>III. <HI>Ʋse.</HI> Let us all suffer a word of Exhortation to be added to a word of Reproof. And here I beg it hear∣tily, that men would erect a <HI>Court of Inquisition</HI> in their own breasts, and <HI>cite and try themselves before them∣selves.</HI> Put these Questions home, and give Conscience leave to answer with all imaginable freedom.</P>
<P>Are we Lambs, or Wolves; Doves, or Vultures, and Birds of Prey?</P>
<P>Don't our Language betray us?</P>
<P>Do we know what Spirit we are of?</P>
<P>We all do impropriate the Name of <HI>Evangelici,</HI> Chri∣stians and Professors of the Gospel: but let us all take heed that we deal not with the Gospel as the <HI>Jews</HI> did with the Law, who carry'd it along with them in their <HI>Cloaths,</HI> but not in their <HI>Hearts;</HI> so we have it in out∣ward Profession, but express it poorly in Heart and Life.</P>
<P>How ridiculous is it for men to have Names and Ap∣pellations which they do not in the least answer! How absurd is it to be called <HI>Christians,</HI> and yet not to have the spiritual <HI>Anointment</HI> of Heavenly Graces upon us!</P>
<P>There are some, as <HI>Salvian</HI> expresses it, are <HI>Christians fine Christo.</HI> Our Names should be indicative of our Natures, otherwise thou art a Christian by an <HI>Anti∣phrasis.</HI> It is noted of the <HI>Roman</HI> Bishops, that they have been very ridiculous in their choice of Names at their Creation: A <HI>Coward</HI> would be called <HI>Leo;</HI> a <HI>Cruel</HI> one, <HI>Clemens,</HI> or <HI>Ʋrbanus;</HI> an <HI>Impious</HI> one, <HI>Pins;</HI> a <HI>Carnal</HI> one, <HI>Celestinus;</HI> a <HI>Loose</HI> one, <HI>Severus;</HI> a <HI>De∣formed</HI> one, <HI>Formosus;</HI> and a <HI>Devil, Eugenius.</HI> Let men either live as they are called, <HI>Christians;</HI> or be called as
<PB N="39" REF="21"/>
they live, <HI>Pagans.</HI> Art thou called a Believer? shew it by thy Faith. Art called a Saint? shew it by thy Holi∣ness. A Disciple? shew it by thy Knowledge. Are ye called Brethren? shew it by your Love, and shew your Love by your regard to this Precept of God's in my Text:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Col. 4.6.</NOTE> <HI>Let your Speech and Reproof be always with Grace, seasoned with Salt, that ye may know how ye ought to answer every man.</HI></P>
<P>Christianity of all Religions is the meekest and most humble; 'tis founded upon the Blood of Christ, who is <HI>a Lamb slain;</HI> 'tis consigned and sealed by the Spirit of Christ, who descended like a gall-less Dove; <HI>Our God is a God of Peace and Love,</HI> and will not be served with wrathful Affections.</P>
<P>Doth the God of Heaven need <HI>a Tongue set on fire of Hell? Have I need of Madmen,</HI> saith <HI>Achish?</HI> Will our Saviour always stand in need of <HI>Asses?</HI> I mean of such who are destitute of that Wisdom which is from above, which is characterized to be <HI>first pure, and then peaceable.</HI> There are some sorts of Men, whom we may <HI>bray in Mortar,</HI> and yet they have their retentive faculty, <HI>their folly will not depart from them.</HI> They still either <HI>slabber</HI> or <HI>foam</HI> at the mouth; they shall either <HI>flatter</HI> or <HI>rage.</HI></P>
<P>If I were addicted either to <HI>Invectives</HI> or <HI>Satyrs,</HI> I am sure I have here scope enough: But I will with∣draw my hand, lest I should seem to involve my self in the guilt of that Sin which this Discourse was prima∣rily design'd against.</P>
<P>I shall conclude with die last Branch of my Applica∣tion; which is,</P>
<GAP DESC="missing" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page missing〉"/>
<P><PB N="40" REF="22"/><HI>Fourthly,</HI> Exhortatory, and by way of Admo∣nition.</P>
<P>If thou must not refuse to afford thy helping hand to a <HI>fallen Beast,</HI> withdraw it not from a <HI>fallen Bro∣ther:</HI> Put on Bowels which are Humane, and highly improved by the Doctrine of Christ, who hath furnish∣ed us with Arguments beyond all contradiction, to enforce our Duty. If we love God or our selves, we must not hate our Brother. Whose Eye doth not weep, whose Heart doth not ake, to see the Misery of such a person, whom nothing cooler than unquenchable burnings, and nothing lighter than the heavy strokes of an incensed and Almighty hand, can make sensible of their sinful Omissions of this, nature?</P>
<P>We must all cry <HI>Guilty</HI> at our <HI>Arraignment</HI> and <HI>In∣dictment</HI> for our <HI>Copartnership</HI> with others in their Of∣fences: we have not prevented that Sin we have had fair Opportunities to crush in the very Egg. <HI>Jeroboam made Israel to sin:</HI> But how? He neither forbid them by <HI>Word,</HI> nor prevented them by <HI>Ex∣ample.</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gal. 2.14.</NOTE>It is said, St. <HI>Peter</HI> compelled the Gentiles to <HI>Ju∣daize.</HI> How did he so? Not by what he <HI>preached,</HI> but by what he <HI>practised:</HI> They sinned after the simi∣litude of their Spiritual Father's Transgression. How many <HI>Transgressors have we beheld,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 119.158.</NOTE> <HI>and</HI> never <HI>grieved because they kept not God's Word?</HI> Doubtless not to do Good, is to do Evil. We have Sins enough of our own to answer for. <HI>Our Father, died in his own sin,</HI> said <HI>Zelophehad's</HI> Daughters. Our own Sins are sufficient
<PB N="41" REF="22"/>
enough to our Ruine, we need not the <HI>additional aid</HI> other Mens; yet we every day call in for fresh Contributions to our own personal Transgressions, and no way more than this, by <HI>connivence</HI> at the Miscarri∣ages and Transgressions of others, to whom we are suffi∣ciently enough authorized to give check.</P>
<P>Be not therefore deterred from your Duty, because your habitual neglect of it has been of so long stand∣ing. You must force your selves against all presenting Difficulties; the Objections of your own <HI>Singula∣rity,</HI> and the reproved Sinners <HI>Obstinacy,</HI> must not be entertained, but repelled with all Christian Reso∣lution. I acknowledge it is no easie matter to bear a Reproof well, tho never so well administred. No Su∣gar can bereave a Pill of its natural bitterness; and it fares with Offenders, as with those who are awakened out of their sleep, they are unquiet, and ready to brawl at their best Friends. Dogs in a chase will sometimes bark at their own Masters. There are few like the Woman of <HI>Samaria,</HI> who lov'd <HI>Christ</HI> the better for finding her out in her sin. But remember, <HI>thy Lord will be ashamed of thee, if thou art of him;</HI> and who∣ever is ashame'd of his <HI>Commandments,</HI> is asham'd of his <HI>Lord</HI> that enacted them. If They can boldly <HI>sin,</HI> way should not We boldly <HI>reprove?</HI> Only Sin is truly shameful; and it is a very commendable importunity to sollicite men to be kind to themselves, and to <HI>di∣sturb</HI> them till they consult their own <HI>Everlasting Rest.</HI> For fear of offending thy <HI>Brother,</HI> wilt thou resolve to offend <HI>God?</HI> Whose displeasure is most to be dread∣ed, <HI>God</HI>'s or <HI>Man</HI>'s? Remember he is far from being
<PB N="42" REF="23"/>
impertinent, who will not suffer his Brother undistur∣bedly to go to Hell: He is far from being a busie-body, who engages himself to save his Brother who is on the brink of Ruine. To be employ'd where God calls, is sufficient Commission for any man to act upon. Do your Duty, leave the success to God, who is promi∣sed to bless his own Institutions. Resolve upon a spee∣dy complying with your Duty. Life is uncertain; <HI>He</HI> may die who <HI>wants</HI> our Reproof, <HI>We</HI> may die who are to <HI>give it,</HI> and so be out of the reach of our Cha∣rity: <HI>Our Mouths</HI> and <HI>Their Ears</HI> will in a short compass of time be stopp'd with <HI>Ashes.</HI> Do not there∣fore persist in the neglect of this Duty any longer. <HI>Omissions</HI> will damn as certainly as <HI>Commissions;</HI> and it is all one whether we go to Hell for <HI>one Sin</HI> or <HI>many.</HI> Be not therefore too thrifty of thy Tongue, when a word may do much good. We are not born all to ourselves, but somewhat to our Brother, Neighbour, and Friend; and we are guilty of the loss of that Soul we might save, and do not.</P>
<P>I am sure <HI>(with the Apostle)</HI> that <HI>He cannot love God whom he hath not seen, who loves not his Brother whom he hath seen,</HI> and can endure to <HI>see mise∣rable.</HI></P>
<P>In being thus Friends to <HI>others,</HI> we chiefly befriend <HI>our selves;</HI> and never let us think much of our pains, when we are rewarded with so great Blessings for our Work.</P>
<P><PB N="43" REF="23"/>Now <HI>God himself, and our Father,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Thes 3.11, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> <HI>and our Lord Jesus Christ, make you to increase and abound in love towards one another, and towards all men; to the end he may establish your hearts unblamable, in Holiness before God, even our Father, at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ with all his Saints.</HI> Amen.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

