<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The stumbling-block of disobedience &amp; rebellion cunningly imputed by P.H. unto Calvin, removed in a letter to the said P.H. from I.H.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Harrington, James, 1611-1677.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A45622</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H822</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R35985</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">15585336</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 15585336</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">103956</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A45622)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103956)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1150:4)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The stumbling-block of disobedience &amp; rebellion cunningly imputed by P.H. unto Calvin, removed in a letter to the said P.H. from I.H.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Harrington, James, 1611-1677.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>16 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for D. Pakeman ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1658.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Caption title.</NOTE><NOTE>Imprint from colophon.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</NOTE><NOTE>Includes bibliographical references.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Heylyn, Peter, 1600-1662. --  Stumbling-block of disobediance and rebellion cunningly laid by Calvin.</TERM><TERM>Politics in the Bible.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A45622">
<STC T="W">H822</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">15585336</BIBNO>
<VID>103956</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB N="1" REF="1"/>
<HEAD>THE
STUMBLING-BLOCK
OF
DISOBEDIENCE &amp; REBELLION
Cunningly imputed by P. H. unto
CALVIN, removed in a Letter to
the said P. H. from I. H.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q>Let no man put a Stumbling-block in his bro∣thers
way,</Q>
<BIBL>Rom. 14. 13.</BIBL>
</EPIGRAPH>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Gave my judgment upon your late book
(that I mean against <HI>Calvin</HI>) in such man∣ner
among some Gentlemen, that they de∣sired
me to write something in Answer to it,
which if there happen to be need I may;
In the mean time it will, perhaps, be enough if I acquaint
you with as much as I have acquainted them. In this
<PB N="2" REF="2"/>
book of yours you speak some things as a Polititian only,
others as a Polititian and a Divine too. Now to repeat a
few, and yet as many I think as are needful of each kind,
I shall begin with the former.</P>
<P>The Rise, Progress, and Period of the Common-wealth
of <HI>Lacedemon</HI> is observable in Authors by these
steps,</P>
<P>1. The Insufficiency of the Monarchy.</P>
<P>2. The Form of the Commonwealth.</P>
<P>3. An Infirmity in the Form, and a cure of it.</P>
<P>4. The Corruption aud Dissolution of the whole.</P>
<P>All which happened within the compasse of eight hun∣dred
years.</P>
<P><HI>To the first you say,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 39, 40, 41</NOTE> That the Spartan Kings were
as absolute Monarchs as any in those times, till <HI>Eurytion,</HI>
or <HI>Eurypon,</HI> to procure the favour and good will of the Ras∣call-rabble
(<HI>so you commonly call the people</HI>) purchased
nothing but the losse of Royalty, beside an empty name unto
his Family, thence called the <HI>Eurypontidae.</HI></P>
<P>It is true that <HI>Plutarch</HI> in the Life of <HI>Lycurgus</HI> sayes,
That <HI>Eurypon</HI> was the first, who to obtain favour with the
people, let loose the reins of Government, and
this he saith there without shewing any necessity that lay
upon the King so to do; nevertheless that such necessity
there was is apparent in <HI>Agis,</HI> where he affirmeth, That
a King of <HI>Lacedemon</HI> could never come to be equal unto
any other King, but only by introducing Equality among
the people; forasmuch as a servant or Lieutenant of <HI>Se∣leucus,</HI>
or <HI>Ptolomy,</HI> was worth more then ever were all the
Kings of <HI>Sparta</HI> put together. Which latter speech if a
man consider the narrowness of the Laconick Territory,
being but a part of <HI>Peloponnesus,</HI> must needs evince the
former action to have been not so voluntary in <HI>Eurypon,</HI>
as in prudence unavoidable. But <HI>Eurypon</HI> having by this
means rather confessed the infirmity of the Monarchy,
then introduced any cure of the Government, it remain∣ed
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
that the people not yet brought under fit Orders must
needs remain in disorderrs as they did till the institution of
the Commonwealth.</P>
<P>The Monarchy that is or can be absolute, must be
founded upon an Army planted by Military Colonys
upon the overballance of Land being in dominion of the
Prince; and in this case there can neither be a Nobility,
nor a People to gratifie, at least without shaking the
foundation, or disobliging the Army. Wherefore the
Spartan Kings having a Nobility or People to gratifie,
were not absolute. It is true, you call the Kings of
<HI>France</HI> absolute, so do others, but it is known that in
the whole world there is not a Nobility nor a People so
frequently flying out or taking Armes against their Prin∣ces
as the Nobility and People of <HI>France.</HI></P>
<P>The Monarch that is founded upon a Nobility, or a
Nobility and the people (as by the rise and progresse of
the Norman line in our story is apparently necessary)
must gratifie the Nobility or the Nobility and the people
with such Laws and liberties as are fit for them, or the
government (as we have known by Experience, is found
in <HI>France,</HI> and no doubt was seen by <HI>Eurypon</HI>) becom∣eth
Tyrannical, be the Prince otherwise never so good a
Man.</P>
<P>Thus <HI>Carilaus</HI> in whose Reigne the Commonwealth
was instituted by <HI>Lycurgus,</HI> is generally affirmed to have
been a good man, and yet said by <HI>Aristotle</HI> to have been
a Tyrant; it remaineth therefore with you to shew how a
good man can otherwise be a Tyrant then by holding Mo∣narchical
government without a sufficient balance, or if
you please, how he that shall undertake the like, (be he ne∣ver
so good or well deserving a man) can be any other;
Or confesse that not the favour of Princes (by which if
they be well balanced they lose nothing) nor the usurpa∣tion
of the people (by which without a popular balance
they get nothing) but the infirmity of the Monarchy
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
caused the Common wealth of <HI>Lacedemon,</HI> And what
less is said by <HI>Plutarch,</HI> or thus rendred by your self;
<HI>Not the people only sent messages to</HI> Lycurgus <HI>for his coun∣sel,
but the Kings were as desirous he should return from
his travels,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">P. 41.</NOTE> <HI>in hope that his presence would bridle and re∣strain
the people; but</HI> Lycurgus <HI>applyed not himself unto
either, being resolv'd to frame both into one Common-Wealth.</HI></P>
<P><HI>To the form of this Common Wealth, you say,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">P. 43.</NOTE> That
whatever the Kings lost, the people got little by this altera∣tion,
being left out of all imployment in affairs of state,
and forced to yeild obedience unto Thirty Masters, whereas
before they had but two.</P>
<P>A strange affirmation seeing the Oracle conteyning
the model of <HI>Lacedemon</HI> is thus recorded by your Au∣thor,
<HI>When thou hast divided the people into Tribes and
linages, thou shalt establish the Senate, consisting with the
two Kings of thirty Senators, and assemble the people as
there shall be occasion, where the Senate shall propose and
dismiss the people without suffering them to debate.</HI> Now
who seeth not that the people having no right to debate,
must therefore have had the right to resolve, or else
were to be assembled for nothing? but the Ultimate re∣sult
is the soveraign power in every government. It is
true the Greek of the Oracle is obsolete, and abstruse,
but then it is not only interpreted by <HI>Plutarch</HI> in the
sense I have given, but by the Verses of the Poet <HI>Tyr∣teus,</HI>
which the Kings themselves, though they would
have made other use of, acknowledged unto the people
to be Authentick▪
<Q><L>They having of <HI>Apollo</HI> sought,</L>
<L>This Oracle from <HI>Delphos</HI> brought;</L>
<L>Vnto the Spartan Kings, among</L>
<L>The Senators, it doth belong</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="3"/>
To moderate in Royal Chairs,</L>
<L>And give their Votes in all Affairs;</L>
<L>And when they have proposed these,</L>
<L>The People chose what ere they please.</L></Q></P>
<P>Of many other Testimonies, I shall add no more
then one out of the <HI>Isocrates; I am not ignorant</HI> (saith
he, to the Areopagites) <HI>that the</HI> Lacedemonians <HI>flourish
for this cause especially, that their government is popu∣lar.</HI></P>
<P><HI>To the infirmity of this form, and the cure of it you
say;</HI> That the Royalty and power of the Kings being
thus impaired,<NOTE PLACE="marg">P. 45.</NOTE> the people absolutely discharged from hav∣ing
any hand at all in publick government, and the Autho∣rity
of the Senate growing every day more insolent and pre∣dominant
by reason that (<HI>albeit the Senators were elected
by the people</HI>) they had their places for term of life, the
Kings resolved upon a course of putting the people into such
a condition as might inable them to curb and controle the
Senators, to which end they ordained the Ephori, <HI>Magi∣strates
to be annually chosen out of the body of the peo∣ple.</HI></P>
<P>In which first you make that to be a practise of the
Kings against the Senate, which by your Author is plain
to have been a combination of the Kings, and the Se∣nate
against the people; for the people upon the inso∣lency
and predominancy of the Kings, and the Senate,
fell, as is in that case, the inevitable nature of them,
upon counsel how to defend themselves, and so assumed
the power of debate. Hereupon the Kings <HI>Theopompus</HI>
and <HI>Polidore</HI> would have added unto the tenor of the
Oracle, that if the people went about by debate to
change the propositions of the Senate, it should be law∣ful
for the Kings and the Senate to null the result of the
people; which practise if it had past, must have made the
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
Kings and the Senate altogether uncontrollable; where∣fore
the people incensed at it, <HI>put a bitt into the mouth
of the Senate, by the institution of the Ephori:</HI> This is
the clear sense of <HI>Plutarch,</HI> which he taketh out of <HI>Pla∣to,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">De Leg. 3.</NOTE>
who affirmeth the Ephorate to have been set up a∣gainst
the hereditary power of the Kings; with whom
agree both <HI>Aristotle</HI> and <HI>Cicero;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Pol. lib. 2.</NOTE> the former affirming
this Magistracy to contain the whole Common Wealth,
inasmuch as the people having obtained it, were quiet;
and the later that the Ephori in <HI>Lacedemon</HI> were so op∣posed
to the Kings,<NOTE PLACE="marg">De Leg 3<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></NOTE> as the Tribunes in Rome to the Con∣suls.
Now if other Authors attribute the institution of
the Ephori unto the Kings, and there be a story affirm∣ed
as well by <HI>Plutarch</HI> as others, that <HI>Theopompus</HI> hav∣ing
thus created the Ephori, and being told by his
Queen he had done that which would leave narrower
power to his children, answer'd well, that it would leave
that which would be narrower, but longer: This is nei∣ther
any Riddle nor kind of contradiction to the for∣mer
sense: Seeing, when we say that <HI>Henry</HI> the Third
instituted the Parliament to be assistant to him in his go∣vernment,
we no more doubt of that, then how it is to
be understood. Nor if his Queen had said as shee of
<HI>Lacedemon,</HI> and our King had made the like answer,
would that have alter'd any thing, or proved the wo∣man
to have been, (as you will have it) the better Pro∣phet,
seeing either Government lasted longer for either
reformation, nor came to alter, but through the altera∣tion
of the ballance, which was nothing to the womans
prophecy.</P>
<P>The ruine of this Ballance, and corruption of the
Common wealth, you wholly omit to the end, that
picking up your objections against the Government in
vigour, out of the rubbish and dissolution of it, you
may cast dust in mens eyes, or perswade them <HI>that the
Ephori trusting to the power and interest,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">P. 55.</NOTE> <HI>they had in the
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
Communalty, came to usurp upon the Kings, and to be Ty∣rants
as they are called by</HI> Plato <HI>and</HI> Aristotle, so you af∣firm.</P>
<P>But the truth is thus recorded by <HI>Plutarch</HI> in the life of
<HI>Agis.</HI> So soon as the <HI>Lacedemmoans</HI> having ruin'd
<HI>Athens,</HI> became full of gold and silver, the Common
wealth began to break; Nevertheless, the lots or divi∣sion
of lands made by <HI>Lycurgus</HI> yet remaining, the E∣quality
of the foundation held good, till <HI>Epitadeus</HI> an
ill-natur'd fellow became Ephore, and having a mind to
dis-inherit his son, got a Law to pass whereby any man
might dispose of his lot as he pleased: This by him pur∣sued
of meet malice to his son, was hurri'd on by the a∣varice
of others, whose riches came thus to eate the
people so cleerly out of their lands, that in a short time
there remained not above an hundred Freeholders in all
<HI>Sparta.</HI> This he shews to have been the rise of the O∣ligarchy:
The Oligarchy thus balanced totally exclu∣ded
the people, and murther'd <HI>Agis,</HI> the first King that
was ever put to death by the <HI>Ephori;</HI> and to these times
(about which <HI>Plato</HI> and <HI>Aristotle</HI> lived) relateth that
Tyranny, which they who (as was shewn) commended
the <HI>Ephorate</HI> in the Common wealth, now laid unto it
in <HI>Oligarchy:</HI> Thus have you fetcht arguments against
a Common wealth, that are nothing to it. Again,
whereas <HI>Agis</HI> and <HI>Cleomenes,</HI> by the restitution of the
lots of <HI>Lycurgus</HI> were assertors of popular power,
you insinuate them to have been assertors of <HI>Monarchy;</HI>
such is your play with humane Authors, or as a poli∣titian.
Now let us see, whether you have dealt any thing
better with Scripture, or been more careful as a Divine.
In order to this Discovery, I shall repeate that peice of
<HI>Calvin,</HI> which you <HI>call the stumbing block of disobedi∣ence.
Calvin</HI> having preached obedience to your good
approbation comes at length to this expression. <HI>But
still I must be understood of private persons; for if there be
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
now any popular officers ordained to moderate the licentious∣ness
of Kings (such as were the Ephori,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Calv. Inst. lib. c. 20. §. 31.</NOTE> <HI>set up of old a∣gainst
the Kings of</HI> Sparta, <HI>the Tribunes of the people a∣gainst
the Roman Consuls, and the</HI> Demarches <HI>against the
Athenian Senate, of which power perhaps as the world now
goes, the three estates are seized in each several Kingdom
when solemnly assembled) so far am I from hindring them
to put restraints upon the exorbitant power of Kings, as
their office binds them, that I conceive them rather to be
guilty of perfidious dissimulation, if they connive at Kings
when they play the Tyrants, or wantonly insult on the
people; in that so doing they betray the liberty of the sub∣ject,
of which they know themselves to be made Guardians
by Gods own ordinance.</HI></P>
<P>What <HI>Calvin</HI> sayes of the <HI>Athenian</HI> Demarches, they
having been Magistrates of another nature, is a mistake,
but such an one, as destroyes no other part of his as∣sertion,
the rest of the Parenthesis, or that which he saith
of the Ephori, and the Tribunes being confirmed as hath
been already shewn by <HI>Plato</HI> and <HI>Aristotle,</HI> by <HI>Cicero</HI>
and <HI>Plutarch.</HI> Wherefore of the Ephori and the Tri∣bunes
enough; now why the estates in a Gothick Mo∣del
should be of less power, no Polititian in the world
shall ever shew a reason; the estates are such by virtue
of their estates, that is of their over-ballance in domi∣nion,
you are then either speculatively to shew how the
over-ballance of dominion should not amount unto Em∣pire,
or practically that the over-ballance of dominion
hath not amounted unto Empire, and that in a quiet
Government, or it can be no otherwise in a quiet Go∣vernment,
then that the over-ballance of dominion
must amount unto Empire. This principle being now
sufficiently known, is the cause it may be why you chuse
in this place to speak rather like a Divine,<NOTE PLACE="marg">P. 290.</NOTE> as you suppose,
then a Polititian. For <HI>you would fain learn,</HI> you say, <HI>of</HI>
Calvin, <HI>in what part of the Word of God we shall find any
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>
such Authority given to such popular Magistrates, as he
tels us of.</HI></P>
<P>To which by the way I answer, That God founded
the Israelitish Government upon a popular balance,
that we find the people of Israel judging the tribe of
<HI>Benjamin,</HI> and by the Oracle of God, levying War a∣gainst
them, which are acts of Soveraign power, there∣fore
a popular ballance, even by the ordinance of God
himself expressed in Scripture,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Judg. 20▪</NOTE> amounted unto Em∣pire.</P>
<P>But you, when you have asked <HI>in what part of the
Word of God we shall find any such Authority given to popu∣lar
Magistrates;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">P. 290,</NOTE> answer, <HI>Not in the Old Testament you are
sure. For when</HI> Moses <HI>first ordained the Seventy Elders,
it was not to diminish any part of that power which was in∣vested
in him, but to ease himself of some part of the burthen
lying upon him,</HI> as you will have <HI>to appear plainly by the
18<SUP>th</SUP> of</HI> Exodus, <HI>where</HI> Moses <HI>upon the advice of</HI> Jethro
<HI>chose able men out of all Israel, and made them Rulers of
Thousands, Rulers of Hundreds, Rulers of Fifties, and
Rulers of Tens.</HI> Now I am sure that about this time the
number of the men of Israel was above six hundred thou∣sand,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Num. 1. 46.</NOTE>
and so any man may be sure that the elders thus
chosen (should we count but the Rulers of the thousands
only) must have come at the least to six hundred, where∣fore,
you cannot be sure that this makes any thing to the
election of the seventy elders.</P>
<P><HI>Well, but</HI> out of these <HI>(say you)</HI> God afterwards in the
Eleventh of Numbers, willed <HI>Moses</HI> to chuse the seventy
Elders.</P>
<P>You may do me a greater favour then you can sudden∣ly
imagine, to tell me really for what cause, or upon
what authority your speech is so positive, that God wil∣led
<HI>Moses</HI> to choose the seventy Elders out of those that
were chosen in the Eighteenth of <HI>Exodus;</HI> For whereas
<HI>Moses</HI> is willed to choose them out of such as he knew to
<PB N="10" REF="6"/>
be elders, such there were in honour among the people,
though not in power before the election of those ad∣vised
by <HI>Jethro,</HI> as appears. Ex. 3<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 16. &amp; 4. 29. But
had this been as you would have it, what is the necessity,
that because there lay an appeal unto <HI>Moses</HI> from those
in <HI>Exodus</HI> (that is from the <HI>Jethronian</HI> Elders, or Courts
which sat afterwards in the gates of the Temple, and
of every City,) therefore there must needs lye an ap∣peale
from the seventy Elders, or the <HI>Sanhedrim</HI> unto
<HI>Moses,</HI> especially while the whole stream of <HI>Jewish</HI>
writers or <HI>Talmudists,</HI> (who should have had some
knowledg in their own Common-Wealth) unanimously
affirms that there was no such thing? Whereupon to
the election of the former Elders,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Grotius ad Ex. 18. 21.</NOTE> saith <HI>Grotius, in the
place of these came the Judges in the gates, and in the
place of</HI> Moses <HI>the</HI> Sanhedrim. Nor need we go farther
than the Scripture, for the certainty of this assertion,
where the seventy are chosen not to stand under <HI>Moses,</HI>
but with him,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Num. 11.</NOTE> not to diminish his burthen, or bear it
under him, with an appeal in difficult cases to him, as
is expressed in the election of the <HI>Jethroinan</HI> Elders, but
to bear the burden with him, and without any mention
of such appeal. <HI>Moses</HI> before the election of the <HI>Je∣thronian</HI>
Judges had the whole burthen of Judicature lying
upon him, after their election, the burden of the ap∣peals
only, wherefore if the seventy Elders were indeed
instituted to bear the burthen with <HI>Moses,</HI> there thence∣forth
lay no appeal unto Moses, which is yet clearer in
this precept,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 17. 8.</NOTE> <HI>If there arise a matter of controversie within
thy gates,</HI> (which plainly is addrest to the <HI>Jethronian</HI>
Courts) <HI>too hard for thee in judgment, then shalt thou come
unto the Priest and the Levite</HI> (by which in the sense of
all Authors <HI>Jewish</HI> and Christian is understood the <HI>San∣hedrim),
or to the Judg that shall be in those dayes</HI> (the
Suffes or Dictator) <HI>and they shall shew thee the sentence of
Judgment;</HI> whence by the clear sense of Scripture,
<PB N="11" REF="6"/>
all matter of appeal in Israel, lay unto the <HI>Sanhedrim.</HI>
Your next Argument, that there must be <HI>nothing in all
this but easing the supreme Magistrate of some part of the
burthen, which was before too heavy for him,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">P. 292.</NOTE> <HI>without any
diminution, in the least respect of his power; is, that when
God had taken of the Spirit which was upon Moses, and
put it upon the seventy Elders, the Spirit yet rested upon</HI>
Moses <HI>in as full a measure as it did at first:</HI> I grant in a
fuller, for I believe his wisdom was the greater for this
diminution of his power, it being through the nature
of the ballance, apparently impossible that he could
be any more then a Prince in a Common-wealth; but
your argument can be of no force at all, unless you
will have him to have been less wise, for not assuming
soveraign power, where without confusion, it was alto∣gether
impossible he should have held it: A Pince in a
Common-wealth subsisteth by making himself, or be∣ing
made of use unto the free course of popular orders;
but a soveraign Lord can have no other subsistance or se∣curity,
then by cutting off or tearing up all roots, that
do naturally shoot or spring up into such branches. To
conclude, if the Congregation of the people, in law to
be made, had such power as was shewn, and in law, so
made, the ultimate appeal lay unto the <HI>Sanhedrim;</HI> why,
are not here two estates in this Common-wealth, each
by Gods own ordinance, and both plain in Scripture?
well, but when they came (you will say) to make unto
themselves Kings, what ever power they had formerly,
was now loft. This at best were but to dispute from the
folly of a people against an ordinance of God, for what
less is testified by himself in those words to <HI>Samuel,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 8. 7.</NOTE>
<HI>They have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me
that I should not raign over them.</HI> The Government of
the Senate and the people, is that only which is or can
be the government of lawes and not of men, and the
government of lawes▪ and not of men, is the govern∣ment
<PB N="12" REF="7"/>
of God and not of men:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Arist pol. 3. c.</NOTE> <HI>He that is for the go∣vernment
of lawes, is for the government of
God, and he that is for the government of a man,
is for the government of a beast.</HI> Kings, no question,
where the ballance is monarchical, are of divine right,
and if they be good the greatest blessings that the go∣vernment
so standing can be capable of; but the ballance
being popular, as in Israel, in the Grecian, in the <HI>Sici∣lian</HI>
Tyrannies, they are the direst curse that can befal
a nation. Nor are divines, who will alwayes have
them to be of divine right, to be hearkened to, seeing
they affirm that which is clean contrary to Scripture, for
in this case saith <HI>Hosea, They have set up Kings and not
by me, they have made Princes and I knew it not.</HI> Pha∣raoh
may impose the making of brick without the al∣lowance
of straw,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hos. 8. 4.</NOTE> but God never required of any man
or of any government, that they should live otherwise,
then according to their estates. It is true if a mans
want make him a servant; there are rules in Scripture
that injoyn him the duty of a servant: But shew me
the rule in Scripture that obligeth a man who can live
of himself unto the duty of a servant. Hath God less
regard unto a nation then to a man? Yet the peo∣ple
of Israel, continuing upon a popular Agrarian,
though God forwarned them, that by this means they
would make themselves servants, would needs have a
King;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hos. 13.</NOTE> whence saith the same Proph<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. <HI>O Israel, thou
hast destroyed thy self, but in me is thine help, I will be
thy King</HI> (which foretels the restitution of the Com∣mon-wealth,
for) <HI>where is any other that may save thee in
all thy cities? and thy Judges of whom thou saidst give me a
King and Princes. I gave thee a King in mine anger</HI> (that is
in <HI>Saul) and I took him away in my wrath</HI> (that is in the
captivity, so at least saith <HI>Rabbi B<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>chai,</HI> with whom agree
<HI>Nachmoni, Gerschome,</HI> and others. <HI>Kimchi,</HI> it is true, and
<HI>Maimonides</HI> are of op<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on, that the people making
a King, displeased God not in the matter, but in the
<PB N="13" REF="7"/>
form only, as if the root of a tree, the ballance of a
government, were form only and not matter: nor do
our divines yet, who are divided into like partys, see
more then the <HI>Rabbys.</HI> Both the Royalists and the
Common-wealthsmen of each sort, that is whether
divines or <HI>Talmudists</HI> appeal unto the letter of the law,
which the Royalists (as the Translators of our Bible) ren∣der
thus;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Deut. 17. 14.</NOTE> <HI>When thou shalt say</HI> (the Common-wealths∣men,
as <HI>Diodati</HI> thus, <HI>If thou come to say) I will set a
King over me, like all the nations that are about me, thou
shalt in any wise set him King over thee, whom the Lord
thy God shall choose.</HI> The one party will have the law
to be positive, the other contingent, and with a mark
of detestation upon it, for so where God speaketh of
his peoples doing any thing like <HI>the nations that were a∣bout
them</HI> it is every where else understood. But let
these (which are no nicities) be as you will; who seeth
not that to argue from this place, for the necessity of the
King,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Verse 9.</NOTE> is as if one from that foregoing should argue for
the necessity of the Judges. The words are these, <HI>Thou
shalt come unto the Priest and to the Levitè</HI> (which, as
was said, is to the <HI>Sanhedrim) and</HI> (that is or) <HI>to the Judg
that shall be in those dayes.</HI> Yet that the Judg not by a∣ny
necessity implyed in these words, but through the
meer folly of the people came to be set up in Israel, is
plain by <HI>Josephus,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Book 5. c. 2▪</NOTE> where he shews that the Israelites lay∣ing
by their Armes. And betaking themselves unto their
pleasures, while they did uot as God had commanded, root
out the Canaanites from among them, but suffered them
to dwell with them, suffered also the form of their Com∣mon-wealth
to be corrupted, and the Senate to be bro∣ken;
the Senators nor other solemn Magistrates being
elected as formerly; which both in word and fact is con∣firmed
also by the Scripture. In words, as where it is thus
written. <HI>When</HI> Josua <HI>had let the people go</HI> (that is, had
dismissed the Army, &amp; planted them upon their popular
<PB N="14" REF="8"/>
ballance) <HI>the children of Israel went every man unto his
inheritance to possess the land,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Judg. 26.</NOTE> <HI>and the people served the
Lord all the dayes of</HI> Josua, <HI>and all the dayes of the Elders
that out-lived</HI> Josua (that is, while the <HI>Sanhedrim</HI> con∣tinued
after him, but when the Elders hereof came to
dye, and the people elected them no successors) <HI>they did
evil in the sight of the Lord</HI> (and having broken their
civil orders, forsook also their religion, the government
whereof depended upon the <HI>Sanhedrim) and served Ba∣lim.</HI>
And for the matter of fact included in these
words, it farther appears, where <HI>Judah said unto</HI> Sime∣on
<HI>his brother come up with me into my Lot,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Indg. 1. 3.</NOTE> <HI>that we
may fight against the Cananites, and I likewise will go
with thee into thy lot; so</HI> Simeon <HI>went with him.</HI> By
which the tribes leaguing at their pleasure one with ano∣ther,
it is plain, that the <HI>Sanhedrim</HI> their common Liga∣ment
was broken: Now except a man shall say that this
neglect of Gods ordinance was according unto the law
of God,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Pacuvious apud Livium. lib. 23</NOTE> there is no disputing from that law to the necessi∣ty
of the judg, which happened through no other then this
exigence (<HI>quippe aut rex, quod abominandum, aut quod unuus
liberae civitatis consilium est, senatus habendus est</HI>) wherefore
the judg of Israel was not necessitated by the will of God,
but foreseen only by his Providence, not imposed by the
law, but provided by it as an expedient in case of necessi¦ty,
and if no more can be pleaded from the law, for the
judg against whom God never declared, much less is there
to be pleaded from the same for the King, against whom
he declared so often. There is nothing more clear nor
certain in Scripture, then that the Commonwealth of Isra∣el
was instituted by God, the judges and the Kings no o∣therwise
then through the imprudence and importunity of
the people. But you who have no better name for the peo∣ple
in a common-wealth, then the <HI>rascal rabble</HI> will
have Kings at a venture to be of divine right, and to
be absolute; whereas in truth if divine right be derived
<PB N="15" REF="8"/>
unto Kings from these of the <HI>Hebrews</HI> only, it is most
apparent that no absolute King can be of divine right:
for these Kings if they were such by the law alledged,
then by the same law they could neither multiply horses
nor wives, nor silver, nor gold, without which no King
can be absolute; but were <HI>to keep all the words of this
law and these statutes,</HI> and so by consequence were
regulated Monarchs;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Dan. 17.</NOTE> Nay, could of right enact no
law, but as those by <HI>David</HI> for the reduction of the
Ark, for the regulation of the Priests, for the election
of <HI>Solomon,</HI> which were made by the suffrage of the peo∣ple,
no otherwise then those under the Kings of Rome,
and ours under the late <HI>Monarchy.</HI> What then is at∣tributed
by <HI>Calvin</HI> unto popular Migistrates, that is
not confirmed by Scripture and reason? yet nothing
will serve your turn but to know what power there was
in the <HI>Sanhedrim,</HI> to control their Kings: to which I
answer, that both <HI>Skickardus</HI> and <HI>Grotius</HI> with the full
consent of the <HI>Talmudists</HI> have assured you, that in case
the King came <HI>to violate those lawes and statutes it
was in the power of the</HI> Sanhedrim, to bring him unto cor∣poral
punishment. Moreover it is shewn by the later out
of <HI>Josephus,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">De jure B. ac. p. Lib. 1. Cap. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></NOTE> that <HI>Hircanus,</HI> when he could not deliver <HI>He∣rod</HI>
from the <HI>Sanhedrim</HI> by power, did it by art: Nor is
your evasion so good as that of <HI>Hircanus,</HI> while you hav∣ing
nothing to say to the contrary, but that <HI>Herod</HI> when
he was questioned, was no King, shufle over the business
without taking any notice as to the point in controversy,
that <HI>Hireanus</HI> who could not save <HI>Herod</HI> from the questi∣on
was King.</P>
<P>The manner of the restitution of the <HI>Sanhedrim</HI> made
by <HI>Jehoshaphat</HI> plainly shews,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Chr. 19.</NOTE> that even under the Monar∣chy
the power of the <HI>Sanhedrim</HI> was coordinate with that
of the King, at least, such is the Judgment of the Jewish
writers, for saith <HI>Grotius,</HI> the King (as is rightly noted
by the <HI>Talmudists,</HI>) was not to judg in some cases,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ad Mat. 5.</NOTE> and
<PB N="16" REF="9"/>
to this the words of <HI>Zedekia</HI> seem to relate, where to
the <HI>Sanhedrim</HI> demanding the Prophet <HI>Jeremiah,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ier. 38. 5.</NOTE> he said
<HI>behold he is in your hands, for the King is not he that can
do any thing without you.</HI> Nor (except <HI>David</HI>) had ever
any King <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ssion or vote in this councel: to which soon
after he adds, that this court continued till <HI>Herod</HI> the
great, whose insolencie, when exalting it self more and
more against the law, the <HI>Senators</HI> had not in time as
they ought, suppressed by their power; God punish∣ed
them in such manner for the neglect of their duty,
that they came all to be put to death by <HI>Herod,</HI> except
<HI>Sameas</HI> only, whose foresight and frequent warning of
this or the like calamity they h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d as frequently con<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>em∣ned.
In which words <HI>Gr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tius</HI> following the unanimous
consent of the <HI>Talmudists</HI> (if they knew anything of their
own orders) expresly attributes the same power unto the
<HI>Sanhedrim,</HI> and chargeth them with the same duty in
Israel, that is attributed unto the three estates in a Go∣thick
Model, and charged upon these by <HI>Calvin.</HI></P>
<P>Thus that there never lay any appeal from the <HI>Sanhe∣drim,</HI>
unto <HI>Moses</HI> nor (except when the Jews were in cap∣tivity,
or under provincial government) to any other
Magistrate, as also that they had power upon their Kings,
being that your self say, <HI>Is the objection Paramount, and
which not answered,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 289.</NOTE> you confess that the three estates cox∣vened
in Parliament, or any other popular Magistrate
Calvin <HI>dreames of, notwithstanding <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> discontinuance; or
non usage on their parts, or any prescription alledged by
Kings to the contrary, may resume and exercise that Au∣thority
which God hath given them when ever they shall find
a fit time for it:</HI> And this letter sh<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wing plainly that
you have in no wise answered this objection; it re∣mains
that your whole book (even according to your
own acknowledgment,) is confuted by this Let∣ter.
Or if you be of another mind, I shall hope to
hear farther from you.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<PB REF="9"/>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed for <HI>D. P<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>keman,</HI> at the Rainbow in
Fleetstreet, 1658.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

