<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The last words of a dying penitent being an exact account of the passages, proceedings, and reasons on which was grounded the first suspicion of his being concerned in the bloody, inhumane murder of Dr. Clinch, on the 4th of January 1691, between the hours of nine and eleven, with a brief observation on what was sworn by most of the witnesses against him, for which he was executed on the 15th on April 1692 ... / written with his own hand after condemnation, Hen. Harrison.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Harrison, Henry, d. 1692.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A45670</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H892</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R3657</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12701991</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12701991</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">65954</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A45670)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65954)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 815:22)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The last words of a dying penitent being an exact account of the passages, proceedings, and reasons on which was grounded the first suspicion of his being concerned in the bloody, inhumane murder of Dr. Clinch, on the 4th of January 1691, between the hours of nine and eleven, with a brief observation on what was sworn by most of the witnesses against him, for which he was executed on the 15th on April 1692 ... / written with his own hand after condemnation, Hen. Harrison.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Harrison, Henry, d. 1692.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[1], 31 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed, and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1692.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Clench, Andrew, d. 1692.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2008-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A45670">
<STC T="W">H892</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12701991</BIBNO>
<VID>65954</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE LAST WORDS OF A <HI>Dying Penitent:</HI> BEING An Exact Account of the Passages, Proceedings, and Reasons on which was grounded the first Suspicion of his being concerned in the Bloody inhumane Murder of Dr. <HI>Clinch,</HI> on the 4th of <HI>January</HI> 1691. between the hours of Nine and Eleven: With a Brief Observation on what was Sworn by most of the Witnesses against him. For which he was Executed on the 15th of <HI>April</HI> 1692. The which he leaves to the World to Judg. Trusting as to his Innocency in this, and relying on God Almighties Pardon for all his manifold sins; in and through the Merits and Mediation of Jesus Christ he hopes to be saved.</P>
<Q>Jesus Christ came into the World to save sinners, of whom I am the chief,
<BIBL>1 Tim. 1.15.</BIBL></Q>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="statement of authenticity">
<P>Written with his own Hand after Condemnation. </P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>HEN. HARRISON.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="license">
<P>Licensed</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE><HI>April</HI> 16. 1692.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed, and are to be Sold by <HI>Randal Taylor</HI> near <HI>Stationers-Hall,</HI> 1692.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The People expect a Confession always at the time of any Mans Execution: Therefore at that hour when it shall please God to call me to it, that I may have nothing more to do than to recommend my Body and Soul to him that gave it, I have writ this, which has a little taken my thoughts from my Duty to God, for which I emplore his Pardon.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">I beg of the Reader to make no Nice Construction of my words, but to take the real honest meaning.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">I have writ this merely, and only for the satisfaction of my Relations, Friends and Acquaintance. I have not had time to digest it into Method, because Time is precious with me now.</HEAD>
<P>IN the first place I will give an Account of my first Acquaintance with that Gentlewoman Mrs. <HI>Vauwick,</HI> for whom the World believes I committed this bloody inhumane Murther, and for which I now suffer.</P>
<P>About two years ago I was brought acquainted with her, being a Widdow, by a Gentlewoman of my Acquain∣tance; and had not been above 2 or 3 times in her Com∣pany, till I was Arrested for 40 l. at that time I having got a Commission for Cornet in my Lord <HI>Danbies</HI> Regi∣ment; whereupon my Friend came to see me in Prison, and with her this Gentlewoman: I told them I was un∣done;
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
for I had but just got my Commission, and if my Lord should hear of it, I should lose it; and my Rela∣tions would never do any thing for me, who were able to furnish me with such a Sum as was fitting for that Post. Whereupon this Gentlewoman took pity of that my mis∣fortune, and trusting to my Honesty, became bound for that Debt, by means whereof I had my Liberty: But in a Months time the Regiment was quite off; and ever since I have been quite out of Employ. But after this I several times visited the Gentlewoman, and found her very Melancholy, I then not knowing any of her Con∣cerns; but at last prevail'd with her to tell me the occa∣sion, which was to this effect: (I will but hint just on the heads of those Matters that were her Ruin and my Death. I could have writ a whole Volume on this Sub∣ject, had it not been at this time, which is precious to me, and ought to be employed in nothing else, but in Prayers to Almighty God for the forgiveness of my sins, and to prepare me for my latter end; but I hope God will forgive me, because I write nothing but Truth, to the best of my knowledg.)</P>
<P>This Gentlewoman had left her 500 l. to be laid out in a Purchase for her self during Life, and afterwards for the use of her Children. This money lying for some time dead in Dr. <HI>Edisburies</HI> hands, one of the Masters of Chan∣cery, She applied her self to one Mr. <HI>Samuel Hartlib</HI> to find her out a Purchase for the said money. This <HI>Hart∣lib,</HI> as I was informed, was a Man formerly of very good business and Credit, but at that time was very poor and needy. He brought her acquainted with one Mr. <HI>Row,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Edwards,</HI> who were the sole Actors of a Pur∣chase of Houses in <HI>Buckingham-Court,</HI> tho there were se∣veral concerned, as Mr. <HI>Royor,</HI> Mr. <HI>Royley,</HI> Mr. <HI>Chambers,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Bayley,</HI> who had Mortgages of the said 2 Houses. But in short, the purchase was made, and Mr. <HI>Row</HI> got in
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
to be Trustee, by the help of his good Friends Mr. <HI>Hart∣lib</HI> and Mr. <HI>Edwards,</HI> and was confirmed so by a Decree in Chancery. Pray observe, that this 500 l. was all this poor Woman had in the World; and the Purchase was made for 550 l. for which fifty pounds one of the said two Houses was Mortgaged to the said Mr. <HI>Chambers</HI> at that very time: But pray note, that before the Purchase, she told Mr. <HI>Row,</HI> that she had taken up 50 <HI>l.</HI> in Houshold Goods, and owed some 15 or 20 l. more, and unless she could have an Hundred Pounds more out of her own money, (to pay off her Debts) she would not meddle with it: They promised her faithfully that she should have it at the Sealing of the Writings, at which time the money was to be paid for the said Purchase. But pray now observe, Here was the immediate Ruin to the poor Widdow, and also had been to her 4 small Children, if her Relations had not taken them when they were just a going to the Parish, and in the long run is my unhappy End, God forgive them.</P>
<P>At the time of receiving the money, her Trustee Mr. <HI>Row,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Edwards</HI> his Confederate, and Mr. <HI>Royley,</HI> and some others, being at a Tavern, they seemingly quarrelled amongst themselves, insomuch, that she thought they would have fought; but it was about di∣viding the money, which was over and above the real Value of the Purchase; and the poor Woman expecting still her Hundred Pounds according to the promise made her, she began to examine Mr. <HI>Row,</HI> on whom she relied, having put all she had in the World for her self and four Children to live upon, into his Trust, Where is my Hundred Pounds, that I may carry it home and pay my Debts? Whereupon Mr. <HI>Row</HI> said, Do you see Ma∣dam what Rogues these are? they have received the money this Morning; Hang them, Hang them, never trouble your self, as I am your Trustee, I'le serve you,
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
and indeed he has serv'd her, and me too, as you will find in the Sequel of this unhappy Paper. Says <HI>Row, Madam, I have Fifty Pounds in my Trunk which has not seen day this Seven Years, you shall have that to morrow; and my Credit can raise you Fifty or an Hundred Pound more in a day or two's time.</HI> This was about <HI>June</HI> or <HI>July</HI> 1690. but on what day I cannot tell, because I have not the Writings: But from the day of her paying the money, she could scarce ever see Mr. <HI>Row;</HI> but when she did, he made frivolous Excuses of paying away a great Sum of money, and such like; but that he was a raising money, which she should have this day, and the other day; but alas his Credit could not raise Five Pounds in the whole World at that time, as I was credibly informed; and as all persons that knew him do know to be true, he be∣ing at the same time either a Prisoner at large in the Kings Bench, or a Soldier in one of the Companies of Kings-Guards for his Protection. This is most certainly true, when the Widdow, and others of her Acquaintance informed me of the truth of this, she then intreated, and begg'd of me with Tears and Prayers, to assist her in this her deplorable Condition. I could not refuse it her, considering the great Obligation she had first laid on me: Therefore out of Gratitude I could do no less than help her. Now for what past after, I can affirm to be Truth of my own Knowledg: As I am a dying Man I will not say any thing but what is Truth, to the best of my knowledg. Now she being deluded by him and his Confederate Mr. <HI>Edwards,</HI> and she not having the Hun∣dred Pounds according to promise, out of her own money, she was presently ruined, lost her Credit with her Creditors, to whom she promised payment at that time when she made the Purchase, and so day after day, and week after week, as he promised her she should have it by his procurement, which he could not perform, by
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
reason of his base dealing in the World. At this time she had a House very well furnished in the City, and was forced to absent her House, and leave her Children and Servants only there; and she was forced day after day to take Goods out of her House, to dispose of to main∣tain her Children, and follow him up and down from Tavern to Tavern, in expectation of his raising her the Hundred Pounds, which she could not do her self, by reason the Estate in Law was in him: But now pray ob∣serve, the two Houses were sold her as well Tenanted then at 40 l. <HI>per annum</HI> each House, out of which there was 30 <HI>l. per annum</HI> Ground-Rent to be paid; but no sooner was the Purchase money paid, but the Tenants left the Houses, being only Tenants at Will; so that the Houses lay empty all this while, and the Ground-Rent and Kings Taxes running on, she was head and ears up in Debt; and no body would take the Houses, because Mr. <HI>Row</HI> was concerned: So that she was forced to quit her House she then lived in in the City, and live in one of her own Houses.</P>
<P>Now comes the dismal Story of the Hundred Pounds borrowed of Dr. <HI>Clinch,</HI> which was the occasion of her Ruine, and my unhappy Misfortune.</P>
<P><HI>Row</HI> not performing his promise of supplying her with the Hundred Pounds, she applied her self to Dr. <HI>Clinch,</HI> who was her very good Friend, and her Husbands before her. He furnished her with the money, and paid it ho∣nestly; but would not lend it, unless Mr. <HI>Row</HI> would joyn with her in a Lease or Mortgage of one of the two Houses, and be bound with her for the money, because she could make no Security her self; which he readily did, that he might the better defraud her. But at that time, Counsellor <HI>Fairbeard</HI> being out of Town at <HI>Tun∣bridge,</HI> the Dr. would do nothing till his return, only in the mean time he supplied her with 30 l. at three several
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
times, and paid it thus, 15 <HI>l.</HI> at one time, and 10 <HI>l.</HI> at another, and 5 <HI>l.</HI> at another; which Mr. <HI>Row</HI> received to redeem her Goods which she had pawned to supply her necessities. It is true, he did redeem some of her Goods, but she could not have any Account of the lay∣ing out of her money, till at last Mr. <HI>Fairbeard</HI> coming to Town, and the Writings were drawn by him, and afterwards sealed, and this was not till <HI>November</HI> fol∣lowing; the remainder of the money was paid by Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI>'s Order at Sir <HI>Francis Child</HI>'s Shop at <HI>Temple-Bar;</HI> but at the receiving of it, there a dispute arose betwixt Mr. <HI>Row</HI> and the Widdow, Mr. <HI>Row</HI> not permitting her to receive the money, unless he had 20 <HI>l.</HI> under pre∣tence, that there was so much due to him by a Bill he de∣livered her the Night before; which was a base, unrea∣sonable Bill; and withall, that there was Monies rather due to the Widdow from Mr. <HI>Row,</HI> upon a fair Account betwixt them; but nevertheless the Widdow said in my hearing, Mr. <HI>Row</HI> take ten or fifteen pounds, and let us go to the next Tavern, and take you one, and I will take another, to adjust the Accounts betwixt us: No said <HI>Row,</HI> Madam you shall not receive a penny, unless I have 20 <HI>l.</HI> and then I will meet you at the Tavern, which he then had: So she and I went to the Tavern, Mr. <HI>Row</HI> pro∣mised he would come to us to settle the Accounts, we stay'd two hours for him, and then he sent word, he had met with some persons about other business, and could not come, but would wait on her another time at her own House; but he never came at her, tho she sent for him several times, but kept out of the way, all her Concerns lying at Random; her hands being tyed so, that she could do nothing without him, as to the letting of the other House, and several other matters too tedious now to mention.</P>
<P>Now pray observe, That the Dr. at the time the Wri∣tings
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
were Sealed, or thereabouts, assigned over the same Security, or made some other Security, or Mortgage to <HI>Row</HI> of the said House; <HI>Row</HI> giving the Dr. Bond to see the Covenants performed in the Deeds made from Mr. <HI>Row</HI> (being Trustee) and the Widow, to Dr. <HI>Clinch;</HI> which Covenants were these, That the Dr. should be paid Quarterly 6 <HI>l.</HI> odd Money, and so continue till the Doctor's whole Money was paid, which would be in Five years time or thereabouts: Now pray also observe, That the last Money was but paid in <HI>November</HI> 1690, and the first quarterly Payment became due at Quarter-day next following. For the Dr. expected that quarterly Pay∣ment, from the time he had lent the first 30<HI>l.</HI> at 15<HI>l.</HI> one time, 10<HI>l.</HI> another, and 5<HI>l.</HI> another; as I first mentioned: Tho the Case is intricate, I would make it as plain as I can, that the Truth may be understood: For <HI>Row</HI> several times said he had done that which would puzzle 20 Law∣yers.</P>
<P>Observe, That Mr. <HI>Row</HI> made it his Business both to the Widows Relations, and other People concerned with her, that I had ruined her, and spent all she had, when as you may find by this, that all she had was but 500<HI>l.</HI> and it was every Penny of it paid away for the Purchase; and that she only had Forty One Pounds Fifteen Shillings, most of which, was paid away at the receiving of it, to some of her Creditors. And that for 3 Months I sup∣ported her and her Children, partly with my own Money, and by getting in Debts that were due to her, besides an endless Trouble I had in bringing Mr. <HI>Row</HI> to an Account, which is not yet done.</P>
<P>It is desired that her Relations will take notice, that at the time of the Purchase, and at the payment of the Mo∣ney, after Mr. <HI>Row</HI> got in to be Trustee, he got her to sign a Deed, particularly a Covenant in the Deed was to this or like effect, That after the Death of Mrs. <HI>Vauricke</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>
and her 4 Children, the Estate to come to him and his Heirs. Upon which I often used to say, That he designed to break the Widdows Heart, and Starve the Children, that the Estate might come to him and his Son.</P>
<P>Now <HI>Row</HI> being Trustee, and also having a Deed from the Dr. for which he was glad; he domineered and ranted about, saying, That he had Houses in <HI>Buckingham</HI> Court, and kept the poor Woman under, that she durst not do any thing, neither could she, by reason of his being Trustee, and also having that Deed from the Dr. But now I knowing the abuses done the poor Woman, and that she could never get him to come to any Account, she applied her self to me again to right her, if I could by any means: Upon which I went to Mr. <HI>Fairbeard</HI> and told him what had past; and that Mr. <HI>Row</HI> was an ill man; and that we could never get him to come to any Account, as he promised he would do in his hearing at Sir <HI>Francis Child's</HI> Shop, he being then present: Mr. <HI>Fair∣beard</HI> said he could not believe it, for Mr. <HI>Row</HI> was a man of Credit and Reputation; and as he told him, he was an Attorny of the Common-Pleas. I made answer, that he was no such man, but an Impostor and a Cheat: where∣upon he advised me to go to Mr. <HI>Cooke</HI> the Prothono∣tary at the Temple, and search whether he was an Attor∣ney of the Common-Pleas or no; and if he was not, I should take a Summons from my Lord Chief Justice, and he would come and justifie he own'd himself to be an Attorney of the Common-Pleas, and so by that means have him turned out from being Trustee: Now I finding him not to be so, I did take out a Summons from my Lord Chief Justice of the Common-Pleas, and Mr. <HI>Row</HI> meet∣ing me according to the Summons, desired me to let him alone, and he would come to an Account, and deliver up his Trust, and do any thing else I would have him; and this he promised before Mr. <HI>Hales</HI> of the Temple, an
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
Attorny of the Common Pleas; but for 3 weeks or a month after, we could neither see nor hear of him, till one came and informed us that he was to be a Witness in <HI>Westminster-Hall,</HI> and there we had a Summons from my Lord Chief Justice <HI>Holt,</HI> to appear before him; which was done: And being before my Lord, we had a small hearing of the Cause, as I may call it; for we had there Mr. <HI>Lloyd</HI> of the Temple our Counsel, and my Lord hear∣ing what was alledged against him, told him, that he was an ill man, and said thus to <HI>Row, You are a fine Fellow to be a Trustee.</HI> My Lord finding that he was a Trustee made in Chancery, advised us to make an end, and spoke thus to Mr. <HI>Lloyd, As you are her Counsel, let Mr.</HI> Row <HI> take another, and make an end; for the poor Woman will be ru∣ined,</HI> or to this effect. Mr. <HI>Row</HI> readily answer'd he would, and that he would bring Mr. <HI>H.</HI> (any one may judge the meaning of that.)</P>
<P>The time and place being appointed, Mr. <HI>Lloyd,</HI> the Widow, and my self, went there, where we met Mr. <HI>Row,</HI> and 2 or 3 Fellows of his Gang, but no Mr. <HI>H.</HI> was there; Mr. <HI>Row</HI> said, what should I have Counsel, I can do my business my self; Mr. <HI>Lloyd</HI> told him, he was not to ar∣gue the Case with him but Mr. <HI>H.</HI> and they two were to make an end, if they could agree; whereupon Mr. <HI>Lloyd</HI> was angry with him, and went away: So that he was then upon the Hide and Seek again, putting us every day to great Expences; for he did not care to part with his Trusteeship: And for us to come to my Lord Chief Ju∣stice again, would put the Widow to more Charges, and that my Lord could do nothing in it, because he was a Trustee in Chancery.</P>
<P>Now what to do we could not tell, but we then peti∣tioned the Lords Commissioners, and Mr. Serjeant <HI>Tre∣mayne</HI> our Counsel: Upon hearing what was alledged against the said Mr. <HI>Row,</HI> the Lord Commissioner <HI>Raw∣linson</HI>
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
said, it was the most barbarous Case he ever heard. Pray note, That <HI>Row</HI> was to appear that day but durst not; knowing the Villany that he had committed, where∣upon by an Order of Court, a Messenger was ordered to take <HI>Mr. Row</HI> into Custody; (the Petition and Orders ought to be inserted here, but that my little time I have to live ought to be otherwise employed.) Now after the Messenger was awarded against him, he absconded himself from his Dwelling-house, and all other places he then used; so that the Messenger of the Chancery <HI>Mr. Bush,</HI> and my self, daily hunting after him for near the space of a month, but could not take him. Pray observe here, that this was in <HI>April</HI> 1691. and also observe, that from <HI>Christmas</HI> before till that time, <HI>Mr. Row</HI> daily and hourly threatned to seise her Goods, and take possession; and she did leave her House for fear of it, for some little time, expecting to be relieved by the Lords Commissioners, but she left her Children and Maid in possession: Now <HI>Row</HI> by force entred, without any manner of Law; for he turned the Children out of Doors, and sold the Bed from under them, and took the rest of the Goods that were in the House. Now is the time that Dr. <HI>Clinch's</HI> Name comes to be mentioned, and I beg of you observe, I will make it as clear as I can, and speak nothing but the Truth to the best of my Knowledg, and as I hope to see God in Glory. Now when <HI>Mr. Row</HI> had turned the poor Fatherless Children out of Doors, &amp;c. Then the Widow applied her self to the Dr. and told him what had past, and wondered why he would not keep the Se∣curity in his own hands, but make it over to <HI>Row:</HI> Said she to the Dr. I dare trust you with all I have in the World. I am now using endeavours to get <HI>Row</HI> turned out of his Trusteeship, and bring him to an Account for the money he owes me, and the Goods he has wronged me of; for he twice robbed the House of the Locks, Keys
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
and Bolts, under pretence of his being Trustee. I hope no body can call it any thing else but Robbery, when she owed him nothing, but he was in her Debt 50 l. or thereabouts, and she could not take the Law of him, because he was her Trustee. So that the Widow solicited the Dr. several times with a great many Prayers and Sup∣plications, to stand her Friend till such time as he was righted in Chancery.</P>
<P>And now was the time that <HI>Row</HI> applied himself to the Dr. and insinuated himself so far into the Doctors favour as to make him believe that it was all false; and that he was the wronged man, and that she owed him a great deal of moneys, and withall told him, that it was not he that had ruined the Widow and Fatherless, but one <HI>Mr. Harrison,</HI> who was a Gamester, and spent and play'd away all her money; and so <HI>Mr. Row</HI> and his Agents made it their business to make him believe so, and every one else that was concerned, but more particularly her Re∣lations, fearing lest they should undertake her just Cause, being monied People, and persons of great Note and Credit; and he did effect his design, for from that time till now her Relations would not look upon her, nor hear any thing of her, because he had so bespattered her concerning me.</P>
<P>Now was the time I told her, that I would use my en∣deavours and interest with the Dr. who was my very good Friend, and for several years had known him; for he had been my Physitian; and many times when he saw me, told me he would come Day or Night to serve me, if I had need for him. Nay further than that, at the time the Duke of <HI>Norfolks</HI> Regiment was to be raised, he told me, if I would have a Commission in that Regiment, he had that Interest with the Duke, that he believed he could do any thing with him; but I told him I was engaged to a Person of Quality already. Now let the Reader
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
judge, whether or no I had any reason to injure the Dr. or much more to Murder him. Now was the time also I solicited the Dr. upon the Widows Account, who al∣ways shewed me Civility and Respect, and never an An∣gry word past betwixt us. And also about this time the Dr. imploy'd one <HI>Mr. Johnson</HI> of <HI>Furnivals-Inn,</HI> to look after the business: Says the Dr. <HI>Mr. Harrison,</HI> I do not under∣stand the Law, and besides that, I have a great deal of business otherwise, I cannot trouble my self; but I have left it all to <HI>Mr. Johnson:</HI> Upon this, I told the Widow what the Dr. had done, That he had left it all to one <HI>Mr. Johnson;</HI> whereupon she replied, That she was got out of the Frying-pan into the Fire, for her Relations knew who he was; but I was altogether a Stranger to <HI>Mr. Johnson.</HI> Now pray observe, that at that time all our Applications to the Dr. or <HI>Mr. Johnson,</HI> was to let her have a little more money, till she had made an end in Chancery, and got <HI>Row</HI> out from his Trusteeship; for she intended to undertake some Imploy to maintain her self and Children, and that the Dr. should have possessi∣on of both the Houses for his Security; and we would endeavour to get a Decree in Chancery for that purpose. The Dr. and I many times argued the Case, and once or twice, computed the In-come of the Estate, and what might be lent upon it: The Dr. was sensible of the Wrongs done the Widow, and would have helped her in any thing, if Mr. <HI>Johnson</HI> had not prevented him. Now you must understand the Widow could do nothing to help her self as to raising of Mony, for these 2 Reasons: First, Because <HI>Row</HI> was Trustee, and not then turned out, nor is yet; as you will understand by the Sequel of the Story: So now to come back to Mr. <HI>Row,</HI> where I men∣tioned him as to his absconding himself; that the Mes∣senger could not take him, whereas by an other Order, made the Twenty Sixth day of <HI>May,</HI> 1691. It was or∣dered
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
one Mr. <HI>Royor</HI> and <HI>Royley,</HI> Mr. <HI>Edwards</HI> and Dr. <HI>Clinch,</HI> were to attend Sir <HI>John Hoskyns,</HI> about the Mat∣ters in question; for you must know, that we had the wole Business on the Stage, as to all the Persons concern∣ed in putting that Purchase upon her, and by what de∣vices and means <HI>Mr. Row</HI> got in to be Trustee. Now this was the time that Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI> first began to be displeased, and so was <HI>Mr. Fairbeard</HI> his Counsel, and <HI>Mr. Johnson,</HI> for bringing his, Name in question, where so black a Case appeared to the Lords Commissioners, on <HI>Row</HI>'s Account, saying, <HI>Have not I lent my Mony, and paid it honestly?</HI> Yes, Sir, I know it; but <HI>Row</HI> received the most of it, and the Widow cannot get an Account of it; and it was by our Counsel's Advice that we did it; for by the Dr's appearing before the Mr. in Chancery, all was made clear, how Mr. <HI>Row</HI> and his Confederates were the Persons that had ruined the Widow and her Children, as by the Re∣port does appear, which ought to be inserted here. But no more of that. I hope now her Relations will have pity of her disconsolate condition, being the most wrong∣ed Widow in the World, to whom I have ordered the Papers of the Proceedings of her Cause to be carefully delivered. Only thus much of the Report made by Sir <HI>John Hoskyns,</HI> which I shewed my Lord Chief Justice at my Tryal. But he told me, it would signifie nothing to my Tryal; which is thus <HI>verbatim.</HI> And as for Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI> his matter, I find that the said Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI> was desired by the said <HI>Mrs Vauwick</HI> and <HI>Mr. Row,</HI> presently after the said Purchase of the said 2 Houses, to lend the said Mrs. <HI>Vauwick</HI> an Hundred Pound to furnish one of the said Houses; and there being a Debt of 14 <HI>l.</HI> that was due to Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI> from the said Mrs. <HI>Vauwick</HI>'s late Husband Deceased, and about 3 <HI>l.</HI> 17 <HI>s.</HI> for Interest thereof, the said Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI> did lend the said Mrs. <HI>Vauwick</HI> Two Gui∣neas more, which made it up Twenty Pounds; and the
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
said Mrs. <HI>Vauwick</HI> secured the said Twenty Pounds by her Bond; and the said Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI> at their, the said <HI>Row</HI> and <HI>Vauwick</HI>'s Desire, did undertake to lend it, upon his be∣ing secured the said 100 <HI>l.</HI> and the said 20 <HI>l.</HI> in all 120 <HI>l.</HI> by a Mortgage of one of the said Two Houses, to be paid at times in the Deeds for that purpose mentioned, the which 100 <HI>l.</HI> I find was paid, and disposed, and re∣ceived thus, 41 <HI>l.</HI> 15 <HI>s.</HI> to the said Mrs. <HI>Vauwick,</HI> 5 <HI>l.</HI> to Mr. <HI>Fairbeard</HI> and his Clerk for Writings, 3 <HI>l.</HI> for the ensuring Mrs. <HI>Vauwick</HI>'s Life, and 50 <HI>l.</HI> 5 <HI>s.</HI> to the said Mr. <HI>Row</HI> for the use of Mrs <HI>Vauwick.</HI></P>
<P>Now we having got this Report, all our business was done with Dr. <HI>Clinch,</HI> and this Report was Signed, <HI>8th of August</HI> 1691. by Sir <HI>John Hoskyns.</HI> By this Report it appears, who wronged the Widow, as you will find also by a Petition here inserted, upon which the Widow was to have an Hearing. The Petition was thus <HI>ver∣batim.</HI></P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="petition">
<HEAD>To the Right Honourable the Lords Commissi∣oners of the Great Seal of <HI>England,</HI> the Hum∣ble Petition of <HI>Anna Katherina Vauwick,</HI> and her 4 small Children, sheweth,</HEAD>
<P>THat your Petitioner has been basely defrauded of all she has by <HI>Robert Row,</HI> a pretended Attorney of the <HI>Common Pleas;</HI> and that your Petitioner being advised by the Lord Chief Justice <HI>Holt</HI> to petition your Lordships, provi∣ded he did not come to an Account, and pay your Petitioner the Monies he so unjustly detained from her, upon pretence of being her Trustee: And the said <HI>Row</HI> failing his Pro∣mise to the said Lord Chief Justice, your Petitioner petitioned your Lordships accordingly about 4 Months ago; and upon hearing what was alledged by Mr. Serjeant <HI>Tremaine,</HI> your Petitioners then Counsel, your Lordships thought it a very
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>
hard Case, and were pleased to order a Messenger to take him into Custody. But he absconding himself for the space of a Month, your Lordships were pleased to refer the matter to Sir <HI>John Hoskyns,</HI> to examin the same, which he hath done. But by reason of the many Delays of the said <HI>Row,</HI> your Petitioners having no Support, but what Friends has given them out of Charity, she having pawned and sold all her Goods and Wearing Apparel for Sustenance for her Children, and in bringing the said <HI>Row</HI> to an Account, that your Petitioner and her Children are ready to starve, and that for this Month last past they have scarce eat or drunk any thing but Bread and Water.</P>
<P REND="indent"><HI>Your Petitioner therefore humbly prays in tender Commiseration to your Petitioner and her Childrens Sufferings, to appoint a Day for the said</HI> Row <HI>to At∣tend, and that the Masters report by your Lordships particular Order may then be heard; and that your Petitioner and her Children may have such present Relief from the said</HI> Row, <HI>as to your Lordships great Wisdom shall seem meet. Amd your Petiti∣oner shall ever Pray.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>Now this Petition for a Hearing before the Lord's Commissioners was delivered to the Clerk of the Petiti∣ons about a Week or Ten Days before <HI>Michaelmas</HI> Term last, but not having Mony, it was not Signed; and within few days after the Widow was Arrested by one <HI>Taylor</HI> an Upholsterer, who is an Acquaintance of Mr. <HI>Row</HI>'s; but whether by the contrivance of <HI>Row</HI> or no, I dare not say, tho we suspected it, he dreading what would become of him when such a barbarous Case should be laid open. Now pray observe, that the Wi∣dow was Arrested about Two Months, or thereabouts, before the Dr. was murdered, and not at his Suit. Pray take notice, and withal observe the part of the Report
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>
inserted here, relating to Dr. <HI>Clinch,</HI> and also the Petiti∣on, and likewise who it is that was in the wrong, and who had ruined the Widow, whether Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI> or <HI>Row.</HI> And now to whom any Malice or Revenge ought to be done, whether to the Doctor, who had honestly paid the Mony, or to <HI>Row,</HI> who had not only, with his Con∣federates, (the Persons formerly mentioned) cheated her above an Hundred Pounds in the Purchase, and also 2 Quarters Rents, as the rest of the Report makes out, and also as you find by the Report here, 50 <HI>l.</HI> 5 <HI>s.</HI></P>
<P>Now she being Arrested, and in the Compter Two Months before the Drs. Death, and not at his Suit, let all the World judge, whether or no the Dr. was murder∣ed upon her Account or no. And I do protest in the Presence of Almighty God, and as I hope for Salvation, I had not spoken to the Dr. in 3 Months time before his Death, the last time being at his own House, to my best remembrance. And Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI>'s own Coachman owned to me, That he believed it was about 3 Months. And pray let the Reader consider, that there was no Advan∣tage could be had, and that it would be nothing in the Widows way, if it had pleased God that Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI> had died in his Bed. And also observe, that the Widow had not Five Shillings at that time, nor could not tell where to get one Guinea in the World, if it could have procu∣red her Liberty: For at that time her Acquaintance were making a Purse for her, to bring her <HI>Habeas Cor∣pus;</HI> for the Marshal told me, he would take my Word for her Liberty: Therefore you must know by this she had no Mony to give me to hire a Ruffian. Now it plea∣sed God that Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI> was most barbarously murdered, on the <HI>4th</HI> of <HI>January,</HI> betwixt 9 and 11 at Night. I need not mention the manner, because 'tis too well known. Now it being such a barbarous black Deed, startled all the Town. It seems, before the next Night it was
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
given out that Mr. <HI>Row</HI> and my Self knew the 2 Ruffians that committed this Fact; but the next Day after it was done, being <HI>Tuesday,</HI> it was 2 a Clock before I heard of it, which was at <HI>Joe</HI>'s Coffee House going into <HI>Salisbury</HI>-Court, where I was told of the Murther, and the man∣mer of it, as they heard it was done: I remember very well what I said, These were the boldest daring Villains I ever heard of; What, to Murther a Man in the open Streets, and at that time of the Night, and carry him through the City in a Coach when all the Watch was set? And I do remember that I took Pen and Ink, and writ a Letter to the Widow in the <HI>Compter,</HI> which was to this or the like Effect: <HI>Madam, I just now have heard of the blackest inhuman Murther that ever was known; but before this I suppose you have heard of it, because it is all over the Town, if not, it's thus: Doctor</HI> Clinch <HI>was last Night barbarously Murthered in a Coach in</HI> Leaden Hall-<HI>street.</HI> And so writ, as I heard how it was done, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> The same Night I was at one <HI>Clinch</HI>'s Coffee-House in <HI>Mitre</HI>-Court, where every one was talking of it, for it was a general Discourse. The same Night I was to see for a Gentleman there who ow'd me Mony, and he came in whilst I was there, and told me, that he had received a Bill out of the Country, and desired me to meet him at the <HI>Sugar-Loaf</HI> in <HI>White Fryers,</HI> and dine with him the next Day; which Words were spoke publickly. Upon which, I suppose, the Constable was directed; for the next Day I came there, and enquired for the Gentleman, and they told me he was at <HI>Clinch</HI>'s Coffee-House; and going there, I met the Constable, who as soon as he saw me, said thus, or to the like Effect; Mr. <HI>Harrison,</HI> I am sorry to meet with you, I have my Lord Chief Justice's Warrant against you: For what? said I. Go to the <HI>Sugar-Loaf</HI> and I'll tell you, said he; yes, with all my Heart. When we came there, several of Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI>'s Friends
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>
were there; what past is not material: So they carried me to the Constable's House in <HI>Grays-Inn-Lane,</HI> where we staid about 2 Hours, because my Lord was busie there: We discoursed about Mr. <HI>Row,</HI> and the Business on which I have writ before, and I told them, I had not seen Mr. <HI>Row</HI> this long time, nor the Dr. to my Knowledg, for <HI>Row</HI> and I were perfect Enemies, not knowing then he was suspected to be one with me; but being brought before my Lord, <HI>Row</HI> was there; and he brought Witnesses where he was, and Bail with him: But now pray observe my failing, I being surprized, be∣ing examin'd w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere I was, I told my Lord; That I was at such a Place fhrom 7 or 8 or thereabouts, till 11 or thereabouts; but not having the Persons there to justifie it, I was sent to <HI>Newgate,</HI> and <HI>Row</HI> Bailed. Now pray observe, that Mr. <HI>Row</HI> and my self were suspected then to be the 2 persons; now I being committed, and a scandalous Libel coming out the next Day, made all the World believe I was the Man that committed it. I was almost Distracted, and I thank God that he did not give me over to Despair; but at last I was a little setled in my Mind, and began to consider, That it was for my Sins, my former Sins, he suffer'd this Judgment to come upon me, and I became calm and considered, and did, and ever since have, blessed be his Holy Name for this his Fatherly Chastisement; and he has ever since given me Patience under all my Sufferings, and supported me un∣der all my Afflictions till this time; and I trust and firm∣ly believe, he will not forsake me at the Hour of my Death. After a day or two being in Prison, I sent for the People of the House where I was, and desired them to recollect themselves what time I came there, and how long I staid there; and sent to those Persons that were in Company, to know certainly the time, for they were all partly Strangers to me: I had an Account given
<PB N="19" REF="11"/>
me, for I could not recollect every thing my self; but you will understand in my Case following: And when my Witnesses had given me the satisfaction, the Sessions coming on about 10 days after, I had all my Witnesses there, and Petitioned for my Tryal; but was put off, because the Coroner had not brought in his Inquest. Now pray observe, that the Coroner had been with me, and took my Examination, before that Sessions; and promised me he would let me have two days notice of my Tryal; but he did not: So that I tired my Friends with wait∣ing, and my Witnesses being Strangers, that Expence was all lost. Now knowing my Innocency, and believ∣ing that the Prosecutors desired nothing more than to find out the Truth, I frankly sent them a Copy of my Case, and also another to the Coroner; the doing of which was my ruin: And I told my Lord the same at my Tryal; and he made Answer, "I was to blame in that: And thus it was <HI>Verbatim.</HI></P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="account of defence">
<HEAD>An Exact Account of the just Defence I made concerning my Innocency, touching the Inhuman Murther of Dr. <HI>Clinch,</HI> on the <HI>4th</HI> of this Instant <HI>Janu∣ary,</HI> betwixt <HI>9</HI> and <HI>11</HI> a Clock.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>My first Proof.</HEAD>
<P>MR. <HI>Jones</HI> my Landlord, and Landlady, and the Maid, with one <HI>Turner</HI> a Porter, plying at <HI>Shooe-Lane</HI> end in <HI>Fleet-street,</HI> who carried my Port-Mantle-Trunk at or near 8 a Clock on that Night, to my Lodg∣ings, at the <HI>Golden Ball</HI> in <HI>Paul</HI>'s Church-yard; and af∣ter I had given Orders for a Fire to be light, I went from thence, and told them, I would be at home again betwixt a 11 and 12.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>My second Proof.</HEAD>
<P>That betwixt 8 and 9 a Clock the same Night, I
<PB N="20" REF="12"/>
came from my said Lodgings, and went along <HI>Fleet-street,</HI> to the <HI>King's Head</HI> in <HI>Crown Court</HI> in <HI>Chancery Lane,</HI> over against <HI>Serjeant</HI>'s <HI>Inn,</HI> where I play'd at Cards, from 9 a Clock or thereabouts, till 11 a Clock or thereabouts, the same Night; to prove this, the Master of the <HI>King's Head,</HI> his Wife and Maid, one Mr. <HI>Baker</HI> an Ironmonger, Mrs. <HI>Whiple</HI> a Cornet's Wife, one Mr. <HI>White</HI> and his Wife.</P>
<P>To Confirm the Testimonies of these Persons, during the time we play'd at Cards, these two Accidents fell out; at 10 a Clock or thereabouts, a Hubbub arose in the said Court, about the Pumping a Woman that had pickt a Gentleman's Pocket: The other was about a quarter of an Hour after, That one <HI>John Allan,</HI> a Drawer at the <HI>King's Head</HI> Tavern at the end of <HI>Chancery Lane,</HI> came to the <HI>King's Head</HI> in <HI>Crown Court;</HI> he being somewhat Impertinent and Sawcy, as I thought, I rose from my Seat, went to the Door, and struck at him with my Muff; which the Drawer remembers.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>My third Proof.</HEAD>
<P>That Mr. <HI>White</HI> came to call his Wife home about half an Hour past ten a Clock, and found me at Cards with the said Company.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>My fourth Proof.</HEAD>
<P>That at my return home from that Place, at 11 a Clock or thereabouts, to my Lodging<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, one Mr. <HI>Sutton</HI> and one Mr. <HI>Russel,</HI> Gent. of my Acquaintance was in a Coach, at the <HI>King's Head</HI> Ta∣vern door at the end of <HI>Chancery Lane,</HI> drinking a Glass of Sack; They told me, They were going to the <HI>Horse-Shooe</HI> Tavern in <HI>Drury Lane,</HI> and desired me to go along with them; and I did go into the Coach to them: But I considering that it was too late, presently came out of the Coach again, and so walk'd all along <HI>Fleet street,</HI> home to my Lodgings in
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>
<HI>Paul</HI>'s Church-yard, and was at home at half an Hour past 11 a Clock, or thereabouts,</P>
<P>Pray observe, that I came from Mr. <HI>Humpstead</HI>'s Lodg∣ings before the Port-Mantle-Trunk was carried to my Lodgings, which he swore at 9 a Clock, when it was before 8 I was with him; which has given all the Sus∣picion.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>Now let any one judge, whether it looks like as if I were guilty, to give my Adversaries an Account of my Witnesses, and what they could testifie for me: But my Design in this, was That when they had found what I said to be true, I was in hopes they would have suffer'd me to Bail: But instead of that it turned to my ruin; for Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI>'s Coach man went to them, and abused them all, and every Body else that took my part; but however the second Sessions coming on, all my friends and Wit∣nesses attended two Days in hopes of my Tryal; my Wit∣nesses being in the same House where theirs was, and they seeing me so well provided, my Tryal was put off till the third Sessions, upon pretence that they had disco∣vered something more. Now I being in Prison, and with∣out Mony, and had given them all this trouble, and waiting two Sessions, all the time of the Sessions, they were very uneasie; besides being abused by Dr. <HI>Clinch</HI>'s Coach∣man, they would not trouble themselves any more. But this I had forgot, that most of them denied coming, be∣cause they said they should be abused and vilified, be∣cause the Murther was so black that was laid to my Charge. Whereupon I was forced to Petition the Lord Chief Justice for <HI>Subpoenas,</HI> which was granted me, which was both a great Charge and Trouble, I being confined, that I could not look after it my self; tho' I was promi∣sed, I should either be Tryed or Balled; but instead of that I was more strictly confined. Now From the last
<PB N="22" REF="13"/>
Sessions till this, my Enemies were at work how to bring their Designs about; the first thing I heard was, That there was a Boy made away, and, as it was reported, by my Contrivance; and then he was put in the Gazette; but not being found out, at my Tryal his Examination was produced as an Evidence, which was allowed of as good, according to Law, and I believe it might be so, because my Lord Chief Justice said it was Law. Now I do protest I never heard of any Boy an Evidence against me, till it was told me in the Press-yard, That a Boy was made away that was an Evidence against me; whereup∣on I answered, Why did they not try me last Sessions, for then they had the Boy? But I found there was no occasion for him this Sessions, considering the two young Maids this Sessions, one concerning the Handkerchief and the other seeing me in the Coach at <HI>Brownlowstreet</HI>-end, as you will hear anon; God forgive them and those that put them upon it. Now this Sessions coming on, I was forced to have Subpena's, and the same Charge and Trouble again as I had been at before: But now it was too late, for Mr. <HI>White</HI> and his Wife kept out of the way, and so that they could not be found, nor did appear: I know not the Reason, but God forgive them, I fear there was foul Dealing. Mrs. <HI>Whiple</HI> did not appear, and the Maid could not come, because the House could not be left alone. Now the Day of my Tryal being come they would have put it off again, but that my Lord Chief Justice would not suffer it, and I pressing for it, it was granted me; and I must own my Lord had all the Pati∣ence imaginable, so that I can find no Fault with Judges or Jury. I will now mention the most remarkable Pas∣sages that I can remember as to the Evidence against me. The first was, to satisfie the Court the occasion of my be∣ing suspected to be one of the Persons that committed the Fact, about the Hundred and twenty Pounds lent by the
<PB N="23" REF="13"/>
Doctor to the Widow, my Acquaintance; but what he swore I cannot remember; but as I was informed, he was the Person that gave the first Suspicion of me to be the Man; if so, God forgive him, for I had not seen him in three Months before the Doctor was murthered. The next that swore (for I cannot remember every thing, but this Passage) That I came to his Chamber, and laid my Hand upon my Sword, and said, I would be reveng∣ed on the Doctor: It is false, as I am a dying Man; for there was no Discourse of the Doctor, but Matters relating to himself; for the Doctor was always willing to do any thing for the Widow's Good, but was prevented by him. As for the two Witnesses at the Coffee-House, that swore that I said, That I should say, <Q REND="margQuotes">God D—him, he ought to have his Throat cut.</Q> And the Woman more particularly swore this, that I said, <Q REND="margQuotes">What, would he have a Woman of your Quality go to Service? G.D. him, he ought to have his Throat cut.</Q> Pray observe, this Woman comes to <HI>Newgate.</HI> I coming to her, said, Mrs. <HI>Joe,</HI> I wonder you can sleep in your Bed, knowing the Wrongs you have done me; she presently answered, <Q REND="margQuotes">Lord! Captain <HI>Harri∣son,</HI> all I said was, That you said he ought to be hanged, but I believe it was in your Passion, and I really think you are as Innocent as I am:</Q> Which was the reason why I asked in Court, What she had for swearing that? This is true upon my Salvation.</P>
<P>I am sorry that I have not the Trial, and then I could better answer it: And I will not tell a Lye, now I am going out of the World, therefore would only hint at those things I am sure are false, and will not name any Person, but leave it to God to touch their Hearts in his due Time, for it cannot be expected I can remember all that was said in Court; I will only mention the particu∣lar Sayings, and let them remember it after my Death. As to the Witness that said, I was at his Lodgings at nine
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>
a Clock exactly, and that I had a Gentleman staying be∣low for me, and that I had urgent Business to do that Night, and several other Discourses about the poor Wo∣man that Night: God forgive him for being positive to an Hour; I might have believed it might have been that Time he swore, if Circumstances relating to the Gown, which he may know (by reading the Account of my Defence before mentioned) must satisfie him to the contrary, though I fear the World cannot understand my Meaning; but I write this meerly for himself, that he may recollect himself of what he has done; when he knows in his Conscience my Business was another thing.</P>
<P>Now as to that Man in the <HI>Compter,</HI> who swore that the Night before the inhuman Murther was done, I was there, and being in Discourse with the Widow, he hearkned at the Door, and heard me say, G. D. me, I would have the Blood of <HI>Hinch</HI> or <HI>Clinch.</HI> This, or to the like effect, was what he swore; I never said, I would be the Death of <HI>Hinch</HI> or <HI>Clinch</HI> in my Life, as I must appear at the Judgment Seat of God to answer it. As to that poor Wo∣man, I pity her, whose Evidence was, That I was at her House on S. <HI>Thomas Day</HI> last, and had on a Black Shabby Sute, I think, were her Words. Upon my Sal∣vation it is false, for I have not had a Black Coat on in three Months Time, before the Doctor was murthered, as several can Testifie, nor never wore any Coat but that I had on when I was brought before my Lord Chief Ju∣stice, which was the same I had on at my Tryal, in three Months Time before the Murther: I shall answer her Evidence no more.</P>
<P>As to the 2 Maids, I never heard of them as Evidences against me till I saw them in Court; therefore you will think I had a hard Task to go through; but God be thanked he supported me then, and believe he will con∣tinue
<PB N="25" REF="14"/>
it to me, and also assist me at the Hour of my Death.</P>
<P>As to the first Maid or Girl, about fifteen or sixteen Years old, as I take her to be, she keeps her Mother's Apple-shop: Her Evidence was, I told her, That I was a Parliament Man, and that one Day being out of the Room, she saw a Handkerchief there, and went to the Maid below, and said, Can this be a Parliament Man, and have such a Handkerchief as this? of such a like Piece the Maid had an Apron, and they compared them toge∣ther, and they were almost alike. Now the Handker∣chief that was about the Doctors Neck, when he was Murthered, was produced in Court; and she swore that was the Hankerchief, or very like it: This was her Evi∣dence. To the best of my Knowledg, or to the same Ef∣fect, upon my Salvation, it is false, for I never in my Life said I was a Parliament Man: or ever had I such a Handkerchief in all my Life as that was, to the best of my Knowledg.</P>
<P>As to the other Maid who swore, That she saw me by the glimmering of a Lamp in the Coach, at the end of <HI>Brownlow</HI> Street, and heard me talk, and was with me in Prison, and heard my Voice before she came into the Room where I was, and said, That was the Voice that I heard in the Coach that Night when the Doctor was Murthered. And I asked, Why she did not declare it before? Which my Lord Chief Justice observed; but the Gentleman who was Council against me, as I take it, put into her Head, and said, it was Scruple of Con∣science, and that her Mother, or some Body else, would not let her meddle in such a dangerous Business. God forgive her, she did my Business; and God forgive them that put her upon it.</P>
<P>As to that Person who swore I said I was but just come out of <HI>Kent,</HI> and had been out of Town a Fortnight or
<PB N="26" REF="15"/>
three Weeks: God forgive him, I leave it to his own Conscience, and pray to God that he would reform his Course of Life. I do not say this as a Reflection, God forbid I should, but rather as an Exhortation, that if he reads this, he may repent himself of the Wrongs done me.</P>
<P>And as for the Person who swore against me, of my being at his Lodgings exactly at 9 a Clock, which was the occasion of my unhappy Death, being false; for it was at 8, which I convinced him of in Prison upon Cir∣cumstances. God Almighty pardon him, and lay it to his Heart, that he may truly repent himself; and withal let him remember the Bond: He knows my mean∣ing.</P>
<P>I have writ these Remarks upon my Tryal, which will be insignificant to Strangers; for they will be scarcely understood by any but the Parties concerned, who have falsly sworn against me: And God in his due time touch their Hearts, that they may sincerely repent themselves; and I freely forgive them, as I hope God in his Infinite Mercy will do me at the last Day. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<P>I have one thing to add, That after my Condemnation, the next day a most scandalous Pamphlet came out, En∣tituled, <HI>An Impartial Account of the Notorious Wicked Life of Captain</HI> Harrison: One Passage in it I must take Notice of, which is this, My Rascally Behaviour towards the Duke of <HI>Monmouth,</HI> when he suffered on <HI>Tower Hill.</HI> I thank my God no one could be more sorry than my self for his unhappy end: As to the rest of it, being so scandalous, that all my Friends, Gentle∣men and Acquaintance, know to the contrary: But it is hard that for the Lucre of a Penny, a Man dares write so many Lies; but God forgive them that did it; for he would have writ the same upon his own Brother upon the like Occasion.</P>
<P><PB N="27" REF="15"/>I have writ this chiefly for my Relations, Friends and Acquaintance, who I do not fear but that they will be∣lieve me: And as for the rest of the World I leave it to them to judge as they please, till it shall please God to bring to Light this black Deed of Darkness, which he certainly will at his good appointed time; <HI>Not our Will but his be done.</HI> And now to conclude, The greatest thing that grieves me, as to this World, is, My Relati∣ons; but let this be their Comfort, as well as my Hap∣piness, That I am Wronged, and that I am Innocent; and I do heartily beg of God to forgive those that falsly Swore against me; and more particularly that Person who was the first Author of the Suspicion: For I do bless the day wherein I was falsly Accused; for by that means I was brought to a sight of my former Sins, and do acknowledge it is God's Justice and just Judgment, for which I give Praise to his Holy Name, that I have this time to bewail, and repent my self of all my Sins, begging Pardon of all those I have any ways wrong'd, forgiving heartily every one that has wronged me; even those I do most heartily forgive who are the occasion of my Death; as I hope God will forgive me, and re∣ceive me unto his Everlasting Kingdom, through the Me∣rits and Mediation of Jesus Christ, his only Son, my Lord and Saviour. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="consolatory Scriptures">
<PB N="28" REF="16"/>
<HEAD>Comfortable Sayings in the Holy Scri∣pture, on which I rely, and put my Confidence and Trust in, through Jesus Christ my Saviour.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">At the first opening of the Holy Bible, after the lying down upon the Ground in the Con∣demned Hole, after being found Guilty.</HEAD>
<Q><BIBL>ISAIAH III.</BIBL>
ARise, shine, for the light is come, and the Glory of the Lord is risen upon thee; for behold the darkness shall cover the earth, and gross darkness the people, but the Lord shall rise upon thee, and his glory shall be seen upon thee; for in my wrath I smote thee, but in my favour have I had mercy on thee glory to be to thee for this thy comfort, O Lord.</Q>
<Q><BIBL>PSALM LXXI. 3.</BIBL>
Deliver me, O my God, out of the hand of the ungodly, out of the hand of the unrighteous and cruel man. — <MILESTONE N="6" UNIT="vers."/> I am become as a monster unto many, but my sure trust is in thee, <MILESTONE N="9" UNIT="vers."/> For my enemies speak agianst me, and they that lay wait for my soul, take their counsel together, saying, God hath forsaken him, persecute him and take him, for there is none to deliver him. <MILESTONE N="10" UNIT="Vers."/> Go not far from me, O God, my God, haste thee to help me. <MILESTONE N="23" UNIT="Vers."/> My Lips
<PB N="29" REF="16"/>
be fain, when I sing unto thee, and so will my soul whom thou hast delivered.</Q>
<P><HI>O God,—I faithfully trust in thee, to deliver me; and believe thou wilt not forsake me, but that thou wilt in this my Trouble make haste to help me.</HI></P>
<Q><BIBL>MATTHEW XI. 28.</BIBL>
Come unto me all you that labour and are heavy la∣den, and I will give you rest</Q>
<P><HI>O Lord, I confess, I am heavy loaden with my Sins, but I trust in thee, that thou wilt ease me, and that thou wilt give Rest to my Sick, Sinful Soul; O cleanse it with the precious Blood of my Saviour.</HI></P>
<Q><BIBL>MATTHEW XVII. 11.</BIBL>
For the Son of Man is come to save that which was lost, &amp;c.</Q>
<P><HI>O Jesus Christ, my Saviour, I firmly believe thou wilt save me; for I was lost to thee, but now am found, thanks be to God my Saviour.</HI></P>
<Q><BIBL>1 TIMOTH. I. 15.</BIBL>
This is a true saying and worthy of all men to be re∣ceived, That Jesus Christ came into the world to save sinners.</Q>
<P><HI>Glory be to thee O God, I heartily believe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and that thou camest to save Sinners, and me the greatest of Sinners.</HI></P>
<CLOSER>Now into thy Hands I commend my Sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>t.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB N="30" REF="17"/>
<HEAD>Mr. <HI>Harrison</HI>'s Letter to his Friend.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Dear Cousin,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>NOw accept of any hearty thanks for all your and your Wife's Services, and loving Kindnesses, and God Almighty reward you: I am now preparing my self for another World, and do heartily forgive all my Enemies. There were four of my Witnesses that did not appear, one Mr. <HI>White</HI> and his Wife, the Maid of the House where I was, and one Mrs. <HI>Fairlace;</HI> let not God lay my Blood to their Charge, and God forgive all those that swore falsly against me. And whether before my Execution or after God is pleased to bring to Light this Murder, I am sure he will do it; then the World will know my Wrongs: In the mean Time I resign my Soul and Body to him, who is a just God, and by this Means will bring me to himself. This Affliction is a great one, and more than Human Nature can bear; but I trust in him, that he will not lay more on me than he will give me the Grace if his Holy Spirit to undergo, and indeed I look upon it as a Fatherly Chastisement; for whom he loves he chastises: For if I had my Deserts he might have taken me in the midst of all my Sins, and have rewarded me with the Punishment of the everlasting Prison (Hell) pre∣pared for all impenitent Sinners; but I hope he will give me the Grace of his Holy Spirit, to repent my self of all my Sins, which I have and do, and shall with the Help of him, with an Humble, Lowly and Obedient Heart, and not in the least Cloak or Dissemble them, before my Heavenly Father, who gave up his only begotten Son to die for Sinners, and me the greatest: And I hope he will give me his Grace to follow his Example, who was falsly Accused, Condemned and suffered a shameful Death upon the Cross, I being now falsly accused, and to suffer a shameful Death; at which Time I sincerely and heartily
<PB N="31" REF="17"/>
beg of him, to support me, which I trust in God he will, humbly begging Pardon, and confessing the Sins I have been guilty of. Now, one thing I beg of you, for Christ his sake, That you will take it from me, a dying Man, without the least Hopes of Pardon here, from any Mortal Man, That I am Innocent, Clear and Free in Thought, Word and Deed of this Bloody, Barbarous, unheard of Murther, the which several Times I have protested to you my Innocence, and for which I do suffer; surely knowing and certainly be∣lieving, no Salvation can be had from Almighty God, the Searcher of Hearts, to any one who at the Hour of Death dies with a Lie in his Mouth; therefore desire your Prayers for me (being really Innocent) and all other good Christians Prayers, <HI>That God Almighty will be pleased to bring to Light this Bloody Deed, not when we would have him, but at his own appointed Time; not our Will, but his be done.</HI> And I beg of you, let me see you, for I have desired, That you and Cosen C—, and a Divine or two (and no Body else) may come to me, for I will not now Discourse any Persons relating to Worldly Affairs, but what may tend for the Salvation of my poor Soul. So recommending you to God, I rest,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>The most Wronged Man, the most Unhappy Man, as to this World, yet one of the most Happy Men through Christ my Saviour, in whom I trust for my Eternal Salvation,</HI> HEN. HARRISON.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

