<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The last speeches of the two ministers Mr. John King, and Mr. John Kid, [brace] at the place of execution at Edenburgh on the 14th day of August, 1679.</TITLE><AUTHOR>King, John, d. 1679.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A47415</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing K508</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R39063</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">18208261</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 18208261</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">107131</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47415)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107131)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1125:25)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The last speeches of the two ministers Mr. John King, and Mr. John Kid, [brace] at the place of execution at Edenburgh on the 14th day of August, 1679.</TITLE><AUTHOR>King, John, d. 1679.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kid, John, d. 1679.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 29 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[Edinburgh? :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1680.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Separate t.p. for speech by John Kid, dated 1679.</NOTE><NOTE>Imperfect: print show-through; torn, begining-page 11 of defective Huntington Library copy spliced at end.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>King, John, d. 1679.</TERM><TERM>Kid, John, d. 1679.</TERM><TERM>Covenanters --  Scotland.</TERM><TERM>Presbyterianism.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A47415">
<STC T="W">K508</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">18208261</BIBNO>
<VID>107131</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE LAST SPEECHES OF THE TWO MINISTERS
Mr. <HI>JOHN KING,</HI> and Mr. <HI>JOHN KID,</HI>
At the Place of EXECUTION AT EDENBURGH On the 14<HI>th</HI> day of <HI>August,</HI> 1679.</P>
<P>Printed in the Year, 1680.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE PUBLISHER TO THE READER.</HEAD>
<P>HAving observed that of late years it is become Customary to publish the dying Speeches of such as have been in a Publick manner Executed as <HI>Criminals;</HI> I thought the sight of these Speeches (not as Speeches or Discourses only, but) as the Speeches of these two (so much talk'd of) Men, would to most be very acceptable; all persons I believe being curious to know what they would say in their Circumstances, I did not think it necessary to make any Animad∣versions
<PB REF="3"/>
upon them, but lea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e it to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of every Reader to make his own Remarks, (it being as easie to animadvert in this Case as to read) I would as unwillingly impose my Comment upon others, as I would be imposed upon my self.</P>
<CLOSER>Farewel.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="speech">
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE SPEECH OF Mr. <HI>JOHN KING.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Men and Brethren,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I Do not doubt but that many that are Spectators here, have some other end, than to be edified by what they may see and hear in the last words of one going to Eternity; but if any one of you have Ears to hear, (which I nothing doubt but some of this great gathering have) I desire your Ears and Attention, if the Lord shall help and permit me to speak, to a few things.</P>
<P>I bless the Lord, since infinite Wisdom and holy Providence has so carved out my Lot to dye after the manner that I do, not unwillingly, neither by force: It's true, I could not do this of my self, Nature al∣ways having an Inclination to put the evil day far off,
<PB N="2" REF="4"/>
but through Grace I have been helped, and by this Grace yet hope I shall: 'Tis true, through Policy I might have shunned such a hard Sentence, if I had done some things; but though I could I durst not, God knows, redeem my life with the loss of my Integrity and Honesty. I bless the Lord that since I have been apprehended and made a Prisoner, God hath very wonderfully upholden me, and made out that com∣fortable word, <HI>Fear not, be not dismayed, I am with thee, I will strengthen thee, I will uphold thee by the right hand of my Righteousness, Isaiah</HI> 42.10. I thank the Lord he never yet gave me leave so much as to have a thought, much less to seek after any shift that might be in the least sinful: I did always, and yet do judge it better to suffer Affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleasures of Sin for a Season; therefore I am come hither to lay down my life; I bless the Lord I dye not as a Fool dyeth, though I acknowledge I have nothing to boast of in my self: yea I acknowledge I am a Sinner, and one of the chiefest that hath gone under the name of a Professer of Religion; yea amongst the unworthiest of those that have Preached the Gospel; my Sins and Corruptions have been many, and have defiled me in all things; and even in following and doing of my Duty, I have not wanted my own sinful Infirmities and Weaknesses, so that I may truly say, I have no Righteousness of my own, all is evil and like fil∣thy Rags; but blessed be God that there is a Saviour and an Advocate, <HI>Jesus Christ</HI> the Righteous, and I do believe that <HI>Jesus Christ</HI> is come into the World to save Sinners, of whom I am the chief, and that
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
through Faith and his Righteousness I have obtained Mercy; and that through him, and him alone, I desire and hope to have a happy and glorious Victo∣ry over Sin, Satan, Hell, and Death; and that I shall attain unto the Resurrection of the just, and be made Partaker of Eternal Life. I know in whom I have believed, and that he is able to keep that which I have committed unto him against that day. I have, according to my poor Capacity, preached Salvation in his name; and as I have preached, so do I believe, and withal my Soul have commended it, and still do commend to all of you the riches of his Grace, and faith in his Name, as the alone and only way whereby to come to be saved.</P>
<P>It may be many may think (but I bless the Lord without any solid ground) that I suffer as an Evil-Do∣er, and as a busie body in other mens matters; but I reckon not much upon that, having the Testimony of my own Conscience for me. It was the lot of our blessed Saviour himself, and also the lot of many of his eminent precious Servants and People to suf∣fer by the World as Evil-doers: Yea I think I have so good ground not to be scar'd at such a lot, that I count it my <HI>non-such-honour</HI>; and Oh what am I that I should be honoured so, when so many Worthies have panted after the like, and have not come at it: My Soul rejoyceth in being brought into Conformity with my Blessed Lord, and Head, and so Blessed a Company in this way and lot; and I desire to pray that I may be to none of you this day upon this ac∣count a Stone of stumbling, and a Rock of Offence; and blessed is he that shall not be offended in Christ
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
and his poor Followers and Members, because of their being Condemned as Evil doers by the World.</P>
<P>As for these things for which Sentence of Death hath past against me, I bless the Lord my Conscience doth not condemn me, I have not been Rebellious, nor do I judge it Rebellion for me to have endea∣voured in my Capacity what possibly I could for the born-down and ruined Interest of my Lord and Ma∣ster, and for the Relief of my poor Brethren afflicted and persecuted, not only in their Liberties, Privi∣ledges, and Persons, but also in their Lives; there∣fore it was that I joyned with that poor handful; the Lord knows, who is the searcher of hearts, that nei∣ther my design nor practice was against his Majesty's person and just Government, but I always studyed to be Loyal to lawful Authority in the Lord, and I thank God my heart do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h not condemn me of any Disloyalty; I have been Loyal, and I do recommend it to all to be obedient to higher Powers in the Lord.</P>
<P>And that I preached at Field-Meetings, which is the ground of my Sentence; I am so far from acknow∣ledging that the Gospel preached that way was a Ren∣dezvous of Rebellion, as it is so tearmed, that I bless the Lord that ever he counted me worthy to be Wit∣ness of such Meetings; which have been so undoubt∣edly countenanced and owned, not only to the con∣viction, but even to the Conversion of many; there∣fore I do assert, That if the Lord hath had any purer Church in the Land than other, it hath been in and amongst these Meetings in Fields and Houses, so much now despised by some, and persecuted by others.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="5"/>That I preached up Rebellion, and taking up Arms against Authority is untrue, I bless the Lord my Con∣science doth not condemn me for that; this never be∣ing my design; if I could have preached Christ, and Salvation through his name, it was my work; and herein have I walked according to the Light and Rule of the Word of God, as it did become me, though one of the meanest of the Ministers of the Gospel.</P>
<P>I have been looked upon by some, and represented by others to be of a divisive, and Factious Humor, and one that stirred up division in the Church, but I am hopeful that they will all now give me their Charity, being within a little to stand before my Judge, and I pray the Lord forgive them that did so misrepresent me; but I thank the Lord what-ever men have said against me concerning this, that on the contrary, I have often disswaded from such ways and practices, as contrary to the Word of God, and of our Covenanted and reformed Religion; and as I ever Abhorred division, and Faction in the Church, as that which tends to its utter Ruine, if the Lord prevent it not. So I would in the bow∣els of my Lord and Master, if such an one as I am may presume to perswade, and Exhort both Ministers and Professors; if there be any Consolation in Christ, if any comfort of love; if any Fellowship of the Spi∣rit, if any bowels and mercies that you be like minded, having the same Love, being of one ac∣cord, of one mind in Lowliness of mind; let each esteem others better than themselves, <HI>Phil.</HI> 1.12. Harmoniousness and Honesty in the things of God,
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
can never enough be sought after, and things that tend to the prejudice and hurt of Christs interest, can never enough be fled from and avoided.</P>
<P>And as I am come hither willingly to lay down my Tabernacle, so also I die in the belief, and faith of the Holy Scriptures, and in the faith of the Apostles, and primitive Christians, and Prote∣stant Reformed Churches, and particularly the Church of <HI>Scotland,</HI> whereof I am a poor member: That have been so wonderfully carried on against so many Oppositions, by the mighty Power and goodness and Wisdome of God, I bear my Wit∣ness and Testimony to the Doctrine and worship, Discipline and Government of the Church of <HI>Scot∣land, by Kirk</HI> Sessions, Presbyters, Synods with Assemblies.</P>
<P><HI>Here he also bore his Testimony to the So∣lemn League and Covenant.</HI></P>
<P>Also I bear Testimony to our pub∣lick confessing of sins, and Ingagements to duties, and that either as to what concerns the reformati∣on of the whole Church in general, as also the causes of Gods wrath, the neglecting of which is feared, to be one of the greatest causes of Gods wrath this day against the Land: I also give wit∣ness and Testimony unto the protestation, given in against the Receiving the Malignant party into places of power and trust, contrary to our Solemn Ingagements, and Obligations to God, also I adhere
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
unto our Confession of Faith, Larger and shorter Catechisms. I witness my Testimony against <HI>Po∣pery,</HI> which is so greatly increased, yea so much Countenanced, and professed openly by many, and that without the least punishment; I bear wit∣ness against the Antichristian <HI>Prelacy</HI> now—esta∣blished by a Law contrary to our Vows to Al∣mighty God, and against defending all our Solemn Oaths, and ingagements, as a thing that Calls for Divine Vengence.</P>
<P><HI>Here he bore witness against all Oaths con∣trary to the Covenant: And then proceed∣ed thus.</HI></P>
<P>Also I bear my Testimony against all Error, Schisme, Heresie, contrary to our ingagements to God, and especially against that Reviving again, and Soul deluding evil or rather Devilry Qua∣kerisme so much Connived at, if not allowed and Countenanced by many, whose Office it is to re∣strain it, as also against all the Steps and Courses of Backslidings, defections, which have been and now are on Foot in the Land, and against all branches and parties thereof, under whatsoever name or No∣tion;
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
moreover, I bear my Testimony to all the Testimonys both formerly and of late, by suffering and banished witnesses, and to all the Testimonies by our first suffering Gentlemen, Noble-men, and others, that have suffered in this City and Kingdome, who Chearfully laid <HI>down their lives with admira∣ble Divine Assistance,</HI> and all those who have laid down their lives, as also to those who have Sealed their Testi∣mony, either with suffering imprisonment or Ba∣nishment upon this account, Score, and quarrel.</P>
<P><HI>Here he bore his Testimony against their Act of Supremacy.</HI></P>
<P>As also I bear my Testimony against the Cess imposed by the late Convention of Estates, where∣by the Enemies of Christ, and his Church, are sup∣plyed with all necessaries, for the utter extirpating of the interest of Christ in this Church.</P>
<P>And there is one thing more I would say, that the Lord seems to be very wroth with the Land. The causes are many, first the dreadful sleights our
<PB N="9" REF="7"/>
Lord Jesus Christ, has received in the Offers of his Gospel.</P>
<P>Secondly, The Horrid profanity that has o∣verspread the whole Land, That not only Re∣ligion in its Exercise, but even Common Civility is gone.</P>
<P>Thirdly, there is the Horrid perjury in the mat∣ters of our vows and ingagements, its to be fea∣red will provoke the Lord to bring his Sword upon these Lands.</P>
<P>Fourthly, The dreadful formality and stupidity in the duties of Religion, which is introduced, like that which came upon the Careless Daugh∣ters.</P>
<P>Fifthly, Horrid ingratitude, what do we render to him for his goodness? is not the most of all that we do, to work wickedness, and to strengthen our selves to do evil, and want of Humility under all all our Breaches? We are brought Low, and yet we are not Low in the sight of God, what a dreadful Covetousness, and minding our own things more than the things of God, and that a∣mongst all Ranks? would to God that there were not too much of this among many, who are Ene∣mies to the Cross of Christ, and mind earthly things.</P>
<P>And yet I dare not say, but there are many faithful and precious to him in <HI>Scotland,</HI> both of Ministers, and Professors, whom I trust God will keep stedfast, and who will Labour to be found faithful to their Lord and Master, and whom I hope he will make a brazen wall and Iron Pil∣lars,
<PB N="10" REF="8"/>
and as a strong defenced City, in the fol∣lowing of their duties in these sad evil times; but it were to be wished, That there were not too many to strengthen the hands of the evil-doers, and make themselves Transgressors, by endea∣vouring to build again that which formerly they did destroy; but let such take heed of the flying Roll, <HI>Zach.</HI> 5. And let all the Lords Servants and Ministers take heed that they watch, and be stedfast in the faith, and quit themselves like men, and be strong, and set the Trumpet to the mouth, and give Seasonable and faithful warning to all Ranks Concerning sins, and duties, especially a∣gainst the sins of this sinful time: it is to be La∣mented and sadly Regretted by many of the Lords people, That there has been so much silence and fainting, even amongst Ministers of how great Concernment it is; now in this sad Juncture, let Ministers consider well, what it is that God calls for at their hands; To be silent now, especially when so many Cruel and Horrid things are Acted, when they are so much called, and ought to be concerned to speak even upon the Peril of their lives, certainly a dreadful sin in the light of God, their silence must be. I shall only desire that the Lord would open the mouths of his faithful ser∣vants, that with all boldness, they may speak out the mind of their Master, that so the work, inte∣rest, Crown and Kingdome of our Lord Jesus Christ, may not be destroyed, and that the trou∣bles of his poor people, which are precious to
<PB N="11" REF="8"/>
him, may not without a Testimony be ruined▪ I Shall but say a few words.</P>
<P>First, All you that are profane, I would seriously Exhort you that you return to the Lord by seri∣ous Repentance; if you do, iniquity shall not be your Ruine; if you do not, know that the day of the Lords Vengeance is near and hastneth on! Oh know for your comfort, there is a door of mer∣cy yet open, if you be not despisers of the day of Salvation. And you that have been, and yet are, Reproachers and persecutors of Godliness, and of such as live Godly; take heed, Oh take heed, sad will be your day, when God arises to scatter his Enemies, if you repent not for your ungodly deeds.</P>
<P>Secondly, All those who are taken up with their own private interests, and if that go well they Care the less for the interest of Christ, take heed and be zealous, and repent, lest the Lord pass the Sentence, I will spew you out of my mouth.</P>
<P>Thirdly, For the truly Godly, and such as are Lamenting after the Lord, and are mourning for all the abominations of this City, and are taking pleasure in the very Rubbish and Stones of <HI>Zion,</HI> be of good Courage, and Cast not away your Con∣fidence, I dare not say any thing to future things, but surely the Lord has a handful that are preci∣ous to him, to whom he will be Gracious; to these is a dark night at present, how long it will last the Lord knows! Oh let not the sad disasters, that his poor people meet with, though very astonishing, Terrifie you, beware of snares that abound, Cleave
<PB N="12" REF="9"/>
fast to your Reformed Religion, do not Shift the Cross of Christ, if you be called to it, it is better to suffer than sin, account the reproach∣es of Christ greater Riches than all the Treasures of the World.</P>
<P>In the last place, let not my Death be Grievous to any of you, I hope it will be more profitable both for you and me, and for the Church and in∣terest of God, than my life could have been. I bless the Lord, I can freely and Frankly forgive all men, even as I desire to be forgiven of God, pray for them that persecute you, bless them that Curse you. As to the cause of Christ, I bless the Lord I never had cause, to this day, to repent for any thing I have suffered, or can now suffer for his name. I thank the Lord who has shewed mercy to such a vile sinner as I am, and that ever he should advance me to so High a dignity, as to be made a Minister of his blessed and everlasting Gospel; and that ever I should have a Seal set to my Ministry, upon the hearts of some in several places and Cor∣ners of this Land: the Lord visit <HI>Scotland</HI> with more and more faithful Pastors, and send a Reviving day unto the people of God; in the mean time be pa∣tient, be stedfast, unmovable, always abounding in the work of the Lord; and live in Love and peace one with another, and the Lord be with his poor Afflicted Groaning people, that yet re∣main.</P>
<P>Now I bid farewell to all my friends, and dear Relations; Farewell my poor Wife and Children, whom I leave in the good hand of him who is
<PB N="13" REF="9"/>
better than seven Husbands, and who will be a Father to the fatherless. Farewell all Creature com∣forts, Welcome everlasting life, everlasting glory, Wel∣come everlasting love, everlasting praise; bless the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Sic Subscrib.</HI> John King.</SIGNED>

<DATELINE><DATE><HI>August,</HI> 14th. 1679.</DATE> Tolbooth, <HI>Circa horam Septimam.</HI></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="10"/>
<PB REF="10"/>
<P>THE LAST SPEECH OF Mr. <HI>JOHN KID.</HI> AT THE PLACE OF EXECUTION, ON The Fourteenth day of <HI>August</HI> 1679.</P>
<P>Printed in the Year, 1679.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="speech">
<PB REF="11"/>
<PB N="17" REF="11"/>
<HEAD>THE SPEECH OF Mr. <HI>JOHN KID.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Right Worthy and well beloved Spectators and Auditors.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>COnsidering what bodily distempers I have been exercised with since I came out of the Torture, (<HI>viz.</HI>) Scarce two hours out of my naked bed in one day, it cannot be expected, that I should be in Case to say any thing to purpose at this Juncture, especially seeing I am not as yet free of it, however I cannot but Reve∣rence the good hand of God upon me, and desires with all my Soul to bless him for this my present Lot.</P>
<P>It may be there are a great many here that Judge my Lot very sad and deplorable. I must confess
<PB N="18" REF="12"/>
death it self, is very Terrible to Flesh and blood, but as it is an out-let to sin, and an in-let to righ∣teousness, it is the Christians great and inexpressible priviledge, and give me leave to say this, that there is somthing in a Christians Condition, that can ne∣ver put him without the reach of insufferableness, even shame, death, and the Cross being inclu∣ded.</P>
<P>And then if there be peace betwixt God and the Soul, nothing can damp peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ, this is a most supporting ingredient in the bitterest Cup, and under the shar∣pest, and firiest Tryal he c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n be exposed unto▪ this is my mercy, That I have somthing of this to lay Claim unto, <HI>viz.</HI> The intimations of pardon, and peace betwixt God and my Soul.</P>
<P>And as concerning that, for which I am con∣demned, I magnifie his grace, that I never had the least challenge for it, but on the contrary, I Judge it my Honour, that ever I was counted worthy to come upon the Stage upon such a consideration; another thing that renders the most despicable Lot of the <HI>Christian,</HI> and mine sufferable, is a felt and sensible presence from the Lord, strengthening the Soul when most put to it, and if I could have this for my Allowance this day, I could be bold to say, Oh death where is thy sting, and could not but cry out Welcome to it, and all that follows upon it: I grant the Lord from an Act of Soveraignity may come, and go as he pleases, but yet he will
<PB N="19" REF="12"/>
never forsake his people, and this is a Cordial to me in the Case I am now exposed unto.</P>
<P>Thirdly, The exercising and puting forth his glo∣rious power, is able to Transport the Soul of the believer, and mine, above the reach of all Sublu∣nary difficulties, and therefore seeing I have hope to be kept up by this power, I would not have you to look upon my Lot, or any other that is or may be in my Case, in the least deplorable, seeing we have ground to believe, that in more or less he will perfect his power and strength in weakness.</P>
<P>Fourthly, That I may come a little nearer to the purpose in hand, I declare before you all, in the sight of God, Angels and men, and in the sight of that Son and all that he has Created, that I am a most miserable sinner, in regard of my Original and Actual Transgressions. I must confess they are more in number then the Haires of my Head. They are gone up above my Head, and are past num∣bering, I cannot but say as <HI>Jacob</HI> said, I am less then the least of all Gods mercies, yet I must de∣clare to the exalting of his free grace, That to me who am the least of all Saints is this grace made known, and that by a strong hand, and I dare not but say he has loved me, and washed me in his own blood from all iniquities, and well is it for me this day, That ever I heard or read that faithful saying; that Jesus Christ, came into the World to save sinners, of whom I am chief.</P>
<P>Fifthly, I must also declare in his sight, I am the
<PB N="20" REF="13"/>
most unworthiest that ever opened his mouth to preach the unsearchable Riches of Christ in the Gospel. Yea the sense of this made me altogether unwilling to fall about so great a work, until by the importunity of some whose names are precious and savoury to me and many others, I was prevail∣ed with to fall about it, and yet I am hopeful not altogether without some fruit, and if I durst say it without vanity, I never found so much of the presence of God upon my Spirit, as I have found in exercises of that nature, though <HI>I</HI> must still con∣fess attended with inexpressible weakness, and this is the main thing for which <HI>I</HI> must lay down my Tabernacle this day, <HI>viz.</HI> That <HI>I</HI> did preach Christ and the Gospel in several places of this Nation; for which <HI>I</HI> bless him (as <HI>I</HI> can), That ever such a poor obscure person as <HI>I</HI> am, have been thus priviledged by him, for making mention of his grace as <HI>I</HI> was able.</P>
<P>Sixthly, Give me leave to add this word farther, that though there be great appearances, for spread∣ing and preaching this Glorious Gospel, yet <HI>I</HI> fear there is a snare at the bottom, and poyson in that dish which may gender, and be productive, of not only greater Scarcity of Honest preaching and preachers, but a Real Famine of the Word, this <HI>I</HI> say is my fear, and <HI>I</HI> hope God will keep his servants and people from fomenting any thing to the detriment of the Gospel.</P>
<P>Seventhly, <HI>I</HI> am also afraid that the Lord is in∣tending
<PB N="21" REF="13"/>
to multiply his stroaks upon the Land, we have walked seven times contrary to him, and therefore we may lay our account (unless Repen∣tance prevent it) that he will walk seven times contrary to us, there is more and more grounds to fear that a Sword is Brandished in Heaven, a Glittering Sword, sharpned and forbished against the Guilty and Harlot <HI>Scotland.</HI></P>
<P>Eightly, As for the Fifth Cause in my indict∣ment, upon which my sentence of death is foun∣ded, (<HI>viz.</HI>) Personal presence, Twice or thrice, with that party whom they call the Rebels; for my own part <HI>I</HI> never Judged them such: <HI>I</HI> Acknowledge and do believe there were many there that came in the simplicity of their hearts, like those that followed <HI>Absolom</HI> long ago, and <HI>I</HI> am as sure on the other hand there were a great party there that had nothing before them but the repairing of the Fal∣len work, and the restoring the breach, which is wide as the Sea, and <HI>I</HI> am apt to think that such of these who were most branded with mistake, will be found to be most single: but for Rebellion against his Majesties person or Lawful Authority, the Lord knows my Soul Abhorreth the name and thing; Loyal <HI>I</HI> have been, and <HI>I</HI> wish every Christi∣an to be so, and <HI>I</HI> was ever of this Judgment, To give to <HI>Caesar</HI> the things that are <HI>Caesars,</HI> and to God the things that are Gods.</P>
<P>Ninthly, Since <HI>I</HI> came to prison, <HI>I</HI> have been much branded with many that <HI>I</HI> must call Asper∣sions
<PB N="22" REF="14"/>
whereof Jesuitisme is one, I am hopeful there was never one that did converse with me that had the least ground for laying this to my Charge, I know not how it comes to pass it is laid upon me now, except implacable prejudice that some have been prepossest with against me. I am not Ig∣norant that near two years ago, a person of some note in this Church while Living, was pleased to say, <HI>I</HI> was dyed in that Judgment: after he was better informed, he Changed his Note, and said it was misinformation: but now the Lord, before whom <HI>I</HI> must stand, and be Judged by and by, knows <HI>I</HI> have a perfect Abhorrence of that thing. And that it was never my Temptation directly nor indirectly. Though <HI>I</HI> must confess, some few years ago, some were very pressing upon me that <HI>I</HI> would conform, and imbrace Prelacy? But for Po∣pery, and that Trash, it never came nearer my heart than the <HI>Popes</HI> Conclave, and the Alcoran, which my Soul Abhors.</P>
<P>Tenthly, <HI>I</HI> Have also been branded with facti∣ousness, divisive, and seditious preaching, and practices. <HI>I</HI> must confess if it be so, it was more then ever <HI>I</HI> was aware of: according to the mea∣sure that God has given me, it was my endeavor to commend Christ to the hearts and Souls of the peo∣ple, even repentance towards God and Faith towards our Lord Jesus Christ, according to the word of God, confession of faith, and Catechismes Larger and Shorter, yea <HI>I</HI> did press them, when God did cast it in my way to remember their former Obligations
<PB N="23" REF="14"/>
in Doctrine, worship, Discipline and Government, and that they would make it their work to stand to it, in substance and Circumstance, seeing it is so Cryed down in this day, and if this be divisive preaching, <HI>I</HI> cannot deny it.</P>
<P>Eleventhly, <HI>I</HI> am prest in Conscience to bear my Testimony to and Abhorrence of every Invasion, Usurpation, and incroachment that is made or has been made against Christs Royal prerogative, Crown, and Kingdome, Originate upon and derivate from that which they call the Supremacy, <HI>I</HI> was never free to say a Confedcracy with those that <HI>I</HI> Judge have in a great part said a Confederacy with that thing, and the Lord is my record, <HI>I</HI> was never free in my Conscience for that that is called indulgence, neither first nor second, as it was tendered by the Counsel, and as it was imbraced by a great many Godly men in this Land, yea it was never Lau∣dable nor expedient to me, and in effect this is one of the main grounds, why <HI>I</HI> am rendred so Obnoxi∣ous to so many imputations, that <HI>I</HI> have been all along contrary to that indulgence in my Judgment, <HI>I</HI> confess <HI>I</HI> have been so, and <HI>I</HI> die in my Judgment contrary to it, and this <HI>I</HI> Crave Leave to say with∣out any Offence given to the many Godly and Learn∣ed, that are of another Judgment.</P>
<P>Twelfthly, <HI>I</HI> Judge it fit likewise in this Case to leave my Testimony against that Stent, Taxation and Cess, that has been so injustly imposed, so fri∣volently founded, and vigorously carried on by the
<PB N="24" REF="15"/>
Abettors of that contention, and meerly upon no o∣ther account imaginable, but to make a Final Extir∣pation of Christ, and his Gospel Ordinances out of the Land, and how Lamentable it is to consider how many professors did willingly pay it, and were most forward for inciting others to do the same.</P>
<P>In the next place, though to many <HI>I</HI> die desired, yet <HI>I</HI> know to not a few my death is not desired, and it is the rejoycing of my heart, that <HI>I</HI> die in the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has loved me, and given himself for me, and in the faith of the Prophets and Apostles, and in this faith that there's not a name under heaven by which men can be saved, but the name of Jesus, and in the Faith of the Doctrine and Worship of the <HI>Kirke</HI> of <HI>Scotland,</HI> as it is now established according to the word of God, Confession of faith, Catechisms Larger and shor∣ter, and likewise <HI>I</HI> joyn my Testimony against Po∣pery, Perjury, Profanity, Heresie, and every thing contrary to sound Doctrine.</P>
<P>In the Close, as a dying person, and as one who has obtained mercy of the Lord to be faithful, <HI>I</HI> would Humbly leave it upon godly Ministers to be faithful for their Lord and Master, and not to hold their peace in such a day, when so many ways are taken for injuring of him, his name, way, Sanctu∣ary, Ordinances, Crown and Kingdome, <HI>I</HI> hope there will be found a party in this Land, that will con∣tinue for him, and his Matters, in all Hazzards, and as faithfulness is called for in Ministers, so pro∣fessors
<PB N="25" REF="15"/>
would concern themselves that they Coun∣tenance not, nor abet any thing inconsistent with former Principles and practices. Let the Land con∣sider how Neuteral and indifferent we are grown in the matters of God, even like <HI>Ephraim</HI> long ago, a Cake not turned.</P>
<P>Next how far we are fallen from our first love, how far we are degenerated from the noble Vine into which the Lord did once plant us; Lamentable it is how far we are gone in the way of <HI>Egypt,</HI> drinking the Wa∣ters of <HI>Sichar,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>Again, What a woeful Spirit of bitterness is pre∣dominate in this Land, in this our Age, <HI>Ephraim</HI> vex∣ing <HI>Judah,</HI> and <HI>Judah Ephraim; Manasseth Ephraim,</HI> and <HI>Ephraim Manasseth,</HI> the growing dogedness of this temper almost amongst us all, portends terrible things from the Lord against <HI>Scotland.</HI></P>
<P>Fourthly, Reformation neither designed nor pra∣ctised; what means all this deformity that is come to pass in these days, instead of the contrary? how many of us are pulling down that which we have been building up; how many of us calling good evil, and evil good, dis-owning and dis-savouring that which some∣time we judged our honour to testifie for and to a∣vouch.</P>
<P>Fifthly, A Publick Spirit in contending for God in his matters, in substance and circumstance, according to our Vows and Obligations, is much wanting amongst us at this day.</P>
<P>Farther I am prest in Conscience to make honourable mention of all those glorious things that God has done in <HI>Scot.</HI> since the year 1638. the abundant measure of his spirit that has been power'd out upon his <HI>people.</HI></P>
<PB N="26" REF="16"/>
<P><HI>Here he spoke much concerning the Solemn League and Covenant; and afterwards pro∣ceeded as followeth.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="27" REF="16"/>And moreover I bear my Testimonies against all other Confusions, Imprisonment and Blood, that is or may be intended against those of the Land that desire to keep their Garments clean, whether in Prison or out of Prison</P>
<P N="6">6thly, As concerning that which is the ground of my death, <HI>viz.</HI> Preaching here and there in some Cor∣ners, I bless my God I have not the least challenge for it; and though those that Condemned me are pleased to call such Preachings Rendezvouses of Rebellion, yet I must say this of them, they were so far from be∣ing reputed such in my Eyes, that if ever Christ had a People or Party wherein his Soul took pleasure, I am bold to say these Meetings were a great part of them; the shineing and Glory of God was eminently seen amongst these Meetings, the convincing Power and Authority of our Lord went out with his Ser∣vants in those blasphemously nick-named Conventi∣cles; this I say without reflection upon any; I have a word to say farther, that God is calling persons to Re∣pentance, and to do their first work; Oh that <HI>Scot∣land</HI> were a mourning Land, and that Reformation were our practice, according as we are sworn in the Covenant.</P>
<P>Again, that Christians of Grace and Experience would study more streightness and stability in this day, when so many are turning to the right hand, and ma∣ny to the left; he that endureth to the end shall be sav∣ed; he has appointed the Kingdom for such as con∣tinue with him in his Temptations.</P>
<P>Next, if ever you expect to have the Form of the House shewed you in all the Laws thereof, goings out thereof, and comings in thereof, then think it no
<PB N="28" REF="17"/>
shame to take shame to you for all that has been done, sitting down on this side <HI>Jordan</HI> is like to be our bane. Oh when shall we get up and run after him till he bring us into the promised Land, let us up and after him with all our heart, and never rest till he return.</P>
<P>I recommend my Wife and young one to the care and faithfulness of the God of <HI>Abraham, Isaac,</HI> and <HI>Jacob,</HI> the God that has fed me to this day, and who is the God of my Salvation, their God and my God, their Father and my Father, I am also hopeful, that Christians, Friends, and Relations, will not be un∣mindful of them when I am gone.</P>
<P>Lastly, I do further bear my Testimony to the Cross of Christ, and bless him that ever he count∣ed me worthy to appear for him in such a lot as this: Glory to him that ever I heard tell of him, and that ever he fell upon such a method of dealing with me as this, and therefore let none that loves Christ and his Righteous Cause be offended in me.</P>
<P>And as I have lived in the faith of this, that the three Kingdoms are married Lands, so I dye in the faith of it, that there will be a resurrection of his Name, Word, Cause, and of all his Interest therein, though I dare not determine the time when, nor the manner how, but leave all these things to the infinitely wise God, who has done, and will do all things well. Oh that he would return to this Land again, to repair our breaches, and take away our back-sliding, and appear for his work: Oh that he were pacified towards us; Oh that he would pass by <HI>Scotland</HI> once again, and make our time a time of Love, <HI>Come Lord Jesus, come quickly.</HI> Himself hasten it in his own time and way. The Lord is my light and life, my joy, my song,
<PB N="29" REF="17"/>
and my salvation; the God of his chosen be my Mer∣cy this day, and the inriching comforts of the holy Ghost keep up and carry me fair through, to the Glo∣ry of his Grace, to the edification of his people, and my own eternal advantage. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Sic Subscrib.</HI> John Kid.</SIGNED>

<DATELINE><DATE><HI>August,</HI> 14th. 1679.</DATE> Tolbooth, <HI>Ante horam Septimam.</HI></DATELINE></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="18"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="18" MS="y"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="19"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="19"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="20"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="1" REF="20"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="2" REF="21"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="3" REF="21"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="4" REF="22"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="5" REF="22"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="6" REF="23"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="7" REF="23"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="8" REF="24"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="9" REF="24"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="10" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="11" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="12" REF="26"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="13" REF="26"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

