<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Notes upon Stephen College grounded principally upon his own declarations and confessions, and freely submitted to publique censure / by Roger L'Estrange.</TITLE><AUTHOR>L'Estrange, Roger, Sir, 1616-1704.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A47895</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing L1281</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R7200</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12920163</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12920163</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">95363</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A47895)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95363)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 986:23)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Notes upon Stephen College grounded principally upon his own declarations and confessions, and freely submitted to publique censure / by Roger L'Estrange.</TITLE><AUTHOR>L'Estrange, Roger, Sir, 1616-1704.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 48 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Joanna Brome ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1681.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Colledge, Stephen, 1635?-1681.</TERM><TERM>Popish Plot, 1678.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A47895">
<STC T="W">L1281</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12920163</BIBNO>
<VID>95363</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<P><PB REF="1"/>
NOTES
UPON
Stephen College.</P>
<P>Grounded Principally upon his own
Declarations and Confessions,
And freely submitted to
PUBLIQUE CENSURE.</P>
<P><HI>By</HI> Roger L'Estrange.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed for <HI>Ioanna Brome;</HI> at the <HI>Gun</HI> at the West∣end
of St. <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard, 1681.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Reader.</HEAD>
<P>IT is not the part of a <HI>Christian,</HI> nor indeed of a
<HI>Man,</HI> to Insult upon the Miserable, either in their
<HI>Memories,</HI> or in their <HI>Persons:</HI> Beside that the
Criminal here in question has already satisfied Publique
Iustice, and is gone to his Place to receive according to
his Works. This does not hinder yet, but that a man
may honestly endeavour the putting of a Check to those
Clamorous Out-crys that are daily sent forth against the
Government upon this occasion; as if the whole business
of <HI>College</HI> were only a <HI>Perjurious Combination</HI> of
<HI>Papists</HI> against <HI>Protestants,</HI> in the Person of that
Wretched Malefactor; and the <HI>Protestant Religion</HI>
to stand or fall with the <HI>Protestant Joyner,</HI> It is the
Intent now of these Papers, to lay open the <HI>Malice,</HI> and
the <HI>Falshood</HI> of these Calumnies: Not so much for the
<HI>Vindication</HI> of the <HI>Proceeding,</HI> as for the <HI>Disabusing</HI>
of the <HI>Common People;</HI> for the <HI>Best Argu∣ment
for Authority is the Reason of the Laws;
and in these Cases the Vigorous Execution of
them upon the</HI> Seditious, <HI>is the only effectual Re∣medy.</HI></P>
<P>It is not that I pretend to Illustrate the Iustice of the
<PB REF="3"/>
<HI>Court,</HI> or of the <HI>Verdict,</HI> by any Additional Remarques
of my own, but effectually (upon other Grounds and E∣vidences)
to bring the Offender to a new hearing; where∣in
I shall remit my self to the Iudgment and Conscience
of any Indifferent Reader, whether there be not Matter
sufficient, from whence fairly to Infer, and to Presume
him Guilty of the most material Parts of his Accusation,
even without the aid of anything that was produc'd a∣gainst
him at his Tryal.</P>
<P>As for those that are curious to be more particularly
inform'd, I must refer them to the Printed Tryal it self;
and so I shall close up my Preface with my <HI>Lord Chief
Justices Opinion upon the Verdict.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Lord Chief Iustice (to the Pris'ner.)</HI> These things
when I look upon them, and consider the complexion of
your defence, it makes an easie Proof have Credit. But
I think there was a full Proof in your Case; yet I say, if
there had been a great deal less Proof, the Jury might
with Justice have found you <HI>Guilty.</HI> And because you
now declare your self <HI>Innocent</HI> of all you are charged
with, I think my self bound to declare here in Vindica∣tion
of the Country, and in Vindication of the Justice
of the Court, that it was a <HI>Verdict</HI> well given, and to the
satisfaction of the Court, and I did not find my Brothers
did dislike it. This I say to you out of Charity, that
you may incline your mind to a submission to the Justice
that hath overtaken you, and that you may enter into
Charity with all men, and prepare your self for another
life.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>NOTES
UPON
Stephen College.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§. 1. The Proceeding against <HI>College</HI> Re∣presented
as a Design against the <HI>Pro∣testant
Religion.</HI></HEAD>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>HE main stress of the Cause here in Con∣troversie,
lies upon a Pretended Zeal for</HI>
Religion, <HI>and in such a manner too, as if
the very</HI> Name <HI>of a</HI> Protestant <HI>were a</HI> Su∣persed
as <HI>for a</HI> Traytor, <HI>and an Exemption
from the Ordinary Methods of</HI> Law <HI>and</HI>
Iustice. [This Design <HI>(says</HI> College) is not only against <HI>Me,</HI>
but against <HI>all the Protestants.</HI> Trayal, <HI>p.</HI> 5.] <HI>And a∣gain</HI>
[This is a most Horrid Conspiracy to take away my life;
<HI>and it will not stop here; for it is against all the Pro∣testants
in England.</HI> Ibid. <HI>p.</HI> 6.] ['Tis time to have a
Care <HI>(says</HI> Aaron Smith) when our <HI>Lives</HI> and <HI>Estates</HI> and
<HI>Al</HI> are beset here. <HI>Ibid. p. 13.]</HI> [My Lord <HI>(says</HI> College <HI>a∣gain)</HI>
I do not question but to prove this one of the Hellishest
Conspiracies that ever was upon the face of the Earth: And
<PB N="2" REF="4"/>
these the most Notorious Wicked Men; an absolute design
<HI>to destroy all the Protestants in</HI> England, that have had
the Courage to oppose the Popish Plot. Ibid. <HI>p. 36.] And
then in his last Speech,</HI> [I am as certainly Murder'd by <HI>the
hands</HI> of the Papists as Sr. <HI>Edmundbury Godfrey</HI> himself
was, though the thing is not seen.] <HI>And once again in his
other Speech, Printed for</HI> Edith College, [I dye <HI>(says he)</HI>
by the hands of the Enemies of the Great God, his Christ,
his Servants, his Gospel, and my Country, to which I wil∣lingly
submit, and earnestly pray mine may be the last <HI>Prote∣stants
Blood</HI> that Murdering Church of <HI>Rome</HI> may shed
in <HI>Christendom.]</HI></P>
<P>It is no wonder if the Ringing of this Emphatical Re∣flection
<HI>[the Blood of Protestants; a Design upon all the
Protestants</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> &amp;c. over and over in the Ears
of the Multitude, create Unquiet Thoughts, and work
some extraordinary Effects upon the minds of the com∣mon
People. It will be well therefore to ask <HI>Stephen
College</HI> what he means by that <HI>Protestant Religion</HI> that is so
much <HI>Endanger'd;</HI> and <HI>who</HI> and <HI>where</HI> those <HI>Papists</HI> are,
upon whom he Charges this <HI>Hellish Conspiracy:</HI> for we
have none as yet in sight that can fall within the compass
of his Challenge; but <HI>his Majesty himself,</HI> and the <HI>Ordi∣nary
Ministers of Iustice</HI> acting according to the <HI>Known
Laws,</HI> and in the <HI>Regular Methods of Iudicial Proceedings.</HI>
Now upon a due Examination of this matter, there will
be found a great difference betwixt <HI>Colleges Protestants,</HI>
and <HI>Ours;</HI> and betwixt <HI>Our Papists</HI> and <HI>His:</HI> So that
the Snare lies in the double acceptation of the <HI>Word,</HI> by
which they labour to Impose upon the World, that the
<HI>Schismatiques</HI> are the <HI>only True-Protestants,</HI> and those of
the <HI>Church</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> in a <HI>Confederacy</HI> against them with
the <HI>Papists:</HI> But we shall take <HI>Colleges Religion</HI> as he has
deliver'd it with his own lips; and gather from thence
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
what may be the <HI>Cause,</HI> and the <HI>Profession</HI> that he con∣tends
for.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§. 2. The meaning of <HI>Colleges</HI> Prote∣stants.</HEAD>
<P><HI>I</HI> Was ever a <HI>Protestant;</HI> (says <HI>College)</HI> I was <HI>born</HI> a
<HI>Protestant; I have</HI> liv'd <HI>so, and so, by the Grace of
God, I'le</HI> dye: Of <HI>the Church of England,</HI> according to
the <HI>Best Reformation</HI> of the Church, from all <HI>Idolatry,</HI>
from all <HI>Superstition,</HI> or any thing that is contrary to the
Gospel of our Blessed Lord and Saviour. <HI>Colleges last
Speech.</HI></P>
<P>In this Clause he Declares himself upon his Death, to
be a <HI>Protestant of the Church of England,</HI> according to the
<HI>Best Reformation,</HI> &amp;c. Now there is <HI>No Church of Eng∣land</HI>
but that which is Established by <HI>Law,</HI> both in <HI>Do∣ctrine</HI>
and <HI>Discipline;</HI> unless you will make the <HI>Dissenting
Protestants,</HI> to be <HI>Assenters,</HI> and <HI>Consenters;</HI> and <HI>Feake</HI>'s,
<HI>Owen</HI>'s, <HI>Ralphson</HI>'s, <HI>Baxter</HI>'s, <HI>Meade</HI>'s, <HI>Ienkins</HI>'s <HI>Separate
Congregations</HI> to be <HI>severally the Church of England;</HI> which
no man certainly in his Right Wits will pretend to do.
So that either he dy'd a True Son of the <HI>Established Church
of England,</HI> according to the Genuine Import of the Ex∣pression;
(and as most manifestly he would have it
thought, he did) or else his Design was to go off with
a <HI>Desperate Equivocation</HI> betwixt his Teeth, if he was any
other than what he Pretended to be: and it comes all to
a <HI>Case,</HI> as to the <HI>Truth</HI> of his <HI>Profession,</HI> whether ye take
him the <HI>One</HI> way, or the <HI>Other.</HI> There may be Another
Note upon it, which is, that he would give to understand
by This Profession that he had always <HI>Liv'd,</HI> and that
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
now he <HI>Dy'd,</HI> the <HI>same sort of Protestant;</HI> which is a
<HI>Point-Blank-Contradiction</HI> to that which now follows.</P>
<P><HI>Upon the Sheriffs Desiring him, for the satisfaction of
the World, to declare what Church he meant; whether</HI>
Presbyterian, <HI>or</HI> Independent, <HI>or the Church of</HI> England;
<HI>or</HI> what? <HI>His answer was</HI> [Good Mr. Sheriff, for your sa∣tisfaction,
for Twenty years and above, I was under the
<HI>Presbyterian Ministry,</HI> till His Majesties Restauration.
Then, I was Conformable to the Church of <HI>England,</HI> when
that was Restor'd; and so continu'd, till such time as I saw
<HI>Persecution</HI> upon the <HI>Dissenting People,</HI> and undue things
done in their <HI>Meeting-Places.</HI> Then I went among them, to
know what kind of People those were; and I take God to
Witness, since that time I have used their <HI>Meetings,</HI> viz. the
<HI>Presbyterians; others</HI> very <HI>seldom,</HI> and the Church of
<HI>England.</HI> Last Speech.</P>
<P>By this it appears that <HI>College</HI> was a <HI>Presbyterian before</HI>
the Late Rebellion, as well as quite <HI>thorough</HI> it. He saies
nothing, what brought him over to the Church of <HI>Eng∣land</HI>
at last; but that it was the <HI>Persecution</HI> of the <HI>Dissen∣ters</HI>
that carried him off again: And yet he told us but
just before, that he was of <HI>That Reformation</HI> which was
Freest from <HI>Superstition</HI> and <HI>Idolatry;</HI> though there was
nothing of that we see in this <HI>Pretended Cause</HI> of his <HI>Re∣lapse.</HI>
The Remainder of this Paragraph is <HI>Mysterious,</HI>
and <HI>Perplext;</HI> and there is too much <HI>Reason</HI> to fear that it
was Intricated on purpose that he might be <HI>Vnder∣stood
one way,</HI> and <HI>Mean another.</HI> But however, if
there be any thing to be made out of it at all, it is, that
he dy'd of the <HI>Presbyterian</HI> Persuasion. I would not
force any thing, to Discredit the words of a Dying man;
but if any man can reconcile this Passage, either to it self,
or with several other Expressions of his in Prison, some
two or three days before his death, they will do him a
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
Kind, and a Charitable Office; for I must confess, I can∣not
bring them to any sort of Consistence.</P>
<P>A matter of two or three days before his Execution,
two Divines of eminent Piety and Worth, gave the Pri∣soner
a Visit, and among other Discourses suitable to his
Condition, and the occasion, It was ask'd him, Q. <HI>What
Church are ye of? A.</HI> Of the Church of <HI>England.</HI> Q. <HI>As
by Law Establish'd? A.</HI> No, I am not. Q. <HI>How d'ye
mean the Church of</HI> England <HI>then? A Presbyterian?
A.</HI> No. Q. <HI>An Independent? A.</HI> No. Q. <HI>An Ana∣baptist?
A.</HI> No. Q. <HI>A Quaker? A.</HI> No. Q. <HI>Where's
that Church in</HI> Christendom <HI>then, that you will own your
self a Member of? A.</HI> That's to my self; I will not tell
ye. And he gave at another time his Reason for't. <HI>If
it were known</HI> (saith he) <HI>what Church I am of, my faults
would be laid upon my whole Church.</HI> How does this agree
now with his Profession at the Place of <HI>Execution?</HI> Or
where shall we find that <HI>Individuum Vagum</HI> of <HI>Colleges
Protestant?</HI></P>
<P>There were some Circumstances concerning my Lady
<HI>Rochester,</HI> of which hereafter; and others grounded
upon the Information of a <HI>Somerset-shire</HI> Gentleman, that
have prevail'd upon many People to take him for a <HI>Pa∣pist,</HI>
which Information runs thus.</P>
<P><HI>That the</HI> Informant <HI>Lodging at the House</HI> of one <HI>P.</HI> a
Victualler in <HI>Wich-street,</HI> in <HI>Michaelmas</HI> Term, 1677.
there came into the Room where he was (upon a <HI>Sunday</HI> in
the Evening) a certain Person who was called by the name
of <HI>College;</HI> and sitting down there, enter'd into a discourse
concerning the Lord of <HI>Rochester,</HI> whereupon the Informant
told <HI>College</HI> that he heard the Lady <HI>Rochester</HI> was turn'd
<HI>Papist;</HI> who thereupon demanded, <HI>what he meant by a Papist?</HI>
to which he answer'd, One that maintain'd the Tenents of
the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> mentioning some of them; as <HI>Pur∣gatory,
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
Prayers to Saints,</HI> &amp;c. whereupon the other under∣took
to defend the said Tenents, and with great Vehemence
told him, that he would bring him Books the next day that
should overthrow all Arguments to the contrary: And told
him farther, that his name was <HI>Gollege,</HI> and not <HI>College;</HI>
and that he had wrought for my Lord of <HI>Rochester</HI> at <HI>Eu∣more:</HI>
But the Informant never saw him before, nor since,
only his Landlord told him that he was a <HI>Joyner,</HI> and liv'd
at the back-side of his House.</P>
<P><HI>Colleges</HI> Answer to this Point was, that he believ'd this
might be his <HI>Brother,</HI> who was a <HI>Ioyner</HI> by <HI>Trade,</HI> and
<HI>dy'd</HI> a <HI>Papist,</HI> in <HI>October,</HI> 1678. He wrote his name
<HI>Gollege;</HI> Lodg'd near <HI>Wich street,</HI> and (as he conceiv'd)
had done work for my Lord <HI>Rochester</HI> at <HI>Eumore;</HI> which
seems to have been the ground of that mistake. Beside
that, <HI>College</HI> had several times Confess'd that he had
<HI>strong and frequent Impulses on his spirit against Popery:</HI>
Insomuch that if he did but see any book in defence of it,
he would prefently set all his work aside to get it an∣swer'd;
declaring himself also against it at the place of
Execution, in these words, <HI>[I do with all my soul, and did
ever since I knew what Religion was, Abhor and Detest the
Church of</HI> Rome, <HI>as Pernicious and Destructive of Humane
Society.]</HI></P>
<P>I shall leave it now to the Readers choice whether a
<HI>Papist,</HI> or <HI>not?</HI> Although for my part, I am strongly per∣suaded
of the <HI>Negative;</HI> but what kind of <HI>Protestant</HI> to
make of him, we are yet to seek. We shall see next how
he stood affected to the Church of <HI>England;</HI> but so as
to separate his <HI>Opinions</HI> from his <HI>Practices,</HI> which are re∣serv'd
for another place.</P>
<P>He received his <HI>Sentence, Aug.</HI> 18. and <HI>Suffer'd</HI> upon
the 31. In this <HI>Interim</HI> the Bishop of <HI>Oxford</HI> provided
all that was possible for his Relief and Consolation, with
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
infinite Compassion and Honour; appointing several
eminent Pious and Learned Divines to Administer unto
him in his Distress. The Reverend Dr. <HI>Marshal</HI> went to
him first, who being call'd away by bus'ness, Dr. <HI>Hall</HI>
supply'd his place, from whose hand he receiv'd the
Blessed Sacrament soon after his Sentence; but his De∣votion-duties
were still distracted with some interjected
Excursions of his own; and he was heard to say, that <HI>as
he did not disdain the Prayers of the Church, so he did not
delight in such Prayers, neither could he joyn heartily with
those that did not pray by the</HI> Spirit. It was observed by
one of these Reverend Gentlemen that assisted him, that
when he came to the Prayers for the <HI>King, Queen,</HI> and
the <HI>Bishops,</HI> instead of <HI>Amen,</HI> he said <HI>Lord have mercy
upon them,</HI> though he joyn'd in an <HI>Amen</HI> to all the rest.
Two days before his Execution, one of them desir'd him
to prepare himself for the Holy <HI>Eucharist,</HI> to whom he
return'd this Answer. <HI>It is no more than a Shell and
Form of your own making; as if I eat a piece of Bread, and
drank a glass of Wine, and at the same time remember'd my
Saviour.</HI> In this manner he refus'd it: Nor would he
suffer this Gentleman to pray with him at all upon the
day of his Execution; declaring that nothing gave him
satisfaction but <HI>Extemporary Prayer.</HI> The Doctor Admi∣nister'd
to him by the <HI>Liturgy,</HI> and so did Dr. <HI>Marshal</HI>
pray with him likewise; but still he would have sallies
also of his own. Little <HI>Schismatical Ianeway</HI> tells a long
story, (and against himself too) <HI>(Num. 42.)</HI> where he
says that <HI>College was urg'd with divers Arguments to make a
Publique Confession;</HI> whereas it was only propounded to
to him to Confess, <HI>Conditionally,</HI> and not <HI>Absolutely,</HI> as he
maliciously represents it. True it is, that he gave hopes
at first of some tractable inclinations toward the Enter∣tainment
of the <HI>Liturgy;</HI> but upon <HI>Munday morning</HI>
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
there was found with him a certain unknown <HI>Quaker;</HI>
and from that time till the <HI>next Wednesday</HI> (the day of
his Execution) he was harden'd against all Attempts;
and this Obstinacy of his was said to arise from a sug∣gestion
of the <HI>Quakers,</HI> that without dashing the Credit
of those Witnesses, the Protestant Cause would be in
danger to be lost. He press'd very earnestly that <HI>Titmarsh,
the Preaching-Anabaptist-Tanner,</HI> might come and Pray
with him; and he was privately sent for, but not suf∣fer'd
to come at him.</P>
<P>You have here an account of the <HI>Protestant-Ioyners
Religion</HI> from his own lips, which is Resolv'd at last in∣to
a meer <HI>Enthusiastical Whimsie.</HI> The <HI>Quaker</HI> pleases
him; the <HI>Anabaptist</HI> pleases him; and yet he is neither
the <HI>one</HI> nor the <HI>other,</HI> nor a <HI>Presbyterian;</HI> nor an <HI>Inde∣pendent;</HI>
nor a <HI>Church-of-England-man,</HI> and yet a
Friend to <HI>all</HI> but the <HI>Right;</HI> and Conciliable even to
those Opinions that are yet at an Inconciliable Variance
one with another. Let the Reader now determine un∣der
these Circumstances, whether <HI>that Protestant Per∣suasion</HI>
that makes such a noise in this Controversie, be a
<HI>Religion</HI> or a <HI>Faction;</HI> or how it is possible either to <HI>De∣stroy</HI>
or to <HI>Defend that Religion</HI> which is no where to be
<HI>found.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§. 3. What is meant by the <HI>Papists</HI> in Con∣spiracy
against <HI>Colleges Protestants.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THE <HI>Protestant Ioyner</HI> has left us at a great loss in
the fore-going Section, about the meaning of his
<HI>Protestant Religion:</HI> But then he makes some amends
for't in telling us very plainly what he means by the
<PB N="9" REF="7"/>
<HI>Papists.</HI> It is a part of his <HI>Charge,</HI> That he reckon'd the
<HI>Church,</HI> the <HI>King,</HI> and <HI>all his Adherents</HI> for <HI>Papists;</HI> and
we have his own Words and Papers to prove every jot as
much as that amounts to, even to the minutest Circum∣stances
of the Accusation.</P>
<P><HI>[This</HI> (says he) <HI>is not the first time, my Lord, the Pa∣pists
have design'd to take away my life; though it be the first
time they went about to take it</HI> away by a <HI>Law.</HI> Tryal. p. 39.
What is this now to say, but that the Ordinary Mini∣sters
of Justice, in the Orderly Execution of their Du∣ties,
are <HI>Murtherers</HI> and <HI>Papists?</HI> And it is yet more ex∣plicitly
set forth in the <HI>first Section,</HI> as we have seen al∣ready.
How often has he been heard, even in the pre∣sence
of Mr. <HI>Harleton</HI> of St. <HI>Pauls Church-yard,</HI> to whom
he appeals from Mr. <HI>Masters's Evidence,</HI> that <HI>old Rowly</HI>
(his <HI>Cypher</HI> for the <HI>King) was a Papist?</HI> and it was his
common discourse in <HI>Coffee-Houses</HI> at a venture, as num∣bers
of Persons are able and ready to justifie, if need
should require it. What's the meaning of his drawing
the <HI>King</HI> with <HI>Two Faces</HI> in his <HI>Raree Show, one</HI> towards
<HI>Popery,</HI> the <HI>other</HI> towards <HI>Protestantism?</HI> And the <HI>Two
Houses</HI> at his Majesties <HI>Back, in a Chest of Rome</HI> (as he
calls it) in the <HI>Ballad?</HI> What's the meaning of the <HI>Eng∣lish
Clergy</HI> Riding <HI>Tantivy</HI> after a <HI>Iesuite</HI> in <HI>another</HI> of his
<HI>Prints?</HI> With these words of Explanation, <HI>Room for
the Church? For Rome Boys:</HI> with this Conceit at
the <HI>Church-door, Out Phanatiques; In, Popery:</HI> And
the <HI>Bishop of Bath and Wells</HI> Personated in it, with a
<HI>Patch</HI> on his check, and the mark upon him of a <HI>Church-Papist?</HI>
Or what say ye of the <HI>same Bishop again, kissing
the Popes Toe</HI> in <HI>another</HI> of his Pieces, Entitled <HI>Hats for
Caps;</HI> with the whole <HI>Hierarchy</HI> in't, making Court to
<HI>his Holiness</HI> for <HI>Preferment?</HI> And then there's the Learn∣ed
device of a <HI>Scale</HI> to the <HI>Papacy, 1. Servitor. 2. Pupil.
<PB N="10" REF="8"/>
3. Batchelors. 4 Master. 5. Priest. 6. Doctor. 7. Dean.
8. Bishop. 9. Cardinal. 10. Pope.</HI> With these words to't.
<HI>[The Gradual way to make a Pope Infallibly: All done by
the Sign of the Cross, and a little School Conjuring.</HI> Here's
abundantly enough to shew <HI>What,</HI> and <HI>Who</HI> they are
that he calls <HI>Papists,</HI> without need of any other Evi∣dence
or Explication. But it will be said perhaps that
these <HI>Pictures,</HI> and especially the <HI>Raree Show</HI> are not yet
prov'd to be <HI>Colleges.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§. 4. The Libellous <HI>Pictures,</HI> and Particu∣larly
the <HI>Raree Show</HI> prov'd to be <HI>Colleges.</HI></HEAD>
<P>MY Lord, <HI>(says College)</HI> as to the Papers Charg'd
upon me to be mine, I declare I know not of
them. <HI>Tryal. pag.</HI> 74. I cannot deny but that they were
in my House; but that I was the <HI>Author,</HI> or did take them
in, is as great a Mistake as ever was made. <HI>Ibid.</HI> I know
nothing of the <HI>Printing</HI> of them, nor was I the <HI>Author</HI> of
them. <HI>Ibid.</HI> I do declare I know nothing of the <HI>Original,</HI>
the <HI>Printer,</HI> nor the <HI>Author.</HI> p. 75. <HI>There's a great deal
more of this stuff in the</HI> Tryal, <HI>to the same purpose; but
I shall lay no hold of any thing he says in his</HI> Defence, <HI>save
where he</HI> Confesses: <HI>But it will be allow'd, I hope, that
some weight might be laid upon what he delivers in that
which is publish'd under the Title of</HI> A True Copy of the
Dying Words of Mr. <HI>Stephen College,</HI> left in Writing un∣der
his own hand, and confirmed by him at the time of Ex∣ecution,
<HI>Aug.</HI> 31. 1681. at <HI>Oxford,</HI> Publish'd by his own
Relations, and Printed for <HI>Edith College.</HI></P>
<P>As to the Printed Papers <HI>(says he)</HI> which <HI>Dugdaie</HI>
produced in the Court, I do declare, I never saw them, call'd
<PB N="11" REF="8"/>
the <HI>Raree Show,</HI> and <HI>Intercepted Letter [in his hand]</HI>
before that time, <HI>(the meaning of these words</HI> [in his
hand] <HI>I do not understand)</HI> and therefore <HI>could</HI> not, and
<HI>did</HI> not <HI>decypher</HI> any of the Pictures to him. It's utterly
false. I was not the <HI>Author</HI> of those Verses call'd the <HI>Raree
Show,</HI> neither do I know who <HI>was,</HI> or the <HI>Printer,</HI> or ever
own'd my self the <HI>Author</HI> of either of them Papers to him in
my life.</P>
<P>Now by this train of wild Circumlocutions, a body
would think that <HI>College</HI> had been wholly Innocent of any
hand in the Promoting of that Scurrilous and Malicious
Libel, especially considering some passages of his in the
other Speech that was Printed for <HI>T. Basset. I take God
to witness</HI> (says he) <HI>and do freely acknowledge, I have sought
my God with tears several times, to inform me if so be I had
with any Word transgressed at any time.]</HI> He does not
find himself Guilty it seems, of so much as one <HI>Word</HI> a∣miss,
but appears to purge himself upon his <HI>Death,</HI> as to
that particular, which naturally resolves into this Con∣clusion;
that either he had nothing to do with that Pa∣per,
or otherwise that he approv'd the Design and Con∣tents
of it, though one of the most Insolent Pieces of Se∣ditious
Ribaldry that ever saw the light. <HI>[Monstrous
foul Beast, Thief, Child of Heathen</HI> Hobbs.] This is the
Language of the <HI>Protestant Ioyner</HI> to his <HI>Sovereign.</HI> Let
the world judge by this of <HI>his Religion,</HI> and of <HI>theirs</HI> too
that side with him; and in so doing, become Abettors
and Partakers of his Crimes. But we shall now make it
as clear as the light it self, that he went off the Stage
with a sad account to answer for upon this very Point.</P>
<P>First, He own'd to Mr. <HI>Atterbury▪</HI> the Messenger, <HI>all
the Papers that were found in his House</HI> to be his <HI>own,</HI>
whereof the <HI>Raree Show</HI> was <HI>one;</HI> telling him moreover,
that <HI>If there was any Treason in those Papers, the Wisest
<PB N="12" REF="9"/>
man in</HI> England <HI>was mistaken.</HI> And so says <HI>Aaron Smith</HI>
in his Paper of <HI>Instructions</HI> to him at <HI>Oxford. [The</HI> Raree
Show, <HI>&amp;c. and the</HI> Pictures <HI>are not Treason.]</HI> Taking
for granted that the <HI>Raree-Show,</HI> &amp;c. would infallibly be
made out against him.</P>
<P>The <HI>Design</HI> of this <HI>Raree-Show,</HI> drawn with a Pencil
upon <HI>Dutch Paper</HI> in <HI>Black-lead,</HI> was found, it seems,
lying upon his Table, and afterwards mis-lay'd. So that
<HI>College</HI> dodg'd them upon that point, at the Tryal, and
disown'd it in these words <HI>[I am sure you could never find
the</HI> Original <HI>of any such thing in my House.]</HI> But though
this was a <HI>point-blank denial</HI> of a <HI>Truth;</HI> there is this to
be said yet in Extenuation of it, that his Life was at stake,
and he made the best of his Plea. But this is no Excuse
yet for his <HI>Double-dealing</HI> after his <HI>Sentence,</HI> and upon the
place of <HI>Execution.</HI> He was Interrogated in the Castle
some few days before he suffer'd, whether he did not
with his own hand draw the design for the Ballad of <HI>A
Raree-Show?</HI> and whether <HI>that very Draught</HI> was not ta∣ken
with the other Prints, in his <HI>House?</HI> His Answer
was, that <HI>he was neither the</HI> Author <HI>of the Verses or Ballad,
nor did he</HI> know <HI>either the</HI> Author, <HI>or the</HI> Printer. And
then for the <HI>Design,</HI> he bad them <HI>shew it</HI> (knowing it to
be lost) <HI>and he would own it, if it were his.</HI></P>
<P>Now to expound this Riddle, 'tis probable he did not
know the <HI>Author,</HI> nor the <HI>Printer;</HI> and yet it is clear
that the <HI>first design</HI> was of his <HI>drawing;</HI> and by him ac∣commodated
to the <HI>Verses,</HI> without so much as knowing
who was the <HI>Poet.</HI> He might possibly deliver that
Draught also to have it <HI>Cut,</HI> without knowing the <HI>Gra∣ver;</HI>
as it is certain that he did deliver the <HI>Verses</HI> to be
<HI>Printed,</HI> though perhaps without knowing the <HI>Printer:</HI>
And this does evidently appear from the Testimony of
the <HI>Printer himself.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="9"/>
The <HI>Printer</HI> confesses and declares upon the sight of
one of the Papers found at <HI>Colleges,</HI> that it was wrought
at <HI>his Press;</HI> that he did it for <HI>Franck Smith,</HI> who told
him that it was a <HI>Merry▪ Ioking thing,</HI> but a <HI>Truth▪</HI> which
Corresponds with the Evidence, that <HI>College</HI> said it was
<HI>[as true as that Gods in Heaven.</HI> The Printer Informs
likewise, that <HI>Francis Smith,</HI> upon the reading of the
Staves to him <HI>Expounded</HI> them; (but without the <HI>Pi∣cture)</HI>
and told him that there was a <HI>Captain</HI> with a <HI>Pack
at his back,</HI> and that was the <HI>King;</HI> and that He in the
<HI>Mire</HI> was the <HI>King;</HI> and that He with the <HI>Two Faces</HI> was
the <HI>King again▪</HI> and that it was <HI>a Merry Iocose thing, and
had been sung before several Lords at</HI> Oxford: Which Par∣ticularities
do punctually agree with the Evidence against
<HI>College,</HI> from whom undoubtedly <HI>Franck Smith</HI> receiv'd
the <HI>Manuscript;</HI> and <HI>College,</HI> it seems, told <HI>Smith</HI> no more
upon this occasion, than what he had told before to o∣ther
People. The Book-seller, I find, knew well enough
what he did too, being very earnest with the Printer not
to discover his <HI>Name,</HI> but to say that <HI>he had the Copy from
a Gentleman, to him unknown;</HI> adding moreover these
words <HI>[A body may be Troubled about it, but there's no</HI>
Treason <HI>in it▪]</HI></P>
<P>Now after all that is said, lest it should be suggested
that there's no positive Proof yet against <HI>College,</HI> that he
had any thing to do with this Libel, we shall now put
that Question out of all dispute. There was a Paper of
<HI>Colleges Intercepted,</HI> which upon Examination he utterly
<HI>deny'd</HI> at <HI>first;</HI> but finding himself <HI>Discover'd,</HI> he <HI>Con∣fess'd</HI>
it. This was some few days before his Execution.
The Paper here intended, was the <HI>Speech,</HI> word for
word, that was Printed for <HI>Edith College;</HI> which being
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to the Joynor, he acknowledg'd it to be of <HI>his own
Hand-writing;</HI> and <HI>so is</HI> the <HI>Manuscript</HI> also of the <HI>Raree-Show</HI>
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
from whence that Ballad was Printed; and I have
the <HI>Original</HI> at this Instant by me, to satisfie any man
that shall make a doubt whether or no it was of <HI>Colleges
Writing.</HI> Besides that, he sung the Ballad in several
places, and particularly at Sir <HI>Philip Matthews</HI>'s, at <HI>South∣cot,</HI>
as divers Persons of Credit are ready to attest: And
by the token that Sir <HI>Philip</HI> charg'd him to <HI>forbear, for he
would not suffer any such thing in his House;</HI> or to this
effect.</P>
<P>I cannot but deplore the Infatuated blindness of this
Unhappy Creature, that should now at his last Extre∣mity,
instead of discharging his soul by a publique and
sincere Repentance, be troubling of his head with Shifts
and Reservations, as if he were contriving how to cast a
mist before the Eyes of God and Man; and in a case so
open too, that half an eye sees thorow it. And yet I
cannot but have more Charity for his endeavour to shuffle
it off in the one Speech, than for his saying just nothing
at all of it in the other: Unless as he has wrapt up the
particular Crimes for which he suffer'd, in his last general
Act of Charity and Confession. <HI>[Whomever I have of
fended in word or deed, I ask every man's pardon; and I
forgive the World with all my soul all the Injuries I have re∣ceived]</HI>
This is the best that can be made on't: And
without large allowances for distraction of thought, and
want of consideration, 'tis more than a man can justifie.
In <HI>Basset</HI>'s Speech, he cannot so much as charge himself
with any offensive <HI>Word,</HI> though upon the Scrutiny,
<HI>he had sought the Lord with Tears for Information. [I as
little thought</HI> (says he) <HI>to come to this as any man that
hears me this day; and I bless God, I have no more deserved
it from the hands of men, than the Child that sucks at his
Mothers breast, I bless God for it.]</HI> Now in the Speech
Printed for <HI>Edith College,</HI> he seems to contradict this, but
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
it is in terms so entangled and dubious, that I must leave
the Reader to make his own ghess upon it, only recom∣mending
this to his observation; that he speaks Intelli∣gibly
enough in all other cases, but where either his Re∣ligion,
or his Crime is the Question: As for example,</P>
<P>There be some other Scandalous and Malicious Reports
thrown upon me, as that I should own all that was Sworn a∣gainst
me, except <HI>Hains</HI>'s Evidence, and the like: To all
which I have been examined by Dr. <HI>Marshal,</HI> whom the Bi∣shop
of <HI>Oxon</HI> did voluntarily send to me the day after I was
Condemned; and that Worthy and Pious Dr. <HI>Hall,</HI> who
came to me, and from whom I received the Blessed Sacra∣ment
on <HI>Sunday last,</HI> to whom I did make the same Con∣fession
and Acknowledgment as I have here Inserted; parti∣cularly
the which I do again affirm is Truth, as I shall answer
it to God Almighty: Only I did acknowledge as my fault, I
did believe I might have been Guilty on some Occasions, and
in heat of talk, to have uttered some words of Indecency,
not becoming my Duty, concerning the King or his Council;
<HI>and if so, I do beg their Pardon.] Now the Reader is
left to his choice, whether to understand [ONLY] as an
Exception to the Truth of his Confession, as who should
say</HI> 'Tis all True but that; <HI>or to take it for an</HI> acknowledg∣ment,
<HI>of having been Intemperate that way: Or other∣wise,
as a bare supposition, as if he had said,</HI> I do rather
incline to think I might sometimes lash out that way; but if
I did, it was in a Passion; and if I ever did any such thing,
I ask their Pardon. <HI>So that here's nothing clear and open,
to answer, either the expectation of the world, or the
duty of a Person in his Condition; but only a wandring
vein of Ambiguity, and Incoherence, to amuse the Rea∣der,
and to perplex the Period. Or if it means any thing
else, it bears only the Countenance of a faint acknow∣ledgment
of a Mildemeanor, in a direct Contradiction to
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
what he delivered by word of mouth at his death; Con∣firming
the Truth of what he</HI> Confesses <HI>in the</HI> One <HI>Paper,
and</HI> denys <HI>in the</HI> other (<HI>in his own words</HI>) with his last
b<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eath, and sealing it with his dearest. Blood.</P>
<P>It is with great unwillingness that I have enter'd upon
this office; but since the Faction has taken the freedom
to arraign the Justice of the Nation, on the behalf of this
Pretended Innocent, I reckon'd it my duty on the other
hand, to expose in some measure the Fraudulent Practices
of the Pris'ner; and I make no doubt but to Evince un∣to
any man whatsoever, that will but hear and attend
Common Reason, that over and above the Proofs and
Circumstances that appear'd at his Tryal, there is in these
Sheets sufficient to make out the Credibility of his Accu∣sation.
But in my way to the main bus'ness, I shall give
ye in the next Section some short touches of his disinge∣nuous
proceedings in other cases.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§. 5. <HI>Colleges Doublings</HI> and <HI>Mistakes</HI> about
the Bus'ness of the <HI>Lady Rochester,</HI> and
<HI>Father</HI> Thompson, and his Entertain∣ment
of Mr. <HI>Sergeant.</HI> Some Notes
upon the Evidence of Sir <HI>William Jen∣nings,</HI>
and Mr. <HI>Masters,</HI> and his Com∣plaints
of Ill <HI>Usage.</HI></HEAD>
<P>I shall not charge my self with a Critical Dissection of
all <HI>Colleges</HI> Disguises and Mistakes, but make my Ob∣servations
upon such, and so many of them as may serve
for a Foundation to the Reader, for some competent
judgment upon the rest. And first to the Report
concerning the Lady <HI>Rochester.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="12"/>
It pass'd for current here in the Town, that the Lady
<HI>Rochester,</HI> upon her Death-bed declar'd that <HI>College</HI> was
the man who first brought the Priest to her, that Per∣verted
her to the Faith of the Church of <HI>Rome;</HI> which
being a thing true in it self, is not unlikely to have been
in such manner declar'd by the said Lady; but whether
it <HI>was</HI> or was <HI>not</HI> so, it matters not. But this <HI>Rumour</HI>
however open'd all Peoples mouths about the Town,
that <HI>College</HI> was a <HI>Papist.</HI> Upon his Report, <HI>College,</HI> pre∣tended
to purge himself of that Calumny, in both the
Speeches afore said formerly cited, and first in that of
<HI>Edith Colleges,</HI> in these words,</P>
<P>'Tis Reported I should be the occasion of Perverting the
Lady <HI>Rochester,</HI> and brought a Priest to her; one <HI>Tom∣son,</HI>
alias <HI>Conyers:</HI> I deny it, <HI>all I did</HI> was at the Request
of the Earl of <HI>Rochester,</HI> who gave me a Letter to deliver
to him; which I did, but knew not the Contents; neither
did that Lady report any such thing of me at her death.</P>
<P>There be a great many other strange Reports that I
have heard since I have been a Pris'ner; That I should be
a means to Convert the Countess of <HI>Rochester,</HI> by bringing
one <HI>Thompson</HI> a <HI>Priest</HI> to her. Truly <HI>all that I was con∣cern'd
in,</HI> was some fifteen or sixteen years ago, I Lodged
at Col. <HI>Vernors,</HI> that Married the Lady <HI>Brooks:</HI> The
Family were <HI>Papists,</HI> the <HI>Brooks's</HI> were <HI>Papists,</HI> and there
was this <HI>Thompson;</HI> and I did suppose him a <HI>Priest</HI> in
the House, though I never saw him at Popish Service,
or Worship, though I was there half a year; but come∣ing
afterwards to my Lord <HI>Rochester</HI>'s, about some busi∣ness
I had to do for him, and several other Persons of
Quality, he sent for me one Afternoon from the Parso∣nage
in <HI>Adderbury,</HI> to his House, and his Lady and he
stood together: He sent to me, and asked me if my
Horse were at home? <HI>said he,</HI> I would have you carry
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
this Letter to Mr. <HI>Thompson,</HI> if you are at leisure this Af∣ternoon:
<HI>My Lord I am at leisure to serve you.</HI> So I took
a Letter from his hand, and his <HI>Lady</HI>'s too, as I remem∣ber,
(he made an offer that way) Sealed with his own
Seal, and carried it to <HI>Thompson,</HI> and deliver'd it to him,
and he told me that he would wait upon my Lord, for it
was for some Lands my Lord did offer to raise money for
some occasions. <HI>This is the truth of that Scandal.</HI></P>
<P>Note that in the former Speech he says, <HI>all I did,</HI> was,
<HI>&amp;c.</HI> and in the other <HI>All that I was concern'd in,</HI> was, <HI>&amp;c.</HI>
And at the bottom <HI>[This is the Truth of that Scandal.]</HI>
Giving the Reader to understand by this way of deliver∣ing
himself, that he had spoken the <HI>Truth,</HI> the <HI>whole
Truth,</HI> and <HI>nothing but the Truth; so help him God.</HI></P>
<P>Now to Confront these Peremptory Assertions of his,
It is certain, that the day before the Lady <HI>Rochester</HI> fell
sick, she said that <HI>College</HI> was a <HI>Papist,</HI> in the hearing of
several Persons; having said the same thing also before,
publiquely at the Table of a Lady in that Neighbour∣hood,
as will be sufficiently attested by many People of
unexceptionable Credit, living near the place; if the
matter shall be in such sort question'd, as that it may be
worth the while to prove it, and that the persons con∣cern'd
in the Enquiry shall think fit to own their Names.
The ground of this Honourable Ladies mistake, is sup∣posed
to have been the Zeal of <HI>Colleges</HI> Interessing him∣self
in the good Offices of bringing the said Priest unto
the Lady.</P>
<P>That which he says of carrying a Letter to <HI>Thompson,</HI>
upon such considerations, and in such manner as he repre∣sents
it, is probably a <HI>Truth:</HI> But it is not as he renders it,
<HI>[All that he did,</HI> or <HI>[All that he was concern'd in</HI> upon that
affair; for he has several times told a worthy Gentleman,
a Trustee to the Lord <HI>Rochester,</HI> and divers others, That
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
he the said <HI>College</HI> being about Fourteen years since a
Trooper under the Earl of <HI>Rochester,</HI> my Lord imploy'd
him to bring one <HI>Thompson</HI> a Priest to his Lady, to draw
her to the <HI>Romish Faith;</HI> and that he brought him to my
Lady several times; and that by this <HI>Thompsons</HI> means
she was perverted. This will be prov'd (if Insisted up∣on)
by several Persons of Worth and Credit in and a∣bout
<HI>Bridgwater.</HI> The Inducement to the employing of
<HI>College</HI> upon this Errand, was his being in League at that
time with a Maid-Servant of my Ladies, who was after∣ward
his Second Wife, and made use of as a Proper In∣strument
for the Obliging of <HI>College</HI> to a Service of that
kind. Nor was this the only Letter, as may be unde∣niably
prov'd, that <HI>College</HI> carried upon that subject.
We'l see now what he says to the bus'ness of Mr. <HI>Ser∣geant.</HI></P>
<P>It's said I Harbour'd Priests and Iesuits; and they in∣stance
in one <HI>Sergeant,</HI> who lay at my House in <HI>Carter-Lane,</HI>
Nine years since, by the name of Dr. <HI>Smith,</HI> a Doctor
of Physick; brought to me by one <HI>Monless</HI> an Apothecary in
the <HI>Old Baily;</HI> and one Mr. <HI>Field</HI> a <HI>Wollen-Draper</HI>
within <HI>Ludgate;</HI> and was there as a Dr. of <HI>Physick,</HI> and
<HI>I knew for no other,</HI> (Speech <HI>by</HI> Edith College.</P>
<P>It is said that I had a Priest several years in my House,
viz. <HI>Sergeant</HI> that came over from <HI>Holland</HI> to Discover.
About some ten years ago, that very same man came to me,
but <HI>was a Stranger to me;</HI> and he came to me by the name
of Dr. <HI>Smith,</HI> a Physitian, and there was an Apothecary in
the <HI>Old Bailey,</HI> and a <HI>Linnen-Draper</HI> within <HI>Ludgate</HI> that
came with him. They brought him thither, and took a Cham∣ber,
and lay about half or three quarters of a year, at times,
by the Name of Dr. <HI>Smith,</HI> and as a Physitian. This is the
Truth of that, and no otherwise. This is the Entertainment
of <HI>Sergeant. (Bassets Speech.)</HI></P>
<P><PB N="20" REF="14"/>
Upon the comparing of these two passages, you will
find in the former, that he denys the Knowledge of <HI>Ser∣geant,</HI>
any further than as a Dr. of Physick; and in the
latter, slips it over with saying only that he was a Stran∣ger
when he came to him. Now it is a certain Truth,
(and proveable beyond dispute, so to be) that <HI>College</HI>
knew this Dr. of Physick to be Mr. <HI>Sergeant,</HI> even while
he Lodg'd in his House. And then for the <HI>Draper</HI> (whom
he makes to be a <HI>Linnen-Draper</HI> in the <HI>one</HI> Speech, and
a <HI>Woollen</HI> in the <HI>other,</HI> It is absolutely averr'd (as I have
it from a sure hand) that this Draper never knew
where Mr. <HI>Sergeant</HI> Lodg'd, till he himself told him his
Lodging.</P>
<P>Next to the bus'ness of Sir <HI>William Iennings,</HI> and Mr.
<HI>Masters,</HI> it is remarkable, that though he fenc'd and
shifted upon his Tryal, and takes express notice of them
in his Speech Printed for <HI>Edith College,</HI> yet he makes no
particular mention of them at his last <HI>Speech</HI> by word of
mouth, notwithstanding the weight and effect which
those Witnesses had with the Jury: But in his <HI>Written
Speech,</HI> which was Published by his Relations, you have
these words.</P>
<P>As to what Mr. <HI>Masters</HI> Swore, he was Vnjust to me in
omitting that part of our discourse concerning the Parliament
in <HI>Forty;</HI> For when he Curs'd them, and the Last Parlia∣ment
at <HI>Westminster</HI> also; and said <HI>they were alike;</HI> and
charged them in <HI>Forty</HI> with beginning the <HI>War,</HI> and cutting
off the <HI>Kings Head:</HI> I denied both, and said it was the
<HI>Papists</HI> that began that War, and the Death of the King
was the Fatal Consequence of it, which Mr. <HI>Charleton</HI> the
Draper in Pouls Church-yard countessisse; the discourse be∣ing
at the further end of his Shop, and he present; into
which, <HI>Masters</HI> seeing me go, came apace from towards his
<PB N="21" REF="14"/>
own Shop, and as I believe, on purpose to Quarrel with me,
for which God forgive him.</P>
<P>I shall have occasion by and by to handle this Point
more at large. So that no more needs to be said at pre∣sent,
but that <HI>College</HI> has several times in Mr. <HI>Charletons</HI>
Company, <HI>Iustifi'd the Proceedings</HI> of 1641. and pro∣nounced
the <HI>King</HI> to be a <HI>Papist,</HI> as Mr. <HI>Charleton</HI> I pre∣sume
will easily call to mind, if there should be any oc∣casion
to refresh his memory upon that subject. [And that
which he says to Sir <HI>William Iennings</HI> likewise, is no more
than an <HI>Empty Cavil,</HI> without any colour of a <HI>Defence.]</HI></P>
<P><HI>To come now to the Ill Usage that he Complains of</HI>
[I was <HI>(says he in his last Speech)</HI> under most strange Cir∣cumstances
as ever any man was. I was kept Pris'ner so
close in the <HI>Tower,</HI> that I could have no Conversation with
any, though I was certain the Popish Lords had it every day
there, though I could have none. I could not tell the Wit∣nesses
that were to Swear against me; I could not tell what it
was they Swore against me; for I could have no Copy of the
Indictment, nor no way possible to make any preparation to
make my defence, as I ought to have done, and might have
done by Law. I had no liberty to do any thing, <HI>as I am
a dying man.]</HI></P>
<P>Now for the Truth of this, I shall refer the Reader to
his <HI>Two Petitions</HI> to his Majesty; the <HI>one</HI> of <HI>Iuly</HI> 28. and
the <HI>other</HI> of <HI>August</HI> 11. prefix'd to his <HI>Tryal,</HI> and two <HI>Or∣ders
of Council</HI> thereupon. In the <HI>Former,</HI> he prays <HI>that
leave may be given to Mr.</HI> Thomas Smith, <HI>and Mr.</HI> Robert
West, <HI>to come to him; and also to have the use of Pen,
Ink, and Paper, in order only to make his Legal and Iust
Defence; and also to have the Comfort of seeing his two
Children;</HI> which was all granted him as he desired. In
his <HI>Second Petition</HI> of <HI>August</HI> 11. he makes a Preambular
Acknowledgment in these following words.</P>
<P><PB N="22" REF="15"/>
In full assurance therefore of the great Iustice and Clemen∣cy
of your Majesty, and this Honourable Board, which he
hath lately had some <HI>Experience</HI> of, and doth with all
Humility and Thankfulness acknowledge, <HI>&amp;c. And then
he further prays,</HI></P>
<P>Your Petitioner doth humbly beseech your Majesty and
this Honourable Board, that he may have a Copy of the In∣dictment
against him, or the particular Charges of it: That
his Council and Solicitor may have free Access to, and private
Conference with him; and because their own private affairs,
or other accidents may call away some of his Council from his
Assistance, that Mr. <HI>Wallop,</HI> Mr. <HI>Smith,</HI> Mr. <HI>Thompson,</HI>
Mr. <HI>Datnel,</HI> Mr. <HI>West</HI> of the <HI>Middle-Temple,</HI> Mr. <HI>Holles</HI>
of <HI>Lincolns-Inn</HI> Mr. <HI>Rotherham,</HI> Mr. <HI>Lovel,</HI> Mr. <HI>Rowny</HI>
of <HI>Creys-Iun,</HI> Mr. <HI>Pollexsin,</HI> Mr. <HI>Ward</HI> of the <HI>Inner-Temple,</HI>
may be assign'd him for <HI>Council;</HI> and <HI>Aaron
Smith</HI> for his <HI>Sollicitor,</HI> and that he may have a Copy of the
<HI>Jurors</HI> to be return'd upon his Tryal some days before his
Tryal. <HI>Hereupon it was Order'd by his Majesty in
Council, That the Friends and Relations of Stephen
College, a Pris'ner in the Tower, shall have liberty
of Visiting, and freely Conversing with him, and
the Lieutenant of the Tower, (having first caused
their Names to be taken in Writing) is to suffer
such Friends and Relations to have Access to the said
Stephen College without any Interruption from
time to time accordingly.</HI></P>
<P>Here's a Clamour, ye see, upon a False and Ground∣less
Suggestion, deliver'd upon the Credit of a Dying
Man, as the true state of his Condition, when yet it was
no other in effect, then the saying over of his Lesson from
the dictate of his Sollicitor.</P>
<P>Before ye Plead <HI>(says</HI> Aaron Smith <HI>in his Paper of</HI> In∣structions)
speak to this purpose.</P>
<P><PB N="23" REF="15"/>
My Lords, I have been used not only unlike an <HI>Innocent,</HI>
or an <HI>English-man,</HI> but I believe more barbarously than any
Convicted Villain under the Tyranny of <HI>Turky,</HI> or <HI>France:</HI>
When I was first Apprehended, I was, contrary to the Privi∣leges
of a Citizen of <HI>London,</HI> hurried out from thence before a
Secretary of State. <HI>Here's the King and his Government
Charg'd with</HI> Tyranny, <HI>and his Majesties Authority sub∣jected,
even in a case of</HI> Treason, <HI>to the jurisdiction of my</HI>
Lord Mayor. [I might with as much Iustice have been hang'd
at <HI>Tyburn</HI> by the way, as to be brought hither to be <HI>Murder'd,</HI>
with a little more <HI>Formality. And then a little lower:</HI> [I
will not be Murder'd in Hugger mugger.] Answer thus <HI>(says</HI>
Aaron Smiths <HI>Paper)</HI> if the Attorney General, or any other of
the Kings Councel Interrupt ye; or when you have done, tell ye,
you Arraign the Iustice of the Nation.</P>
<P>When you come to open your own Evidence <HI>(says</HI> Smith's
Paper <HI>again)</HI> speak to this purpose: [I hope you will not bring
so much Scandal upon your selves <HI>[My Lords and Gentlemen
of the Jury]</HI> as to be the <HI>Popes Drudges;</HI> and give the
first blow to the <HI>Protestant Cause,</HI> by Convicting me upon
such Infamous Evidence. <HI>And lastly,</HI> Give an Account
of your going down to <HI>Oxford,</HI> and that you went, be∣cause
<HI>Haines</HI> had Sworn the Papists design'd to destroy
the Parliament there.] <HI>So that</HI> College, <HI>ye see, was In∣structed,
not only in a Scandalous method of Reviling the
Court, but he was also told what Cause he should Assign
for his going to</HI> Oxford, <HI>and directed to cast it upon</HI>
Haines'<HI>s</HI> Oath, <HI>as a colour rather of his</HI> Sollicitors Invention,
<HI>than the</HI> true <HI>and</HI> real Motive <HI>that carry'd him</HI> thither.</P>
<P>Before I go any further, it will become me to distinguish
betwixt <HI>Colleges Two Speeches.</HI> The one was deliver'd by
<HI>word of mouth,</HI> upon the Cart, at the time of his Execu∣tion.
The other was convey'd from him out of the Castle,
to some of his Relations in <HI>Writing;</HI> and this was the
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
Paper, which at the first he deny'd the sending of, and af∣terwards
confess'd.</P>
<P>Having now laid open what it is, or rather what it is
not, which in <HI>Colleges</HI> case is call'd the <HI>Protestant Religion;</HI>
the meaning of <HI>Colleges Protestants</HI> and <HI>Papists:</HI> Having
prov'd the <HI>Libellous Pictures</HI> upon him, and given the Rea∣der
a tast of his <HI>Vnfaithful dealing,</HI> even to the last: We
shall here proceed to a fair and impartial Deliberation up∣on
the subject matter of his <HI>Charge,</HI> and leave the Reader
to his own thoughts, whether <HI>Guilty or not Guilty</HI> upon the
whole matter.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§. 6. Notes upon <HI>Colleges</HI> ordinary way of
<HI>Discourse</HI> and <HI>Conversation.</HI></HEAD>
<P>IN my way to the Capital Branch of his Charge <HI>(i. e.</HI>
the Design of <HI>Seizing the King,</HI> and <HI>Subverting the
Government)</HI> it will not be amiss to take some notice of
the humor of the man in the ordinary way of his <HI>Behavi∣our</HI>
and <HI>Conversation:</HI> The Biass of his <HI>Inclinations</HI> and <HI>Opi∣nions,</HI>
and other circumstantial Discoveries of his <HI>Imagina∣tions</HI>
and <HI>Purposes,</HI> with a respect to those Seditious ends.
And yet it may be looked upon, perhaps as an Idle and a
Superfluous undertaking, to put my self to the trouble of
proving that by Particular Instances, which might be as
well done by a General Appeal to all the Clubs and Cof∣fee-houses
about this Town wheresoever he haunted: for
they can every one of them bear witness to his Intemperan∣ces
against the Government; and that when he was not ma∣king
himself and the Company sport in his way of Ridi∣culing
the King, the Duke of <HI>York,</HI> the Church, and the
Court, the man was as good as out of his Element.</P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="16"/>
They told me <HI>(says he, speaking of some of the Lords of
the Council) there was Treason</HI> Sworn against me; truly
they surprized me when they said so; for of all things in the
world I thought my self as free from that, as any man. I
asked them if any man living had the confidence to Swear
Treason against me? They said <HI>Several, Three or Four,</HI> as
I remember. <HI>Last Speech.</HI></P>
<P>As to what <HI>Dugdale, Smith, Turberville,</HI> and <HI>Hains</HI> Swore
against me, they did Swear such Treason that nothing but a
Mad-man would have Trusted any body with. <HI>Ibid.</HI></P>
<P><HI>And again</HI> [It is a very <HI>unlikely</HI> thing that I should speak
<HI>Treason</HI> to <HI>Dugdale.]</HI></P>
<P>There are two things now worthy of Consideration in
this Point (even setting aside the positive Proofs of the
Treason spoken.) First, <HI>Did</HI> he speak the Treason where∣of
he stands Accused ot <HI>not?</HI> Secondly, It may be a Que∣stion,
<HI>What</HI> it is that he calls <HI>Treason?</HI> It is notoriously
known to most that ever knew the man, that it was his
common Guise to talk of his Majesty at such a Desperate
Rate, that People were afraid to give him the Hearing;
and that he has been caution'd hundreds of times to keep
his Tongue in's Head; or, if he did not, <HI>he would talk
himself at last to the Gallows.</HI> Why should it be such a <HI>Sur∣prize,</HI>
now, to this Rash and Violent Man, to hear that
there was <HI>Treason</HI> Sworn against him; when every man
(almost) that kept him Company, warn'd him of it, and
foretold him what it would come to at last? And then,
how frivolous again is the <HI>Manner</HI> of his Discharging him∣self
from the Treasons Sworn against him by the <HI>Witnesses?</HI>
None but a <HI>Mad-man</HI> (he says) would have <HI>Trusted</HI> any
body in such a case. And yet it appears from the Tenor of
his whole Conversation, and the frequent Advices of his
Friends, that he Trusted any man that came next, with
as much as that amounts to. And now once more, to the
<PB N="26" REF="17"/>
<HI>unlikelihood</HI> of his speaking such things to <HI>Dugdale:</HI> Let
the Reader ask and answer himself, as to the <HI>Probability</HI> of
his being as free with <HI>Dugdale,</HI> as he was with <HI>other</HI> peo∣ple.
Let not any man take this for a Rambling Story up∣on
a bare Hear-say; for I am ready to prove and justifie the
truth of every particular: Not as the Author of the <HI>No
Protestant Plot</HI> takes upon him, with an <HI>[I do assure all the
world,</HI> &amp;c (Page 19.) <HI>My self and divers others have seen
the Original,</HI> &amp;c. (Page 18.) And this same <HI>I,</HI> and <HI>My
Self,</HI> a <HI>Quidam</HI> all this <HI>time,</HI> that a man does not know
where to find: But for the Satisfaction of any man that
doubts, I have here expos'd the Authors name with this
Pamphlet.</P>
<P>They told me <HI>(says</HI> College <HI>again)</HI> it was Sworn against me
that I had a design to pull the King out of <HI>Whitehal,</HI> and to
serve him as his Father was serv'd, or to that purpose: The
<HI>Loggerhead, his Father,</HI> or that kind of Language. I <HI>did
deny it then,</HI> and <HI>do now deny it,</HI> upon my <HI>Death. Last
Speech.</HI></P>
<P>This Denial I suppose, speaks to both the Members of
this Period: The <HI>Design</HI> upon the Person of the <HI>King;</HI>
and the Villany of the <HI>Foul Language</HI> upon his Late, Bles∣sed
<HI>Father.</HI> To the <HI>Former</HI> we have allotted a Section by
it self, and the Latter may be fairly concluded (I think)
out of his own mouth. First (says he) <HI>I thought that the
Parliament that sate last at</HI> Westminster, <HI>did stand up for
the Peoples Rights after the same manner that the Parliament
in Forty did,</HI> (Tryal, Page 83.) So that after a most abomi∣nable
Scandal upon the <HI>last Parliament</HI> at <HI>Westminster</HI> in
the <HI>Comparison,</HI> he justifies the <HI>Rebellion</HI> in the <HI>Application.</HI>
And then again, <HI>I did maintain</HI> (says he) <HI>that they</HI> (the Par∣liament
of Forty) <HI>were an Honest Good Parliament, and
much of opinion with the Parliament that sate last at</HI> West∣minster,
<HI>which was for the true Interest of the Nation,</HI> Page 81.
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
Now if I understand this matter aright, It is Tacitly to call
the King all the Tyrants and Murderers which that Traite∣rous
Faction call'd him. And besides, What's the meaning
of <HI>[Like Father Like Son]</HI> in his <HI>Raree Show?</HI> But <HI>First,</HI>
as appears by the Context to Involve them both in <HI>the same
Fate:</HI> And <HI>Secondly</HI> to represent them both under <HI>the same
Character.</HI> That is to say (in short) to apply all those Bruta∣lities
of Language which he has in that Libel and else∣where,
bestow'd upon the <HI>Son,</HI> to the Reproach and Dis∣honour
of his Martyr'd <HI>Father.</HI> To finish this point, He
had a kind of <HI>Idiome</HI> by himself, and seldom Discours'd
of his <HI>Majesty,</HI> his <HI>Royal Highness,</HI> the <HI>Hierarchy,</HI> or the
<HI>Privy Council,</HI> but in the Style of <HI>Old Rowley, Mack,
Tantivies</HI> and <HI>Tories.</HI> [Old Rowley (says he) <HI>is as errant
a Papist as his Brother.]</HI> And this was his note at every turn.
[Old Rowley (says he again) <HI>cares not a half-penny what
becomes of the Crown, or how he leaves it in Debt, or what
becomes of his People as to matter of Religion,</HI> &amp;c.] At an
other time <HI>[They are come</HI> (says he) <HI>to</HI> change <HI>Candles at
Court</HI> already; <HI>but we'l make them</HI> eat <HI>'em too, before we have
done. [When we have done with the</HI> Papists (says he in an∣other
Company) <HI>We'l do well enough with the</HI> Bishops.]</P>
<P>Now here's another Passage to a very honest man of his
own Trade, and a Loyal Subject. This person being out
of Town about a week before the opening of the <HI>Oxford-Parliament,</HI>
fell into Company with <HI>College;</HI> well
Mounted and a Case of Pistols before him, not far from
<HI>Enfield. Mr.</HI> College (says he) <HI>what will the Parliament do
at</HI> Oxford? By God (says <HI>College)</HI> I know what they'l
do. They'l begin with the Bill of Exclusion. The King
has no money, and he gets not a penny without it. <HI>Well</HI>
(says the other) <HI>but what if his Majesty will not pass it?
We shall see then</HI> (says <HI>College) who are the</HI> Papists. <HI>We'l run</HI>
them <HI>down</HI> first, <HI>and then we shall do well enough with the</HI>
<PB N="28" REF="18"/>
Clergy. <HI>We'l level them with the Ground. We are Ten to
One.</HI> Is not this a Broad sign made at the King? And does
it not precisely answer the very Pinch of the Evidence?
And methinks he spake home to <HI>another Ioyner</HI> too, that
charg'd him with the neglect of his <HI>Trade;</HI> and all the
reply he made, was the laying his hand upon his Sword,
as if he had said, <HI>This is it that I intend to trust to.</HI></P>
<P>There are so many instances of his Pragmatical medling
Humor, that the recital of them would cost more Time
and Paper than the thing is worth. A Gentleman in dis∣course
with <HI>College</HI> in the <HI>Castle</HI> at <HI>Oxford,</HI> was telling him
(after many professions of his Innocency) <HI>Mr.</HI> College
(says he) <HI>you know I have my self at</HI> Cornbury <HI>heard you
many times talk undutifully of the Government. Now me∣thinks,
you that are but a Mechanick should not presume to
meddle with things so much above ye.</HI> Was it any harm (says
he) for <HI>Amos to leave his Cows?</HI> Nay he was so Bold and
Inconsiderate when things went otherwise than he would
have them, that upon the Dissolution of the <HI>Last Westmin∣ster
Parliament,</HI> he went presently away to <HI>Dick's Coffee-House</HI>
in a Hufl. <HI>Well</HI> (says he) <HI>I perceive here's no good to
be done. We must e'en draw our Swords and Fight it over again.</HI>
These were the words, or to this effect.</P>
<P>The Turbulence of his Spirit was seen upon all occasi∣ons,
where there was but the least colour for the fastening
of a Scandal upon the King, the Church, and his Majesties
Ministers of State and Justice. His Vein lay much toward
<HI>Doggerel</HI> and <HI>Designing,</HI> as he has plentifully given the
world to understand in his Learned <HI>Drawings,</HI> which are
still charged with the utmost Rudeness, Malice, and Scur∣rility
imaginable: Insomuch that the Treason of his <HI>Heart</HI>
is laid as open in those Cuts, as that of his <HI>Tongue</HI> was at
his Trial; with this single Difference, that the one was
only a wish, and the other an <HI>Overt Act,</HI> and a declared Re∣solution.</P>
<P><PB N="29" REF="18"/>
This device call'd the <HI>Catholique Gamesters,</HI> is a vene∣mous
Libel upon all the Orders of the Government; and
first upon the <HI>King himself,</HI> charging all the Pretended Mis∣carriages
of State, in <HI>Shew,</HI> upon the Papists, but in <HI>Truth,</HI>
and <HI>Effect,</HI> upon his <HI>Majesty.</HI></P>
<P>It is a Libel upon the <HI>House of Peers,</HI> by the Culling out
of so many Lords by Name, under the Title of <HI>Protestants,</HI>
and Representing in that number only <HI>Two Bishops,</HI> that
is to say, <HI>Hereford</HI> and <HI>Lincoln,</HI> implying all the rest to be
<HI>Papists.</HI> In the House of <HI>Commons,</HI> he tells us of <HI>Pensioners
who Voted by Contents, got Bills to Pass against the Common
Good,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>And then he descends to the <HI>Bench,</HI> and the <HI>Iury,</HI> where
he brings in the Pope, speaking of the Priests and Jesuites
in these words:
<Q><L>Hell keep the rest from <HI>Justice</HI> (we call <HI>Fury,)</HI></L>
<L>And send them <HI>Wakeman's</HI> or a <HI>Gascoign Jury:</HI></L>
<L>Pick'd, Brib'd, Instructed how to murther Truth,</L>
<L><HI>From</HI> Grand St. Martins Bull, <HI>and</HI> Cits Wide Mouth.</L></Q>
And take them quite through, they are all of the same
Style and Design: And I would have any man tell me
now, if a body may not charitably enough conclude, that
whosoever <HI>Defames</HI> the Government at This rate, wishes
it <HI>Overturn'd;</HI> and if he had but Power and Opportunity,
would do his part toward it. I should be ungrateful, now
I am upon this subject, if I should not acknowledge the
Honor he has done me in divers of his Emblematical Pie∣ces.
He has presented the world with <HI>Six Towzers,</HI> and
<HI>L'Estrange</HI> with <HI>Four Fair pair of Gallows.</HI></P>
<P>Here's nothing hitherto, but what may very well pass
for the Preamble to a Conspiracy, and he that considers
his Haunts, the Company he kept, the Access he had to
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
the Private Cabals and Consultations of the Faction; to∣gether
with his forwardness to thrust himself into all Po∣pular
Brawls and <HI>Contests,</HI> and that Stubborn Obstinacy
which was natural to him, will undoubtedly look upon
him as an instrument every way qualified for such a pur∣pose.
As they were carrying away <HI>Sam. Harris</HI> about
the Treasonous Libel that cost Mr. <HI>Fitz-Harris</HI> his Life,
and a Crowd of People about him, a very honest Gentle∣man,
a friend of mine, saw <HI>College</HI> whispering with a Per∣son
then in Power, from whom he went immediately to
make his way to <HI>Harris;</HI> but the press was so great that
he was forc'd to deliver his Message to him over Three or
Four Heads, and so call'd to him just over the shoulder of
the Gentleman, my friend. <HI>Come</HI> Sam. (says he) <HI>take a
good heart, Mr.</HI> Such a one—(naming the person) <HI>makes
no doubt but to bring ye off.</HI></P>
<P>And to shew ye now what Credit <HI>College</HI> had with his
Party, (but to what purpose in this particular I cannot say)
He took his Hat which was very broad Brim'd, and hold∣ing
it in his hands with the inside upward, <HI>I have given
away</HI> (says he) <HI>twice as much money as this Hat would hold,
Brims and all.</HI> Now I suppose this money was not thrown
away to make Ducks and Drakes; so that I cannot recon∣cile
this Declaration of his to a certain Passage in his Last
Speech, <HI>viz. [I take God to witness, I never had one Six∣pence,
or any thing else, to carry on any Design; and if it
were to save my life now, I cann't Charge any man in the
world with any design against the Government (as God is my
Witness) or against his Majesty, or any other Person.]</HI></P>
<P>The Explication of this Clause depends upon the know∣ledge
of what is meant by these words, [ANY DESIGN:]
for the Expression is too <HI>large</HI> to be <HI>True,</HI> if it be taken in
the <HI>Latitude:</HI> and if it be understood with a <HI>Restriction,
i.e.</HI> that he knew of no Design against the <HI>King,</HI> or the
<PB N="31" REF="19"/>
<HI>Government,</HI> the Principle of Forty one (by him asserted
in his Tryal) brings him off, when the Rebellion it self
was declared to be <HI>FOR</HI> the <HI>King,</HI> and the <HI>Government;</HI>
so that 'tis but his placing the Government in the <HI>People,</HI>
or the <HI>Two Houses,</HI> to Countenance the Equivocation:
And finally, The disclaiming of a Design against any other
person goes a little too far methinks; for by his own Con∣fession
there was a Design carried on against the <HI>Papists.</HI></P>
<P>It would be proper enough in this place to render some
Account of his Deportment at <HI>Oxford</HI> in the <HI>Prison.</HI> He
was, at first coming, Stubborn and Captious, Insisting up∣on
the Rights of an <HI>English-man,</HI> and Menacing his Keeper
till he was brought to better Terms, by telling him plain∣ly
what he was to trust to. Nothing put him more out of
Patience, then telling him of his <HI>Pictures.</HI> In his behavi∣our
in Company he seem'd always to be very little con∣cern'd;
but his Keeper says he had terrible Agonies when
he was by himself that kept him waking sometimes whole
nights. A little before he dy'd, Mr. <HI>Gregory</HI> the <HI>Sheriff</HI>
came into his Room with an Order to have his Body de∣liver'd
<HI>whole</HI> to his Friends. Upon the sight of the Seal,
he leapt from his Bed with a great deal of Joy; expect∣ing
it might have been a Pardon; but upon finding the
mistake, he threw himself down again in a deep Disquiet.
He says in his <HI>Dying words (Printed for E.</HI> College) That
the Messenger who brought him the Message of his Death,
told him he might save his Life, if he would confess who
was the cause of his coming to <HI>Oxford,</HI> and upon what
Account, which was ill done of the Messenger; for it was
not only <HI>without,</HI> but contrary to <HI>Orders.</HI></P>
<P>He was in the main very ignorant of any thing of <HI>Re∣ligion;</HI>
and he would say that he <HI>found,</HI> and that he was
<HI>guided</HI> by the Spirit; and this was his perpetual Refuge.
What Principles he had were <HI>Enthusiastical.</HI> As for In∣stance,
<PB N="32" REF="20"/>
He said that Eating and Drinking in the Eucharist,
and so washing in Baptism was to be understood in a Spi∣ritual
Sense, aud declar'd that he receiv'd no benefit by
the Prayers of the Church. He spake of the <HI>Quakers</HI> as
<HI>the People of God,</HI> and particularly of one that had been
with him as <HI>the honestest man that ever he knew.</HI> It was re∣ply'd
to him by a Reverend Divine, that the <HI>Quakers</HI> de∣ny'd
in effect, <HI>Christianity it self:</HI> As the <HI>Two Sacraments,</HI>
and a <HI>Succession of Ministers.</HI> And next they deny'd both
the <HI>Divinity,</HI> and <HI>Satisfaction of our Saviour;</HI> naming <HI>Pen,</HI>
whom <HI>College</HI> said he very well knew, but did not own
him in that Principle. His Favourite was Mr. <HI>Baxter,</HI>
whom he heard more than Dr. <HI>Owen;</HI> and his Opinion was,
that God had a <HI>Church</HI> in all the <HI>Sects</HI> in <HI>England.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ 7. <HI>College</HI> Iustifies the Grounds and
the Proceedings of the late Rebellion.</HEAD>
<P>AFter these Pregnant and Undeniable Proofs of so ma∣ny
Virulent and Audacious Outrages upon the <HI>Per∣son,</HI>
and <HI>Dignity</HI> of his Majesty, and the very <HI>Form,</HI> as
well as the <HI>Administration</HI> of the Government. It remains
now only to be considered how far the Malefactor was
Principled toward the Actuating of that Malice, and by
what Methods he proponnded the putting of those Dis∣loyal
Inclinations into Execution.</P>
<P>First, As to his <HI>Opinion</HI> of the <HI>Sovereignty,</HI> according to
the Constitution of this Kingdom, we shall not need to
look any further for't, than into his own words, and the
inevitable Conclusion which naturally arises from them.
He appeals from Mr. <HI>Masters</HI> to Mr. <HI>Charlton</HI> in St. <HI>Paul's
Church-yard,</HI> about his Justifying the Parliament of <HI>Forty,</HI>
<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
and yet it is a known Truth, that he has several times ju∣stify'd
that Parliament in the hearing of Mr. <HI>Charleton.</HI> He
does acknowledge in his Tryal (Page 82.) That he said,
<HI>That Parliament did nothing but what they had</HI> Just Cause
<HI>for, and that the Parliament that last sate at</HI> Westminster,
<HI>was of the same opinion.</HI> Now in saying this, he takes up∣on
himself the Owning of all the Principles, whereupon
they proceeded in that Controversie betwixt the <HI>King</HI> and
the <HI>Two Houses:</HI> And in so doing, strips the King of all
his Regalities, and Lodges the Supremacy in the Lords
and Commons. <HI>[The</HI> Papists <HI>began the War</HI> (he says) <HI>The</HI>
Papists <HI>broke off the Treaty at</HI> Uxbridge; <HI>and the</HI> Papists
<HI>cut off the Kings Head,</HI> Page 81.] And in that case, He
Justifies the Old Parliament. What can be clearer now,
than that if this King should have been press'd upon the
same Terms with his Royal Father, After the same manner
as the <HI>Papists Began,</HI> and <HI>Pursu'd</HI> the Former War, and
brought his <HI>Late Majesty</HI> to the <HI>Block,</HI> Just so it should
have been call'd <HI>another Popish Exploit,</HI> the Reducing of
this <HI>King</HI> to the <HI>same Extremities:</HI> And as they made the
<HI>Late King,</HI> the <HI>Church,</HI> and the <HI>Royal Party, Papists</HI> in
the <HI>One Rebellion,</HI> they would have treated <HI>this King,
Church,</HI> and all his <HI>Faithful Subjects</HI> too, as <HI>Papists</HI> too in
<HI>another Rebellion.</HI> These are the <HI>Oxford Papists</HI> fairly
Expounded. And under this Ambiguity it is, that he Co∣vers
and Disguises his pretext of Faith and Affection to
the King and his Government: That is to say, as he in∣tends
the Kings Authority to be Virtually Resolv'd into
the Two Houses: And this Seditious Maxim is a little
more expresly set forth in his <HI>Raree Show.</HI> In which Libel,
there is a Figure of a Man with a Chests at's Back, which
he Explains to bemeant of the King, with the Lords and
Commons in a Box, and Pluck'd down in the Mire by
Three Fellows, with these words to illustrate that Passage,
<Q><PB N="34" REF="21"/>
<L>So, so, the Gyant's down,</L>
<L>Let's MASTERS out of Pound, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L></Q>
In which two Verses is laid open, both the Design of De∣throning
the King, and in the word MASTERS the Do∣ctrine
of the Supremacy of the Two Houses.</P>
<P>Now for a further Confirmation of his Opinion, He
declar'd to Mr. <HI>Crosthwait</HI> in the <HI>Castle</HI> at <HI>Oxford,</HI> That he
believ'd it lawful to <HI>Resist</HI> the King, in case he should in∣vade
his <HI>Property;</HI> and he endeavour'd to defend it by
several Arguments, till at length he was (at least) seeming∣ly
Convinc'd of his Mistake. This makes it abundantly
Evident what he thought of the <HI>Lawfulness</HI> of such <HI>Resi∣stance,</HI>
if the Case of <HI>Property</HI> should come to be the <HI>Que∣stion;</HI>
And it rests only now to make it out that he did
take <HI>Property</HI> to be the Question; and then all his Preten∣sions
of Respect to the King, and to the Government fall
to the Ground: As what's the meaning of that Passage in
his <HI>Raree Show,</HI> where he charges the King with
<Q><L>Fleecing <HI>Englands</HI> Flocks,</L>
<L>Long Fed with Bits and Knocks, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L></Q>
but to denote the <HI>King</HI> to be a <HI>Tyrant</HI> and an <HI>Oppressor?</HI></P>
<P>Now to sum up briefly what is already delivered; Here
are all the <HI>Fore-runners</HI> of, and <HI>Dispositions</HI> to a <HI>Rebellion,</HI>
as clear as the Noon-day, and <HI>College</HI> deeply engag'd in
every Point. First the General Pretence of a Design up∣on
the <HI>Protestant Religion,</HI> as the Foundation of a <HI>Popu∣lar
Discontent.</HI> 2dly. <HI>That General Religion,</HI> in such a
manner as it is represented, is not any where to be found.
3dly. Under the Notion of the <HI>Papists,</HI> to Invade this Re∣ligion,
the <HI>Church Establish'd,</HI> the <HI>King</HI> and his <HI>Party</HI> are
<PB N="35" REF="21"/>
most apparently struck at. 4thly. All manner of <HI>Defama∣tory
Libels</HI> are <HI>Contriv'd, Publish'd,</HI> and <HI>Promoted</HI> by <HI>Col∣lege
himself</HI> toward the Enflaming of a <HI>Sedition.</HI> 5thly.
It is Remarkable, <HI>Colleges Shuffling</HI> and <HI>Equivocating,</HI> to
Evade the <HI>Charge,</HI> which is, nevertheless made out against
him at last. 6thly. There is an Undeniable Discovery of
his <HI>Disaffection,</HI> even to the Degree of a <HI>Mortal Hatred,</HI>
both to <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>State.</HI> And 7thly. Considering the Me∣thod
of <HI>Colleges</HI> Proceedings, with the Tendency of his
<HI>Practices, Principles,</HI> and <HI>Persuasions,</HI> what could any
man believe less (even without any further Evidence)
than that <HI>College Meditated,</HI> and <HI>Designed</HI> the Improve∣ment
of all Occasions to the Subverting of the <HI>Govern∣ment;</HI>
and, in such manner too, as it is imputed to him?</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§. 8. There was a Design upon the King
at <HI>Oxford,</HI> and <HI>College</HI> manifestly En∣gag'd
in the <HI>Conspiracy.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THat there was a Plot to be Executed at <HI>Oxon,</HI> will
be granted, I presume, by any man that has but
eyes in's head, and looks that way: And <HI>this</HI> a <HI>Republican
Plot</HI> too, carried on under the pretended Apprehension
of a <HI>Popish</HI> one. But the Multitude were to be mov'd and
prepar'd for't: And see the course now that they took to
work upon the Passions of the Common People. The first
thing to be done was throughly to possess them that the
<HI>Papists had a Design upon the Parliament at</HI> Oxford; and
consequently upon the <HI>Protestant Religion;</HI> the <HI>Liberties</HI>
and <HI>Properties</HI> of the <HI>English Nation.</HI> To this purpose,
How many Impudent and Ridiculous <HI>Shams,</HI> by Coun∣terfeit
Tickets, and Letters were Expos'd in the daily Pa∣pers
<PB N="36" REF="22"/>
of Intelligence, which at that time were swallowed
whole, as the very Oracles of the <HI>Vulgar? [Several Pa∣pers</HI>
(says the <HI>Protestant Mercury,</HI> Numb. 24.) <HI>have been
dropt about the City, that there would be a</HI> Massacre at Ox∣ford
<HI>on the 25th. instant, and that the 5th. of</HI> November
<HI>will be turned into the 25th. of</HI> March, (1681.) <HI>and one of
these was thrown into a Shop in</HI> Grace-Church-street. But
you shall now have the Letter it self at large, with all its
appertinences.</P>
<P><HI>London, March</HI> 16. This very morning, Letters were
found in several places in this City, unseal'd; purporting a
warning of a Dangerous Design to Destroy the Parliament;
particularly one Letter was found in Mr. <HI>Brett's</HI> Shop,
a <HI>Linnen-Draper</HI> in <HI>Grace-Church-street,</HI> which was
supposed to be put in at a Cleft in the Window: His man
finding it when he open'd the Shop, Communicated the same
to his Master, who caused him to subscribe the Paper, that he
might be able to testifie it was the same that he found; and
then Presented it to one of our <HI>City Magistrates,</HI> who we
suppose by this time has made his Majesty acquainted with the
Contents, which were as followeth:</P>
<LETTER>
<HEAD>To all the Noble Members of this most Honorable en∣suing
Parliament in General.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Noble Lords and Gentlemen,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>Though I dare not, nor am I in a condition to discover the
whole substance of some Hellish Designs now on foot against
his Majesties Royal Person, and against you all at <HI>Oxford;</HI>
yet though I was sure to be Racked for it, I must and will give
you a Hint of them as followeth.</P>
<P>Remember the Fifth of <HI>November,</HI> which is now to be the
25th. of <HI>March;</HI> which, if not prevented, will be the utter
destruction of both King and Parliament, and all <HI>True Pro∣testants</HI>
in his Majesties Dominions.</P>
<P><PB N="37" REF="22"/>
And if that fail, beware of many thousands that lie in wait
for your Lives, whose Design is so closely carried, that it will,
I doubt, be a hard matter to discover it, until it be too late.</P>
<P>Mark well what I say, and make not slight of it, as ye ten∣der
your Lives and Fortunes, and the Kingdoms safety. I
say, make not slight of it, as you tender your Lives and For∣tunes,
and the Kingdoms safety.</P>
<P>I am in a mean condition, and under many Afflictions, but
cannot discover my self as yet. Thus wishing you all happy
success, I take leave.</P>
<CLOSER><POSTSCRIPT>
<HEAD>This Letter was Superscribed as followeth.</HEAD>
<P>To all <HI>True Protestants,</HI> who love the King and Parlia∣ment,
whosoever finds this Note, let him with all speed repair
to some Elected Members of the <HI>Parliament, and present it
to them.</HI> (Ben. Harris'<HI>s Protestant Domestique, Numb.
107.)</HI></P>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P><HI>You shall see now how the humor is followed,</HI>
Numb. 110.</P>
<LETTER>
<HEAD>A Letter importing some Cursed and Treasonable Designs
still Carrying on (by the Ever Plotting Papists) against his
Majesties Royal Person, and the Protestant Religion, being
lately found in the Wood of <HI>Bally-Holly</HI> in the County of
<HI>Cork,</HI> in the Kingdom of <HI>Ireland,</HI> by a Gentleman of the
County of <HI>Lymrick</HI> as he Travelled through that Wood: He
thought it of that Concern to the Publique, that he immediate∣ly
gave it to the Earl of <HI>Barrimore,</HI> to be by him transmitted
to his Grace the Duke of <HI>Ormond,</HI> Lord Lieutenant of that
Kingdom, which was done (as we are inform'd) by the said
Earl accordingly. A True Copy of which Letter followeth,
<HI>viz.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Brother David,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I received a Letter lately, wherein I understand that we
shall go on with our Design before <HI>Easter-day.</HI> We shall
<PB N="38" REF="23"/>
have Encouragements to destroy <HI>Heretiques,</HI> Lord <HI>Br.</HI> will be
one of the Persons to destroy the <HI>Heretical King,</HI> and <HI>Mon∣mouth.</HI>
Encourage all our Friends to keep their Arm pri∣vate.
I am</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours till death, <HI>Allen Condon.</HI></SIGNED>
<DATELINE><DATE>Jan. 8.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P><HI>Superscribed to</HI> David Raach, Parish-Priest <HI>of</HI> Bally-Holly.
<HI>This was Publish'd</HI> April 1. 1681.</P>
<P>There would be no end, if I should go through with all
the Cheats upon that Juncture, of the same stamp. One
more only and I have done.</P>
<P>Letters from <HI>Ireland</HI> say that there was a Great Leading
Priest, a man of great Request among the <HI>Popish Party,</HI> ha∣ving
been very Active in carrying on their Designs, was some∣what
troubled in Conscience (being upon his Death-bed) at
some things which he had kept secret, sent for some <HI>Prote∣stants</HI>
of the Neighborhood, unknown to the <HI>Papists,</HI> whom he
had formerly been obliged to, to come and see him e're he de∣parted;
who coming according to his request, the Priest Ex∣pressed
himself to this Effect.</P>
<LETTER>
<P>God hath put it in my heart to warn ye to have a care of
your selves; for you, and all the rest of the Protestants are
design'd to be Massacred; It was to have been done some time
since, but an accident obstructed it; so that the day is not cer∣tainly
appointed, though the thing is fully concluded on:
therefore defend your selves as well as you can. The same
thing is designed in <HI>England.</HI> Ib. Numb. 112.</P>
</LETTER>
<P>Now as all these Stories were only Forgeries and Con∣trivances
to put the Hot-headed and credulous Fools of
the Faction into a Ferment, and prepare them for any vio∣lent
Attempt; the Project did so far also take effect, as
to draw together armed multitudes into a Resolution and
<PB N="39" REF="23"/>
Confederacy, to oppose whatsoever should be presented
unto them under the colour of a <HI>Popish Design:</HI> And they
that had so little Wit or Honesty, as to run to <HI>Oxford,</HI> and
so Accoutred, upon such an <HI>April-Errand,</HI> would un∣doubtedly
have gone through with their work upon a
good occasion, when they were so far onward in their
way. Here was a very extraordinary Concurrence of Pal∣pable
Impostures, accommodated to the same End, and
meeting upon the same nick of time too. And this is not
all neither; for there were several Printed Papers, of
Clamor, and Complaint, against the Kings taking his
Guards with him, under a Pretext that they would hinder
the Liberty of Debates, and over-awe the Parliament.
This Circumstance does very much favour the Presumpti∣on
of a Plot upon the Government; far if they were a∣fraid
of a <HI>Popish Attempt,</HI> his Majesties Guards would
have been a good Security against it, and no inconveni∣ence
to them at all, unless in case of a <HI>Phanatical Conspiracy:</HI>
so that their apprehension of the <HI>Guards</HI> is a very fair In∣terpretation
of what they meant by the <HI>Papists.</HI></P>
<P>If there was not a <HI>Plot,</HI> what meant the Distinguishing
Marks of the <HI>same-Colour'd-Ribbon in their Hats,</HI> with <HI>No
Popery No Slavery</HI> in them, for their Motto: and such
quantities of them distributed for the discrimination of
the Party? And why that <HI>Motto</HI> either? but first to inti∣mate
a notorious Scandal upon the King, as if his Majesty
were <HI>Popishly,</HI> and <HI>Tyrannically Inclin'd.</HI> And 2dly. As
an Ostentation of their Force and Resolution to Oppose
any Power whatsoever, even under the colour of that
Bare Pretence.</P>
<P>From this <HI>Probability</HI> of a <HI>Seditious Design,</HI> we shall
come closer now to a <HI>Proof</HI> of the <HI>thing it self;</HI> and see
how far <HI>College</HI> was concern'd in't, both from his own
Words and Actions; and from the Agreement of other
<PB N="40" REF="24"/>
Evidences with the Points of his Accusation: Not med∣ling
at all with the merits of his Cause, as they appeared
upon his Tryal.</P>
<P>As for what Arms I had <HI>(says he)</HI> and what Arms others
had, they were for our own Defence, in case the Papists should
make any Attempt upon us, by way of Massacre, or any Inva∣sion
or Rebellion, that we should be ready to defend our selves.
God is my Witness, this is all I know: If this be a Plot, This
I was in; but in no other. But never knew of any Numbers or
Times appointed for Meeting; but we said one to another, that
<HI>the Papists had a Design against the Protestants</HI> when we
did meet, as I was a man of General Conversation; and in
case they should rise, we were ready: But then they should be∣gin
the Attempt upon us. <HI>Last Speech.</HI></P>
<P>It is to be noted first, that they were all <HI>Armed.</HI> 2dly.
That they Communicated among themselves, and enter'd
into a kind of League of <HI>Conjunction.</HI> 3dly. That they
Reputed themselves strong enough to Encounter such a
Body of men, as (if we may believe them) threatned De∣struction
to the Government. And 4thly. That they were
resolv'd to put it to the hazard, if the Papists should at∣tempt
any thing: So that here's a <HI>Form'd Conspiracy</HI> ac∣knowledg'd;
and so many men as good as listed, but how∣ever
link'd in a common Design, without any Authority
or Commission: And we know very well what the Law
says in this case, let the intent of it be what it will. We
said to one another <HI>(says he)</HI> that <HI>the Papists had a design
against the Protestants;</HI> and then that <HI>we were Ready, but
They should begin the Attempt;</HI> which may seem to qualifie
the matter by making it only a <HI>Defensive War.</HI> But still,
even that War it self, without the Kings Commission, is a
plain Rebellion. And this is not yet the worst on't; for
in Vindicating the War of the <HI>Two Houses</HI> in 1640. <HI>&amp;c.</HI> and
their Proceedings under the same disguise of calling the
<PB N="41" REF="24"/>
<HI>Kings Friends Papists;</HI> and pretending that the <HI>King</HI> in
his <HI>Person</HI> made War against his <HI>Authority</HI> in the <HI>Lords and
Commons;</HI> and under that colour, representing themselves
to be only upon the <HI>Defensive:</HI> In Vindicating that War
(I say) which was a <HI>Hellish Rebellion,</HI> it is but Consonant
to their Principles, to justifie the same Proceedings over
again, under the same Pretensions.</P>
<P><HI>He says further in his other Speech,</HI> [I never was engag'd
in any manner of Plot or Conspiracy whatsoever in my life, a∣gainst
the Kings <HI>Person,</HI> Laws or Government, or know of
any that is or was, the Papists only excepted—It is utterly
false that I was to have seiz'd the <HI>King,</HI> either at <HI>White-Hall,</HI>
or at <HI>Oxon;</HI> and I do here solemnly declare I knew not of so
much as one single Person on Gods Earth that was, or would
have stood by me in that Attempt.] <HI>And to the same effect he
says over again in his</HI> last Speech.</P>
<P>I shall not force these words of his beyond a fair Con∣gruity
with the tenour of what he says in other places up∣on
this subject; though the liberty he has taken through∣out,
of speaking more or less than the just and naked Truth,
and wrapping himself up in Disguises and Reserves, so as
best to serve his purpose, might justifie me in the freedom
of taking him at the <HI>worst,</HI> where there is any place for a
<HI>double meaning. [He never engag'd against the Kings Per∣son</HI>
(he says, <HI>&amp;c.)</HI> Did not that Parliament, whose Cause,
Doctrine, and Proceedings, <HI>College</HI> has so highly approved,
say the same thing? And not only Disclaim their being <HI>A∣GAINST</HI>
the <HI>Person</HI> of the <HI>late King;</HI> but declare openly
to the World, the greatest Tenderness and Veneration for
him that was possible? What shall we say then of <HI>him</HI> that
speaks <HI>their very Words,</HI> upon the <HI>same Grounds,</HI> and under
the <HI>same Circumstances;</HI> but that he has the <HI>same Thoughts</HI>
also (which he in truth Confesses too) with those, who
under that pretence advanc'd a <HI>Rebellion</HI> against their <HI>So∣vereign?</HI>
<PB N="42" REF="25"/>
What does he mean again by saying that <HI>[HE
was not to have Seiz'd the King,</HI> &amp;c.] Is it that <HI>He himself</HI>
was not to do it with his <HI>own hands?</HI> Or that the <HI>Sove∣reignty</HI>
being lodg'd in the <HI>Two Houses,</HI> his <HI>PERSON</HI>
might be <HI>Seiz'd,</HI> and the <HI>KING</HI> remain untouch'd? There
is another Sentence in the same Speech, that speaks a little
plainer yet. <HI>[I did not understand</HI> (says he) <HI>but when I serv'd
the</HI> Parliament, <HI>I serv'd the</HI> King <HI>too.]</HI> Which in the Ac∣ceptation
of <HI>Forty</HI> and <HI>Forty-One,</HI> sounds as much as <HI>King
and Parliament</HI> on the <HI>one</HI> side, in opposition to <HI>Charles
Stuart</HI> on the <HI>other.</HI></P>
<P>Now as to the Plot of Seizing the Person of the
<HI>King,</HI> if the Witnesses had not made it out accor∣dingly
to the very <HI>Letter,</HI> I should rather have suspected
a design under the countenance of <HI>Loyal Service,</HI> to inter∣pose
a <HI>Force</HI> betwixt his <HI>Majesty</HI> and <HI>some Pretended Danger.</HI>
And this officious zeal to be follow'd with seizing half a
dozen (perhaps) of his Majesties most necessary <HI>Ministers</HI>
and <HI>Friends.</HI> And then a Proclamation immediately of
some damned Hellish <HI>Plot;</HI> a parcel of good Statutable
<HI>Knights of the Post</HI> to make it good, and there had been
the work done. This would have been no Ridiculous
thing to imagine, if his Majesty had not had over and a∣bove
his <HI>Guards,</HI> the <HI>Honour</HI> and <HI>Fidelity</HI> of the <HI>Two
Houses</HI> of his <HI>Security.</HI></P>
<P><HI>There are a great many slippery Passages in</HI> Colleges two
Speeches [Had the Papists <HI>(says he)</HI> or <HI>their Party</HI> offer'd to
destroy the Parliament, as was sworn, and fear'd they would,
I was there to have liv'd and dy'd with 'em.]</P>
<P>Here's a Disjunction of the <HI>Papists,</HI> OR <HI>their Party;</HI>
which I cannot tell what to make of, unless he ranges the
Servants of the <HI>King,</HI> and the <HI>Church</HI> in a Confederate
subserviency to the <HI>Papists,</HI> which is but consonant to what
he has said elsewhere. There is a doubtful Clause too in
<PB N="43" REF="25"/>
his <HI>last Speech [Men</HI> (says he, speaking of the <HI>Presbyterians)
without any manner of design; but to serve God, serve his
Majesty, and</HI> keep <HI>their</HI> Liberties <HI>and</HI> Properties.] Now
<HI>Colleges</HI> way of <HI>keeping his Property,</HI> is to <HI>Fight</HI> for't, in
case the <HI>King</HI> should <HI>Invade</HI> it, as he profess'd to a Divine
a little before his Execution: Beside that the word
<HI>[KEEP]</HI> seems to lean a little that way, especially from
a man that <HI>first supposes</HI> his <HI>Property</HI> to be <HI>Invaded;</HI> and
<HI>then declares</HI> his resolution to <HI>resist the King,</HI> in case of such
<HI>Invasion.</HI></P>
<P>We shall now as briefly as may be, apply matter of <HI>Fact</HI>
to the Capital parts of his <HI>Charge.</HI> The <HI>Designing</HI> of the
Sculpture to his <HI>Raree-Show</HI> is prov'd upon him so point
blank, that he himself had not the face to deny it: And
<HI>that Draught</HI> made him as <HI>Guilty of,</HI> and as <HI>Answerable for
the Malicious intent of it,</HI> as if the <HI>Ballad</HI> had been origi∣nally
his <HI>own:</HI> His <HI>Publishing</HI> of it was a <HI>further</HI> Aggrava∣tion
of the Crime; and the Pleasure he took in <HI>Singing</HI> it
up and down (as he did to several eminent Persons of
quality) and in <HI>Exposing</HI> it, made all that was in it his own
too. In that <HI>Doggrel Copy</HI> there is Chalk'd out the very
Train of the whole <HI>Conspiracy;</HI> and so plainly too, that
it will not bear any other Construction: As for example.
<Q><L>Help <HI>Cooper, Hughs</HI> and <HI>Snow,</HI> with a Hey, with a Hey,</L>
<L>To pull down <HI>Raree-Show,</HI> with a Ho.</L>
<L>So, so, the <HI>Gyant's down,</HI></L>
<L>Let's <HI>Masters</HI> out of Pound,</L>
<L>With a Hey Tronny Nony Nony No.</L></Q></P>
<P>Here's first the <HI>King</HI> to be <HI>pull'd down</HI> (under the <HI>Rarce-Show)</HI>
and <HI>Cooper, Hughs,</HI> and <HI>Snow</HI> (being Officers belong∣ing
to both Houses) are to represent the <HI>Lords and Com∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>s</HI>
in the <HI>doing</HI> of it; which reflects as odious a scandal
<PB N="44" REF="26"/>
upon the <HI>Two Houses</HI> as upon his <HI>Majesty.</HI> In the next
place he supposes the <HI>King</HI> to be <HI>down;</HI> and to answer that
phansie, there are three Fellows in the <HI>Plate,</HI> lugging of
him in the <HI>Dirt:</HI> And then follows <HI>[Let's</HI> Masters <HI>out of
Pound:]</HI> which is only to say, That now the <HI>King</HI> is <HI>down,</HI>
the <HI>Lords and Commons</HI> are to take upon them the Admini∣stration
of the <HI>Government.</HI> But let us see how he goes
on.
<Q><L>And now y'ave <HI>freed</HI> the Nation, with a Hey, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L>
<L>Cram in the <HI>Convocation,</HI> with a Ho;</L>
<L>With <HI>Pensioners,</HI> All and some</L>
<L>Into this Chest of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>With a Hey, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L></Q></P>
<P>The <HI>first line</HI> here makes the <HI>Freedom</HI> of the <HI>Nation</HI> to
ensue upon the <HI>Deposing</HI> of the <HI>King.</HI> The <HI>second</HI> sends the
<HI>Convocation</HI> after him. The <HI>third,</HI> all those whom he is
pleas'd to call <HI>Pensioners:</HI> And the <HI>fourth</HI> makes them all
to be <HI>Papists.</HI> Here's the <HI>King,</HI> the <HI>Convocation,</HI> and the
<HI>Pensioners</HI> gone already. Now see what's next.
<Q><L>And thrust in <HI>Six and twenty,</HI> with a Hey, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L>
<L>With <HI>Not Guilty,</HI> good plenty, with a Ho:</L>
<L>And Hoot them hence away,</L>
<L><HI>To</HI> Cullen <HI>or</HI> Breda:</L></Q></P>
<P>We have here the very <HI>Track</HI> of the Conspiracy, as it
was prov'd at his <HI>Tryal.</HI> The <HI>Bishop's</HI> are to be dispatch'd
away too, and the <HI>Not Guilty-Lords,</HI> in the Vote upon
my Lord <HI>Stafford.</HI> And at best, to be all of them driven
out of the Nation, as the <HI>Late King</HI> was, and a great part
of his <HI>Adherents.</HI> We shall now conclude this point with
the two last lines:
<Q><L>Halloe, the Hunts begun, with a Hey, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L>
<L>Like Father, like Son, with a Ho, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L></Q></P>
<P><PB N="45" REF="26"/>
I have in my hand the <HI>Manuscript</HI> of <HI>Colleges own writing,</HI>
from whence this Ballad was Printed; where it is to be
noted, that instead of <HI>Halloe,</HI> it was in the Original, <HI>Stand
to't;</HI> but <HI>that struck out,</HI> and <HI>Halloe interlin'd</HI> in the <HI>place</HI>
of it; the other being too broad a discovery of the Vio∣lence
they intended. Let me further observe, that this
Song was Calculated for <HI>Oxford;</HI> that is to say, both for
the <HI>Time,</HI> and the <HI>Place, When,</HI> and <HI>Where</HI> this Exploit was
to have been executed. And now for a close; What can
be the meaning of <HI>Like Father, like Son;</HI> but a <HI>design</HI> and
<HI>encouragement</HI> (as appears from the Connexion) to serve
them <HI>both alike;</HI> and to conclude both <HI>Father</HI> and <HI>Son,</HI> un∣der
<HI>one and the same Condemnation.</HI></P>
<P>The Faction did, without dispute, flatter themselves
that they should find Friends, even in the Parliament it
self, to Authorize them in their Enterprize; (but they
were egregiously mistaken it seems in their measures.) And
they grounded their Hopes upon the Interest they had
made in most places of the Kingdom to secure an Election
for their turn. This Prospect and Confidence does most
notoriously appear in the contrivance of the <HI>Raree-Show,</HI>
which in truth looks liker a Song of <HI>Triumph,</HI> as for a thing
<HI>already</HI> done, then a bare <HI>Project</HI> and <HI>Exhortation</HI> toward
the doing of it: Insomuch that they have in this Ballad de∣lineated
the very <HI>Scheme</HI> of their Intentions. It is a thing
very remarkable too, that the same Pulse beats still in all
their Pamphlets of Appeal to the Multitude; which speaks
them clearly to be animated with the same souls, and di∣rected
to the same end. As <HI>Vox Patriae</HI> for the purpose,
(among forty others.) What is it, but under the Notion of
<HI>Petitions</HI> and <HI>Addresses,</HI> in the name of the People of <HI>Eng∣land,</HI>
a certain <HI>Compendium</HI> of Instructions toward the
Forming and carrying on of a <HI>Conspiracy?</HI> This Libel lays
out the very Model of the Plot, for which <HI>College</HI> was
<PB N="46" REF="27"/>
<HI>Try'd, Condemn'd,</HI> and <HI>Executed.</HI> It prescribes the Removal
of <HI>Councellors</HI> and <HI>Officers,</HI> the ordering of the <HI>Militia,</HI> the
Retrenching the Power of the <HI>King,</HI> the Dissolving the Or∣der
of the Church, the setting all sorts of Heretiques at
liberty, the Calling and Continuing of Parliaments at the
Peoples pleasure. And all this Address'd to the Commons
in Parliament in such a manner; as if his Majesty were
scarce worth Consulting upon the matter; only instead
of <HI>Seizing the King,</HI> and Governing <HI>without</HI> him, they
have found out a way of giving their Representatives some
blind and general hints of what they would be at; and then
honestly tell them, that <HI>they'l stand by them with their Lives
and Fortunes, let them do what they please.</HI></P>
<P>It is also a further Confirmation of this Plot, the Cor∣respondence
betwixt Mr. <HI>Fitz-Harris</HI>'s <HI>Declaration,</HI> and
the several Points given in Evidence against <HI>College.</HI></P>
<P>Mr. <HI>Fitz-Harris</HI> declar'd that there was a design to Seize the
King. Of this he spake often, and said, when the Party had
Seiz'd the King, they would have oblig'd him to call a Parlia∣ment,
which should sit until the Bill of Exclusion against the
Duke were pass'd; all evil Councellors remov'd, and men of
their Chusing put into places of Trust; the <HI>Militia</HI> settled, and
the Navy put into Good hands; all Grievances Redress'd;
and all things order'd to their own liking. And had this De∣sign
succeeded, he said the Bishops and others of the Clergy
would have suffer'd severely. (Dr. <HI>Hawkins's Narrative,</HI>
Pag. 4)</P>
<P>This Account of a Combination does not only Nick the
several parts of the Evidence against <HI>College,</HI> but it does
most exactly answer the Method of <HI>One and forty,</HI> which
<HI>College</HI> justifies; and consequently approves of the same
thing over again in so doing.</P>
<P>Now Mr. <HI>Fitz-Harris</HI> being demanded as a Dying man,
whether this that he had declared concerning the Design to
<PB N="47" REF="27"/>
seize the King were true; He call'd God to witness that it was
every word true.</P>
<P>And does not the Information against <HI>George Wetheridge,</HI>
taken <HI>September</HI> 21. 1681. speak as home to the same
effect?</P>
<P>Is not the tyde strangely turn'd <HI>(says he)</HI> Were not the
<HI>Parliament men</HI> at <HI>Oxford,</HI> and those that were with 'em,
(being to the number of 40000 men Arm'd) great Fools that
they did not seize the King there? And if that they had want∣ed
strength <HI>(says he)</HI> I would have been one to have assisted
them: And that they should have brought the King to <HI>London,</HI>
to <HI>Guild-Hall;</HI> and there the Parliament should have sat, and
have kept his Majesty there till they had made their own Terms
with him. And the same Information adds further, that
<HI>Wetheridge</HI> said <HI>the King was a Papist; and had a design
to bring in Popery and Arbitrary Power,</HI> and Reign as the
King of <HI>France,</HI> &amp;c] <HI>To m<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ltiply Instances would be
to over-do the thing that I pretend, wherefore this shall
suffice.</HI></P>
<P>If I were bent upon unnecessary Cavils, I might enlarge
my self abundantly in farther Observations upon the In∣sincerity
both of <HI>College</HI> himself, and some of his Evidence,
and prove that one of his prime Compurgators (how ho∣nest
a man soever he reputed him in the Court) has more
than once declar'd what warnings he had given him to have
a care of his tongue; and that he talk'd at such a desperate
rate, that it was not safe for any man to keep him com∣pany.
Colleges <HI>dying words are, that he rode his own Horse,
spent his own Money, and neither was invited, or had depen∣dency
on any person whatsoever:</HI> When yet the People of the
<HI>Red Lyon</HI> in <HI>Henly</HI> do affirm, that he and a Companion of his
drank <HI>one quart of raw Sack, one of Mull'd, one of Butter'd,</HI>
and then a <HI>Pint</HI> more of the <HI>last;</HI> beside one Quart of
<HI>Butter'd Sack</HI> in the Morning, which was all plac'd to the
<PB N="48" REF="28"/>
Account of another Person. It will not become me to des∣cant
upon any Inconsistencies among <HI>Colleges Evidence's</HI> at
his Tryal, out of the Respect and Veneration that I both
owe, and bear to the Honour of the Court, and to the
Methods of Publique Justice: I could otherwise in the
case of <HI>Lun,</HI> and even of Dr. <HI>Oats himself,</HI> find Mr. <HI>Colleges</HI>
Advocates picking-work. Nay they were so hard put
to't, that they brake in upon Justice <HI>Warcup</HI> himself; a
Person that has been, even by themselves celebrated all a∣long
for his zeal in the Discovery of the Horrid Plot; a
Person particularly Interessed by the Lords, in several Ex∣aminations;
and by their Lordships particularly recom∣mended
to the King for his Faith and Sedulity in that great
affair. But these People understand no other measures of
Honesty, then as it squares with their designs. As to <HI>Tur∣bervile</HI>
and <HI>Dugdale</HI> (the two Principal Evidences) <HI>College</HI>
himself had very little to say against them.</P>
<P>In one word, the matter is here plainly and nakedly set
forth. The <HI>Protestant Ioyner</HI> has left the World wholly
at a loss for his <HI>Religion:</HI> He has both in his <HI>Words</HI> and
<HI>Practices</HI> declar'd himself a deadly Enemy to the Govern∣ment.
His <HI>last</HI> Speech is a Compound of <HI>Equivocations</HI>
and <HI>Disguise:</HI> He Justifies those that destroy'd the <HI>late King;</HI>
and by the same reason he may justifie the same design up∣on
<HI>This.</HI> To conclude, let the Reader judge upon what
is here deliver'd, whether or no there was a Design against
the King at <HI>Oxford;</HI> and how far <HI>College</HI> was engag'd in the
<HI>Conspiracy.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

