<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A letter to a member of Parliament with two discourses enclosed in it : I. the one shewing the reason why a law should pass to punish adultery with death, II. the other shewing the reasons why the writ, De hæretico comburendo, should be abolish'd.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A48198</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing L1682</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R10913</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12387027</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12387027</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">60862</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A48198)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60862)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 766:19)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A letter to a member of Parliament with two discourses enclosed in it : I. the one shewing the reason why a law should pass to punish adultery with death, II. the other shewing the reasons why the writ, De hæretico comburendo, should be abolish'd.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>8 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1675.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Heresy.</TERM><TERM>Adultery --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A48198">
<STC T="W">L1682</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12387027</BIBNO>
<VID>60862</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A LETTER TO A MEMBER OF PARLIAMENT.</P>
<P>WITH TWO DISCOURSES Enclosed in it.</P>
<P N="1">I. The One shewing the <HI>Reason</HI> why a <HI>Law</HI> should pass to punish <HI>Adultery</HI> with <HI>Death.</HI></P>
<P N="2">II. The Other shewing the <HI>Reasons</HI> why the <HI>Writ, De Haeretico Comburendo,</HI> should be abolish'd.</P>
<Q><L>Non partis studijs agimur, sed sumsimus arma</L>
<L>Consilijs inimica tuis, ignavia fallax.</L></Q>
<P>Printed <HI>Anno</HI> 1675.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The <HI>Publisher</HI>'s Advertisement:</HEAD>
<P>These <HI>Papers</HI> are made publick, not in Pre∣sumption to informe the <HI>Parliament;</HI> but only to give them an Occasion, to think of the <HI>Subjects</HI> they treat of, it being wholely unimaginable but that the <HI>United Wisdom of the NATION</HI> will find out better and other <HI>Reasons</HI> for the Establishment of the Things they propose.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Dear Friend.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><HI>WHen I review alone the grand Entertainments of</HI> Learning, <HI>I used to meet with in your Conversation, the</HI> Wit <HI>of the</HI> Poets, <HI>the</HI> Reason <HI>of the</HI> Philosophers, <HI>your Excellent</HI> Observations <HI>upon the</HI> Actions <HI>of</HI> Persons <HI>illustrious in</HI> Arms, <HI>who have lived in the several Ages of the World, my</HI> Affliction <HI>is almost unimaginable to be separated from you: When you went up to the</HI> Parliament, <HI>there is nothing could have stay'd me (who can scarce be happy a Moment of my Life without you) behind you in the Country, but my Infirmity of Health, and a certain Desire of enjoying the Comfort and Pleasures of the Spring. You know, when we parted, how I conjur'd you alwayes to bear in Mind that grand Rule,</HI> Inter pericula libertatis aut veritatis silent amicitiae et inimicitiae, <HI>and then the Light of your own Mind will dispel and overcome the Darkness of others without Noise or Tumult: This World is govern'd by particular</HI> Hatreds <HI>and</HI> Friendships, <HI>not by the Reasons of Things; and there is nothing can keep you constant in your</HI> Integrity, <HI>but the having a perpetual Eye to that Rule. I also then told you, you should look abroad as well as at home, keeping your Eye on</HI> Forreign Affairs; <HI>for although</HI> Hannibal <HI>be not yet</HI> ad portas, Philip <HI>is at</HI> Olynthus. <HI>I have herein enclosed the Papers I promised you, in which I claim no</HI> Property <HI>against your absolute Power over them, do what you will with them: You know, the one contains a Discourse shewing the Reasons why</HI> A∣dultery <HI>should be Punished with</HI> Death; <HI>the other, why the Writ,</HI> De Hae∣retico comburendo, <HI>should be Abolished.</HI> Adultery, <HI>it is the greatest of all</HI> Thefts, <HI>a</HI> Theft <HI>of which no Restitution can be made,</HI>
<Q><L>—Nulla reparabilis arte,</L>
<L>Laesa pudicitia est, deperit illa semel.</L></Q></P>
<P>Marriage <HI>of late hath been looked on as an Engin, a Toil to cath Mankind in; the</HI> Magistrate <HI>had need encourage it to prevent</HI> Depopulations: <HI>and to be alwayes</HI> secure <HI>and</HI> certain <HI>of our</HI> Wives, <HI>is in my Iudgment the best of</HI> Encouragements. <HI>As to the Abolishing the Writ,</HI> de Haeretico combu∣rendo, <HI>you know I ever have had a</HI> Pitty <HI>&amp;</HI> Charity <HI>for Mankind, acknowledg∣ing in all a Communion of Minds and Mortality, and particularly for those that dissent from me in Religion,</HI> Omnis animus veritate invitus privatur: <HI>No</HI> Beauty <HI>is so pleasant, so agreeable to the Eye as Truth is to the Soul; and all would love it, if they could discover it: As there is but one certain</HI> Existence <HI>of Things, so there is but one determinate</HI> Truth <HI>of them, the same to all Un∣derstandings, God's and Man's both. If after all my Search and Labour in</HI> Knowledge, <HI>I cannot discover a Beam of Truth to guide and lead me into an Unity of Mind with God, am I to be made a</HI> Criminal, <HI>and dealt with as a</HI> Malefactor? <HI>He is Infinite, and knows all Things; but my poor Understan∣ding knows one Thing, and doubts of a Thousand: We are here in the Body</HI>
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
tristi et obscuro Domicilio; <HI>and the inspired Apostle himself saith,</HI> we see darkly, and but through a Glass. <HI>God hath unfolded himself in as great Variety in the Minds of Men, as he hath done in the Material World: The Seed of Religion springs up variously in Human Souls, as we see the seminal Forms do out of the Earth; and would it not be Madness or Folly to destroy &amp; cut up all</HI> Trees <HI>and</HI> Plants <HI>but the</HI> Oak? <HI>I am not without all</HI> Jealousie, <HI>that it is possible, we in</HI> England <HI>may return back again to the</HI> Church of Rome, <HI>not only because I see in History</HI> Monarchies <HI>more subject to Changes then</HI> Common-Wealths <HI>in Matters of Religion, and observe how indefatigable that</HI> Infallible Church <HI>(in its own Iudgment) is to revenge our</HI> Schism <HI>from it upon us, and so may weary us out at last, &amp; how unsafe they apprehend them∣selves at</HI> Rome, <HI>while the Power of the</HI> Sea <HI>is in the Hands of</HI> Hereticks; <HI>but chiefly from the wild</HI> Philosophy <HI>and</HI> Atheism <HI>of the present Age,</HI> Atheism <HI>being a Preparation to receive any</HI> Colour <HI>or</HI> Tincture <HI>in Religion. I would have the Law of</HI> Burning of Hereticks <HI>repeal'd, lest we should see that Day. It is a</HI> Law Sanguinary <HI>with a Witness, written like</HI> Draco'<HI>s in</HI> Characters <HI>of</HI> Blood, <HI>as barbarous as that of</HI> Ordeal, <HI>or</HI> Tryal by Battail, <HI>built upon no Reason, but upon a</HI> Self Opinion <HI>every Sect hath, that it hath a</HI> Monopoly <HI>of God to it self, and upon no Scripture I know of, but the</HI> Monkish <HI>Gloss,</HI> Haereticos de vita.</P>
<P><HI>My</HI> Dear Friend, <HI>Although</HI> Gentlemen <HI>of fine Parts are sooner debauch'd in</HI> popular Assemblies <HI>under a</HI> Monarchy, then <HI>Men of plainer Wisdom; as</HI> Native Beauty <HI>is less subject to be tempted by others, then</HI> Beauty <HI>accompanied with the Ornaments of Art: I doubt not at all your</HI> Integrity <HI>in this</HI> Parlia∣ment, <HI>you are not a Man of</HI> fluttering Principles <HI>betwixt</HI> Kravery <HI>and</HI> Ho∣nesty, <HI>you will herd in your</HI> Vote <HI>with no</HI> Cabal, <HI>but go with the</HI> Squadron volante, <HI>as</HI> Reason <HI>upon every Debate appears to you; I know you account a</HI> Liberty of Judgment <HI>in an uninterested</HI> indifference <HI>of Mind without Fears or Hopes, a</HI> Grandeur <HI>and</HI> Excellence <HI>above the Rewards of</HI> Wealth <HI>from the</HI> Court, <HI>or of</HI> Fame <HI>from the</HI> People; <HI>nor am I afraid that amidst the</HI> Plea∣sure <HI>or</HI> Business <HI>of the City, you will depart from the</HI> Contemplative Life, <HI>but be alone with your own Mind, and drink of the Spring of Truth there, which overflowed so constantly your Conversations with me in the Country:</HI>
<Q><L>Non Venus, aut vinum sublimia pectora fregit,</L>
<L>Officiumve fori—</L></Q></P>
<P>And, as for our <HI>Friendship,</HI> which has been a Communion of <HI>Minds</HI> &amp; <HI>Fortunes</HI> for several Years, I have no <HI>Cloud,</HI> no <HI>Umbrage</HI> of <HI>Iealousie</HI> towards you. <HI>Friends</HI> in this World are not like <HI>Satyrs</HI> or <HI>Centaurs</HI> without real Existence, as <HI>Cardan</HI> under a <HI>Mel ncholy</HI> complains they are; I am sure I have found one which (as he sayes) <HI>he neve<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> was so happy in his Life to do.</HI> I will detain you no longer from the Care of the <HI>publick Affa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs.</HI> I am Dearest <HI>Sr</HI></P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE>April 17. 1675.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Your most sincerely affectionate Friend.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="discourse">
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>A short Discourse why a Law should pass in <HI>England</HI> to punish <HI>Adultery</HI> with <HI>Death.</HI></HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><L>Publicus assertor, vitiis suppressa levabo</L>
<L>Pectora, vindictae quis{que} favete suae.</L> <BIBL><HI>Ovid.</HI></BIBL></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>IT will be necessary before I give my <HI>Reasons</HI> why such a <HI>Law</HI> should pass, that I do explain what <HI>Adultery</HI> is, the Notion of it being ordina∣rllly mistaken.</P>
<P><HI>Adultery</HI> is the <HI>lying of a Single or Married Man with another Man's Wife,</HI> and not the <HI>lying of a Married Man with a Single Woman.</HI> Thus it was constantly apprehended among the <HI>Iews,</HI> to whom God gave the Law, <HI>Thou shalt not commit Adultery:</HI> And <HI>David</HI>'s Sin was the taking the poor Man's <HI>Ewe Lamb</HI> from him, which lay in his Bosom, when he had Flocks enough of his own. I presume, there is none doubts the <HI>Chri∣stian Magistrates</HI> Power to make such a <HI>Law; Death</HI> is already amongst us the Penalty for <HI>less Crimes:</HI> We punish boldly with <HI>Death</HI> a <HI>Horse-stealer</HI> or a <HI>Cut-purse</HI> without any Scruple at all; and is not my <HI>Property</HI> in my <HI>Wife</HI> of dearer &amp; nearer Concern to me, then my <HI>Horse,</HI> or a little <HI>Pocket-money?</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>primary Law</HI> of <HI>Nature</HI> is the Observance of our <HI>Contracts;</HI> for in∣deed, without this there could be no Government: the State of <HI>Nature</HI> would still have continued; this Crime intrenches highly on this Law, dis∣solving the <HI>Family-Government;</HI> it is a Breach of the Solemnest Contract (entered into <HI>pro bono publico, Marriage</HI> being <HI>seminarium Reipubl.)</HI> ima∣ginable: That is the Nature of the <HI>Crime,</HI> but the <HI>Magistrate</HI> is chiefly to concern himself in the Consequences of it; and they are more mischievous where the <HI>Woman</HI> breaks the <HI>Contract</HI> on her Part; for thereby a <HI>Spurious Issue</HI> that robs the <HI>Husband</HI> by wholesale of his Estate, of all his own and his Ancestors Acquisitions, is brought into his Family. The Crime is then a Complication of all the <HI>Wickedness</HI> in <HI>Lust, Breach</HI> of <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Robbery;</HI> And therefore I may justly infer that seeing Men <HI>equally</HI> concur with Wo∣men to transact it, they are justly <HI>equally punishable.</HI></P>
<P>If a Man shall violate the <HI>Companion</HI> of the <HI>King,</HI> or the <HI>Companion</HI> of the <HI>Eldest Son</HI> and <HI>Heir</HI> of the <HI>King,</HI> it is <HI>high Treason:</HI> by this we see the Care of the Law, no <HI>Spurious Issue</HI> should <HI>inherit the Crown;</HI> should we not take some proportionable Care of our own Estates?</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="4"/>
We may do well to reflect upon the Example of other Nations, as of the <HI>Iews</HI> (for many Ages the only known People of God) amongst whom <HI>Adultery</HI> was punished with <HI>Death,</HI> upon the Example of the <HI>Gentes mo∣ratiores</HI> among the <HI>Heathens;</HI> of the <HI>Athenians,</HI> who upon <HI>Solon</HI>'s Law punished this Crime <HI>Capitally;</HI> of the <HI>Romans,</HI> who in Imitation of <HI>Solon</HI>'s Law, set down for their Law in the 12 Tables, <HI>Moechum in adulterio de∣prehensum necato.</HI> Afterwards in the <HI>Roman</HI> State it was lawful for the Husband, until the <HI>Lex Iulia</HI> in <HI>Augustus</HI> his Time, <HI>Uxores in adulterio deprehensas sine judicio impune necare.</HI></P>
<P>We may also consider what the <HI>Christian Church</HI> has done for the Sup∣pression of this Sin: In the first and best Times of <HI>Christianity</HI> they did all they could (having not <HI>jus vitae ac necis)</HI> against it. The <HI>Pennance</HI> then for it was perpetual to the <HI>Hour</HI> of <HI>Death. Zepherynus</HI> Bishop of <HI>Rome, anno</HI> 216. moderated the <HI>Pennance,</HI> but the <HI>African Churches,</HI> and par∣ticularly the grand <HI>Tertullian</HI> opposed it as an Innovation.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ancyran</HI> Council, <HI>anno</HI> 315. ordains 7 <HI>Years Pennance</HI> for it. And the Council of <HI>Eliberis</HI> ordains, that he that commits <HI>Adultery again after Pennance</HI> for the <HI>First Fault,</HI> should not be taken into Communion at the Hour of <HI>Death.</HI></P>
<P>In after Ages, when the <HI>Roman Church</HI> was resolved upon a <HI>Corlibacy</HI> in her <HI>Clergy,</HI> It was necessary the Sin should be looked on with a <HI>gentle Eye,</HI> &amp; now it is dwindled down into a <HI>Peccadillo,</HI> but is in Truth like the <HI>Pe∣cadillo</HI> of not believing in God at all; for if ever he gave a Law to Man, it is one to prohibit <HI>Adultery.</HI> Several of the Reformed <HI>Countries,</HI> who have recover'd themselves from under the Empire of Wit and Fraud over their <HI>Consciences</HI> by that Church, punish the Crime at this Day with Death.</P>
<P>As for us in <HI>England,</HI> our present Law is not without the Infusions of the <HI>Roman Church</HI> upon it in this Case; all the Remedy the injur'd Hus∣band hath by our Law, is, to sue a <HI>Divorce</HI> in the <HI>Spiritual Court,</HI> and be cozen'd with a Sentence of Separation <HI>a Mensa &amp; Thoro,</HI> a Crafty Inven∣tion against the plain Gospel.</P>
<P>If the Husband kill the <HI>Adulterer,</HI> or his Wife found by him in <HI>ipso actu,</HI> the Law excuseth him in this Case from <HI>Murder,</HI> but condemns him of <HI>Man-Slaughter,</HI> and hangs him <HI>if he cannot read;</HI> what a poor Remedy hath the Injur'd Man? If he kill the <HI>Adulterer</HI> deliberately, not provoakt by Ocular Demonstration, it is <HI>Murder.</HI> Besides all this, the present Law being so defective, the Crime grows upon it; 'tis common, and this Age gives it the soft and gentle <HI>French</HI> Names of <HI>Gallantry</HI> and <HI>Divertise∣ment,</HI> in Apology for it: What ought the <HI>Magistrate</HI> to do in this Case, but to pursue this Crime as far as his Hand can reach, to the Grave it self, and then <HI>Expectet Deum Ultorem?</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="discourse">
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A short <HI>Discourse</HI> shewing the <HI>Reasons</HI> why the <HI>Writ, De Haeretico comburendo</HI> should be abolished.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><L>Chrysippus non dicit idem nec mite Thaletis</L>
<L>Ingenium dulci{que} senex vicinus Hymeto.</L> <BIBL><HI>Juvenal.</HI></BIBL></Q>
<Q>Paena errantis est doceri. <BIBL><HI>Plato</HI> cited by <HI>Grotius.</HI></BIBL></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>BEfore I give my <HI>Reasons,</HI> it will be necessary to shew the State of the Law at present upon this <HI>Writ:</HI> Before the Sta<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>te, 2 <HI>H. 4. cap. 15. No Person could be convict of Heresie, but by the</HI> Arch-Bishop <HI>and all the Clergy of the</HI> Province, but by that Statute <HI>any particular</HI> Bishop <HI>might in his</HI> Dio∣cess <HI>convict of Heresie, and issue forth his Precept to the</HI> Sheriff <HI>to burn the Person he had convicted;</HI> a Law whereby the <HI>Clergy</HI> gain'd a Dominion over the Lives of the Subjects independent upon the Crown: it was repeal∣ed by the <HI>Stat. 25. H. 8. cap.</HI> 14. but so as <HI>particular</HI> Bishops <HI>may still con∣vict; but without the Kings Writ,</HI> De Haeretico comburendo, <HI>first obtained, no Person convict can be put to Death;</HI> and so the Law stands at this Day.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>My REASONS are these.</HEAD>
<P N="1">I. The Continuance of this <HI>Writ</HI> in force amongst us, is a standing <HI>Re∣proach</HI> to the <HI>Christian</HI> Religion we profess (a Religion of Love and Peace) If it be not to be propagated in the whole by Force and Blood∣shed, certainly a Part of it as a particular Point of Faith in it, is not. In the Gospel of Christ all the <HI>Punishment</HI> of <HI>Heresie</HI> and of <HI>Infidelity</HI> it self, are adjourned over, and left to the other World.</P>
<P N="2">II. If an <HI>Act</HI> pass to abolish this <HI>Writ,</HI> it will be an <HI>Act</HI> of <HI>Indulgence</HI> in part, and give an <HI>Assurance</HI> to all Persons of a <HI>different Iudgment</HI> from the present <HI>establisht Church, that they are secure as to their Lives under the Government.</HI></P>
<P N="3">III. If <HI>Popery</HI> should ever return back into <HI>England,</HI> there must a <HI>Par∣liament</HI> sit to repeal such an <HI>Act,</HI> before any <HI>Protestant</HI> for his Opinion could be put to Death.</P>
<P N="4">IV. Such an <HI>Act</HI> would leave the Power of the present Church to <HI>con∣vict, excommunicate</HI> and <HI>imprison</HI> Untouched▪ only would take away their barbarous Execution of her Sentence.</P>
<P><PB N="8" REF="5"/>
If it be objected, <HI>the Writ is grown Obsolete and disused and so need not be taken away:</HI> The Answer is obvious; <HI>Not so obsolete neither:</HI> It was used in King <HI>Iames</HI>'s Time; However, it's fit it should not remain as a Snare among our Law; for the Case concerns <HI>Life</HI> or <HI>Death:</HI> and the <HI>Papists</HI> use the <HI>Writ</HI> constantly against the <HI>Protestants;</HI> but they never against them.</P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="5"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

