<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Asteria and Tamberlain, or, The distressed lovers a novel / written in French by a person of quality ; and rendred into English by E.C., Esq.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Astérie ou Tamerlan. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>La Roche-Guilhen, Mlle. de (Anne), 1644-1707.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A49593</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing L447</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R10866</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12330636</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12330636</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">59666</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A49593)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59666)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 189:13)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Asteria and Tamberlain, or, The distressed lovers a novel / written in French by a person of quality ; and rendred into English by E.C., Esq.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">Astérie ou Tamerlan. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>La Roche-Guilhen, Mlle. de (Anne), 1644-1707.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>E. C., Esq.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[9], 190 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Robert Sollers ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1677.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Translation of: Astérie ou Tamerlan.</NOTE><NOTE>Attributed to La Roche-Guihen. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</NOTE><NOTE>Another ed. was published as: Royal lovers, or, The unhappy prince.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A49593">
<STC T="W">L447</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12330636</BIBNO>
<VID>59666</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="license">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>With Allowance</P>
<CLOSER><DATE>May 12.
1676.</DATE>
<SIGNED>Roger L'Estrange.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>ASTERIA AND TAMBERLAIN; OR, THE Distressed Lovers: A NOVEL.</P>
<P>Written in <HI>French</HI> by a Person of Quality.</P>
<P>And rendred into <HI>English,</HI> by <HI>E. C.</HI> <ABBR>Esq;</ABBR></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed for <HI>Robert Sollers,</HI> at the Flying Horse in St. <HI>Paul</HI>'s Church-Yard. 1677.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE HONOUR'D MADAM▪ Madam, <HI>M. P.</HI></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Have made bold to dedi∣cate this little piece to your Ladyship to give the World a publick Testi∣mony how great an ho∣nour I receive from the
<PB REF="3"/>
friendship you are pleas'd to make me blest with.</P>
<P>I never had any reason to accuse my self of guilt from any haughty vanity before I became known to you, I was till then so inconside∣rable, I thought there was nothing capable to give me the least Elevation: But, Madam, I have felt since the force of your Charms, wherever you bestow so high a favour there's no re∣sisting the fate of that pride which unavoidably,
<PB REF="3"/>
attends it, and I can't but glory now in my exalted∣ness which springs from your bounty, which other∣wise would render me a no mean Criminal.</P>
<P>One may have good thoughts of ones self for be∣ing a Religious Votary to Heaven; and Madam, I know not wherein the fault lies, if I ingenuously con∣fess, I have at present no indifferent ones as to my own regard, in being with so much Devotion yours,
<PB REF="4"/>
especially when that awful respect I bear you, is re∣ceived with so great an ac∣knowledgment of kind∣ness from you.</P>
<P>You'll find the ensuing History full of various and perplexed Accidents from which your distress'd <HI>Asteria</HI> is at last happily delivered through the con∣stancy of her Love to the as faithful and generous <HI>Adanaxus.</HI> And, Ma∣dam, let me humbly in∣treat you, what ever Risque
<PB REF="4"/>
I may run of displeasing you by this hardy adven∣ture, to give me your par∣don for the rash address I have made to you; since it was beyond my power to overcome the Ambition I had to signalize my self by the quality of,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Honoured Madam, </SALUTE>
<SIGNED>Your most Humble, and Obedient Servant,E. C.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="novel">
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB N="1" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>ASTERIA, OR TAMBERLAIN.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">A NOVEL.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The First <HI>PART.</HI></HEAD>
<P>WIth a great deal of Reason is Fortune made to stand upon a Globe, which is under an Impossibility of having a∣ny solid steadiness, being the first Principle of all Revolutions. We are furnished from Antiquity with se∣veral notable Examples of her Ca∣pricious humour: The Rise of Mo∣narchies, the Elevation of mean and obscure persons to places of the highest rank and dignity; the Down
<PB N="2" REF="6"/>
fal of an Infinite Number of Kings, and the ruine of Empires, are as so many signal Instances of her Incon∣stancy. But because we will n<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> absolutely relie upon those of the past distant Ages for the Justificati∣on of this Truth, we will make our reflections upon Accidents less re∣mote, and see in the misfortunes o <HI>Bajazet,</HI> with what Soveraignty she at pleasure does dispose of the De∣stiny of Mankind.</P>
<P><HI>Bajazet</HI> was of the Illustriou Blood of <HI>Ottoman;</HI> his Birth had exalted him to the Empire of the <HI>Turks,</HI> and his Valour was so bright that it dazled the glory of those four great Princes who preceded him in it: he had almost brough <HI>Europe</HI> under his submission, as he had made all <HI>Asia</HI> tremble. Hi Laws were revered in the most re¦markable Parts of the Earth; and never had any man acquired to himself a Renown more glorious.</P>
<P><HI>Tamberlain,</HI> Emperour of th
<PB N="3" REF="6"/>
<HI>Tartars,</HI> put a stop to the course of this prosperity: he was of a low and obscure birth, but having with violence through the succour of Arms placed himself upon a Throne, which others with tremb∣ling ascended, his happy destiny surmounted that of <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s; he triumphed over him, and at that time when he look'd upon <HI>Europe</HI> and <HI>Asia,</HI> as easie conquests, he de∣solated his Country, reduced his Fa∣mily to a peregrine condition, and carried him Captive to <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> which was <HI>Tamberlain</HI>'s most belov∣ed City, as being built by him. The Wife and Daughter of <HI>Bajazet</HI> were partakers of his misfortune; the former of whom died a little while after, but the Daughter, be∣ing, either more couragious, or of a more robust and resolute Spirit, was better able to resist the attaques of Fortune, and became the admiration of the <HI>Tartars,</HI> as she had been of all those who had seen her in her Fa∣thers Palace.</P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="7"/>
<HI>Themir, Tamberlain</HI>'s Eldest Son, who was one of the first, felt the ef∣fect of this admiration: he had an ab∣solute Empire over his Father's mind, and had abused it by his ill conduct, even to the banishing of <HI>A∣danaxus</HI> from the Court, otherwise called the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> his yong∣er Brother; and he had improved this affection to a thousand cruelties a∣gainst the unfortunate <HI>Bajazet:</HI> it was He, who had sacrificed in his sight the eldest and dearest of his Sons, ruined the famous City <HI>Seba∣stia,</HI> took away the Princess <HI>Asteria</HI> his Daughter from the Palace of <HI>Bursa,</HI> and without any pity aban∣doned all the Empire of that mise∣rable Prince, to the violence of the <HI>Tartars.</HI></P>
<P>But Love punished him for all those Inhumanities, and his heart, as barbarous as it was, was sensible of the Charms of the fair <HI>Asteria,</HI> so that much against his will he did learn the use of sighs; and though
<PB N="5" REF="7"/>
they were prevented with too great outrages from being favourably re∣garded, yet his Rage to see him∣self despised by the generous, but resolute Princess, threw him into the last extremity of desperation.</P>
<P>He was violent and furious in his Temper; and though he had been capable of Sentimenrs more mode∣rate, yet the Princess was inspired with no mean and inconsiderable ones. He spoke as soon as he per∣ceived himself prest to it, but it was with so much boldness, that <HI>Asteria</HI> found she was coming under a new persecution, more afflictive and tor∣menting to her, than all the other: she answered the passionate Declara∣tions of <HI>Themir</HI> with a disdainful, fierceness, which many times set him in such a heat and fury that can∣not be expressed but with a great deal of difficulty. He imagined that <HI>Bajazet,</HI> whose courage was not re∣bated by his misfortunes, did forti∣fie this aversion, and by a new
<PB N="6" REF="8"/>
piece of Injustice, removing him from his Daughter, he was shut up in a prison at a good distance from the Palace, and <HI>Asteria</HI> kept in her Apartment with a greater Guard than she had before.</P>
<P>This procedure gave an accessi∣on to the Princesse's hatred, and in∣raged her more than ever, which made <HI>Themir</HI> become more furious. He went to visit <HI>Bajazet</HI> in his Pri∣son, and indeavoured sometimes by intreaties, and sometimes by threat∣nings, to bring him to a compli∣ance; but having made an unpro∣fitable attempt, he straight had re∣course to the blind Friendship of his Father, and discovering his pas∣sion to him, and the fatal conse∣quences that might attend it, he did so effectually prevail upon his ten∣derness, that he brought him to that pass of undertaking all things that might be for his satisfaction.</P>
<P>He went then directly to <HI>Asteria</HI>'s Apartment, with a resolution not to
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
spare any means likely ro make her flexible. He made her offers, intrea∣ties, and from thence fell to re∣proaches, and still finding her con∣stant in despising his gists and inju∣ries, he became so furious, that he thought he was obliged in point of honour to conquer her; and told her with an absolute imperi∣ous tone, that if she was resolved to persevere in her Obstinacy, he knew very well how to make her repent of it in the person of her Father.</P>
<P>The Princess at those words was struck with a mortal terrour; Do not invelope <HI>Bajazet</HI> in a Resist∣ance where he is not at all concern∣ed, said she to him, pouring down a torrent of tears; the Just refusal I make to marry the murderer of <HI>Ortobulus</HI> my Brother was inspired into me by my own resentments, which were every way legitimate, and if it merits any punishment, on∣ly I ought to suffer it. Leave the
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
days of <HI>Bajazet</HI> to their Natural end, they cannot last very long, and no ways trouble the tranquillity of your Son; you ought to exercise your vengeance upon my life only, and it is against me that every thing proves an earnest solliciter to you. No, no, replied <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> I know better how to chuse my victims, and since for my Son's misfortunes, his days are fastened unto yours, you shall live, but you shall live to see that Father, who is so dear to you, expire in sufferings, and you shall never boast without a punishment, theh aving scorned the Alliance of the greatest Prince in the Earth. He went out as he ended those words; and the overwhelmed Princess fell into a dreadful swoon in the arms of her Woman, who had much ado to recover her from that weakness.</P>
<P>The cruelty of <HI>Tamberlain</HI> did not only consist in words, <HI>Asteria</HI> had order the next day to go to
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
<HI>Bajazet</HI>'s prison, and to dispose him for death, or for a marriage of her with <HI>Themir.</HI> Fatal Choice! for a Daughter who did so dearly love her Father, and detest that un∣worthy Lover! the sight of <HI>Bajazet</HI> had never been permitted her since their Separation; she had often de∣manded it, and would have given the best part of her blood to ob∣tain it; but the fatal condition that was put upon it rendered it then in∣supportable to her, she refused to go, and resolved to do her self some violence, but at last considering that that Obstinacy might possibly hasten her Father's death, she obey∣ed, and suffered her self to be con∣ducted, all over-whelm'd in tears, to the place where they were to bring her; she found there the <HI>Turkish</HI> Emperor so changed that she received his embraces without be∣ing able to speak a word. <HI>Bajazet</HI> asked her what return had obliged the Tyrant to grant her to come
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
and see him: the last of all his cruelties, Seignior, said <HI>Asteria</HI> to him; the severest effect of his In∣justices; in a word, what ever he has in the world that can be most tormenting to us. She then ex∣plained to him in a few words the sad mystery of her visit, and taking away from him all hope that <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI> could ever be made flexible, she gave him fully to know that there was nothing between a shame∣ful and cruel death, and the marri∣age that was so much desired. <HI>Ba∣jazet</HI> could not forbear sighing ve∣ry often during her Discourse; and sometimes casting upon the Princess such looks as were full of pity, and then again throwing most fierce and disdainful Ones on those <HI>Tartars,</HI> who by the Emperors order had waited on her. <HI>Tamberlain</HI> then must judge of my Sentiments by his own, said he to her, if he per∣swades himself that I am capable of betraying the blood and the memo∣ry
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
of my Son, in joyning you to his executioner: No, my dear <HI>Orto∣bulus,</HI> added he, lifting up his wa∣try eyes to Heaven, your <HI>shade</HI> shall never blush at an action so lit∣tle worthy him who had given you a Being: you judge well, Daugh∣ter, pursued he, to think that mine is hateful to me, and that in the de∣plorable estate to which I am redu∣ced, I shall not make a great sacri∣fice to the <HI>Manes</HI> of <HI>Ortobulus,</HI> and to your repose, though I should a∣bandon it to the cruelty of my E∣nemies: but, my <HI>Asteria,</HI> I will tell you more, and those Ministers of the horrid Acts of <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> that do attend you, may report it to him; that though this Marriage might restore me to my highest Fortune, and I might hope from it for felicities as tranquill and untrou∣bled, as my destiny has been uncon∣stant; yet faithful to the remem∣brance of my Son, and jealous of a glory, which all the prosperities of
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
the <HI>Tartars</HI> cannot obscure, I would resist what he exacts from us with the same courage you see me now refuse it. Thus then, Seignior, in∣terrupted the Princess, you are re∣solved for a death that will expose me to all that can be imagined most bloody and dismal. Think, that for my despair, I may be able to sur∣vive you: that the weakness of my Sex does neither permit me to make such escapes, or go about such un∣dertakings, as if I had the strength of the contrary: that I shall always remain <HI>Tamberlain</HI>'s Captive, and the victim of <HI>Themir</HI>'s violences: and that through pity you owe this conversation to the perils where∣with I am threatned: Think your self, replied the Emperour, that you will become the companion of all my miseries; if you force me to prolong those dayes which the cru∣elty of my fate hath rendered but too long already: think, that after the loss of an Empire, and liberty,
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
there is more weakness in support∣ing ones disgraces, than in seeing ones self sacrificed to them; and in∣stead of exciting an unworthy pity which my glory would utterly dis∣allow, do you remember you have your extraction from the most illustrious blood in the World, and so look upon my death as an action that will crown all the former ones of my life: I shall leave you Bro∣thers, whom possibly the bounty of Heaven will regard and pity. My death will suffice to appease its an∣ger, and from it you may receive assistances that will secure you from falling under those evils which so much disquiet you. Ah! Seignior, answered <HI>Asteria,</HI> let us then joynt∣ly expect these Succours, for I will have none of them, if you do not likewise partake with me: Will you then marry <HI>Themir?</HI> Interrupted the Emperour coldly, will you re∣solve that the <HI>Ottoman shade</HI> shall reproach you for the shameful
<PB N="14" REF="12"/>
mingling the blood of <HI>Tamberlain</HI> with his? I would have you live, Seignior, cried the Princess out ve∣ry grievously, or else I would die with you: At these words her Spi∣rits failed her, which obliged them to carry her back to the Palace, without having made any conclusi∣on: and though <HI>Bajazet</HI> was sensi∣bly touched at her grief, yet did he see her go away without changing his Resolution in the least, and con∣tenting himself in putting up vows to Heaven for her, he waited his death with that undauntedness, which is only the partage of great and generous Souls.</P>
<P>Those, who had been witnesses of <HI>Asteria</HI>'s visit, made a very faithful relation of it to <HI>Tamberlain</HI> and <HI>The∣mir,</HI> without ever forgetting the ob∣stinacy or the fierceness of <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s answers. But yet they made some further efforts upon him and the Princess, to obtain of them the con∣sent they desired; but at last per∣ceiving
<PB N="15" REF="12"/>
the more they were prest to it, the more they shewed their stubborness and resolution, the <HI>Ot∣toman</HI> Prince was taken from his Prison, and conducted to the place where Criminals were commonly put to death. All those <HI>Tartars,</HI> that made any profession of vertue, de∣tested that action; <HI>Axalla, Tamber∣lain</HI>'s favourite, and one who was greatly renowned for his extraordi∣nary valour, used his utmost indea∣vours to prevent it; but the Prince had a greater influence upon his Fa∣ther's spirit, and the unfortunate <HI>Bajazet</HI> was unworthily conducted to the Scaffold where he was con∣demned to lose his head.</P>
<P>But how considerable soever the person was, yet was not this Impe∣rial Majesty suffered to have any re∣spect: he went to the fatal place, as if he was the meanest of all Man∣kind, without any thing to distin∣guish him, besides his resolution, and an Air of greatness which it was im∣possible
<PB N="16" REF="13"/>
for all his miseries to despoil him of: he was sorrowful, but withal sedate; and if his eyes had not in them all that vigour and sprightli∣ness as before, they lost not their vi∣vacity from any prospect of fear or weakness. The houses were deso∣late, for all people flockt to the place of execution; And that con∣fusion having obliged a cavalier, who was just then arrived at <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> to demand the cause of it of some Inhabitants; he no sooner under∣stood it, but spurring on his Horse with all the violence imaginable to the Scaffold, he rode through the throng, and came up close to it just in that particle of time, as they were going to put a period to the days of one of the greatest men in the World. His cryes and name sus∣pended that fatal blow: Hold, cry∣ed he out, it is <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> it is the son of <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> who commands it of you. This Prince was dearly beloved by the <HI>Tartars,</HI> and they
<PB N="17" REF="13"/>
with an extream affliction resented his absence; so that they solemnized his return with showts of joy, which for some little time he gave way to; and then pray'd th<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouldiers, who assisted at that action, to stay till he had seen the Emperour before they proceded any further. He ran to the Palace, where he gave an agreeable surprise, to those whom his absence had afflicted, and parti∣cularly to <HI>Axalla,</HI> who alwayes had a most passionate love for him.</P>
<P>Notwithstanding the difference <HI>Tamberlain</HI> had put between his two Sons, the merit of <HI>Adanaxus</HI> dispu∣ted in his breast against the natural inclination he had for <HI>Themir,</HI> and his unexpected sight caused in him so sensible a joy, that it forced him to express it in a shower of Tears; the Prince received his embraces up∣on his knees, and continuing in this submissive posture, Seignior, said he to him, you see again at your feet a rash man, who assured of your
<PB N="18" REF="14"/>
goodness, is come to demand of you a favour of the last importance. 'Tis not the pardon of an absence which you have not approved, I am wil∣ling to be pu<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>shed for it; but, Seignior, it is the life of <HI>Bajazet,</HI> for which I am here upon my knees an humble sollicitour of your genero∣sity. 'Tis an Enemy of a famous name and of a blood that is illustri∣ous, who is no longer in a conditi∣on to prove fatal to you, and whose precipitated loss may be a blemish to your reputation. Think, Seignior, how happy it is to be in an estate to do favours of this kind to persons who have reigned gloriously, and who are depressed meerly through the capriciousness of fortune. Con∣sider, that of all vertues in Monarchs, Clemency is the most glorious, and deserving praise: And at the name of a Son who conjures you to it, sig∣nalize yours in the favours of a great, though now a wretched Em∣perour.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="14"/>
Those words of the Prince of <HI>Tanais</HI> did not less astonish <HI>Tamber∣lain,</HI> then his return had affected him; he could not refrain commen∣ding within his breast the generosi∣ty of his Son; but the importance of his demand ballanced this moti∣on, and made him remain unresol∣ved. If it was any thing perswa∣sive to him, to see prostrate at his feet a Son worthy of esteem, and the uncertainty where he had passed his life rendered him yet more dear, yet <HI>Bajazet</HI> contemning, and rebel∣lious to his designs, kept up his in∣dignation. You ought to let me resent the pleasure of seeing you again, said he to the Prince, with∣out intermixing it with the trouble to demand of me a kindness which it is impossible for me to grant you: <HI>Bajazet</HI> has but too much deserved that death to which he is condem∣ned; he is an insolent Captive, whose arrogance nothing is capable to mo∣derate, who never speaks my name
<PB N="20" REF="15"/>
but with contempt, and who would not spare my life, if he had over it that power which I have over his. I have for a long time indur'd it, but now my patience is quite worn out, and there are so many reasons which authorize what I do, that I should be blamed of imprudence or weakness, should I act otherwise. Whatsoe∣ver reasons you are pleased to al∣ledge for his ruine, Seignior, Answe∣red <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> you yet have more to pardon him; The Example you will leave to posterity, the pleasure that comes from a good action, and your own glory, which would be deeply concerned in causing so great a Prince to fall, whom his severe destiny has delivered into your hands, ought to triumph over all those other considerations. Think, Seignior, that <HI>Bajazet</HI> has not long since seen what you are at present, yet the fate of Arms is capricious, it may do again for him what it has done for you; and if you are out of
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
a prospect of fearing; you have Sons, who may one day meet with Conquerours, and who may implore the same grace I now demand: Do not you then give an Example of in∣humanity, but make some reflection upon the uncertainty of what future times may prove.</P>
<P><HI>Tamberlain</HI> began to stagger at the pressing Reasons of the young Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> he revolved in his mind the circumstances of <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s fate, what he had been, what he was, and considering that he him∣self was risen from a mean fortune to one of the most glorious conditi∣ons of life, and that he might by some return or other fall into the last of miseries, even that in which he saw his Enemy. You have conquered me, Prince, said he to his Son, the tenderness I have for you carries me above my resentment, and in a day that Heaven sends me a Son which I have lamented, it is just Igrant you something may testify
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
how acknowledging I am: Let <HI>Ba∣jazet</HI> live, I am willing to consent to it, but my Son, you must endeavour to overcome his pride, and make, if possible, an unjust Princess com∣pliant, whom the condition of a Captive, my entreaties, my offers, the love and submissions of <HI>Themir,</HI> have not been able to get her con∣sent to marry him, and if you are as sensible of my satisfaction as I am of yours, order it so, that the consent of <HI>Bajazet</HI> to this marriage, be the reward of that life you render to him. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> understood by that discourse, that <HI>Themir</HI>'s love for <HI>A∣steria</HI> was the cause of that cruelty that <HI>Tamberlain</HI> was going to com∣mit, and overjoyed that it was re∣vealed to him, he made what hast he could to prevent its being ef∣fected.</P>
<P>He got himself upon the scaffold, where <HI>Bajazet</HI> with an unshaken con∣stancy did wait his doom. He cut the Cord that tyed that Prince his
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
hands, and saluting him with as much espect as if <HI>Bajazet</HI> had been upon he <HI>Ottoman</HI> Throne. Receive, Seig∣nior, said he to him, this service from a man, who happy as he esteems him∣self in rendring it to you, would not at the price of all his blood but have done it, and who would give a thou∣sand lives such as his, if he had them, to make you forget the necessity that obliged him to give you so shameful a mark of that esteem and conside∣ration he has for you.</P>
<P><HI>Adanaxus</HI> had a charming Meen, and delivered his words with an a∣ction so tender and generous, that <HI>Bajazet</HI> was more enamoured with his sight, than with that life he had conserved to him. He regarded him with all the attention possible to be given to a discourse so extraordina∣ry, and as if his misfortune had not wrought any alteration upon his spi∣rit. Although my life be given me upon condition, said he to him, and by it I prolong those evils which I
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
should be glad to put a period to, yet I receive it from you without a difficulty, and the condition in which I am, does not keep me from being sensible of this obligation, the tran∣scendent virtue you discover does already interess me in what concerns you, and I receive no small consola∣tion in that I have furnished you with a means of giving such remar∣kable proofs, of it. Let us go, Prince, pursued he, holding out his hand to him, let us return from the Scaffold to the Prison, and there wait for the last decrees of heaven: You shall see me again, <HI>Asteria,</HI> added he, drying up some tears, which the remembrance of that Princess drew from his eyes, you shall see me again, if that tender love of yours for a miserable Father, has not made it fatal to you.</P>
<P>Whilst the people by their cryes were applauding the generosity of <HI>Adanaxus</HI> and the safety of <HI>Bajazet,</HI> he was reconducted to his prison, and the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> having gi∣ven
<PB N="25" REF="17"/>
orders for all things that might sweeten it to him, returned to the Palace. He there met with <HI>Themir,</HI> who complemented him, but with so much coldness and indifference, that one might visibly observe in it the remains of that old hatred that had obliged <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to leave <HI>Tar∣tary.</HI> He was extremely troubled to find him still so implacable, but as he did not intend to make a long stay at <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> being called elsewhere by powerful reasons, he resolved for some time to bear with the injustices of his Brother; and af∣ter he had spent part of the Evening with <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> he withdrew to his Apartment with <HI>Axalla,</HI> in a trans∣port of joy, that he had relieved <HI>Bajazet</HI> from so ignominious a death.</P>
<P>As soon as they were without wit∣nesses, they began to speak to one another in their usual way of an open freedom: There had continually been between them a very strict
<PB N="26" REF="18"/>
bond of friendship, and though <HI>Ax∣alla's</HI> age was already advanced, he was of such a sweet and obliging temper, that persons of all Ages were infinitely taken with his company, and he was not less charming in his conversation, than was his valour to be feared when ever he came into the Field. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> asked him a thousand questions, both about the war, and indeed every thing else he thought himself ignorant of; <HI>Axalla</HI> gave him a particular account of all things, and struck him with a hor∣ror for the inhumane actions of <HI>The∣mir,</HI> especially for the death of young <HI>Ortobulus,</HI> whom with his own hand he had cruelly murthered, af∣ter a battel where that young Prince had done immortal actions, and from whence he went out so wounded, that he might have expected the suc∣cour of a generous Enemy, with a great deal of more reason than the death he had received.</P>
<P><HI>Adanaxus</HI> was enraged at that cru∣el
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
piece of barbarity, but passing from discourses of war to those of love, <HI>Axalla</HI> who had a most infi∣nite respect for <HI>Asteria,</HI> by having sometimes the priviledge of seeing her, gave a most noble Character to <HI>Adanaxus</HI> of all those charms that rendred her adorable. She had so many, and they were so advantage∣ously represented by <HI>Axalla,</HI> that he was surprised not to find in the Prince the least motion of curiosity, and blamed him for his too great indifference for Ladies. You de∣ceive your self, <HI>Axalla,</HI> replied the Prince of <HI>Tanais,</HI> sighing as he spake, that Sex has too great an Empire o∣ver me, and my heart could speak to you more justly than any tongue, of the sensible proof I have made of it. 'Tis neither any contempt nor any fear of <HI>Asteria</HI>'s charms, that keeps me from having a curiosity to see them: I honour beauty where∣ever I see it, and am too much pre∣vented by another object, to have
<PB N="28" REF="19"/>
any fear of that of the Princess, but I am not willing to present before her the Son of a man who within this hour would have rob'd her of her Fathers life, as also the brother of him that murthered <HI>Ortobulus.</HI> I will, if possible, during that little stay I shall make at <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> act with some profit for his repose, and en∣deavour before I see her, by my ser∣vices to efface whatsoever the names of <HI>Tartar,</HI> of the Son of <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> and of the Brother of <HI>Themir</HI> might have, that is detestable to her. What Seignior, said <HI>Axalla,</HI> are you in pain whilst you continue here, that you talk of your removal? and have you given us a sence of the joy of your return, only that we should have the greater grief to think of your departure? When you shall have heard the reasons of it, replied <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> you will confess they are not unlawful, but that it is necessa∣ry for my repose to go from <HI>Samar∣canda.</HI> You know Seignior, replied
<PB N="29" REF="19"/>
<HI>Axalla,</HI> the passionate interest I have taken all my life for your concerns, and I am in an earnest impatience to have your reasons told me, therefore I shall be infinitely obliged to you, if you will give me some small ac∣count of them. That I can do very easily, replied the Prince, we are here alone, and this Relation will not be long. Then beginning with some particularities a little more remote,</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="story">
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
<HEAD>The History of Prince <HI>Ada∣naxus.</HI></HEAD>
<P>YOu are not ignorant, said he to his friend, of the reason that obliged me to leave <HI>Tartary,</HI> the violences of <HI>Themir</HI> a∣gainst my most innocent actions, the indulgence the Emperour shewed to his proceedings, and the fear of not being in a continual power to sup∣port them without doing things of a dangerous consequence; All that, I say, you know as well as my self, and made me indeed resolve, among strangers to seek out a more happy life than that I enjoyed in my own Country.</P>
<P>I parted from <HI>Samarcanda</HI> without any retinue, concealing my true name under that of <HI>Arsanes,</HI> and not designing to tarry in any place, but
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
where I might acquire some glory, I visited all <HI>Asia</HI> without finding the employment I sought for. After that I passed into <HI>Europe,</HI> which I knew to be more oppressed with war, and I arrived there at a time that <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s forces were just sinking under the <HI>Grecian</HI> Empire. I knew <HI>Tamberlain</HI> had a most invincible ha∣tred for the <HI>Ottomans,</HI> and that all the <HI>Tartars</HI> had the like affections, and though I found them unjust, yet to do nothing that might one day reproach me, I cast my self into the Emperour <HI>Paleologus</HI> his party, who made head against the <HI>Turks</HI> on the side of <HI>Thrace,</HI> whilst those two Sons <HI>Andronicus</HI> and <HI>Emanuel</HI> defended other Provinces. My first essay was very favourable to my reputation, and without any ambition of being thought a Hero, I may affirm to you <HI>Axalla,</HI> that my actions began to make the name of <HI>Arsanes</HI> eminently considerable. The Emperour gave me many signal testimonies of his
<PB N="32" REF="21"/>
esteem, and finding himself in a dan∣ger out of which I had the fortune to disengage him, he made a publick acknowledgment of the service I did him, and would not permit me to be absent from him.</P>
<P>We had a pretty equal success in both Armies, the battels were so much favoured by the season, but Winter coming on we were oblig'd to give our Troops some rest: The <HI>Turk</HI> retired into his Country, and <HI>Paleologus</HI> went back again to <HI>Con∣stantinople,</HI> where his Sons were or∣dered to meet him. We arrived there nevertheless a Month before them: the Court was very glorious, the Empress, besides her two daughters, <HI>Eudoxia</HI> and <HI>Leonida,</HI> had about her person a great many others, as con∣siderable by their birth, as they were most killingly fair to all their behol∣ders. Mine were dazled with them without being wounded, and hea∣ven which had other persecutions in reserve for me, in this occasion ren∣dred
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
love unpowerful. The grate∣ful Emperour did very obligingly sound my Elogy to all the world, and unknown as I was at <HI>Constantinople,</HI> I bore there a quality but little dif∣ferent to that I ought to have been in. Because the war was in no like∣lihood to be concluded, I was wil∣ling to spend some time at the Court, receiving there a thousand civilities from the Emperour, the Princesses, and from the most considerable a∣mong the <HI>Grecians.</HI></P>
<P>A few days after our arrival, the Emperour received the news that the Princes had defeated a party of the <HI>Ottomans,</HI> and taken a good number of them prisoners, but that which qualified the joy of this good success, was that among those pri∣soners there was a Lady so beautiful, that it was reported <HI>Andronicus</HI> was become passionately in love with her. <HI>Paleologus</HI> who was sufficiently ac∣quainted with the uncontroulable humour of his Son, and who knew
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
very well that he had no moderati∣on in him, when ever he had a mind to any thing, did much fear the con∣sequences of this passion, and as soon as <HI>Andronicus</HI> and the prisoners were arrived, he perceived his fear was too legitimate. When first the re∣port came to us of that love, I con∣demned the frailty and easiness of that Prince's heart, and the inequa∣lity of his choice. But <HI>Axalla,</HI> I was punished likewise by the same fate, for I no sooner had cast my eyes up∣on her who had conquered him, but I felt the kindlings of an ardour in me, which fully assured me that I was fallen into the same condition. <HI>Axalla,</HI> what all the beauties of <HI>Greece</HI> had not the power to do, was in one moment effected by a Fair un∣known: the satigue of a great jour∣ney and the grief of her captivity, could not render her less beautiful to my eyes. Her paleness appeared to me to be infinitely charming, and the indifference▪ which in that con∣dition
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
she shewed to gain any victo∣ries, rendred her in my opinion more deserving to conquer all. Many hearts were forced to submit to her powers as well as mine, and <HI>Neris,</HI> (for so the Captive was called) in a short time became the charm of all <HI>Paleologus</HI>'s Courtiers, as she was the object of jealousie among all the <HI>Gre∣cian</HI> Ladies.</P>
<P>As soon as I perceived my love, and was out of all hopes to overcome it, I found my self the Rival of <HI>Andro∣nicus,</HI> I was one unknown, he was the Emperour's Son and could pre∣tend to all things, where I could hope for nothing; but as repute and fortune do not always contribute to the felicity of Lovers, but it is love and the disposition of hearts which does determine it, I resolved to conceal mine and thought I might succeed better by that discretion than by a publick declaration which possibly might be a means to remove me from the adorable <HI>Neris.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="36" REF="23"/>
You may very well conceive, <HI>Ax∣alla,</HI> that that procedure so contrary to my wishes, did not give me a small affliction, my passion encreased eve∣ry day and my mind was divided between the necessity of being silent and that of speaking, so that I could not resolve with my self which to en∣cline to, my reason made me fly that which a violent inclination compel'd me to look after, maugre all its po∣liticks. My eyes sometimes were not so circumspect as they ought to have been, and when by accident they were cast upon those of <HI>Neris,</HI> they made her a thousand declarati∣ons, but whether she did not under∣stand them, or whether she was a∣fraid to do it, those dumb discour∣ses were very short and withal but seldom.</P>
<P>In the mean time <HI>Andronicus</HI> con∣jured the Emperour by all the en∣treaties and submissions imaginable, that might perswade a Father to re∣sign <HI>Neris</HI> to his love. The inequali∣ty
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
of Fortune, he said, was suffici∣ently recompenced by the merit of <HI>Neris;</HI> and besides her beauty which was extreme surprising, she abound∣ed with so many charms both in her wit and humour, that the Prince thought he had a sufficient Autho∣rity openly to make this demand; the Emperour acknowledged all the advantage of <HI>Neris;</HI> and he had a very high esteem for her, and in his breast did not absolutely con∣demn the Sentiments of <HI>Andronicus;</HI> but having more profitable Allian∣ces in his eye, for the good of the Empire: and the calamities where∣with <HI>Greece</HI> was menaced, not be∣ing able to be avoided, but by the support of a puissance which might oppose the <HI>Ottoman</HI> Forces; he in∣deavoured to divert his Son by po∣licies of State; but seeing him un∣capable of them, he, like an abso∣lute Father, forbad him ever to speak to him any further about the marriage: this prohibition increas∣ed
<PB N="38" REF="24"/>
the fierceness of <HI>Andronicus;</HI> and made him to answer the Emperour in terms that were little respectful, and from that time he laboured to put himself into a condition to be only dependent upon himself.</P>
<P>Things were in these circumstan∣ces for two Months, and the Princes stayed well near three at <HI>Constanti∣nople,</HI> before I had ever spoke to <HI>Neris</HI> any otherwise then in general conversation. It was hard to meet with occasions of speaking to her in private, and I durst not openly seek them; but an accident presented one to me, which I did not in the least expect, and which you may well ima∣gine I did not fail to make use of.</P>
<P>I was walking one Morning in the Palace Gardens, where commonly I was wont to reflect upon my ad∣ventures, and for that purpose I sought out the most solitary places to walk in. I found <HI>Neris</HI> in one of them that was least frequented; and besides the ravishing surprise her
<PB N="39" REF="24"/>
sight gave me, I had a greater to see her in such a place, and at such a time. O <HI>Axalla,</HI> how beautiful did she appear to me, and in what a transport was I at my good fortune? One might observe in her complexi∣on a kind of blushing freshness, like to that which is borrowed from Sleep; the undress she was then in presented to ones eyes a thousand Beauties which most commonly she kept concealed. And the trouble she had upon her when she saw me, gave me a pretty kind of an I do not know what timidity, which ren∣dered me more passionate and har∣dy. I cannot tell whether she took notice of it, or whether it was only in civility that she judged it conve∣nient to withdraw, but she had done so, if I had not stayed her. Ah, fair <HI>Neris,</HI> said I to her, do not car∣ry away with you all the delicacies of these places; But suffer an un∣fortunate stranger to enjoy by your presence those he never thought to
<PB N="40" REF="25"/>
meet with. <HI>Neris</HI> seemed astonish∣ed at my discourse, and looking with her face towards the ground; A miserable Captive, said she, is a very unfit person to contribute to the delights of any place, and in a conversation so languishing as yours you will but throw away that time, which you may imploy to a much better purpose. Would to Heaven, Madam, replied I, I could give all that of my life, and withal you would permit it, I would never else∣where seek a satisfaction which only you can procure me. Such an ear∣nestness you now express would be altogether new, answered she very negligently, and you would have much a do to perswade me into a faith that you had so passionate a one for that which till now appear∣ed to me very indifferent to you. I confess, replied I, without presu∣ming to dive into what might oblige <HI>Neris</HI> to speak so, I took upon me an Indifference absolutely repug∣nant
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
to those sentiments that were real in me: But, Madam, the move∣ments of the Heart, and those of the countenance do not alwayes run parallel, and if you please to have that goodness to distinguish them, I could very well justify that indiffe∣rence whereof you accuse me. I accuse you of nothing, interrupted <HI>Neris</HI> very briskly, and perceive your in∣difference is less criminal, than perhaps would be a closer applicati∣on, but whatsoever your move∣ments are, the calamities I indure do not give me the libertie to con∣cern my self about them, and the un∣happiness of my life is so great, that it does not permit me to think of things wherein I have no Interest. Ah! Madam, cryed I to my self, in a transport of passion, you never had a greater in any heart in the World then you have in mine: there is none so absolutely devoted to you, and though you seem to set so light by it, there shall never be
<PB N="42" REF="26"/>
any capable to give you the services that this shall undertake for you. I have made it my great care and bu∣siness to conceal what I discover to you now, that so I might not ex∣pose my self to the fury of a Rival, who at <HI>Constantinople</HI> is more pow∣erful then I am, and who I fear has enough to countermand my staying in it; but since my fate gives me this opportunity to speak to you without any witnesses, suffer me to explain, Madam, and to tell you, though I appear here unknown yet your condition might be as happy with <HI>Arsanes</HI> as with the Son of the Emperour of <HI>Greece.</HI> All the while I was speaking, <HI>Neris</HI>'s eyes were fixed on mine, and in spight of all her reservedness, I knew by her blushing, by her silence, and by a joy that seemed full of fear, which at last appeared in her face, she wished there might be no untruth in what I had said. One must love very passionately to penetrate into all
<PB N="43" REF="26"/>
these things, but I did not lose any one circumstance of them and ma∣king an happy application of them to my self, I became thereby both more Eloquent, and hardy. I made use of that time that <HI>Neris</HI> was si∣lent to give her an account of the birth of my passion, and did it with so much sincerity that I began to make her believe it. She said no∣thing to me at that time, for the coming in of some persons obliged her to retire: But I could very well guess it by the looks she gave me; and I flattered my self with this thought, that when one has the art to perswade well, one is not very far from that of pleasing well too.</P>
<P>From that time I had my eyes more languishing upon her, <HI>Neris</HI> accustomed her self to their lan∣guage, and sometimes likewise hers in her supprise made me such Dis∣courses as were very obliging; af∣terwards I found out several ways
<PB N="44" REF="27"/>
to renew the conversation in the Garden, where I spoke in such a tender and pressing manner, that I brought <HI>Neris</HI> to a compliance of receiving the offer of my love: the first mark she gave me of her esteem, was her making me the confident of her thoughts, she confessed she had a natural aversion for <HI>Androni∣cus,</HI> that his greatness and his for∣tune were not capable of shaking her, and though he should be pos∣sessor of <HI>Paleologus</HI>'s Throne, he should never be dearer to her heart, nor more agreeable to her eyes. I answered <HI>Neris,</HI> that I was afraid this aversion was general for all men: and she made me to under∣stand by a sigh, one half of which her Modesty deprived me of, that in her breast the Fate of <HI>Andronicus</HI> did not determine that of the rest of Mankind. I did whatever I could to improve the discourse, and to find out what her fortune was: But all I could learn from her was
<PB N="45" REF="27"/>
that she was born in the heart of <HI>Africa,</HI> of a quality sufficiently il∣lustrious, and that she had been ta∣ken by the Pyrates, and afterwards sold to those whom <HI>Andronicus</HI> had taken prisoners.</P>
<P>My passion every day grew more violent, and I wished from my soul that Heaven would be pleased to find out a way for me to show it to <HI>Neris</HI> by some extraordinary ser∣vice: but that was difficult to bring about in a Forreign Court, where I was without any power. My de∣stiny was so favourable to me as to overcome that difficulty, and you shall hear of an adventure which you could never have imagined.</P>
<P>The preoccupation of <HI>Androni∣cus</HI> seemed to increase by the re∣sistance that was made against it, and the Emperour not knowing a∣ny further what means to use to re∣move it, thought that absence only could do the business, and that he was obliged by necessity to deprive
<PB N="46" REF="28"/>
the Prince of an object that became fatal to the repose of a State. He had no very specious pretence pub∣lickly to put that design into exe∣cution, and indeed I know not when he would have had one, if be∣ing conscious as he was of the vio∣lent humour of his Son, he had ad∣ventured to serve himself with any, which made him resolve that <HI>Ne∣ris</HI> should be privately carried a∣way, and that free liberty should be given her to go where she pleased.</P>
<P>It was an easie matter for him to effect it, &amp; Princes do not want per∣sons, who, without examining the commands they give them, do blind∣ly run to perform all their Orders. The design was told them, and the hour stated; and <HI>Neris</HI> was taken from her Apartment, about the middle of the night, and making her to cross the Palace-Gardens, she was conducted to the sea-side which ran by them, where waited a Ves∣sel ready to set sail for the first port
<PB N="47" REF="28"/>
dependant upon any other Prince. <HI>Neris</HI> is Naturally of an even and well balanced temper, and not easi∣ly carried out to make any out-cries or rude efforts. But as she thought her Ravishers were imployed by the Prince, she threatned them with the Emperours Authority, and present∣ed to them the injustice they com∣mitted upon the person of a Cap∣tive, who was then without any to defend her; those words reached a place where very frequently I u∣sed to spend the best part of the night in walking, I presently knew it to be <HI>Neris</HI>'s voyce, and finding them going to use some violence to her: No, Madam, said I, putting my hand to my sword, you shall not be taken away before my Face, and though I be single in your defence, yet possibly I may behave my self with success enough to make these rash men repent they ever under∣took such an Enterprise; those fel∣lows laughed at the threats I made
<PB N="48" REF="29"/>
them, and dividing themselves, one part of their company to ingage with me, whilst the rest were to carry <HI>Neris</HI> away, they did what they could to get to their Boat. But, <HI>Axalla,</HI> one is not sensible of any danger when one is imployed in the preserving of the object of our de∣voted Love. I laid down two of the Villains at my Feet with the first passes I made, and so clearing my way to <HI>Neris,</HI> with a reverse blow, I struck off the man's Arm who held her, and gave her the liberty of saving her self by running through the Garden. Those persons who were ordered to carry her away, without making any great attempt upon my life, left me to run after her, and by that means rescued me from a danger, in which I should o∣therwise most certainly have fell. I pursued them, and forcing them to turn and ingage with me; I had received two dangerous wounds, before some of the Emperour's
<PB N="49" REF="29"/>
Guards, who were got thither by <HI>Neris</HI>'s outcries came to my Suc∣cour, and knowing me to be highly in the favour of their Master, they obliged those that resisted me to be∣take themselves to their heels; they would not have fled, had they dared to discover themselves, for they were Messengers of an Order that was sufficiently warrantable, but they were sworn to secrecy till they had got her to Sea, and they judged it better for them to ac∣quaint the Emperour with what had happened, than to run the ha∣zard of publishing what they had such a strict charge to conceal.</P>
<P>I lost so much blood, that my strength was quite gone, and I fell at <HI>Neris</HI>'s Feet in a trance: but yet my weakness did not prevent me from hearing the obliging com∣plaints she made against Fate, and the affliction wherewith she did ac∣cuse her self for my misfortune; she her self indeavoured what she
<PB N="50" REF="30"/>
could to stop my bleeding, but the pleasure I resented in perceiving <HI>Ne∣ris</HI> to take such pains, made my blood gush out with greater vio∣lence, so that all thought it would prove fatal to me; they recondu∣cted me to my Apartment, and <HI>Ne∣ris</HI> was led by <HI>Andronicus</HI> unto hers, who was come thither at the noise he heard of her being taken away; He bewailed me, protested solemn∣ly he would be revenged on the Author of that bold attempt, and <HI>Neris,</HI> ignorant all this while of the truth, demanded the next day ju∣stice of the Emperour for it in her name and mine. He was obliged either to grant it her, or publickly to justifie the procedure, and not daring to take the latter course, through the fear he was in of his Sons furious transports, he sent one of his principal Officers to declare to me the mystery of that Enter∣prise, and to testifie to me the grief he was in, that she should be the oc∣casion
<PB N="51" REF="30"/>
of my loss of so much blood: the same Officer was ordered to discourse with me about the means of imposing silence upon <HI>Neris,</HI> and of stifling the business; she believes her self mightily obliged to you, said the Gentleman to me, and at the first word will put it up, if you will but advise her to it. Counsel her not any farther to search into the business, but let her un∣derstand that possibly a greater noise would bring along with it but more troublesome consequences.</P>
<P>I knew what I had to say to <HI>Ne∣ris,</HI> and was not in a power to hide any thing from her; but that so I might have some pretence for see∣ing her without being under any suspicion; I promised to obey the Emperor's will, and that procured me many a happy hour with the fair <HI>Neris</HI> by way of visit to me.</P>
<P>She acquainted me how that since that accident <HI>Andronicus,</HI> fearing lest any other should be strongly
<PB N="52" REF="31"/>
pressing her to marry, assured her he had found out a way to marry her himself in spight of the Empe∣ror; you may very well imagine what Counsel I gave her, and what discourses Love put into my head. My prayers and protestations ren∣dring her more opposite to the de∣sires of <HI>Andronicus,</HI> did likewise render my Rivals passion more im∣petuous. She grew into a fury; and one day among the rest, after some propositions more pressing yet than ordinary, he made her know, she was to fear the worst that could be from his violence, and that he was now weary of using only his Intreaties and Submissions. I be∣gan then to leave my Chamber, and went to make my first devoirs to the Empress, where I met with <HI>Neris</HI> going out of the Princess's Apart∣ment, and knew by the sadness of her Countenance, that her breast laboured under a very great afflicti∣on: the Prince was just gone from
<PB N="53" REF="31"/>
making those threatnings to her which I have told you of: her heart was almost dead with fear, and her eyes ready to burst into a shower of tears: what has happe∣ned to you, Madam, said I to her? your eyes reveal something that is fatal to my love, and if my jealou∣sies be just, though altogether weak, and a stranger as I am here in this place; yet you shall see I'll make my vengeance be dreaded by them. I can easily judge what you can do by that which you have done al∣ready, answered <HI>Neris</HI> to me; But, <HI>Arsanes,</HI> all your generosity cannot hinder me from <HI>Andronicus</HI> his per∣secutions. He continues his addres∣ses to me to marry him, and now threatens to use his power, if he finds not his Love sufficient. Ah! Ma∣dam, said I, interrupting her, in a great passion, and how do you re∣ceive his threats? As a person, pur∣sued <HI>Neris,</HI> who imagines nothing can be more cruel than for ever to
<PB N="54" REF="32"/>
be ingaged to a man whom I can∣not love. Ah! Madam, continued I, you shall never then be ingaged to him, relie upon the word and conduct of a Prince, who in any o∣ther place than <HI>Constantinople,</HI> would not submit either to the Son of the Emperor of <HI>Greece,</HI> or to a∣ny other Prince in the world. Have Courage, Madam, take elsewhere upon you a quality more conforma∣ble to your merit, than that of a Cap∣tive; the Sea and my valour shall find us wayes for it, by conducting you eitherto the place of your Birth, or to such retreats as shall be far e∣nough from <HI>Andronicus</HI> his attempts upon you: be not afraid of my Love, it is extreme indeed, but my respect is extreme likewise: You shall find in me a passionate Guide to whom the person is sacred, and a Defender, who will sacrifice his fortune and his life to your safety. <HI>Neris</HI> hearkned to me with a great deal of indulgence, and testified to
<PB N="55" REF="32"/>
me by her looks the acknowledge∣ment of her heart; but yet I could not perswade her to it; therefore I thought my true name might have a greater influence over her than my words, and acquainted her with it: but it would put me to a great deal of pains to express to you the trouble that this Declaration gave her.</P>
<P>She looked upon me a good while, as if she had not known me, blushed, sighed, was speechless, and indeed all her Actions showed me the confusion so great a surprise put her into. However she assured me, that being fully perswaded of the reality of my discourse, she would have a grateful sense of my offers, which should be as lasting as her life: but the more considerable I became to her she had the less de∣sire to hazard so great a Prince. I neither forgot to make use of Oaths, or Prayers, to conquer those Scru∣ples, and to oblige her to remove
<PB N="56" REF="33"/>
from <HI>Constantinople,</HI> but all my ef∣forts were insignificant: she alledg∣ed to me reasons of respect, to which for fear of displeasing her, I was for∣ced to submit; and leaving me, as if she was fearful, she might in her turn be vanquished: do not joyn your self to my misfortunes, Seignior, said she to me, perhaps fate will not distinguish you from <HI>Neris,</HI> and you may fall into such evil circumstances, as may make me to despair that I was the cause of them.</P>
<P>I would have followed her to in∣treat her not to harbour such a fear, and to assure her that in what soe∣ver place her fortune should con∣duct her, I would inseparately wait upon her: but the Empress crossing the place where we were, to go to the Walks, perceived me, and hav∣ing called to me, obliged me to at∣tend her.</P>
<P>In the mean time <HI>Andronicus</HI> was not Idle; he had in part discovered
<PB N="57" REF="33"/>
the cause of <HI>Neris</HI>'s being carried a∣way, and believing he might do what he had a mind to against a Fa∣ther who was resolved to deprive him of the sight of his Mistress: he got together a good number of lu∣sty resolute young Fellows, &amp; made a dangerous Insurrection. The Em∣peror resisted it as well as he could, and I was so fortunate at that time, not to be a little profitable to him. <HI>Andronicus</HI> was taken, and added the shame of being overcome, to that of having made an attempt upon the Crown, and the life of his Father. The older and more experi∣enced of the Emperors Council, were for having him to spend the remainder of his dayes in prison; Prince <HI>Emanuel,</HI> being of a most ad∣mirable sweet disposition, opposed that advice, and with some advan∣tages he might hope to have over the unfortunate <HI>Andronicus,</HI> he did so ingeniously work upon the Em∣perours Spirit, that after the first
<PB N="58" REF="34"/>
heats of resentment were over, he received the Rebel's pardon, and promis'd him to forget the Crime.</P>
<P>But he had more need to repent of that too great clemency of his; <HI>An∣dronicus</HI> did not appear submissive but to get his libertie, which he no sooner obtained, but he made a new insurrection, and as you have heard, almost brought the <HI>Grecian</HI> Em∣pire to its last destruction. I could not ingage my self in these dissor∣ders, I had in the former been so much concern'd as I have told you; but scarce had they begun to break out, but <HI>Neris</HI> disappear'd at <HI>Con∣stantinople,</HI> without any bodies be∣ing able to discover either the rea∣son of her departure, or the place where she had chosen her retreat. At first I accused the Emperour for ha∣ving caused her to be carried away a second time; and besides my grief I made to him a confession of my Love, and I conjured him to tell me where I should find what he had
<PB N="59" REF="34"/>
convei'd away from me: But he so∣lemnly protested he knew nothing of her flight. I could not turn▪ my suspicions upon <HI>Andronicus,</HI> for he was almost driven to desperation at it, and from that accident derived the chief pretence of his revolt. All hope then abandon'd me▪ but only that of searching my self for her, which made me prepare to do it in all the corners os the Earth; but I was surprised by a violent Feaver, which kept me languishing very neer two Months at <HI>Constantinople.</HI> The Emperour had given them or∣ders to pursue his ungrateful Son, and to make him fly where he might never hear of him again. Prince <HI>Emanuel</HI> had command of the Army, and as I extreamly ho∣nour'd him, I should have been ex∣ceeding glad to have kept him com∣pany; but the Remembrance of <HI>Neris</HI> was so much upon my Spirits, that I could not think of doing any thing, but to go and find her
<PB N="60" REF="35"/>
out. I parted from <HI>Constantinople,</HI> after I had complemented the Em∣press, and embarked my self to pass into <HI>Africa,</HI> where according to what <HI>Neris</HI> had told me, I hoped I should hear some news of her. I will not tell you how oft I exposed my self to death, how many dangers I ran, sometimes beaten by tempests, some∣times assaulted by Pyrates; how many Countries I have seen, al∣most unknown to Mankind, with a thousand other circumstances of my voyage, they would make my relation too prolix: Let it suffice I tell you that I have learnt no news of <HI>Neris,</HI> and that her ab∣sence serves only to augment my passion. After I had spent four Years unprofitably I came again in∣to <HI>Asia,</HI> I understood the great revolutions that had happened there▪ the downfall of the <HI>Otto∣man</HI> Empire, and the captivity of the dreadful <HI>Bajazet;</HI> I must ac∣knowledge, <HI>Axalla,</HI> I could not
<PB N="61" REF="35"/>
keep my self from pittying him, and knowing <HI>Tamberlain</HI>'s humour, I did fear what has come to pass, and what I have been so happy to prevent: the thoughts of it made me tremble again, and how unjust so∣ever the Emperour had been to me, yet did Love infuse something in him of a paternal tenderness: I came back with all the hast I could to <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> where I arrived just in sufficient time to prevent the misfortune which would never have given me any comfort. You have now in a few words a very faithful account of the estate of my life, if you have at any time been sensible of the power of Love, you may judg, <HI>Axalla,</HI> if any thing be ca∣pable to give me a repose, so long as I shall hear nothing concerning <HI>Neris.</HI></P>
<P>The Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> having left off speaking, <HI>Axalla</HI> told him for his consolation all that he could
<PB N="62" REF="36"/>
think was able to make any im∣pression on his spirit. It was late e're they parted, and the Inquie∣tudes of <HI>Adanaxus</HI> being renew'd by the recital he had made, caused him to pass the night away in the greatest sorrow imaginable.</P>
<P>In the mean time the Princess <HI>Asteria</HI> had very deeply resented the Joy of <HI>Bajazet's</HI> safety, the suc∣cour he had received came from a very dear hand, and the Prince, igno∣rant of his happiness, had no mind to foresee that the daughter of the <HI>Turkish</HI> Emperour was the same per∣son he had loved under the name of <HI>Neris</HI> in the Court of <HI>Paleologus,</HI> and whom he still loved with so violent a passion. The report of <HI>Adanax∣us</HI>'s return had no sooner came to the ears of the <HI>Ottoman</HI> Princess, but all her grief for him was suspended. She loved this young Prince as much as her vertue could permit her, he had a very tender place in her remembrance, and she could
<PB N="63" REF="36"/>
not without a transport hear he had been preserved in so tedious a Voy∣age; but when to this news was joyned the service he had lately rendered her in the person of <HI>Baja∣zet,</HI> her joy became so powerful, that she could no longer keep it concealed in her breast. She did imagine he knew her for <HI>Neris,</HI> and her return into <HI>Bursa</HI> was with too much noise not to have been pub∣lished in <HI>Greece,</HI> she flattered her self with the thoughts that he still lov'd her, since he came so far, and that too to give her so eminent an instance of it: and looking out <HI>Axalla,</HI> who, as she had observed, frequently did visit him, she in∣genuously confess'd she had an ex∣tream kindness for the Prince, and most passionately complayned to him that he had not given her the means to tell him her self how greatful a sense she had of the ser∣vice he had done her. I know so perfectly the character of your
<PB N="64" REF="37"/>
Soul, Madam, replied <HI>Axalla,</HI> that I foresaw that gratitude, before it was possible for me to see the effects of it; and I would fain have obli∣ged the Prince to do what you de∣sire: But as he is indued with a sin∣cerity beyond example, he acknow∣ledged to me the unwillingness he had to present-before your eyes a Prince, who cannot be innocent in your account since he is the Son of <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> and the Brother of <HI>Themir: Asteria</HI> grew pale at these words, and giving them a cruel explication, she fancied the Inte∣rests of blood had absolutely stifled those of Love, and that <HI>Neris</HI> was no longer charming to <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> since he knew her to be the daugh∣ter of <HI>Bajazet.</HI> But yet she pre∣tended something else was the cause of her trouble, and the rest of the conversation was spent in general complements and civilities. But as soon as <HI>Axalla</HI> was retired, she called a Woman, who had accom∣panied
<PB N="65" REF="37"/>
her in All her misfortunes, and from whom none of her thoughts were a reserve. Ah, <HI>Xaira,</HI> said she to her, what have I learnt? Alas, in vain I flattered my self with the thoughts of be∣ing beloved by <HI>Adanaxus</HI> at his return, and hoped to see him again with the same transports which he expressed when I was at <HI>Con∣stantinople.</HI> He was only concer∣ned for my Father out of generosi∣ty, <HI>Neris</HI> was not in the least the occasion of that adventure, and far from doing any meritorious service to me, and expecting any recompence from it, he came not to see me, but to prefer the duty of the Son of <HI>Tamberlain</HI> to those of the passionate <HI>Arsanes.</HI> Alas! <HI>Xaira,</HI> how criminal is my weakness rende∣red, and how good would it be for me to follow that example he set before me, if I was capable of intimating it. I had in my misfor∣tunes the comfort to believe he did
<PB N="66" REF="38"/>
not any wayes contribute to them, they were less afflictive to me, and in a time when Heaven had taken all things from me, I flattered my felf with the thoughts that he re∣served for me a heart which I had no less an esteem for, then for the Empire of <HI>Bajazet.</HI> But I have lost it, <HI>Xaira,</HI> that heart which was so dear to me, that I gave it all my own; <HI>Adanaxus</HI> will not bely the cruelty of the blood of <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> and more barbarous then our Ty∣rants, he procures the sorrowful <HI>Asteria</HI> a misfortune which all the cruelties of the Emperour of the <HI>Tartars</HI> were not able alone to give her. I do declare the punishment of it by the criminal remembrance I have conserved of a Man, who has only testifyed to me an incon∣stant affection, and by the weakness which forces me still so deeply to resent his levity.</P>
<P><HI>Xaira</HI> interrupted the Princess by indeavouring to comfort her, and
<PB N="67" REF="38"/>
told her all she thought was capable to make her doubt her misfortune, or to reinforce her courage; but she gave no great heed to her, but abandoning her self wholly to her error, she cast a thousand reproach∣es upon the young Prince, whilst he, blindly carried away with the desire of finding out his <HI>Neris,</HI> was preparing for a second Voyage all the Earth over, and found a great deal of difficulty to give his gene∣rosity a few dayes rest at <HI>Samarcan∣da.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Themir</HI> had seen him arrive there with an inraged mind, and could not suffer him to continue in it without giving him some Testimonies of it. He had flattered himself with the hopes that he should never have seen him again, and perceiving he was not returned, but only to pre∣serve a victime from the effect of his vengeance, he was continually pressing <HI>Tamberlain</HI> to put <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> con∣ditions in execution, upo<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>h
<PB N="68" REF="39"/>
he had granted to the Prince the life of <HI>Bajazet,</HI> or else to have him reconducted to the Scaffold from whence he had been taken.</P>
<P><HI>Tamberlain</HI> persecuted on the one hand with the solicitations of his Son, and excited on the other hand by his own natural cruelties, com∣manded Prince <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to go visit the <HI>Turkish</HI> Emperour and to imploy the credit which so strict an obligation had given him with him, to obtain <HI>Asteria</HI> of him. But though <HI>Adanaxus</HI> was fully per∣swaded that he should never bring <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s Spirit to a compliance to such a demand, yet he owed so much obedience to <HI>Tamberlain</HI> as this came to. He went then to the pri∣son where <HI>Asteria</HI>'s Father was, with a resolution to use all the honoura∣ble means he could to gain him to it, and to make him consider after all, that the quality of being Em∣press of the <HI>Tartars</HI> was not a thing for a Captive Princess to contemn.</P>
<P><PB N="69" REF="39"/>
Though <HI>Bajazet's</HI> life was only conditional, the service he had re∣ceived from the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> had wrought in him all the effect it could do upon a mind that is truly grateful: he had none of those barbarous blindnesses that lessen the value of civilities done to a person, and then confound them with inju∣ries. It was not from the hands of <HI>Adanaxus</HI> that the effects of his mis∣fortune did proceed; he knew him not but by a considerable service he had done him, and he received his visit with a great deal of satisfacti∣on, Seignior, said <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to him, after they had ended their first com∣plements, if it had pleased Heaven to have seconded my vows, I would have rendered you my submissions in a place more worthy of you than this is, but since my good inclinati∣ons prove weak, and mauger all my intreaties, you are still a prisoner. I am come to offer you all that may contribute to make this place less
<PB N="70" REF="40"/>
grievous to you. Seignior, answe∣red <HI>Bajazet,</HI> according to the fashi∣on I now lead my life, it very little concerns me in what place I spend it, for all are equal to me in <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI>'s Dominions. But do not think, Seignior, that this indiffe∣rence extends its self even to what I ow you, and that it extenuates a∣ny thing of my obligations to you. I am neither forgetful of the valour, manner, or circumstances of it: For I protest to you my greatest afflicti∣on is that I am not in a capacity of testifying to you my real resent∣ments: I have done so little, Seig∣nior, replied the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> in comparison of the reparation I owe you, that it deserves not your remembrance; but as nothing is so afflictive to those who love and are acquainted with glory, as to see such a person as you in fetters, I would willingly do so much as may make my intentions pass for effects. If you have any concern for the re∣pose
<PB N="71" REF="40"/>
of those who are likewise joyn∣ed with you in your misfortune, Seignior, you ought to be more pi∣tiful to your self, and consider on the means that are offered you to get out of this place. Pardon me, if knowing, as I do, your just aversi∣on for <HI>Themir,</HI> I presume once more to propose him to you for the Prin∣cess your Daughter. In a more hap∣py time I should not do this out∣rage to the hatred which exaspe∣rates you; but the pressing necessi∣ty of your Affairs, the continual fears in which you put <HI>Asteria▪,</HI> all that which threatens you, and what may happen, are such powerful rea∣sons, as I am forced to speak to you of it. I am sensible that <HI>Themir,</HI> is accused of many crimes, and I cannot own that he is not guilty as to your particular: but, Seignior, the love he bears the Princess may render him more reasonable, he would not be the first whom this passion should have changed, and
<PB N="72" REF="41"/>
what speaks more in his favour than all things else is, that there is not any thing to which upon <HI>Themir</HI>'s consideration <HI>Tamberlain</HI> cannot be obliged. I confess, Seignior, it is a hard thing to conquer ones self in matters of such importance as this; but what cannot the courage of <HI>Ba∣jazet</HI> do? If I could tell any other means how to deliver you out of this place, I would not have pro∣posed this to you. Ah! would to Heavens, that in contempt of <HI>The∣mir</HI>'s repose, and of my own life, I could imagine any any other way; I would not balance the electing of it; but Seignior, nothing but this remains, of consenting to the Mar∣riage of <HI>Asteria,</HI> and therefore I would conjure you to make some reflections upon it.</P>
<P>Prince, answered <HI>Bajazet,</HI> coldly, I do not doubt but that you would serve with zeal all those who could any wayes move your pity, since I have made such a convincing expe∣rience
<PB N="73" REF="41"/>
of it; but I am both surpri∣sed and afflicted, that after you have treated me like a Prince, and have set some value upon the actions of my life, you look upon me as the slave of <HI>Tamberlain.</HI> Do not you judge of my Sentiments by my misfor∣tunes, it is not in the power of chains and fetters to make me forget my name, nor can any torments debase the mind of a Prince who has pre∣scribed Laws to the <HI>Ottoman</HI> Em∣pire, and has been the destiny of many others. You do not possibly know, that this <HI>Themir,</HI> which you offer to me for a Son in Law, is the Author of all my sufferings; that it was his criminal hand, that basely before mine eyes did spill the blood whom I intirely lov∣ed, whose vertues promised an end∣less happiness to my life, and whom I saw expire by his sword without being able to give him any Succour. Ah! Seignior, if you believe me to have any valour and resolution,
<PB N="74" REF="42"/>
judge by the tears that this remem∣brance fetches from me, unto what excess my indignation swells. 'Tis one of <HI>Themir</HI>'s most bloody out∣rages, but it is not the only One, <HI>Bursa</HI> pillaged; <HI>Sebastia</HI> destroyed; my Children become Fugitives; my Wife, oppressed with the rigours of her captivity, dead; <HI>Asteria</HI>'s imprisonment; my own, and the treatments I have met with in it, are as so many effects of his furies: and ah! would you have me, Seig∣nior, renounce my hatred in favour of an Enemy who has so well de∣served it? No, no, let <HI>Tamberlain</HI> look to his own Rights, and give me leave to injoy the freedom of my breast; it is a comfort to me in my misfortunes to think that this liberty cannot be ravished from me, but that I can without any remorse or scruple wish to see <HI>Tartary</HI> o'r∣whelmed with Enemies that may be merciless; <HI>Samarcanda</HI> abandoned to flames and pillage; <HI>Themir</HI> to
<PB N="75" REF="42"/>
serve as a victim to the cruelties of a mutinous people; and <HI>Tamberlain</HI> to follow the Chariot of a Conque∣ror, as little generous as himself. My liberty possibly may be too great, Seignior, but I cannot dis∣semble my thoughts, and indeed, it is that sincerity which obliges me to assure you, that if Heaven would be favourable to my desires, I would do no less for your fortune than I would for my vengeance; for I have a very valuable esteem for your merit, and do conserve in me a heart that is not unsensible of my obligation to you. I am too much indebted to your goodness my self, replied <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> for putting so high a value upon services that are so inconsiderable; and give me leave to answer you with the same liberty, there is not any thing I would refuse to do to deserve it. But, Seignior, must I renounce the hopes of obtaining any thing from you? consult a little the necessity
<PB N="76" REF="43"/>
of the time, and do some violence upon your self to escape the fatal consequences that may attend your refusal: the present time is so wretched that it puts me into a ca∣pacity of dreading the future, in∣terrupted <HI>Bajazet,</HI> and there is no∣thing that we need to fear, when we have only a life to look after, which derives all its troubles and torments from the length of it. But, Seignior, that I may not be reproach∣ed for slighting your negotiation, and that I may let you know how dear I account your kindnesses to me; let <HI>Themir</HI> restore me my li∣berty; let him leave me to injoy the wrecks of my fortune with some equality; in a word, let him follow the example of your genero∣sity, and then I will hearken to his Propositions; but a heart like mine knows not how to yield to any thing, when I am in chains, and I have a soul too resolute, to give to the least of my Actions an appear∣ance
<PB N="77" REF="43"/>
of a base and cowardly con∣straint.</P>
<P><HI>Adanaxus</HI> found so much of the Hero in <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s discourse, that he could not answer him any further; only he assured him he would im∣ploy his utmost power to incline <HI>Tamberlain</HI> to grant him the liberty he demanded; and so immediately went to find out the Emperour his Father, to whom he forgot nothing that might any wayes be conducive to bring things to such a conclusion; but the Proposition was not receiv∣ed, nor indeed so much as hearkned to.</P>
<P>What, said <HI>Tamberlain</HI> to him, when possibly by a Sentiment that discovers too much of humanity, I do consent that <HI>Themir</HI> should mar∣ry the Daughter of the Captive <HI>Bajazet,</HI> do I not bestow upon him a Grace that is sufficiently conside∣rable? He would fain prescribe me Laws in my Empire, and get to him∣self a liberty, who has cost me so
<PB N="78" REF="44"/>
many thousand men: No, no, so easie a compliance would load me with an Eternal shame; and all <HI>Asia</HI> would call me to an Account for so important a prisoner: Let him pe∣rish, since he is resolved on't, and let <HI>Themir,</HI> to render himself happy, make use of the Rights and Privi∣ledges of his Victory. We have too much neglected them, and the reso∣lute <HI>Bajazet</HI> thinks to prevail upon the Remonstrances of our weakness. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> was very much troubled at this Determination; and though <HI>Tamberlain</HI> was resolved to have him execute it, and also forbad the Young Prince to bring him back so much as the least resistance to it, yet could he not forbear making some unprofitable intreaties: but at last he was commanded to pursue it so absolutely, that he was forced to do it, and he retired into his Apart∣ment, as much afflicted at <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s unhappiness, as if he had known the secret Interest he ought to take in it.</P>
<P><PB N="79" REF="44"/>
In the mean time <HI>Asteria</HI> entered into the Chamber of this illustrious Prisoner. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> had obtained their liberty of seeing one another; he said that those Interviews might be conducive to the happy success of his Negotiation; and the Prin∣cess having heard that the Prince had been long in discourse with the <HI>Turkish</HI> Emperor, came to know the subject of it.</P>
<P>Ah! Daughter, said <HI>Bajazet,</HI> as soon as he saw her, how opportune∣ly do you come to console me under that vast accession of grief which I have now received. Prince <HI>Ada∣naxus</HI> to whom I am redevable for my life; and who has prevented my having for him so high an e∣steem, is joyned to our Tyrants for my persecution, and has made such discourses to me, which coming from him are more insupportable, than all that <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> or <HI>Themir</HI> were ever able to invent. <HI>Adanax∣us</HI> persecute you, Seignior, inter∣rupted
<PB N="80" REF="45"/>
<HI>Asteria,</HI> after a languishing manner! yes, he does, but in so handsom a fashion, pursued <HI>Bajazet,</HI> that in appearance I have no cause to reproach him for it; he speaks to me in the behalf of <HI>Themir,</HI> and seems to propose him to me as the means of facilitating my liberty; but all things well considered, it is still to make an attempt upon the just motions of my hatred, and this proceeding is more afflictive to me, coming from a Man to whom I am so much obliged, then if it had come from my most irreconcileable enemies.</P>
<P>The Princess was so disturbed at <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s discourse, that she was at a loss how to return any answer to it; she sighed, and in spight of all oppo∣sition she could not refrain shedding some tears, to which the <HI>Turkish</HI> Emperour gave such an explication, as they did not deserve; but, Daughter, pursued he, looking up∣on her very stedfastly, I perceive
<PB N="81" REF="45"/>
this greatly afflicts you; would you have forgot what you owe to the resentments of your Father, and to the blood of <HI>Ortobulus,</HI> and should the <HI>Tartar</HI> Prince have come to speak to me at your intreaty? at mine? Just Heavens! cried the sor∣rowful Princess: Ah! Seignior, you penetrate into the sentiments of my breast greatly to my disadvantage, to think I am in the least capable to ingage <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to speak in <HI>The∣mir</HI>'s favour, how you o'rwhelm me with joy, my Child, added <HI>Bajazet,</HI> in giving me this protestation, let it be to you an indispensable Law; and because possibly we may not al∣ways injoy this liberty of conver∣sing together, observe diligently this I am going to say, that what vi∣olence soever is used against me, do not you betray any weakness at it; prefer this charge of mine to all that a paternal affection can inspire you with: be you generous by my ex∣ample, and give up your life with
<PB N="82" REF="46"/>
mine, if it be necessary, rather than betray my just resentments against <HI>Themir.</HI></P>
<P>The Princess presently promised the Emperor her Father what he had exacted from her obedience; the disinteressed Love of the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> had given her a real ten∣derness: she had not the power to defend her self from being in love with a person who was so worthy of her kindness; and being sensi∣ble by a cruel experience, that though he should deserve it less, she could not get him from her breast, she withdrew to her own Apartment so drowned in sorrow, and filled with despite, that she had almost resolved upon some actions that would have been unworthy both of her moderation and cou∣rage. She made <HI>Xaira</HI> to be called, to whom she recited all that <HI>Baja∣zet</HI> had told her, and accompanying her discourse with a thousand re∣proaches against her faithless adorer,
<PB N="83" REF="46"/>
she stirred up so much pity in her woman, that she appeared as much afflicted as the Princess. He is un∣faithful, this <HI>Arsanes,</HI> said she to her, who seemed so little capable of infidelity; he betraies both his oaths, and my hopes, and not only forgets the Love he promised <HI>Neris,</HI> but he would with his own hands deliver her into those of an unworthy Rival. Ah! <HI>Xaira,</HI> how treacherous is the Sex of Men, how fatal is that of ours, and how wretch∣ed and little experienced do we discover our selves, when we be∣lieve any thing that Mankind tells us? <HI>Xaira</HI> made her no answer but with her tears, which were mingled with those of the Princess, but fate was preparing for them occasions of grief that were more legitimate, and they ought to have reserved those they then shed for a more pressing opportunity.</P>
<P><HI>Bajazet</HI> was Master of the moti∣ons of his Soul, and kept them from
<PB N="84" REF="47"/>
breaking out by any action contrary to his constancy; but he could not prevent the impression they made upon his health. The Prince of <HI>Tanais</HI> his visit had extreamly trou∣bled him; that of <HI>Asteria</HI> had much increased it, and all this succeeding the preparatory of an unworthy punishment, and of a long retinue of miseries, made him fall into a sickness which he no sooner felt coming upon him, but he judged it would be his mortal one. If he was affected with it, it was only with joy; and the violence of his distemper did not in the least de∣prive him of his reason, for he per∣ceived with pleasure by the dimi∣nution of his health, that his suffe∣rings were now ready to take their leave of him, and to end with his life. Yet he lay languishing many dayes; but finding himself almost at his last period, he ordered that <HI>Asteria</HI> should be called; and the Princess observing in his counte∣nance
<PB N="85" REF="47"/>
the infallible presages of his death, fell into such an agony of grief, that it wanted but little to cast her into the resembling conditi∣on. The dying Emperour indea∣voured as well as he could to com∣fort her; he commanded her to re∣ceive the assistances of the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> as from the only person could give her such as were gene∣rous, and disinteressed; and being desirous to ingage that Prince not to betray his confidence in him; he sent to beg of him the favour to come unto his prison. The Prince would not have stay'd for this In∣treaty, if he had not apprehended his visit might be troublesome: he went to him in all haste, and <HI>Baja∣zet</HI> reaching out his hands to him; merciful death is now going to free me from the Tyranny of <HI>Tamber∣lain,</HI> Seignior, said he to him, and I on a suddain feel that fate is robbing him of the pleasure to bring me new persecutions, or to exercise his
<PB N="86" REF="48"/>
generosity, if ever he should be made capable of it. I should look upon this so much longed for mo∣ment without any trouble, if I did not apprehend it would prove fatal to the unfortunate <HI>Asteria;</HI> and that having no longer the resolution of her Father to support her, she will fall into a misery that will be more dreadful to her than the most shame∣ful death in the world. Relieve me, Seignior, from this fear, and please to give me your promise to protect a deplorable Princess, whom at my death I commit into your hands. Captivity, death, and the other caprices of fortune have not yet been capable to render <HI>Bajazet</HI> a suppliant; but a paternal affecti∣on has greater influence than all these things, and you see me with tears beseeching you to defend <HI>A∣steria</HI> against the violence of <HI>Themir.</HI> She is prudent and couragious; but she is young, and my Child, pro∣mise me, Seignior, that she shall have
<PB N="87" REF="48"/>
your pity, and that in her you will consider the remains of a precious blood, that will owe all her glory to you, if you afford it a generous succour against the violence of her Tyrants.</P>
<P><HI>Adanaxus</HI> was so moved by <HI>Ba∣jazet</HI>'s discourse, that he could not refrain his tears; he would not have ballanced giving him all the promises he was able to exact, if he had not apprehended himself too weak to make them good; and this Impuissance rendering him some∣what reserved; <HI>Bajazet,</HI> though he knew himself sufficiently generous, suffered himself to be surprized with some little diffidence, and or∣dered the Princess to be called, that she might indeavour to bring <HI>Ada∣naxus</HI> to a determination by her presence, or to give her stricter or∣ders than yet she had received. She had heard the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> was with the Emperor, and wavering between a secret desire of seeing
<PB N="88" REF="49"/>
him again, and an inraged passion she thought he justly deserved, she had past away the time of <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s conversation with him in such dis∣quietudes as can never fully be ex∣prest: there were still some marks of her trouble upon her counte∣nance, and the tears she was so pro∣digal of at her Father's sickness, had made her eyes all red, as they had put an extream paleness into her face; but yet this change made her not unknown to the eyes of the <HI>Tartar</HI> Prince, he came up three or four steps to her, and his surprise not permitting him to come any farther, he stop'd and became immoveable: and found himself at that juncture of time capable of doing nothing but giving her his most languishing regards. He at last pronounced the Name of <HI>Neris</HI> many times over, with such remarkable demonstrati∣ons of Love, that <HI>Asteria</HI> was al∣most certain of her errour, and be∣came as weak as <HI>Adanaxus.</HI> The <HI>Turk∣ish</HI>
<PB N="89" REF="49"/>
Emperor looking upon them with as great an astonishment as sen∣sibility, was going to demand of them the reason of their so strange surprise, but he was prevented by the coming in of Prince <HI>Themir.</HI></P>
<P>Possibly he hop'd, that as the ex∣tremity of his sickness did render him more weak, it likewise would make him more complying, and he came to make his last essay to con∣quer his valiant resolution: but it seemed to have an accession by the sight of <HI>Themir;</HI> and <HI>Bajazet</HI> ima∣gining that that Prince came but to tyrannize over the last moments of his life, was so seised with rage and horror, that he fell into mortal con∣vulsions. The Princess ran to him almost distracted with grief, and the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> making an effort upon himself to succour a man who was become so dear to him, sent for all <HI>Tamberlain</HI>'s Physicians, though their art to him was unprofitable. <HI>Bajazet</HI> gave them no other signs of
<PB N="90" REF="50"/>
life, but by his looks, which though dying, yet expressed the horror he had for <HI>Themir;</HI> and expiring in the Arms of the afflicted <HI>Asteria,</HI> she had reason enough to make her reproaches against <HI>Themir,</HI> for that his visit had some minutes sooner hastened the death of the unfortu∣nate <HI>Bajazet.</HI></P>
<P>She did not conceal from him this new cause of her resentment; but forcing away those Sobs which hin∣dered her Speech; Go on, Barbari∣an, said she to him, expose me still to thy sight for some time, and by that excess of thy cruelty joyn the miserable <HI>Asteria</HI> to the Emperor her Father, and to Prince <HI>Ortobulus.</HI> Those words having struck Prince <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to the Soul, he went to conjure <HI>Themir</HI> to render himself sensible, now it was in his power, and to grant to the tears of <HI>Asteria</HI> some hours of solitude. But <HI>The∣mir</HI> too much hated his Brother, and had observed him to be too fa∣vourably
<PB N="91" REF="50"/>
distinguished by the <HI>Turk∣ish</HI> Emperor, and his Daughter, to receive his Counsels with any pati∣ence. I did not come hither, said he very fiercely to him, to receive any advice from you; and I can scarcely apprehend the motive of this confidence, though I would in∣stantly punish the Author of it, if I did not observe in it some circum∣stances which I would examine be∣fore ever I did inflict that punish∣ment. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> found himself no longer to be in a suffering humour, and since he knew his <HI>Neris</HI> was <HI>A∣steria,</HI> he quickly perceived in <HI>The∣mir</HI> such qualities that might make him dispence with his wonted mo∣deration. What would be a bold∣ness in Another, said he to him, must be called by another name in the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs;</HI> and if till now the respect I owed to the Emperor has constrained me to some obser∣vances; even that respect obliges me to defend in my person the ho∣nour
<PB N="92" REF="51"/>
of his blood, and to prevent the doing any outrage to it. <HI>The∣mir</HI> stormed at those big words he said to him, and but that <HI>Axalla</HI> ve∣ry fortunately came in, the presence of the Princess would not have been powerful enough to have kept the two Brothers from a bloody in∣gagement: but that Illustrious Fa∣vourite making use of the power he had over the spirit of <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> to oblige him to withdraw, and the extream affliction that <HI>Asteria</HI> was in, having at last constrained <HI>The∣mir</HI> to leave her to her repose, this difference was suspended, and <HI>Axal∣la</HI> ran to advertise the Emperor of it, that so he might put his Autho∣rity in force to make an absolute ac∣commodation between them.</P>
<P>But on the other hand the proud <HI>Themir</HI> was no sooner got to the Palace, but he caused <HI>Odmar</HI> to be sought for: This person had been Governour of the Prince of <HI>Tarta∣ry,</HI> of a wicked and pernitious spi∣rit,
<PB N="93" REF="51"/>
and a barbarous humour, and who had inspired into him by a dangerous education, those vio∣lences and furious resolutions, which made him capable of so ma∣ny cruelties, and he would lay his contrivances with so much artifice and security, that though he had been of his blood, they could not have more resembled those of <HI>Od∣mar.</HI> As he was <HI>Themir</HI>'s only con∣fident, it was in the Counsels of a man so capable as he was to give him such as were conformable to the violent transports he was at that time in, that that Prince was so earnest to have him found out, that he might be relieved from the trouble that possest him, whilst the afflicted <HI>Asteria</HI> poured out a flood of tears for her Father's death, in her Apartment of the Palace, whither she had been reconducted; and <HI>Ax∣alla,</HI> who found the Emperor inga∣ged with some of his Nobles about very important Affairs, could not
<PB N="94" REF="52"/>
say any any thing to him of the Princess; but being by his Orders commanded to attend him, <HI>Ada∣naxus</HI> was deprived of the consola∣tions that that Prince might give him, and of learning from him the truth of her adventure, and his coming again to know that <HI>Asteria</HI> proved to be his <HI>Neris.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>The End of the First Part of <HI>Asteria.</HI></TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="part">
<PB N="95" REF="52"/>
<HEAD>ASTERIA, OR TAMBERLAIN. A NOVEL.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">The Second <HI>PART.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THe First Counsels that <HI>Odmar</HI> gave <HI>Themir,</HI> after he had understood what had past in <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s prison, were to search into the Sentiments which induced the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> to be so sensi∣ble of his loss, and <HI>Asteria</HI>'s grief; and what made him so fierce in his Answers; and pressing <HI>Themir</HI> with an opinion that they might possi∣bly proceed from Love, he instilled
<PB N="96" REF="53"/>
into him a hatred against the young Prince, which proved the occasion of a very violent jealousie.</P>
<P>They fell presently upon their search, and as nothing was difficult to them, they made the next day all those come before them, who had attended <HI>Bajazet</HI> in in his sickness; and the least pro∣mise of a Prince, who was able to do all things, made them affirm that before <HI>Themir</HI> came into the room, the <HI>Turkish</HI> Emperor, and <HI>Adanax∣us</HI> frequently flung themselves into one anothers embraces; at the sight of <HI>Asteria</HI> the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> seemed extraordinarily surprized, and had often called her by ano∣ther Name then that they knew her by: there was nothing more need∣ful to perswade suspitious spirits, than that the acquaintance of the Princess and <HI>Adanaxus</HI> was not of a new foundation, but there was a particular understanding and in∣trigue between them. In <HI>Themir</HI>'s
<PB N="97" REF="53"/>
first rage, he thought upon nothing, but stabbing his Brother before <HI>Asteria</HI>'s face; but <HI>Odmar,</HI> who was more prudent in his cruelty, con∣vinced him that it would be a great deal better to destroy such an Ene∣my with more safety, and less noise.</P>
<P><HI>Themir</HI> too much relied upon <HI>Odmar</HI>'s advice, not to submit him∣self to it; and fearing lest the Prince of <HI>Tanais</HI> should find out some way to see the Pricness, he was resolved to take the surest mea∣sures he could to prevent him in it: and addressing himself to the Em∣peror, he told him, that <HI>Asteria</HI> be∣ing deprived of having any further fears for her Father, might be con∣triving now how to make her es∣cape, and therefore it would be re∣quisite to have her Guards doubled, and not to permit any body to make her any Visits. <HI>Tamberlain</HI> present∣ly consented to that new precauti∣on, and made <HI>Themir</HI> Master of that affair, who immediately commanded
<PB N="98" REF="54"/>
an Officer to go and double <HI>Asteri∣a</HI>'s Guard, and to forbid any en∣trance into her Apartment besides himself; the Officer obeyed him, but as he was coming up to the Princess's Chamber, he met <HI>Ada∣naxus,</HI> who was just joyned with <HI>Axalla,</HI> as he was coming from it; the sight of the Guards made the Prince question the truth of it; he presently asked them what was the occasion of their being in that place; and having learned it, his first choler had e'n almost proved fatal to them. He had laid his hand upon his Cimetar, but the pru∣dent <HI>Axalla</HI> representing to him the necessity he had to suffer <HI>Themir</HI> freely to act his pleasure, through his want of power to oppose him in it with success, and that by such a violent procedure he might possi∣bly loose the means of being ser∣viceable to the Princess with the Emperour, who was so strangely fond on <HI>Themir,</HI> that he looked
<PB N="99" REF="54"/>
upon him as one, whom he had not the power to deny any thing. <HI>A∣danaxus</HI> was perswaded by him, contenting himself with a deep sigh; he was just going to give <HI>Axalla</HI> an account of his acquaintance with <HI>Asteria;</HI> not having as yet met with any convenient opportunity to do it, as also of the design he had to go and aggravate to <HI>Tamberlain</HI> the cruelties that were used against an illustrious, and a miserable Princess, when he perceived <HI>Themir</HI> coming towards him, whose impatience of knowing whether his Orders were put in execution had caused him to be upon the back of the Guards; they looked upon one another with eyes that no whit discovered the re∣lation that was between them, and <HI>Themir</HI> beginning the discourse in a very opprobrious and scornful man∣ner; have you been consoling <HI>A∣steria</HI> after the Death of <HI>Bajazet,</HI> said he to him? and may we hope that the acknowledgement she owes
<PB N="100" REF="55"/>
you will be any obligation to make her satisfie the Emperor's pleasure and my desires? you express your desires by violences so outragious to a generous breast, replied <HI>Adanax∣us,</HI> that I can scarce believe they can be favourably heard: and the negotiations I have undertaken in your favour are too ill grounded to give you any hopes of their hap∣py success; the indeavours you use in explaining them, answered <HI>The∣mir,</HI> do contribute much to the rendring of them unprofitable, and I have great obligations to you which I am sufficiently informed of, we may one day discourse of them more o∣penly, added he, with a furious look; in the mean time, I shall go and know of the Princess what you have done for me. As he ended those words, he turn'd towards <HI>Asteria</HI>'s Apartment, and <HI>Axalla</HI> got the Prince of <HI>Tanais</HI> away, for fear lest at the return some other discourses more fierce and bit∣ter should make them proceed to worse actions.</P>
<P><PB N="101" REF="55"/>
I will leave you near <HI>Asteria,</HI> said <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to him, when they were got to another place. You are just now come from her, have you not procured some abatement of her grief? or does she still abandon her self to it with the same vio∣lence? I did not entertain her long, replied <HI>Axalla;</HI> but, Seignior, since you are pleased to speak of <HI>Asteria,</HI> preferably to what we may say of <HI>Themir,</HI> give me leave to take no∣tice, that you seem to be very sen∣sible of her misfortunes, and the scruple you made of seeing her has not been able to stand against the first moments of her sight. Ah! dear <HI>Axalla,</HI> answered the Prince, it is not from to day that her sight has had its effect upon my heart, and to tell you in one word the most surprising thing that ever you have heard; that <HI>Asteria</HI> whom you see at <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> is the same <HI>Neris</HI> to whom I did devote my self in the Court of the <HI>Grecian</HI> Empe∣ror.
<PB N="102" REF="56"/>
What? Seignior, interrupted <HI>Axalla,</HI> can it be true you tell me? and has the Daughter of <HI>Bajazet</HI> before this last Captivity felt the miseries of a former one? Alas, an∣swered <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> it is but too cer∣tain for my repose: yes, <HI>Axalla,</HI> it is the Father of <HI>Neris,</HI> to whom <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI> has procured all these mis∣fortunes; I am of that blood which is so justly hateful to her; but what heightens my affliction to the last extremity, is that I have made use of all my Rhetorick to get her to be delivered over to the barbarous <HI>Themir;</HI> and she may suspect me of having preferred a base and unwor∣thy complaisance for the desires of of my Father, to that fidelity which is redevable from me to her.</P>
<P><HI>Axalla</HI> could scarce recover him∣self out of this surprise, and any o∣ther besides the Prince would have had a difficult task to convince him of the reality of what he then heard; but his sincerity not leav∣ing
<PB N="103" REF="56"/>
in him any room to doubt of so extraordinary a truth, and fore∣seeing the disorders that this acci∣dent was likely to bring into the Imperial House of <HI>Tartary.</HI> Ah! Seignior, said he to the Prince with grief, how fatal is this <HI>Neris</HI> to those States where her destiny has con∣ducted her, and how cruel a way does she take to revenge <HI>Bajazet</HI> of the rigours of his captivity: let us not think of the revenges she may exercise over the Children of <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> answered <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> and reflect upon nothing but how to make her know the real senti∣ments of <HI>Arsanes:</HI> If I did follow my transports, I should indeavour to find at her feet either my death or justification; but yet I am not less respectful than she is cruel; my sight would possibly trouble her and yet I study the tranquillity of her life: go then, and see her, I con∣jure you, you are now acquainted with our Interests; improve those
<PB N="104" REF="57"/>
of the passionate <HI>Adanaxus;</HI> the tears that <HI>Neris</HI> sheds, have not con∣cealed her anger from me, and whe∣ther she considers me as the son of the Tyrant, or as a Lover that is unworthy of her, it is most cer∣tain that she indeavours to shun me.</P>
<P>So far as <HI>Axalla</HI> durst venture himself in the favour of <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> being more generous then he was politick, he made him a promise to do whatsoever he desired; where∣upon the Prince reassumed some hopes, but they were cruelly abu∣sed; when <HI>Axalla</HI> told him, that having been to see <HI>Asteria,</HI> his en∣trance into her apartment had been refused him. This indignity was very outragious to such a person as he was; but he presently under∣stood that this was an effect of <HI>The∣mir</HI>'s precautions, and of <HI>Odmar</HI>'s counsels; and the only thing he then could do, was to advise the Prince to patience; but yet it was not in his power to keep him from
<PB N="105" REF="57"/>
making his complaints to the Empe∣ror of the severities that were u<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed to <HI>Asteria.</HI></P>
<P>Seignior said he to him, <HI>Baja∣zet</HI> is dead; there only now re∣mains a fair young Princess in your fetters, whose Eminence and Sex should make you dispense with suf∣fering her to feel the weight of them; yet, Seignior, after the death of a Father whom she so dearly loved, in a time that she is capable of nothing but tears; her guards are doubled, she is reduced to seek her consolati∣on in her grief, and you use such rigorous and cruel securities, as if she was capable of troubling your Empire, or of tearing your Con∣quests from you: and what opini∣on of the <HI>Tartars</HI> will this treat∣ment cause all the rest of the World to have, Seignior? they will take us to be <HI>Barbarians,</HI> and that not without reason; a little more mild∣ness would make them frame more advantageous Ideas of us, and the
<PB N="106" REF="58"/>
Princess <HI>Asteria</HI> would have the less to suffer, and the less to complain of. I do not mean <HI>Asteria</HI> shall play the Tyrant here, answered <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> nor do I think a Con∣querour who has destined her for his Son, ought not to give any ad∣vantageous Idea's of his clemency. You are convinced of her hatred for <HI>Themir,</HI> as likewise of what she is able to make him undertake to shun it; it is that consideration which makes me permit those pre∣cautions he has taken; if she was less violent, I would command you to go and see her, and indeavonr to perswade her, but you are the Son of <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> and that is suffi∣cient to keep her from hearkening to you. The Prince would fain have returned his Father an answer, and possibly would have accquain∣ted him▪ with the reason of his be∣ing so sensible of <HI>Asteria</HI>'s captivity, but the Emperor did not give him time to do it, but went out about
<PB N="107" REF="58"/>
some important affair. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> clearly perceived that he could not change the faoe of things, and therefore retired▪with his mind full of a thousand bloody imaginati∣ons.</P>
<P>In those measures the Artificious <HI>Odmar</HI> had caused <HI>Themir</HI> to take, there was not a word mentioned of <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> for fear it might be thought it was a result of his hatred, and of their first fallings out: and <HI>Odmar,</HI> who was continually im∣proving himself in the favour of the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> that so he might prevent appearances, would not at all be seen in the matter, but con∣tented himself with secretly▪ ma∣king the dangerous poison to work of which his breast was so full: He sought out whatsoever might dis∣cover to him the intrigue between <HI>Asteria,</HI> and Prince <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> and the effect did so abundantly recom∣pence his cares, that by seducing two of the domestiques, he came
<PB N="108" REF="59"/>
to understand that they had their first acquaintance at <HI>Constantinople,</HI> and that <HI>Adanaxus</HI> had not run through so many remote places as they had follow'd him to, but only to find her out. <HI>Odmar</HI> overjoy'd at this new assurance, confirmed <HI>Themir</HI> that his brother was now his Rival, and redoubled a rage in him, the effects of which were preven∣ted by those very reasons before mentioned.</P>
<P>In this manner two Months were spent, <HI>Themir</HI> daily proved <HI>Asteri∣a</HI>'s persecutor which made her lead a life suitable to the grief she had up∣on her, <HI>Adanaxus</HI> was perpetually languishing for her, and the Empe∣ror suffered all things to run which way was most agreeable to the Son whom he little better then ado∣red.</P>
<P>One night, when <HI>Adanaxus</HI> could take no repose, he went out of his own apartment into a great long Terrace, full the length of <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI>'s
<PB N="109" REF="59"/>
palace; the Princess's chamber joyned to it, and it was to be neer it at least that he chose that place to pass away his hours of inquietude: The Moon shone very bright, and the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> had no sooner leaned himself against one of the Ballisters that incom∣passed the Terrace, but turning his head at the noise of some sighs he heard emitted near him, he per∣ceived a Lady whom he immediate∣ly knew to be the Princess: her guards, less severe then their Ma∣ster, permitted her that liberty, which she only made use of in the night, and she had so little a de∣sire of discovering her self to him, that she did whatever she could to prevent his seeing of her: Not that she did not know <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> but to prevent her errour, she was going to deprive him of her com∣pany. But the Prince did not give her time to do it; he came, and threw himself at her feet, and
<PB N="110" REF="60"/>
kept her by an amorous violence; notwithstanding all her▪ indea∣vours to get away from him. 'Tis true her heart did not absolutely give way to those resentments; but a motion more powerful then despite, pleading in <HI>Adanaxus</HI>'s fa∣vour, did somewhat qualify an an∣ger that could not withstand the imperious force of Love, and made that innocent joy prevail of seeing a person dearly beloved af∣ter so long and tedious an absence; the Prince was offering several times to speak, without being able to find expressions: this silence was looked upon by <HI>Asteria</HI> as a Remorse, though she found her self disposed to pardon him if he was truly penitent, yet she had no mind to make a present discovery of her weakness to him; what transports do bring you again to <HI>Asteria</HI>'s feet, said she to him, is it in favour of <HI>Themir</HI> that you come with this submission, and
<PB N="111" REF="60"/>
do you address your self to me, as to the unfortunate <HI>Bajazet,</HI> to desire my hand for the murtherer of my Brother? This reproach gave the Prince of <HI>Tanais</HI> some new hopes, and as jealousie is not a work of in∣difference, he thought if that was the real cause of <HI>Asteria's</HI> anger, he ought not to believe it invincible. I do not lye at your feet as <HI>Themir's</HI> protector, Madam, replied he, it is my Love, which absence and time has not the power to diminish, that has brought me hither again: And if I have demanded the daughter of the <HI>Turkish</HI> Emperour for the Son of <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> it was through my igno∣rance that his <HI>Asteria</HI> was my adora∣ble <HI>Neris.</HI> Did not you know it, in∣terrupted the Princess, have you been the only person in <HI>Paleologus's</HI> Court, who has been ignorant of it? my return to <HI>Bursia</HI> madé a sufficient noise to be publickly known; and I am assured there is not one that dwels at <HI>Constantinople,</HI> who has not
<PB N="112" REF="61"/>
heard that <HI>Neris</HI> was <HI>Bajazet's</HI> daugh∣ter. Ah! Madam, replied the Prince, do you think your loss permitted me to wait patiently at <HI>Constantinople,</HI> for the effects wherewith it must needs be attended, and do you be∣lieve, <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> who had endea∣voured to make you understand how absolutely he was at your devotion, could after your departure with a∣ny quietness live in a City where on∣ly your fair eyes had the power to keep him? Ah <HI>Neris,</HI> how injurious is this suspicion, and how ill a cha∣racter have you framed of my Love, if you have been capable of any? being overwhelmed with grief for your absence, I could not find any <HI>Asylum</HI> for my despair, but was for∣ced to bear it with that ardor, which is inseparable from the most passio∣nate adorers over unknown Seas, and through the desarts of <HI>Africa,</HI> and without ever being frightened at a thousand deaths which were daily present to my eyes, I still con∣tinued
<PB N="113" REF="61"/>
my wandring, and guided only by my grief, even to that mo∣ment in which my destiny proved so happy as to bring me to you again; and yet you have accused me for having unworthily heard news of you in <HI>Paleologus</HI> his Palace, and possibly upon that reflection have hated me. What, interrupted <HI>Aste∣ria</HI> once more, is it possible that you should not have had any know∣ledge of the truth of my conditi∣on? No, Madam, pursued <HI>Ada∣naxus,</HI> I have heard nothing but what has preserved me in my errors; as soon as ever you disappeared, a violent, as well as hasty seizure re∣duced my life almost to its last peri∣od; and I was yet languishing un∣der that distemper, when I embar∣ked to find you out through all the places of the World. Remember, cruel <HI>Asteria,</HI> the confidence you made me, and judge whether I ought to look for you in <HI>Bursa,</HI> whom I thought in <HI>Egypt,</HI> in <HI>Mauritania,</HI>
<PB N="114" REF="62"/>
in <HI>Ethiopia,</HI> or in any other part of <HI>Africk,</HI> could I inform my self of <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s daughter, when I was running after an <HI>African</HI> Lady, and could I, to say no more, be in that remission you suspected me of, since I gave you what reserve all the movements of my life, and all the affections of a heart, which you have wrong'd by your mistrustful∣ness?</P>
<P>The Princess hearkened to <HI>Ada∣naxus</HI> his Justification with all that content and satisfaction which the certainty of a happiness that one desires and hopes for could produce. I confess, said she to him, when he had done speaking, my suspicions have been unjust; but, Seignior, consider whither I could do less, ha∣ving such probabilities of the truth of your desertion, I was perswaded you must needs know me, and at a time wherein as much a Son of <HI>Tam∣berlain,</HI> and Brother of <HI>Themir</HI> as you were, I looked upon you still
<PB N="115" REF="62"/>
no otherwise then as a Prince that was very dear to me, then as a Man in whom the blood of our Tyrants did strike no horrour in me; you came back to <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> you did to speak the truth, do a great ser∣vice for <HI>Bajazet,</HI> but you refused to see me; and went to demand me of my Father for one that was a <HI>Barbarian,</HI> whom I have a thousand reasons to detest; was not all this enough to allarm my tenderness, can you find any thing in my resent∣ment to complain of, if you consi∣der the cause of it, had not an in∣difference after such an occasion been more injurious for you, then the anger which I have not been a∣ble to conceal? Yes, Madam, an∣swered the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> you have too many reasons to look up∣on me as guilty, and I have a thou∣sand more to be eternally sensible of your favour and goodness: But my Princess, ought I not to fear that those great Events which have a∣stonished
<PB N="116" REF="63"/>
all the earth, those tean and sufferings which mine have pro∣cured to you, the outrages you have received from them, and the persecution you are still exposed to besides this birth which I owe to <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> should change my de∣stiny, and keep me from finding in <HI>Asteria</HI> the Adorable <HI>Neris?</HI> Seig∣nior, pursued she, <HI>Asteria</HI> will alwayes have the same esteem for you as the Slave of <HI>Paleologus▪</HI> had, and she is already sufficiently in∣debted to you not any longer to conceal from you, that you have had as great a share in her tears, as the effects of that fortune which has authoriz'd the shedding of them, as the deaths, the Prisons, and the ruin of a glorious Empire have sometimes given to other remem∣brances; and I confess, that even in this moment I am now speaking to you, all my sorrow is removed by the joy of my finding you ac∣cording to my desires. I should be
<PB N="117" REF="63"/>
ungrateful, cryed the Prince▪ if I would not sacrifice my whole life to estify my acknowledgements of your favours, and indeed what is there I ought not do to render my self worthy of the glorious esteem of my Princess! I am convinced you deserve more, pursued <HI>Asteria,</HI> and the kindness I have for you is no less redevable to your merit then your services; but, Seignior, how different is our destiny at <HI>Samarcan∣da</HI> from what it was at <HI>Constantino∣ple,</HI> every thing went opposite to the desires of <HI>Andronicus,</HI> and here all things contribute to those of <HI>Themir;</HI> the Emperour bears him out in hiscruelty; the People ap∣plaud his crimes; and I have no∣thing but my hatred to stand by me. You make nothing then of my Love, pursu'ed the Prince, do you think that shall be idle whilst <HI>The∣mir</HI> is so active? Pray, Madam, judg more kindly of it, it cannot be either weak or fearful, since it is
<PB N="118" REF="64"/>
inspired by you and the zeal of it will not suffer any thing to be diffi∣cult, to give you a discovery of its ardour, yes, Madam, whilst I in∣joy my life, I will be an invincible obstacle to the vows and protestati∣ons of <HI>Themir;</HI> I know very well there's no way in the World which he will not attempt to take it from me; but if the <HI>Tartars</HI> fear him, without vanity I may say they love me; the Emperour may in little time be less blind, and more reaso∣nable, and with some help possibly I may e're long present to my Prin∣cess a more happy condition, then that I am as yet constrained to see her languish in. This hope has no prospect of likelyhood in it, repli∣ed <HI>Asteria,</HI> and how favourable soe∣ver <HI>Tamberlain</HI> may be to you when those changes shall come upon him, as you fancy; yet he will never be favourable enough to give the pre∣ference of <HI>Themir:</HI> and then what designs will not your Brother con∣trive
<PB N="119" REF="64"/>
against your life? He is cruel, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mbitious, violent, and what is more, <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> he is jealous, he knows that we have formerly been acquainted, though by what means, it has yet been impossible for me to learn. But I will assure you since my Father's death he hath given me such Intimations of it, as I've but too plainly understood. Fear no∣thing from it, Madam, answered the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> I am no lon∣ger that weak and diffident <HI>Adanax∣us,</HI> whom thedominering carriage of an elder Brother did formerly send away from <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> I am now a passionate Lover, that will defend what he adores against all the at∣tacks of an insulting and audacious Rival, I will firmly maintain by my courage the glorious ambition of deserving you; and when it shall be imploy'd for that honour there is not any danger that can shock the resolution of <HI>Adanaxus.</HI></P>
<P>The Prince would have held the
<PB N="120" REF="65"/>
conversation longer, but that <HI>Aste∣ria,</HI> who was fearful of being surpri∣sed intreated him to retire, but not without a mutual promise of loving one another, in spight of all the op∣positions that might combat with their passion. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> spent the rest of the night in a joy he had ne∣ver before resented: Nothing more could be desired from <HI>Asteria,</HI> and if <HI>Themir</HI> did prove his persecution, the trouble was not weighty e∣nough to ballance the pleasure he had in thinking how tender he was in the affections of his Princess: but whilst he was thus diverting himself with the pleasantnessof his thoughts, his destiny was cruelly preparing for him new traverses.</P>
<P><HI>Themir</HI> now no longer doubt∣ed <HI>Adanaxus</HI> being his Rival, both what <HI>Odmar</HI> had drawn from some of his own Servants, and the other Circumstances in <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s Prison, made it clear to him; but still as <HI>Od∣mar</HI> was never without his spyes,
<PB N="121" REF="65"/>
for he employed I know not how many creatures for that purpose, he presently heard of the interview in in the Terrace, and the two lovers who thought they had had no other witnesses of their conversation than the Night and their love, were both seen and heard. <HI>Themir</HI> was even ready to burst with rage at it, <HI>Od∣mar</HI> likewise was put into a strange fury, and after a long times consi∣deration about what was most con∣venient to be done, the advice was that <HI>Adanaxus</HI> should be permitted to make an attempt that might be more convincing, that so they may demand reason of the Emperour: But <HI>Odmar,</HI> pursued <HI>Themir,</HI> to what end should we give him far∣ther time, for him to do me more outrages, are not the affronts he has done me already great enough? No Seignior, added <HI>Odmar,</HI> all that you can do at present, will neither re∣establish your repose nor the safety of your love: But urge the Empe∣rour
<PB N="122" REF="66"/>
to put <HI>Asteria</HI> into your posses∣sion, since you are so desirous to be united to her. Ah, but what shall we do with <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> interrupted the cruel <HI>Themir?</HI> What Seignior, answered <HI>Odmar,</HI> what other Prin∣ces do that are enraged with those things which prove their trouble, leave to me the concern of his de∣stiny, it shall be such as shall be wor∣thy of his boldness. Well then, pur∣sued <HI>Themir,</HI> il'e rest upon your ad∣vice, and demand of the Emperour the last sureties of his love.</P>
<P>At these words <HI>Themir</HI> went to find out <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> but as he was coming into the Terrace where the Prince of <HI>Tanais</HI> had entertained <HI>A∣steria,</HI> he perceived him at the other end of it, the sight of <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> and the place where he thought he had so lately met with a very sensible outrage inflamed his fury; he strait forgot <HI>Odmar's</HI> advice, and fancying his Brother was only walking there to see the Princess, he made up to
<PB N="123" REF="66"/>
him with a precipitation that argued his impatience: The young Prince very prudently shunned him, per∣ceiving his rage: But <HI>Themïr</HI> obser∣ving it; Stay, said he to him, and give me an account of the reasons that make you look after my Ca∣ptive, and of those secret plots you have laid to night against me. Speak with more respect of so great a Prin∣cess, as you think worthy to be made your Spouse, replyed <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> looking upon him very fiercely, and consider that you demand a satisfa∣ction from a man that owes you none, and who is not now in a hu∣mour to give you any. What, cry∣ed <HI>Themir,</HI> do you think to brave me after you have offended me, or do you imagine that my resentment will spare you? I have suffered so much from your pride, pursued <HI>A∣danaxus,</HI> as I am resolved to bear with it no longer: who has given you the priviledge of commanding
<PB N="124" REF="67"/>
a person over whom you have no o∣ther advantage than what the name of Elder Brother affords you, that you think to make your self his Ma∣ster or Emperour? I ought not to give you an account any otherways than in sacrificing you to my ven∣geance, interrupted <HI>Themir,</HI> putting his hand upon his sword, and I owe my self that sacrifice upon too many reasons: A very weighty blow was the consequence of <HI>Themir</HI>'s words, which hit upon <HI>Adanaxus's</HI> shoulder, who avoiding the second, put himself into a posture of defence and would have done it in such a manner as would have been fatal to <HI>Themir,</HI> if <HI>Axalla</HI> with some other <HI>Tartars</HI> of quality, brought thither by the noise they made, had not come and flung themselves between them. <HI>Themir</HI> was so base as to strike the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> in the arms of those that held him, but seeing it was impossible for him to satisfie his revenge; Your indiscreet zeal deprives my resent∣ments
<PB N="125" REF="67"/>
of a victim I am going now to demand of the Emperour, said he to those that kept him off from the Prince. Away he went as soon as he had spoke these words, and <HI>Ada∣naxus</HI> continuing the discourse, You will not, pnrsued he, let him come before the Emperour, without gi∣ving me the liberty of going to de∣fend my self? We will follow you thither if you please, Seignior, re∣plied <HI>Axalla:</HI> Let us go then, con∣tinued the Prince, who came to <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI> almost as soon as <HI>Themir.</HI> Im∣mediately the Emperour cast his eyes upon the blood that ran from the wounds of the young Prince, and he was not so little in his affections, as to behold it without a trouble: what blood is that which runs down your cloaths, <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> said he to him, It is mine, answered the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> very modestly: From whom comes this, pursued the Em∣perour, with looks that sufficiently denoted the passion he was in? Is
<PB N="126" REF="68"/>
there any in <HI>Samareanda</HI> that dares lift up his hand against you? Yes, Seignior, interrupted the violent <HI>Themir,</HI> there are those that would give him death if you did not hin∣der them, and in it give him that punishment he deserves, in affront∣ing me with so much boldness as he has done: I have a thousand things to accuse him, he has done me secret offences, and when I would have had him given me an account why he did so, with scorn he answered me. As for my discourse, said <HI>Ada∣naxus,</HI> it has been a great deal more moderate than it ought, and as for my action, I believe I could defend a life; for which the Emperour still reserves some kindness.</P>
<P><HI>Tamberlain</HI> then knew with an excess of grief, that his Sons found it difficult to vanquish that violent an∣tipathy which had disunited them, since that six years absence had not wrought any change upon them. Though he did in his heart condemn
<PB N="127" REF="68"/>
<HI>Themir,</HI> and render justice to the discretion of <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> yet he had such a tender love for the former, as to sacrifice all his equity to him, and desiring to reconcile them, Heaven, said he to them, surely has not brought you together, to en∣gage you in new quarrels, which are so hateful to it: Shall I ne∣ver see you in that happy state of friendship, which would render your lives and my repose pleasant to me? shall it be in a continual uneasie∣ness by your divisions? <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> said he to the young Prince, do something to please me, testifie to <HI>Themir</HI> that you are sorry for the outrage you have done him: And, you pursued he, addressing himself to the other, receive the submission of your Brother as becomes you: No Seignior, interrupted <HI>Themir,</HI> just as <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> who had resolved to sacrifice his resentment to the com∣mands of the Emperour, was going to obey him; I will not pardon him,
<PB N="128" REF="69"/>
but let him know by the vengeance you owe me, that he is not to go unpunished who will dare to offend him that has the advantage of being your eldest Son. Whatever dispo∣sitions the Emperour of the <HI>Tartars</HI> had to favour <HI>Themir,</HI> yet this vio∣lent procedure was very displeasing to him: You may be sure I would punish <HI>Adanaxus</HI> if he were crimi∣nal, replied he, but I do not see he is so, for having defended a life which you assaulted, without con∣sidering that he is my Son as well as you, and if the priviledge of birth has given you some advantages, that ought not to make any difference between you in my breast, do not you give me the disquiet of seeing you rebellious to my will: Submit your self to it Prince, since I com∣mand it you. I must acknowledge my trouble, Seignior, in that I can∣not be so obedient as I ought, pursu∣ed <HI>Themir,</HI> but the crime of <HI>Ada∣naxus</HI> then will have very strange
<PB N="129" REF="69"/>
consequences: you ow to my re∣pose and possibly to my life what I now demand of you: and since you refuse it me I find that I am less hap∣py than I thought my self to be, and that my loss would not be very con∣siderable to you. He went out at those words, and <HI>Tamberlain</HI> who lo∣ved him more dearly than all the world, (though he learn'd the truth of what had passed from other faith∣ful persons and from <HI>Axalla,</HI> in whom he repos'd his greatest confidence▪) commanded <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to do what he could to get the friendship of his Brother. If <HI>Asteria</HI> be grateful, ad∣ded he, you have a sure way to ap∣pease the resentment of the cruel <HI>Themir, Bajazet</HI> is no longer in a condition to impose any laws upon her, intercede for your Brother, and do your endeavours to overcome an unjust a version: She ought to esteem you and credit you, after what you have done for her; and if you can in∣cline her to be favourable to <HI>Themir▪</HI>
<PB N="130" REF="70"/>
you will engage him to your friend∣ship and to clemency, and you will procure me a repose, which it is im∣possible for me to injoy, so long as you are disunited.</P>
<P>The Prince of <HI>Tanais</HI> found in himself no disposition to give him that obedience he desired: There were within him such obstacles a∣gainst it as were not to be vanquish∣ed, and perceiving the Emperour fix'd upon the happiness of <HI>Themir,</HI> he went away from him, resolving rather to perish, than to see <HI>Neris</HI> in the power of a Rival, and of such a one whom she mortally hated.</P>
<P>But whilst by the diligence and care of <HI>Axalla,</HI> who waited on him, the Chirurgeons applied their reme∣dies to his wounds, <HI>Themir</HI> was on∣ly breathing out revenge: how he might destroy <HI>Adanaxus</HI> was the on∣ly thing he had been employed a∣bout since he had left the Emperour, and he was no less studious how he might sacrifice his brother to his im∣placable
<PB N="131" REF="70"/>
hatred, than to possess him∣self of <HI>Asteria</HI> in spight of all right or reason. <HI>Tamberlain</HI> had put a kind of equality betwixt them, which made him almost mad, and in the fury he was then in, not <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI> himself was secure from the horror of his designs, he forgot that his Father had ever had any blame∣able weaknesses for any besides him∣self, and whatsoever he had done like an unjust man or like one enra∣ged, was a pure effect of his blind passion, the Prince of <HI>Tanaîs</HI> had of∣fended him and went unpunished, he could not digest the outrage, and it was in the Arms of his dear <HI>Od∣mar,</HI> that he went to seek out his cruel consolations. I am betrayed, <HI>Odmar,</HI> said he to him▪ <HI>Adanaxus</HI> triumphs over the weakness of the Emperour, and he is ceased to be what heretofore he was. I thought it was sufficient to make my com∣plaints, to have my revenge granted, and that <HI>Tamberlain</HI> would have a∣bandoned
<PB N="132" REF="71"/>
that Rival to the safety of my repose. But I am the Victim on the account of love, and if I give him time to gain upon that Spirit which is already wavering betwixt us, I may also be the victim on that of nature. But <HI>Odmar,</HI> he must pe∣rish, it must be all his blood that must satisfie my despair, and assure my pretensions. Well, Seignior, he shall perish, interrupted <HI>Odmar,</HI> with that fury that ordinarily follows the resolution of great crimes, and we will sacrifice to your repose a victim that is so much your due: Let us have an ungrateful captive, and if it be necessary let us carry your re∣venge even to <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> do you dissemble and leave to me the care of managing the rest. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> must needs fall under the designs that I have laid, and that love which so much crosses yours, must be the occasion of his ruine. I will cause him to be suspected by the Emperour for making an attempt upon his
<PB N="133" REF="71"/>
Throne and upon his Life, and in∣velop him in the horrors of a crime of which I shall not find it difficult to contrive sufficient probabilities. <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI> is jealous of his glory, and of the Soveraign Authority. <HI>Ada∣naxus</HI> shall dye hated by his father, his Ruine shall appear legitimate, you shall enjoy the tranquillity that that can procure you▪ and if the Em∣perour by an unheard of inconstan∣cy, protects him and abandons you, you shall then break out, the revolt will be permitted you, and it may be something more. But Prince, pur∣sued <HI>Odmar,</HI> perceiving <HI>Themir</HI> to grow pale, you change colour what makes you to despair, does nature still seem to work in you? Ah! think that <HI>Adanaxus</HI> is beloved by the un∣grateful <HI>Asteria,</HI> and that he may yet usurp the power and influence you have got over the Emperour's mind, to stir you up to a revenge that is legitimate.</P>
<P>These fatal counsels which flatter∣ed
<PB N="134" REF="72"/>
<HI>Themir</HI>'s fury, began to work a calm upon his spirit, he resolved to feign obedience to the commands of <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> whilst <HI>Odmar</HI> was laying his designs, and the Emperour at last taking that dissimulation for a sincere return, forgat the disquiets that their enmity had raised in him.</P>
<P>But whilst <HI>Themir,</HI> whose jealousie still kept up his cruel humour, hid his bloody intentions under indiffe∣rent appearances, the Princess <HI>Aste∣ria</HI> had some secret fore-notices of it. She was not ignorant of what the unmerciful Prince was capable, and when <HI>Odmar</HI> was labouring the performance of his horrible designs, she trembled for the Prince whom they threatned. At first the joy of finding <HI>Adanaxus</HI> faithful again was resented without having any thing to trouble it, but representing to her self to what perils his love exposed him; Alas! said she, if the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> came back to <HI>Samarcanda,</HI>
<PB N="135" REF="72"/>
but to serve as a Victime to the cru∣elties of <HI>Themir,</HI> wherefore has he justifyed himself? I was not any whit concerned in his life, so long as I doubted his heart; but he is innocent, and now my tenderness makes me sensible of all that inte∣resses him, Ah! <HI>Themir,</HI> spare his blood, if you have any considera∣tion for my life, or at least com∣pleat all thy crimes by the death of <HI>Asteria.</HI></P>
<P>The Princess made not these com∣plaints upon light and trivial con∣jectures, <HI>Themir</HI> was not reserv'd enough punctually to observe the si∣lence that <HI>Odmar</HI> imposed upon him; and being transported by his choler, when he was with the Princess, he gave her by his threatning very great suspicions of some bloody en∣terprise.</P>
<P>Time made his intentions break forth, <HI>Odmar</HI> gave out such orders aswere very faithfully executed, and they Iaboured night and day to
<PB N="136" REF="73"/>
make the Prince suspected by the Emperour. The weakness he had for <HI>Themir,</HI> was not the only one of which he was▪capable; whatsoever concerned his authority, was very afflicting to him, and he was jealous of it after an extraordinary manner. <HI>Odmar</HI> had found some persons▪ whom the hopes of raising their for∣tunes had made his creatures▪ and caused several hints to be given to <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> which all agreed in the main, yet they came from dif∣ferent persons. His quality of be∣ing Governour of <HI>Themir</HI> and those places of eminence he was in, made him greatly honoured among the <HI>Tartars,</HI> and having spent his whole life in Cabals, and by a tedious con∣sultation thought upon all things that made to his advantage, and was pleasing to him, it was not dif∣ficult for him to hit upon such trea∣sons as he had contrived against him, and to gain persons of the same constitutionsand temper as he was<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at
<PB N="137" REF="73"/>
last by his wicked and malicious or∣ders, the first thing that shocked <HI>Tamberlain</HI>'s spirit, and that submit∣ted reason and truth to the weak∣ness of fear, was a person's telling him that <HI>Adanaxus</HI> had held very blamable correspondencies with <HI>Bajazet:</HI> Which was presently back∣ed with anothers acquainting him, that being most passionately in love with his Daughter, he had returned to <HI>Samarcanda</HI> only to quit him from his fetters; that he had seve∣ral times made an attempt upon the fidelity of the <HI>Oltoman</HI> Prince's Guards to procure his escape; that he sided with his Sons, in the de∣sign of coming to seek their re∣venge of him; that to that pur∣pose he held secret Intelligences with the <HI>Tartars,</HI> and that an In∣testine War joyned to the former fu∣ry of the <HI>Turks</HI> rallied by <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s Sons, might produce very great changes in his Empire. To these false conjectures were added the
<PB N="138" REF="74"/>
reasons of <HI>Adanaxus</HI>'s extraordina∣ry Rhetorick and earnestness to save <HI>Bajazet</HI> from his deserved pu∣nishment, and of his care and pains to render the irksomeness of his pri∣son as pleasant to him as he could: besides they refreshed the Empe∣rours memory with the excess of grief the Prince had discovered at <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s death; his private confe∣rence in the night on the terrace with <HI>Asteria,</HI> the difference that had been between him and <HI>Themir,</HI> and in a word all things that might put an evil interpretation upon the acti∣ons of the innocent Prince of <HI>Ta∣naïs. Tamberlain,</HI> who upon the like occasion would have lost all af∣fections for <HI>Themir,</HI> presently empty∣ed his breast of all for <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> and not being capable of examining any thing, he ordered that <HI>Odmar</HI> should be found out, to whom he told all that this treacherous base man knew a great deal better then himself; and after a great many
<PB N="139" REF="74"/>
threats, the cruel <HI>Tartar</HI> vehement∣ly uttered against the young Prince, he commanded him to go and secure <HI>Adanaxus</HI>'s person, and to carry him to the Tower of <HI>Samarcanda.</HI> Pardon me, Seignior, answered the d'issembling <HI>Odmar,</HI> if I beg of you not to lay this command upon me, how criminal soever the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> is, he is the Emperours Son, and the Brother of an illustrious Prince, whom I have had the ho∣nour to bring up; and I don't find my self powerful enough to go and be the pronouncer of his mis∣fortune. I have a horror for his wicked designs, as I have pitty for his Youth. You are his Father, Seignior, use some indeavours upon that occasion and try your utmost efforts to moderate your resent∣ments, the perfidious wretch spoke after this manner, being very well perswaded that <HI>Tamberlain</HI> was too deeply prepossessed with his fear to hearken to him. What <HI>Odmar,</HI> said
<PB N="140" REF="75"/>
he to him, do you advise me to a<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Indulgence which will it may be both cost me my Empire and my life? Your pitty is unjust, and I cannot too severely punish the am∣bitious <HI>Adanaxus:</HI> but yet I will not constrain you; but <HI>Calib,</HI> con∣tinued he, perceiving the Captain of his Guards coming in, shall be charged with the Commissions that you refuse. In short, he appointed <HI>Calib,</HI> who being much about the fame humour with <HI>Odmar,</HI> went presently to the apartment of the Prince of <HI>Tanais</HI> with a considera∣ble Number of the Emperour's Guards.</P>
<P>He was alone when <HI>Calib</HI> came in, for <HI>Axalla</HI> had just before left him; his love, his justification, and his quarrel with <HI>Themir</HI> was for several hours the Subjects of their discourse; and he was still reflecting upon what they had said, when he per∣ceived <HI>Calib</HI> coming in, what would you have, said the Prince to him▪ not
<PB N="141" REF="75"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ery well knowing him? Your <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>word, Seignior, replied <HI>Calib,</HI> which the Emperour commands you <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o put into my hands, and to go <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>long with me to the Tower of <HI>Sa∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arcanda:</HI> As I had never been wont to receive the honour of any visits from <HI>Calib,</HI> answer'd <HI>Adanax∣is,</HI> I thought at first he only came thither to make me some extraordi∣nary complements, shall I not see the Emperour continued he, and will you tell me nothing of my crime? I have no further orders, Seignior, replied <HI>Calib,</HI> then to conduct you to the Tower: and for the satis∣faction you desire of me, I must con∣fess, I was never made a Confident of the secrets of my Master. You act discreetly, replied the Prince; here <HI>Calib,</HI> take the Sword that you de∣mand of me, the name of the Em∣perour shall make me at any time render my arms; let us go to the Tower you are to conduct me to; if I ever do come out of it, I will
<PB N="142" REF="76"/>
not forget that you were my guide thither, and besides will be mind∣ful of your discretion. <HI>Calib</HI> re∣turned him no answer, because that <HI>Adanaxus</HI> just then went out. They were to cross the great terrace to go into one of the Courts of the Palace where the Charriot waited that was to carry him. <HI>Asteria</HI> was leaning at her Chamber-Window, and thinking on the Prince of <HI>Tana∣ïs,</HI> just as he saw him in the midst of <HI>Tamberlain</HI>'s Guards without his Sword, though she had been fan∣cying him a thousand times in that posture before then, yet was not her surprise less great; she gave a horrible shriek, which obliged the Prince to cast his eyes that way, and he had no sooner done so, but he perceived her sinking into the arms of <HI>Xaira.</HI> The news of his misfortune would have been a great deal less dreadful to her then this accident proved: He used all his Oratory to perswade <HI>Calib</HI> to per∣mit
<PB N="143" REF="76"/>
him the favour of going to his Princess; but whether through fear <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r crueltie, the <HI>Tartar</HI> would not <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onsent to it: but he was obliged <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o go to the Tower without any more delay, where he was shut up. As soon as he was come thither, they <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ook care to redouble <HI>Asteria</HI>'s Guards; and besides the affliction she was in, to know that her servant was become a Prisoner, she was de∣prived of the consolation of having daily intelligence from him, being afforded no other company but that of <HI>Themir</HI>'s of all the Servants she <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad at <HI>Samarcanda.</HI></P>
<P>The Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> his being carried to prison occasioned a very considerable noise in <HI>Tamberlain</HI>'s Court; he was generally beloved, and his destiny was in a high degree lamented, and amongst the most grave and sober sort of persons, there were but few of them who would not with all their Souls have done his vertue justice: But there was
<PB N="144" REF="77"/>
nothing to be done in his favour: the zeal of his friends was now un∣profitable to him, and against both the commands and the pleasure of the Emperor, the generous <HI>Axalla,</HI> as being the most perswaded of <HI>Ad∣anaxus</HI>'s innocence, became the most sensible of his misfortune: he saw no likelyhood of undeceiving a weak Father, so great a Lover of his fortune, and prevented by Im∣postors, who too well knew his humours and his fears, and had ma∣naged their business with a great deal of prudence and safety; but however he went to see the Empe∣ror and to speak to him concerning the Prince, but he was presently commanded silence; and judging that he might indanger himself to be suspected, and consequently to lose his liberty, if he spake any more to a Man, who by his trans∣port had made himself uncapable of understanding reason, he retired with an extream regret but as he did
<PB N="145" REF="77"/>
not so much fear his disgrace any otherwise then as it might give him an absolute defeat from being any longer in a condition of serving <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> he made it his business to gain over to him the gallantest persons of the Court, that he like∣wise might have a party to speak in the favour of <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> and la∣bour his justification, and try if they could not in time melt down <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI>'s heart into some tenderness for his captiv'd Son.</P>
<P>In the mean time <HI>Themir</HI> was tri∣umphing; <HI>Odmar</HI>'s projects met with such successful beginnings, that he could not but expect the consequen∣ses of them would be resembling: The Emperour would hearken to nothing but the counsels of his Rage and Error, and the ruine of the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> appearing now past all prevention unto the contri∣vers of it, his barbarous Brother was before hand pleasing himself with the agreeable thoughts of it;
<PB N="146" REF="78"/>
and his hopes buoying him up, with such a delightful flattery, he went directly to <HI>Asteria,</HI> whom he found in a condition conformable to her grief. But in spight of all her tears and heaviness, (more charming then ever yet she had appeared to the sight of <HI>Themir)</HI> her eyes, which an extraordinary paleness rendered languishing, were not∣withstanding full of a Majestick cho∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er; she was then sitting upon a Couch, and without ever rising off it, she thus addrest her discourse: Are you come, said she to him, to make your boast that you have re∣duced <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to a Prison, as a new instance of you crueltie? Is he only guilty because he has with pitty resented the unhappinesses of <HI>Bajazet?</HI> And as this compassion obliges me to have a resembling in∣terest for him, should you have proved false to you furious trans∣ports upon my consideration, if you had spared him? I ought to have
<PB N="147" REF="78"/>
done that which you reproach me for, answered the unjust Prince of <HI>Tartary,</HI> and this Rival sufficiently deserves my hatred, since I ow your aversion to him. You only ow it to your crimes, interrupted <HI>Asteria,</HI> to those barbarous sentiments which have made you find such sweetness in the death of <HI>Ortobulus,</HI> in the ruine of my Mother, in the loss of <HI>Bajazet,</HI> in my captivity, and in a word in all your unworthy threat∣nings of me. Thus Madam, repli∣ed <HI>Themir,</HI> you impute all the events of fate to me, and I am culpable still, because <HI>Adanaxus</HI> conspires against the Emperour. I shall not go about to justify my self any lon∣ger to you; but fear least you do not quite exhaust my patience; such a haughty pride does not alwayes meet with submissive Souls, and since I have suffered so much from your ingratitude, I may very law∣fully make use of my rights and pri∣viledges. I understand your mena∣ces,
<PB N="148" REF="79"/>
pursued the Princess; but since I have nothing more to fear for <HI>Bajazet,</HI> they have not the pow∣er to frighten me: consider▪ Hea∣ven sometimes puts bounds to its an∣ger, it is not alwayes deaf to the prayers of the unfortunate and mise∣rable, but does reserve still its thun∣ders for the punishments of Tyrants. You ought then to make a Tryal, answered <HI>Themir,</HI> how far one may go without its succour and to begin to make a more profitable use of my Authority. I confess I am tyred out with those tedious and servi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e respects I have paid you, and in a short time, you shall either consent to my desires, or else not be in a condition to bring any obstacle to them. He went away as he ended those words; and though they had struck a terror into the Princesses soul, yet it was no small relief to her to see the <HI>Barbarian</HI> go out of her room, and leave her the liberty of finding consolations in her constancy
<PB N="149" REF="79"/>
against all the afflictions she was o'rewhelm'd with.</P>
<P><HI>Axalla,</HI> and his friends did in∣cessantly labour to put a stop to the most pressing of them, they exami∣ned with all the care they could, when were those moments that the Emperour found in his breast any return of tenderness for his young Son, at last they began to find him in a humour to hearken to what might be said in his favour, then it was they conjured him to make a solid reflection upon <HI>Adanaxus</HI>'s car∣riage, and what severity soever he resolv'd to use against him, he could not find any of his actions blame∣able, and deserving condemnation: his moderation in the unworthy treatments of <HI>Themir,</HI> his submissi∣on to the commands of the Empe∣rour, and particularly to the last he had received from him, coming again into his memory, he began to fear he had acted with too much precipi∣tation; and reproaching himself for
<PB N="123" REF="80"/>
it as a default of paternal love, he perceived himself in one of those inquietudes which ordinarily do usher in a deep repentance. He was as soon come to himself as he had been provoked, being incapa∣ble of himself to be carried out to any great violences, but subject to a credulity which made him often take Chimera's for truths, and the wicked and poisonous counsels of flatterers for a sincere zeal. These kind of humours almost continually go from one extremity to the other, <HI>Tamberlain</HI> past from that so favou∣rably for the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> that he could not take any comfort in his being so much inraged against him. I have been too cruel said he in those reflections, to condemn <HI>Adanaxus</HI> upon discourses which I've not given him time to op∣pose and answer: Those accusers, may not they be deceived in what they charge him with, and is his justification impossible? Weak
<PB N="151" REF="80"/>
Prince, continued he, search into the procedures of your Son with more mildness and tranquillity; what, would you sacrifice him to your fears, and possibly to your er∣rors? Consider that a Prince ele∣vated upon the Throne of <HI>Asia</HI> ought to prevent accidents with a greater moderation; have you seen <HI>Adanaxus</HI> in the troops of <HI>Bajazet</HI> during that abscence which has de∣prived you of him? Has fame, that publishes all things, ever told you any thing of him that you have need to complain of? and in the extremity to which <HI>Bajazet</HI> was re∣duced when <HI>Adanaxus</HI> arrived at <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> can you find any pro∣bability that his return was design'd by the <HI>Ottoman</HI> Prince, or by his daughter? He saw him not but by thy orders, and did not obtain his life but by arguments very advanta∣geous to thy glory, and which it was impossible for thee not to yield to. Those very arguments which
<PB N="152" REF="81"/>
have convinced me, become now thy crimes, thou wouldst make him suffer punishment for having perswa∣ded thee to be generous. No <HI>Tam∣berlain,</HI> do not thou become the talk or rather the horrour of the world by such an action, but seek the inno∣cency of thy Son and not his ruine, and if he be deeply smitten with the charms of that beauty, so fatal to the repose of thy blood, content thy self in bringing despair to his affection by giving that <HI>Asteria</HI> to <HI>Themir.</HI></P>
<P>This change of the Emperour was soon observed, by the friends and persecutors of the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs: Odmar</HI> was quite enraged at it, and did not doubt but that the love and care of <HI>Axalla</HI> did much contribute to it, he would with all his soul have destroyed him with <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> but how ruinously ingenious his en∣vy and revenge were, it could do nothing against <HI>Axalla's</HI> glory, and he was obliged to confine his rage
<PB N="153" REF="81"/>
only in seeking out ways he thought might be most fit and proper to coun∣terplot him, in hindering the justi∣fication of <HI>Adanaxus.</HI></P>
<P>In the mean time <HI>Tamberlain</HI> came more and more to himself, and was considering among all those that were about him, who should be the man he had best pitch upon to be sent to examine the Prince of <HI>Tanais,</HI> and from his mouth to be informed when and how he got his acquaint∣ance with <HI>Bajazet</HI> and <HI>Asteria:</HI> af∣ter a great deal of balancing upon the election, he concluded that <HI>Tal∣mis</HI> should be the man, one who was of a considerable eminence a∣bout him, he was endowed with a great deal of wit and honesty, <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI> knew <HI>Adanaxus</HI> had a high esteem and service for him, and <HI>Tal∣mis</HI> appearing more fit than any o∣ther to take upon him such an office, and to discharge it with honour, re∣ceived the commands of the Empe∣rour, and performed them with as
<PB N="154" REF="82"/>
much justice as zeal. He went to the young Prince, and addressing himself with all that respect which was due to the Son of the Emperour, he humbly beseeched him not to take it ill, if he propounded some questions to him that he had in com∣mission from his Father. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> satisfied with his submission, frankly told him all he had before acquaint∣ed <HI>Axalla</HI> with, and afterwards his surprise, when at the death of <HI>Baja∣zet</HI> he knew his <HI>Asteria</HI> again for <HI>Neris: Talmis</HI> being informed of the truth, made a very faithful recital of all the circumstances to the Em∣perour, and fortified them with ar∣guments that were so powerful for the innocence of the Prince, that <HI>Tamberlain</HI> was more than half per∣swaded of them, but yet he thought it prudence to see whether the Prin∣cess and <HI>Adanaxus</HI> would be found in the same story. He went to her Apartment early the next morning, and after he had excused himself for
<PB N="155" REF="82"/>
the unseasonableness of the hour he had chosen; Madam, said he to her, I am not of right to flatter my self with the thoughts of obtaining any grace from you, yet I am come to demand one of you, upon which all my tranquillity does depend. The Princess thought that <HI>Tamberlain</HI> was come again to be sollicitous for <HI>Themir,</HI> and therefore looking on him very stedfastly, It is not likely in good earnest, replied she, you should effect a thing that the death of <HI>Bajazet</HI> has not been able to make me resolve upon. 'Tis not that now which brings me to you, pursued the Emperour, I only am come to demand of you how <HI>Adanaxus</HI> be∣gan his acquaintance with you▪ what correspondence <HI>Bajazet</HI> had with him, and what intelligences he may still have with your Brothers; and I swear to you, that were he convicted of a thousand designs ei∣ther upon my Empire or my life, <HI>A∣danaxus</HI> should find his pardon from
<PB N="156" REF="83"/>
your confession, and that I will sa∣crifice my most just resentments to your sincerity. Thought the Prin∣cess could not much believe <HI>Tamber∣lain</HI>'s discourse, yet because she had nothing to hazard in telling him the truth, she made him the very same relation as the Prince had done be∣fore to <HI>Talmis:</HI> but indeed if she did pass over her tender affections to him, it was easily discoverable, that she did it through modesty. It is sufficient Madam, said the Emperour to her when she had done speaking▪ I will keep my word with you, and set <HI>Adanaxus</HI>'s Prison wide open to you. You will do him justice, an∣swered <HI>Asteria,</HI> and his innocence is manifest enough to oblige you to restore him his liberty.</P>
<P>These stories agreeing together wrought a calm upon a great-part of <HI>Tamberlain</HI>'s troubles, the sincerity of the Princess he himself discovered▪ <HI>Talmis</HI> was no way suspected by him, and nothing now remained but
<PB N="157" REF="83"/>
only to confound the accusers of <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> the Emperour was just going to send for them when he saw <HI>Odmar</HI> coming up to him: The feign∣ed compassion he shewed for the un∣happiness of the Prince of <HI>Tanais,</HI> made <HI>Tamberlain</HI> believe he would receive abundance of joy at the ap∣pearances of his justification. <HI>Odmar,</HI> said he to him, the pity you have testified for my Son, and which I condemned in you was just: all things perswade me that he is not guilty, and you have appeared so sensible of his misfortune, that you cannot but receive as great a satisfa∣ction to learn the happy success of it. This was a thunderclap that made the perfidious <HI>Odmar</HI> think it would have struck him dead upon the spot, but as he was the best man in the world to manage a dissimulation, he concealed his trouble and confessed that he was overjoyed at this resolu∣tion. He asked the Emperour whence it proceeded, and by what means
<PB N="158" REF="84"/>
he came to be informed of the Prince's innocence. <HI>Tamberlain</HI> with all the obliging civility imaginable, gave him an exact account of it, and continuing to entertain him with the same confidence; It is necessary, ad∣ded he, that those who have been the cause of <HI>Adanaxus</HI>'s disgrace, should be examined before him, and that their punishment should re∣venge his glory, if he was not found guilty of any crime; make them to be sought out <HI>Odmar,</HI> they are known to you, and I my self will ex∣amine the source and progress of this calumny. Seignior, answered <HI>Odmar,</HI> so hasty a procedure will go near to exasperate them, therefore let us manage the business with more secrecy, and if you please to take my advice, do not discover your thoughts, one word is enough to allarm them, and their flight will defeat you of the revenge you may take, it will be hard for me to get them together, and bring them here
<PB N="159" REF="84"/>
upon other pretences, give me on∣ly time to bring this to pass, and in the mean while conserve against the Prince <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> all the appearan∣ces of your first anger. This pre∣caution seemed reasonable to the Emperour, he embraced <HI>Odmar,</HI> and entrusting him with the conduct of this affair, he put a stop to the dis∣covery he so much desired.</P>
<P>As soon as <HI>Odmar</HI> was gone from him, he gave his rage the full swinge, and after he had examined whatso∣ever might put things into disorder again, and make the accusations seem probable, he saw every way so many things to confound him, and so little security, that he thought he could not do better than to send away the informers. As they had done nothing without his orders, he immediately took this precauti∣on, and sent them from <HI>Samarcanda</HI> the same night, and having given them time enough to advance their flight, he went to find out the Em∣perour,
<PB N="160" REF="85"/>
with a grief and perplexity in his face so admirably counterfeit∣ed that it appeared natural. I saw sufficiently, Seignior, said he to him, that there was but one word necessary to render your intentions publick, and to counterplot your absolute satisfaction: I have been in vain looking out for those whom I was charg'd to bring before you: they are fled, so that none of them are to be found in <HI>Samarcanda.</HI> Well then, answered the Emperour, this flight does fully convince me of the innocence of <HI>Adanaxus.</HI> If he had been guilty, his enemies would have stayed without ever fearing any thing of the event of this busi∣ness: Yet <HI>Odmar,</HI> we had best send so many in pursuance after them, that we may from some of them hear what is become of those fugitives. Yes, Seignior, answered the faith∣less <HI>Tartar,</HI> that is but requisice, and that I will labour with all the care I can. In short, he sent out several
<PB N="161" REF="85"/>
persons, but he knew very well which way to send them so that they should never be the wiser: But yet all this could not be managed with∣out some noise: the friends of the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> had great resent∣ments of joy at it, and <HI>Axalla,</HI> who only was cautious of himself upon the consideration of <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> saw now that it was time to complete his happiness, and addressed himself to the Emperour to sollicite him for it: The Emperour presently yielded, and commanded him to go to the Tower, and bring the Prince from it: This was a very pleasing order to a person who had so tender a pas∣sion for him as <HI>Axalla</HI> had; he ac∣cepted of it with transport, and af∣ter he had continued with the Em∣perour a little while longer, to take away the reliques of his inquietude, he ran with the resembling fury of a Lover to his dear <HI>Adanaxus.</HI> Though the Prince could not expect any thing that might be fatal from
<PB N="162" REF="86"/>
<HI>Axalla,</HI> yet he had a thousand dis∣mal Idea's in his fancy when he saw him: Must I then dye, my dear <HI>Ax∣alla,</HI> said he to him embracing him, and are you come to be a companion of my misfortune? No Seignior, an∣swered <HI>Axalla,</HI> I come to restore you liberty, which only your virtue and the justice of the Emperour has gi∣ven you. He then acquainted him∣with the change of his condition, the weak effort his enemies had made against him, and the Prince uncer∣tain of the consequences which that might occasion, appeared unshaken, he went towards the Palace, in∣forming himself by the way of <HI>Aste∣ria,</HI> and he had the joy to know by the acclamations of the people, that they had been as sensible of his im∣prisonment, as they were of his li∣berty.</P>
<P>When he came up to the Empe∣rour he threw himself at his feer, which action made him blush through confusion, as it did also
<PB N="163" REF="86"/>
cause him to sigh through repen∣tance. <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> said he to him, after he had done embracing him, I have not done any thing against you which I am not resolved to re∣pair, and as I no longer doubt but that the crimes you have been accu∣sed of are only forged, so I would already have revenged you of those who were the inventers of them, if they were not got out of the reach of my anger: To be plain with you, I am sufficiently sensible of your in∣nocence, for it I have believed my tender affections to you, and you are also redevable for one part of your justification to the Princess <HI>A∣steria.</HI> You have the freedom to go and pay her your acknowledgments for it, and judge of the return of my friendship, by this first effect of my indulgence. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> blushed to hear his Princess named; and it was not difficult for <HI>Tamberlain</HI> to interpret the emotion; but after he had learn'd from the Prince's mouth,
<PB N="164" REF="87"/>
the same things that <HI>Talmis</HI> had re∣ported to him; You have a Rival in <HI>Themir,</HI> said he to him, whose pre∣tensions are strengthned upon my promises, and whom I cannot deny my protection against your flame, though I know that you have the ad∣vantage of a longer service, as well as of the gratitude of the Princess: But <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> is it not possible to conquer your self, and by a gene∣rous effort—Seignior, cryed the Prince, if I were unfaithful to <HI>Aste∣ria,</HI> I could become so to you: He that can prove a Traitor to his love will never have any great conside∣rations for nature, and I should ren∣der my self worthy of your Chains, if I were capable of doing the least effort to break those of the Prin∣cess.</P>
<P>As the young Prince ended these words, <HI>Themir</HI> entred; his paleness expressed the despair he was in, and the looks he darted upon <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> sufficiently testified that his Soul was
<PB N="165" REF="87"/>
full of a thousand bloody resoluti∣ons. <HI>Tamberlain</HI> seemed as if he did not mind them, and asked him if he came to share in his brother's joy to which he returned no answer, and the Emperour according to his usu∣al complaisance, not being willing to press him any farther, contented himself in giving to the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> the caresses that were due to him, and publickly protested that there were not any punishments which those who had unjustly accu∣sed him, ought not to expect.</P>
<P>As soon as <HI>Adanaxus</HI> had the free∣dom to retire, he took the benefit of that the Emperour had given him, to see <HI>Asteria,</HI> and the jealous looks of <HI>Themir</HI> were not powerful e∣nough to prevent him from it. It would be very hard to tell, which of the two were the most sensible of the pleasure they resented in seeing one another again: Silence and sighs are the first marks of those kind of joys, and there is more said in an a∣morous
<PB N="166" REF="88"/>
trouble and confusion, that in a set and orderly discourse. Oh▪ how eloquent were the eyes of <HI>A∣danaxus</HI> then, and how attentive were those of the Princess to hearken to them? As he entred he flung him∣self at her feet, and after he had been there a good while, without her having the least power to make him rise, at last, Madam, said he to her, the great mystery of my love is known to the Emperour, this know∣ledge has not hindered my liberty, and I am come to pay you my ac∣knowledgements for having procu∣red it me. What an honourable sa∣tisfaction is it to me to see my self prostrate at your feet, and not to ow it to any thing but your self. You ow me nothing for having done justice to a truth which was profitable to you▪ interrupted the Princess▪ and though I should not have this testimony to your services, my heart would have compelled me to render it you. Is it possible for
<PB N="167" REF="88"/>
me to forget, without the last ingra∣titude, that you have been prodigal of your blood for <HI>Neris,</HI> treated a wretched Unknown like a Princess, run through Seas and Land to seek me out, and have done so many ge∣nerous services for the unfortunate <HI>Bajazet?</HI> You set too high a value upon those that are so little deserv∣ing, replied <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> but as for me my Princess, what do I not ow you, to suffer at your feet the Son of <HI>Tam∣berlain</HI> and the Brother of <HI>Themir?</HI> I do not confound the vices of <HI>The∣mir</HI> with your vertues, replied <HI>A∣steria,</HI> nor your services with the outrages that have been done me; and if I do hate your Brother as one that is worthy of my aversion, I love you, Seignior, because you deserve to be beloved, and because <HI>Bajazet</HI> has not imposed upon me such laws as are contrary to the sentiments of my breast. You see now my fears were but too well grounded, and you ought not to doubt but that
<PB N="168" REF="89"/>
the misfortune you have escaped was a design of the Prince of <HI>Tartary,</HI> for the future take more precauti∣ons against him, let the Emperour know it was <HI>Themir</HI> that would have ruined you. Alas Madam, answer'd the Prince, the Empire that my Bro∣ther has over the mind of <HI>Tamberlain</HI> makes your commands be extreme∣ly difficult, none can accuse him without rendring himself at the same time suspected by the Emperour, and to testifie the least suspicion against him would be to prove my own de∣stroyer. And what will you do then pursued <HI>Asteria?</HI> Adore you, my Princess, interrupted <HI>Adanaxus</HI> with a melting fervency beyond expres∣sion, and this devotion shall be the glorious imployment of my life. Your fidelity is dear to me, replied she, but in this present occasion it is not sufficient for me, and if you love me you must think upon some way to conserve your self, and what would you do your self, Madam,
<PB N="169" REF="89"/>
added the Prince, I would replied <HI>Asteria,</HI> despise <HI>Themir</HI> unto my last breath, render by my resistance all his pretensions useless, and though I would not do it for my self, believe me I would do it for you. Ah Ma∣dam, cryed the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs:</HI> ought I to be afraid of any thing af∣ter this glorious assurance? Alas, Seignior, answered <HI>Asteria,</HI> this as∣surance as sincere as it is, can it do any thing against Irons, Prisons, Im∣postors, and to conclude, against all the other ways that <HI>Themir</HI> is able to make use of to destroy you? Can my affection render you immortal, and am I more certain of your life, because I love you? Give me the sa∣tisfaction to see you mistrust all things, and then I shall value what∣ever you do to put your self in a condition that may secure you from your enemies. Yes Madam, pursued <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> I will obey, I will be care∣ful of my life, I will foresee, if it be possible, the designs that may be
<PB N="170" REF="90"/>
hatched against me, and I will forget nothing that may make me capable of deserving the favours of my charming Princess.</P>
<P>At the end of these discourses, and some others much resembling them, <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> who since he found that his <HI>Neris</HI> was <HI>Asteria,</HI> had never met with an opportunity to demand of her those adventures of hers that he was ignorant of; burning with an earnest impatience of knowing them, conjured her to give him a Relation of them which she presently consent∣ed to, and thus began her discourse▪</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="story">
<PB N="171" REF="90"/>
<HEAD>The History of the Princess <HI>Asteria.</HI></HEAD>
<P>WHen <HI>Andronicus</HI> defeated the <HI>Turks</HI> who were to be my guide, I was going from <HI>Bursa</HI> to <HI>Sebastia</HI> to meet my Mother, who was to pass the Win∣ter with the Emperour; our Troops were on the side of <HI>Thrace, Bajazet</HI> had designs upon <HI>Constantinople,</HI> and it was not believed that in the Winter <HI>Paleologus</HI> his Sons, harde∣ned by the little opposition they found, would venture to go into the lesser <HI>Asia;</HI> but in their way they took us; I concealed my name, not knowing into what hands I was fallen; but having learnt it was in <HI>Andronicus's,</HI> and afterwards under∣stood his sentiments for me, I made
<PB N="172" REF="91"/>
it my particular business to keep it from being known, and through the natural aversion I had for him, and the fear of seeing <HI>Paleologus</HI> ap∣prove of his Son's Love and of be∣ing the victime of a peace between the two Empires; it fell out very luckily for me that I did so, the Emperour of <HI>Greece</HI> would not au∣thorize an alliance unknown, and in all probability unequal; which gave me a very sensible joy, because my hatred for <HI>Andronicus</HI> augmen∣ted as soon as ever I had a sight of you. I quickly perceived how my heart pleaded in your favour by the trouble and melancholiness I resen∣ted, when I beheld you render your submissions with too much assiduity to the Princess of <HI>Greece:</HI> and time, and your procedure having as∣sured me of your heart, I blush'd sometimes to think I was the daugh∣ter of <HI>Bajazet,</HI> and that when I with scorn refused the vows of <HI>An∣dronicus,</HI> I hearkened with pleasure
<PB N="173" REF="91"/>
to those of one unknown: but that confusion produced no effects which were not favourable to you. I told you nothing of my true birth, not so much out of any mi∣strustfulness, as out of a certain scruple I then had: I was very desi∣rous to know whether you had only a kindness for my person; but I did it out of policy, after you had told me yours. I was not ignorant of <HI>Tamberlain</HI>'s hatred to the <HI>Otto∣mans:</HI> and fearing lest your senti∣ments should resemble his, I made that a secret to you, the reserve of which I thought I sufficiently re∣compenced by my weakness for you. I began in the mean time not to be in a power to be silent to you, but had insallibly told you all, if <HI>An∣dronicus</HI> had but for some days sus∣pended the design he had been me∣ditating since the unhappy success of his enterprise at <HI>Constantinople;</HI> but he made me be carried away then when I thought least of it, and those
<PB N="174" REF="92"/>
fellows more hardly and resolute then those of the Emperour, imbar∣ked me in a Vessel, which in a short time brought us to a very strange and lovely House, which they were assured of. At first I accused the Emperour for this second carrying me away, but I was undeceived, when <HI>Andronicus</HI> reduced to his flight by the wicked success of those unfaithful enterprises of his against his Father, came to find me in the place where I had been conducted: I was fearful of all things from the violences of a desperate and furi∣ous Spirit; and therefore to inspire him with a greater respect then I thought he might have had to one unknown, I told him I was daugh∣ter to the Emperour of the <HI>Turks:</HI> This news appear'd to him to be much to his advantage, and he ima∣gined that in restoring me to <HI>Baja∣zet,</HI> he might not only obtain me from him, but he might with great∣er facility conquer his Father's Em∣pire,
<PB N="175" REF="92"/>
in promising to share it with me. He then accquainted me with his design, and desired me to con∣sider of it as an effect of the passion he had to please me. You may ea∣sily believe that the hopes of re∣turning to <HI>Bajazet</HI> made me resolve upon some complaisance: at last we arrived at <HI>Bursa,</HI> and we were received there with all the joy that could be inspired into the Emperor, and my Mother, by the return of a daughter whose loss they had be∣wailed: The <HI>Grecian</HI> Prince had very extraordinary honours passed upon him, but when he explained his Intentions to <HI>Bajazet</HI> and that he perceived him much averse to fa∣vour them, he fell to reproaches, and from thence to threats, which had but too bloody effects. He went in great fury from <HI>Bursa,</HI> and mar∣ched towards his Father's Army, which he found driven back by the valour of <HI>Ortobulus,</HI> who had the command of ours in the Emperor's
<PB N="176" REF="93"/>
absence, even within sight of <HI>Con∣stantinople.</HI> He made his peace by a thousand submissions, related his adventures, and seeing the <HI>Greeks</HI> every way weakned, he himself se∣creetly laboured the relieving of the <HI>Tartars. Tamberlain</HI> sollicited by <HI>Andronicus,</HI> and jealous of <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s glory whom he hated, got toge∣ther all the forces of <HI>Asia,</HI> and brought where ever he went both horror and desolation. At last this <HI>Tamberlain</HI> famous by our disgraces, and eminent by our misfortunes, without any pitty burnt our Cities, sacrificed our people, and reduced, by that fatal success that did attend him, a Prince who was seen ready to share almost the World, with the rest of the Princes, to that de∣plorable condition into which he is fallen.</P>
<P>Whilst these evils were happe∣ning, notwithstanding my grief I did not loose the remembrance of <HI>Adanaxus,</HI> nor forget the cares of
<PB N="177" REF="93"/>
informing my self of him. I was confirmed of your absence, and was perswaded that you must needs learn who I was, I did imagine you had not gone from <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> but only to escape fighting with my Fa∣ther, and this very thought gave me a great consolation: at last Seignior, <HI>Bursa</HI> was ravaged, af∣terwards <HI>Sebastia, Themir</HI> haled us from the Palace, and made us take this voy age to <HI>Asia,</HI> where we were seen to follow the Chariot of that cruel Conquerour; and which cost my Mother her life. Our captivity preceded that of <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s some few days, and I have often heard him say, that being over whelmed with a mortal grief, after <HI>Ortobulus</HI>'s misfortune whom <HI>Themir</HI> had massa∣cred before his eyes, and the loss of the last battle, having suffered his Horses to carry him up and down without any design or hope through unknown desarts. He met with a Shepherd, who was all alone by
<PB N="178" REF="94"/>
the side of a River pleasing himself with playing some rural airs upon his Oaten pipe, the Emperor look'd upon him a long time admiring at the sweetness of his condition, and then sighing: Oh! Too happy Shepherd, said he to him, how worthy is thy state of envy, to have nothing to spend but thy dayes, which bloody ambition never cros∣ses; <HI>Bajazet</HI>'s calamities will furnish you with matter for your Songs, and you may hereafter in your pit∣tiful Numbers say, unfortunate Prince thou shalt never more see thy delightful <HI>Sebastia,</HI> nor thy dear <HI>Ortobulus.</HI> This Shepherd with the sight and words of the Emperour, offered him his little cottage, but that retreat was not very long servi∣ceable to him. <HI>Themir</HI> by his in∣quisition for him quickly resembled his fate to that of ours. She ended this discourse with a thousand tears, which made <HI>Adanaxus</HI> repent that he had been the unhappy cause of
<PB N="179" REF="94"/>
them, and after he had imployed some time in drying them up, he left her, to teturn to the Empe∣ror.</P>
<P>In the mean time <HI>Odmar</HI> was flat∣tering the transports of <HI>Themir</HI> with the hopes of a more successful crime, and promised him the ruine of <HI>Ada∣naxus</HI> with very powerful assuran∣ses, and counsel'd him to go once more, and make his last efforts to <HI>Asteria.</HI> Seignior, said he to the Emperor, I've now dispensed with all that has hitherto made me sup∣port the contempts of <HI>Asteria,</HI> will you give me your consent to impose upon her inclinations to make me happy, for I do not think you will authorize <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to thwart my pretensions, and especially upon the account of <HI>Asterïa,</HI> whom I may call my conquest, by the blood she cost me whilst he abandoned you▪ Indeed I have no intention to pre∣fer <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to you, answer'd the Emperor, but you have your liber∣ty
<PB N="180" REF="95"/>
to satisfy your Love. But Son, are you stedfastly resolved to marry a Maid that cannot love you, who will look upon you as her Tyrant in your most pleasing moments, and become a torment to your Life. <HI>India, China, Egypt, Arabia,</HI> have Princesses, who will procure us such alliances as may be advantageous, and who are blest with charms, if Fame may be believed: You will bring▪ to your self a more quiet happiness, and the daughter of <HI>Ba∣jazet</HI> will see her folly punished by a contempt she will repent she had ever merited. No, Seignior replied <HI>Themir,</HI> I will have no other hap∣piness then that I demand of you. Well then added <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> give her some days respite to her mour∣ning. Seignior, interrupted <HI>The∣mir, Asteria</HI> will never soften by time, and it is unprofitable to throw it away. I will not prescribe you any long time, pursued the Empe∣ror, and then you shall have all my
<PB N="181" REF="95"/>
Authority. <HI>Themir</HI> complyed with the Emperor and by an affected kind of submission got himself com∣mended for it. He presently went to fling himself at the feet of <HI>Asteria;</HI> and <HI>Adanaxus</HI> being a greater per∣secution to him then his love, he sought out <HI>Odmar,</HI> who advised him to give the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> the liberty of seeing the Princess for some few days, that so he may be deprived of it for ever.</P>
<P><HI>Adanaxus</HI> did not trouble himself about forming of bloody designs, but imploying all his desires to his Love, one obliging word from the Princess did move him more then the possession of an Empire could have done.</P>
<P>He spent one evening with her with as much sweetness and tran∣quillity, as if he had neither had Rivals nor enemies, and was taking his leave of her with the ravishing joy of a successful Lover, when he heard a crying in the Palace, that
<PB N="182" REF="96"/>
the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> was dead. It is impossible to express <HI>Asteria's</HI> re∣sentments at these pitiful cries, <HI>A∣danaxus</HI> was so newly gone from her that she had not had the time to undress her self since that separa∣tion▪ and to hear his death pro∣claimed, struck her with an asto∣nishment that gave her almost a mortal paleness, and she fell into a swoon that held her so long, as made her women believe she was quite expired.</P>
<P>The cryes increased up and down the Palace, <HI>Tamberlain</HI> was fright∣ned at it, and <HI>Axalla</HI> enraged at the cruel destiny of so young a Prince, ran to the place where the massacred body lay (which was at the foot of a pair of Stairs that led to <HI>Asteria's</HI> Apartment.) He embraced it all bloody as it was, but it was not long e're by the light of several Flambeaus that the Servants brought, he dis∣covered that the person departed was <HI>Themir</HI> and not <HI>Adanaxus:</HI> Oh
<PB N="183" REF="96"/>
how great was <HI>Axalla's</HI> joy? What was the surprise of <HI>Odmar</HI> in behold∣ing his dear hopes in the condition he thought the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> had been. The Emperour was also come to this place, and by his transports testified, how cruelly the loss of a Son so tenderly beloved, was like to be revenged. <HI>Adanaxus</HI> came thither too at the same time, and troubled at <HI>Themir</HI>'s fate; how ex∣custable soever he would have been, if he had not bewailed it. Ah! Seignior, said he to <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> who∣soever is the murtherer of my Bro∣ther, he shall only dye by my hands. 'Tis I, interrupted <HI>Odmar,</HI> with an undaunted resolution, 'tis I who have given to the unfortunate <HI>The∣mir,</HI> that destiny which I only de∣signed for thee: and when I thought thy death certain, I my self was the publisher of it by my outcries. I saw you go to <HI>Asteria's</HI> Apartment, and having long since resolved thy destruction, I waited here to sacri∣fice
<PB N="184" REF="97"/>
thee, to give a pleasing surprise to <HI>Themir</HI> by the noise of thy death, my first designs not having been suc∣cessful, I would not ow the execu∣tion of this last to any other hand, than mine own: but fortune has proved base to me, and betrayed my intentions, and <HI>Themir</HI> who in all likelihood would have prevent∣ed me with resembling ones, is now unfortunately fallen under the hor∣ror of my stabs▪ <HI>Odmar</HI> spake like a man despairing, who only owed his unhappiness to his crimes; and perceiving the astonishment that e∣very body was in by his discourse, gave him opportunity to pursue it. <HI>Themir</HI> was wicked through my care to make him so; continued he, for finding dispositions in him confor∣mable to my desires, I made it my business to improve the malignity of them: He was absolutely mine and I was ambitious to see him have the Empire, but <HI>Tamberlain,</HI> be not surprised with so blind▪ a passion, but
<PB N="185" REF="97"/>
render justice to nature; for <HI>The∣mir</HI> was my Son, and in the first days of your own, your absence du∣ring the war of <HI>China,</HI> and the re∣sidence of your Queen at <HI>Cambalu,</HI> favouring my ambition, I very hap∣pily made an exchange of them: your young Prince died naturally in the exile to which I had sent him, and mine enjoying his place, would, had it not been for this fatal acci∣dent, have reigned over the <HI>Tar∣tars:</HI> He was ignorant of his birth, and I had used my utmost industry, and address to make him dear to you, and <HI>Adanaxus</HI> to meet with your hatred, or at least your indif∣ference, whom I looked upon as the only obstacle that could trouble me. But yet after the precaution of so many years, and the flattering Idea's I fed my self withal, I have inhu∣manely deprived my self of him, these are the effects of unconstant fortune, she yet demands one more, and he who has not trembled to
<PB N="186" REF="98"/>
reach the heart of his Son, ought not to have any pity for his own. At those words he ran a poniard up into his body, and then throwing himself upon that of <HI>Themir,</HI> he there expired in a moment. The death and the last words of <HI>Odmar</HI> produced new causes of astonish∣ment, <HI>Tamberlain</HI> had not the power to recover himself out of his, to think that he had given the whole Empire of his Soul to an impostor, who had committed so many inju∣stices against him, and caused the ruine of his true Son. This dread∣ful accident which was so great a justification to the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs,</HI> obliged the Emperour to make him a publick reparation for what was past, and not being able to tarry a∣ny longer in a place that was float∣ing with such odious blood, he re∣tired to his Apartment, and the ge∣nerous <HI>Adanaxus</HI> after he had or∣dered that the wretched Bodies should be buried, returned to the
<PB N="187" REF="98"/>
Princess, not doubting but that the <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eport of his death had sufficiently larm'd her.</P>
<P>He found her in that dismal swoon <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he fell into at the first outcry. Just Heavens, cryed he, seeing her in hat condition, shall I never enjoy a <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>appiness without such afflicting al∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ays, those tears and the name of <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Princess which he several times <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>epeated, began to make her come o her self. <HI>Asteria</HI> at last opened <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er eyes, and casting them upon <HI>A∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>anaxus;</HI> Ah! Seignior, said she to him, is it you I behold? Yes, Ma∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>am, replied the Prince, <HI>Themir</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as met with that destiny which was <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>repared for me, <HI>Ortobulus</HI> is re∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enged, I am without a Rival, I <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow need not fear any other to per∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cute me, and for my greater joy, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat <HI>Themir,</HI> who was so odious to <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y Princess by too powerful reasons, was not of the blood of <HI>Adanaxus.</HI> The Prince of <HI>Tanaïs</HI> who perceiv∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="in gutter" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <HI>Asteria,</HI> began to gather strength
<PB N="188" REF="99"/>
by the joy he had inspired into her at the Relation, gave her a true and full account of all the circumstances▪ and passages of it, how he had esca∣ped death in passing through the Terrace.</P>
<P>The rest of the Night passed in confusion, <HI>Asteria</HI> beheld her affe∣ction innocent, the murtherer of <HI>Ortobulus</HI> was not her Lover's Bro∣ther, and with a greater ease and tranqulllity than ever, enjoyed the pleasure of seeing her self beloved by him.</P>
<P>This accident divested <HI>Tamberlain</HI> of that cruel Meen he had before, and which made him be looked up∣on with so much fear; now all his severity with <HI>Themir</HI> had its sepul∣ture; his eyes lost their fury; and put a very pleasing sweetness on his face, and all those whom the ad∣dress and subtlety of <HI>Odmar,</HI> and his complaisances for <HI>Themir,</HI> had re∣moved from his esteem, received then fresh assurances of it from him.</P>
<P><PB N="189" REF="99"/>
As <HI>Adanaxus</HI> only now took up all his thoughts, he minded nothing but how to complete his happiness. He went to visit <HI>Asteria,</HI> testified to her the sincere grief he had at the af∣flictions he had procured her, resto∣red her all the conquests he had made in her Father's Kingdom, to dispose of how she pleased, and of∣fered her the Crown of the <HI>Tartars</HI> with <HI>Adanaxus.</HI> It was not possi∣ble that such a proffer as this could be displeasing to the Princess, She loved the Prince of <HI>Tanaïs, Bajazet</HI> had given him his esteem, and she thought she could not do any wrong to his memory in marrying him; but as he had left her Brothers, she ac∣quainted the Emperour that she could not dispose of her self without their allowance. This reason ap∣peared to him but just and equita∣ble, he order'd <HI>Alizanes</HI> and <HI>Calix∣tus</HI> two illustrious <HI>Tartars,</HI> to go and find them out. The impatience of <HI>Adanaxus</HI> made some little mur∣mur
<PB N="190" REF="100"/>
at it, but he was necessitated to submit to the Princess. <HI>Bajazet's</HI> Sons were found on the ruines of the <HI>Ottoman</HI> Empire, rallying by the help of their Neighbours such for∣ces, they thought might be sufficient to go out against <HI>Tamberlain.</HI> The Letters of <HI>Asteria</HI> and the conquests which were restored, put an end to that design; they now were think∣ing only how to raise up the Throne of <HI>Bajazet;</HI> which <HI>Mahomet</HI> the youngest of those Sons some few years after the death of the other▪ brought again to its first splendour▪ The <HI>Tartars</HI> returned, having mana∣ged their negotiation with success▪ <HI>Adanaxus</HI>'s love was authorized, and the marriage of <HI>Asteria</HI> recom∣penced his fidelity in the great City of <HI>Samarcanda,</HI> where they passed away their days in a lasting happi∣ness, after so many long and tedious persecutions.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="100"/>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

