<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A true copy of a letter written by N. Machiavill in defence of himself and his religion translated from an original copy.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Neville, Henry, 1620-1694.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A50367</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing M141</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R4918</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12982268</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12982268</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">96172</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A50367)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96172)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 389:17)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A true copy of a letter written by N. Machiavill in defence of himself and his religion translated from an original copy.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Neville, Henry, 1620-1694.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Machiavelli, Niccolò, 1469-1527. Works. English. 1675.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>35 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for R. Bentley ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1691.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Taken from Neville's translation of Machievelli's Works (1675) and previously published separately as: The publisher or translator of Nicholas Machiavels whole works ... concerning the following letter of Nicholas Machiavels, wherein he clears himself of the aspersions alleg'd by some on his writings. 1688.</NOTE><NOTE>"The letter is suppositious; it was probably written by Henry Nevile"--Cf. BM.</NOTE><NOTE>Letter written to Messieur Zenobio and dated: 1st of April 1537.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Machiavelli, Niccolò, 1469-1527.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A50367">
<STC T="W">M141</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12982268</BIBNO>
<VID>96172</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A
True COPY
Of a
LETTER
Written by
<HI>N. Machiavill,</HI>
IN
DEFENCE of Himself,
And His
RELIGION. Translated from an Original Copy.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed for <HI>R. Bentley</HI> in <HI>Covent-Garden,</HI> 1691.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="notice">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>AN
ADVERTISEMENT.
TO THE
READER,
Concerning this LETTER.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Courteous Reader,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IT hath been usual with almost all those who have Tran∣slated
this Author into any Language, to spend much of
their time and Paper in Taxing his Impieties, and Con∣futing
his Errours, and false Principles, as they are
pleased to call them: If upon perusal of his Writings I
had found him guilty of any thing that could deceive the Sim∣ple,
or prejudice the rest of Mankind, I should not have put thee to
the hazard of reading him in thy own Language, but rather have
suffered him still to sleep in the obscurity of his own, than en∣danger
the World; but being very well assured of the contrary,
and that this Age will rather receive advantage than dammage
by this Publication, I did yet think that it was fit to say some∣thing
in a Preface to vindicate our Author from those Slanders
which Priests, and other byast Pens have laid upon him. But
still I thought that it might prove a bold and presumptuous Vn∣dertaking,
and might excite Laughter, for a Person of my
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
small Parts and Abilities, to Apologise for one of the greatest
Wits, and profoundest Iudgments that ever liv'd amongst the
Moderns. In this perplexity, I had the good fortune to meet
with this Letter of his own writing, which hath deliver'd me
from those scruples, and furnished me with an opportunity of
justifying this great Person by his own Pen. Receive then
this choice Piece with benignity, it hath never before been
Published in any Language, but lurkt for above 80 years in
the private Cabinets of his own Kindred, and the descendants
of his own Admirers in <HI>Florence;</HI> 'till in the beginning of the
Pontificat of <HI>Urbane</HI> the <HI>VIII</HI>th, it was procured by the Ie∣suits,
and other Busybodies, and brought to <HI>Rome,</HI> with an
intention to divert that wise Pope from his design of making
one of <HI>Nicholas Machiavill</HI>'s Name and Family Cardinal, as
(notwithstanding all their opposition) he did not long after.
When it was gotten into that City, it wanted not those who
had the judgment and curiosity to copy it, and so at length
came to enjoy that priviledge which all rare Pieces (even the
sharpest Libels and Pasquils) challenge in that Court, which
is to be sold to strangers: One of which being a Gentleman of
this Countrey, brought it over with him at his return from
<HI>Florence,</HI> in the year 1645. and having Translated it into
English, did communicate it to divers of his Friends, and by
means of some of them, it hath been my good fortune to be ca∣pable
of making thee a Present of it; and let it serve as an
Apology for our Author, and his Writings, if thou thinkest
he need any. I must confess, I believe his Works require
little, but rather praise, and admiration; yet I wish I could
as well justify one undertaking of his not long after the writing
of this Letter; for we find, in the story of those times, that in
the Month of <HI>August</HI> following, in the same Year 1537 this
<HI>Nicolo Machiavelli</HI> (except there were another of that Name)
was committed Prisoner to the <HI>Bargello,</HI> amongst those who
were taken in Arms against <HI>Cosimo,</HI> at the Castle of <HI>Monte∣murli;</HI>
notwithstanding all his Compliments in this Letter to
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
that Prince, and profest Allegiance to him. If this be so, we
must impute it to his too great Zeal to concur with the desires
of the Vniversality at that time, in restoring the Liberty of their
Country, which hath so far dazel'd the Iudgments even of Great
and Wise Men, that thou seest many Grave Authors amongst the
Antients have even commended, and deify'd the ingratitude and
treachery of <HI>Brutus</HI> and <HI>Cassius.</HI> But certainly this Crime of
his would have been much more unpardonable, if he had liv'd
to see his own Prophecy fulfill'd in the Persons and Descendents
of this Great <HI>Cosimo;</HI> for there was never any Succession of
Princes since the World began, in which all the Royal Vertues,
and other Qualities necessary to those who Rule over Men, were
more eminently perspicuous, than in every individual of this
Line; so that those People have as little cause as ever any had,
to lament the Change of their Government, their great Dukes
having been truly Fathers of their Country, and treated their
Subjects like Children, though their Power be above all limitation,
above all fundamental Laws; but they having no Law, are a L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w
to themselves. I cannot chuse but instance in some few of their
benefits to their People; First the making the River <HI>Arne</HI> Navi∣gable
from <HI>Pisa</HI> to <HI>Florence</HI> in a Year of dearth, that so the Poor
might be set on work, and have bread; and the Traffick of both
Cities infinitely facilitated: Their making at their own charge a
Canal from <HI>Lucerne</HI> to <HI>Pisa;</HI> their erecting at <HI>Pisa</HI> a Famous
Vniversity, paying the Professors, who are Eminent for Learning,
and discharging all other incidences out of their own Revenue;
besides the raising Stately Buildings for Schools and L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>braries;
their fonding a Renowned Order of Knighthood, and keeping the
Chapter in the same City, and ordering a considerable number of
Knights constantly to reside there; both which were intended and
performed by them, to increase the Concourse▪ and restore the
Wealth to the once oppulent Inhabitants of that place. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
New Building, Fortifying, and Infranchising <HI>Lucerne</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
by abolishing their own Cust<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ms, they mig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t inrich their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
and make that Port (as it now is) the Magazine f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he <HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣vant</HI>
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
Trade: And lastly, their not having in 140 years ever
levy'd any new Tax upon their People, except in the year 1642
to defend the Liberties of <HI>Italy</HI> against the <HI>Barbarians.</HI> These
things would merit a Panegyrick, if either my parts, or this short
Advertisement would admit it; I shall conclude then, after I
have born a just and dutiful Testimony to the Merits of the
Prince who now Governs that State, in whom (if all the Princely
Vertues and Endowments should be lost) they might be found and
restor'd again to the World: As some ingenious Artists in the
last Age, retriev'd the Art of Sculpture by certain <HI>bas rilievo</HI>'s
remaining on some Pillars, and Walls at <HI>Rome.</HI> The Prudence,
Magnanimity, Charity, Liberality, and above all, the Huma∣nity,
Courtesie and Affability of this Prince, though exceeding
expressions, yet they are sufficiently known, not only to his own
Subjects (the constant Objects of his Care and Goodness) but even
to all Strangers, more particularly to our Nation; he having un∣dertaken
a troublesome Iourney to visit this Kingdom, and to
make it witness and partake of his transcendent Generosity and
Bounty, which he hath continued ever since, as can be testified by
all who have had the honour to wait upon him in his own Country,
or the good fortune but to see him in ours. I my self, who have
been so happy to be admitted into his presence, and have been
honoured since, in having his Highness my Customer for many
choice Books, to increase (not his knowledge, for that is beyond
receiving any addition by Books) but his Curiosity and his Li∣brary;
do think my self bound in duty to take this poor opportu∣nity
of testifying my gratitude and devotion to this Excellent
Prince. As to this Letter I have nothing more to say, but that
thou mayest see how right this Author was set in Principles of Re∣ligion,
before he could have the information which we have had
since from the Pens of most Learned and rational Controversists
in those Points; and therefore thou mayest admire the Sagacity
of his Iudgment. Read him then, and serve God, thy Country, and
thy King, with the knowledge he will teach thee. Farewell.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A
True Copy of a LETTER</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Written
By <HI>N. Machiavill,</HI> &amp;c.</BYLINE>
<P>THE Discourse we had lately (dear <HI>Messieur
Zenobio</HI>) in the Delightful Gardens of our old
deceased Friend <HI>Rucellai Cosimo,</HI> and the pres∣sing
importunity of <HI>Messieur Giulio Salivati,</HI>
that I would use some means to wipe off the
many aspersions cast upon my Writings, gives you the pre∣sent
trouble of reading this Letter, and me the pleasure of
writing it: which last would be infinitely greater, if I
were not at this day too Old, and too Inconsiderable, and
by the Change of our Government, wholly uncapable of
performing either with my Brain or my Hand any further
Service to my Country. For it hath ever been my Opi∣nion,
that whosoever goes about to make Men publickly
acquainted with his Actions, or Apologise to the World
for imputations laid upon him, cannot be excused from va∣nity,
and impertinence, except his Parts and Opportuni∣ties
be such as may enable him to be instrumental for the
good of others: And that he cannot atchieve that excel∣lent
end, without justifying himself from having any indi∣rect
and base ones, and procuring trust from Men, by
clearing the Repute of his Justice and Integrity to them.
But although this be far from my Cale, yet I have yielded
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
(you see) to the intreaty of <HI>Messieur Giulio,</HI> and the rest
of that Company, not only because I am sufficiently (both
by the restaint of our Press, and the discretion of the Per∣son
I write to) assured that this Letter will never be made
publick; but for that I esteem it a duty to clear that ex∣cellent
Society from the scandal of having so dangerous and
pernicious a Person to be a member of their Conversation;
for by reason of my Age, and since the loss of our Liberty,
and my Sufferings under that Monster of Lust and Cruelty
<HI>Alexander de Medici,</HI> set over us by the Divine Vengeance
for our Sins, I can be capable of no other design or enjoy∣ment,
than to delight, and be delighted, in the Company
of so many Choice and Virtuous Persons, who now assemble
themselves with all security under the happy &amp; hopeful Reign
of our new Prince <HI>Cosimo;</HI> and we may say, that though our
Commonwealth he not restored, our Slavery is at an end;
and that he coming in by our own choice, may prove (if I
have as good Skill in Prophecying as I have had formerly)
Ancestor to many Renowned Princes, who will govern this
State in great quietness, and with great Clemency; so that
our Posterity is like to enjoy ease and security, though not
that Greatness, Wealth and Glory, by which our City hath
for some years past (even in the most factious and tumul∣tuous
times of our Democracy) given Law to <HI>Italy,</HI> and
bridled the ambition of Foreign Princes. But, that I may
avoid the <HI>loquacity</HI> incident to Old Men, I will come
to the business. If I remember well, the Exceptions that
are taken to those poor things I have publisht, are reduce∣able
to three; first, That in all my Writings I insinuate my
great affection to the Democratical Government, even so
much as to undervalue that of Monarchy in respect of it;
which last I do, not obscurely, in many passages, teach, and
as it were perswade the People to throw off. Next, That
in some places I vent very great impieties, slighting and
vilifying the Church, as Author of all the Misgovernment in
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>
the World, and by such contempt make way for Atheism and
Profaneness; and lastly, that in my Book of the Prince I teach
Monarchs all the execrable Villanies that can be invented, and
instruct them how to break Faith, and so to Oppress and Enslave
their Subjects. I shall answer something to every one of these;
and that I may observe a right method, will begin with the first.
Having lived in an Age when our poor Country and Govern∣ment
have suffered more Changes and Revolutions than ever
did perhaps beyall any People in so short a time; and having
had, till the taking of <HI>Florence,</HI> my share in the managing of
Affairs, during almost all these Alterations, sometimes in the
Quality of Secretary of our City, and sometimes employ'd in
Embassages abroad; I set my self to read the Histories of An∣tient
and Modern Times, that I might by that means find out
whether there had not been in all Ages the like Vicissitudes
and Accidents in State Affairs, and to search out the Causes of
them; and having in some sort satisfied my self therein, I
could not abstain from scribling something of the two chief
kinds of Government, Monarchy, and Democracy, of which
all other forms are but mixtures: And since neither my Parts
nor Learning could arrive to follow the steps of the Ancients,
by writing according to Method and Art, as <HI>Plato, Aristotle,</HI>
and many others have done upon this Subject; I did content
my self to make slight Observations upon both, by giving a
bare Character of a Modern Prince, as to the Monarchical
frame, and as to the popular chusing the perfectest and most
successful of all Governments of that kind upon Earth; and
in my Discourses upon it, following the Order of my Author,
without ever taking upon me, to argue problematically, much
less to decide which of these two Governments is the best: If
from my way of handling matters in my Discourses upon
<HI>Livy,</HI> and from those incomparable Vertues and great Actions
we read of in that History, and from the Observations I make,
Men will conclude (which is I must confess my Opinion) that
the excellency of those Counsels and Atchievements, and the
<PB N="10" REF="6"/>
improvement which Mankind, and as I may so say, Humane
Nature it self obtained amongst the <HI>Romans,</HI> did proceed natu∣rally
from their Government, and was but a plain effect and
consequence of the perfection of their Commonwealth; I say,
if Readers will thus judge, how can I in reason be accus'd for
that? It would become those who lay this blame upon me to
undeceive them whom my Papers have misled, and to shew
the World to what other Causes we may impute those admi∣rable
Effects, those Heroick Qualities and Performances, that
Integrity, and purity of Manners, that scorning of Riches and
Life it self, when the Publick was concerned: if they please to
do this, they will oblige my Readers, who will owe to such
the rectifying of their Judgments, and not at all offend me,
who have reason'd this matter impartially, and without pas∣sion,
nor have possitively affirmed any thing. But what if this
part of my Accusation had been true? why should I be con∣demned
of Heresy or Indiscretion for preserring a Common∣wealth
before a Monarchy? Was I not born, bred, and
employ'd in a City, which being, at the time I writ, under
that Form of Government, did owe all Wealth and Greatness,
and all prosperity to it? If I had not very designedly avoided
all dogmaticalness in my Observations, (being not willing to
im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tate young Scholars in their declamations) I might easily
have concluded from the Premises I lay down, that a Demo∣cracy
founded upon good Orders, is the best and most excel∣lent
Government, and this without the least fear of confuta∣tion;
for I firmly believe, that there are none but Flatterers
and Sophisters would oppose me, such as will wrest <HI>Aristotle,</HI>
and even <HI>Plato</HI> himself, to make them write for Monarchy, by
misapplying some loose passages in those great Authors; nay,
they will tell their Readers, that what is most like the Go∣vernment
of the World by God, is the best, which wholly de∣pends
upon his Absolute Power. To make this Comparison
run with four feet, these Sycophants must give the poor Prince
they intend to Deify, a better and superiour Nature to Huma∣nity,
<PB N="11" REF="6"/>
must create a necessary dependance of all creatures upon
him, must endow him with infinite Wisdom and Goodness,
and even with Omnipotency it self. It will be hard for any
man to be misled in this Argument, by Proofs wrested from
Theology, since whosoever reads attentively the Historical part
of the Old Testament, shall find that God himself never made
but one Government for Men, that this Government was a
Commonwealth (wherein the Sanhedrim or Senate, and the
Congregation, or popular Assembly had their share) and that
he manifested his high displeasure when the rebellious People
would turn it into a Monarchy. But, that I may not strike
upon the Rock I profess to shun, I shall pass to that which is,
indeed, fit to be wipt off, and which, if it were true, would
not only justly expose me to the hatred and vengeance of God,
and all good Men, but even destroy the design and purpose of
all my Writings; which is to treat in some sort (as well as
one of my small parts can hope to do) of the Politicks; and
how can any man pretend to write concerning policy, who
destroys the most essential part of it, which is Obedience to all
Governments? It will be very easie then for <HI>Giulio Salivati,</HI> or
any other Member of our Society, to believe the protestation
I make; that the animating of private Men, either directly or
indirectly, to disobey, much less to shake off any Govern∣ment,
how despotical soever, was never in my thoughts or
Writings; those who are unwilling to give credit to this, may
take the pains to assign in any of my Books the passages they
imagine to tend that way (for I can think of none my self)
that so I may give such person more particular satisfaction. I
must confess I have a Discourse in one of my Books to en∣courage
the <HI>Italian</HI> Nation to assume their antient valour, and
to expel the <HI>Barbarians,</HI> meaning (as the Antient <HI>Romans</HI> us'd
the word) all Strangers from amongst us; but that was before
the Kings of <HI>Spain</HI> had quiet possession of the Kingdom of
<HI>Naples,</HI> or the Emperour of the <HI>Dutchy of Milan;</HI> so that I
could not be interpreted to mean, that the People of those two
<PB N="12" REF="7"/>
Dominions should be stirr'd up to shake off their Princes, be∣cause
they were Foreigners, since at that time <HI>Lodovic Sforza</HI>
was in possession of the one, and King <HI>Frederick</HI> restored to
the other, both Natives of <HI>Italy;</HI> but my design was to exhort
our Countrymen not to suffer this Province to be the Scene of
the Arms and Ambition of <HI>Charles</HI> the VIII<HI>th,</HI> or K. <HI>Lewis</HI> his
Successor; who, when they had a mind to renew the old
Title of the House of <HI>Anjou</HI> to the Kingdom of <HI>Naples,</HI> came
with such Force into <HI>Italy,</HI> that not only our Goods were
plundered, and our Lands wasted, but even the Liberty of our
Cities and Governments endanger'd; but to unite and oppose
them, and to keep this Province in the hands of Princes of our
own Nation; this my intention is so visible in the Chapter it
self, that I need but refer you to it. Yet, that I may not an∣swer
this imputation barely by denying, I shall assert in this
place what my Principles are in that which the World calls
Rebellion; which I believe to be not only a rising in Arms a∣gainst
any Government we live under, but do acknowledge
that word to extend to all Clandestine Conspiracies too, by
which the peace and quiet of any Country may be interrupted,
and by consequence the Lives and Estates of innocent Persons
endanger'd. Rebellion then, so described, I hold to be the
greatest Crime that can be committed amongst Men, both a∣gainst
Policy, Morality, and in <HI>Foro Conscientiae:</HI> But notwith∣standing
all this, it is an Offence which will be committed
whilst the World lasts, as often as Princes tyrannize, and, by
Inslaving and Oppressing their Subjects, make Magistracy,
which was intended for the Benefit of Mankind, prove a Plague
and destruction to it: For let the terrour and the guilt be never
so great, it is impossible that Humane Nature, which consists
of Passion as well as Vertue, can support with patience and
submission the greatest Cruelty and Jnjustice, whenever either
the Weakness of their Princes, the Unanimity of the People,
or any other favourable accident, shall give them reasonable
hopes to mend their Condition, and provide better for their
<PB N="13" REF="7"/>
own interest by Insurrection: So that Princes and States ought,
in the conduct of their Affairs, not only to consider what
their People are bound to submit to, if they were inspir'd from
Heaven; or were all Moral Philosophers; but to weigh likewise
what is probable <HI>de facto</HI> to fall out, in this corrupt Age of
the World, and to reflect upon those dangerous tumults which
have happen'd frequently, not only upon Oppression, but even
by reason of malversation; and how some Monarchies have
been wholly subverted, and changed into Democracies, by the
Tyranny of their Princes, as we see (to say nothing of <HI>Rome</HI>)
the powerful Cantons of <HI>Swisserland</HI> brought by that means, a
little before the last Age, to a considerable Commonwealth,
courted and sought to by all the Potentates in <HI>Christendom.</HI> If
Princes will seriously consider this matter, I make no question
but they will Rule with Clemency and Moderation, and re∣turn
to that excellent Maxime of the Antients (almost explo∣ded
in this Age) that the Interest of Kings, and of their Peo∣ple,
is the same, which Truth it hath been the whole Design of
my Writings to convince them of.</P>
<P>Now having gone thus far in the description of Rebellion;
I think my self obliged to tell you what I conceive not to be
Rebellion. Whosoever then takes up Arms to maintain the
Politick Constitution, or Government of his Country, in the
Condition it then is, I mean, to defend it from being Changed,
or Invaded, by the Craft or Force of any Man (although it
be the Prince, or Chief Magistrate himself) provided, that
such taking up of Arms be Commanded, or Authorised by
those who are, by the Orders of that Government, legally
intrusted with the Custody of the Liberty of the
People, and Foundation of the Government: This I hold to
be so far from Rebellion, that I believe it laudable, nay, the
Duty of every Member of such Commonwealth; for that he
who Fights to Support and Defend the Government he was
born and lives under, cannot deserve the odious name of Re∣bel,
but he who endeavours to destroy it. If this be not
<PB N="14" REF="8"/>
granted, it will be in vain to frame any mixt Monarchies in
the World; yet such is at this day the happy Form under
which almost all <HI>Europe</HI> lives, as the People of <HI>France, Spain,
German, Poland, Swethland, Denmark,</HI> &amp;c. Wherein the Prince
hath his share, and the People theirs; which last, if they had
no means of recovering their Rights, if taken from them, or
defending them if invaded, would be in the same Estate as
if they had no Title to them, but liv'd under the Empire of
<HI>Turkey,</HI> or of <HI>Muscovey.</HI> And since they have no other Remedy
but by Arms, and that it would be of ill Conquence to make
every private man judge when the Rights of the People (to
which they have as lawful a Claim as the Prince to his) are
Invaded▪ which would be apt to produce frequent, and some∣times
causeless Tumults; therefore it hath been the great
Wisdom of the Founders of such Monarchies, to appoint Guar∣dians
to their Liberty; which if it be not otherwise exprest,
is and ought to be understood to reside in the Estates of the
Country, which for that Reason (as also to exercise their share
in the Soveraignty, as making Laws, Levying Money, <HI>&amp;c.</HI>)
are frequently to be Assembled in all those Regions in <HI>Europe,</HI>
before mentioned. These are to assert and maintain the Or∣ders
of the Government, and the Laws established, and (if it
cannot be done otherwise) to arm the People to defend them,
and repel the force that is upon them. Nay, the Govern∣ment
of <HI>Aragon</HI> goes further; and because in the intervals of
the Estates or Courts many accidents may intervene, to the
prejudice of their Rights, or <HI>Fueros,</HI> as they call them; they
have, during the intermission, appointed a Magistrate, called
<HI>El Iusticia,</HI> who is, by the Law and Consti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ution of that
Kingdom, to Assemble the whole People to his Banner, when∣ever
such Rights are incroacht upon; who are not only
justified by the Laws for such coming together, but are
severely punishable in case of refusal. So that there is no
question, but that if the Kings of <HI>Aragon,</HI> at this day very
powerful, by the addition of the <HI>Naples</HI> Kingdom, and of
<PB N="15" REF="8"/>
<HI>Sicily,</HI> and the Union with <HI>Castile,</HI> should, in time to come,
Invade their Kingdom of <HI>Aragon</HI> with the Forces of their New
Dominions, and endeavour to take from them the Rights
and Priviledges they enjoy lawfully by their Constitution,
There is no question, I say, but they may (though their King
be there in person against them) Assemble under their <HI>Iusti∣cia,</HI>
and defend their Liberties, with as much Justice, as if they
were Invaded by the <HI>French,</HI> or by the <HI>Turk.</HI> For it were
absurd to think, since the People may be legally assembled
to apprehend Banditti Robbers, nay, to deliver a Possession
forceably detain'd against the Sentence of some inferiour
Court, that they may and ought not to bestir themselves to
keep in being, and preserve that Government which maintains
them in possession of their Liberty, and Property, and defends
their Lives too, from being Arbitrarily taken away. But I
know this clear Truth receives opposition in this unreasonable
and corrupt Age; when Men are more prone to Flatter the
Lusts of Princes than formerly, and the Favourites are more
impatient to bear the impartiality of Laws, than the Son<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of
<HI>Brutus</HI> were; who complain'd, <HI>Leg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s esse Surdas;</HI> that is,
though they were fine Gentlemen, in favour with the Ladies,
and Ministers of the King's <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leasures, vet they could not
Oppress, Drink, Whore, nor Kill the, <HI>Sbiri,</HI> Officers of Justice,
in the Streets, returning from their Night Revels, but the
Execution of the Laws would reach them▪ as well <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s others;
who, in the times of <HI>Tarquin</HI> it seems, found the Prince more
exorable. Nay, the very Divines themselves help with their
fallacies to oppugne this Doctrine; by making us believe, as
I said before, that it is God's will all Princes should be abso∣lute;
and are so far in a Conspiracy against Mankind, that
they assert that in the Text (<HI>This shall the manner of your King
be</HI>) God was giving that People the <HI>Ius Divinum</HI> of Govern∣ment,
when in truth he was threatning then with the Plagues
of Monarchy. But I spare the Divines here, since I shall have
occasion, in Discoursing of my next Accusation, to shew how
<PB N="16" REF="9"/>
that sort of People have dealt with God's Truths, and with
the Interests of Men; and to be as good as my word, I shall
presently fall upon that Point, having been so tedious already
in the former.</P>
<P>I am charged then in the Second place with Impiety, in
villifying the Church, and so to make way for Atheism. I
do not deny but that I have very frequently, in my Writings,
laid the blame upon the Church of <HI>Rome;</HI> not only for all
the Misgovernment of Christendom, but even for the depra∣vation,
and almost total Destruction of Christian Religion it
self in this Province. But that this Discourse of mine doth,
or can tend to teach Men Impiety, or to make way for
Atheism, I peremptorily deny; and although for proof of my
innocence herein, I need but refer you, and all others, to my
Papers themselves, as they are now Published; (where you
will find all my Reasons drawn from Experience, and frequent
Examples cited, which is ever my way of arguing) yet since
I am put upon it, I shall in a few Lines make that matter
possibly a little clearer; and shall first make protestation, that
as I do undoubtedly hope, by the Merits of Christ, and by
Faith in him, to attain Eternal Salvation; so I do firmly Be∣lieve
the Christian Profession to be the only true Religion now
in the World: Next, I am fully perswaded that all Divine
Verities, which God then designed to teach the World, are
contained in the Books of Holy Scripture, as they are now
extant, and received amongst us. From them I understand,
that God Created Man in Purity, and Innocence; and that
the first of that Species, by their frailty, lost at once their
Integrity, and their Paradise, and intail'd Sin and Misery upon
their Posterity. That Almighty God, to repair this loss, did,
out of his infinite Mercy, and with unparallel'd Grace and
Goodness, send his only Begotten Son into the World, to
teach us new Truths, to be a perfect Example of Vertue,
Goodness, and Obedience; to restore true Religion, degenera∣ted
amongst the <HI>Iews</HI> into Superstition, Formality, and Hy∣pocrisie;
<PB N="17" REF="9"/>
to die for the Salvation of Mankind, and in fine, to
give to us the Holy Spirit, and to regenerate our Hearts, sup∣port
our Faith, and lead us into all Truth. Now if it shall ap∣pear,
that as the lusts of our first Parents did at that time dis∣appoint
the good intention of God, in making a pure World,
and brought in, by their disobedience, the Corruptions that are
now in it; so, that since likewise the Bishops of <HI>Rome,</HI> by
their insatiable Ambition and Avarice, have designedly, as
much as in them lies, frustrated the merciful purpose he had
in the happy restoration he intended the World by his Son,
and in the renewing and reforming of Humane Nature, and
have wholly defac'd and spoil'd Christian Religion, and made
it a Worldly and a Heathenish thing, and altogether uncapa∣ble,
as it is practised amongst them, either of directing the
ways of its Professors to Vertue and good Life, or of saving
their Souls hereafter. If, I say, this do appear, I know no rea∣son
why I, for detecting thus much, and for giving warning to
the World to take heed of their ways, should be accused of
Impiety, or Atheism, or why his Holiness should be so enra∣ged
against the poor Inhabitants of the Vallies in <HI>Savoy,</HI> and
against the <HI>Albigesi,</HI> for calling him Antichrist. But to find
that this is an undoubted Truth, I mean, that the Popes have
corrupted Christian Religion, we need but read the New Testa∣ment
(acknowledged by themselves to be of Infallible Truth)
and there we shall see, that the Faith and Religion Preacht by
Christ, and settled afterwards by his Apostles, and Cultivated
by their Sacred Epistles, is so different a thing from the Chri∣stianity
that is now Profest, and Taught at <HI>Rome,</HI> that we
should be convinc'd, that if those Holy Men should be sent by
God again into the World, they would take more pains to
confute this Gallimaufry, than ever they did to preach down
the Traditions of the <HI>Pharisees,</HI> or the Fables and Idolatries
of the <HI>Gentiles,</HI> and would in probability suffer a new Martyr∣dom
in that City, under the Vicar of Christ, for the same
Doctrine which once animated the Heathen Tyrants against
<PB N="18" REF="10"/>
them. Nay, we have something more to say against these
Sacrilegious Pretenders to God's Power; for whereas all other
false Worships have been set up by some Politick Legislators,
for the Support and Preservation of Government, this false, this
spurious Religion, brought in upon the ruines of Christianity
by the Popes, has deform'd the face of Government in <HI>Eu∣rope,</HI>
destroying all the good Principles and Morality left us
by the Heathens themselves; and introduced instead thereof,
Sordid, Cowardly, and Impolitick Notions; whereby they
have subjected Mankind, and even great Princes and States
to their own Empire, and never suffer'd any Orders or Maximes
to take place, where they have power, that might make a
Nation Wise, Honest, Great, or Wealthy. This I have set
down so plainly in those Passages of my Book which are com∣plain'd
of, that I shall say nothing at all for the Proof of it
in this place, but referr you thither, and come to speak a little
more particularly of my first assertion; That the Pope and
his Clergy have depraved Christian Religion. Upon this Sub∣ject,
I could infinitely wish, now Letters begin to revive a∣gain,
that some Learned Pen would employ it self, and that
some Person verst in the Cronology of the Church (as they
call it) would deduce out of the Ecclesiastical Writers the time
and manner how these Abuses crept in, and by what Arts and
Steps this <HI>Babel</HI> that reaches at Heaven, was built by these
Sons of the Earth: But this matter, as unsuitable to the bre∣vity
of a Letter, and indeed more to my small Parts and
Learning, I shall not pretend to, being one who never hither∣to
studied or writ of Theology, further than it did naturally
concern the Politicks; therefore I shall only deal by the New
Testament, as I have done formerly by <HI>Titus Livius,</HI> that is, make
Observations or Reflections upon it, and leave you Messieur
<HI>Giulio,</HI> and the rest of our Society, to make the judgment,
not citing like Preachers the Chapter, or Verse, because the
reading of Holy Scripture is little us'd, and indeed hardly
permitted amongst us. To begin at the top, I would have
<PB N="19" REF="10"/>
any reasonable Man tell me whence this unmeasurable Power,
long claim'd, and now possest by the Bishop of <HI>Rome,</HI> is deri∣ved;
first, of being Christ's Vicar, and by that (as I may so
say) pretending to a Monopoly of the Holy Spirit, (which
was promised and given to the whole Church, that is, to the
Elect, or Saints) as is plain by a Clause in St. <HI>Peter</HI>'s Sermon,
made the very same time that the miraculous Gifts of the Spi∣rit
of God were first given to the Apostles, who says to the
<HI>Iews</HI> and <HI>Gentiles, Repent, and be Baptised every one of you,
in the name of Iesus Christ, for the Remission of Sins, and ye
shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost; for this Promise is to
you, and to your Children, and to all that are afar off, even as
many as the Lord our God shall call.</HI> Next, to judge infallibly
of Divine Truth, and to forgive Sins as Christ did: Then to
be the Head of all Ecclesiastical Persons, and Causes in the
World; to be so far above Kings and Princes, as to Judge,
Depose, and Deprive them, and to have an absolute Juris∣diction
over all the Affairs in <HI>Christendom, in Ordine ad Spiri∣tualia;</HI>
yet all this the Canonists allow him, and he makes
no scruple to assume, whilst it is plain, that in the whole New
Testament there is no description made of such an Officer to
be at any time in the Church, except it be in the Prophecy
of the <HI>Apocalypse,</HI> or in one of St. <HI>Paul</HI>'s Epistles, where he says,
<HI>Who is it that shall sit in the Temple of God, shewing himself that
he is God.</HI> Christ tells us <HI>his Kingdom is not of this World,
and if any will be the greatest amongst his Disciples, that he must
be Servant to the rest;</HI> which shews, that his Followers were
to be great in Sanctity, and Humility, and not in Worldly
Power. The Apostle <HI>Paul,</HI> writing to the Christians of those
times, almost in every Epistle, commands them <HI>to be obedient
to the Higher Powers,</HI> or Magistrates, set over them; and St.
<HI>Peter</HI> himself (from whom this extravagant Empire is pre∣tended
to be deriv'd) in his first Epistle, <HI>bids us submit our
selves to every Ordinance of Man▪ for the Lord's sake, whether
it be to the King, or,</HI> &amp;c. And this is enjoyn'd, although it
<PB N="20" REF="11"/>
is plain, that they who Govern'd the World in those days,
were both Heathens, Tyrants, and Usurpers, and in this sub∣mission
there is no Exception, or Proviso for Ecclesiastical im∣munity.
The Practice as well as Precepts of these Holy Men
shews plainly that they had no intention to leave Successors
who should deprive Hereditary Princes from their right of
Reigning for difference in Religion, who without all doubt,
are by the appointment of the Apostle, and by the Principles
of Christianity, to be obeyed and submitted to (in things
wherein the Fundamental Laws of the Government give them
power) though they were <HI>Iews,</HI> or <HI>Gentiles.</HI> If I should tell
you by what Texts in Scripture, the Popes claim the Powers
before mentioned, it would stir up your laughter, and prove
too light for so serious a matter, yet because possibly you may
never have heard so much of this Subject before, I shall in∣stance
in a few: They tell you therefore that the Jurisdiction
they pretend over the Church, and the Power of pardoning
Sins, comes from Christ to St. <HI>Peter,</HI> and from him to them.
<HI>Thou art</HI> Peter, <HI>and upon this Rock I will build my Church.
I will give thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven; what ye
bind</HI> (this is spoken to all the Apostles) <HI>on Earth, shall be
bound in Heaven, and what ye bind,</HI> &amp;c. From these three
Texts, ridiculously apply'd, comes this great Tree, which
hath with its Branches overspread the whole Earth, and
killed all the good and wholsome Plants growing upon it.
The first Text will never by any Man of Sense be understood
to say more, than that the Preaching, Suffering, and Mi∣nistry
of <HI>Peter</HI> was like to be a great Foundation and Pillar
of the Doctrine of Christ; the two other Texts, (as also a∣nother
spoken by our Saviour, to all his Apostles, <HI>Whose Sins
ye remit, they are remitted, and whose Sins ye retain, they are
retained</HI>) are by all the Primitive Fathers Interpreted in this
manner: Wheresoever you shall effectually Preach the Gospel,
you shall carry with you Grace, and Remission of Sins to
them which shall follow your Instructions; but the People
<PB N="21" REF="11"/>
who shall not have these joyful tidings communicated by you
to them, shall remain in darkness, and in their Sins; but if
any will contest, that by some of these last Texts, that Evan∣gelical
Excommunication, which was afterward brought into
the Church by the Apostles, was here pre-signified by our
great Master; how unlike were those Censures to thos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
thunder'd out (as he calls it) by the Pope? These were <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Edification, and not Destruction, to afflict the Flesh for the
Salvation of the Soul; that Apostolical Ordinance was pro∣nounced
for some notorious Scandal, or Apostacy from the
Faith, and first decreed by the Church; that is, the whole
Congregation present; and then denounced by the Pastor, and
reached only to debar such Person from partaking of the
Communion, or Fellowship of that Church, 'till Repentance
should re-admit him, but was followed by no other prosecu∣tion,
or chastisement, as is now Practised. But suppose all
these Texts had been as they would have them, how does
this make for the Successors of St. <HI>Peter,</HI> or the rest? Or how
can this prove the Bishops of <HI>Rome</HI> to have right to such
Succession? But I make haste from this Subject, and shall urge
but one Text more, which is, <HI>The Spiritual Man judgeth all
Men, but is himself judged of none:</HI> From whence is inferred
by the Canonists, that first the Pope is the Spiritual Man, and
then that he is to be Judge of all the World; and last, that he
is never to be liable to any Judgment himself; whereas it is
obvious to the meanest Understanding, that St. <HI>Paul</HI> in this
Text means to distinguish between a Person inspired with the
Spirit of God, and one remaining in the state of Nature;
which latter he says cannot judge of those Heavenly Gifts,
and Graces, as he explains himself, when he says, <HI>The natural
Man cannot discern the things of the Spirit, because they are
foolishness unto him.</HI> To take my leave of this matter, wholly out
of the way of my Studies, I shall beg of you Messieur <HI>Zenobio,</HI>
and of Messieur <HI>Giulio,</HI> and the rest of our Society, to read over
carefully the New Testament, and then to see what ground
<PB N="22" REF="12"/>
there is for Purgatory (by which all the Wealth and Great∣ness
hath accrew'd to these Men) what colour for the Idola∣trous
Worship of Saints, and their Images, and particularly
for speaking in their Hymns and Prayers to a piece of Wood
(the Cross I mean) <HI>Salve Lignum,</HI> &amp;c. and then <HI>fac nos dig∣nos
beneficiorum Christi,</HI> as you may read in that Office; what
colour, or rather what excuse for that horrid unchristian and
barbarous Engine called the Inquisition, brought in by the
Command and Authority of the Pope; the Inventer of
which, <HI>Peter</HI> a Dominican Fryer, having been slain amongst
the <HI>Albigesi,</HI> as he well deserved, is now Canoniz'd for a
Saint, and stiled <HI>San Pietro Martire.</HI> In the dreadful Prisons
of this Inquisition, many Faithful and Pious Christians (to say
nothing of honest Moral <HI>Moors,</HI> or <HI>Mahometans</HI>) are torment∣ed,
and famisht, or if they out-live their Sufferings, burnt
publickly to death, and that only for differing in Religion
from the Pope, without having any Crime, or the least Mis∣demeanor
prov'd or alledged against them; and this is inflicted
upon these poor Creatures, by those who profess to believe
the Scripture, which tells us, <HI>that Faith is the gift of God,
without whose special illumination no Man can obtain it;</HI> and
therefore is not in Reason or Humanity to be punished for
wanting it. And Christ himself hath so clearly decided that
point, in bidding us <HI>let the Tares and the Wheat grow together
'till the Harvest,</HI> that I shall never make any difficulty to
call him Antichrist, who shall use the least Persecution what∣soever,
against any differing in Matters of Faith from himself,
whether the person so diffenting be <HI>Heretick, Iew, Gentile,</HI> or
<HI>Mahometan.</HI> Next, I beseech you to observe in reading that
Holy Book (though Christian Fasts are doubtless of Di∣vine
Right) what ground there is for enjoyning Fish to be
eaten (at least Flesh to be abstained from) for one full third
part of the year, by which they put the Poor to great hard∣ship;
who not having Purses to buy wholsome Fish, are sub∣jected
to all the Miseries and Diseases incident to a bad and
<PB N="23" REF="12"/>
unhealthful Diet; whilst the Rich, and chiefly themselves,
and their Cardinals, exceed <HI>Lucullus</HI> in their Luxury of Oy∣sters,
Turbots, tender Crabs, and a Lake Fish not known here,
brought some hundreds of miles to feed their gluttony, upon
these penitential days of abstinence from Beef and Pork. It
may be it will lie in the way of those who observe this, to
inquire what St. <HI>Paul</HI> means, when he says, <HI>that in the latter
days some shall depart from the Faith, forbidding to Marry, and
commanding to abstain from Meats, which God hath Created to
be received with thanksgiving:</HI> But all these things, and many
other abuses brought in by these perverters of Christianity,
will I hope e're long be inquired into by some of the Disciples
of that bold Fryer, who the very same year in which I pro∣phesied
that the Scourge of the Church was not far off, be∣gan
to thunder against their Indulgences, and since hath
question'd many Tenents long received and impos'd upon
the World. I shall conclude this Discourse, after I have said a
word of the most hellish of all the Innovations brought in
by the Popes, which is the Clergy; these are a sort of Men,
under pretence of ministring to the People in Holy things,
set apart, and separated from the rest of Mankind (from
whom they have a very distinct, and a very opposite inte∣rest)
by a Humane Ceremony call'd by a Divine Name, <HI>viz.</HI>
Ordination; these, wherever they are found (with the whole
body of the Monks, and Fryers, who are called the Regular
Clergy) make a Band which may be called the <HI>Ianizaries</HI> of
the Papacy; these have been the Causers of all the Solicisms
and Immoralities in Government, and of all the Impieties and
Abominations in Religion, and by consequence of all the
Disorder, Villany, and Corruption we suffer under in this de∣testable
Age. These Men, by the help of the Bishop of <HI>Rome,</HI>
have crept into all the Governments in <HI>Christendom,</HI> where
there is any mixture of Monarchy, and made themselves a
third State; that is, have by their Temporalities (which
are almost a third part of all the Lands in <HI>Europe,</HI> given them
<PB N="24" REF="13"/>
by the blind Zeal, or rather folly of the Northern People,
who over-ran this part of the World) stept into the Throne,
and what they cannot perform by these Secular Helps, and
by the dependency their Vassals have upon them, they fail
not to claim and to usurp by the Power they pretend to have
from God, and his Vicegerent at <HI>Rome.</HI> They exempt them∣selves,
their Lands, and Goods from all Secular Jurisdiction,
that is, from all Courts of Justice, and Magistracy, and will
be Judges in their own Cause, as in matters of Tithes, <HI>&amp;c.</HI>
and not content with this, will appoint Courts of their own,
to decide Soveraignly in Testimentary Matters, and many
other Causes, and take upon them to be the sole Punishers
of many great Crimes, as Witchcraft, Sorcery, Adultery, and
all Uncleanness: To say nothing of the fore-mentioned Judi∣catory
of the Inquisition, in these last Cases they turn the
Offenders over to be punisht (when they have given Sen∣tence)
by the <HI>Secular Arm,</HI> so they call the Magistrate, who
is blindly to execute their Decrees, under pain of Hell fire;
as if Christian Princes and Governours were appointed only
by God to be their Braves, or Hangmen. They give Protection
and Sanctuary to all Execrable Offenders, even to Murderers
themselves (whom God commanded to be indispensably
punisht with death) if they come within their Churches,
Cloysters, or any other place which they will please to call
Holy Ground; and if the ordinary Justice, nay, the Sove∣raign
Power, do proceed against such Offender, they thunder
out their Excommunication, that is, cut off from the Body
of Christ, not the Prince only, but the whole Nation, and
People; shutting the Church doors, and commanding Divine
Offices to cease, and sometimes even authorizing the People
to rise up in Arms, and constrain their Governours to a sub∣mission;
as happen'd to this poor City, in the time of our
Ancestors; when for but forbidding the Servant of a poor
Carmilite Fryer (who had vowed Poverty, and should have
kept none) to go armed, and punishing his disobedience with
<PB N="25" REF="13"/>
Imprisonment, our whole Senate, with their Chief Magi∣strate,
were constrained to go to <HI>Avignon</HI> for Absolution,
and in case of refusal, had been Massacred by the People.
It would almost astonish a Wise Man to imagine how these
Folks should acquire an Empire so destructive to Christian
Religion, and so pernicious to the Interests of Men; but
it will not seem so miraculous to them who shall seriously
consider, that the Glergy hath been for more than these
Thousand Years upon the catch, and a form'd united
Corporation against the purity of Religion, and the Inte∣rests
of Mankind; and have not only wrested the Holy
Scriptures to their own advantage (which they have kept
from the Laiety in unknown Languages, and by prohibi∣ting
the reading thereof) but made use likewise, first, of
the blind Devotion and Ignorance of the <HI>Goths, Vandals,
Huns, &amp;c.</HI> and since, of the Ambition and Avarice of
Christian Princes, stirring them up one against another, and
sending them upon foolish Errands to the Holy Land, to
lose their Lives, and to leave their Dominions in the mean
time exposed to themselves, and their Complices; they
have besides kept Learning and Knowledge amongst them∣selves,
stifling the light of the Gospel; crying down Moral
Vertues as splendid Snares, defacing Humane Policy, de∣stroying
the purity of the Christian Faith and Profession,
and all that was Vertuous, Prudent, Regular, and Orderly
upon Earth; so that whoever would do God, and Good
Men service, get himself immortal Honour in this Life,
and Eternal Glory in the next, would restore the good
Policy (I had almost said, with my Author <HI>Livy,</HI> the
Sanctity too) of the <HI>Heathens,</HI> with all their Valour, and
other Glorious Endowments: I say, whoever would do
this, must make himself powerful enough to extirpate this
Cursed and Apostate Race out of the World; and that you
<PB N="26" REF="14"/>
may see this is lawful, as well as necessary, I shall say
but one word of their Calling, and Original, and
then leave this Subject. The word Clergy is a term
wholly unknown to the Scriptures, otherwise than in
this sense. A peculiar People, or God's Lott, used often
for the whole <HI>Iewish</HI> Nation, who are likewise called a
Kingdom of Priests in some places. In the New Testa∣ment
the word <HI>Cleros</HI> is taken for the true Believers,
who are also called the Elect, and often the Church,
which is the Assembly of the Faithful met together; as
is easily seen, by reading the beginning of most of St.
<HI>Paul</HI>'s Epistles; where, writing to the Church, or <HI>Gala∣thian</HI>
Churches, he usually explains himself to all the
Saints in Christ; sometimes to all who have obtained
like Faith with us; sometimes to all who in all places call
upon the Name of the Lord Jesus, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> By which, it ap∣pears,
that neither the word Church, nor Clergy, was in
those days ever appropriated to the Pastors, or Elders of
the Flock, but did signify indifferently all the People as∣sembled
together; which is likewise the litteral construction
of the word <HI>Ecclesia,</HI> which is an Assembly, or Meeting:
In these Congregations or Churches, was performed their
Ordination, which properly signifies no more than a De∣cree
of such Assembly, but is particularly used for an
Election of any into the Ministry. The manner was this,
sometimes the Apostles themselves in their Perigrinations,
and sometimes any other eminent Member of the Church,
did propose to the Society (upon Vacancy, or other ne∣cessity
of a Pastor, Elder, or Deacon) some good Holy
Man to be Elected; which Person, if he had Parts, or
Gifts, such as the Church could Edify by, was chosen by
lifting up of hands, that is, by Suffrage; and oftentimes
hands were laid upon him, and Prayer made for him.
These Men so set apart, did not pretend to any Con∣secration,
<PB N="27" REF="14"/>
or Sacredness, more than they had before; much
less to become a distinct thing from the rest of Mankind;
as if they had been Metamorphos'd, but did attend to
perform the several Functions of their Calling, as Prophe∣sying,
that is, preaching the Gospel, Visiting the Sick, <HI>&amp;c.</HI>
and never intermitted the ordinary business of their Trade,
or Profession, unless their Church or Congregation was
very numerous; in which case, they were maintain'd by
Alms, or Contribution, which was laid aside by every
Member, and Collected the first day of the Week by the
Deacons; this was said to be given to the Church, and
was imploy'd by Suffrage of the whole collective Body to
the Poor, and to other incidences; so far was it from Sa∣criledge
in those days, to employ Church Goods to Lay
uses. From these words, Church, Clergy, Ordination, Pa∣stor,
(which last hath been Translated of late years Bishop)
you see what Conclusions these Men have deduced, and
how immense a Structure they have raised upon so little
a Foundation, and how easily it will fall to the ground,
when God shall inspire Christian Princes and States to re∣deem
his Truths, and his poor enslaved Members out of
their clutches, and to bring back again into the World,
the true Original Christian Faith, with the Apostolical
Churches, Pastors, and Ordination, so consistent with Mo∣ral
Vertue, and Integrity; so helpful and conducing to the
best and most prudent Policy, so fitted for obedience to
Magistracy, and Government, all which the World hath
for many years been depriv'd of, by the execrable and
innate ill quality, which is inseparable from Priestcraft, and
the Conjuration or Spell of their new invented Ordination,
by which they cry with the Poet <HI>Claudian,</HI>
<Q><PB N="28" REF="15"/><L>Iam furor humanum nostro de pectore sensum,</L>
<L>Expulit &amp; totum spirant praecordia Phaebum.</L></Q>
Which makes them so Sacred, and Holy, that they have
nothing of Integrity, or, indeed, of Humanity left in them.
I hope I shall not be thought impious any longer, upon
this Point; I mean for Vindicating Christian Religion
from the assaults of these Men, who, having the confidence
to believe, or at least profess themselves the only Instru∣ments
which God hath chosen, or can chuse, to teach and
reform the World (though they have neither Moral Ver∣tues,
nor Natural Parts, equal to other Men for the most
part) have by this pretence prevailed so far upon the com∣mon
sort of People, and upon some too of a better qua∣lity,
that they are perswaded their Salvation, or Eternal
Damnation, depends upon believing, or not believing of
what they say. I would not be understood to disswade any
from honouring the true Apostolical Teachers, when they
shall be re-established amongst us, or from allowing them
(even of right, and not of alms or courtesie) such Emolu∣ments
as may enable them cheerfully to perform the duties
of their Charge, to provide for their Children, and even
to use Hospitality, as they are commanded by St. <HI>Paul.</HI>
But this I will Prophesie before I conclude, that if Prin∣ces
shall perform this business by halves, and leave any
root of this Clergy, or Priest-craft, as it now is, in the
ground; or if that Famous Reformer, fled some years since
out of <HI>Picardy,</HI> to <HI>Geneva,</HI> who is of so great Renown for
Learning, and Parts, and who promises us so perfect a
Reformation, shall not in his Model wholly extirpate this
sort of Men; then I say I must foretell, that as well the
Magistrate, as this Workman, will find themselves
<PB N="29" REF="15"/>
deceived in their expectation, and that the least Fibra of
this Plant will overrun again the whole Vineyard of the
Lord, and turn to a diffusive Papacy in every Diocess,
perhaps in every Parish. So that God in his mercy in∣spire
them to cut out the Core of the Uulcer, and the
bag of this Impostume, that it may never ranckle, or fester
any more, nor break out hereafter, to diffuse new cor∣ruption
and putrefaction through the Body of Christ,
which is his Holy Church, nor to vitiate and infect the
good Order, and true Policy of Government. I come
now to the last branch of my Charge, which is, That I
teach Princes Villany, and and how to Enslave and Oppress
their Subjects: In which Accusation I am dealt with as
poor Messieur <HI>Agnolo Canini</HI> was, who, as they report,
being a very Learned Practiser of the Laws, and left the
only Man of this profession, one Autumn in our City,
the rest of the Advocates being fled into the Country for
fear of a Contagious Disease which then reigned, was
commanded by our Judges to assist with his Counsel
both Parties, and to draw Pleas as well for the De∣fendant,
as the Plaintiff, else the Courts of Justice must
have been shut up. In the same manner my Accusers
handle me, and make me first exhort and teach Subjects
to throw off their Princes, and then to instruct Monarchs
how to Enslave and Oppress them; but I did not expect
such ingratitude from mine own Citizens; or to be serv'd
as <HI>Moses</HI> was, when he was upbraided for killing the
<HI>Egyptian,</HI> by one of his own People, for whose sake he
had done it; whereas he believed they would have under∣stood
by that action, that he was the Person whom God
intended to make use of in delivering them from the hor∣rid
Slavery they were then under. If any Man will read
over my Book of the <HI>Prince</HI> with impartiality, and ordi∣nary
<PB N="30" REF="16"/>
Charity, he will easily perceive that it is not my
intention therein to recommend that Government, or
those Men there described, to the World; much less to
teach them to trample upon good Men, and all that is
Sacred and Venerable upon Earth; Laws, Religion, Ho∣nesty,
and what not.</P>
<P>If I have been a little too punctual in designing these
Monsters, and drawn them to the Life in all their Linea∣ments,
and Colours, I hope Mankind will know them, the
better to avoid them; my Treatise being both a Satyr a∣gainst
them, and a true Character of them. I speak no∣thing
of Great and Honourable Princes, as the Kings of
<HI>France, England,</HI> and others, who have the States and Or∣ders
of their Kingdoms, with excellent Laws and Costitu∣tions,
to found and maintain their Government; and who
reign over the Hearts, as well as the Persons of their Sub∣jects.
I treat only of those Vermine, bred out of the
corruption of our own small Commonwealth, and Cities,
or engender'd by the ill blasts that come from <HI>Rome,</HI> as
<HI>Olivarol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ da Fermo, Borgia,</HI> the <HI>Baglioni,</HI> the <HI>Bentivogli,</HI>
and a hundred others, who having had neither right, nor
honourable means to bring them to their power, use it with
more Violence, Rapine and Cruelty upon the poor People,
than those other Renowned Princes shew to the Boars,
the Wolves, the Foxes, and other Savage Beasts, which are
the Objects of their Chace and Hunting. Whosoever in
his Empire over Men is ty'd to no other Rules than those
of his own Will and Lust, must either be a Saint to mo∣derate
his Passions, or else a very Devil incarnate; or if
he be neither of these, both his Life and Reign are like
to be very short; for whosoever takes upon him so exe∣crable
an Employment, as to Rule Men against the Laws
of Nature, and of Reason, must turn all topsey turvy, and
<PB N="31" REF="16"/>
never stick at any thing; for if once he halt, he will fall,
and never rise again. I hope after this I need say little to
justify my self from the Calumny of advising these Mon∣sters
to break their Faith, since to keep it, is to lose their
Empire; Faithfulness and Sincerity being their mortal E∣nemies:
And <HI>Vguccione della Faggivola,</HI> to one who upbraid∣ed
him, that he never employ'd honest Men, answered,
honest Men will cut my throat; let the King use honest
Men, meaning the King of <HI>Naples,</HI> who was Established
in this Throne, and had right to it. But that I may
have occasion to justify my self against a little more
than I am accused of: I will confess, that in a Work,
where I desired to be a little more serious than I was in
this Book of the Prince, I did affirm, that in what way
soever Men defended their Country, whether by breaking
or keeping their Faith, it was ever well defended; not
meaning in a strict moral sence, or point of Honour; but
explaining my self, that, <HI>de facto,</HI> the infamy of the breach
of word would quickly be forgotten, and pardon'd by
the World, which is very true; nay, what if I had said
that good success in any Enterprize (a far less considera∣tion
than Piety to our Country) would have cancel'd the
blame of such a perfidy?</P>
<P>I might have alledged a thousand Examples for the
truth of this; to take one for all, we see the treachery
which <HI>Caesar</HI> (whom I compare to <HI>Cataline</HI>) used toward
his fellow Citizens; not only not detested by Posterity,
but even crowned with Renown, and immortal Fame,
insomuch as Princes to this day (as I have observed else∣where)
think it an honour to be compared to him, and
the highest pitch of Veneration their Flatterers can arrive
to, is to call them by the name of one who violated his
Faith, and Enslav'd his Country.</P>
<P><PB N="32" REF="17"/>I hope that in shewing as well these Tyrants, as the
poor People who are forced to live under them, their
danger; that is, by laying before the former, the hellish
and precipitous Courses, they must use to maintain their
Power; and by representing to the latter what they must
suffer, I may be Instrumental, first, to deter private
Citizens from attempting upon the Liberties of their
Country, or if they have done it, to make them lay down
their ill-gotten Authority, and then to warn the rest of
the Nobility and People from those Factions and Malignan∣cies
in their several Commonwealths and Governments,
which might give hope and opportunity to those who are
Ambitious amongst them, to aspire to an Empire over them.
However it prove, I hope I am no more to be blamed
for my attempt, than that Excellent Physician of our Na∣tion
is, who hath lately taken so much pains to compose
an excellent Treatise of that foul Disease, which was not
long since brought from the New World, into these
parts; wherein, though he be forced to use such expres∣sions
as are almost able to nauseate his Readers, and talk
of such Ulcers, Boils, Nodes, Botches, Cankers, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> that
are scarce fit to be repeated; especially when he handles
the Causes of those Effects; yet he did not intend to teach
or exhort Men to get this Disease, much less did he bring
this lamentable infirmity into the World; but describes it
faithfully as it is, to the end Men may be deterr'd, and a∣void
the being infected with it, and may discern and
Cure it, when ever their incontinence and folly shall pro∣cure
it them. I shall say no more in this matter, but, to
conclude all, make a protestation, that as well in this
Book, as in all my other Writings, my only scope and
design is to promote the interest and welfare of Man∣kind,
and the peace and quiet of the World; both which
<PB N="33" REF="17"/>
I am so vain as to believe, would be better obtained,
and provided for, if the Principles I lay down were
followed, and observed, by Princes and People, than they
are like to be by those Maximes which are in this Age
most in vogue.</P>
<P>For my self, I shall only say, (and call you all to Witness
for the Truth of it) that as by my Birth I am a Gentleman,
and of a Family which hath had many Chief Magistrates
of Justice in it; so I have been used in many Employ∣ments
of Great Trust, both in our City and Abroad, and
at this Hour, I am am not in my Estate one Penny the
better for them all nor should I have been, although I had
never suffered any Losses by the Seizure of my Estate, in
the Year 1531. For my Carriage, it hath ever been void
of Faction and Contention; I never had any Prejudice
against the House of <HI>Medici,</HI> but Honoured the Persons of
all those of that Family, whom I knew, and the Memory of
such of them as Liv'd before me, whom I acknowledge to have
been Excellent Patriots and Pillars of our City and Common∣wealth:
During the turbulent times of <HI>Piero,</HI> and after his
Expulsion out of <HI>Florence;</HI> though my Imployments were
but Ministerial, my Advice was ask'd in many Grave Mat∣ters,
which I ever delivered with Impartiality and Indiffe∣rence;
not espousing the Heady Opinions of any, much less
their Passions and Animosities, I never sided with any Party
further than that the Duty of my Charge oblig'd me to
serve the prevailing Party, when possest of the Govern∣ment
of our City; this I speak for those Changes which
happen'd between the Flight of the said <HI>Piero de Medici,</HI> and
the Horrid Parricide, committed by <HI>Clement</HI> the 7<HI>th</HI> upon
his Indulgent Mother, joyning with his greatest Enemies,
and uniting himself with those who had used the most Tran∣scendent
Insolence to his own Person, and the highest Vio∣lence
<PB N="34" REF="18"/>
and Fury the Sun ever saw, to his poor Courtiers and
Subjects; that so accompany'd, he might Sheath his Sword
in the Bowels of his own Desolate Country. At that time,
and during that whole Siege, I must confess, I did break the
Confines of my Neutrality, and not only Acted as I was
commanded barely, but rouz'd my self, and stirr'd up others,
Haranguing (in the streets and places of the City) the Peo∣ple
to defend, with the last drop of their Blood, the Walls
of their Country, and the Liberty of their Government,
taking very hazardous Journeys to <HI>Ferruccio,</HI> and the rest,
into the <HI>Mugello</HI> and other parts, to bring in Succours and
Provisions to our languishing City; and Acting as a Sol∣dier
(which was a new Profession to me) at the Age of a∣bove
Sixty, when others are Dispenced from it. For all
which I had so intire a Satisfaction in my Mind and Con∣science,
that I am perswaded this Cordial made me able to
support the Sufferings which befell me after our Catastrophe,
and to rejoyce in them so far, that all the Malice and Cru∣elty
of our Enemies, could never draw one word from me
unsuitable to the Honour I thought I merited, and did in
some sort enjoy, for being instrumental to defend (as long
as it was possible) our Altars and our Hearths. But all that
I have undergone, hath been abundantly Recompenced to
me, by the Favour and Courtesie of the Most Excellent
<HI>Seigneur Cosimo,</HI> who hath been pleas'd to offer me all the
Preferments the greatest Ambition could aspire to; which
I did not refuse, out of any scruple to serve so incomparable a
Prince, whose Early Years manifest so much Courage, Hu∣manity,
and Prudence, and so Fatherly a care of the Pub∣lick
Good, but because I was very desirous not to ac∣cept
of a Charge which I was not able to perform,
my Years and Infirmities having now brought me to a
Condition, in which I am fitter to live in a Cloyster
<PB N="35" REF="18"/>
than a Palace; and made me good for nothing but to
talk of past times, the common Vice of Old Age; so
that I did not think it Just or Grateful, to Reward this
Excellent Person so ill for his Kindness, as to give him
an useless Servant, and to fill up the place of a far better.
This is all I think fit to say of this matter: I chuse to
address it to you <HI>Messieur Zenobio,</HI> for the constant Friend∣ship
I have ever Entertain'd with you, and formerly with
your Deceased Father, the Companion of my Studies,
and Ornament of our City. And so I bid you Fare∣well.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE>This 1st <HI>of</HI> April 1537.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

