<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="3">An appendix to the late antidote against idolatry Wherein the true and adequate notion or definition of idolatry is proposed. Most instances of idolatry in the Roman Church thereby examined. Sundry uses in the Church of England cleared. With some serious monitions touching spiritual idolatry thereunto annexed.</TITLE><AUTHOR>More, Henry, 1614-1687.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A51287</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing M2642</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R223783</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99834062</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99834062</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">38541</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A51287)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38541)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1837:4)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="3">An appendix to the late antidote against idolatry Wherein the true and adequate notion or definition of idolatry is proposed. Most instances of idolatry in the Roman Church thereby examined. Sundry uses in the Church of England cleared. With some serious monitions touching spiritual idolatry thereunto annexed.</TITLE><AUTHOR>More, Henry, 1614-1687.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 59, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>printed by I. R. for Walter Kettilby, at the Sign of the Bishops-Head in St. Pauls Church-yard,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>MDCLXXII,</DATE>
<DATE>1673.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Signatures: A⁴ B-D E⁶.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original at the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Catholic Church. --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2002-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A51287">
<STC T="W">M2642</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99834062</BIBNO>
<VID>38541</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>AN APPENDIX To the late Antidote against IDOLATRY.</P>
<P>WHEREIN The true and adequate Notion or Definition of Idolatry is proposed.</P>
<P>Most Instances of Idolatry in the Roman Church thereby examined.</P>
<P>Sundry uses in the Church of England Cleared.</P>
<P>With some serious Monitions touching Spiritual Idolatry thereunto annexed.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>I. R.</HI> for <HI>Walter Kettilby,</HI> at the Sign of the <HI>Bishops-Head</HI> in St. <HI>Pauls Church-yard,</HI> 1673.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Reader,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I Shall not wonder if thou be at a loss, what to impute this my so sudden appear∣ing in publick again upon the same Subject, for I must con∣fess, I my self am in some sort at a loss what to impute it to. Whether to the excess of my zeal in a cause of so great im∣portance, or to my impatience to be freed from these Polemi∣cal Engagements, which are not so suitable to my Genius. But so far as I know my own meaning it is both. And there∣fore having since my last by
<PB REF="3"/>
further converse with either books or men, discovered, as I conceive, the utmost that can be said touching the point be∣twixt Me and my Antagonist, for the more timely assisting so weighty a truth, and for the freeing my self from any fu∣ture trouble, I have here afore∣hand obviated whatever I can suspect he may return as materi∣al, in answer to my Reply. This it may be, may save us both any further labour, at least it will my self. For I profess my self to have neither hope nor ability of satisfying others by any o∣ther evidences, than by which I find my self so fully and clearly satisfied.</P>
<P>That I have vindicated some
<PB REF="3"/>
uses in our own Church from all suspicions of Idolatry, is but what I owe to her, as a professed member of her body, and to the honour and memory of our pious and judicious Refor∣mers. That I have annexed some few Monitions touching <HI>spiritual</HI> Idolatry, is for the rescu∣ing my self also from the im∣putation of an over Bigotical zeal against the <HI>external</HI> or <HI>ritual.</HI> For I am abundantly aware how little the avoyding the <HI>out∣ward</HI> or <HI>ritual</HI> Idolatry will avail to salvation unless we also seri∣ously endeavour to purify our selves from the <HI>inward</HI> or <HI>spiritual,</HI> without which purity no man shall see God. But in pretence of cleansing our selves from
<PB REF="4"/>
the <HI>inward,</HI> to make nothing of the <HI>outward,</HI> is the fruit of that false spirit that appeared in the <HI>Gnosticks</HI> of old, and has expresly showed it self in these latter times, amongst some high flown <HI>Enthusiasts,</HI> who have had the boldness to declare that there is no such thing as <HI>external</HI> Ido∣latry. Which is spoken with as much soundness of truth, as if they should declare, That there is no such thing neither as <HI>out∣ward</HI> Murder, Adultery, Perju∣rie, and Blasphemie. But our blessed Saviour, that infallible example of life, has taught us a better lesson of fulfilling all righteousness. And they that will be externally wicked, what have they but their own vain
<PB REF="4"/>
boast to witness their integri∣ty? That God would deliver thee and my self and all men, from all manner of Hypocrisie, that we may injoy God in the simplicity of Heart and a good Conscience, to our present and everlasting comfort, is the earn∣est desire of</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Thine in the love of the Truth,</HI> H. More.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>Errata sic corrige.</HEAD>
<P><HI>PAge</HI> 23. Line 20. for <HI>chance,</HI> r. <HI>shame.</HI> p. 24. l. 6. for <HI>mind,</HI> r. <HI>mine,</HI> p 25. l. 16. r. <HI>fouly.</HI> p. 26. l. 17. r. <HI>real.</HI> p, 29. l. 22. r. <HI>it is.</HI> p. 32. l. 13. r. <HI>be, commensu∣rate.</HI> p. 37. l. 26. for <HI>mind</HI> r. <HI>mine.</HI> p. 38. l. 29. r. <HI>bis bounty.</HI> p. 40. l. 28. for <HI>dispute,</HI> r. <HI>dispell.</HI> p. 45. l. 27. for <HI>a motion,</HI> r. <HI>admotion.</HI> p. 48. l. 28. r. <HI>at the name.</HI> p. 54. .l 24. r. <HI>live we as.</HI> p. 55. l. <HI>penult. for they</HI> r. <HI>these.</HI> p. 59. l. 8. r. 1 <HI>John</HI> 5.20.21.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="appendix">
<PB N="1" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>AN APPENDIX To the late Antidote against IDOLATRY.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>I.</HI> A brief account of his proceeding in his Antidote against Idolatry.</HEAD>
<P>I Have already, in my <HI>Antidote against Idolatry,</HI> with sufficient useful evidence and certain∣ty discovered what is and ought to be held to be idolatry amongst Christians; but in such a way, that I only exhibited several cases or instances of Idolatry, and proved them some∣times, rather by Testimony either Divine, or the common suffrage of men, I mean such as are Christians, than from the intrinsick general No∣tion of Idolatry, not at all intended to be propo∣sed in that Treatise; that method I then took, be∣ing sufficient for the use and purpose then aimed at, which was to convince the World by plain and obvious Arguments, what things professed and
<PB N="2" REF="6"/>
practised in the Roman Church might justly be esteemed Idolatrous.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>II.</HI> The definition of Idolatry with the useful∣ness thereof.</HEAD>
<P>But now for the greater satisfaction of the more curious and Philosophical Genius, out of those several instances in the abovesaid Treatise, I shall draw one common Notion or Definition, both true and adaequate, which will be a certain measure whereby we may expeditely understand whatever is truly Idolatry, and what not. For, it is plain, that to whatsoever the Definition be∣longs, the thing defined belongs to the same, and to whatsoever the Definition does not belong, the thing defined cannot belong to it. Of so great importance is it therefore to propose a true and adaequate Definition of Idolatry. Which I con∣ceive is this; <HI>Cultus superstitiosus quo peculiaritates Divinae violantur.</HI> Idolatry is a kind of supersti∣tious worship, whereby the peculiarities of the Godhead are violated. There is no kind nor act of Idolatry which will not fall under this general Notion, nor any kind or act of <HI>Ritual</HI> worship that falls under it, that is not Idolatry, as will more plainly appear after our explication thereof.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>III.</HI> The explication of the Definition.</HEAD>
<P>As for the Term defined, <HI>Idolatry,</HI> there is no man so unskilfull, (though according to the Notation of the word, it signifies properly the worship of an Image or Idol,) as to think that to be the adaequate sense of Idolatry, since they that worship the Sun are acknowledged to be Idolaters,
<PB N="3" REF="6"/>
though they worship him without an Image; And therefore that scruple passed over, nothing hinders but that the Notion of Idolatry may be as large, as the proposed Definition, which is, <HI>superstitious worship whereby the peculiarities of the Godhead are violated.</HI> I add <HI>superstitious</HI> to <HI>worship,</HI> that the <HI>Genus</HI> may be the more <HI>immediate</HI>; and by <HI>supersti∣tious,</HI> I understand <HI>pseudoreligious,</HI> if I may so speak, that is false, or depraved religious worship: And I name <HI>no object,</HI> because I would not restrain it to any one kind of object, but be the pretence of worshipping God, Saints, Angels, or what ever object else, when it is in such a way, as that the Divine peculiarities are violated, that is Idolatry according to this Definition. Superstitious wor∣ship therefore is the <HI>Genus</HI> of the Definition, what remains, the <HI>difference,</HI> viz <HI>whereby the peculiari∣ties of the Godhead are violated.</HI> I am fain to make use of this more general and abstract term, <HI>peculi∣arities,</HI> that it may comprehend whatever things are peculiar to God, whether his <HI>Attributes</HI> or <HI>Rites</HI> chosen and appropriate to his own worship, which his own <HI>choice</HI> is enough to make peculiar to him, though closely look't into, they may have also a <HI>natural</HI> significancy of those excellencies that are proper to the Godhead. Such are the having a Temple and a Symbolical presence e∣rected for invocation and worship, praying be∣fore that Symbolical presence, having incense burnt before it, and Lamps or Candles light up, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> These and the like were the modes that God made choice of, to signify the honour and
<PB N="4" REF="7"/>
worship due to himself, and therefore to use them to any else, is a violation of his peculiarities. For by the <HI>violation of the peculiarities of the Godhead,</HI> I understand any kind of prophanation or vilification of them, either by obscuring or lessening of them in himself, or else by communicating of them to others. As to set up such a Symbolical pre∣sence to be worshipped towards, as pretends to <HI>represent</HI> God, who is <HI>irrepresentable,</HI> as being infinite in Majesty and Greatness, this were to lessen, obscure, or indeed to abolish the infinite glorious Majesty of God, which is peculiar to him, and so to make an Idol of him, and therefore were gross Idolatry. But to erect a Symboli∣cal presence to a Creature, that is Idolatry upon the other score, it implying Omnipresence or Omnipercipience to be in that Creature.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>IV.</HI> What a Symbolical presence is.</HEAD>
<P>For, a Symbolical presence is nothing else but <HI>some figure or imagerie, instituted or erected for the invoking of supplicating, or any way religiously worshipping that invisible Power or Spirit for whom it is erected or made.</HI> So that in brief, all Idolatry is such as either turns God into an Idol, or turns an Idol, that is, the Creature we give religious worship to, in some respect, into a God, in give∣ing it something which is peculiar unto him.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>V.</HI> That that religious worship of Daemons which was truly Idolatry, was really Divine.</HEAD>
<P>Whence for the utter taking away all litigi∣ousness about terms, That <HI>religious</HI> worship which misapplyed or given to any Creature constitutes
<PB N="5" REF="7"/>
Idolatry, may rightly and truly be also called <HI>Di∣vine</HI>; and is so, if it make the act Idolatry: for that implyes that it violates some <HI>peculiarity</HI> of the Godhead, and attributes it to the Creature, which is, as to that respect, to make a God of it. And such Divine worship as this was, that which the Heathens gave to their Daemons, though they took it to be only religious, and such as did not appertain peculiarly to God himself; as is parti∣cularly observable in the <HI>Platonists,</HI> whom yet neither St. <HI>Austin,</HI> nor any other serious Christi∣an will stick to conclude to have been Idolaters in their Daemon-worship. And therefore, if we will but use <HI>just weights</HI> and <HI>measures,</HI> whatever Chri∣stians do the like things to Saints and Angels, pre∣tending it is not <HI>Divine</HI> worship, but an inferiour <HI>religious</HI> worship, they must be also judged to com∣mit Idolatry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>VI.</HI> The way of convincing the Romanists of I∣dolatry in this Treatise.</HEAD>
<P>And this was one way of convincing the Ro∣man Church of their Idolatries. But laying aside all these more exteriour and obvious Arguments, we will deal now more precisely and Philosophically, and argue only from the most intrinsecal and essen∣tial <HI>Topick</HI> in all <HI>Logick,</HI> and examine the Roman Idolatries by the inmost Notion and Definition of the Thing, shewing that even that which seems to be only by Divine Declaration Idolatry, is also, if more rationally considered, Idolatry according to the proposed Definition.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="part">
<PB N="6" REF="8"/>
<HEAD><HI>VII.</HI> That the forbidding to worship God by an Image, is the natural sense of the second Commandement.</HEAD>
<P>As the worshipping God by an Image, is plainly declared Idolatry by God himself in the second Commandement, <HI>Thou shalt not make to thy self any graven Image,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>Thou shalt not bow down to it, nor worship it,</HI> &amp;c. The bowing down to and worshipping a graven Image, though in pretence to worship God thereby, is plainly prohibited by this Commandement. For the prohibition of worshipping any other God, is sufficiently evident in the first Commandement, <HI>Thou shalt have no o∣ther Gods but me.</HI> Whereby he pronounces that he alone will be worshipped: whence it naturally follows, that this next precept is at least chiefly a∣bout the purity and congruity of his own worship, forbidding to worship him by any Image, in bow∣ing to it, or worshiping it, though in reference to himself. This is the most natural, and indeed the necessary sense of this precept, if we consider the extream incredibility of any other senses, that are offered, or can be offered.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>VIII.</HI> All other senses plainly impossible and incredible.</HEAD>
<P>For let us suppose first, that the sense is, <HI>Thou shalt not bow down to, nor worship the graven Image (that thou makest and settest up,) thou shalt not worship the Image it self instead of God or for God.</HI> It would be a prohibition of a thing even impossible to hu∣mane Nature to do: that a Jew suppose should worship an Image that himself has made of some
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
log of wood or stone, instead of or for the God that brought him out of the land of <HI>Egypt,</HI> and the house of Bondage, &amp; indeed that created the whole World, as if he could take the Image for this God, and not worship it in reference to him. How nugatorious would they make the Divine Law-giver by such a prohibition, to interdict those things which it is impossible for men to doe? And now let us suppose the other sense of the pre∣cept to be, (and I can neither meet with nor devise any more,) <HI>Thou shalt not make to thy self any Idol,</HI> that is to say, no Image of any Heathen God or of any false God whatsoever; that this cannot be the chief∣ly intended sense thereof is plain. First, from the apparent superfluity of this precept, that being so strictly and apertly interdicted before, <HI>viz.</HI> That they should have no Pagan gods, nor any gods whatever besides <HI>Jehovah.</HI> Which while they hold to, it is impossible they should make to themselves any Images or Idols of those gods to bow down to or worship. So that this prohibition would be su∣perfluous, if that was the only meaning of the commandement. And then in the second place, this sense is incoherent with the words following; <HI>For I am a jealous God.</HI> Which implyes suspicion of some foul dealing betwixt any Member of his Spouse, the Church, and Himself; that they may communicate any thing of that which is peculiarly due to himself unto another. But if the Jews should make an Idol, that is, the Image of some Pagan God, and worship it, the mat∣ter would be past suspicion, they would apertly and
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
professedly be found false to <HI>Jehovah,</HI> and to commit Adultery with another God.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>IX.</HI> The golden Calf no intended Image of <HI>A∣pis,</HI> but the Symbolical presence of <HI>Jehovah.</HI></HEAD>
<P>To which you may add in the third place, that God himself has thus interpreted this commande∣ment, that he will not be worshipped by an Image, though erected and worshipped in reference to himself; as is most undeniably plain in the golden Calf which <HI>Aaron</HI> made, which was not intended for the Image of <HI>Apis</HI> the <HI>AEgyptian</HI> God, but was the Symbolical presence of <HI>Jehovah.</HI> Indeed St. <HI>Steven</HI> sayes, Act. 7.39, 40. <HI>And in their hearts they turned back again into Aegypt,</HI> (it may be in the grossest sense if they could have brought <HI>Aaron</HI> to their lure) <HI>saying unto</HI> Aaron, <HI>make us Gods to go before us.</HI> But it is most likely, that this is only a reprehension of their <HI>AEgyptianizing</HI> in matters of Religion, desiring to have some visi∣ble Object and Figure to sustain their Faith, and spend their Devotion on, according to the mode of <HI>AEgypt,</HI> who gave Divine worship to Images. This mode of Religion their minds hanker'd after, as their mouths elsewhere watered after the flesh∣pots of <HI>AEgypt,</HI> for which they are also taxed, <HI>Psal.</HI> 106.19. <HI>They made a Calf in Horeb, and worshipped the Molten Image. Thus they changed their glory,</HI> that is, the God of <HI>Israel,</HI> or his Divine presence, <HI>into the Similitude of an Ox that eateth grass.</HI> As if <HI>Iehovah</HI> the Almighty, Infinite and Eternal God, that did such <HI>great things in</HI> Aegypt, <HI>wonderous works in the land of</HI> Ham, <HI>and fearful things by
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
the Red-sea,</HI> could be representable by any such fi∣gure. So that in this <HI>they quite forgat God their Saviour,</HI> both what an excellent being he is, and utterly irrepresentable by Imagery, and forgat his commandement (which is one special and mate∣rial way of forgetting him) <HI>Thou shalt not make to thy self any graven Image, thou shalt not bow down to it, nor worship it.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>X.</HI> That the History of the golden Calf plainly implyes that sense thereof.</HEAD>
<P>But there is no place so convincing, that the golden Calf which <HI>Aaron</HI> made, was made and worshipped in reference to <HI>Iehovah,</HI> as what oc∣curres in the very History. God had promised to the people, he would send an Angel before them to keep them in the way, <HI>Exod.</HI> 23.10. This the People knowing and despairing of <HI>Moses</HI> being found again, or impatient of his stay so long in the Mount, (which St. <HI>Steven</HI> interprets a rejecting of <HI>Moses,</HI> or putting him from them, <HI>Act.</HI> 7.39. for that is spoken of <HI>Moses,</HI> not of God) they come to <HI>Aaron,</HI> (<HI>Exod.</HI> 32.) and say unto him, <HI>Vp make us Gods which shall goe be∣fore us,</HI> which <HI>Aaron</HI> immediately assents to, and receiving their ear-rings, made a molten Calf of them, whereupon they said, <HI>These are thy Gods O Isra∣el, which brought thee out of the land of Aegypt.</HI> And <HI>Aaron</HI> built an Altar before this Image which himself had made, and made proclamation and said, <HI>To morrow is a feast to the Lord,</HI> that is, to <HI>Jehovah.</HI> And on the morrow, according to this procla∣mation, they celebrate the Feast, and of∣fered
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
burnt offerings <HI>&amp;c.</HI> to this Image. Now let any unprejudiced man judge to whom this symbolical presence could be erected but to <HI>Jehovah.</HI> Did not the Israelites ask of <HI>Aaron</HI> what God had promised? the Angel in whom God would place his Name there? Did <HI>Aaron</HI> at all stick to fulfill their desire? Do not the People say of this symbolical presence, <HI>These are thy Gods O Israel,</HI> or which is all one, <HI>This is thy God O Israel,</HI> (as <HI>Nehemiah</HI> has it <HI>Chap.</HI> 9. <HI>v.</HI> 18.) <HI>that brought thee out of the Land of Aegypt,</HI> which is utterly impossible for them to understand of the golden Calf which was but newly made, and therefore is necessarily understood of that God that brought them out of <HI>AEgypt,</HI> which is <HI>Jehovah,</HI> no Aegypti∣an Deity, but he that brought all those Plagues on <HI>AEgypt</HI> and delivered his People with an high hand. And lastly, is not an Altar built before the same symbolical presence, and a feast proclaim∣ed there to be celebrated to the Lord? What more perspicuous coherence can be desired for the cer∣tainty of the sense of any passage of Scripture?</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="11" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XI.</HI> The gross repugnancies impli'd in supposing the Calf to be the symbolical presence of the God <HI>Apis.</HI></HEAD>
<P>All things run smooth on this Hypothesis. But supposing this Calf the Symbolical Presence of <HI>Apis</HI> an Aegyptian Deity, who had the form of an Ox, (which might give some of the Antients oc∣casion, as I suppose, to think it was so, they not considering that <HI>Cherub</HI> also signifies an Ox or Calf, and that one of the Angelical forms in the
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
Chariot of God is both an Ox, and is called a Cherub, and that the Cherubins in the Ark were of this figure, which is a symbol of the Angels, who are the Chariot of God, <HI>Psal.</HI> 68▪ 17. <HI>The Chariots of God are twenty thousands, even thousands of Angels, and the Lord among them as in Sinai in the holy place,</HI> where this Chariot or Chariots (be∣cause it consisted of four parts) was seen by <HI>Aaron,</HI> like that by <HI>Ezekiel,</HI> where one part had the form of an Ox or Calf, and all four the feet of Oxen. So little estranged is the form of an Ox or Calf from the use of representing the presence of the God of Israel,) but suppose, I say, it is not the symbolical presence of Jehovah, but of the Aegyptian <HI>Apis,</HI> according to the conceit of some out of the respect they bear to the Fathers, what an harsh and intolerable reproach is it in the mean time to Gods High Priest, to affirm that he did thus profanely and impiously make an <HI>AEgyptian Idol</HI> for the <HI>People of God</HI> to worship, and so assisted them in the grosly breaking of both the first and second Commandement at once, and even then when the People did but desire the promise to be made good to them, that the visible presence of God, or his Angel in whom his Name was, might go along with them, and that <HI>Aaron</HI> notwith∣standing instead of this, should make the symbo∣lical presence of a forraign God! Besides that the people themselves had not this judgment of it, they declaring it to be the symbolical presence of him that brought them out of the Land of <HI>AEgypt.</HI> Nor could they possibly believe the Aegyptian <HI>Apis</HI>
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
to have done so, to have inflicted all those plagues on his own Land in the behalf of a forraign peo∣ple. Besides that they were all along declared by <HI>Moses</HI> to be done in the Name of the God of <HI>Israel</HI>: to whom also <HI>Aaron</HI> builds an Altar before this Calf, and proclaimes a Feast to <HI>Jehovah,</HI> which, if by this Calf were meant the <HI>AEgyptian Apis,</HI> would be as repugnant, as to say, <HI>Apis</HI> and <HI>Jehovah</HI> are all one.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="12" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XII.</HI> The Certainty hence, that the second Com∣mandement forbids the worshipping God by an Image.</HEAD>
<P>Wherefore we can be of nothing more sure than that this Golden Calf of <HI>Cherub</HI> was erected by <HI>Aaron</HI> to <HI>Jehovah,</HI> and so understood by the People. The worshipping whereof notwithstanding is a∣greed on all sides to have been Idolatry. From whence it plainly follows, that the second Com∣mandement forbids the worshipping God by an Image, which was the thing to be proved Nor do I know by what evasions those of the contrary o∣pinion can escape the clearness of this proof and precept. God so plainly interpreting the meaning of his own Law, by his severe vengeance on the worshippers of the golden Calf, though erected to himself.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="13" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XIII.</HI> Two evasions to shun this sense, The first from the <HI>Septuagints</HI> Translation of <HI>Pesel</HI> proposed and answered.</HEAD>
<P>The best and most ordinary evasions are these two. The first that the <HI>Septuagint</HI> translating <HI>Pe∣sel</HI> not <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Sculptile,</HI> but <HI>Idolum,</HI> do plainly
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
enough insinuate, that an Image to the true God is not there forbid for worship but Idols only, or Images, of the Heathen Gods, or any false Gods. But those that argue thus do not consider that <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> in Greek is of as indifferent and large a signification as <HI>Imago</HI> in Latin, or Image in Eng∣lish. <HI>Plotinus,</HI> when he was desired to sit to have his Picture drawn, said, he would not have them give themselves the trouble of making <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, an Image of an Image, or Shadow of a Sha∣dow. So that we way with better reason ima∣gine the <HI>Septuagint</HI> to have chosen this word as an universal Bar against not only <HI>Statue-worship,</HI> but even <HI>Picture-worship</HI> also: Or to have made choice of <HI>Idolon,</HI> rather than <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Sculptile,</HI> because it signifieth more determinately such <HI>Sculptilia</HI> as are Images, or have Imagery on them, that they should not be bowed to in a religious way; not for∣bidding to direct their worship towards every thing that is carved, when it does not at all pretend to make God <HI>representable,</HI> as Imagery does. So that there being these Reasons so obvious, why the <HI>Sep∣tuagint</HI> might Translate <HI>Pesel</HI> Idolon, rather than <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Sculptile,</HI> the inferring they did it in reference to the Idols of the Heathen, is of no force.</P>
<P>And besides, suppose that <HI>Pesel</HI> signifies an Idol, in the sense of the adverse party; what do they get by it, when as the text then will run thus, <HI>Thou shalt not make to thy self any Idol or Image of any Heathen God, nor the likeness of any thing that is in Heaven above, or in the earth beneath,
<PB N="14" REF="12"/>
thou shalt not bow down to them, nor worship them.</HI> It is manifest that yet for all this all manner of Image-worship, or Picture-worship is forbidden; not only of the Heathen Gods, but all whatsoe∣ver, and therefore they cannot be worshipped, no not in reference to the true God himself. Or if you would understand the following words, <HI>viz. Nor the likeness of any thing in Heaven a∣bove, &amp;c.</HI> still of the Heathen Gods Images, (which is perfectly illogical, and impossible for any one that attends to reason to admit, the object of the precept being plainly here distributed in∣to two parts. The first part the Idols or Ima∣ges of the Heathen Gods, the other whatever other similitudes or Images besides:) Yet if these words could be drawn to the same sense with the other, so that the Images of the Heathen Gods, or any false Gods might be understood by them, and that the whole prohibition were concer∣ning such like Images or Idols, that would also not∣withstanding clash with the next words following, <HI>For I am a jealous God</HI>▪ For in this case, as I noted above, the matter would be beyond jealousie, it would be a confessed act of spiritual Adultery, w<SUP>ch</SUP> is Idolatry. But to Argue from the mention of Gods jealousie, that the Image must be meant of some strange God, (for what Husband would be jealous of his Wife, for honouring or kissing his own picture?) that is no more than a witty sophism built upon a false Hypothesis; as if the mans picture could as easily rob the man of what is due to him from his Wife, as an Image rob God
<PB N="15" REF="12"/>
of what is due to him. For the Image being visible, &amp; God invisible, there is manifest danger of joyning ones devotion, which is all that God can have of us, to the garish Image, more than to God, and the true Notion of him in our minds; and that by worshipping Him in such a vile manner, we may be brought off afterwards to worship other Gods, as mean as we have made him by this sort of worship.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="14" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XIIII.</HI> The second evasion touching the Cheru∣bins on the Mercy-seat, proposed and an∣swered.</HEAD>
<P>The next evasion, which seems most conside∣rable, is, in that they pretend that God himself has interpreted his own Law to another sense than we would have, in commanding golden Cherubins to be set on the Mercy-seat for his own worship. This excuse is very trite a∣mongst the <HI>Romanists,</HI> and the second Council of <HI>Nice</HI> alledges the same, but it is plain that it falls exceeding short of the case. For the scope of the second Commandement is not the forbidding all Image-work in the places of worship, but the bowing to Images and worshipping them, which the case of the Cherubins does not reach. For the people was never commanded to bow down to or worship the golden Cherubins, nor do the Jews profess themselves to have done so, but to have bowed down to and worshipped God alone. And besides that they were not intended for an Object of the Peoples worship or adoration is plain, in that they were carefully hid from their
<PB N="16" REF="13"/>
sight. And if they could penetrate with their imagination through the vail, and make them∣selves present hard by the Cherubins, their po∣sture plainly shows they were never intended to be worshipped, their faces not being turned to∣wards the People to receive their salutations, but towards one another. Indeed if they were an object, that it was their declared duty to worship, when they saw them, the same religious affection may be conceived to be directed towards them through the vail. But formal adoration to a visi∣ble object while it is hid and made invisible, is, methinks, as uncouth and unnatural, as the bow∣ing to some Person on the other side a brick∣wall, in which there is not the least loop-hole to see thorough. <UNCLEAR>Wherefore</UNCLEAR> there being no pre∣cept to the people of the Jews, to bow down to the golden Cherubins, and to worship them, nor it being any professed practice of them, and the posture of the Cherubins being such as intimates they were not made to be worshipped by them, and they being carefully hid from the eyes of the people that they might not see them, (though they were symbols of the special presence of God, and Notes or Instruments for the directing their adoration thitherward to God in a special man∣ner there present) it is evident they were no ob∣ject of the peoples worship, and that they were neither to bow down to them, nor worship them, though they bowed toward them, as a determina∣tive circumstance of their worship of God. This is so plain, that I believe no man that considers it
<PB N="17" REF="13"/>
can have the confidence to deny it. <HI>viz.</HI> That the Cherubins were not the object of the Peoples worship, much less intended so by God.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="15" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XV.</HI> A difficulty touching the High Priests bowing in the Holy of Holies proposed.</HEAD>
<P>But the great difficulty, as it seems to some, is, how the High Priest, when he went into the Holy of Holies, (which he did once by the year,) and bowed as they conceive before these Cherubins bare and open to his sight, could so behave himself as not to be guilty of bowing to graven Images and worshipping them. Which if he did, I must confess that the Romanists have no contemptible plea for their interpretation of the second Commandement, as if it were not against worshipping the true God by an Image. But to this difficulty I answer these two wayes.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="16" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XVI.</HI> The first way of answering it, by deny∣ing the fact, if it could not be done without bowing towards the Cherubins as an object.</HEAD>
<P>First, that if the High Priest when he was in the Holy of Holies, could not bow to worship God by that gesture, but he must also bow to∣wards the Cherubins <HI>objectively,</HI> and not meerly <HI>circumstantially,</HI> I do flatly deny that he did bovv there. And they can never prove that he did, there being no mention thereof in the Scripture, vvhere his behaviour in that place is described▪ <HI>Levit.</HI> 16. But there being a plain prohibition in the second Commandement to bovv to graven Images and to vvorship them, it is from hence demonstrable that the High Priest in this case
<PB N="18" REF="14"/>
would not. For if <HI>to obey be better than sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of Rams,</HI> 1 <HI>Sam</HI> 15.22. certainly the High Priest could not but see that obedience to so plain and strict a commande∣ment, as <HI>Thou shalt not bow down to any graven Images, nor worship them,</HI> &amp;c. was better than the breaking that command under pretence of wor∣shipping God by bowing unto them, namely to the Cherubins. Wherefore we may be certain that in this case he would not bow towards them. But if he could bow towards them without in∣curring this danger, the difficulty is taken away, and the true sense of the second Commande∣ment remains firm and inviolable; that God him∣self is not to be worshipped by an Image, by bowing to it and worshipping it.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="17" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XVII.</HI> The second way by asserting that he might bow in such circumstances, as that the Cherubins were no object of his wor∣ship.</HEAD>
<P>But now besides this, in the second place, if any one think it so probable that the High Priest did bow some time towards the Mercy Seat, when he was in the Holy of Holyes, let us pitch upon that which is most likely, namely when he made his nearer approach thereto, to besprinkle it with blood: it is manifest there is no colour of saying, that in these circumstances he bowed to or worshipped the Cherubins.</P>
<P N="1">1. Because the first thing that he was to do, when he was to enter within the vail, <HI>was to take a censure full of burning coales of fire, &amp; his hands full
<PB N="19" REF="14"/>
of sweet incense beaten small, and to bring them within the vail, and to put the incense on the fire before the Lord, that the cloud of the incense may cover the Mercy seat that is upon the testimonie, that he die not. Levit.</HI> 16.12, 13. Which is a sign that he was not to dare so much as to look towards the Mer∣cy seat, much less to worship towards it, till all on the Mercy seat, the golden Cherubins and all were hid in a cloud of incense, which is like the hiding of them from the sight of the Peo∣ple by the vail. And that therefore their golden luster was to be no object of worship, as being thus enveloped with smoak, not to be seen at any distance.</P>
<P N="2">2. But now, when the High Priest approaches up nearer to the Mercy seat, which we have supposed the more likely time of worshipping, let us see what possibility there is of his appear∣ing guilty of worshipping the Cherubins, though he should then bow towards the Throne of God, more than in that former circumstance. For the two Cherubins were placed at the two ends of the Mercy seat, and that with their faces one to∣wards another, not to any that came up to the Mercy seat, which is no fit posture to be wor∣shipped in, if they could be seen by any glimme∣rings in this thick Cloud of smoak. And if they could, they would be only a direction to the High Priest, as well to overlook them, as to give them a go by, in following that intimation God has given him in <HI>Exodus,</HI> Chap. 25. <HI>And
<PB N="20" REF="15"/>
there will I meet with thee, and I will commune with thee from above the Mercy seat, from between the two Cherubins, which are upon the Ark of the Testi∣mony.</HI> And in the Psalms he is described sitting betwixt the two Cherubins, <HI>Psalm</HI> 8.1. and 99.1. This is a plain case then, that the High Priest could not but conceive that special presence of God to be seated betwixt the two Cherubins, and therefore directing his devotion and gesture according to that instruction, his bowing must be towards that presence, betwixt the two Che∣rubins, from the Mercy seat upwards; as if the invisible Majesty was seated there as on a Throne or Chair of state. The bowing to whom can no more concern the Cherubins, than the bow∣ing to a Prince on a wide Throne or Chair can concern the imagery on the arms of the Chair a∣dorned, suppose, with two Eagles heads or the like. Can any one conceit any worship done to these two Eagles heads, when the Parties bowing is directed to the face and Person of the Prince above, and betwixt the Eagles heads; though the Eagles heads stand in a fairer posture to be bowed to, than the faces of the Cherubins. It is therefore every way plain and manifest, that as the People of the Jews did not, so neither did their High Priest bow to, or in any sense wor∣ship the Cherubins in their bowing thitherward, but only him that sat betwixt the Cherubins, which was the thing to be demonstrated. And that therefore there is no evasion left to elude the force of the second commandement, that
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
so strictly prohibits the worship of the true God by any graven Image, which therefore according to the sense of that Commandement must be I∣dolatry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="18" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XVIII.</HI> The Idolatry forbidden in the second Commandement, reduced to the proposed definition of Idolatry.</HEAD>
<P>It remains now that we reduce this kind of I∣dolatry, (as we in order shall also do all the rest,) to our general definition of Idolatry, that it may appear to be so, even according to the plain Nature and Notion of the thing, namely, in that by worshipping God by an Image the peculi∣arities of the Godhead are violated, which seems evident here upon a double score, both from making the infinite irrepresentable Divine Ma∣jesty representable by an Animal-Figure, which debases and vilifies the peculiar excellency of the Godhead, which is so infinitely beyond any visi∣ble form whatsoever, and therefore no Animal Figure can pretend to be the representative there∣of; as also from the giving Divine worship to these Animal Figures, or Symbolical presences, which is peculiar to God.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="19" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XIX.</HI> No distinction betwixt Hieroglyphical and representative Images when Divine wor∣ship is done to them.</HEAD>
<P>Which Divine worship does plainly argue them representative Figures, not meerly Hiero∣glyphical, whether they that worship them will call them so or no. As is apparent from the first of the <HI>Romans,</HI> where the Apostle plainly de∣clares
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
of those wise men of the Heathen who knew God, yet were so foolishly subtil and phan∣tastical as to worship him in the Images of Men, Birds, four-footed Beasts and creeping things, which they could not but know, were but at the best Hieroglyphicks of him, no per∣sonal representatives of his Godhead, yet for∣asmuch as they worshipped those Figures, they are said <HI>to have changed the glory of the incorrupti∣ble God into the Images of these corruptible Creatures.</HI> For in worshipping these Images in reference to God, they naturally acknovvledg or suppose a fitness in them to represent the glory of God, or his Divine presence, vvhich therefore must needs be an unspeakable vilification of his infinite glori∣ous Majesty. And what pretence can there be for any Figure, or Symbolical Presence to have divine wor∣ship done to it, or to be an object thereof in any sense, if it vvere conceived to have no fitness to represent the Divinity. And therefore the Psalmist according to this natural Notion, inferres from the <HI>Israelites</HI> vvorshipping the Golden Calf, that they turned the glory of God into that Creature, <HI>Psalm.</HI> 106.19. <HI>They made a Calf in</HI> Horeb, <HI>and worshipped the Molten Image. Thus they changed their glory into the similitude of an Ox that eateth grass.</HI> Which ansvvers very fitly to that of <HI>St.</HI> Paul, <HI>They changed the glory of the incorruptible God into an Image made like to a corruptible man,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>Rom.</HI> 1.23.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="20" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XX.</HI> That in worshipping these representative Images in reference to God, divine worship
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
is given unto them, as suppose to the Image of God the Father.</HEAD>
<P>And that the vvorshipping of these represen∣tative Images in reference to God, is the giving of Divine vvorship to them, is manifest out of Scripture, as <HI>Acts</HI> 7. <HI>And they made a Calf in those dayes and sacrificed to the Idol.</HI> To say it vvas but <HI>sacrificium Relativum</HI> or <HI>Transitivum,</HI> that passed to God, not <HI>Terminativum,</HI> that termina∣ted in the Calf it self, is but School-cobvveb-stuff. Sacrifice is a peculiar vvorship belonging to God, and by no distinction or evasion can any thing else partake in it, so as to have it offered to it. This is evident in this kind of Divine vvor∣ship, and there is the same reason of them all. They vvorshipped the Calf in <HI>Horeb,</HI> but in re∣ference to <HI>Jehovah,</HI> as plainly appears out of the Historie, and therefore vvith <HI>Latria relativa,</HI> or <HI>transitiva</HI> not <HI>terminativa.</HI> But does this distincti∣on of so subtil Texture cover their chance? No certainly. If this distinction vvere good, and vvould justify their act, vvhy does either the <HI>Psalmist,</HI> or St. <HI>Steven</HI> find fault? It is apparent therefore that Divine vvorship is so due to God alone, that it is in no sense due to any thing else, but that even the meer natural or external act must be to him only. And therefore he will not be wor∣shipped by an Image, that the Image may not in any sense partake of his worship; which yet it will in the natural externality thereof, if we do it towards the visible Image. For outwardly we behave our selves no otherwise
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
towards the Image than towards God himself, nor make any other external Application to the one than to the other. As suppose there was an Image of God the Father in the shape of an Old man, and one would make his adoration to God towards this Image, with that mind, with that devout look, with that solemn and serious motion of the spirits in the eyes, that is befitting the profound reverence we owe to God, this natural, visible, and external act of worship passes plainly upon this Image, as well and in such sort as on God himself, and is such as no greater nor more lively expression of his highest devotion can be made by any suppliant. To whom then but to God alone can this belong? And therefore to make these expressions to a senseless stock and stone, is the foulest violation of the divine peculiarities that can be, by communicating them to so unworthy a subject, as well as by lessening, ob∣scuring, or rather abolishing the infinite glorious Majesty of the Godhead, by supposing him or im∣plying him representable by a wretched Statue of wood, metal or stone, as I noted before.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="21" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXI.</HI> That there is the same reason concerning the Image of Christ.</HEAD>
<P>And now for the Statue or Image of Christ, if it be worshipped towards with such a religious look and devout cast of the eyes as before, signi∣ficative of the highest veneration that is due to God, or can by us be given to him, it is apparent that this exteriour ritual worship is done to this Image also; nor can be any more doubted, than if kissing of this Image were the Ritual performance and it
<PB N="25" REF="17"/>
were kissed, that this Image was the Object of the kissing with all the exteriour devotionalness used therein: and that therefore this Image thus ado∣red, though but relatively, partakes of divine wor∣ship. By which communication the peculiarities of the Godhead are plainly violated, as well as by burning Incense, or otherwise sacrificing to the Image; as St. <HI>Steven</HI> complains of the <HI>Israe∣lites</HI> sacrificing to the golden Calf, though in relation to <HI>Jehovah,</HI> which cannot excuse the I∣dolatry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="22" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXII.</HI> That Relative Idolatry is as down-right Idolatry as Relative Adultery and Murder down-right Murder and Adultery.</HEAD>
<P>For let any one judge in common sense and rea∣son, whether a foul unfit action to an undue object can be excused by an intended relation to a fit one. Nothing can be more enormously incongruous, than the giving divine worship which is <HI>Latria</HI> to a carved stock or stone, ordinarily called <HI>Idolum,</HI> or <HI>I∣mago.</HI> And the giving this <HI>Latria</HI> to this <HI>Idolum</HI> is that which is most properly <HI>Idololatria.</HI> But if in giving <HI>Latria</HI> to this <HI>Idolum</HI> which is so hugely unfit an object, in relation to a fit one, all is well, and the fact lawful, the short and the long then is, That <HI>relative Idolatry</HI> is lawful, which is as good sense as to say, That relative Murder, or relative Adulte∣ry is lawful. As if to kill the next innocent man to wreak ones revenge on the nocent, that deserved to be killed, would excuse that Act from down-right Murder; or to lye with another Woman with an intended kinde
<PB N="26" REF="18"/>
remembrance of his own in her absence were not down-right adultery. Why then is not this relative Idolatry down-right Idolatry, as well as relative murder and adultery down-right adultery and murder? and why is relative murder and a∣dultery still down-right murder and adultery, but because that intended reference or relation takes not away the Specifick turpitude of the Fact? How then can the intended relation in relative Idolatry take away the Specifick turpitude of that Fact? so that it remain not down-right Idolatry still.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="23" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXIII.</HI> That relative Idolatry is real and proper Idolatry, even according to the nice Notion of the Schools.</HEAD>
<P>Which it does even in the nice Notion of the very Schools, the <HI>Latria</HI> in this case being <HI>really</HI> not transitive or relative, <HI>quatenus Latria,</HI> but ter∣minated on the very Idol it self. For <HI>quatenus Latria,</HI> it can pass no further in <HI>truth</HI> and <HI>reality</HI> but ends there; and in relation to God the act ceases to be <HI>Latria,</HI> the honouring or worship∣ping of him, but changes its Species, and be∣comes an act of contempt, reproach, and disobe∣dience against him, and a foul dishonouring of him. Nor can the <HI>intention</HI> of the Religionist alter the specification of the Act, but that it will be a dishonouring of God, though the <HI>Act</HI> can∣not be avoided but it will have God for its <HI>Ob∣ject,</HI> but he will be the Object of this Act un∣der this specification namely of dishonour: As in that Physician that intended by such a Medicine
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
to cure such a Patient, but does really poyson him thereby, the Patient notwithstanding the Physicians intention is no Object of a real cure, but of the quite contrary of his poysoning him. Wherefore no <HI>real Latria</HI> passing to God in this relative Idolatry, but only dishonour and reproach, the <HI>Latria</HI> is in <HI>truth</HI> (let the <HI>intention</HI> be what it will,) terminated in the Image or Idol, and there∣fore is Idolatry, in the most proper and Scholastick sense. For one and the same Act, as it may have two contrary <HI>Specifications,</HI> in respect of two several Objects, so it may have two several <HI>ter∣minations</HI> in respect of the same. As suppose one Person loves a Rose, another has a great Antipathy against it, a third brings a basket of Roses into the room; this one act is both a gratification and a displeasure; a gratification to him that loves Roses, a displeasure to him that has an Antipa∣thy against them; the Act of gratification termi∣nates in one of these Objects, the Person that loves Roses, the Act of displeasure terminates on the other. Just so the Act of <HI>Latria</HI> or Di∣vine honour terminates on the Image or Idol, the Act of dishonour and reproach on God, who is provoked and disobeyed. What can be more plain? Wherefore the Divine honour terminating on the <HI>Image</HI> of Christ, and not passing to <HI>him</HI> in <HI>reality</HI> and <HI>truth,</HI> but only in our <HI>fond intention,</HI> it is ma∣nifest that the peculiarities of God are here vio∣lated, and that it is proper Idolatry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="24" TYPE="part">
<PB N="28" REF="19"/>
<HEAD><HI>XXIV.</HI> Whether the doing Divine worship towards the Image of Christ violates the irrepresentableness of the Godhead or no, as also towards the holy Ghosts.</HEAD>
<P>But there is a more curious question whether the worshipping of the Image of Christ with Divine worship does involve also the other violation of the peculiarities of the Godhead in making it thus re∣presentable by an Image. For Christ being Man as well as God seems to make the case different from that of the Image of God the Father. But I answer the case is still the same, Christ being the eternal, infinite, glorious Majesty of God, as well as he is Man, and uncapable of Divine wor∣ship but so far forth as he is that infinite Majesty. Wherefore he that sets up an Image, and calls it the Image of Christ, and does Divine worship to∣wards it, does as palpably make the eternal infi∣nite Majesty of the Godhead representable by a carved stock or stone, as he that does Divine wor∣ship toward such a carved Image of God the Fa∣ther. For the Father and the Son are equal, and therefore the Son equally irrepresentable as to that of him which is capable of Divine worship, which this Image pretends to represent, in pretending to be the Image of Christ, and therefore violates that peculiarity of the infinite glorious Majesty of God, that makes it irrepresentable by any bodily Figure. He that worships Christ, worships the very God∣head, and therefore must not blaspheme his Ma∣jesty, by making him representable by any corporeal Image. The Godhead indeed is hypostatically in∣templed in the humane nature of Christ, but it is the
<PB N="29" REF="19"/>
the eternal and infinite divinity there that we adore. So little scruple need either Jevv or Turk have to turn Christians, upon any Idolatry vve are guilty of in vvorshiping Christ.</P>
<P>And vvhat I have said of the Images or Statues of the Father and the Son, the same is to be said of the Image of the Holy Ghost. A Dove may be the Hieroglyphick of him as that description of the Ancient of dayes in <HI>Daniel</HI> is an Hieroglyphick of God the Father. But to do Divine worship to∣ward such an Image of a Dove, it is absolutely the same Idolatry that was in so doing to the Image of God the Father, and of Christ.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="25" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXV.</HI> That no symbolical presence but only the holy humanity of Christ is capable of divine worship done towards it.</HEAD>
<P>No symbolical presence therefore or consistent visible animal figure saving the holy humanity of the Lord Jesus Christ, which is Hypostatical∣ly united with the eternal Divinity, can have di∣vine worship done towards it, but it is Idola∣try <HI>ipso facto.</HI> It the peculiar priviledge of the holy humanity of Christ, to be capable of ha∣ving divine worship done towards it, because of its Union with the Divinity, as it is the pri∣viledge of the Body of a wise and vertuous Person, for the wisdom and vertues sake that re∣sides only in his Soul, to have that great reve∣rence done towards it, by reason of the Soul with which it is Hypostatically united. But the Soul once separate by Death, the Body accord∣ing to the common sense and practice of all men
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
ceases to have that reverence done towards it that it had before. So that there is naturally a peculiar middle kind of honour, greater than a∣ny Creature besides has a capacity of, though less than Divine, that accrews to Christs huma∣nity, in vertue of his being Hypostatically u∣nited with the Godhead, which the Image of Christ is not. And therefore besides that gross I∣dolatry above specified, in doing Divine worship towards his Image, there is also a violation of the priviledge of this holy humanity of Christ, towards which living Symbolical presence of the Godhead only it had been proper to do Divine worship, when he was visible here upon Earth; upon a clear declaration of this Union. Which was more apertly, and more seasonably manifested afterwards by St. <HI>John.</HI> But considering the un∣expressable profound Humility of our Saviour, who upon ones saying to him, Good Master, straight way rebuked him, declaring there was none good but one, which is God, <HI>Mark</HI> 10.17. it seems hugely probable, that if any would have done express Divine worship towards his visible Humanity, as the <HI>Lycaonians</HI> would have sacrificed to <HI>Paul</HI> and <HI>Barnabas,</HI> that he would have decli∣ned it. But this only by the by.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="26" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXVI.</HI> The necessity of the Romanists ac∣knowledging of <HI>Latria relativa</HI> done to Ima∣ges relating to God.</HEAD>
<P>Hitherto of Images relating to God, to which the second <HI>Nicene</HI> Council, (that excellently learn∣ed and judicious Patriarch of <HI>Constantinople Photius</HI>
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
being Interpreter) assigned <HI>Latria relativa,</HI> which <HI>Azorius</HI> the Jesuite also acknowledges to be the constant opinion of the Roman Theologers. And indeed it seems necessary it should be so, to make the best sense of that kind of Religion: for they burn incense to these Images which is a sacrifice. And they putting up their prayers before them, and lifting up their eyes and hands towards them, with compellations common to the Image and Prototype, this is also the sacrifice of prayer offe∣red to them, as much if not more direct and ex∣press, than the sacrifices offered on the Altar be∣fore the Golden Calf were to it; which yet be∣cause it was done on the Altar before that I∣mage, St. <HI>Steven</HI> full of the holy Ghost, declares, that they sacrificed unto the Idol.</P>
<P>Wherefore it being so evident, that in these Cases they are to acknowledg that they give <HI>Latria</HI> to these Images, it seemed the wittiest and safest invention to declare in general, that the Images relating to God are to have <HI>Latria</HI> done to them, but not <HI>absoluta</HI> but <HI>relativa,</HI> which, they conceive, makes it an inferiour kind of <HI>Latria,</HI> since this Relative <HI>Latria</HI> (because of its Relativeness) is incompetible to God. But how well this will do their business, I have al∣ready noted.</P>
<P>But that this is the sense of their Church, even of the Council of <HI>Trent</HI> it self, is noted and confessed by <HI>Azorius,</HI> and natural if not ne∣cessary for every one to acknowledg, that is se∣rious in the worship of these Images. For if it
<PB N="32" REF="21"/>
were not <HI>Latria relativa,</HI> but such a worship as the Images were capable of, and might be the ultimate Object of themselves, and it terminate there, how small and mean, and how lovv a kind of Worship would this be! So that it would prove to be a meer fooling or trifling with Images to no purpose, the worship of the Image though relating to God not at all advancing our ado∣ration of him, but rather necessarily casting us (by restraining the worship to what the Image it self is the ultimate object of,) into the faint∣est and meanest mode of worshipping that can be expressed, if it be but what it should be com∣mensurate to so mean an Object. Wherefore it is altogether incredible, that this should be the meaning of worshipping of Images relating to God, or that any of the People that are taught to vvorship them, should not vvorship them vvith that height of affection and veneration they use to God, for as much as the Image relates to God, and that they are taught according to the very Council of <HI>Trent,</HI> that by the Image of Christ vvhich they vvorship, they vvorship Christ him∣self. So plain is it, that the act of vvorship be∣fore an Image relating to God, is an intended adoration of God himself, according the Coun∣cil of <HI>Trent.</HI></P>
<P>But for the occasional shuffles of any private Doctours of that Church, that would have the worship of incurvation, and the signs of devotion accompanying it, terminated on the Image it self, to make sure it may be in no sense <HI>Latria,</HI> at what a
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
loss vvill they be to ansvver touching the burning of incense, and praying to God before these Images that relate to him. Besides that the second com∣mandement does plainly meet vvith such shufflers, vvhich universally forbids any bovving to, or vvorshipping Images relating to God, and vvill not be put off by any evasion. <HI>For I am a jealous God,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>Nor vvas it unfit to give so forcible a stop, though less methodical to a subterfuge so unna∣tural and irrational. I vvill add also so repugnant to the Council of <HI>Trent,</HI> (vvhich is the touch∣stone of their faith,) vvho in these express vvords declare, <HI>Per Imaginem Christi Christum adoramus.</HI> And that adoration vvhich is done to Christ, is divine adoration and consequently <HI>Latria.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="27" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXVII.</HI> The reduction of the worship of Saints and Angels, to the proposed defini∣tion of Idolatry, and particularly their invo∣cation and making of vowes to them.</HEAD>
<P>We proceed now to the consideration of the Images, or Symbolical presences of Saints and Angels, and to all the modes of their religious worship: of which, Invocation is the most princi∣pal, and as it were the scope and foundation of all the rest. Which worship of theirs I shall al∣so plainly discover to be Idolatrous, by manifest reduction to my proposed definition of Idolatry. Which I will do with all brevity, there being no difficulty at all in the business. And I will begin with Invocation, which as I have proved in my Antidote, can belong to no invisible Power or
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
Spirit, saving to God alone. Forasmuch as no man can have any solid faith or assurance that they can hear our Invocation, or that they have any Omni∣presence, or Omnipercipience, no not so much as Terrestrial. Whence it it plain, that in invoke∣ing them one of the Divine peculiarities is viola∣ted or prophaned by being communicated to a Creature, when of right it is only to be attribu∣ted to God; the Saints having no such Omniper∣cipiency or Omnipresency in them, as Doctour <HI>Thorndike</HI> himself cannot but confess, according∣ly as I have noted at the end of my Reply.</P>
<P>But to invoke them or pray to them for such things as it is in Gods power only to give, which all Papists do, as Dr. <HI>Thorndike</HI> plainly asserts, nor can it be put off upon pretence of a figura∣tive speech, (as I have proved in my Reply,) this is double Idolatry, as violating two Divine peculi∣arities at once, both the Omnipresence or Om∣nipercipience of God, and also his Omnipotence, they giving that power to a Creature which is in God alone. But making Vowes to any Saint or Angel in such dangers as a Creature may have power to rid us from, is but the same kind of I∣dolatry that simple Invocation, if they be both mental, or both vocal.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="28" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXVIII.</HI> The Idolatry of erecting Temples, Altars, Images, or Symbolical presences to Saints, or Angels, reduced to the pro∣posed definition.</HEAD>
<P>And novv for the erecting Temples, Altars, Images or Symbolical presences to Saints or
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
Angels, all which is manifestly done in reference to their invocation, it is thence plain, that all this is done to an Idolatrous end, and therefore upon this very consideration has the smut of I∣dolatry upon it. But besides, more distinctly. God having appropriated these modes of being vvorshipped to himself, and his judgement being so infallible, vvhat befits him and is most proper for him, when he will be vvorshipped in a more <HI>external</HI> and <HI>ritual</HI> vvay, it is evident presumpti∣on and prophanation of the peculiarities of his Godhead, as to <HI>external</HI> vvorship, to communi∣cate them to the Creature, as I have proved in my Antidote. And lastly, the very nature of the thing demonstrates the Idolatry, they being stand∣ing significations of the natural peculiarities of God communicated to a Creature. For a Tem∣ple and Symbolical presence is fitly and secure∣ly erected to God, because we are sure of Gods residence and presence there, as <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> intimates the inhabitation of the Divinity in it. Let there be as many Symbolical Presences and Temples as you will, and at what distance you will, God is certainly at home in them all, as being Omni∣present. But for a finite invisible Power or Spirit, though there were but one erected thereto, there is no assurance of that Spirits residence there, or if the effect of any Spirit be there, that it is not some other Spirit than he to whom the Temple or Symbolical presence was erected, that it is not one Angel or Saint for another, nay, a Divel in∣stead of that Saint or Angel. But those Temples
<PB N="36" REF="23"/>
and Symbolical presences being erected in seve∣ral distant places, it emplyes they are in several distant places at once, which is the only peculi∣arity of the Godhead; as I have noted in my Re∣ply. Which incongruities are also to be observed in either one single Altar, or many in distant places of the World, to the same Saint or Angel. And besides it has that odious relation to a sacri∣fice, and imports that the Saints and Angels are also sacrificed to, which is plain and confessed Ido∣latry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="29" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXIX.</HI> An Evasion obviated.</HEAD>
<P>Nor is it any excuse, that the Temple and Altar is pretended to be erected and dedicated to God only in a principal sense, but to the Saint in a <HI>secundarie</HI> respect, as <HI>less principal.</HI> For be∣sides that God is jealous and impatient of any Partner, in the honours that are due to himself, (though they were only <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> not <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) their in∣tention cannot change the natural signification of building Temples and Altars to a finite Creature. Which as I have already noted, <UNCLEAR>implyes</UNCLEAR> its Om∣nipresence which is proper and peculiar only to God; And therefore this communicating a pecu∣liarity of the Godhead to a Creature is Idolatry according to the plain definition thereof, let us intend what we will.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="30" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXX.</HI> The Idolatry of bowing to the Images of Saints and Angels wherein it consists.</HEAD>
<P>As for their superstitious worship done towards the bare Symbolical presences, or open Images of Saint or Angel, supposing it the very same they
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
would do to the Saint or Angel themselves if they were visible, that this implyes them <HI>repre∣sentable</HI> is no Idolatry. For the making them representable by an Image, does not at all violate the peculiarities of the Godhead. But the Ido∣latry is in that the Act naturally supposes them cer∣tainly present, for it is not sense to bow to an absent Person; and these Symbolical presences being many, and at far distant places at once, that the Saint or Angel is in more places than one at once, and in such sort ommipresent as none can be acknowledged but God alone, and so that Divine peculiarity is violated by this bowing to the Symbolical Presences or Images of Saint or Angel.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="31" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXXI.</HI> The hazard of the vulgars doing that Devotion which is due to God in their worshipping the Images of Saints and Angels.</HEAD>
<P>And though there be no necessary connexion betwixt the things, yet there is an exceeding great hazard in the vulgar sort especially, when they bow to these Images of Saint or Angel, or pray to them before the said Images, there is an hazard of running into the highest Devotion, and reverential affection and passion, that hu∣mane nature is excitable into or can express by his look or mind, and profoundly devout motion of the spirits of his eyes, which passion and sig∣nification thereof is due to God alone, and it is the most sordid Idolatry imaginable to apply it to either Saint or Angel, much more to the ve∣ry <UNCLEAR>images</UNCLEAR> of them made of wood or stone, though never so well painted or gilt. It is manifest I say, that by such a worship a special peculiarity
<PB N="38" REF="24"/>
of the Godhead is violated, who alone is to be worshipped with that kind of Devotion. Which yet I have seen simple folk to express to the I∣mage of a Saint, as fully as I could ever discern to be done by the devoutest man in his pray∣ers to God. So that this note is not made at random, without just occasion and ground. And if this be done to the Image of a Saint, you may be sure it will not fail to be done to Images that relate to God. But that is besides our present Scope.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="32" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXXII.</HI> The reduction of burning of Incense and setting up lights before them.</HEAD>
<P>As for t<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e burning of Incense and setting up lights before the Symbolical presences of Saints and Angels, it being so plainly an imitation of the burning incense, and lighting up lamps be∣fore the Symbolical presence of <HI>Jehovah</HI> in the Holy, it is plainly a violation of his peculiarities, so judged by his own election and choice. And as for the incense, it is a sacrifice, and the most noble and significant sacrifice, as I have noted in my <HI>Reply.</HI> And they may as well depress the sacrificing of sheep and oxen into a lower ceremonie, as this of incense. For by the use and consent of Nations, the one is no more restrained to the supream God than the other. And the lamps and shew bread seem to indicate <HI>Jehovah</HI> to be the Father of lights, from whom proceeds every good and per∣fect gift, and who feeds with bounty every li∣ving thing. And the lights set up before the Ima∣ges of Saints and Angels do at least intimate, that light and comfort is to be expected from suppliants
<PB N="39" REF="24"/>
that make their addresses to them at these Sym∣bolical presences, as if they were there present to assist them that invoke them, &amp; implore their help. Which I have again and again inculcated to be an implying and attributing an Omnipresency or Omnipercipiency to these finite created spirits, and consequently a violation of the Peculiari<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies of the Godhead. Thus easily are the various acts of Idolatry observed in the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> in their worshipping Saints and Angels, reduci∣ble to the plain definition and true general No∣tion of Idolatry which we have proposed. As for those high compellations, to the blessed Vir∣gin especially, such as plainly signify the peculiar excellencies of the Godhead, they are so openly Idolatrous that they want no reduction.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="33" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXXIII.</HI> That the pretended intricacies in the mystery of the holy Trinity, cannot with any reason at all be alledged against the clear de∣monstrations that the doctrine if Transubstanti∣ation is false.</HEAD>
<P>As neither their <HI>Artolatria</HI> does to them that are free and believe that which is most certainly true, that the bread is not transubstatiated, as I have again and again undeniably demonstrated it not to be in my <HI>Antidote against Idolatry,</HI> and in my <HI>Reply.</HI> The clearness of which demonstrati∣ons, the pretended intricacies in the mystery of the holy Trinity cannot obscure; there being so vast a difference both betwixt the Objects them∣selves, and the faculties in this case, and that. For in Transubstantiation the Object is Matter or
<PB N="40" REF="25"/>
body, a substance finite and comprehensible both by our senses and reason. In the mystery of the Trinity, the object is the infinite incomprehensi∣ble Deity, a substance incorporeal, or spirit, which is quite out of the reach of our senses in the lowest notion thereof; but the transcendency of the Triune Godhead above our reason also, though not contrary unto it. And then our faculties conver∣sant about Transubstantiation, are all the five senses rightly circumstantiated, the organ, di∣stance and medium duly fitted and proportionated, and therefore the senses necessarily capable of discerning what the object is, whether this body or that, suppose whether the body of a man, or a piece of bread. And besides this, not only the exteriour reason, but that which the Greeks call <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> (which contains the first and self-evident com∣mon Notions or Axiomes, that are without syllo∣gism noematically true,) layes fast hold on the ob∣ject in this controversy. Transubstantiation being easily resolvible into a flat and manifest contra∣diction to these, as I have abundantly shown in my <HI>Antidote</HI> and <HI>Reply.</HI> But there is no contra∣diction at all, to either sensation or common no∣tion in the mystery of the Trinity, only exteriour reason and imagination raise some mists and ob∣scurities about it. Which well exercised minds in contemplation can easily discern, and dispute from this venerable mystery, so far forth as it is ex∣hibited to us in the ancient symbols of the Catho∣lick Church. Wherefore of two desperate cases it is the more hopeful, that the bread being not tran∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ubstantiated, and yet they taking it to be so, they
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
may scape being Idolaters, than that it is transub∣stantiated to save them from Idolatry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="34" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXXIV.</HI> That the believing the bread not to be there, does not all clear the Romanists from down-right Bread-worship which is Idolatry.</HEAD>
<P>And I must confess I was once inclinable to this opinion my self, that in this case they are not I∣dolaters (see my <HI>Idea of Antichristianisme,</HI> Book 1. Chap. 13. sect. 6.) before I had more closely and carefully considered the point. And the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> does not want at this day witty Patrons, and of admirable art and eloquence, to perswade the heedless into this security, That though the bread should not prove transubstantiated, yet they cannot be bread-worshippers, while they believe it is; for if they believe it is transubstantiated, they believe it not to be there, namely within the <HI>Symbols</HI> or <HI>Species,</HI> and thence they pretend it is demonstra∣tively evident that they cannot worship it, but only Christ, into whose substance it is believed to be transubstantiated. For whatever is taken, say they, for an object of worship, the understanding must affirm, (either truly or falsly,) that it is there whither the worship is directed. Which arguing bears a smart plausibility with it. But I an∣swer, That what is made an object of worship through mistake, there is no need the understand∣ing affirm it is there, but rather the contrary. For it does not think the undue object is there but the due one. Those that worshipped the Sun, that is, that which we call the Sun, and understand thereby a flammeous body devoid of sense and understanding,
<PB N="42" REF="26"/>
that appears alike to the sight of the Sun-wor∣shippers, and to ours, (as the species appear the same to those that believe the bread transub∣stantiated, and to them that believe it not,) be it called what it will, they did not believe that which we know to be the Sun, to be there, but an intellectual Deity, which the Sun is not; and yet we all acknowledg them for all that to have been Sun-worshippers and Idolaters. Where∣fore using <HI>just weights and measures,</HI> we must conclude the Romanists Bread-worshippers and Idolaters, the bread not being transubstantiated, since their worship then lights upon bread in∣stead of Christ, as the Sun-worshippers upon the Sun instead of an intelligent Deity. He that strikes his Friend in the dusk of the Evening, thinking it is his Enemy, thinks his friend is not there, who notwithstanding finds himself the Object of his stroak, and wishes he had not been there. This Idolatry I must confess is commit∣ted through mistake, but so is all Idolatry that is committed in good earnest, so that this can∣not excuse the fact from so grievous a crime. And that it is Idolatry is evident, Divine worship being given to a piece of bread, which is a pe∣culiarity of the Godhead, and must be given to none but him. And the violation of any Divine peculiarity is Idolatry by the proposed definition thereof.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="35" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXXV.</HI> The application of the Heathen Ido∣latry to this definition, besides his present scope.</HEAD>
<P>By vertue of which we demonstratively have
<PB N="43" REF="26"/>
shown the sundry Idolatries of the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> in their worshipping the Image of Christ, in their worshipping and invocating Saints and Angels, and in their adoration of the Eu∣charist. And in vertue of the same Definition, the Idolatries of the Heathen might be as clear∣ly demonstrated in their worshipping the supream God by Images, and in their religious worship they did to Daemons, which this definition would prove to be Divine. But this would be quite besides my present purpose, and neither useful nor sutable to the subject in hand.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="36" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXXVI.</HI> The great difference betwixt religious respect and preference, and Divine worship.</HEAD>
<P>It remains now only that we free several Ce∣remonies used in our own Church from the im∣putation of Idolatry, by application to this defi∣nition, as well as we have evinced several of theirs to be Idolatrous by the same. Which will be a no less useful, and it may be a more pleasant consideration to our own, to see how little hold the adverse party can take of these small strings to pull us back again into Popery. For if the definition of Idolatry be unapplicable to them, it is manifest they cannot be Idolatrous. And the inapplicability is so easily discoverable, that there will be no need to insist long on this mat∣ter. In the general then we are to note what a vast difference there is betwixt religious worship properly so called, which is the same with Di∣vine worship, and pious or religious affection and respect, or preference of one thing before another,
<PB N="44" REF="27"/>
for its relation it has to the objects, or exercise of our Religion, or Divine worship. It is but an homely Proverb, <HI>Love me and love my dog,</HI> but it may be of no impertinent significancy in this place. For it is not understood of the love of friendship, but of such a love as that inferiour Creature is ca∣pable of, and is fit to give him in relation to his Master, to whom we owe the love of friendship. So they that have a real Divine reverence for God, it is no wonder they find an inclination in them∣selves of bearing some reverence, or having some respect to those things or persons, that in a special manner relate to him. Whether it be Priest or Tem∣ple, or any holy utensil or the like. Which reve∣rence is quite different from that Divine worship or reverence that is due to God himself, (more different than the love to ones Friend, and to his Spaniel,) and therefore can be no peculiarity of the Godhead, and consequently no violation of his peculiarities to give it to another. Which is the true Notion of Idolatry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="37" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXXVII.</HI> The keeping our hats off in the Church, freed from Idolatry by this Definition.</HEAD>
<P>We will illustrate this with some few examples, and so conclude. They that keep off their hats in the Church, and do it even then when Divine Service is not a doing there, are not by any means conceived to do that Divine reverence or worship which is peculiarly due to God, unto the fabrick they are under, but because this place is set apart for holy uses, and is of a different nature from or∣dinary places that have no such relation to God and his Divine worship, out of an habitual deep devout∣ness
<PB N="45" REF="27"/>
toward God they also express this more infe∣riour affection and reverence to the place of his worship, by way of distinction and preference of it before other common places, be they never so mag∣nificently built. Which is not to give it a reverence a∣ny thing equal or of the same kind with that we give to God, but only a greater and another sort of reve∣rence than we would give to any place that is not re∣lated to him. And this is no more Idolatry than <HI>Moses</HI> his putting off his shooes, because the ground was hallowed by the special presence of God there. And therefore it was not unfit to show some reverence thereto in those circumstances, and not to prophane it and soyl it by his dirty shooes. Nay, indeed ne∣cessary, having that express command of God for it. Or if one should do so of himself in such a meaning of reverence as I have intimated, though it might be superstitious under Christianity, yet it could not be Idolatrous, no peculiarities of the Godhead being violated thereby.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="38" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXXVIII.</HI> As also kissing the Bible in the administration of Oathes.</HEAD>
<P>Kissing the Bible also in the administration of Oathes, which is in use amongst us, (and might ac∣cording to the proper Notation of the Latine word, be called Adoration, that word signifying properly either the a motion of our mouth to the thing kissed, or the admotion of our own hand to our mouth, and so by kissing it signifying chiefly our kindness and affection, but withal our respect to the Person or thing we in this manner salute,) this Ceremony here is only an ex∣pression of our love and value we have even for the
<PB N="46" REF="28"/>
<HI>material</HI> word of God, as I may so speak, by reading whereof we find such Divine comforts and refreshments, and which gives us to know the will of God, and that salvation which is through Jesus Christ revealed in this book. And if a man after the serious reading of a Chapter therein, his heart being full of joy and holy con∣solation, should at the close of all kiss the Bible as he layes it down, out of a pious affection unto the very instrument of communicating such grace and comfort unto him, what more Idolatry were there in this, than in such an ones hugging his Bible in the Pulpit before the People, to signify how dear it was to himself, and should be to them all?</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="39" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XXXIX.</HI> That bowing towards the Altar or Communion-table does not fall within the verge of the true Notion or Definition of Idolatry.</HEAD>
<P>And as for bowing towards the Altar, they that so do, questionless intend by that action, a∣doration to God properly, or in the highest sense, so called, so that it is one species of <HI>Latria.</HI> Which can be no Idolatry in it self, to be directed to∣wards a place, sith it cannot be done at all, but it will be directed toward some place or other. And if the Church for uniformity sake appoint one place rather than another, so long as it is but towards it only, it can be no Idolatry. For it is no more Idolatry to worship God towards a place, than in a place: for both these are but Circumstances, not Objects of Divine worship. But now it being concluded fitting to use adoration
<PB N="47" REF="28"/>
when we first come into Gods house, as also for uni∣formity sake towards one certain place or part thereof, and all the place being in some sort holy, but yet a preference of one part before another, because of the more than ordinary devotion used there in celebrating the most endearing Mysteries of our Religion, the death and passion of our blessed Saviour, and our union with him by par∣ticipation of his Flesh and Blood, that place where the symbols of this are exhibited, and these great and endearing mysteries celebrated, it is no wonder if it have the preference in our Religious affection and respect before all the places in the Church, to be as it were the di∣rect<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Eve instrument toward what part of the Church we should do our adorations, namely that the Altar or Communion Table should be this in∣strument of direction, and that this should be the peculiar Honour done to it, to be so. In which sense it is bowed towards, as the Mercy seat of old <HI>was</HI> by the Jews, and the Book of their Law under a Canopee in their Synagogues now <HI>is,</HI> without the least shew or suspicion of Idolatry.</P>
<P>For Divine worship is not at all done to that, in any of those cases, towards which it is di∣rected, but only to God himself; There being no Animal Figures exposed to receive the wor∣ship as in the case of the Heathen, and the Eucha∣ristick bread being in no sense at all a Symbo∣lical presence as well as having no Imagery on it, but both Bread and Wine mere Tokens of the Body of Christ slaine, crucified or sacrificed,
<PB N="48" REF="29"/>
and of his blood shed for us. Which therefore are not the Person of Christ, nor Hypostatically united to his Person in this condition, and conse∣quently the symbols thereof cannot be any sym∣bolical presence, as I have also noted in my <HI>Re∣ply.</HI> The Altar therefore has the honour of be∣ing a directive instrument <HI>whither,</HI> as the Church has <HI>where</HI> to do divine worship. But the wor∣ship is no more done <HI>to</HI> the Altar, by being done <HI>towards</HI> it, than it is done <HI>to</HI> the Church by being done <HI>in</HI> it. Forasmuch as there is no Animal Figure thereon, as the Ancient Pagans conceived their Gods to appear in se∣veral such shapes, and therefore worshipped them in them. For this would be a personal representa∣tive, and so receptive of the worship done towards it, according to the manifest sense of Scripture, and natural interpretation of reason, but here being no such Statue or Image there erected all is safe.</P>
<P>Wherefore all the honour the Altar receives in these adorations made towards it is this, that it is used as a directive instrument for people to show which way they are to set their faces, when they make these adorations to God, which is far from giving any Divine worship to the Table or Altar, and therefore is far out of the reach of our definition of Idolatry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="40" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>LX.</HI> Nor bowing to the name of Iesus.</HEAD>
<P>And so whereas all the names and attributes of God are holy, and we have a greater reve∣rence for them, than for any words or names that do not relate to God, (though we do not
<PB N="49" REF="29"/>
owe Divine worship or reverence to them, for as much as they are not God, but words that pass away as other sounds do,) whereas I say, all the names of God are holy, yet because the name Jesus exhibits to us the manifestation of God in the most endearing circumstances; there∣fore as the Mysteries celebrated on the Altar caused that preference of it before all other parts of the Church for to do our worship <HI>towards,</HI> so this name of Jesus above all other Names or words, that signify God or his attributes, may well be made use of to determine the time and occasion <HI>when</HI> in Divine service we should more exuberantly vent our devotion in the worship∣ping God our Saviour, especially the Scripture seeming to hint some such thing to us. And this is the honour done to the Name of Jesus, that at the naming thereof we take occasion to do profound reverence and Divine worship to our eternal Redeemer. Whence it is plain, that that honour that accrews to the Name of Jesus, or to the Altar, by bowing <HI>at the naming</HI> of the one, and <HI>to∣wards the site</HI> of the other, is far from any Di∣vine honour, and that therefore the peculiarities of the Godhead are not thereby violated, nor a∣ny Idolatry committed.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="41" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XLI.</HI> Nothing that has the least shew of Idolatry required of our Church, in cele∣brating the Lords Supper.</HEAD>
<P>And now lastly, as for the Eucharist or holy Symbols of Bread and Wine, that we kneel not to
<PB N="50" REF="30"/>
them I have sufficiently intimated in my <HI>Reply,</HI> but are in that posture as being in devout ejacu∣lations to God, our hearts breathing towards him in the receiving this holy sacrament, and this is all the due reverence I see requi∣red by the Rubrick of our Church, or a∣ny direction thereof, for the celebrating these holy mysteries.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Chaitable constructi∣ons of some private Do∣ctours ex∣pressions.</NOTE> And if any particular Doctours of the Church talk of worshipping the Sacra∣ment, if it be such affection and reverence as is expressed to the word of God, that this is with∣out any violation of the Divine peculiarities, I have above noted, and that therefore it can be no Idolatry; and if they speak of adoration pro∣perly so called, I charitably suspect they meant adoration done <HI>towards</HI> the Symbols as I have above explained the doing of it <HI>towards</HI> the Altar, that is, as using them as <HI>directive Instruments</HI> to∣wards which we doe our adoration to Christ, but not to them as any Objects thereof. Which I should think would be hard for any man to imagine, that is conscious to himself, what a motion the Soul is in, when it does an act of real and sincere adoration, or Divine worship, and considers what it is to be in any sense the Object thereof. He would find it such horrid ill Syntax, to make any thing in any sense the object of adoration besides God, that he would be utterly ashamed of it, and find it more ab∣sonous and incongruous, more impertinent and troublesome, than if one when he were to worship
<PB N="51" REF="30"/>
the visible Sun, should interpose a burning rush-candle betwixt his eye and the Sun, and tye himself to worship that also, as an object in reference to the Sun, while he pretends ulti∣mately at the same time to worship the Sun it self, it is plain it would be a distraction and im∣pediment to him.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="42" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XLII.</HI> The reason of some mens prone∣ness to adoration of outward objects.</HEAD>
<P>Which makes it suspicable that those that are so forward to have adoration done to outward objects, are not eager enough to joyn their hearts and minds with that eternal invisible power, which is best felt in the least distraction of thoughts, but would stick in these outward things, and so lay Religion at last as flat as the Earth, and suffer the Souls of men to grow stupid in carnality. Wherefore I presume better of any particular Doctours of our Church, than that they have a∣ny such meaning as to assert the lawfulness of a∣doration or Divine worship to the Eucha∣ristick Symbols, which is an undue object of that worship, that it may pass to a due one, that is to Christ, for this I have plainly proved above to be Idolatry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="43" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XLIII.</HI> The sense of the Church not to be interpreted by the rash expressions of any private Doctour.</HEAD>
<P><PB N="52" REF="31"/>But if any of our Church should speak so in∣considerately, what is that to the Church her∣self, that contains herself far within this com∣pass? And they that are of the Church, are not tyed to any particular mens opinions, but to the general profession and practice of the Church. Which by these instances, that yet are those that are most scrupled at, you may see how clear she is from the least spot or soil of Idolatry, according to the true Notion and Definition thereof, she using no rites of worship where∣by the Peculiarities of the Godhead are viola∣ted.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="44" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XLIV.</HI> The great Peril in leaving a more pure Church for an Idolatrous one.</HEAD>
<P>And therefore I hope these brief pains of mine, in so freely and faithfully examining the rites of the Roman Church and of our own, by this so intelligible a Rule, will prove as well ac∣ceptable as seasonable to all that have any serious care of their salvation, and they will take heed in this slippery Age, how they leave a pure Church for a Church so plainly soiled with ma∣nifold spots of Idolatry, but those in that soiled Church provide better for themselves, by en∣tring Communion with that Church that is more pure. And in the mean time I hope they will excuse my more than ordinary zeal in a mat∣ter of so exceeding great moment, and which so <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="page cropped" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>early concerns our eternal happiness, it being
<PB N="53" REF="31"/>
so expresly declared in Scripture, that no Idola∣ter shall inherit the Kingdom of Heaven.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="45" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XLV.</HI> Of Spiritual Idolatry, several in∣stances thereof, as Covetousness, which the Apostle calls Idolatry.</HEAD>
<P>Which as it is undeniably true, and confessed on all sides, concerning this external <HI>ritual</HI> I∣dolatry, so certainly is it no less true of the <HI>in∣ternal</HI> or <HI>spiritual,</HI> if we do not sincerely endea∣vour to rid our selves of it. For there are other sorts of Idolatry, than we have hitherto insisted on, and such as we are as carefully to shun, as we tender our own salvation. Saint <HI>Paul</HI> expresly names one of this kind, and calls it by the very name, <HI>Mortifie therefore your Members which are upon Earth, Fornication, Vncleanness, Inordinate affection, evil Concupiscence, and Covetousness which is Idolatry, Colos.</HI> 3.5. The word is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>the love of money,</HI> which I suppose the A∣postle doth not count Idolatry, for the Imagery that ordinarily is upon Coins, but for the trust and repose they put in uncertain Riches. And there is the same reason in any worldly interest whatsoever, in power, friends, and what ever else. Those that trust in these more than in the living God, do plainly commit <HI>Spiritual Ido∣latry. Trust ye in the Lord for ever, for in the Lord Iehovah is everlasting strength,</HI> Isa. 26.4. <HI>The Lord is my Rock and my fortress, my God, my strength in whom I will trust,</HI> Psalm 18.2.
<PB N="54" REF="32"/>
<HI>Yea, though he kill me, yet will I trust him,</HI> saith <HI>Job,</HI> Job 13.15. And so must we do, whome∣ver he should permit to kill us, or any wayes per∣secute us, being assured that nothing can come amiss to them that are his, and put their trust in him. But if when visible comforts fail, our trust fails in the invisible God, it is a sign we made the Creature the Rock of our confidence, and gave that to it, which is a peculiarity of the Godhead, which is plainly Idolatry.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="46" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XLVI.</HI> The harbouring a false Idea of God, horrid and affrightful, another kind of Spiritual Idolatry.</HEAD>
<P>As is also to raise a false Idea of God, more horrid and affrightful than the most terrible I∣dols of the Heathen, and to flatter this, and our selves as special favourites of it, because we be∣lieve it to be such as we have falsly imagined it, of adamantine severity or rather cruelty to in∣finitely the greatest part of mankind inevitably to be damned to everlasting ineffable torments, and our selves fatally and necessarily to be made happy out of a partial fondness to our Persons, before the rest of the world, live as we list, meerly because he will have it so: and that this shall be the bottom of our faith and trust; this certainly would be spiritual Idolatry also, and an egregious violating that pretious Divine Attribute, if not the very Nature of God, whom
<PB N="55" REF="32"/>
Saint <HI>John</HI> has declared to be love, <HI>God is love, and he that abideth in love, abideth in God, and God in him, Iohn</HI> 4.16.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="47" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XLVII.</HI> That those Christians that per∣secute and kill one another for conscientious difference in Religion, turn the God of the Christians into a foul Heathen Idol.</HEAD>
<P>In the law of <HI>Moses</HI> it is forbidden to offer strange incense or strange fire, and it is as strictly forbidden in the Gospel of Christ. For when his Disciples would have had him fetch fire down from Heaven, as <HI>Elias</HI> did, for an affront done to their Lord and Master, he rebuked them saying, <HI>You know not of what spirit you are,</HI> Luk. 9.54. Bitter and destructive zeal (the A∣postle calls it <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) is the strange fire or Incense not to be offered to the Lord under the Gospel. For nothing is more estranged from the Spirit of the Gospel than it. <HI>John</HI> 16.2. <HI>The time comes,</HI> saith our Saviour, <HI>when any one that kills you will think he does</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> that he does God an acceptable piece of Divine worship or service, as if he offered an Oblation or Sacrifice to him. And this is indeed that strange Incense, fire and sacrifice that all Reli∣gionists offer to God, (be they of what perswa∣sion they will, Pontifician or Protestant) that per∣secute and kill the one the other for consci∣entious difference in Religion, as if they were the weapons of Christs warfare. Who yet has so
<PB N="56" REF="33"/>
expresly said, By this shall all men know that you are my Disciples if you love one another. But in persecuting, killing, and sacrificing one ano∣ther thus in a barbarous zeal, thinking they do <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, make an oblation of Di∣vine worship to God thereby; they turn the li∣ving God of the Christians, which is Love it self, into the foulest Idols of the Heathen, who used to be worshipped with the bloody sacrifi∣cing of men; and therefore plainly commit spi∣ritual Idolatry, violating and defacing the pe∣culiar character of the God of the Christians, while they thus pretend to worship Him.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="48" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XLVIII.</HI> The laying out all the strength of our Bodies and Souls, for the satisfaction of our own will, another instance of this Idolatry.</HEAD>
<P>Saint <HI>Paul</HI> exhorts the Romans, <HI>Chap.</HI> 12. to present their bodies a living sacrifice, holy, ac∣ceptable unto God, which he calls <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>our reasonable Latria,</HI> viz. that Divine worship which is most fit and reasonable to give to God, namely, that we dedicate and devote all the powers and faculties of our souls and bodies, (for in that it is called <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>a living sacrifice,</HI> the soul is manifestly implyed) unto his service. This is our reasonable and fitting <HI>Latria</HI> we owe to God; and therefore if we imploy all the powers of our mind and strength of our body, to serve our selves, and
<PB N="57" REF="33"/>
our own carnal and worldly desires, it is evi∣dent we make an Idol of our selves, and give that worship to our selves, that is reasonable to give to God only.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="49" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>XLIX.</HI> The letting out the fulness and entireness of our affection to any Creature, another instance thereof.</HEAD>
<P>And whenas it is written, <HI>Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart and all thy Soul,</HI> that is to say, the greatest strength and fulness of thy affection shall be entirely carryed out towards him, and other things be loved only for his sake, God challenging this as his peculiar due, if we let this height and entireness of affection go to any other person or thing, friend, wife, child, repute, plea∣sure or whatever else, this peculiarity of God is violated, and it is most certainly a kind of spiri∣tual Idolatry. Which makes it less to be won∣dred at, that people are so frequently crossed in those things or persons that they so excessively love. And therefore it is our safety as well as our duty to have our affections moderate to all things saving to God alone, where there can be no dan∣ger of excess.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="50" TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>L.</HI> The making our selves the ultimate end of our actions and services of God, an egregi∣ous instance of this spiritual Idolatry.</HEAD>
<P>And lastly, (for this is an argument so copious
<PB N="58" REF="34"/>
that a man may easily lose himself in it) It is well known and cannot be denied but that God is the ultimate end of all. He is so in himself, and ought to be acknowledged so by us both in our words and actions. Wherefore if we make our selves the ultimate end of our actions, and our own Happiness as our own, and not as ac∣cording to the will and nature of God, so that we serve and worship God for our own sakes, mak∣ing as it were a crafty bargain with the all-wise God, and performing it too (which is worst of all) no further than it stands with our own pre∣sent ease, security and interest, preferring these before his will and command, this also is mani∣fest Spiritual Idolatry, and we again make an Idol of our selves in making our selves the ultimate end of our Actions. For there can be but one ultimate end, which is the will of the Father, the light of the knowledg of God in the face of Jesus Christ manifested in us, who is the brightness of his glory and express Image of his person. Who declared in the flesh, he came not to doe his own will, but the will of him that sent him.</P>
<P>This therefore is the supreme Law and will of God touching the purity of his worship, that we have no will nor end of our own. For as we are to have but one God, <HI>Hear O Isra∣el, the Lord thy God is one God,</HI> Deut. 6.4. so we are to have but one will, even the will of the God whom we worship. Which we have not, if we have any self-will, or self-ends, unsubor∣dinate to the will of God. Whose Will and
<PB N="59" REF="34"/>
Law is the Law of an <HI>unself-interested Love</HI> that is ready to act, and content to suffer any thing for the Good of the Creation of God, be it never so bitter and painful, as was most exemplarily conspicuous in our blessed Saviour. And of this it is that that bosome friend of our Lord Jesus witnesses in the close of his Epistle, John 5.20. <HI>And we know that the Son of God is come, and has given us an understanding that we may know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jesus Christ. Little Chil∣dren, keep your selves from Idols.</HI> Amen.</P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>The End.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

