<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A Mystery of godlinesse and no cabala, or, A sincere account of the non-conformists conversation ... occasioned by a bitter and malitions [sic] paper called the Cabala.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A51680</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing M3184</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R7629</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13239362</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13239362</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">98617</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A51680)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98617)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 429:16)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A Mystery of godlinesse and no cabala, or, A sincere account of the non-conformists conversation ... occasioned by a bitter and malitions [sic] paper called the Cabala.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Birkenhead, John, Sir, 1616-1679.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[3], 40 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>[s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1663.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Sometimes ascribed to Sir John Birkenhead. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Birkenhead, John, --  Sir, 1616-1679. --  Cabala.</TERM><TERM>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A51680">
<STC T="W">M3184</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13239362</BIBNO>
<VID>98617</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A
MYSTERY
OF
GODLINESSE, AND NO
CABALA; Or a sincere Account of the
<HI>NON-CONFORMISTS</HI>
CONVERSATION. From the 24. of <HI>August</HI> to this time. For the conviction of Adversaries, the in∣struction
of the ignorant, the confirming of
the weak, and the satisfaction of all. Occasioned by a bitter and malitious Paper,
called the
<HI>CABALA.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed in the Year, MDCLXIII.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A
MYSTERY
OF
GODLINESSE
AND NO
CABALA;
Or a sincere Account of the
NON-CONFORMISTS
CONVERSATION. From <DATE>the 24. of August</DATE> to this time. For the conviction of Adversaries, the instruction of
the ignorant, the confirming of the weak, and the satis∣faction
of all. Occasioned by a bitter and malitious Paper, called the
CABALA.</HEAD>
<P>WHen the fears and jealousies of some concerning
us are so restlesse, the malice of others is so im∣placable,
that we suffer not only for what we
have done, but for what we may do, and we are not only
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
obnoxious to Authority for those miscarriages the world
hath seen us guilty of, but unto the Tongues and pens of
men; for those likewise the world may imagine us guilty
of: To justifie his Majesties clemency over us, to give the
world a reason of the hope that is in us, to satisfie all sober
men, and to to promote tee peace and settlement of our na∣tive
Country, we declare.</P>
<P>1. That it is true indeed, we cannot come up in all
things to their judgement who are over us, as we know they
could not come up to ours, when we were advanced over
them; and as we could not allow them any publick em∣ployment
or encouragement when they could not comply
with us, and our Laws and Constitutions, so we cannot ex∣pect
any publick employment or encouragement from
them, now we dissent from, and cannot close with their
Laws and Constitutions: Yet it is true, that we <HI>submit
patiently</HI> to that Authority which we cannot <HI>obey chearfully;</HI>
really we cannot conform in <HI>conscience,</HI> and really we can∣not
resist in <HI>conscience;</HI> for we must needs <HI>be obedient, not only
for wrath, but for conscience sake:</HI> we suffer, yet we repine
not; we murmur not, we <HI>speak no evil of Dignities;</HI> we
dare <HI>not curse the King, no not in our thoughts:</HI> we desire to
<HI>fear God,</HI> we desire to <HI>honour the King;</HI> and we would not
meddle with them that are given to change, or to Innovati∣ons;
they of us pay tribute from whom tribute is due, cu∣stome
from whom custome, and fear from whom fear; and
his Majesty hath our hearty prayers day and night before
the Throne of Grace for a blessing upon himself and Go∣vernment;
and if we could renounce the whole Covenant,
yet would we not renounce that part of it, wherein we have
<HI>promised, sincerely, really, constantly, in our several vocations, to
endeavour, with our Estates and Lives, to preserve and defend
the Kings Majesties Person and Authority, that the world may
bear witnesse with our Consciences of our Loyalty, and that we
have no thoughts or intention to diminish his Majesties just power
and greatnesse:</HI> for indeed we (whatever the world may
think of us) desire to honour his Majesty: 1. For the
Lords sake, by whom Kings reign, who by a special provi∣dence
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
hath set our gracious King over us. 2. For our own
sakes, who though we are not capable of preferment under
his Majesty, yet owe unto him our lives, which he hath par∣doned,
our liberties and estates, which he secures to us, and
the protection he affords us: It is a mercy that we may live
comfortably as Christians, though we cannot be employed
and preferred as Ministers.</P>
<P>2. It is true we have different apprehensions in many
things from other men, and in many things we are other∣wise
minded; but we are resolved, in those things, to which
we have already attained, to walk by the same Rule, to
mind the same things, and if we cannot be of one mind, we
desire to be of one heart; and to preserve unity of affections
in our differ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ces of judgement.</P>
<P>We desire heartily, that the small things we differ in
should not have so much power to divide us, as the great
things we agree in should have to unite; however we beg
of the Lord heartily, that we may live peaceably with all
men; we desire earnestly to seek truth and peace, and to
follow peace and holinesse, without which, we think, we
cannot see the Lord: we desire to be just in our dealing,
harmlesse and innocent in our behaviour and carriage, and
to have our conversation honest in the world, that whereas
some speak against us as evil doers, they may by our good
works, which they shall behold, glorifie God in the day of
visitation; and though we are sorry to hear it, that some
think it strange that we run not with them to the same ex∣cesse
of Ryot, speaking evil of us, yet will we sit still, knowing
that they shall give an account unto him who <HI>judgeth righ∣teous
judgement.</HI></P>
<P>3. Without all dangerous, offensive, or suspitious designs
or complottings, which we abhor, have, we fince the twenty
four of <HI>August,</HI> held up our private Devotions in the Apo∣stles
Doctrine, and fellowship, and breaking bread from
house to house, and in prayers, loving as brethren; at these
our Meetings we plot nothing but the saving of souls, com∣forting
the weak, reclaiming the erroneous, instructing the
ignorant, building poor souls up in their faith, as helpers of
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
their joy, for the perfecting of the Saints, the work of the Mi∣nistry,
the edifying of the body of Christ, and helping our
brethren in the publick ministry, who since our withdraw∣ing
have a great burden lying upon them; some may
preach Christ out of envy, some out of discontent, but
Christ is preached, and we dare boldly say, nothing but
Christ crucified is preached among us: wherefore we re∣joyce,
and we hope they rejoyce too, ever since we hope
without offence we have preached the Word, and have been
instant in season▪ and out of season, reproving, rebuking,
and exhorting with all long-suffering and doctrine: here
have we no thoughts of our King and Countrey, but
thoughts of peace; no words of either, but serious Exhor∣tations
to obedience under the one, and ear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>st prayers for
the peace and prosperity of the other: we <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sire indeed to
converse profitably, to improve our time and opportunities
usefully, to provoke one another to love and to good works.
In obedience to his Majesties Laws for peace and order, we
have no factious Conventicles; in compliance with his
Majesties good inclination, for serious holinesse, for sober
friendship we converse with one another lovingly, we meet
at one anothers habitations friendly and neighbourly, we
open our doubts one to another sincerely, and endeavour to
resolve one another satisfactorily; we pray unanimously,
one reads, another openeth what is read, and presseth home
what is so opened; and so with prayers, and a hymn, and
a little refreshment we dismisse one another, and take our
leave▪ the Prophets speak, two or three, and the others
judge; if any thing be revealed unto another that sitteth
by, the first holdeth his peace, for we all prophecy one by
one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted; but we
must needs say, whatever in suggested to the contrary, that
among us the spirits of the Prophets are subject to the
Prophets; for we own, that God is not the Author of con∣fusion,
but of peace, as in all the Churches of the Saints:
we hope there is so much of the English genius of Friend∣ship
and good nature abroad in the world, that none will
censure us, either for familiar meetings, which are neigh∣bourly,
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
or for making good use of those meetings which
is Christian: Indeed we were unsufferable, if we set up pri∣vate
meetings in opposition to publick Assemblies; but its
a common observation by this time, that we never go toge∣ther
privately the same hour that others meet publickly;
and indeed we are glad when they say unto us, <HI>Let us go up
to the House of God.</HI> One thing we have desired of the Lord,
that while we seek after, that we may dwell in the House of
the Lord all the daies of our lives, to behold the beauty of
the Lord, and to enquire in his Temple. And its seldome
that we escape any opportunities of joyning with the pub∣lick
Assemblies, for though we cannot administer in the
Church, yet we cannot separate from the Church: we
would not partake with the Churches sins, least we be defi∣led;
we would not remove from the Church, least we be
nothing: And indeed we desire only in private to set home
upon our hearts what we have gained in publick; we would
second the Ministers at home, whom we cannot assist a∣broad:
Its true, they of us that fear the Lord, speak often
one to another, but we dare not speak any thing that is a∣miss,
for we know the Lord hearkeneth and heareth us,
and a Book of Remembrance is written before, for them
that fear the Lord, and think upon his Name.</P>
<P>4. Forasmuch as there is no well-affected Christian that
is not deeply sensible of the unsetledness, division, animosi∣ties,
prophaneness, decay of Trade, and other calamities,
whereby our Native Country is exposed to the pity of
Neighbours, and the scorn and insultation of Enemies; we
do effectually endeavour to work our hearts to a sound hu∣miliation
for our own sins, which have contributed too
much to the common calamities, seeing we are so unhappy
as to add to the measure of publick provocations, we can∣not
but be so compassionate, as to endeavour to add to the
measure of publick prayers, humiliations and intercessions.</P>
<P>5. To prevail with God the more effectually, we zeal∣ously
stir up our Neighbours and Friends to be passionately
affected with the present Estate of the Churches and Ser∣vants
of Christ, that as they helped on their miseries by their
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
sins, so they may assist in their recovery, by their tears, sighs
and prayers.</P>
<P>6. We endeavour by all means to gain just notice, and a
true account of the estate of our Native Country; that as
the men of <HI>Issachar,</HI> we may be men understanding the
times, and knowing what <HI>Israel</HI> ought to do; and herein
we observe: First, our sins we allow, to the great dishonor
of the Majesty of the holy God we serve, and the purity
of the holy Gospel we profess: And secondly, the judge∣ments
we lye under, by reason of these sins; our great de∣sign
is to root up the greatest evil, that is Sin, and draw
neer the highest good, that is God, that he would take de∣light
in us to do us good, and would receive us graciously,
and love us freely.</P>
<P>7. We deeply lay to heart, and secretly mourn for the
sins of the people, representing them to our thoughts in
their heynous nature and circumstances, humbly entreating
the Lord for their serious repentance of them, and earnest∣ly
deprecating the judgements provoked by them; so that
we lay together both the evils we feel, and those we have
too just cause to fear, and in a due sense of both, we desire
to humble our selves, and others, under the mighty hand of
God.</P>
<P>8. And therefore whensoever we have an opportunity to
speak from God to his people in the publick Assemblies,
we desire to speak a present truth, and to lay open and be∣wail
the sins of the time, and to awake the people with all
zealous exhortation to a lively and just sorrow for all
the overflowings of wickedness, and to a vehement and
godly striving against the stream thereof by their prayers and
utmost endeavours, day and night constantly pouring out
their hearts in strong cryes and servent prayer to our God,
that he will be pleased to visit us in mercy and compassion,
and cause the light of his countenance to shine upon us.</P>
<P>9. And however, privately we set apart one day at least
in every week for this holy end and purpose, wherein we
humble our selves in private fasting and prayer, till it please
our God to return to his in his wonted pity and compassi∣on,
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
and put an end to our sins and miseries, recovering us
to that first state of Innocence, peace and plenty, which we
were happy in before our late miscarriages.</P>
<P>10. We do restrain our wonted pleasure, not allowing the
liberty of that mirth and lawful refreshment which we
might formerly make use of, while the hand of God lieth
thus heavily upon us.</P>
<P>11. We do not allow our selves the neglect of any good
means of prayer, reading, meditation and conference,
whereby the peace and welfare of this Church and State
may be procured and maintained, and shall carefully avoid
all words and actions, ways and means, which may at all
tend to the widening of the unhappy breaches, and the en∣creasing
the many and woful differences among us, <HI>seeking
peace,</HI> and <HI>ensuing it,</HI> studying now in our leisure time, to
look into the bottom of Controversies, that we may bring
differences to as narrow a compass as we can, beget a mu∣tual
good understanding and satisfaction among sober
men, clearing up things as far as lieth in our power for the
reuniting of all honest and faithful hearts in a firm concord
of Christian love, endeavouring to discover and defeat
all the devices and machinations of Satan, and his En∣gines,
against the peace and welfare of the Church in all
parts of the world, especially in these wherein we are
interested.</P>
<P>12. And particularly <HI>considering our selves,</HI> our own mis∣carriages
and infirmities, we shall not as afore fly out upon
the weakness, defects, or excesses of our Fathers or Brethren,
aggravating the blame of those their actions or Opinions,
which may be capable of a gentler or milder construction,
resolving to look as charitably upon all their proceedings,
who are otherwise minded in matters of an inferiour Na∣ture,
bending our whole endeavours against known sin, and
open prophaness, the great Enemies of our peace and settle∣ment:
As we have preached, so we desire to live, that chari∣ty
that suffereth long, and is kind, is not easily provoked,
thinketh no evil, beareth all things, believeth all things,
hopeth all things, endureth all things.</P>
<P><PB N="8" REF="6"/>
13. And to that purpose we have first of all laid aside all
our lesser Opinions among our selves, and our little separa∣tions
and divisions, and resolvedly knit our selves together
in an entire affection one to another, that by this all men
may know <HI>that we are Christs Disciples, because we love one a∣nother,</HI>
and are ready to shew all mutual respects of Christi∣an
love, and observance to each other upon all occasion
loving as Brethren: As likewise we shall in all meekness of
spirit lovingly converse with, and kindly, affectionate to,
and respectful towards all our Fathers and Brethren in
their places, living without offence, and blameless.</P>
<P>14. We mourn, but not <HI>as men without hope;</HI> that our
gracious God will find out a way to have mercy upon us,
and to chear up his countenance towards all his Chosen
Ones, wiping (as that holy Bishop said) <HI>all tears from their
eyes, and all spots from their faces,</HI> and answering the holy
desires of their hearts, in shewing them <HI>Sion</HI> in perfect beau∣ty,
and that not by overturning any part of the Govern∣ment,
but by opening our hearts to see our errours, and
close one with another, by turning the heart of <HI>the Father
towards the Child, and of the Child towards the Father, least God
come and smite the earth with dicurse.</HI></P>
<P>15. In the mean time we possess our Souls in patience,
and we keep silence before God, waiting upon him that hi∣deth
his face from <HI>Jacob;</HI> for his Spirit of love, unity, peace
and concord, resolving to continue thus doing, till we re∣ceive
an answer from heaven.</P>
<P>16. Its true, there are many of us whose bodies will not
bear that austerity of fasting and humiliation which our
cause may require, yet they that cannot fast do pray, and
they that cannot spare a day in seven, can spare an hour in
twelve, and make up the rest in frequent and servent ejacu∣lations.</P>
<P>17. Whereas some have pretended that we set up a Go∣vernment
within a Government, and that we have an Au∣thority
among our selves, we must let the world know we
are all equal, and we have no formality or Ceremony a∣mong
us, but a free and voluntary entrance, left open for
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
all comers into this strict course of Christian Austerity,
without any noyse, without the required notice of any,
but God and their own conscience, that all may well know
and see, that here is no design than meerly Spiritual, aim∣ing
at nothing but Religious Transactions, between God
and our own Souls, and consisting in the performance of
the unquestionable exercises of Piety and holy Devotion.</P>
<P>18. Since we have been uncapable of speaking to the
people the things that are of everlasting concernment, we
have recommended to them the writings of good men, pi∣ous
and peaceable, who being <HI>dead yet speak,</HI> and poor men
we know may read a good book, when they cannot hear a
good man; and we our selves teach them from house to
house, with tears day and night, as the Apostles did, leaving
with them such books as Mr. <HI>Baxters Call,</HI> his <HI>Now or Ne∣ver,</HI>
his <HI>Directions for Peace of Conscience,</HI> his <HI>Saints Everlast∣ing
Rest,</HI> Mr <HI>Bolton,</HI> Dr. <HI>Sibbs,</HI> Mr. <HI>Perkins,</HI> Mr. <HI>Dod,</HI> and
Dr. <HI>Preston.</HI></P>
<P>19. We settle mens judgements upon most firm and solid
principles, leading to peace and holiness, leading them
through that safe and middle way that is equally distant
from all the extremes men have run into in their hearts a∣bout
some points of Religion, as particularly in the
points now in difference among us, we teach our people,
that though we cannot conform to the Church without sin,
yet they cannot separate from it without sin; we cannot
administer according to the prescribed form, but we and
they can hear according to it; we must joyn with the
Church in our duties, though we are not guilty of her in∣firmities;
we teach them that it is one thing to hold com∣munion
with a Church that is under some miscarriages, and
another thing to act those miscarriages; what we chiefly
insist on, are things much comporting and agreeing with
the spirit of the Scriptures, and things that are most pro∣per
to build men up in their most holy Faith, and to pro∣mote
the power of godliness in their hearts and lives.</P>
<P>20. Its true, we desire to settle our peoples hearts upon
all occasions, but always offering them such things as tend
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
to peace and quietness, and godliness of living, dealing
as faithfully with them, as those who must give an account;
and if therefore we have any interest with them, we improve
for God our Soveraign, and the Church of Christ, for
whose distressed members we sometimes solicit them with
success, and find them willing above their strength and abi∣lity,
and we hope the Lord will not forget their work and
labour of love, and yet we desire not to wrong any Mi∣nister
in his place, for indeed we stated the point of Mini∣sters
maintenance upon such grounds, that we are perswa∣ded
no sober Christian, with whom we have any interest,
will withdraw any thing that is due from any man that la∣bours
in the Word and Doctrine, and watches for their
Souls: And though we are otherwise represented, yet our
great endeavour is, by a discreet interposition to allay and
fix the people to a due temperament (gently guiding some
mens well-meaning zeal by such rules of moderation, as are
best to restore and preserve the health and peace of this
Church and Kingdome, much pleasing our selves in that
good and firm understanding which would thence grow
between his most Excellent Majesty and his good people,
all jealousies being laid aside, our own and our Posterities
Interest lay before us many strong obligations to seek and
preserve the peace and welfare of the Land of our Nativity;
the offence which some mens dangerous medling and over∣busie
interpositions have contracted upon our profession, we
have resolved to expiate by such moderations for the future,
as might not only check the excesses of our practise, but of
our Opinions too, no men having a greater kindness for
peace and settlement preserved in truth, unity and order,
then our selves, whom it most concerns, whether we consi∣der
our consciences; callings or interests, as knowing, that
nothing undermines to much in our Authority and Call∣ing,
as those dangerous dissentions wherein the people learn
to shake off both.</P>
<P>21. It is true, we cannot own that Episcopacy now esta∣blished,
so as to undertake it our selves, yet we would sub∣mit
to it as to every Ordinance of man for the Lords sake,
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
whether to the King as Supreme, or to those <HI>who are sent
by him,</HI> whose great charges and care is like enough to
betray them to some errours, and many enemies, whereof
they canno but contract good store, while so eminent and
so active, they provoke that envy which improved to a po∣pular
<HI>odium,</HI> is able to overcast the highest Merit and Inte∣grity;
wherefore the Bishops have our prayers, pity, and as∣sistance;
and although we cannot in our judgement ap∣prove
all that they do, driven it may be rather by the▪ tem∣per
of the people and unhappiness of this age, then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
their own disposition to any height and rigour of action;
yet we allow not that their persons or Government should
be exposed to the malapartness of the loose and irreverent
multitude, who take a bold liberty to despise <HI>Dominions,</HI>
and to speak evil of <HI>Dignities,</HI> whereas we have always
taught, that men should cheerfully submit to the Authori∣ty,
when they cannot in <HI>Conscience</HI> allow all the practises of
those that are over them in the Lord: Indeed, we never
met with a more perplexed conjuncture of affairs, then the
late business of Bishops, when between our unsatisfiedness
in <HI>Conscience</HI> under that <HI>Government,</HI> and the woful necessi∣ty
if we shaked off that of being under none, we run head,
long to that which we thought then expedient, rather then
we should suffer some <HI>inconvenience</HI> under that which, well
regulated we must▪ always approve as just, preferring the
humour of some particular men, before the reason of the
Christian World: Well experience hath taught us▪ that
we had better live where nothing is lawful, then where all
things are so; that Anarchy is the greatest oppression, li∣centiousness
the greatest grievance and an unbounded liber∣ty
the greatest slavery▪</P>
<P>22. Indeed we allow it for weaker Christians, who
have not their hearts enlarged with an ability to express
their own wants and desires, both lawful and convenient
to help themselves in prayer, the use of a prescribed form,
wherein they may have their own case and condition more
pithily and affectionately then they are able to express it
themselves, and if the use of such a form do prove a means
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
to warm the affections, and enkindle their grace, we
looking not upon it as any quenching of the Spirit, it be∣ing
not in our apprehension essential to the nature of pray∣er,
that it be either read, or rehearsed by memory, or by
immediate suggestion, but rather that it be delivered out
of the book, or out of the heart, with <HI>understanding</HI> and
suitable affections, with humility and confidence, and an
inward sense of our <HI>condition;</HI> nor is there any great diffe∣rence
betwixt repeating by memory, and reading out of a
book, the memory being but a kind of invisible book for
the register of our thoughts, though in this case it should
be especially remembred, that in the use of such prescript
forms, to which a man hath been accustomed, he ought to
be narrowly watchful over his own heart, for fear of that
lip-service and formality which in such cases we are more e∣specially
exposed unto; but yet for any one so to fit and sa∣tisfie
himself with his Prayer-book, as to go no further,
this were still to remain in his <HI>Infancy,</HI> and never grow in
grace or gifts; and withall, its very hard for a man to find a
prescribed form that may suit with our several emergencies;
and therefore indeed we do not tye our selves so precisely
to any particular form of words, though of our own
composing, and fitted to our <HI>condition,</HI> but that we may ei∣ther
add or alter, according as our emergent occasion, or
some new affection suggested shall require: Sometimes we
feel our hearts more warm, our desires more vigorous, and
our expressions more copious and ready: And in this case
we suffer not our selves to be streightened or confined to any
form, but take our liberty to expatiate more freely, accord∣ing
as we find our inward: in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>argements.</P>
<P>23. Amongst all the stratagems of Satan, whereby he
would undermine Religion, and pervert the souls of men,
though there cannot be any more unreasonable, yet there
was never any more unhappily successful then the raising
and cherishing fears and jealousies in the world, that Reli∣gion
in the height and exaltation of it, is an Enemy to Go∣vernment;
and that to be a through-paced, a sincere and
zealous Christian, is to be dangerous to the State: We
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
therefore, as Ministers of this Religion, are bold in the evi∣dence
&amp; truth of the Gospel, to say that (whatever the men
of the world judge of us) we profess Christian Religion
in so harmless and innocent a way, that we have studied
and endeavoured to state the Rights of <HI>Civil Government</HI>
upon the clearest and firmest principles, to secure them by
the most powerful obligation, and to urge them upon men
by the most efficacious motives of rewards and punishments
in the world: And we profess sincerely, that we look upon
our late miscarriages as most unhappy scandals to our Reli∣gion,
and those ingaged in them so for us, to persist still
as Enemies to the Cross of Christ, and men born to bring
our holy Christian profession into jealousie, suspition, and
disgrace with the powers of the earth, and to stir up the
Kings of the earth to stand up, and the Rulers to take coun∣sel
together against the Lord, and against his Christ, that
they should break their bonds in sunder, and cast their cords
from them: We are so sensible of the original and institu∣tion
of Government, of the end and use of it, in respect of
good and evil men, and thereof the necessity of subjection
for <HI>Conscience</HI> sake, and of the sin and danger of resisting
an <HI>Ordinance</HI> of God, considering that they who resist pri∣vately
or openly by word or deed, resist to their own dam∣nation;
that we cannot allow any person upon any pre∣tence
whatsoever, in any manner whatsoever, to vilifie, de∣spise,
murmure against, disparage, undermine, or oppose
lawful Authority that is set over him, we say upon any
pretence whatsoever, either 1. In respect of the person go∣verning,
as Errour, Heresie, Idolatry, harsh Administration,
or the like, in which cases the servants of God in all Ages
had no other remedy but patience, and prayer, and crying
mightily to the Lord, 1 <HI>Sam</HI> 8. 9, 11, 12, 18. as they did
under <HI>Tiberius, Caligula, Claudius</HI> and <HI>Nero,</HI> those Monsters
of mankind. Or 2. In respect of the persons governed, be
they never so holy seeing, best of men, yea God and Man in
this case obeyed unto the death. 3. In respect of any causes
whatsoever, though it be Religion, whereof we conceive
the Magistrate ought to have the greatest care, so that we
are perswaded in our <HI>Consciences,</HI> that to them who have
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
imbraced Christianity in the true and genuine spirit of it, as
we hope we have all done; and to those who without vile
affections, and carnal interests, shall apply themselves to
know the mind of God delivered in Scripture: As we hope
we do with peaceable submission, and patience is a clear duty
under any Government; so that though the Spirit of the Ru∣ler
be stirred against them, yet they cannot stir out of their
place.</P>
<P>24. And as we are thus justly affected to Soveraignty, as
knowing by whom the powers are ordained, as we dare not
curse the King in our heart, or revile the Ruler of the peo∣ple,
much lesse slander the footsteps of Gods Anointed; as
we submit for conscience sake to every Ordinance of God;
yea to every Ordinance of man for the Lords sake, not da∣ring
to disobey in regard of the Oath of God; and pay
custome where custome, and tribute where tribute. So in∣deed
whatever apprehensions men have of us abroad in the
world, we desire to fill up every relation conscionably and
faithfully according to the Rule, and as men that desire to
approve our selves to God and men; as 1. to our calling, we
desire to be faithful, neither suppressing nor corrupting the
truth, to take heed to our selves, and to all the flock of God,
over which the holy Ghost hath made us overseers, to feed
the Church of God which he hath purchased with his own
blood: We desire to speak from the heart to the heart, to
feel in our selves what we speak, to others; that we may
serve God with our spirit in the Gospel of his Son, that we
may save our selves and those that hear us; that we may
walk from love to God, to the glory of God, and the sal∣vation
of our souls, as able, faithful, resolute, industrious, in
preparing <HI>for,</HI> and exercising of our Ministry, and as com∣passionate
of souls, preaching the Word purely, plainly, pru∣de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tly,
powerfully and sincerely, administring the Sacra∣ments
carefully, instructing our Flocks, advising, admonish∣ing,
and comforting them as we see occasion; being good
examples to Believers, in words in conversation, in charity,
in spirit, in faith, in purity and waiting upon God for suc∣cess:
We desire to be neither too austere in our retiredness,
nor too cheap in our sociablenesse, but carrying so even a
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>
hand, that our discreet affableness may be free from con∣tempt,
and that we may win our people with a loving con∣versation;
as secondly to our Relation, first to our Fami∣lier,
we desire to be the mouth of our people to God by con∣stant
prayers, and the mouth of God to our people by whol∣some
Instructions, and holy Admonitions, loving, tender,
and careful of our nearest Relations, devoting them to
Gods service, and committing them to his care, providing
yet for them honest things in the sight of men, and going
before them in good examples of piety and holy conversa∣tion,
and so over-looking them, as they that have more then
meer bodies committed to our charge: We desire to be fa∣miliar,
meek, humble, and courteous towards all, and
helpful one way or other to our neighbour, as they that
think our selves born to do good, maintaining peace and
love at home and abroad.</P>
<P>25. We think we have fully informed our selves in all the
necessary points of Religion; and we are so firmly ground∣ed
in those fundamental and saving truths, that we will not
be carried about with every wind of doctrine; as for cir∣cumstances,
we neither neglect them, nor yet too eagerly
pursue after them; we receive nothing in Religion upon
trust: nor dare we absolutely follow any guide, but such as
we are sure cannot erre; we have some hours for specula∣tion,
but our Life is to reduce knowledge to practice, and so
much we think we know, as we can live; where we are con∣vinced
we we can submit, where we must dissent we can be si∣lent,
and where we dissent from the Church, we desire to
examine throughly whether we are deceived; we keep close
to those truths which do most promote the glory and grace
of God, the reformation of men, and the salvation of souls:
<HI>Whosoever therefore by pride, or faction, or schisme, or ambition,
or novel fancies, and arrogance, or ignorance, or sedition, or
popularity, or vain-glory, or envy or discontent, or corrospon∣dence,
or any other carnal reason shall cause divisions or offences
by teaching any other doctrine then what we have received, we
look not upon him as the Servant of Christ.</HI></P>
<P>26. We desire we may not be judged for our austere
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>
conversation and strict life; for we desire, so to speak, and
so to do, as they that shall be judged by the Law of Liberty:
We would our discourse were grave, discreet, pertinent,
free from vanity, free from offence: We allow our selves no
corrupt or unsavoury communication; in worldly affairs
we desire nothing may fall from us but what is seasonable
and well advised; in spiritual, such as may minister grace
to the hearers, and such as is sparing and charitable, allow∣ing
neither detraction nor censure; not meddling with any
matters of State▪ but keeping our selves within compasse,
only desiring to understand the times, that we might know
what <HI>Israel</HI> ought to do: In word and actions we desire to
walk circumspectly, to avoid all appearance of evil; to
walk as in sincerity, as in truth, and as in the sight of God;
exercising our selves to a good Conscience, void of offence
towards God and towards men; willing in all things to
live honestly, and endeavouring to live without rebuke in
the middest of a crooked and perverse generation; and if
we are more earnest and serious then ordinarily, you must
know, that we are sensible <HI>how short time is, what eternity is,</HI>
and <HI>what are our immortal souls,</HI> and <HI>what that God is with
whom we have to do.</HI> Our recreation we desire may be safe,
inoffensive and moderate in time and measure, such as may
refresh a tired body and mind, and not effeminate or de∣bauch
them, we would indeed rejoyce, as if we rejoyced not.
We allow our selves so far creature-enjoyments, as nature
requires, and grace moderates, and our God blesseth: we
redeem our time, considering it is not our own improving it
to our best advantage; we know a day or a night well
spent, makes way for Eternity. We desire to be very obser∣vant
of our outward conversation, but we look chiefly at
our inward frame; we live by the precepts, we live upon the
promises, we affect not singularity, we aim at sincerity, our
Habits commend us not to God, yet by our Habits we
would not give offence unto men; our devotion we desire
may be with fear and reverence on the one hand, and with
Faith and sincerity on the other, we watch unto prayer,
and we watch after prayer; and indeed we desire always
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
to watch and be sober, fearing in adversity, and rejoycing in
tribulation, knowing that tribulation provoketh patience,
and patience experience, and experience hope, and hope
maketh not ashamed.</P>
<P>27. Our indeavours to keep a good understanding at
Court by our Friends and Brethren, is loaded by our ene∣mies
(for so some would be still, notwithstanding his Ma∣jesties
endeavours for pacification) with all the obloquies
and exasperations imaginable, and looked upon by some
indifferent men with jealousies and fears; but these men
know not the just motives and pregnant grounds with
which we think our selves furnished for those undertakings,
God knows it is not any interest or party we desire to serve
there, but we pursue the peace and good of the Kingdome,
and endeavour to prevent future dangers, which we may
foresee will in all likelihood follow some mens activity (if
not restrained) by a moderate Interest; not as if we would
stop the course of Law, or weaken Authority, but that we
desire heartily, as many honourable Persons do, with his
Majesty and his Father of blessed memory, <HI>That no Party or
Interest be exasperated</HI> (and the multitude are easier exa∣sperated
then appeased) <HI>by crossnesse, and asperity of some mens
passions, humours or private opinions, grounded only upon diffe∣rences
in lesser matters, which are but the skirts and subburbs of
Religion; wherein</HI> (as his late Majesty of renowned Memo∣ry
observed, as an Angel of God) <HI>a charitable counivance
and Christian toleration of sin dissipates their strength, whom
rougher opposition fortifieth, and puts the despised and oppressed
party into such combinations as may most enable them, yet a full
revenge on those they count their persecutors, who are commonly
assisted with that vulgar commiseration, which attends all that are
said to suffer under the notion of Religion.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Indeed we only desire (what that famous Prince wished)
viz.</HI> That solid piety, and those fundamental truths (which
mend both hearts and lives of men) be kept up and encouraged
with equal justice and impartial favour; and that the outward
circumstances and formalities of Religion devour not all, or the
best encouragement, of learning, industry and piety, but that with
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>
an equall eye and impartial hand favours and rewards he distri∣ted
among all men, as they are found, for their real goodnesse,
both in ability and fidelity worthy and capable of them: This,
<HI>saith that excellent Prince,</HI> will be sure to gain the hearts of
the most, and the best too, who though they be not good them∣selves,
yet are glad to see the severer wayes of virtue at any
time sweetned by temporal rewards.</P>
<P>And though it be suggested, that we are not to be trusted
about his Majesty, although we can make it appear, that
since his Majesty was restored we have passed three years
with so much innocence, and so little compliance with any
Interest or Faction, that not one publick action we did since,
but is capable of a fair and equitable plea; yet since an Act
of Indempnity and Religion is passed, we think it our duty
so for to comply with his Majesties Intention in granting
that Act, as not to mention any thing, how defensible soever,
which he hath commanded should be utterly forgotten, but
to give our present sence of things, we can sincerely professe,
that we have not only a Loyal, but a most affectionate
esteem for his Majesties Person and Government; for since,
besides the general obligation of Subjects, we are bound by
our Religion to prize gratitude above all things; we could
not be just, should we not most earnestly desire the happi∣nesse
of that Prince, unto whose single endeavours we owe
all our Liberty; for we all acknowledge, that his Majesties
personal and passionate interposings did confirm our <HI>In∣dempnity,</HI>
and his most pious and unequalled <HI>Declarations</HI>
have satisfactorily evidenced, that he is not unwilling to in∣dulge
the utmost extent of sober and Christian Liberty,
which, as we have elsewhere professed, are expressions of so
much goodness in the midst of so great power, and after <HI>so∣many
provocations,</HI> that he hath not the heart of a man, much
lesse of a Christian, that hath not a due sence of them; we
are sure they have so throughly possessed us, that if in any
publick action of ours there be any Instance that can be
wrested to the disparagement of his Majesties Royal Autho∣rity
and Government: we intreat the world to take notice,
that we do hereby utterly disown it, as being directly con∣trary
to our professed Principles, which lead us to no one
<PB N="19" REF="11"/>
point of outward practice more strictly and powerfully then
an exact and punctual obedience to his Majesties Com∣mands,
and a chearful submission to his Authority. And
once for all, now it hath pleased his Majesty to enjoyn an
outward conformity, to which we cannot in all things
subscribe, we are resolved, the Lord assisting us, to submit
with chearfulnesse, and to suffer with silence, for as there is
an active disobedience, which is to resist, so there is a passive
disobedience, that is, to repine, neither of which can we by
any means approve of; since whatever we cannot consci∣enciously
do, we think our selves obliged to suffer for, with
as much joy, and with as little resistance, as if any other act
of obedience were called for from us. We may perhaps be
too partial to our selves; but certainly in general we may
pronounce, that whoever is of this temper, whatever his
judgement be, as touching things indifferent in their own
nature, yet he cannot be supposed incompatible with wayes
of publick safety. And over and above all, we are not ca∣pable
of being dangerous to this Government, but by our
Representatives in Parliament, who are now men of such
unspotted integrity towards his Majesties Person and Go∣vernment,
that it is a wonder if malice it self can find the
least suspition of danger.</P>
<P>28. It is true (as some say) that by our diligence,
good husbandry, and the blessing of God upon our endea∣vours,
we have got among us a considerable part of the
treasure of this Land; for we are a people that improve our
time, and follow our businesse, as whose strict profession for∣bids
us those excesses which swallow up other mens time
and estates; Hounds, Hawks, Games, Wine, Women, Playes,
and other vanities, have neither our thoughts nor our pur∣ses,
which we reserve for higher advantage, which we con∣stantly
watch, and as constantly meet with (so great an ad∣vantage
hath the sober against the intemperate) yet out of
what we have, are we ready upon all occasions to assist his
Majesty, and support his Government; yea if, as some would
have, it should please his Majesty to impose upon us a Levy
for our former miscarriages, his Indulgence to us, and for
<PB N="20" REF="12"/>
the peace and tranquillity we enjoy under him, it should be
parted with as chearfully as ever we parted with money in
the heat of the late trouble; neither would we so anxi∣ously
look upon what is gone of our estate, as we would
thankfully take notice of what remains. It is true, we have
got estates some of us in the late troubles, and now we have
places about the King, and indeed we know not how to ex∣piate
former transgression against his late Majesty, but by
endeavouring to be as capable as we can to serve his Son:
Among our many failings we hoped this would have been
none, that we used all means to get into his Majesties ser∣vice,
no place escaping us that could be had for love or mo∣ney;
as we have done amisse, not out of malice, but misin∣formation,
or misapprehension of things, so we hope none
shall be more loyal and faithful then we, who, sensible of our
errours and our injuries, do feel in our own souls most ve∣hement
motives to repentance, and earnest desires to make
some repairations for former defects.</P>
<P>For his Majesties and his Fathers faithful Souldiers and
Subjects, who out of conscience sunk in the same ruine with
their Liege, Lord and Soveraign, we declare, upon all occa∣sions,
when we are called to it, that we think it necessary for
publick settlement, that they should be provided for as may
be just and expedient; such valour and gallantry we con∣fesse
they have shewed, that we heartily wish we may never
want such men to serve our Soveraign, to maintain his Laws
and Kingdomes in such a peace, as wherein they may enjoy
their share and proportion as much as any men; and so
wish withall, that we did close so unanimously in one com∣mon
subjection, that there were no note of distinction left,
and no quarrel remain but this one, <HI>viz. who should be most
Loyal and faithful:</HI> we would have our fellow Subjects live
as strictly and as warily as we do, and they will see, the very
money that is spent upon their vanities would procure them
places as well as ours does us: and as for such of them as
the iniquity of the times, or their own faults have made
poor, our very excesses would support them, and what we
throw away idly would relieve them: we are ready to joyn
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>
in any expedient that may accommodate all grievances,
that if it be possible we may have no more complaining in
our streets. In a word, those that are well inclined on all
sides are ready to agree, but that there are some crafty and
subtle men on both sides, that would keep our distances and
animosities to serve their private ends, which they propose
sometimes to themselves out of the publick ruine, aggrava∣ting
all things with the most odious circumstances, and en∣deavouring
to inflame the vulgar to a temper uncapable of
restraint or Government, that now we are at such a di∣stance,
we look upon it as no lesse a providence, that God
keeps the people within the bound of Law, and the reve∣rence
of Authority, then that he keeps the Sea within its
channel, and the waters within their banks. And thus in∣deed
since our seclusion have we endeavoured to approve
our selves Gods faithful Children and Servants by honour
and dishonour, by evil report and good report, as deceivers,
and yet true.</P>
<P>29. The great discourse of the Nation at this time is their
Taxations, from which some would perswade the world
we under our present discontent make some advantage, in
reference to which our sense hath been always this: 1. That
all our payments are our advantage, we allow his Majesty
a part of our Estate, to secure the whole; we support his
<HI>Government,</HI> he protects our lives and estates from that rage
and rapine which in a few daies may destroy the industry of
many years; we teach men constantly not to be so imperti∣nent,
as to complain of any common charge or burthen
which seems necessary to the present policy, under which
we may have leave to live peaceable and quiet lives, in all
godliness and honesty; no safety to us without the restraint
of other mens lust and violence, and no restraint, without
a <HI>Government</HI> that is able to raise a constant guard to every
man that would live securely under his own Vine, and un∣der
his own Fig-tree.</P>
<P>We know that there are four pillars of Government and
Order. 1. Religion, that setleth the heart of men. 2. Ju∣stice,
that ordereth their lives. 3. Counsel, that may apply
<PB N="22" REF="13"/>
the Rules of Justice and Religion to particular occasions.
4. Treasure, which last is so necessary, that without it, Offi∣cers
will be corrupted, Counsels betrayed, Armies ill paid
and disciplined, Trade obstructed, and a poor Nation will
lye open to the dangerous attempts of an untoward people
at home, and the unneighbourly encroachments of potent
Princes abroad. 2. All payments are of our own imposing,
by our consent in Parliament. 3. Our late miscarriages oc∣casion
our present grievances. 4. Yet we are not now under
the eighth part of former payments: We tell our people,
that our King affords us Christian protection, and there∣fore
we may very well allow him dutiful assistance, by our
lives, estates and prayers.</P>
<P>30. Here we thought to have concluded, but that there
remains two particulars more, whereof we think fit to
give an account, and then we shall set a period to this im∣portunity.</P>
<P>The first is this; <HI>viz.</HI> Why we have been so importunate,
both a little before the 24 of <HI>August,</HI> and ever since, against
Popery.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Its true, that we had verily thought Popery had
rendred it self justly odious, by its own abominations in
doctrine, worship, and bloudy slaughters, and that in these
daies of light and knowledge, to imagine a possibility of
its return upon the Protestant Churches, (which yet hath
been the <HI>Opinion</HI> of divers eminent for Learning and Godli∣ness
among us) was groundless fear, where no fear was:
yet really considering: 1. The vast numbers of Popish E∣missaries,
Priests and Jesuites that swarm among us, English
Colledges, as we are certified, being much emptied by the
reason of multitudes sent hither, whose ways are subtil
and close, whose industry is indefatigable, whose influ∣ence
and efficacy upon all sorts of persons is powerful,
whose support from abroad is past finding out. 2. The
printing and vending so many English Popish books, which
considering the Apostasie of some, the indifference of o∣thers,
distracted by our unhappy divisions, cannot speak
less then a great inclination to a revolt to Popery. 3. The
<PB N="23" REF="13"/>
toleration of Popery publickly by them pleaded for. 4. The
Jesuites designs and models of reducing <HI>England</HI> to <HI>Romes</HI>
obedience, followed and promoted by many deluded Pro∣testants.
5. The union of forreign Popish power, which
how soon the Court of <HI>Rome</HI> (being ever vigilant to improve
such occasions for the propagation of its own greatness)
may make use of, for the extirpation of the Protestant Re∣ligion;
we need not divine. 6. The whole body of Popery
published by Sectaries, especially <HI>Quakers;</HI> upon these con∣siderations
we were awakened, <HI>to contend earnestly for the
faith once delivered to the Saints;</HI> having not the least thought
of any dangerous intimations to the people, as if our Go∣vernours
or Government (both which we think in our con∣sciences
clear in that matter) had any inclinations for, or
were to give any countenance to that Mystery of Iniquity:
And it was therefore that we recommend to our beloved
Congregations: 1. The love of the truth in sincerity. 2. Se∣rious
endeavours to heal the sad breaches and divisions
which are among us. 3. To read good books. 4. To make
<HI>Conscience</HI> of all Family duties. 5. To attend on publick
Ordinances. 6. To be well grounded in the principles of
Religion, and to watch over their hearts.</P>
<P>2. It was given out, that we the dissembling Party had
made an accommodation among our selves, the naked truth
whereof is this; indeed we have endeavoured to follow the
things that make for peace, which we have reduced to
these heads following.</P>
<P>1. Peace with God; if our ways please the Lord, our E∣nemies
will be at peace with us.</P>
<P>1. Of Nature in one common grace, wrought in us
by one Spirit; if we had all one new Nature, we should
have all one mind.</P>
<P>2. Of Judgement; 1. In principles of Doctrine which
we draw up; which are 1. Few. 2. Plain. 3. Weighty.
4. Clear. 5. Subservient to godliness. 6. Universally pro∣fessed.</P>
<P>2. Principles of obedience of Worship, of govern∣ment
contained in the ten Commandments, the Lords
Prayer, the Belief, and the Scripture.</P>
<P><PB N="24" REF="14"/>
3. Of affections; one heart where there cannot be
one mind, kindly affectionate one to another, loving as
Brethren.</P>
<P>4. Of ends; they that agree in the end, will in time
agree in the means.</P>
<P>2. Unity; and that Scripture.</P>
<P>3. Uniformity; that every thing be done according to
Scripture, decency and order, that we be one of one way,
and of one mind, and walk by the same Rule.</P>
<P>4. Order; none stirring out of his place, all studying
to be quiet, and to follow their own business peaceably and
obediently, knowing them that rule over them.</P>
<P>5. The power of Grace and Religion, which is a wis∣dome
from above; first pure, then peaceable, and the pow∣er
of Religion makes for peace. 1. By subduing lusts,
whence come worse. 2. By working that love that beareth
all things, &amp;c. 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 13. 3. By enlightening the mind, dif∣ference
come from ignorance, if we have grace to practise
what we know, God will reveal other things in due time,
and we shall all agree. 4. By subduing that covetousness,
ambition, pride, envy, &amp;c. that disturb the world. 5. The
power of Grace in us will convince all men, that God is in
us of a truth, and so will pacifie the world.</P>
<P>The 6th thing that makes for peace, a great care of weak
and wilful ignorance, which is lazy, and will not search for
truth; bashful, and is ashamed to do it; sullen, and will
not understand.</P>
<P>7. Take care of interest private or publick; keep up a
frame of spirit that looks rather what is just, necessary and
true, then what is expedient and useful.</P>
<P>8. Be humble and teachable, neither proud nor self∣conceited
pertinacy, nor think seriously on this obvious
truth, a man may erre: put on meekness and long-suffer∣ing.</P>
<P>9. Take care of respect of persons, and of prejudice.</P>
<P>10. Be deliberate and sober, proving all things.</P>
<P>11. Have a zeal always guided by knowledge.</P>
<P>12. Let nothing be done through strife, or vain-glory.</P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="14"/>
13. Prudently suspend your judgement and practise, and
if you have faith, have it to thy self.</P>
<P>14. All lawful condiscention and forbearance one with
another, forbearing and receiving one another, and bear∣ing
one anothers burden.</P>
<P>15. Wait by prayer on the God of peace, for your
selves, for your Ministers, for your Magistrates.</P>
<P>16. Mark them that cause divisions, and avoid them.</P>
<P>17. Give up your selves to your faithful Ministers, whose
faith follow, considering the end of their conversation.</P>
<P>18. Be wise unto sobriety, and rather believe then di∣spute,
avoiding all unnecessary questions.</P>
<P>19. Take care of an Innovating Spirit, stand in the
way, ask which is the good way, and walk therein, and
you will find rest for your Souls.</P>
<P>20. Consider one another, so as to provoke one another
to love, and to good works.</P>
<P>21. Let the spirits of the Prophets be subject to the Pro∣phets.</P>
<P>22. Correct and keep down the rising of our knowledge
with humility in our selves, and charity towards others.</P>
<P>23. So long as there is sound agreement in fundamental
truths, and in the simplicity of the Gospel, silence all di∣sputes,
in matters meerly notional and curious, which have
no necessary influence into faith and godly living.</P>
<P>24. Let there be a joynt obedience to the truths wherein
all agree, and pursuance of the end which all profess, where∣unto
we have already attained; let us walk by the same
Rule, let us mind the same things, <HI>Phil.</HI> 3. 26.</P>
<P>25. Out of a serious and single-hearted love of truth,
let us address our selves to the search of holy Scriptures.</P>
<P>26. A mutual and brotherly love, which is a very great
means to work upon the judgements of one another, and
to take off all impediments as usually arise from personal
prejudice in disquisition of truth.</P>
<P>27. Keep your selves to the Analogy of faith, the form
of sound words:</P>
<P>28. Labour against the inward grounds of contention, as
<PB N="26" REF="15"/>
pride, self-love, envy, malice and covetousness, and en∣deavour
after a meek, charitable, yielding, and submissive
disposition of heart and frame of spirit, that may let fall
private interest for the publick.</P>
<P>29. Meet and converse together for a mutual good, un∣derstanding
of one another.</P>
<P>30. Wait upon God for further illumination in all
truth.</P>
<P>31. Let the grounds of Religion be laid by Catechising.</P>
<P>32. Suppress the beginning of religious debates, by a
fair and amicable communication among your selves.</P>
<P>Thus we have given a sincere account of our selves, which
we beseech the Lord to bless, to confirm the weak, to direct
the doubtful, to convince gain-sayers, and to gain peace∣able
and sober men favour with God and men.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="27" REF="15"/>
<HEAD>A
SOLEMN VOW
That we have taken.</HEAD>
<P>VVE the Ministers of the Gospel, in the
Kingdomes of <HI>England, Scotland,</HI> and
<HI>Ireland,</HI> living under one King, and being of one
Reformed Religion, having before our eyes the glory
of God, and the advancement of the Kingdome of our
Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, the honour and hap∣piness
of the Kings Majesty, and his Posterity, and
the true publick liberty, safety, and peace of the
Kingdomes wherein every ones private condition is
included, and calling to mind the treacherous and
bloudy Plots, Conspiracies, Attempts, and practises
of the Enemies of God against the true Religion, and
Professors thereof in all places, especially in these
three Kingdomes, ever since the Reformation of Re∣ligion,
and how much their rage, power, and pre∣sumption
are of late, and at this time encreased and
exercised; whereof the deplorable estate of the Church
and Kingdome of <HI>Ireland,</HI> the distressed estate of the
Church and Kingdome of <HI>England,</HI> and the dange∣rous
estate of the Church and Kingdome of <HI>Scotland,</HI>
<PB N="28" REF="16"/>
are present and publick Testimonies; We have now at
last, (after other means of supplication, Remon∣strance,
Protestations and sufferings) for the pre∣servation
of our selves and our Religion from utter
ruine and destruction, according to the commendable
practise of these Kingdomes in former times, and the
example of Gods People in other Nations; after ma∣ture
deliberation resolved and determined to enter
into a mutual and solemn League and Covenant,
wherein we all subscribe, and each one of us for him∣self
with our hands lifted up to the most High God, do
swear.</P>
<P>And because these Kingdoms are guilty of many sins
and provocatious against God, and his Son Jesus
Christ, as is too manifest by our present distresses and
dangers the fruits thereof; We profess and declare
before God and the world, our unfained desire to be
humbled for our own sins, and for the sins of these
Kingdomes, especially that we have not as we ought,
valued the inestimable benefit of the Gospel, that we
have not laboured for the purity and power thereof,
and that we have not endeavoured to receive Christ
in our hearts, nor to walk worthy of him in our
lives, which are the causes of other sins and trans∣gressions
so much abounding amongst us; And our
true and unfained purpose, desire, and endeavour for
our selves, and all others under our power and
charge, both in publick and in private, in all duties
we owe to God and Man, to amend our lives, and
each one to go before another in the example of a real
Reformation, that the Lord may turn away his wrath
and heavy indignation, and establish these Churches
<PB N="29" REF="16"/>
and Kingdoms in truth and peace. And this Cove∣nant
we make in the presence of Almighty God, the
searcher of all hearts, with a true intention to per∣form
the same, as we shall answer at that great day,
when the secrets of all hearts shall be disclosed. Most
humbly beseeching the Lord to strengthen us by his
Holy Spirit for this end, and to bless our desires and
proceedings with such success, as may be deliverance
and safety to his people, and encouragement to other
Christian Churches groaning under, or in danger of
the yoak of Antichristian Tyranny, to joyn in the
same, or like Association and Covenant, to the glory
of God, the enlargement of the Kingdome of Jesus
Christ, and the peace and tranquility of Christian
Kingdomes and Commonwealths.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="30" REF="17"/>
<HEAD>Bishop HALL'S Holy Order
OF THE
Mourners in SION.</HEAD>
<P>FOrasmuch as there is no well-affected Christian, that
is not deeply sensible of the woful calamity of this
once glorious Church, now humbled into the dust of
confusion, and exposed to the pity of all those forreign
Neighbours, which heretofore blessed it as a singular pat∣tern
of Divine Mercy; and to the scorn and insultation of
<HI>Gath</HI> and <HI>Ascalen:</HI> And for as much as it is, and hath
been ever the practice of the Enemies of our peace, to range
themselves into several Ranks and Files, under various
Forms, Qualities, and Denominations; as on the one side▪
the Society of <HI>Jesus,</HI> the Order of the glorious Virgin, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<HI>Archi-confraternity</HI> of the most holy Trinity, and the rest of
this kind not easie to be numbred: On the other side, Seek∣ers,
Quakers, Shakers, Dippers, the holy Family of Love,
Ranters, and such other Prodigies of Mis-religion and Fa∣ction;
and thereby have found advantage several wayes
for the promoting of our ruine: Why should it not b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
found requisite, that we, the professed Servants of our <HI>Lor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Jesus Christ,</HI> Orthodox and genuine Sons of the Church o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<HI>England</HI> (whose hearts are moved by the good Spirit o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
God to a just resentment of our miseries and dangers)
should firmly resolve (for the countermining of these En∣gineers
of Hell, and Conspirers of our destruction) to ente<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
into a safe, warrantable, <HI>Holy Fraternity of Mourners i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Sion;</HI> whose profession and work shall be a peculiarity o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="31" REF="17"/>
Devotion, striving with servent Prayers and Tears to ob∣tain
from Heaven a seasonable redrefse of these our pressing
Calamities, and a prevention of that utter overthrow and
final Devastation which threatens this miserable Church
wherein we do yet live: And for this purpose may it be
thought meet to tie ourselves by our secret and silent Vows
to these Rules following.</P>
<P>1. That without all offensive, tumultuous and suspecti∣ble
Gomplottings and Conventions, we shall hold up our
private Devotions, and perform these our godly underta∣kings
to that premised end.</P>
<P>2. That there shall be no superiority or subordination
in this holy <HI>Fraternity,</HI> nor any soul more interessed in i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
then other; and therefore no Formality or Ceremony of
admittance into it, but a free and voluntary entrance, lest
open for all comers into this strict course of Christian au∣sterity;
without any noise, without the required notice of
any, but God and their own Conscience, that the world
may well see and know, that here is no other design then
meerly spiritual; aiming at nothing but religious trans∣actions
between God and our Souls: and consisting in the
performance of the unquestionable Exercises of Piety and
holy Devotion.</P>
<P>3. That we shall zealously excite our Neighbours and
Friends to be passionately affected with this sad Estate of
Gods Church, and to be liberal of their sighs, and tears, and
prayers for the happy recovery of it.</P>
<P>4. That we will effectually endeavour to work our hearts
to a found Humiliation for our own sins, which have helpt
to contribute to the common stock of our miseries, and
daily renue our Vows of a more strict and holy obedience,
and a more close walking with our God.</P>
<P>5. That we shall deeply take to heart, and secretly mourn
for, and lament the sins of our people, representing them to
our thoughts in their haynous nature and quality, humbly
begging for their serious repentance of them, and earnestly
deprecating the judgements provoked by them.</P>
<P><PB N="32" REF="18"/>
6. That for this end we shall do our best indeavour to
get just notice of the sad estate of this distracted Church of
ours, and to be truly apprehensive of the peril wherein it
stands, as also of the horrible Blasphemies and damnable
Heresies which have been of late disgoi ged from the mouth
of Hell amongst us, and those hellish practises which have
followed thereupon, to the high dishonour of the Majesty
of that holy God whom we pretend to serve, to the utter
shaming of that blessed Gospel which we professe, for as
much as we cannot mourn for what we know not, nor
mourn enough for what we do not know to be so transcen∣dently
sinful.</P>
<P>As of the sins, whereby we have moved the fierce anger
and wrathfull displeasure of our God against us, so also
shall we take full notice of the judgements, whereby we
have smarted from his most just hand; yea (in a larger
comprehension) of the judgements past, present, emi∣nent;
amongst which, how can we but sorrowfully reckon
the mutual effusion of so much Christian blood, spilt by
the hands of brethren, (and as the Tribes of <HI>Israel</HI> did for
<HI>Benjamin)</HI> bitterly mourn for the slain of our people; of
whom so many on both parts have been swept away from
the earth, in the sury of a violent hostility, as might well
have served to store a populous Nation, or might probably
have over-run the professed enemies of Christendome: To
these we cannot but add the woful disasters and inexpressi∣ble
miseries which do alwayes inevitably attend an inte∣stine
war.</P>
<P>But of all judgement, none have cause to make so deep
an impression in us as the spiritual; as knowing, that as our
God is terrible in all his inflictions, so most of all where he
is least-felt; when he payes us in our own coin; when he
punisheth us with our sins, making one sin the revenger and
executioner of another; when he repayes our actual rebel∣lion
against him with a senslesse obduratenesse, with a plausi∣ble
security and deadnesse of spirit. When he rewards our
neglect and contempt of his Ordinances, with giving us up
to spiritual delusions, and to the seductions of the spirits of
<PB N="33" REF="18"/>
errour, to prodigious whimsies, and spiritual blasphe∣mies.</P>
<P>We shall then (as we have too just reason) lay together
these evils that we feel, with those which we have no lesse
cause to fear; and under the sense of both shall find our
hearts pierced with sorrow, and resolved into the just tears
of our mourning.</P>
<P>8. That we shall not fail both by night and day con∣stantly
to pour out our hearts in strong eries and fervent
prayer to our God, that he will be pleased now at last to visit
this miserable and disconsolate Church in mercy and com∣passion,
and cause the light of his Countenance to shine up∣on
us once again,</P>
<P>9. That the matter of our Prayers shall be the illumina∣tion
and reduction of those our weak Brethren, which of∣send
through ignorance, and out of a well-meant zeal are
in the simplicity of their hearts miscarried into erroneous
wayes, whether of doctrine or practise; for the merciful
conversion of the not-obdured and wilful opposers of the
Truth; for the seasonable confusion of the desperately
malicious enemies of God and his Church; for the settling
of the Church of God in righteousnesse, order and peace,
for the prevailence and happy successe of the Gospel against
all Schism, Heresie, errours in Opinion, and wickednesse of
life; for the discovery and defeat of all the devices and
machinations of Satan, and all his accursed Instruments,
against the Church of Christ in all parts of the world, and
especially in these disjoynted members of it, wherein we
are interessed; for the incouragement and prosperity of
all those that are faithful in the Land, and that are hearty
well-wishers to our <HI>Sion;</HI> for the averting of those heavy
and desolatory judgements which our sins have thus long
and loud called for; and lastly, for the making up of our
deplorable breaches, and reuniting of all honest and faith∣ful
hearts in a firm concord and Christian love.</P>
<P>10. That we shall every week set apart one day for this
holy purpose; wherein we shall humble our selves in private
fasting and prayer, till it shall please our God to return to
<PB N="34" REF="19"/>
us in his wonted Compassion, and to put an end to these
deadly distractions under which we labour.</P>
<P>11. That we shall willingly abridge our selves of our
wonted pleasure; not giving our selves leave to enjoy any
publick meetings of mirth and jollity; nor take the liberty
of those lawful Recreations, which we have formerly made
use of, whiles the Hand of God lies thus heavily upon this
Church and Nation.</P>
<P>12. That it shall be the desire of our hearts, that all
which shall condescend to joyn together in the profession
of this holy Fraternity, be knit together in an entire affe∣ction
to one another, and be ready to show all mutual re∣spects
of Christian love and observance to each other upon
all occasions; being withall in all mecknesse of spirit cha∣ritably
affected to, and lovingly conversing with those their
Brethren and Neighbours, which are not yet so sensible of
the just cause of their humiliation.</P>
<P>13. That in the conscience of our own wants and infir∣mities,
we shall make it our care to spend our main censures
upon our selves, and our own enormities: Not being apt to
flie out upon the weaknesses and defects of our Brethren;
bearing with those that are otherwise minded in matters of
an inferiour nature, not aggravating the blame of those
their Actions, or Opinions, which may be capable of a
gentler and milder construction; and reserving the edge of
our zeal for those foul and grosse offences, which carry
open guilt in their faces, making head against them by all
spiritual resistence and godly endeavours of Reclama∣tion.</P>
<P>14. That whensoever we shall be called to deliver the
Message of God to his people in publick Auditiories, we
shall not fail to lay open and bewail the sins of the time,
and to rouze up our Hearers, with all zealous Exhortati∣ons,
to a lively sense of just sorrow for the universal over∣flowings
of wickednesse, and to a vehement and godly stri∣ving
against the stream thereof, by their prayers and utmost
endeavours.</P>
<P><PB N="35" REF="19"/>
15. That we shall heartily labour not to be found de∣fective
in the use of all good means, whereby the peace and
welfare of Gods Church may be procured and maintained;
and shall carefully avoid all such wayes and meanes, which
may in any sort endanger the widening of the unhappy
breaches, and multiplying of the many and miserable di∣stractions
thereof.</P>
<P>These are the Laws, to which we have thought fit in these
doleful times to bind our selves, in the presence of that
God, who hath graciously wrought in us a feeling compas∣sion
of the publique evils; beseeching him, who is the Fa∣ther
of all mercies, to inable us by the powerful operatio
of his good Spirit, to an effectual performance of all these
our holy engagements, that after the short time of our
mourning in this vale of tears, we may be admitted to be
the blessed partakers of that eternal joy which abides for
all his in Heaven.</P>
<P>Christian Brethren, of what quality soever; I cannot
fear, lest it will seem too much boldnesse in me to invite you
all to take part with me in this holy Fraternity; which
you shall highly wrong if you look upon it as mine, or any
meerly humane institution: No, the Founder of it is in
Heaven; it is the charge of the Holy Ghost himself, by the
hand of his chosen Vessel, <HI>Weep with them that weep:</HI> If our
tears therefore be (as they are) most just, ye are bound to
add yours to them, and shall offend if ye forbear: Neither
can you be ignorant that the Son of God himself whiles
he was visibly here upon Earth, did not only own it as well-pleasing
to him, but encouraged it with the promise of an
assured comfort, and crowned it with no lesse title then
Blessednesse: And if ye look for a more ancient precedent,
even before the Lord of Life was manifested in the flesh, ye
do apparently find this Fraternity of singular note in old
<HI>Jerusalem, Ye know the Man cloathed with white Linnen,
which had the Writers Inkhorn by his side,</HI> had this charge
from the mouth of the Lord himself, <HI>Go through the midst of
the City, through the midst of Jerusalem, and set a mark upon
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
the foreheads of the Men that sigh, and that cry for all the
abominations that be done in the midst thereof.</HI> Lo here, a
company of Mourners marked out for Mercy; even whiles
the Sanctuary is contemptuously defiled, and all <HI>Jerusalem</HI> is
in blood.</P>
<P>Shall I now need any other motive to win you into the
Brotherhood of this sacred Order?</P>
<P><HI>Know then,</HI> that they which sow in tears shall reap in joy;
and he that goeth sorth and weepeth, bearing precious seed, shall
doubtlesse come again with rejoycing, bringing his sheaves with
him.</P>
<P>Know that they are not Tears, but Pearles, that thus fall
from your Eyes, dearly precious to the Almighty, and care∣fully
reserved in his Casket, for the decking of your Souls
to all Eternity.</P>
<P>Know that even the Lord of Glory was a man of sor∣rows,
and that he bedewed <HI>Jerusalem</HI> with his Teares, ere he
watered is with his Blood. If therefore ye will be moved
either with the sweet and unfailable promises of a gracious
acceptation, and a blessed remuneration of everlasting
comfort, or led by the Precept, or the Example of that
dear Saviour, whose Name ye professe to bear, refuse
not, delay not to enter your selves into this so holy, an∣cient,
and highly priviledged Fraternity of Mourners in
<HI>Sion.</HI></P>
<P>Mourn then, my Brethren, mourn heartily, but (as
the Apostle in another case) <HI>Mourn not as men without hope,</HI>
Be not disheartened, O ye faithful Mourners in <HI>Sion,</HI> as
if ye were hopelesly condemned to a perpetual darknesse,
and were doomed to dwell under a Cloud of endlesse sor∣row.
The Almighty will find a time to have mercy upon
his poor Church, and to clear up his countenance towards
his chosen Ones; wiping all tears from their eyes, and all
spots from their faces, and answering the holy desires of
their hearts, in shewing them his <HI>Sion</HI> in her perfect beau∣ty.
Could we but weep soundly, he would smile upon us,
and comfortably shine upon his Sanctuary, and make the
<PB N="37" REF="20"/>
place of his feet glorious, even an eternal excellency, the
joy of many Generations: Indeed for the present, O our
God, thou hast removed our Souls far from peace; thou
hast most justly filled us with thine indignation; for we
have deserved that thou shouldst pour out iniquities upon
us, and shouldst bring upon us the fruits of our own
thoughts, and measure our works into our bosomes; and
cause us to drink at thy Hand the Cup of thy fury, yea,
even to have the dregs of the Cup of trembling to be
wrung out to us, for we have walked every one after the
imagination of his own evil heart; our transgressions
are with us, and are multiplied before thee; and though
we have professed to be humbled under thy mighty hand,
we have not cried to thee in our hearts, when we howled
upon our beds; neither have we loathed our selves in our
own sight for the evils that we have committed; so as
we do now justly lie down in our shame, and our confu∣sion
covereth us, willingly acknowledging that our ini∣quities
have most deservedly turned away thy blessings from
us, and drawn thy judgements upon our heads.</P>
<P>But, O Lord, hast thou so smitten us, that there is no
healing for us? Have we put our selves utterly out of the
reach of thy boundlesse mercies? Art not thou the God
that retainest not thine anger for ever, because thou de∣lightest
in mercy? Oh why shouldest thou then be to us as
a mighty Man that cannot save? O thou the hope of
<HI>Israel,</HI> and the Saviour thereof in time of trouble, return,
return to thy people in the tender bowels of thine infi∣nite
pitty and compassion; humble our Soules throughly
under the sense of our many back slidings and grievous
provocations of the Eyes of thy Glory: Oh strike thou
our heart with an unfeigned repentance of all our evil
wayes, and once again speak peace unto thy servants:
Was there ever a more stiffe-necked and rebellious peo∣ple,
O Lord, then thine <HI>Israel?</HI> more eminent in abu∣sed
mercies? more notorious in all kinds of abominable
wickednesses? more exercised with variety of judgements?
<PB N="38" REF="21"/>
Yet when they cryed to thee in their distresse thou were
still ready to hear, and deliver them, and to renew thy
so often forseited blessings upon them, and wouldst not
let loose thy vengeance upon them till there was no re∣medy.
Behold, we are thy people, though a sinful one;
a second <HI>Israel</HI> both for sins and mercies: Now, Lord,
since it is thy marvellous mercy that we are not yet con∣sumed,
be still pleased to magnifie thy infinite goodnesse
in thy gracious forbearances and our powerful conver∣sion
to thee: And though we cannot but confesse that we
are a sinful Nation, a people laden with iniquity, a seed
of evil doers, yet, Lord, thou knowest that thou hast thy
secret ones amongst us; a people that prayeth, and trem∣bleth
at thy judgements, and waiteth humbly at the
door-posts of thy Sanctuary; a people that defireth to
walk close with thee their God, and to be approved of
thee in all their wayes; a people that figheth and mourn∣eth
for the abominable sins of the Land of their Nativity;
Oh, for their sakes, be thou intreated to hold off thy re∣venging
hand from this sinful Nation, and even yet still
provoke us by thy goodnesse to Repentance, O thou the
righteous and merciful Judge of the world, <HI>who even for
ten righteous persons wouldest have spared a</HI> Sodome <HI>and</HI> Go∣morrah
<HI>from their fiery execution;</HI> be pleased tenderly to
regard the cries of thy many hundred faithful and devout
Soules, that sue to thee for the stay and removal of thy
deserved judgements: Oh do thou look down from Hea∣ven,
and behold from the habitations of thy holinesse
and thy glory, the unsaigned humiliation of thy ser∣vants,
who are prostrate before thee with fasting and
weeping, and mourning; turn away thine heavy displea∣sure
from us, and pitty thy. Sanctuary which is desolate;
so shall our mouthes be full of the praises of thy Name,
and thy Saints shall rejoyce and sing new Songs unto the
God of our Salvation.</P>
<P>In the mean time we shall in silence and hope wait upon
the Lord, that hideth his face from <HI>Jacob,</HI> and not <HI>cease</HI>
<PB N="39" REF="21"/>
to pour out our selves in Tears and Supplications to him
that is mighty to save; neither will we suffer our cheeks
to be dry, or our souls to receive comfort, till we shall re∣ceive
a gracious answer from Heaven, and shall see that the
Lord hath been pleased to shew mercy to his <HI>Sion.</HI></P>
<P>In this condition, we that are <HI>Sions</HI> Mourners shall not
need to be distinguished (as other Orders are wont) by
Colours, Devises, Abiliments. Our qualifications will
be easily discerned by our sad faces, wet eyes, deep sighs,
mortified carriage, willing neglect of those vanities where∣with
others are transported, our holy retirednesse, assidu∣ous
Devotions, and strict professions of Godlinesse, Carry
your selves thus, dear Brethren, and God and his Angels
shall gladly welcome you into that holy Society of Mourn∣ers,
which shall be marked out for preservation here, and for
eternal comfort hereafter.</P>
<P>Lastly, let none of you discourage himself from entring
into this sacred Fraternity, out of the sense of his bodily
infirmity, or the urgent necessity of outward impediments.
There is many an holy Soul that dwells inconveniently,
in a crazy, tottering, ruinous Cottage, ready to drop
down daily upon his head, not able to endure the sub∣straction
of one Meales support: There are not a few well-affected
Christians, whom the necessary exigences at their
Calling and Estate, like so many hard Taskmasters hold
close to their tale of Bricks, not allowing them the leisure
of our limited Devotion. Let all these of both kinds
know, that they have no cause hereupon, either to hold off,
or to think they shall (in this case) need the dispensation
of any superiour power; since their condition doth suffi∣ciently
dispense with it self. Even the severest Casuists of
the <HI>Roman Church</HI> (who are wont to be the rigidest Exa∣ctors
of the outward exercises of Mortification) do, in
these Cases, allow of a just relaxation.</P>
<P><PB N="40" REF="22"/>
My Brethren; if ye cannot fast, yet ye can pray, if your
Stomacks be weak, yet your zeal may be strong; ye can
mourn though ye pine not; and if ye cannot spare a day
in seven, yet ye may spare an hour in twelve, and make up
the rest in your frequent and servent Ejaculations: shortly
if you have truly mourning Souls they will be accepted in
the necessary want of the strict termes of bodily exer∣cises.</P>
<CLOSER>Farewell in the Lord.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

