<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Mr. Pepys to the President, and Governours of Christ-Hospital, upon the present state of the said hospital To the Honour'd Sir John Moor, Kt. and President, and the rest of my honour'd friends, the Governours of Christ-Hospital.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Pepys, Samuel, 1633-1703.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A54297</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing P1451D</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R222473</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99833640</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99833640</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">38118</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A54297)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38118)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2175:15)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Mr. Pepys to the President, and Governours of Christ-Hospital, upon the present state of the said hospital To the Honour'd Sir John Moor, Kt. and President, and the rest of my honour'd friends, the Governours of Christ-Hospital.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Pepys, Samuel, 1633-1703.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Moore, John, Sir, 1620-1702, recipient.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Christ's Hospital (London, England). Board of Governors, recipient.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1698]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Signatures: A.̲,</NOTE><NOTE>Signed at end: S. Pepys.</NOTE><NOTE>Dated at head: York-Buildings. March 30th. 1699.</NOTE><NOTE>Imprint from Wing.</NOTE><NOTE>Copy stained, with heavy print show-through.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Christ's Hospital (London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Orphans --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Charities --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A54297">
<STC T="W">P1451D</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99833640</BIBNO>
<VID>38118</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="1"/>
<HEAD><HI>Mr.</HI> PEPYS To the <HI>President,</HI> and <HI>Governours of</HI> CHRIST-HOSPITAL, <HI>upon</HI> the <HI>Present State</HI> of the said HOSPITAL.</HEAD>
<OPENER>To the Honour'd Sir <HI>John Moor,</HI> K<HI>t.</HI> and <HI>President,</HI> and the rest of my Honour'd <HI>Friends,</HI> the <HI>Gover∣nours of</HI> CHRIST-HOSPITAL. 
<DATELINE>York-Buildings, <DATE>March <HI>30</HI>th. <HI>1699.</HI></DATE></DATELINE>
<SALUTE>Gentlemen,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>YOUR <HI>Resolution</HI> of the 22<HI>th</HI> instant, importing your <HI>Ele∣ction</HI> of me to the <HI>Treasurership</HI> of this <HI>Hospital,</HI> was delivered me by the worthy <HI>Gentlemen</HI> appointed there∣to, with a degree of <HI>Respect</HI> as obliging on <HI>their</HI> part, as the <HI>Mes∣sage</HI> it self was on <HI>Yours</HI>; and both <HI>surprising.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Surprising</HI> I say; but without ought of what (I find) was in too much <HI>Tenderness</HI> apprehended from me by some of this <HI>Body</HI> concern∣ing it; as being <HI>One,</HI> who think nothing <HI>below</HI> the <HI>Character</HI> of any Man to <HI>execute,</HI> in a <HI>Service</HI> of <HI>Charity:</HI> And who therefore in my late <HI>Searches</HI> into the <HI>Condition</HI> of this <HI>House,</HI> descended to <HI>Of∣fices</HI> much <HI>beneath</HI> any thing that can occur in what you are <HI>now</HI> calling me to.</P>
<P>I therefore do most thankfully own the <HI>Proof</HI> you herein tender me of the <HI>Continuance</HI> of your <HI>Esteem,</HI> after the unwelcome <HI>Free∣dom</HI> I have for some time been unavoidably exercising towards you, upon the Unhappy <HI>Subject</HI> of your present <HI>State</HI>; in which <HI>Your selves</HI> are now pleased to give me this <HI>Testimony</HI> of your <HI>acquiescence</HI>: and in the <HI>Redress</HI> whereof, this <HI>Court</HI> shall never <HI>want</HI> any thing within <HI>my</HI> power <HI>improvable</HI> thereto.</P>
<P>But whether in the <HI>method</HI> you <HI>now</HI> propose, is <HI>what</HI> I have made it my <HI>business</HI> for some days to <HI>consider</HI>; without being able to bring
<PB REF="2"/>
my self to any other <HI>Determination</HI> in it, Than that the giving you any <HI>conclusive</HI> Answer (whether of <HI>Acceptance</HI> or <HI>Refusal</HI>) before this <HI>Resolution</HI> of yours shall have passed the <HI>Censure</HI> of <HI>another <HI>Court,</HI></HI> is a no less <HI>Exposing</HI> of <HI>Myself,</HI> than <HI>Imposing</HI> on <HI>You,</HI> (as in a very late <HI>Case</HI>) under the <HI>Ʋncertain</HI> Issue of a <HI>subsequent <HI>Court</HI></HI>; and when <HI>that</HI> is <HI>over,</HI> of the <HI>Lord Mayor</HI> and <HI>Court</HI> of <HI>Alder∣men</HI> also: As <HI>that</HI> without which, by the known <HI>Constitution</HI> of <HI>all</HI> our <HI>Hospitals,</HI> no <HI>Election</HI> of a <HI>Treasurer</HI> is valid. A <HI>Consideration</HI> of more than common <HI>Weight</HI> at this time; from the <HI>Question</HI> under which the <HI>Authority</HI> of that <HI>Court</HI> now lies with <HI>this</HI>; without Ought I can hear-of yet done on <HI>their</HI> side, in its <HI>Assertion.</HI></P>
<P>Which while in <HI>doing,</HI> and for Your clearer <HI>Guidance</HI> in Your <HI>second <HI>Debates</HI></HI> on this matter at the next <HI>Court,</HI> I think it becom∣ing me, in <HI>faithfulness</HI> both to <HI>You</HI> and <HI>Myself,</HI> to lay before You the few following <HI>Considerations.</HI></P>
<P>1<HI>st.</HI> —That I am no <HI>Freeman</HI>; and consequently, according to the <HI>Original <HI>Book</HI></HI> of <HI>Ordinances</HI> by which alone (without entring in∣to the <HI>Reason</HI> of it) <HI>this <HI>Court</HI></HI> and <HI>that</HI> of the <HI>Lord Mayor</HI> and <HI>Aldermen</HI> are at liberty to Act herein; I neither am <HI>capable</HI> of be∣ing Your <HI>Treasurer,</HI> nor <HI>You</HI> nor <HI>They, apart</HI> or <HI>together,</HI> in a <HI>Ca∣pacity</HI> of <HI>making</HI> me <HI>so.</HI> Nor is there, I believe, any one <HI>Instance</HI> to be shewn me, of a <HI>Treasurer</HI> not a <HI>Freeman:</HI> And should therefore most unwillingly subject Myself to <HI>Question,</HI> for meddling <HI>unwarrantably</HI> with a <HI>Revenue</HI> so <HI>Sacred</HI> as that of the <HI>Poor's</HI>; or be an <HI>Occasion</HI> of Your <HI>adventuring</HI> upon <HI>that</HI> in <HI>my</HI> Case, which was <HI>never</HI> yet done in <HI>any,</HI> nor can <HI>now</HI> justifiably be in <HI>this.</HI></P>
<P>2<HI>dly.</HI>—That the <HI>Office</HI> and <HI>Work</HI> of Your <HI>Treasurer</HI> ought not to be estimated by what we have <HI>seen</HI> of it in its <HI>Execution</HI> for some Years <HI>past</HI>; but by the <HI>Condition</HI> the <HI>House</HI> is reduced to, from its being executed no <HI>otherwise.</HI> As being an <HI>Office,</HI> that calls at once for <HI>Qualifications, <HI>such</HI></HI> and <HI>so many,</HI> as rarely meet in the same <HI>Person</HI>: Such are (besides <HI>that</HI> of an approved <HI>Integrity</HI>) <HI>Vigour</HI> of <HI>Mind, <HI>Steadiness</HI></HI> of <HI>Health, <HI>Entire <HI>Leasure, Vninterestedness, <HI>Zeal</HI></HI></HI></HI> for and <HI>Tenderness</HI> towards the <HI>Poor,</HI> General <HI>Experience,</HI> and par∣ticular <HI>Practice</HI> in the Business of <HI>Accounts,</HI> a <HI>Genius</HI> fitted for <HI>Com∣mand</HI> joyn'd with <HI>Temper,</HI> a <HI>Thorough-Insight</HI> into the <HI>Laws</HI> and <HI>Ends</HI> of our <HI>Constitution,</HI> and a <HI>Capacity</HI> of <HI>Controlling</HI> every of our <HI>Officers</HI> and <HI>Masters</HI> in the <HI>Execution</HI> of <HI>their <HI>Dutys,</HI></HI> with a constancy of <HI>Attendance</HI> and <HI>Application</HI> (in his <HI>own Person,</HI> and not by <HI>Others</HI>) to the <HI>Performance</HI> of his <HI>own.</HI> A <HI>Task</HI> both in <HI>Bulk</HI> and <HI>Weight,</HI> too much for <HI>my Age</HI> and known <HI>Infirmities</HI>; Besides the <HI>Disabilitys</HI> I am alone <HI>Conscious</HI> to my self of, for it.</P>
<P>And though <HI>what</HI> I have here to <HI>add,</HI> might not possibly be reckon'd of <HI>Moment</HI> enough <HI>alone</HI> in this <HI>Debate</HI>: yet in <HI>Conjunction</HI> with what is <HI>already</HI> said, I know not how without <HI>Injury</HI> to <HI>my self</HI> to omit the observing; that I can with no <HI>Satisfaction</HI> think of <HI>accepting</HI> of a <HI>Charge,</HI> which <HI>my self</HI> must be own'd to have had the greatest <HI>Hand</HI> in the rendring <HI>Vacant.</HI></P>
<P><PB REF="2"/>3<HI>ly.</HI> — That suitable to my <HI>Advice</HI> to you <HI>elsewhere</HI> on this <HI>Subject,</HI> I do not see with what <HI>Safety</HI> this <HI>Court</HI> can proceed to the giving a <HI>final Discharge</HI> to its <HI>late <HI>Treasurer,</HI></HI> nor how it should expect his being <HI>Succeeded</HI> by any Person of <HI>Sincerity</HI> or <HI>Substance,</HI> till a <HI>State</HI> shall be first <HI>Adjusted</HI> of all your <HI>Accounts, Revenues, Charges</HI> and <HI>Debts,</HI> to your Own and Their <HI>Satisfaction</HI>; and <HI>that</HI> also <HI>laid before,</HI> and <HI>acqui∣esced-in</HI> by the <HI>Court</HI> of <HI>Aldermen.</HI> Besides the <HI>Review</HI> and fresh <HI>Esta∣blishment</HI> fit to be first had of the <HI>Work</HI> and <HI>Instructions</HI> of <HI>that <HI>Officer,</HI></HI> before the <HI>Admission</HI> of a <HI>New.</HI> As foreseeing little <HI>Fruit</HI> from any <HI>Change</HI> of <HI>Hands</HI> (be it <HI>what</HI> it will) where those <HI>Hands</HI> shall be obliged by no other <HI>Rules</HI> nor <HI>Restrictions,</HI> than those we owe our present <HI>Di∣stresses</HI> to.</P>
<P>For the more Successful <HI>Dispatch</HI> of which, as well on the part of your said <HI>Treasurer</HI> as <HI>Your selves</HI>; I submit it to You, whether it may not be <HI>advisable,</HI> that the <HI>Current Work</HI> of this <HI>Office</HI> be for the <HI>Present</HI> lodg'd with a small <HI>Commmittee</HI> of Your <HI>own Number, properly</HI> chosen; till by the <HI>Adjustment</HI> of these Matters, You shall be in a <HI>Condition</HI> of restoring it to its <HI>Ordinary Methods.</HI></P>
<P>4<HI>ly.</HI> — Lastly, That no <HI>Degree</HI> of <HI>Industry, Experience,</HI> or other the <HI>Vertues</HI> (before requir'd) in a <HI>Treasurer,</HI> can alone be thought <HI>Sufficient</HI> at this <HI>Juncture</HI> (where our <HI>Whole <HI>Constitution</HI></HI> lies at once out of Order) to compass its <HI>Reformation,</HI> without equal <HI>Aid</HI> from a no less <HI>vigorous</HI> and <HI>persevering,</HI> however otherwise <HI>meritorious</HI> a <HI>President. <HI>One,</HI></HI> I mean, whose <HI>thorough-knowledge</HI> in the <HI>Design, Powers, Limitations,</HI> and <HI>Orders</HI> of this Pious <HI>Foundation,</HI> and the <HI>Rules</HI> of their <HI>Execution,</HI> is able both to preserve <HI>himself</HI> from being either <HI>discouraged</HI> or <HI>imposed-on,</HI> and by his <HI>Authority, Zeal</HI> and <HI>Vigilance,</HI> to prevent those <HI>Practices</HI> which, from the <HI>want</HI> hereof, the <HI>Generality</HI> of this <HI>House</HI> has been so long <HI>misled</HI> by, to its <HI>Vndoing.</HI> A <HI>Reflection,</HI> that in one word, would <HI>alone</HI> suffice (lay there nothing <HI>else</HI> in my way) to <HI>deter</HI> me from the <HI>Ʋndertaking</HI> You <HI>invite</HI> me to, under the <HI>Circumstances</HI> we at present la∣bour in this <HI>Particular.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Which</HI> having said, and the <HI>Reasons</HI> of it thus <HI>opened</HI>; it remains only for me to <HI>beg,</HI> that my <HI>declining</HI> Your present <HI>Offer</HI> may not be taken for a <HI>Declension</HI> in any part of my <HI>Concernment</HI> for the <HI>Prosperity</HI> of this <HI>House.</HI> Forasmuch as no <HI>Consideration</HI> shall ever <HI>discourage</HI> or <HI>di∣vert</HI> me from the <HI>pursuit</HI> of it; till by <HI>some <HI>Means, <HI>Ordinary</HI></HI></HI> or <HI>Extra∣ordinary</HI> (though much rather the <HI>former</HI>) I see it <HI>restored</HI> to the <HI>State</HI> wherein all <HI>Good men</HI> wish it.</P>
<P>In view whereof, give me leave with great <HI>Satisfaction</HI> once more to <HI>assure</HI> You, that (without any such <HI>Obligation</HI> as <HI>this</HI> of your <HI>Trea∣surership</HI>) neither <HI>You</HI> nor Your helpless <HI>Orphans</HI> shall ever want the best <HI>Effects</HI> of my <HI>Personal Attendance</HI> and <HI>Service,</HI> from the <HI>Moment</HI> that, by <HI>Your thorough-Applications,</HI> and those of the <HI>Court</HI> of <HI>Alder∣men</HI> towards it, I shall have any <HI>Grounds</HI> to <HI>hope,</HI> that such my <HI>Atten∣dance</HI> and <HI>Service,</HI> may be followed with any <HI>Success,</HI> to the <HI>Recovery</HI> of the <HI>lost Honour</HI> of this <HI>House,</HI> by its <HI>Return</HI> to that Religious <HI>Strictness</HI>
<PB REF="3" MS="y"/>
which once distinguish'd it from all <HI>others,</HI> in its <HI>Compliances</HI> with the holy and charitable <HI>Ends</HI> provided-for by its <HI>Munificent <HI>Founders</HI></HI> and <HI>Benefactors</HI>▪ I am</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Gentlemen,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED>Your most humble and obedient Servant, S. Pepys.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

