<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">King Solomon's recantations being an extract out of the famous works of the learned Francis Quarles ... : with an essay, to prove the immortality of the soul, by way of symetry, or connexion.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A56830</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing Q103</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R2993</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12374999</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12374999</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">60559</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A56830)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60559)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 224:3)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">King Solomon's recantations being an extract out of the famous works of the learned Francis Quarles ... : with an essay, to prove the immortality of the soul, by way of symetry, or connexion.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[3], 94 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by J.R. and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1688.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>In verse and prose.</NOTE><NOTE>"Licensed, July 21. 1688. Rob. Midgley"</NOTE><NOTE>Errata: p. 94.</NOTE><NOTE>Advertisements: p. [3].</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Immortality --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A56830">
<STC T="W">Q103</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12374999</BIBNO>
<VID>60559</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>King <HI>Solomon</HI>'s
RECANTATIONS:
BEING AN
EXTRACT
Out of the Famous
WORKS
Of the Learned
<HI>FRANCIS QVARLES,</HI>
Cup-bearer to the Queen of <HI>Bohemia,</HI> Sister
to the blessed Martyr King <HI>Charles</HI> the I. of ve∣nerable
Memory. With an Essay, to prove the
Immortality of the Soul, by way of Symetry,
or Connexion.</P>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="license">
<P>Licensed,</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE>July 21. 1688.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Rob. Midgley.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by <HI>I. R.</HI> and are to be sold by
<HI>Randal Taylor,</HI> near <HI>Stationers-Hall.</HI> 1688.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Advertisements.</HEAD>
<P>T'Here is lately Printed a Book, Intitule
<HI>The way of Life is Pleasant: Or, t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Church of</HI> England <HI>is the Best Guide.</HI> Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>taining
several useful Discourses, for every
Christian to Read and Practise, for the sup∣port
of their Spirits, and comfort of the
Minds: With some Evangelical Reflection
upon the Apostolical Observation of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<HI>Lent-Fast:</HI> With short and useful Prayer
upon the <HI>Church-Festivals,</HI> and most (other
Emergent Occasions: With several prepa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ratory
Prayers for the Holy <HI>Sacrament,</HI> an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Thanksgiving after Receiving. Licensed <HI>Iun</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
the <HI>4th.</HI> 1686. and Sold by <HI>Randal Taylo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>
near <HI>Stationers Hall; I. Harding,</HI> at the <HI>Bi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI>
and <HI>Anchor</HI> in <HI>Newport-street; Rich. Sare,</HI> a
<HI>Grays-Inn Gate</HI> in <HI>Holbourn;</HI> and by most Book
sellers in <HI>London</HI> and <HI>Westminster.</HI> 1686.</P>
<P>KIng <HI>Solomons</HI> Experimental Observations
of Himself, Time and Things; deduct∣ed
from his Recantations, by Way of Solilo∣quie;
in a well digested Method. Sold by
<HI>Randal Taylor,</HI> near <HI>Stationers-Hall.</HI> 168<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>King Solomon's
RECANTATIONS, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<L>OH! 'tis much better not to Thirst at all.</L>
<L>Than Thirst in vain, or quench thy Thir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
with Gall.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hose profit can accrue to Man, what gains</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an Crown his Actions, or reward his Pains:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nless he trample on the <HI>Asp,</HI> and tread</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the young <HI>Lyon,</HI> and the old <HI>Dragon</HI>'s head:</L>
<L>Or else the Clouds of Sorrow may multiply,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d hide from thee the Crystal of the gloomy Sky.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>oad not thy Shoulders by the Sin of unwise desire,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat all thy bedrid Passions may quite expire.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>earch for, and find such Words which have the might,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> intermingle profit with sweet delight;</L>
<L>Than shalt thou have hopeful worth to Crown thy last</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith Peace and Honor; yea such rare Sons thou hast,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nce Frolick, Midnight, Madness, is quite expir'd; and
thou requite</L>
<L>Thy wild attention with Heavenly delight:</L>
<L>Thy courage indeavouring to deserve the name</L>
<L>Of heroick Martyr, by giving thy Body to the Flame.</L>
<L>This will give true Life, so sweet, to every one</L>
<L>That takes pleasure in the Worlds redeeming Son,</L>
<L>From Earths pleasures, by striving to refrain,</L>
<L>Knowing those short-liv'd flattering pleasures vain:</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="3"/>
Therefore rejoycing greatly in true Spiritual ways,</L>
<L>By Heavenly contentment, chearing youthful Days.</L>
<L>Banishing false-eyed Mirth, let it be truly disposest</L>
<L>Of those lewd Firs, that are apt to inflame thy Brea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>For Earths best injoyments are short, and vain;</L>
<L>But for a season rejoycing, but cannot remain,</L>
<L>For feeble Strength, her ruins, smite thee,</L>
<L>And grinds thy clod to dust, tho not afrights thee.</L>
<L>One Generation gives another way,</L>
<L>But Earth abides in one perpetual stay:</L>
<L>The Prince of Light put on his Morning Crown;</L>
<L>But in the Evening lays his Glory down;</L>
<L>Where leaving Earth, to take a short repose,</L>
<L>He soon returns, and rises where he rose.</L>
<L>His Wisdoms choice affections own,</L>
<L>His Churches good, much dearer then his Throne.</L>
<L>For us subduing, beneath the spangled Sky,</L>
<L>What ever might hurt us. That in Wisdom we may
decry</L>
<L>All Evils, and seek all Hevenly sweet felicity:</L>
<L>Yet injoying such pleasures, that Earth could len<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
that I</L>
<L>Might find Earths Mirth and Beauty but vanity.</L>
<L>My thoughts yet pondering all that hath been done</L>
<L>Betwixt the solid Center, and the glorious Son:</L>
<L>And yet no knowledge can reduce the state</L>
<L>Of crooked Nature, to a perfect straight.</L>
<L>For some Mens Ignorance, which surmounts</L>
<L>The learned Language of Arithmeticks accounts.</L>
<L>Oh! then thought I, how are the vain desires</L>
<L>Flesh and Blood</L>
<L>Baffled in their mistaken things, called good:</L>
<L>Yet travel seeks them, yea unwearied Hearts</L>
<L>Makes them the objects, both of Arms and Arts:</L>
<L>Yet many certan obvious Evils attend</L>
<L>Our Ways, to our uncertain Journies end.</L>
<L>We tire the Night in thought, the Day in toil,</L>
<L>Sparing neither sweet nor lucubrated Oyl.</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o seek the things we cannot find, or found;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e cannot hold; or held, we cannot ground</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o firm, as to resist the various swings</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f fickle Fortune, or the frowns of Kings;</L>
<L>That if his Royal Power please to commit</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>is Pastorial Staff, to such as are more fit</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Eat and Drink, Kill, or recommend his Flocks</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o such dumb <HI>Dogs,</HI> of whom ne'r <HI>Wof</HI> nor <HI>Fox</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ill stand in awe; or shew their fears by flight,</L>
<L>Not having Tongues to bark, nor Teeth to bite:</L>
<L>Yet, by the way, advise Obedience; then</L>
<L>Always he sure to please, rather God than Men.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f the Embers of his rage should chance to lye</L>
<L>Rak'd up, or furnace from his angry Eye;</L>
<L>Quit not thy Duty, 'tis thy part to asswage,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y due Obedience, the jealous flames of consuming
rage.</L>
<L>Curse not the King, nor them that bears the Sword;</L>
<L>No, not in Thought, tho Thought express no Word:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or secret report shall vent such hidious things,</L>
<L>To punish those who oppose the legal Authority of
Kings:</L>
<L>For all that attempt thus to act, casts a shame</L>
<L>Upon the beauty of an honor'd Name.</L>
<L>Ah, then, my Soul, take heed to keep thy Heart</L>
<L>At thy right Hand; where, there she will impart</L>
<L>Continual secrets, and direct thy ways</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n secret Ethicks, sweetning out thy Days</L>
<L>With season'd Knowledge; Wisdom past the reach</L>
<L>Of dangerous error; and instruct and teach</L>
<L>Thy Heart-wise silence, Wisdom, when to beak</L>
<L>Thy clos'd Lips, and judgement how to speak,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch wise Mens Words are gracious where they go;</L>
<L>But foolish Language doth themselves o're-throw:</L>
<L>Folly brings in the Prologue, with his Song,</L>
<L>Whose Epilogue is rage, and open wrong.</L>
<L>Yea the tedious actions of every Fool doth try,</L>
<L>The solid patience of the weary standers by;</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="4"/>
Because their weakness knows not how to lay</L>
<L>Their actions posture, in a civil way:</L>
<L>Yea such rude folly stains their Fame,</L>
<L>But fair repute for Wisdom lends a name.</L>
<L>Therefore our steps will measure out the way,</L>
<L>Our Garb, our Looks, our Language doth betray,</L>
<L>Our Wisdom, or Follies read by all we meet,</L>
<L>Our selves proclaiming our Follies in every Street.</L>
<L>But 'tis a grief that grates beneath the Sun,</L>
<L>That like events betides to every one.</L>
<L>A like be false, to Good and Bad, Wise and Foo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Yea both</L>
<L>To him that Swears, and him that fears an Oath.</L>
<L>Better to be a living Creatures, tho vild they plead,</L>
<L>Then to be known a wealthy Wiseman that is dead:</L>
<L>For they that live well, know that they shall die,</L>
<L>Therefore take time; but the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that lie</L>
<L>Rak'd up in deaths cold Em<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs, they know not</L>
<L>Or Good, or Ill, their names are quite forgot;</L>
<L>No Friends they have to Love, nor Foes to Hate;</L>
<L>They know no Virtue to spit Venom at;</L>
<L>They sell no sweet for gains, nor do they buy</L>
<L>Pleasures with pains, or tread beneath the Sky.</L>
<L>But yet go thou rejoyce and Eat, let a full Bowl</L>
<L>Cashire thy Cares, and chear thy frolick Soul,</L>
<L>What Heaven hath lent thee with a liberal Hand,</L>
<L>To serve and chear thy frailty up, command.</L>
<L>Indulge thy weary Flesh with new supplies,</L>
<L>And change of Garments of the purest die.</L>
<L>Refresh thy limbs, annoy'd with sweat and toil;</L>
<L>With costly Baths, thy Head with precious Oyl.</L>
<L>What e'er thy Hand endeavours, that may gain</L>
<L>Contentment, spair not either cost or pain,</L>
<L>For there is no Hand to work, no Power to save,</L>
<L>No Wisdom to contrive within the Grave.</L>
<L>I find the swift not always win the prize;</L>
<L>Nor strength of Arm the Battel; nor the Wise</L>
<L>Grow rich in Fortune; nor the Men of skill</L>
<L>In favour, all as Time and Fortune will:</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en knowing not their time, as Fishes are</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ar'd in the Net, Birds tangled in the snare.</L>
<L>So be the Sons of Men surpriz'd with fears,</L>
<L>When mischief falls upon them unawares:</L>
<L>This Wisdom have I seen beneath the Sky,</L>
<L>Which wisely weigh'd, deserves the Wiseman's Eye;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut when I set my busie Heart to know,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>isdom and Heavens strange workings here below.</L>
<L>For Night and Day my studys did deny,</L>
<L>Sleep to my Eye-lids, slumber to my Eye;</L>
<L>Striving to note each action under Heaven,</L>
<L>Endeavouring to observe and have given</L>
<L>My Soul to God, in due Obedience; having</L>
<L>Sought for true spiritual Wealth worth keeping.</L>
<L>But the poor fruitless labours of deluded Man,</L>
<L>Are vainly spent, being short as a span</L>
<L>Or seeming pleasures, serves to requite,</L>
<L>Long leagues of travel, for one drops delight</L>
<L>Of airy froth; how are ye forc'd to borrow</L>
<L>Strong gales of hope, to sail through Seas of Sorrow.</L>
<L>Why do we thus afflict our labouring Souls</L>
<L>With dregs of Wormwood, and carouse full Bowls</L>
<L>Of boyling Anguish? to what hopeful end</L>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oyl we our craizy Bodies, and expend</L>
<L>Our sorrow wasted Spirits, to acquire</L>
<L>A good, not worth a breath of our desire.</L>
<L>A good, whose fulsome sweetness, clogs and cloys</L>
<L>The Soul, but never lasts nor satisfies.</L>
<L>How poor an Object pleases, and how soon</L>
<L>That pleasure finds an end; how quickly noon;</L>
<L>How quickly Night, and what to Day we prize</L>
<L>Above our Souls, to morrow we despise.</L>
<L>Beneath a trifle, what in former times</L>
<L>We own'd as Virtues, now we tax as Crimes.</L>
<L>Tell me my Soul, What would'st thou buy?</L>
<L>Go in and Cheapen; let thy curious Eye</L>
<L>Make her choice: they will present thy view</L>
<L>With numerous Joys; buy something that's new.</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
The Wiseman's Eyes are in his Head; they stand</L>
<L>Like Watchmen in the Tower, to guard the Land.</L>
<L>At length I cast my serious Eyes upon</L>
<L>My painful Work, and what my Hands had done;</L>
<L>And there I find my Hearts delight was all my gains,</L>
<L>My pleasure was the portion of my pains.</L>
<L>I gave my Eyes, what e're my Heart requir'd:</L>
<L>I denied my Soul no Mirth, my Spirit desir'd</L>
<L>All sorts of Musick, the Spirits delights had I</L>
<L>To please my Spiritual Ear, was beauties to my Eyes</L>
<L>Yet knowledge then affords my Soul no rest;</L>
<L>My roving Thoughts tried Mirth, and was possest,</L>
<L>Of all the pleasures Earth could lend, yet I</L>
<L>Found Mirth and Pleasure all but Vanity:</L>
<L>I laugh'd at laughter as a toyish antick,</L>
<L>And counted all Earths pleasure no less than frantick</L>
<L>Since Hearts that wisely, foolish do incline</L>
<L>To costly fare, and frolick Cups of Wine.</L>
<L>For in those pleasures I find but little solid good,</L>
<L>To Crown the short liv'd Days of Flesh and Blood;</L>
<L>Tho some build great magnifick Palaces, and fraim</L>
<L>Vast buildings to the glory of their name;</L>
<L>Planting Vineyards, whose plump clusters might</L>
<L>Make them fruitful Orchards for their delight.</L>
<L>Rejoycing their Souls with Earthly treasures,</L>
<L>With curious Gardens to refresh their pleasures:</L>
<L>Yet true Wisdom can discern but little real good,</L>
<L>Mistaken Earth so much admiring stood!</L>
<L>What profit hath my Wisdom, then thought I</L>
<L>The height of Wisdom hath her Vanity.</L>
<L>The foolish bauble and the learned bays,</L>
<L>Are both forgotten; in succeding Days</L>
<L>Impartial Death shall Cloath the dying Eyes,</L>
<L>Both of the Ignorant and also of the Wise:</L>
<L>Therefore I hated life, for, from the events</L>
<L>Of humane actions, flows many discontents.</L>
<L>Then slighted I, all that my Hand had done,</L>
<L>In seeking happiness beneath the Sun:</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="5"/>
For what I did, I cannot call my own;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nothers Hand must reap what mine has sown;</L>
<L>Who knows if my surviver is to be</L>
<L>A Wiseman, or a Fool? However, 'tis he</L>
<L>Must spend with ease, what I have earn'd with pain</L>
<L>And Souls vexation; this is all so vain,</L>
<L>For which my Soul thus fool'd with vain persuits</L>
<L>Of blossom happiness that bears no Fruits.</L>
<L>Some Men there be, whose elaborate gains</L>
<L>The fruits of lawful cares and prudent pains</L>
<L>Descend to those who know not pains nor art:</L>
<L>This is a sore vanity, and afflicts the Heart;</L>
<L>For what reward hath Man of all his droyl,</L>
<L>His Evening trouble and his Morning toyl,</L>
<L>His Hearts vexation and his griefs, that run</L>
<L>Through all his labours underneath the Sun.</L>
<L>'I view'd the Chair of Judgment, where I saw</L>
<L>'Instead of righteousness, a perverted Law.</L>
<L>'I view'd the Courts of Equity, and spy'd</L>
<L>'Corruption there; and Justice wrap'd aside.</L>
<L>'Oh! then, (thought I) the of Judge Heaven shall do</L>
<L>'Right to the Wicked, and the Righteous too.</L>
<L>Then puzzel'd in my Thoughts, I thus advis'd,</L>
<L>Heaven suffers mortals to be exercis'd</L>
<L>In their own miseries, that they may see</L>
<L>They are yet not much more happy than the Bee;</L>
<L>They substance of Flesh, tho not the same,</L>
<L>Yet dust to dust, both must turn from whence they
came.</L>
<L>Which rightly way'd, it seems the better choice,</L>
<L>For Man to suck his labours and rejoyce,</L>
<L>Since flashly, troubles doth all things so unframe,</L>
<L>That Earths Content doth scarce deserve the name:</L>
<L>Considering this, what can we advise,</L>
<L>Since we berefit of Wisdom, labouring to be Wise.</L>
<L>Alas! is it not enough, that we poor Farmers
pay</L>
<L>Quit-rent to Nature, at the very Day:</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="6"/>
And at our dying Hour bequeath to thee</L>
<L>Our whole substance, for a Legacy:</L>
<L>I mus'd again, and found when pains had crackt</L>
<L>The harder shell to some heroick act.</L>
<L>Pale envy strikes the kernel with taxation;</L>
<L>Oh, this is vanity, and the Souls vexation!</L>
<L>Thus pausing, Contemplation shew'd mine Eye</L>
<L>A new prospect of humane vanity:</L>
<L>When, the droyling Hand thinks nothing can supply</L>
<L>The greedy wants of his insatiate Eye.</L>
<L>He robs himself, not knows for whose relief,</L>
<L>This is a vanity, and a wounding grief;</L>
<L>Woe to the Man whom danger meets alone,</L>
<L>For there's no Arm to help him but his own:</L>
<L>But if some help put in a timely stroak,</L>
<L>The Cord that's three-fold is not quickly broke.</L>
<L>If eithers feeble Shoulders be betray'd</L>
<L>To a sad burden, there's a mutual aid,</L>
<L>To be a poor Wise Child, is judg'd a thing</L>
<L>More honourable, than to be a vain King.</L>
<L>My Soul, to what a strange disguis'd good,</L>
<L>Art thou bewitch'd? oh, how hath Flesh and Blood</L>
<L>Betray'd thee, to a happiness that brings</L>
<L>No comfort, but from transitory things.</L>
<L>Are not the shady Bowers of Death more sweet,</L>
<L>Than the scorching Sunshine, where we Hourly meet</L>
<L>Fresh evils, like a <HI>Temes,</HI> whose deluded breath</L>
<L>Tickles our Fancies, till we laugh to Death?</L>
<L>When thou hast bound thee to thy God by Vow,</L>
<L>Defer not payment, but perform, it thou</L>
<L>Discharge thy Bonds, for Heaven takes no delight</L>
<L>In those that violate the Faith they plight;</L>
<L>For better 'tis thy Vows were never made,</L>
<L>Then having promis'd, payment never paid.</L>
<L>Let not thy Lips insnare thee, plead not thou</L>
<L>Before thy Angel, 'twas too rash a Vow.</L>
<L>'Tis not the Pills of treasur'd wealth sustain</L>
<L>Thy drooping Spirits, this is all so vain.</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="6"/>
Oft have I seen increasing riches grow</L>
<L>To their great mad Owners overthrow:</L>
<L>Vexing their Souls with Care, and then repay</L>
<L>Unprosperous pains with grief and melts away;</L>
<L>His wealth is fled, and when he shall transfer it</L>
<L>Upon his Heir, there's nothing to Inherit.</L>
<L>Look how he came into the World, the same</L>
<L>He shall go out as naked as he came;</L>
<L>Of what his labouring Heart have brought about,</L>
<L>This dying Hand shall carry nothing out:</L>
<L>This is a wounding grief that as he came,</L>
<L>In every point, he shall return the same.</L>
<L>What profit can his Souls afflictions find,</L>
<L>That toils for Air, and travels for the Wind.</L>
<L>This is an evil, that happiness now and then</L>
<L>Beneath the Sun amongst the Kings of Men:</L>
<L>Then eat and drink, and reap what pains have</L>
<L>Got, to Crown thy Days which thy Creator gave;</L>
<L>'Tis all the portion some will have,</L>
<L>Who study not for happiness in the Grave.</L>
<L>But hark, my Soul, the Morning Bell invites</L>
<L>Thy early paces to a new delight;</L>
<L>Away, away, the Holy Saints Bell rings,</L>
<L>Put on thy Robes and Oyl thy secret wings;</L>
<L>Call home thy Heart, and bid thy Thoughts surcease,</L>
<L>To be thy Thoughts, go bind them to the Peace:</L>
<L>Take good Security, or if such fail</L>
<L>Commit them to the All commanding Jayl;</L>
<L>And thy cram'd Bags there to lie close and fast,</L>
<L>Until thy Heavenly atoning Vows are past:</L>
<L>Confine thy rambling pleasures to the trust</L>
<L>Of vacant Hours, and let thy Wisdom thirst:</L>
<L>Banish all Worldly passions, with their base born Sir</L>
<L>From thy delectable Courts, that Wisdom may come in</L>
<L>Leave all thy servil Fancies in the vail,</L>
<L>Mount thou the secret Hill, and there bewail</L>
<L>Thy dying <HI>Isaac,</HI> whose free gift may be</L>
<L>A living Pledge 'twixt thy God and thee.</L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="7"/>
Take thou no Care, Heaven, will supply</L>
<L>Their craving Thirst with Bottles from thy Eye;</L>
<L>Better it is to be Funeral Guest,</L>
<L>Then find the welcoms of a frolick Feast:</L>
<L>For he that fears the Almighty shall</L>
<L>Out-wear his evils, or find no evil at all.</L>
<L>Wisdom affords more strength, more fortifies</L>
<L>The undejected courage of the Wise:</L>
<L>Yet is there none beneath the Crystial Skies</L>
<L>So just in Actions, or in words so Wise,</L>
<L>That doth always good, or hath not been</L>
<L>Sometimes poluted with the stains of Sins.</L>
<L>What God hath setled in a crooked State,</L>
<L>No industry of Man can make it strait;</L>
<L>Since then the Righteous Man's recompence is such;</L>
<L>Be not too Wise, nor Righteous over much.</L>
<L>Let not thy Flesh suggest thee, or advise</L>
<L>Thee to be Wicked, or too Unwise.</L>
<L>Why should thy too much Righteousness betray,</L>
<L>Thy danger'd Life, and make thy Life a prey?</L>
<L>At passions Language stop thy gentel Ear,</L>
<L>Lest if thy Servant Curse thee, thou should'st hear:</L>
<L>For oftentimes thy Heart will let thee see,</L>
<L>That others have been likewise Curs'd by thee.</L>
<L>This Wisdom, by my travel I attain'd,</L>
<L>And in my Thoughts conceiv'd that I had gain'd.</L>
<L>I gave my studious Heart to watch and pry</L>
<L>Into the bosom of Philosophy.</L>
<L>I laboured to give my self to fly the Art</L>
<L>Of falshood, and the Madness of the Heart.</L>
<L>For whom Heaven favours, shall decline Sins gates;</L>
<L>But the Incorrigible shall be taken by her baits:</L>
<L>But whether shall these, to what strange Religion fly</L>
<L>To find Content, and baulk that hidious vanity,</L>
<L>Which haunts this buble Earth, and makes thee still</L>
<L>A slave to thy preverse infatuated Will.</L>
<L>All this I have (by thee) observ'd, and given</L>
<L>My Heart to not each action under Heaven.</L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="7"/>
There was a time when the oppressers Arm</L>
<L>Oppress'd his Neighbour, to the oppressers harm,</L>
<L>With floods of bitterness, since none of these,</L>
<L>Nor, all can Crown our labours, nor appease</L>
<L>Our raging Hearts. Oh! my deceiv'd Soul,</L>
<L>Where wilt thou take thy Peace? who shall controul</L>
<L>Our unbounded Thoughts, to sweeten out</L>
<L>This span of frailty plung'd and orb'd about</L>
<L>The threatning Firmements; but as a breath</L>
<L>Darts down, and dashes at the doors of death.</L>
<L>Since Waxen-wing'd Honour is not void</L>
<L>Of danger, whether arm'd or injoy'd:</L>
<L>Since Hearts rejoycing, profit have no fruit,</L>
<L>But care both in fruition, and in persuit:</L>
<L>Since laughter is but Madness, and high Diet</L>
<L>Oft ruins our Health and breeds us great disquiet:</L>
<L>Since humane Wisdom is but humane trouble,</L>
<L>And double knowledge makes our sorrow double:</L>
<L>Since what we have, but lights our wish to more,</L>
<L>And in the height of plenty makes us poor;</L>
<L>And what we have not too, to apt to crave,</L>
<L>Even dispossess of what we have.</L>
<L>A good repute is sweeter, far,</L>
<L>Than breaths of Aromatick Oyntments are;</L>
<L>And that sad Day wherein we drew our breath,</L>
<L>Is not so happy as the Day of death:</L>
<L>For here we are but quickly forgot;</L>
<L>Blaze for a season, but continue not.</L>
<L>Tho foolish flatteries entertain</L>
<L>Our Souls with Joy, but all that Joy is vain;</L>
<L>For if both Heaven and Earth should undertake,</L>
<L>To extract the best from Mankind, and to make</L>
<L>One perfect happy Man; and thou art he,</L>
<L>Thy finite fortunes still would disagree.</L>
<L>Man in whose frame the Great Three-One advis'd,</L>
<L>And with a studious Hand Epitomiz'd</L>
<L>The large Volumes, and perfect Story</L>
<L>Of all his Works, the manuel of his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="8"/>
With fear and wonder in whose sovereign Eye,</L>
<L>He breath'd the flames of awful Majesty.</L>
<L>Man a poor shiftless transitory thing,</L>
<L>Born without Sword or Shield, not having wing</L>
<L>To fly from threatning dangers, not to arm,</L>
<L>Or graple with those numerous evils, that swarm</L>
<L>About this new born frailty, wrapt aside</L>
<L>From fair Obedience, to Rebellious Pride.</L>
<L>How is that Power, that was bred and born</L>
<L>The Earths Commander, now become the scorn</L>
<L>Of Dunghil passions, Shipwrack'd with the gust</L>
<L>Of every factious and inferiour Lust?</L>
<L>How is the Sun-bright Honour of his name</L>
<L>Eclpis'd? how is his Glory Cloath'd with shame?</L>
<L>What means that great Creating Power, to frame</L>
<L>This spacious Universe? Was not his name</L>
<L>Glorious enough without a Witness? Why</L>
<L>Did that corrected twilight of his Eye</L>
<L>Unmuzle darkness, and with Morning light</L>
<L>Redeem the Day, from new baptiz'd Night?</L>
<L>There is an evil, which my observing Eye</L>
<L>Hath taken notice of beneath the Skye:</L>
<L>Man's wealth can't instruct him to withstand</L>
<L>The augry stroak of the Almighties Hand;</L>
<L>Since the increase of wealth procur'd by pain,</L>
<L>Preserv'd with fears, with sorrow lost again,</L>
<L>Increaseth grief in the possessors Breast;</L>
<L>What vantage than have Man to be possess'd,</L>
<L>Who knows what's good for Man in this dull balze</L>
<L>Of life is swift, his shaddow flying Days:</L>
<L>Or who can tell when his short Hour is run,</L>
<L>The events of all his toyl beneath the Sun?</L>
<L>The Worlds surviving Lamps do not affright</L>
<L>The pleasing slumbers of his peaceful Night.</L>
<L>There be no Ears, no Eyes, to hear, to see</L>
<L>The living Soul, have not such rest as he,</L>
<L>Who stands upright in Courts, with unshaken Mind;</L>
<L>For the Test proves him, and he is found refin'd.</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="8"/>
If thy superiour happen to incense</L>
<L>His jealous wroth at thy suppos'd Offence;</L>
<L>Do thou thy part, yield, for yielding slacks</L>
<L>The raging flame great transgressions makes:</L>
<L>He that shall dig a pit, that shall prepare</L>
<L>A snare, shall be ensnar'd in his own snare.</L>
<L>Happy is the Just and Holy, for who but he</L>
<L>Can judge of things, or what their Natures be?</L>
<L>For these are Heavens favorits, sent down from
thence,</L>
<L>Unfolding secret Mysteries in Heavenly Eloquence;</L>
<L>Knowing there's a time, true Justice shall preceed</L>
<L>On every purpose, upon every deed.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<HEAD>With God all future Times are
present.</HEAD>
<L>ALL Times to Heaven are now both first and
last,</L>
<L>God sees things present, yea future, as we see
them past:</L>
<L>But we transgress his Laws, 'tis time to part,</L>
<L>For why? the Laws of Nature break the rules of Art.</L>
<L>A smiling Conscience, a contented Mind,</L>
<L>A sober Knowledge, with true Wisdom joyn'd.</L>
<L>Sleep seasonable, moderate and secure;</L>
<L>Actions heroick, constant, blameless, pure:</L>
<L>A life as long as fair, and when expir'd,</L>
<L>A glorious Death unfear'd as undesir'd.</L>
<L>The World is a Book, writ by the eternal Art</L>
<L>Of the great Maker, Printed in Mans Heart.</L>
<L>'Tis falsely Printed, tho Divinely Pen'd,</L>
<L>And all the Errata will appear at the End.</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="9"/>
Believe it Christian, by how much near.</L>
<L>Thou get'st to Heaven, the less will Earth appear:</L>
<L>Call home thy dearest wishes. and recal</L>
<L>Thy hopes; expect the worst that can befal.</L>
<L>Grace giveth Virtue, opinion not Glory;</L>
<L>For Princely favours are but transitory.</L>
<L>Humane Nature, curious without, corrupt within;</L>
<L>A glorious Monument of inglorious Sin:</L>
<L>Yet much our Saviour have endured, yea more</L>
<L>To make us Kings that were but Slaves before.</L>
<L>He that grieves because his grief is so small,</L>
<L>Has a true grief, and the best Faith of all;</L>
<L>He vows his Faith, and the sincere perfection</L>
<L>Of undissembl'd and intire affection;</L>
<L>And such in doing well,</L>
<L>Shall seek for Heaven; not find the flames of Hell.</L>
<L>`Oh! let the Church my Mother instruct me,</L>
<L>Give savory Meat, Cloath and Conduct me</L>
<L>Into my Fathers Arms: These Hands shall never</L>
<L>Trust to the poorness of their own endeavour.</L>
<L>Bring I a Kid, but of my Mothers dressing,</L>
<L>'Twill please my Father, and procure a Blessing.</L>
<L>Most Sins, at least, please Sense, but some are
Treason,</L>
<L>Not only against the Crown of Sense but reason.</L>
<L>But 'tis an error, as foul, to call</L>
<L>Our Sins too great, for Pardon, as too small.</L>
<L>The reason is easie to be riddled out,</L>
<L>One's dispair, the other not doubt.</L>
<L>Lord weaken this Rebellious Flesh,</L>
<L>That's apt to oppose Grace: Oh! quicken, and re∣fresh:</L>
<L>My dull and coward Spirit, that would yield,</L>
<L>And make Proud Satan Master of the Field:</L>
<L>Because 'tis Grave, not Bed, that I am in;</L>
<L>Not a-sleep, but dead in Sin.</L>
<L>Serve God in Plenty, and in Affliction trust;</L>
<L>No thanks to serve our God when he feeds us.</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="9"/>
Promise is a Debt, and Debt implies a Payment;</L>
<L>How can the Righteous then doubt Food and Ray∣ment:</L>
<L>Let not my Thoughts so divided be,</L>
<L>But they mix again, and fix on thee.</L>
<L>Oh! thou who didst appear in cloven Tongues o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Fire;</L>
<L>Direct my Thoughts and with thy self inspire:</L>
<L>That I may search the Scripture, to increase</L>
<L>In the Diviner Knowledge of thy Peace;</L>
<L>That when all things shall cease that are transitory,</L>
<L>Thy Gifts of Grace may be Crown'd with perfect Glory</L>
<L>The Rich Mans sum of untold descended Wealth,</L>
<L>Can give his Body Plenty, but no Health:</L>
<L>The Poor in pains and want possesses all,</L>
<L>The other in plenty finds no Peace at all.</L>
<L>'Tis strange, and yet the cause is easily known;</L>
<L>The one's at Gods finding, the other at his own.</L>
<L>The formers filken Robes, his costly Diet;</L>
<L>Can lend a little Pleasure, but no Quiet.</L>
<L>The latter seldom slacks his Thirst, but from the Pump</L>
<L>And yet his Heart is blithe, his Visage plump.</L>
<L>Such Truths are Subjects, far more fit</L>
<L>For Holy Admiration than for Wit.</L>
<L>'Tis said of <HI>Alexander,</HI> that he complain'd</L>
<L>And wept, because there was no other Worlds to gain</L>
<L>His griefs and thy complaints are not amiss;</L>
<L>He has grief enough that finds no World but this.</L>
<L>Our trust in God for Riches, never must</L>
<L>Exclude our Care, nor Care exceed our tru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</L>
<L>Thy Sacred Will be done, Great God,</L>
<L>To spend, or to suspend thy Rod;</L>
<L>If possible my Will's to miss it,</L>
<L>If otherwise to stoop and Kiss it:</L>
<L>However submit, we shall not be this the worse,</L>
<L>If Conscience Bless, what if <HI>Shimei</HI> Curse.</L>
<L>'Some say the Sacrament's a Supper, and 'tis fit</L>
<L>'To use the posture of a Meal to fit;</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="10"/>
'Can thy Discretion Phares, or thy Zeal</L>
<L>'Give Carnal gestures to a Spiritual Meal:</L>
<L>'A Heavenly Supper and a Fleshy Heart;</L>
<L>'Thy posture has discover'd what thou art.</L>
<L>Of those Sacraments which some call Seven,</L>
<L>Five were Ordain'd by Man and Two by Heaven,</L>
<L>As saith the Eternal Word, whose high Decree</L>
<L>Admits no change, and cannot frustrate be.</L>
<L>What thing is Man? that Gods regard is such:</L>
<L>Or why, should Heaven love wretchless Man so much?</L>
<L>His age is Sinful, and his youth's Vain,</L>
<L>His life's a Punishment, his death's a Pain:</L>
<L>Yea, Man who ought to be a Watch-light in the Temple,</L>
<L>Is as a Snuffer, wants the Oyl of good Example:</L>
<L>Can he be said to fear the Lord that flys him,</L>
<L>Can Word confess him, when as Deed denys him.</L>
<L>For this, Men should strive to have their Hearts relent;</L>
<L>Such Hearts which never knew what Mercy meant.</L>
<L>Gods Love is boundless, apt and free</L>
<L>To turn to Man, when Man returns to thee.</L>
<L>Adjourn thy Sanguine Dreams, awake, arise,</L>
<L>Call in thy Thoughts and let them all advise.</L>
<L>Before the Soul can a true comfort find,</L>
<L>The Body must be prostrate, and the Mind</L>
<L>Truly contrite and repentive within,</L>
<L>And loath the fawning of a bosom Sin:</L>
<L>But Lord, can Man deserve, or can his best</L>
<L>Do justice, equal right, which he transgrest.</L>
<L>When Dust and Ashes mortally offends,</L>
<L>Can Dust and Ashes make Eternal mends:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Heaven unjust? must not the recompence</L>
<L>Be full equivalent to the offence.</L>
<L>What mends by moral Man can then be given,</L>
<L>To the offended Majesty of Heaven.</L>
<L>O mercy, mercy, on thee my Soul relies,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n thee we build our Faith, we bend our Eyes.</L>
<L>If thou wilt, thou canst change our lot,</L>
<L>That we and ours may Live and perish not;</L>
<L><PB N="17" REF="10"/>
Thy Glorious Wisdom, and tender Love</L>
<L>Transcends thy sharper justice will remove.</L>
<L>'Judge not that Field because its stubble,</L>
<L>'Nor him that's poor and full of trouble;</L>
<L>'Tho the one look bare, the other thin,</L>
<L>'Judge not, their Treasure is within.</L>
<L>Injur'd inocency, while the Enemies Unhallow'd Tongue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Makes her a Glorious Martyr in their wro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gs.</L>
<L>The Devils believe, all know they do;</L>
<L>But their belief does make them tremble too:</L>
<L>Men rail at <HI>Iudas,</HI> him that did betray</L>
<L>The Lord of Life, yet do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Day by Day;</L>
<L>They Curse that Traytor Life and Limb,</L>
<L>Tho Curse themselves in Curfing him.</L>
<L>The Thief and Slanderer are almost the same,</L>
<L>The one steals my Goods, the other my good
Name;</L>
<L>The one lives in Scorn, the other dies in Shame.</L>
<L>But from these dark som Clouds Good Lord deliver us,</L>
<L>Let them not interpose betwixt thy Glory and us:</L>
<L>For thou alone art our Creator, in whom we trust:</L>
<L>Some trust too much in their doing well,</L>
<L>In seeking Heaven they find the flames of Hell:</L>
<L>But the pure of Heart have Power to refuse,</L>
<L>Being endow'd with Wisdom, the Evil and Good to
chuse.</L>
<L>He that gives Wisdom to refuse,</L>
<L>Inspires the Art which to chuse.</L>
<L>'In thee, O King, my pensive Soul respires;</L>
<L>'Thou art the fulness of my choice desires;</L>
<L>'Thou art that Sacred Spring, whose Waters burst</L>
<L>'In streams to him, that seeks with Holy Thirst.</L>
<L>'Thrice happy Man, Thrice happy Thirst to bring</L>
<L>The fainting Soul to so sweet a Spring.</L>
<L>God is just, what his deep Counsel wild,</L>
<L>His Prophets told, and justice hath fulfill'd:</L>
<L>But Man, the Child of ruin, to avoid</L>
<L>Less dangers, by a greater is destroy'd;</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="11"/>
Whose Spring is like a Flower for a Days delight,</L>
<L>At Noon we flourish, and we fade at Night.</L>
<L>If Plants be cropt because their Fruits are small;</L>
<L>Think you to Thrive that bears no Fruit all:</L>
<L>But who so Fruitful is, and worthy to Drink this,</L>
<L>Shall be receiv'd unto Eternal Bliss;</L>
<L>Such cannot Dye, the Sacred Nine deny,</L>
<L>All Souls that merits Fame shall ever Dye.</L>
<L>For these must survive, for their self clos'd Eyes,</L>
<L>That now lie slumbering in the dust shall rise.</L>
<L>The highest Heavens have Decreed, to Bless</L>
<L>The Fruitful Souls, and with a fair success;</L>
<L>For that they built their Bliss, not on the blaze of
Glory,</L>
<L>Nor seated their Happiness in things transitory.</L>
<L>O Lord, how great is the Power of thy Hand?</L>
<L>Glorious is thy Name in every Land,</L>
<L>Great God, Unlimited are thy Confines;</L>
<L>And assistest Man in his good Designs.</L>
<L>Thy Mercies like the dew of <HI>Hermon Hill:</HI></L>
<L>Or, like the Oyntment dropping downward still.</L>
<L>Thy Love is boundless, thou art apt and free</L>
<L>To turn to Man, when Man returns to thee.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Sacred Subject, of a Meditation,</L>
<L>Thy Works are full of Admiration:</L>
<L>Thy Judgments all are just, severe and sure;</L>
<L>They quite cut off, or else by lancing Cure.</L>
<L>'My Faith, not Merits, hath assur'd thee mine;</L>
<L>Thy Love, not my Desert, hath made me thine.</L>
<L>Unworthy I, whose drousie Soul rejected</L>
<L>Thy precious Favours, and (secure) neglected</L>
<L>Thy glorious Presence, how am I become</L>
<L>A Bride befitting, so Divine a Groom?</L>
<L>'It is no Merit, no Desert of mine,</L>
<L>Thy Love, thy Love alone, hath made me thine:</L>
<L>Since then the bounty of thy dear Election</L>
<L>Have styl'd me thine. Oh, let the sweet refle∣ction</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="11"/>
'Of thy Illustrious Beams, my Soul inspire,</L>
<L>'And with thy Spirit inflame my hot Desire.</L>
<L>'Unite our Souls; oh, let thy secret rest</L>
<L>'Make a perpetual home within my Breast;</L>
<L>'Instruct me, so that I may gain the skill</L>
<L>'To suit my Service to thy secret Will.</L>
<L>Then shall my Soul that suffers through dispite</L>
<L>Of Error and rude Ignorance, have right:</L>
<L>Then shall my Soul injoy within this Breast</L>
<L>A Holy Sabboth of Eternal rest;</L>
<L>And my dearest Spouse shall Seal me on his Heart,</L>
<L>So sure, that envious Earth may never part</L>
<L>Our joyn'd Souls; let not the World remove</L>
<L>My chast Desires, from so chast a Love.</L>
<L>'All you that wish the bountiful encrease</L>
<L>'Of dearest Pleasures and Divinest Peace;</L>
<L>'I charge you all, if ought my charge may move</L>
<L>'Your tender Hearts, not to disturb my Love;</L>
<L>'Vex not his gentle Spirit nor bereave</L>
<L>'Him of his Joys, that is so apt to grieve.</L>
<L>That he may teach his living Plants to thrive;</L>
<L>And such as are a dying, to revive.</L>
<L>He walks about such tender Plants</L>
<L>To smell their Odours, and supply their wants;</L>
<L>That he may leave his secret Spirit in their Breast,</L>
<L>As Earnest of an Everlasting rest.</L>
<L>To thy Creatour hast my Soul, and let thy Sacre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Vows</L>
<L>Plight Holy Contracts with so sweet a Spouse:</L>
<L>His Left Hand's full of Treasure, and his Right</L>
<L>Of Peace and Honor, and unknown Delight.</L>
<L>Then shall it please our gracious Lord</L>
<L>To Crown, with Audience, his suppliants Word.</L>
<L>O Glory, chace Disloyal Thoughts, let not thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>World allure</L>
<L>My chast Desires from a Spouse so pure.</L>
<L>He'l endow my ardent Soul with sweetness, and inspire</L>
<L>With Heavenly ravishment my rapt Desires.</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="12"/>
O let all times be prosperous, and all places</L>
<L>Be Witness to our undefil'd imbraces.</L>
<L>Sure is the Knot, that true Religion ties;</L>
<L>And Love that's rightly grounded never dies.</L>
<L>'If Error lead not my dull Thoughts amiss,</L>
<L>'My genius tells me where my true Love is:</L>
<L>'He's busie labouring in the flowry Banks,</L>
<L>'Inspiring Sweetness and receiving Thanks.</L>
<L>'Watering those Plants, whose tender Root are dry;</L>
<L>'And Pruning such, whose Crests aspire too high:</L>
<L>'Transplanting, Grafting, Reaping from some,</L>
<L>'And covering others that are newly come.</L>
<L>Then take from each to make one perfect Grace,</L>
<L>Yet would my Love out-shine that borrow'd Face.</L>
<L>So perfect are his Graces, so Divine,</L>
<L>So full of Heaven are those fair looks of thine.</L>
<L>O Sacred Symetry, O rare Connexion</L>
<L>Of many Perfects, to make one Perfection.</L>
<L>O let my Lips, like a perpetual Story,</L>
<L>Divulge thy Graces and declare thy Glory.</L>
<L>Hear comes a Critick, close thy Page,</L>
<L>Thou art no Subject for this Age;</L>
<L>Thou hast no Guilt that does require,</L>
<L>That thou should'st lurk, nor yet retire;</L>
<L>Thou hast no Lustre of thy own,</L>
<L>But what's deriv'd from Heaven alone.</L>
<L>Fear not thy Heaven instructed Page</L>
<L>Will either please, or teach the Age:</L>
<L>For the Wise with ease shall riddle out,</L>
<L>Which is the voice of Wonder, which of Doubt;</L>
<L>For God sends an Angel to protect,</L>
<L>As well from Evil, as to Good direct.</L>
<L>O thou, the beginning, and the end, before whom</L>
<L>Things past, and present, and things to come</L>
<L>Are all alike; O prosper my Designs,</L>
<L>And let thy Spirit inrich my feeble Lines:</L>
<L>Rejoyce, my Soul, and give my Pen the Art</L>
<L>Wisely to move, and me an understanding Heart.</L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="12"/>
Earthly Glories are scarce worth craving to ob∣tain;</L>
<L>They are Happinesses that must be lost again:</L>
<L>Gasp not for Honour, wish no blazing Glory,</L>
<L>For these will perish in an Ages Story;</L>
<L>Nor yet for Power; Power may be carv'd</L>
<L>To Fools, as well as thee that hast deserv'd.</L>
<L>Thirst not for Lands nor Mony, wish for none:</L>
<L>For Wealth is neither lasting nor our own.</L>
<L>Riches are fair Inticements to deceive us;</L>
<L>They flatter while we live, and dying leave us.</L>
<L>What fit of Madness makes us love them thus,</L>
<L>We leave our lives and pleasure leaveth us.</L>
<L>Pleasure is fleeting still and makes no stay,</L>
<L>It lends a smile or twain and steals away.</L>
<L>The pleasures of this World soon abate,</L>
<L>They are lively emblems of our own Estate;</L>
<L>Which like a Banquet at a Funeral show,</L>
<L>But sweeten Grief and serve to flatter Woe.</L>
<L>How slight a thing is Man, how frail and brittle,</L>
<L>How seeming great, how truly little.</L>
<L>We rise securely with the Morning Sun,</L>
<L>But unregarded Die e're Day be done:</L>
<L>Yet his Estate was level, and he hath Free-will</L>
<L>To stand or fall; unforst to Good or Ill.</L>
<L>Such is the State Man was created in;</L>
<L>Within his Power, a Power not to Sin:</L>
<L>His life's a bubble, full of seeming Bliss,</L>
<L>The more it lengthens, the more short it is.</L>
<L>The swelling of his outward Fortune, can</L>
<L>Create a prosperous, not a happy Man.</L>
<L>'A peaceful Conscience is the true content,</L>
<L>'But Wealth is only her Golden Ornament.</L>
<L>'I care not so my Kernel relish well,</L>
<L>'How slender be the substance of my shell.</L>
<L>'My Heart being Virtuous, let my Face be
wan;</L>
<L>'I am to God, I only seem to Man.</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="13"/>
To him the searching of Mens Hearts belong;</L>
<L>Mans Judgment sinks no deeper than the Tongue.</L>
<L>Let shame prevent our Lips, recant and give</L>
<L>To the Almighty his Prerogative.</L>
<L>He overlooks thee, and in one space</L>
<L>Of Time his Eye is fixt on every place.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<HEAD>A Disswasive from placing our
Hopes in transient Happi∣nesses.</HEAD>
<L>BUild not your Bliss upon the blaze of Glory,</L>
<L>Can perfect Happiness be transitory?</L>
<L>Nor in the use of Beauty place your end,</L>
<L>Nor in the enjoyment of a Courtly Friend:</L>
<L>These, if injoy'd, are crost with Discontent,</L>
<L>If not in the pursuit, yet in the event.</L>
<L>Apply thy Heart to Wisdom, with good atten∣tion,</L>
<L>For 'twill inrich thy Soul with fair prevention;</L>
<L>That no foul Treason against thy Blood intended,</L>
<L>Thy Life, thy State, will Loyally be defended;</L>
<L>For Worship, Honor, and true respect</L>
<L>Shall be done to him, whom the Heavenly King do
affect.</L>
<L>Peerless Honours and Princely Rights</L>
<L>Be done, to them in whom this King delights.</L>
<L>The highest Heavens will still conspire to Bless</L>
<L>All faithful Seed, and with a fair success</L>
<L>Their Enemies he'll ty, they shall not make reply;</L>
<L>Not daring to answer nor deny.</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="13"/>
The Heavens grown great with Age must soon
decay,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e pondrous Earth in time shall pass away;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t yet his Sacred Words shall always flourish,</L>
<L>Though Days and Years, and Heaven and Earth do
perish.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an sees like Men, and can but comprehend</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ings as they present are, not as they end.</L>
<L>Man wants the Strength to sway his strong af∣fections;</L>
<L>What Power he has is from Divine direction,</L>
<L>Which oft unseen through dulness of the Mind,</L>
<L>We Nick-name Chance, because our selves are
Blind;</L>
<L>And that's the cause Man's first beholding Eye</L>
<L>Oft Loves, or Hates, and knows no reason why.</L>
<L>If he be Poor that wanteth much, how Poor</L>
<L>he that hath too much, and yet wants more:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ice happy he, to whom the bounty of Heaven</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fficient, with a sparing Hand hath given</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e fairest Crop of either Grass, or Grain,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ot for use, undew'd with timely Rain.</L>
<L>The Wealth of <HI>Crcesus,</HI> were it to be given,</L>
<L>Were not Thank-worthy, if unblessed by Heaven.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Riches, which fond Mort<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s so imbrace,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re not true Riches, it not enlightned with true
Grace.</L>
<L>Wealth interpos'd with too too gross a Care,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey lie obscur'd and no Riches are.</L>
<L>Let not the fawning World to pleasure then invite,</L>
<L>Thy wandering Eyes; the Flesh presents delight.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sist me in my Combat with the Flesh,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elieve my fainting Power, and refresh</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> feeble Spirit. I will not wish to be</L>
<L>Cas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t from the World, Lord, cast the World from
me.</L>
<L>To be afraid to die, or wish for death,</L>
<L>Are Words and Passions of disparing Breath.</L>
<L><PB N="24" REF="14"/>
But wretched Man! were thy condition mine,</L>
<L>I'de not dispair as thou do'st, not repine;</L>
<L>But offer up the broken Sacrifice</L>
<L>Of an humble Soul, before his gracious Eyes.</L>
<L>Whose Works are Miracles of Admiration;</L>
<L>He mounts the Meek amidst their desolation,</L>
<L>Confounds the Worldly Wise, that blindfold they</L>
<L>Grope all in darkness at the Noon of Day:</L>
<L>But guards the humble from reproach of wrong,</L>
<L>And stops the current of the crafty Tongue.</L>
<L>Thrice happy is the Man, his Hands correct;</L>
<L>Beware lest fury force thee to reject</L>
<L>The Almighties Tryal; he that made thy Wound,</L>
<L>In Justice can, in Mercy make it sound.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ear not, tho multiply'd affliction shall</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>siege thee, he at length will rid them all.</L>
<L>In Famine he shall feed, in War defend thee;</L>
<L>Shield thee from Slander, and in Griefs attend thee.</L>
<L>Thy House shall thrive, replenisht with Content,</L>
<L>Which thou shalt Rule in prosperous Government:</L>
<L>For Man <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>licted by the Almighties Hand,</L>
<L>His Faith doth flourish and securely stand.</L>
<L>Yet the worst I'le look for, that I can project;</L>
<L>If better come, 'tis more then I expect:</L>
<L>If other ways I am Arm'd with preparation,</L>
<L>No Sorrows sudden to an expectation.</L>
<L>Lord, to thy Wisdom, I submit my Will;</L>
<L>I will be thankful, send me Good or Ill.</L>
<L>If Good, my present state will pass the sweeter,</L>
<L>If Ill, my Crown of Glory will be greater:</L>
<L>All this experience tells, when I advise</L>
<L>Those, who have taught many, may themselves b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Wise</L>
<L>Tho rising early with the Morning Sun,</L>
<L>Yet unregarded die e're Day be done.</L>
<L>No Gold is pure from dross, tho oft refin'd.</L>
<L>The strongest Ceder's shaken with the Wind.</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est of Men have Sins, none lives secure;</L>
<L>In Nature nothing's perfect, nothing pure</L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="14"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>om mudded Springs, can Crystal Water come.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> some things all Men Sin, in all things some.</L>
<L>Since that my Vesture cannot want a stain,</L>
<L>Assist me lest the Tincture be in Grain.</L>
<L>To thee my great Redeemer do I fly,</L>
<L>It is thy Death alone can change my Dye:</L>
<L>Tears mingled with Blood can scowr so,</L>
<L>That Scarlet Sins shall be as white as Snow.</L>
<L>But wretched Man be not in thought too sure,</L>
<L>Sin steals unseen when we sleep most secure.</L>
<L>By Craft there are, who season error with the taste of truth,</L>
<L>And tempt the frailty of our tender Youth.</L>
<L>What pleasure is in Dainties? if the tast</L>
<L>Be in it self distemper'd, better fast.</L>
<L>Lord, in my Soul, a Spirit of Love create me,</L>
<L>And I will Love my Neighbour tho he Hate me.</L>
<L>I Love the World to serve my turn, and leave her;</L>
<L>Tho i'll not say 'tis no Deceit to cozzen a Deceiver.</L>
<L>She'll not miss me, I less the World shall miss;</L>
<L>To loose a World of G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ief, to injoy a Life Bliss.</L>
<L>By thy Mercy, Lord, to Glory receive me in,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>though my Soul is burthen'd with my Sin;</L>
<L>For thou art Just and bent to a Wise Decree,</L>
<L>Which certain is, and cannot alt'red be;</L>
<L>It seems a Paradox beyond belief,</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t Men in trouble should prolong, relief.</L>
<L>We poor weaklings when we sleep in Sin,</L>
<L>Knock at onr dro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sie Hearts and never lin</L>
<L>Till thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> our sin congealed Eyes,</L>
<L>Lest drown'd in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> we sink and never rise.</L>
<L>The approaching <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> might be at once prevented,</L>
<L>With Pra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs and Pains r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>red, reattented.</L>
<L>We try new ways dispairing of the old;</L>
<L>Love quickens, Courage makes the Spirits bold.</L>
<L>Our God bids go, our Credit bids us stay,</L>
<L>Our guilty fear bids fly another way.</L>
<L>O Earthy Men, make not your Righteous Laws</L>
<L>A trick for gain, let Justice r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e the Cause.</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="15"/>
'O worthless Man, arise and see,</L>
<L>'There's not a twiny thread 'twixt Death and thee.</L>
<L>'This darksome Place thou measur'st may be thy
Grave;</L>
<L>'And sudden Death rides Proud on yonder Wave.</L>
<L>By thoughts dive down into the Abyss of Hell,</L>
<L>And there in Justice doth the Almighty dwell.</L>
<L>Death is a Calander, compos'd by Fate,</L>
<L>Concerning all Men, never out of date:</L>
<L>Yet chear up, I have a message in store</L>
<L>Whose Comforts much, and joyful News is more.</L>
<L>We have yet a Friend Puissant and of Might,</L>
<L>Will see us take no wrong but do us right.</L>
<L>Lets offer up Sacrifice with one accord,</L>
<L>And pay our solemn Vows unto the Lord;</L>
<L>And with penitent Hearts implore him,</L>
<L>And Day and Night pour forth our Souls before him</L>
<L>For shall I be silent; no, I'le speak</L>
<L>Till Tongue be tired, and my Lungs be weak.</L>
<L>Proclaim to us thy Mercy, for we thurst for Grace</L>
<L>For thou art free of Mercy to those that Mercy will
embrace.</L>
<L>O save us harmless from our Foe-mans Jaws,</L>
<L>Who art turned Orator to plead our Cause:</L>
<L>How are thy Mercies full of Admiration,</L>
<L>How sovereign sweet's their Application.</L>
<L>How redef<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed are we with the Rust of Sin,</L>
<L>Which hath abus'd thy Stamp and eaten in.</L>
<L>But yet at length if we repent,</L>
<L>Instead of Plagues and Direful Punishments,</L>
<L>We shall find Mercy, Love, and Heavens Applause;</L>
<L>For the Great Almighty himself will plead our Cause.</L>
<L>Thine Eye that views the moving Spheres above,</L>
<L>Ought to give Praise to him that makes them move.</L>
<L>Here may we see how Prayer and true Repentance</L>
<L>Do strive with God, prevail and turn his Sentence</L>
<L>From Judgment Just, and Plagues Infernal,</L>
<L>To boundless Mercies and to life Eternal.</L>
<L><PB N="27" REF="15"/>
All o're the World how should these Mercies make
a sound,</L>
<L>As Blessings fall, Thansgiving must abound;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dge then did ever Record round thine Ear,</L>
<L>That God forsook the Heart that was fiueere.</L>
<L>But often have we seen that such as Plow</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>wdness and Mischief, reap the same they sow.</L>
<L>The Moral says, all Wisdom that's given</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Hood-wink'd Mortals, first proceeds from Heaven.</L>
<L>Far safer 'tis of things unsure to doubt,</L>
<L>Than undertake to riddle Secrets out.</L>
<L>It was demanded once what God did do,</L>
<L>Before the World was fram'd: Whereunto</L>
<L>'Answer was made, he built a Hell for such</L>
<L>As were too curious, and would know too much.</L>
<L>at such curiosity preceds from him, who can</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ly accuse Man to God, and God to Man;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>no Hourly sows fresh Schisms among the Saints,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ea, buffets them, then laughs at their Complaints.</L>
<L>O Chastity, the Flower of the Soul,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow is thy perfect fairness turn'd to foul:</L>
<L>There are thy Maiden-smiles, thy blushing Cheek,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy Lamb-like Countenance, so fair, so meek;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay not other Virtues serve, but must this Queen</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> made the Subject of Unchast spleen.</L>
<L>So young is Man, that broke with Care and Sor∣row,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e's old enough to Day to die to morrow.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e gives us Passage to endure great Woes,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ath frees us from all Temporal Foes.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t tho secure, my Soul did never slumber,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et do my Woes exceed both weight and number.</L>
<L>Both Poor and Rich, are equal in the Grave;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rvants no Lords, and Lords no servants have.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat needs there light to him that's comfortless;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, Life to such as languish in distress:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bjects of pitty, are Bodies in distress,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd worthy to injoy eternal Rest.</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="16"/>
Lord, make Wise thy Servant; a Wise forecast</L>
<L>Grieves for things present, not for things are past.</L>
<L>Satan have Servants, who can make true boast</L>
<L>They gave away as much as thine have lost:</L>
<L>Others with Learning made to Wisely Mad,</L>
<L>Refuse such Fortunes as <HI>Croesus</HI> never had.</L>
<L>Lord, make me Champion, give me such belief,</L>
<L>A strong and fervent, but not crafty Faith.</L>
<L>I know a forc'd Love neeeds no such great Applause,</L>
<L>Since they Love Ill, that Loves not for a Cause.</L>
<L>I bespeak leave to Answer all this, before I knew</L>
<L>They want no Grief, that find such Friends as you.</L>
<L>Be not discontent, no, no, forbear; for I</L>
<L>Hate less your Censures than your Flattery:</L>
<L>Succour I sought and begged, but none was there</L>
<L>To give the Alms of one poor trickling Tear.</L>
<L>See how I lie devoid of Help or Friend:</L>
<L>O make me humble and mindful of my End.</L>
<L>Lord, make me Just in Image, like my Divin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Creator,</L>
<L>Pollish and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, yea Refine my Nature;</L>
<L>Let me receive all as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thy Hand,</L>
<L>With a thankful Heart as living in thy Land:</L>
<L>And consider the self-same Sorrow</L>
<L>Grieves others to Day, may make me groan to mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
row.</L>
<L>Great King, be my Comfort in my highest Grief,</L>
<L>I will not trust to Mans, but thy relief.</L>
<L>I know Great God, upon my true Repentance</L>
<L>Thou wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t determine to reverse thy Sentence:</L>
<L>Make me, tho in a blind Age Wisely to see;</L>
<L>And in a seeing Age, not b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ind to be.</L>
<L>He that would save his Life, when Honour bids hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
die,</L>
<L>Steals but a Life, and lives by Robbery,</L>
<L>Dishonours his God, and that likens to the Pow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Divine,</L>
<L>That made and placed her in her Fleshly Shrine.</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="16"/>
The Wise and Good-like kind Physicians are,</L>
<L>That strive to heal us by their Care;</L>
<L>Their Physick and their Learning calmly use,</L>
<L>Although the Patient them strangely abuse:</L>
<L>For since the Sickness is they find,</L>
<L>A sad Distemper of the Mind.</L>
<L>The Wiseman in the midst of Woes,</L>
<L>May enjoy and feel a sweet repose:</L>
<L>Might pitty all the Griefs we see,</L>
<L>By compassion Anoint every Malady.</L>
<L>While our selves are calm, our Art improve▪</L>
<L>To rescue them and shew our Love,</L>
<L>That we with open Eyes may see</L>
<L>The brightness of Gods Majesty,</L>
<L>And never more in Chains of Darkness lie,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be secure from Bondage and all Iniquity.</L>
<L>That comforts Divine may fortifie and raise the Soul,</L>
<L>To Heavenly Joys where none can controul.</L>
<L>The World's a hurly burly, and the Court</L>
<L>All Tongues were fill'd with Wonder and Report.</L>
<L>The Watch is set, pursute was made about,</L>
<L>To Guard the King and find the Traytors out,</L>
<L>To punish him according to his due,</L>
<L>That did not Peace nor Loyalty persue.</L>
<L>Had Man been Kind, Loving, True, and always
Good,</L>
<L>As formerly in the Golden Age they stood;</L>
<L>Then had we lived in all Delights and Glory full of
Love,</L>
<L>Blest as the Holy Angels are above.</L>
<L>But now we suffer for evil Deeds,</L>
<L>Reaping the fruit of our ill Weeds.</L>
<L>But thou, O Holy Jesus, who did'st for us Die,</L>
<L>And on the Altar Bleeding for all Men lie;</L>
<L>Bearing all Torment, Pain, Reproach and Shame,</L>
<L>That we by Virtue of the same,</L>
<L>Tho Enemies to God, might be</L>
<L>Redeemed and set at Liberty.</L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="17"/>
Let us likewise favour to others show,</L>
<L>And live in Heaven on Earth below;</L>
<L>Let's prize their Souls, and let them be our gems,</L>
<L>Our valuable Temples and our Diadems,</L>
<L>Rich Spoils and Trophies, our own Joys</L>
<L>Compar'd to Souls, all else are Toyes.</L>
<L>O let them be such unto us, as they were to
thee,</L>
<L>Valued as Vessels of Glory and Felicity:</L>
<L>What would I give, that I might likewise see</L>
<L>The Brightness and true Glory of thy Majesty,</L>
<L>The Joy and fulness of that high Delight,</L>
<L>Whose Blessedness is Glorious, yea Infinite.</L>
<L>And while we feel how much our God doth Love</L>
<L>The Peace of Sinners, how much move,</L>
<L>Sue, and thirst, intreat, lament, and grieve</L>
<L>For all the Crimes in which they live;</L>
<L>And wait, and seek, and call again,</L>
<L>And long to save them from their Pain.</L>
<L>My Memory's like a searce of Lawn. (Alas!)</L>
<L>It keeps things gross, and lets the purer pass,</L>
<L>Which makes me loath my self so vile; O base re∣pute,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> better starve then eat such empty fruit:</L>
<L>Yet dear Lord, let me ne're Confounded be,</L>
<L>Since all my Hope is plac'd in thee.</L>
<L>True Joys alone contentment do inspire,</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rich, content, and make our Courage higher;</L>
<L>The true fear of God, desire and love</L>
<L>Must in the height of all their rapture move:</L>
<L>For content alone's a dead and silent Stone;</L>
<L>The real lite of Bliss is Glory reigning on a Thro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
<L>O let me in a lively manner see</L>
<L>Dear Jesus Eternal Joys in thee;</L>
<L>Inable me to Prai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thy Majesty with all my might,</L>
<L>Whose Grace and Favour is Sweet, yea Infinite.</L>
<L>O let me Love thee, since thy Divine care</L>
<L>Hast promised me a share in thy Kingdom fair.</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="17"/>
'A Sea that's bounded in a Finite Shore,</L>
<L>'Is better far, because it is no more.</L>
<L>'Should Waters endlesly exceed the Skies,</L>
<L>They'd drown the World, and all what e'er we
prize.</L>
<L>'Had the bright Sun been Infinite, the Flame</L>
<L>'Had burnt the World, and quite consum'd the
same.</L>
<L>'That Flame would yield no splendor to the Sight,</L>
<L> ' 'Twould be but Darkness, tho 'twere Infinite:</L>
<L>'One Star made Infinite would all exclude;</L>
<L>'An Earth made Infinite could ne'er be view'd:</L>
<L>'But all being bounded for each others sake,</L>
<L>'He bounding all, did all most useful make.</L>
<L>'And, which is best, in profit and delight,</L>
<L>'Tho not in bulk he made all Infinite.</L>
<L>'He in his Wisdom did their use extend</L>
<L>'By all, to all the World from end to end;</L>
<L>'In all things, all things Service do to all,</L>
<L>'And thus a Sand is endless tho but small;</L>
<L>'And every thing is truly Infinite.</L>
<L>'In its relation deep and exquisite.</L>
<Q><L>'O Lord, be thou within me to strengthen me.</L>
<L>'Without me to keep me.</L>
<L>'About me to protect me.</L>
<L>'Beneath me to uphold me.</L>
<L>'Before me to direct me.</L>
<L>'Behind me to reduce me.</L>
<L>'Round about me to defend me.</L></Q>
<P>O Lord, I beseech thee, give me a longing Affection
after the Pleasures of thy Holy Spirit, because they
are noble, and will advance my Soul to Eternal Happi∣ness;
make me often Contemplate the Joys of Heaven;
the hopes of which is the Joy and Comfort of my Soul.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="discourse">
<PB N="32" REF="18"/>
<HEAD>A short Discourse of the Mor∣tality
of the BODY, and
Immortality, and Excellency
of the SOUL.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Isaiah 26. 19.</BIBL>
<Q>Thy dead Men shall live, together with
my dead Body shall they arise: Awake, and Sing ye
that dwell in Dust: For thy dew is as the dew of Herbs,
and the Earth shall cast out the dead. Glory be to
God on high, and on Earth Peace, Good will towards
Men. Hallelujah.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>1. FIRST, and above all, let us consider how
short, and uncertain our lives are, which
are subject to a Thousand Frailties and
Casualties, and to Death every moment;
insomuch that our whole life is but short and trouble∣some,
and as a Wind that passeth away, and cometh
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ot again, which is evidently declared by the various
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nstances of the Mortality of Frail and Mortal Man:
That our very sleeping and waking, is but a kind of
living and dying; nay, Morning and Evening, is but
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a Emb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>em of the representation of Death, and the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esurrection. For God hath given every Man but a
short time to be upon Earth, so that upon the well
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing it, our well being in Eternity depends. Where∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ore
<PB N="33" REF="18"/>
Divines say, that every Hour or our Life, after
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e are capable of receiving Laws, and knowledge
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f Good and Evil, we must give an Account how
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e spend our Time, to the Judge of Men and Angels:
Therefore we must remember we have a great Work
to do, many Enemies to Conquer, many Evils to pre∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent,
many Dangers to go through, many Necessities
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o serve, much Good to do, many Friends to support,
many Poor to relief, besides the Needs of Nature,
and Relation, our Private and Publick Cares; so that
God hath given every Man Work enough to do, that
there is no room for Idleness; and, yet there is room
for Devotion: Wherefore he spends his Time and
Wealth well, that imploys it in the Service of God, by
setting a part a great Portion of it for Religion, and
the Necessity of Mens Souls, by filling up all the spa∣ces
of his Time with Devotion; and by taking from
Sleep, to imploy in this Exercise.</P>
<P>Secondly, Let him consider that hath but little
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leasure; that he ought to set a part some solemn
Time, for the Venerable Worship of God, Thrice in
the Year, at least, tho he buy it at the rate of any
Labour, and Honest Art; for the quiting of World∣ly
Business, let him attend wholly to Fasting and
Prayer; in the dressing up of his Soul, by Confession,
Meditation, and deep Humiliation; that he may make
up his Accounts, renew his Vows, and improve his
Time, to the Glory of God, and his own Souls good.
Seeing that we know not the Day of our Death, we
ought with all Care and Diligence to prepare for it,
that if it be our Lot to die Young, we may also die
Innocent, before the Sweetness of our Souls are de∣floured;
that we may attain this favour of God, that
our Souls have suffered a less Imprisonment, by being
speedily freed form the load of the Body: For at
Death our Souls are equal to the Angels, and Heirs of
Eternity. For it is observed by some, that after the
time that a Child is Conceived, he never ceaseth to
<PB N="34" REF="19"/>
be to all Eternity; so that if he dies Young or Old h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
hath still an Immortal Soul; and laid down his Bod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
only for a time, as that, which was the Instrumen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of his Trouble and Sorrow; for he will certainly hav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
a more noble Being after Death, than he hath here
Seeing these things are so, let us endeavour to stamp
Religion on our Souls, that God may deliver us from
Unrighteous dealings; may we therefore always hav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
an Ear open, to hear the just Complaints of the Poor
and a Heart full of pitty, to support them; for the
Soul must have the Prehemency over the Body, be∣cause
it is more Noble, and infinitly more to be valu'd
than the Body; for the Body is to turn to Dust with∣in
a little time, but in the mean while, it is nourish∣ed
by sleep, which refreshes it and revives the Spirit.
Wherefore it is said of sleep, it's a kind of Death, and
whatsoever we take from sleep, we add to Life.</P>
<P>Thirdly, <HI>Wherefore be saith, Awake thou that sleep∣est,
and arise from the dead, and Christ shall give thee
light,</HI> Ephes. 5. 14. <HI>Arise,</HI> thou sleepy Soul <HI>call upon
thy God,</HI> Jonah 1. 6. suffer it not to be drowsy or
sleeppy, when it stands upon the bri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ks of Eternity;
but prefer the care of the Soul before all the World,
for it is more to be valued than Ten Thousand Worlds:
Wherefore take heed to your selves, and be Wise in
time, before it is to late; for though you know not
what the Soul is, because you see it not, neither can
you feel it; yet it is a Particle which came from
Heaven, and when it goes out of the Body it goes to
God, to Live for ever; it sleeps not, neither doth it
die, for it is Immortal and of an Immortal Nature,
and so impossible to be destroy'd, for we have our
Saviours own Word for it, when he saith, <HI>Ye cannot
kill the Soul, St.</HI> Luke 12. 4. and when he saith, <HI>My Fa∣ther
is the God of</HI> Abraham, <HI>the God of</HI> Isaac, <HI>and the
God of</HI> Jacob, <HI>St.</HI> Matt. 22. 32. whereby he plainly
shews, that the Soul which is the nobler part of Man,
tho it be taken from the Body, is alive, for saith he,
<PB N="35" REF="19"/>
<HI>My Father is the God of the living, and not of the dead</HI>
as dead, but of the living that are dead. So that th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Souls of all departed people are alive, for althoug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
their Bodies are crumbled to Dust, from whence the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
were taken; their Souls are with God that gave them
or in some place of Gods appointment, according <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
their lives have been, <HI>Because God have prepared ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Mansions for us, St.</HI> John 14. 2. and as we have im∣proved our Talent, so shall our Station be. St. <HI>Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI>
also saith, <HI>That one Star differeth from another Star <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Glory;</HI> and since these things are so, let us not lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
a Minutes time, but improve it to the Glory of Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and our own Souls Good, and begg of him to gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
us a Heart inflamed with Love, and winged wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Duty, that we may give up our Souls totally to h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Adorable Majesty, that he may dwell in the Thro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
of our Souls for ever: And after this Life we may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
admitted to the Vision of Bliss, and have free Inte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>course
with all Holy Souls in those beautious Regions.</P>
<P>Fourthly, 'Tis evident, that Spirits fill no roo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
tho they could see all things, which point is ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
dubious and unsertain; for that Holy Souls can beho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
the visible Actions of Mortal Men, to us is altogeth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
uncertain; tho we doubt not but they do behold wha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>soever
is Acted in those Regions where they dwe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
in those Infinite Dimensions, or Heavenly Habitations
tho they are inriched with Liberty, and made brig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
by Knowledge, derived from the Illustrous and Illum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nated
Power of the Omnipotent God, who is infinit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Communicative to be Good, and to do Good to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Mankind; and hath made the Soul of Man on purpo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
that it might see him in his Kingly Country, whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
St. <HI>Paul</HI> saith, We shall be like him, for we shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
him as he is not, as we now behold him darkly throug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
a Vail in deep Obscurity, but Face to Face in Unva<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed
Glory. And if the Eye of the Body that was ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
for the World, being so little a Ball of Earth a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
Water, can take in all and see the visible World, <HI>i. e.</HI>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat part of it, on which the sight of the Eye can be
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>resent, much more is the Soul able to see and be pre∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent
with all that is Divine and Eternal; tho the Soul
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> unhappily divided from God, is a weak and in∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onsiderable
Creature; but when United to God, 'tis
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Transcendant and Celestial Thing, God being its Life,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reatness, and Power; for as the Apostle saith, he
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat is ioyned to the Lord is one Spirit, for his Omni∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>resence
and Eternity fills the Soul, and makes it able
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> contain all hights and depths, and all things may
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e in it as it were by Thoughts and Intellections; and
Magnanimous desires are the Natural result of such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Magnanimous Capacity: Such a Soul then in respect
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f its Capacity is an Immovable Sphere of Power and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nowledge, and by imagination is able to pass
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rough the Centre of the Earth, and through all
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xistencies; for it is most Capacious and Swift. Com∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and
it then by thought to go into <HI>India,</HI> and sooner
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>en thou canst bid it, it will be there; not as passing
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>om Place to Place, but by Thought and Immagina∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on,
suddenly, in a moment, as you may send it to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaven by the slight of a Thought, as you may at any
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>me command it to fly, tho not by the assistance of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ings in a Bodyly manner, but after the manner that
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouls pass from Place to Place, not locally, but after
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e manner of Spirits: For the Soul of Man is said to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> an Immutable Essence, his Power of Reasoning is
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ive, even when 'tis quiet, and the Body unactive.
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is one and the same for Nature in all Men, tho not
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Indeuments, of it self equally inclined to Great
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ransendent Things; tho in most Men 'tis misguided,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ffled and suppressed; but where it has the common
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssistances that God has prepared for it, it is a Miracu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us
Creature and of near alliance to the Divine Ma∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sty.
For a Man being Wise and Holy, his Soul is,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it were, in the Heavenly World; and it's no trivial
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>jury can make him contend being Liberal and Mag∣nanimous,
<PB N="37" REF="20"/>
he is prone to do Heroical Things, and to
make himself Venerable to his very Adversary; being
averse to all Wroth, Clamour, and Anger scarcely in
any thing being defective, and becomes a great Man
by contemning Danger, having an Infinite felicity in
his Dayly view, and may justly strengthen himself in
the hopes of Divine assistance, knowing the Infinite
value of his Soul, and believing the Blessedness that is
in reserve for it, by reason of the greatness of interiour
Bliss; and is therefore environed with the bright
Beams of his own injoyments, and always beggeth of
God, that as Sin hath abounded, so may Grace super∣abound;
that all Souls may receive the Blessed ad∣vantages
of the Divine Forgiveness; that all may
have the Blessed Assistance of Grace, to lead us into
all Virtues, which are themselves our Aids to bring us
to Glory: For these acquire good Habits, and infuse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Grace, causing us to incline to the secret Study of Fe∣licity,
that we may be even now possessed with sin∣cere
and pure delights; for Godliness is a kind of
God-likeness, a Divine Habit or Frame of Soul, that
may fitly be accounted the fulness of the Stature of
the inward Man. For 'tis an Inclination to be like
God, to please him, and injoy him; and he may be
said to be God-like, that is High and Serious in all
his Thoughts, Humble and Condescending in all his
Actions, full of Love and good Will to all the Crea∣tures,
and bright in the Knowledge of all their Na∣ture,
Covering all the Treasures of God, and Breaths
after the Joys of Heaven. Recollecting all his broken
and scattered Thoughts, nothing less than the Wisdom
of God will please the God-like Man, for God-likeness
is the comment of Amity betwixt God and Man,
Eternity and Immensity are the Sphere of his Acti∣vity,
and are often frequented and filled: With his
Thoughts he must injoy God, or he can enjoy no∣thing,
nor himself; for nothing will satisfie him but
the Glory of his great Creator, the great Counsellor
<PB N="38" REF="21"/>
of Nature, and the perfect Beauty of the whole Uni∣verse.
And to be exalted to this frame is a very su∣blime
and glorious perfection; and Blessed are all those
that are thus Beautified in their Minds, and are Blessed
with such an Angelical Soul, and are thus curiously
acquainted with these things: I heartily wish, that all
that shall happen to peruse these things, may be a
little higher elevated with the true inward Sense of
what is here described, and with the secret Perfecti∣on
of the Decrees of God, and the Nature of his Di∣vine
Essence, that they may be worthy to partake of his
sublimity; and hereby aspire to dwell with him for
ever, and covet the Treasure of his Immensity, and
be able to expaciate therein, by being Blessed with the
Wisdom of an Angel, in being as Divine and Heaven∣lly,
by being truly eminent in inward and outward
Worth; not being either weak or defective: For
Virtue is base and not Virtue while it is remiss, or not
carried to the highest pitch 'tis possible, for then it is
that their Glory shall su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mount the rage of their Ene∣mies;
and their true worth continue Immortally shi∣ning
throughout all Kingdoms and Ages for ever, In∣heriting
the benefits of their own Virtues, in the
Peace and Tranquility of their own happy Conditi∣on;
and this because they have been prepossed with
true gratitude and felicity; and in all their actions been
Cloathed with Meekness, and a condescending beha∣viour,
having been highly kind and serviceable in their
Generation, free from the spots and blemishes of the
World; having frequently arrived to an universal Ap∣plause,
and truly deserved to be exceedingly Honour∣ed
by all People; for it's a very hard matter to Hate
a very excellent Person. No Man was ever uppraided
for being a Wise and Gallant Man; but it often happens
that for some Infirmity that a good Man have, he may
suffer the misfortune of being censured; but meerly
for being Good or Wise, 'tis not usual to suffer re∣proach,
contempt, or slander, for it would be cruel,
<PB N="39" REF="21"/>
for being Wise and Good, Holy and Chast, Just and
Liberal, Honest and Merciful, Meek and Couragious
to be vilified: Perhaps he may be censured and ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
at his first setting out, but when he have made a goo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
proficiency in Goodness, he will be sure to overcome
the rage and malice of his Enemy, because he have
made himself Eminent and Conspicuous, and there∣fore
is admired by all that love Virtue; because he is
a Man of intire and approved Virtue, well known
for a Person of Honour and Worth, and therefore the
first envies and censures abate, because he hath long
exercised Virtue and Goodness, with great Activity
and Courage, Prudence and Wisdom: Thus <HI>Moses</HI> after
his long Meekness and invincible Fidelity to the Jewish
Nation, was in the close of his Life most exceedingly
Honoured by all People, and injoyed a veneration of
high Degree; for his Glory surmounted the rage of his
Enemies; and he will for ever continue Immortally,
shining throughout all Kingdoms and Ages. All good
Men delight in his Eternal Praises; for he is now glori∣fied
and admired for his Sanctity: He therefore is a full
and adequate Object of our early humble Imitation
not in working Miracles, but in Meekness, Love and
Magnanimous Actions, enriched with Liberality, and
made bright by Knowledge, guided by Wisdom to
the highest end; every action being mixt with Gravity
and Chearfulness, for in the due use of these means we
may actually injoy all Blessedness and Glory, Righteous<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ness,
Holiness and Goodness, Love and Christian Cha∣rity
are the true Lineaments and Colours of suchy Men<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Minds; for these are the true Ornaments of every
Blessed Soul, they shine upon the Face and make him
Glorious in the perfection of Beauty. This Man is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Humility, and yet all injoyment amazed at its ow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
nothingness and vileness; yet, at the same time, ra¦vished
with wonder at the height of his Felicity, and
yet this is no Paradox, for the whole System of Religio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
is Mysterious; for the lower the Man is in his ow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="40" REF="22"/>
Eyes, the more doth the goodness of God appear in
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>im, and the more transcendently Sweet is his Adorati∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and Satisfaction; by his gratitude he Sacrifices him∣b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
to the Deity. Pride aimeth at the utmost height
of Esteem and Honour, and is feed by its own Beauty
and Glory, yet Foolishly undermineth the Person it
would advance, with the greatest baseness and shame
imaginable; it devours the Beauty which ought to feed
it, and destroys the Glory in which it delights. The
higher the greater, the more perfectly Glorious and
Blessed the Person is that is exalted, is the baseness and
ingratitude of Pride, and is therefore the dregs of
Impiety; and forfits and renounces all delights, and
blackens whatsoever might appear auspicious, which
provokes detestation in all that delight in the Truth,
for this turns the brigthness of Seraphims into the abo∣minations
of Devils.</P>
<P>Fifthly, Some Men imperfectly Virtuous abhor o∣thers,
for being more excellent than themselves, at
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>east for being more Honourable and more Prospe∣rous;
but this proceeds from a naughty and a vitious
Heart, unacquainted with the Truth of Goodness, and
the true A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mity of real Virtue: For true Goodness is
excellent from the quality of its Object; and all that
have true Goodness dwelling in them, will undoubted∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y
venerate it, and all those in whom they find it; for
whosoever is so happy as to be truely Good, will with
<HI>Moses,</HI> wish that all the Lords People were Prophets,
and that every Soul were a Fountain of Delights. For
it's a Beautiful thing to be exceeding Good, for there
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s an infinite and eternal force in true Goodness, it
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ideth Luster and Beauty to all that are Blessed there∣with;
for it's Beautiful thing to be exceeding Good,
or every degree hereof have exceeding Sweetness in it;
and these are filled with hope Divine, and have infi∣nite
Felicity in their Daily view, they know their Du∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y,
and their Master, and the infinite value of their
Souls, and have a fore tast of interior Bliss: Being
<PB N="41" REF="22"/>
acquainted with the true Habits of Divine Grace, and
are as it were, prone to Celestial Epicurisme, (if
may be premitted so to speak) by being really en∣gaged
in the true Study of Felicity. A Pious Man
hath great Treasures, high Honours, pure Pleasures,
having a true tast of infinite Delights; but is not ra∣vished
with Temporal Pleasures nor Treasures; not
melting with these nor flinching at any Temporal di∣stresses;
for neither of these can move the fixed Mind
of a true good Man, for his Thoughts Divine are up∣on
higher Objects, for his inward Stature is miracu∣lous,
and his Complexion Divine; he pities poor viti∣ous
Princes, that are oppressed with Heavy Crowns
of Vanity, whether of Gold or Emralds, whose Souls
ought to be endued with Generous and Noble Prin∣ciples,
that they may be worthy the infinite perfecti∣ons
of the great God, who giveth liberally to all
Men, and uppraideth not; and would have all Men en∣dued
with Divine and deep Delights, that they may be
eminent and conspicuous in the true exercise of every
Virtue, and be Cloathed with great Activity, Courage
and Prudence, to overcome their Enemies, and in∣herit
the Benefits of their own Virtues, in the Peace
and Tranquility of a happy Condition; by being Libe¦ral
and Kind, Humble and Chearful, Rejoycing and
Trusting exceedingly in God; then shall their Soul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
be even now as happy, as if they had taken Possess∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on
of Heaven. Having taken that City, as it were
Violence or Force, by carrying Virtue to the highe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
pitch humane frailty could exalt it to. God havin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
given us many Lights, to assist our Souls in the com¦pleating
more allurements, to provoke our desir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
after more of Heaven, and its Glorious Injoyment<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
so that all our Inclinations may now become Puri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and Praise, that we may hereby be able to reconci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Men to God, who were formerly Enemies to Gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and Virtue, by putting Embroideries on Religion, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
moving in a Sphere of Wonder: In that his Life is
<PB N="42" REF="23"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ontinual stream of Miracles, for such a Man carries
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Light whereever he goes, for he is Cloathed like
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Son in his Raies, and Reigns like a King by the
sole Power of Virtue and Goodness, in Beautifying
Religion in the due exercise hereof, making himself
great by inriching others; being full of Musick in the
Words of his sweet and pleasing behaviour: This be∣ing
conducive to his own Ease and Honour; the want
therefore of the abovementioned Virtues is pernicious
and destructive, for these Holy Works and Wise Dis∣positions
of Soul are absolutely necessary to qualifie us
for Heaven; For all the Fathers teach us. both An∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ient
and Modern, that good Works are inseparable
attendants upon a justifying Faith; and no Heretick
hat is either Grave or Serious, can deny this sequel:
For this must consequently follow upon the Premises,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or good Works are absolutely necessary to Salvation, tho
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey can in no wise merit it; for far be it from us
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>om decrying good Works or the due use of them, but
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he merit of them. For that there is any real or per∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onal
merit in them, we do indeed d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ry; not but
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat high induments of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is a greater Blessing to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll that are so highly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by the Hand of Heaven,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to be in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iched by them; and good Works are cer∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>inly
conditional to Life Eternal, for in the great Day
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f Mercy, 'twill be said. <HI>Come for ye have done them;
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, God for ye have not done them.</HI> So that tho they
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> not meritorious, yet they are undoubtedly condi∣onal
to Bifs, for the more of these any Man have a
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ue share in, the more happy Eternally will he un∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>oubtedly
be; so that what the Church of <HI>England</HI> in
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>is and in all points do Teach, is most assuredly pure
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d refined, and in all points Conformable to the Pri∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>tire
Times; neither is She pure in Doctrine only,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t in Charity most Catholick, and in hearty Practise
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ost refined, for She admonishes her Children, that
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>yey may not be Strangers to any point of Doctrine
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>at is of moment to Salvation, unless they should
<PB N="43" REF="23"/>
unhappily be Aliens to Felicity, by being Foreigners to
the Truth; but that they may in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is Light learn to
see the true Light, that enlighten every one that
cometh into the World: 'Tis this Beauty of Truth
that maketh Knowledge of such infinite value, as to
repair the Divine Image in us, in which consists the
perfection of our Nature, renews us in the Spirit of
our Minds, purging our Consciences from dead Works,
securing our Minds from that restlesness and unquiet∣ness,
which Minutly attends both the Dominion and
Guilt of Sin, which racks the Mind with dreadful ex∣pectations,
and fills the Consciences with dismal hor∣ror
and direful Confusion, and lays them obnoxious
to the dreadfulest denunciations imaginable, not only
Temporal Improsperity, but Eternal Punishments in
the dismal Shades of the other World. But to avoid
the danger of these, let us convince our understand∣ings,
that we ought to aspire to live Angelical lives,
such as becomes a reformed Religion built upon the
Doctrines of the Apostles, and have all the Marks of
a true Church; so that every one may prove and try
himself, whether he be in the right; for by trying
the Spirits we may know them, if we observe their
Fruits; may we therefore perswade our Affections to
stick close to this refined Religion, that is certainly
the true Path to Heaven, and conducive to Life and
Bliss: For this Church agreeable to the Holy Scrip∣tures
directs to the Treasures of Divine Wisdom and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch Oracles, to which, it is safe to resort, for saving
Knowledge to rule and guide us to a Holy Life; there∣fore
we ought Studiously to imbrace whatsoever we
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>earn from her, since She is now refined and purged
from all Error and Corruption, Superstition, and
whatsoever is contrary to Divine Truth; for in her
Preaching She observes the Method of Christ, by un∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ailing
the very Truth to her Disciples, making Christs
Word to us, as it is in it self, the Power of God to
Salvation. So that now the Gospel with Noon Day
<PB N="44" REF="24"/>
brightness, does cearly shine amongst us, for She
gives us cautionary Advices, and to them subjoins plain
Directions, sheving us how to detect Error and to
love Truth; so that her Counsel may be of the same
effect to us, as the Oral Word was to our Progenitors,
who lived their own Doctrine and Preached their
own Experience, and gave up themselves without re∣serve
to the guidance of Gods Word, inwardly reve∣rencing
every Paragraph of it, as an immediate mes∣sage
from the Almighty: For every thing in Scripture
is sublimely Divine. <Q>Its Doctrine are most accom∣modate,
to the refreshment and building up of our
Minds, and in all respects so ordered, that eve∣ry
one may draw thence what is sufficient for him,
provided he approach it with Devotion, Piety and
Religion.</Q> For the things of God are Spiritually
descerned, as the secret Word of God was fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st dicta∣ted
by the Holy Spirit; so still it must owe its effects
and influence to its Cooperation, for by this its Power
and Energy, insinuatively perswades the Heart to be
led by the Power of it; and to invoke the Divine aid,
by darting Ejaculations up to God, that we may tru∣ly
understand the sense and meaning of his Divinely
Inspired Word, by ke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ping our Minds fixt and attent
upon what we either hear or read that refin'd Thoughts
ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ways poss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> our Minds to convince our Under∣standing,
and perswade our Affection, and intirely
rule our Imaginations; that Divine Meditations may
always prepossess our Minds, and refresh and revive
our Souls; turning out of our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reast all distracting
Phansies, lest our Chr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stianity should vapor away and
disappear, by a pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing to too high degrees of Specu∣lation;
and neglecting to practice plain Truths, for
the practice of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Truths are infinitely of more
use, then to Study curious or critical Remarks upon
those Mysteries, on which God have spread a vail. <Q>I
mention this not to divert any from aspiring to the
highest degrees of Perfection, but to reprove that
<PB N="45" REF="24"/>
preposterous course many ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
est weight upon those things <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
least; and have more Zeal for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
then for express downright Comm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
the one to commute for the contemp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></Q>
For some Men are apt to scruple small thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
not startle at Injustice or Oppression; which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
to be rectified, that Men may have an equa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
to all the Commands of God, not letting any <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
slip their Observation: For he that breaks the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
command is guilty of all, not but that he that brea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
them all is guilty of more severe Punishments, then he
that breaks but one. But the meaning is, he that
breaks one shall not go Unpunished, being deeply guil∣ty
of Disobedience. God having required an equal
regard to all his Precepts, and who so gives him not
their whole Heart, offers to him but a lame and unac∣ceptable
Sacrifice; for any thing less than the full
power of our Wills cannot please God, who is of pu∣rer
Eyes than to behold any the least Evil with appro∣bation;
for his Wisdom being so pure a Majesty, can∣not
be pleased with any thing that is impure of Heart:
Necessary is it therefore, to give him the full of our
Mind, Will and Soul; or, as our Catechism expresses
it, <HI>To serve him with all our strength,</HI> in every Centure
of our Lives. For the more we serve him, the more
and better shall we be regarded, honoured and reward∣ed,
by him the searcher of all Hearts.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Of the excellent Qualification of
the Soul, from its high Extraction.</HEAD>
<P>ALthough Men do not know the Soul, neither
can they see it, because it is like the Eyes of
our Bodies, it sees every thing but it self; but it self
<PB N="46" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> assuredly know that by it we
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> inabled to do actions of Piety
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Consciences dictates to us what is
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> done, for that is a good and faith|
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> that whensoever we do amiss, we do,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> our Souls, and stupifie our Consciences,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Evil or cause others so to do. But to a|
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> let us begg of God, to give us a chast Spi|
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> is the Crown of faithful Souls: Wherefore
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> said of Virginity, that it is the Life of Angels,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> animal of the Soul, the advantage of Religion,
which is a mutual, a strong, and voluntary inclination
to the Worship of God; for it is empty of Cares,
and ought to be full of Prayers, which are fed with
Fastings; it is very advatagious to Devotion and Re∣tirement,
for whosoever is careful of his Time and Be∣haviour
shall not be robbed of his reward, for his
good intentions.</P>
<P>Secondly, Then fail not of being eminent in your
Generations, for Virtue and Piety, by being burning
and shining Lights, unmingled with any manner of
Evil, that you may follow the <HI>Lamb</HI> wheresoever he
goeth: But above all be Humble, for that is the Or∣nament
of our Holy Religion, and it makes you to
differ from the Wisdom of the World. For our Learn∣ing
is then best, when it teaches us Humility, for
to be proud of our Learning is the greatest Igno∣rance
in the World; for our Learning is so long in get∣ting,
and so very imperfect, that the Learnedest per∣son
in the World knows not the Thousandth part of
that which he is Ignorant of; so that he cannot at∣tain
to any Maturity of Knowledge, proportionable to
that of Angels. No Man therefore has any cause to
boast of his excellency, for what thou hast, thou hast
received from God, and art the more Obliged to re∣turn
him Thanks for it; and thou art bound to im∣prove
the Grace that he hath given thee to his Glory.
Consider then that thou wer't nothing before thou
<PB N="47" REF="25"/>
as Born, and what wer't thou in the first Regions of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y dwellings before thy Birth, but uncleaness. What
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ast thou for many Years after, but Weakness and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ailty? As the <HI>Psalms</HI> expresses, <HI>It even as the smoak
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at vanisheth away,</HI> Ps. 102. 3. A great debtor then
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t thou to God, to thy Parents, to the Earth, and all
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e Creatures. For all Men that have ever been, were
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ressed with Hunger, and the Frailties of human Na∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re;
so that the best and wisest Persons are subject
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o the Necessity of Nature; wherefore there is great
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ause of Humility, for the Spirit of Man is light and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oublesome, his Body is bruitish and sickly, he is con∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ant
in his Folly and Errour, inconstant in his Man∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er
and Good Purposes; his Labours are vain, intri∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate
and endless, his Fortune is changeable, but sel∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om
pleasing, his Wisdom comes not till he be ready
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> die; or at least, till he have spent great part of his
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>me in wast: His death is certain, always ready at
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Door, but never far off, upon these or the like Me∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>itations.
If we dwell on them, or frequently retire
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> consider them, we shall see nothing more reasonable
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an to be Humble, and nothing more foolish than to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Proud; Humility consists not in railing against our
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lves, or wearing mean Cloaths, or going softly, or
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>bmissively; but in a hearty and real mean Opinion
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f our selves.</P>
<P>Thirdly, Believe thy self then an unworthy Person, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
heartily as thou believest thy self to be Hungry, Poor,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Sick; when thou art so, love to be concealed and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> esteemed off. Be not troubled when thou art
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ighed and undervalued; and when thou hast done
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ny thing worthy of praise return it to God, who is
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e Giver of the Gift, and Blesser of the Action; and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ive him thanks for making thee the Instrument of
is Glory. Secure a good Name to thy self, by being
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irtuous, Pious and Humble; and when People have
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n occasion to speak well of thee, take no content in
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>raise when it is offered thee, but let thy rejoycing
<PB N="48" REF="26"/>
be in Gods Gift, but let it be alay'd with Fear, lest th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Good bring thee to Evil. Pray often for Gods Grac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
with Humility of gesture and passion of desire, tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
God may be Glorified by thy Example of Humility
which may be as well in a low condition as in a ric<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Begg God <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> irri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h thy Soul with all Graces, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
when thou had attained them, give God thanks <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
them. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ide hinders the acceptance of our Prayer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Humility pierceth the Clouds, and will not give ove<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
till God accepts; neither will it depart till the mos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
high regards: <HI>For he resisteth the Proud, but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Grace to the H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mble, St.</HI> Jam. 4 6. Then begg G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and Pardon, that it may be a remedy and relief a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gainst
Misery and Oppression, and be content in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
conditions; begg Tranquility of Spirit, Patience i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Affliction, that we may gain Love abroad and Peac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
at home. Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sider the blessed S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>iour of the World <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
who left the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of his Father, the Lord of Glory <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
who took upon him the li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of Labour, and came t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
a State of Poverty, to a Death of Mal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, to th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Grave of Death, and the intolerable Calamiti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s which
we deserved: Therefore it's but reasonable, that w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
should be as Humble in the mid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> of our greatest Im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>perfections
and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ins, as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> was in the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
and fulnes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of the Spi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it, g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eat Wisdom, perfect Life▪
and most admirable Virtue. Wherefore be cont<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
with all Thing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that shall happen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>to you, and seek<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
after the Spirit of Peace, which will make you shin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
like Angels, or the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> above; and in so doing you
will not fear Death, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ther fear a dishonest Acti∣on,
and think Im patience far worse than any Disease.
Be ready to do Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d to the destr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yers of your Fam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
for the re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ards of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> doing is very certain, and do te∣stifie
that you have a most no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le Soul within you,
which is a Particle of the Divine R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ys.</P>
<P>Forthly, Dress up your Souls, that they may be fit
to appear before the Majesty of Heaven; for you can
die but once, and if you do not die well, you will
<PB N="49" REF="26"/>
Perish undoubtely for ever: And yet there is no Wise
or Good Man to Perish, for God have ordained an ex∣pedient
help for all Men that they should not Perish,
for he gives us Pardon for our past Offences, and Grace
to prevent us for the future, even the due disposition
of his Holy Spirit, that we may delight in that which
his Majesty delights in; that is, true Virtue and W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s∣dom,
which will cause us to injoy the Blessings that
God sends us, and to bear patiently with Meekness
our Calamities which our own Sins have brought upon
us, may we th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>refore consider this Day is only ours,
for we are dead to yesterday, and we are not Born to
too morrow; these considerations will make us to
bear Poverty, with Nobleness, Patience and Meek∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ess,
and not blame the Providence of God for placing
us in a low F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtune, but in all Troubles and sad Ac∣cidents,
let us take Sanctuary in Religion, and by In∣nocency
cast Anchor for our Souls, to keep them from
Shipwrack, though they be not kept from Storms:
By these means we may fill our Cup full of pure and
unmingled Joys, for no Wise M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n did ever describe
F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>licity without Virtue, no Good M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n did ever think
Virtue to depend upon the Vari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ty of good or bad
Fortune; 'tis no Evil to be Poor, but to be Virtuous
and Impatient; therefore be Patient under Affl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctions,
and begg God to give thee a happy deli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erence out of
them, and be content with Poverty, for that adds
Lustre to thy Person, and may make thy Virtue more
excellent if thou improve it wisely, for there is but
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> things that we feel is so bad, as that we fear.
Many eminent Scholars have been eminently Poor;
some by choice, and more by chance and the invin∣cible
decrees of Providence; wherefore the Rich may
support the Poor, by his Wealth; and, perhaps the
Poor may instruct the Rich in Learning and Expe∣rience;
for it may be observed, no Man had all Excel∣lency
and Felicity in this one Person or Power: Therefore
there is but few Wise and Good Men that would change
<PB N="50" REF="27"/>
Conditions entirely with any Man in the World, for
though some there are that would desire the Wealth
of one Man added to himself, or the Power of another,
and the Learning of a third; yet, still he would re∣ceive
these in his own Person, because he loves that
best, and therefore esteems that most, tho we desire
the Wealthy to Inrich us, the Powerful to Pro∣tect
us, and the Witty to Delight us. Let us con∣sider,
that in the Fortune of a Prince, there is not the
course Robes of Beggary, but there is infinite Cares,
Fears and Dangers; therefore the State of Affliction
is a School of Virtue, wherein there is the Exercise of
Wisdom, the Tryal of Patience, and the wining a
Crown; for this may be said to be the Gate of
Glory.</P>
<P>Fifthly, Therefore we may not expect to be better
treated than the Apostles, and Saints; nay, than the
Son of the Eternal God, the Heir of both the Worlds.
Affliction is oftentime the occasions of Temporal ad∣vantages,
as well as Spiritual; and if we imploy our
Grace and Reason well it will deliver us from extream
Necessitys, and if you will not otherwise be Cured:
If you improve your time w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll, God will deliver you
in his due time, if it be for his Glory and your Good,
for his Power can Sanctifie Poverty to you, and make
it become as necessary as Riches; for tho Poverty
makes a Man dispised, and contemptable, and exposed
to a Thousand Insolencies of evil Persons, and leaves
t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>em defenceless; yet, it may make them look up
to God, and trust more firmly in him the Rock of
their Strength, who will most certainly deliver them
from the cruelty of all Wicked Persons: Wherefore
it is said of Poverty, that it is the Sister of a good
Mind, the Parent of sober Councel, the Nurse of all
Virtue; and this is really true, a great Estate has great
Croses, and a mean Fortune has small ones; for Riches
often bread a Disease in the Souls of them that long
after them, and admire them with too much egar∣ness
<PB N="51" REF="27"/>
when they have them, for Riches are great dangers
to the S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ul, not only of them that covet them, but
al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to most that have them; wherefore let us trust in
Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ist, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ho have promised, that we should have suf∣ficient
for this Life, who have said, that his Father
takes care for us; and we are sure that he knows all
his Fathers Counsels and Kindnesses towards us, for if
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Wisdom gives but a very little, he will make it
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a great way; for if he sends thee but course Diet,
he wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it and make it Healthful to thee, and can
cure a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l the Anguish of thy Poverty, by giving thee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
and the Grace of Contentment; for the Grace
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> God <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> you of Providence, and, yet the Grace
of God feeds and supports the Spirit even in the want
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Providence. And if a thin Table be apt to infeeble
the Body, or Spirit of one used to feed better; yet
the cheerfulness of the Spirit that is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>essed with dew
from above, will make a thin a Table become a deli∣cacy:
If the M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n be but as well Taught, as he is Feed,
by Learning the Duty, when he receives the Reward,
Poverty is therefore in some sense eligible, and to be
preferred before Riches, but in all senses it is very to∣lerable.</P>
<P>Sixthly, But to return to a further inquiry into the
Excellency of the Soul, let us consider the various spe∣culations
that the Soul of Man is capable of entertain∣ing
her self withal, and we shall see that there is
none of greater moment, or closer concernment to her
than this of her own Immortality, and independance
on this Terestial Body; for hereby, not only the in∣tricacies
and perplexities of Providences are made
more easie and smooth to her, and she becomes able
by unraveling this clue from end to end, to pass and
repass safe through this Labyrinth, wherein many,
both anxious and careless Spirits have lost themselves▪
But also which toucheth her own Interest more parti∣cularly,
being once raised to the Knowledge and Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lief
of Good and Evil, so weighty a conclusion <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="52" REF="28"/>
may return to this most certain and most compendious
way to her own Happiness, which is to be acquired
by bearing Affl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ction patiently, and endeavouring to
overcome whatever tempts her, during the time of this
her Pilgrimage, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith a careful preparing of her self,
for her future Condition; by such Noble Actions, and
Heroick Qualifications of Mind, as shall render her most
welcome to her own Country; which belief and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣pose
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in an utter in c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pacity of e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣ther
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
at nothing but what is not in the Power of M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n
to confirm upon her; with C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urage she <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ets upon the
main Work, and being still more <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aithful to her self,
and to that light that asi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s her, at lasts she tasts the
Fruites of her Future Harve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, and does more then pre∣sage
that great Happiness that is accrewing to her, and
quits her from the troubles and anxieties of this pre∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nt
World stays with it in Tranquility and Content,
<PB N="53" REF="28"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at last leaves it with Joy. Therefore let us fur∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>er
consider, that the Soul has Four Qualities, be∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>use
her Faculties are Fourfold: The First, is Un∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erstanding:
The Second, is the Will: The Third,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Memory: The Fourth, is the Affections <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Heart, which is the principle Seat of the Rational
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. The Mind is the inward Act. The Thoughts
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Mind, the Fountain of Counsel, the soul of Life:
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> understand by the Mind, and live by the Soul.
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>A Deceision, or a Demonstration,
of the Mutual and Reciprocal
Relation betwixt the Soul and
the Body.</HEAD>
<P>1. THE true Love of God raises the Soul to the
highest Perfection; the purest and fullest
Love shall wear always the weightiest Crown of Glo∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y:
Where this Love is, if it meet with hard Precepts
it desolves it into sweet promises, and fills the Heart
with the shining Beauty of Soul, ravishing delights by
Divine Respiration, giving it true Repose, causing the
<PB N="54" REF="29"/>
Delights and Pleasures to be as Capacious as the Soul,
that lovely Creature of God, whom his Majesty is al∣ways
pleased to fill with an Ineffable Pleasure; in per∣petually
extending their Knowledge of Intellection,
by Consequences and Lights always New, which they
draw from their Light and their Knowledge, always
acquired, they always find something to be discovered
in the Immense Spaces of Truth, they always find some-Shing
to be enlightned with of the Perfection of the
aupream Essence, which they always see all entire, and
ill exposed to their Eyes, and, which they never
knew so perfectly; but that there always remains
something further to be known and discovered, they
always Drink of this Lively and Eternal Spring, and
are always a Thirst; they drein from thence every
moment, by a full and entire Knowledge of the in∣tuitive
Vision, but they always find it full and inexhau∣stable
to Reason and Intellection, which they always
make a further Progress into, and further still find
something to be known in the Fountain of its infinite
Incomprehensibility. The Reprobate Souls do also
find by the exercise of their reasonings, a Thousand;
and a Thousand New dispairs in their State of Re∣probation
and Misery: The Prophets say, they al∣ways
remain awake to the End; they may always
see their Misery and Woe, which does express the ex∣ercise
of the active Faculty in Unhappy Souls, which
proves that all Souls have out of the Body, the exer∣cise
of the Faculties, of Perceiving, of Imagining,
and of Recollecting, which they do not exercise here,
but dependent upon the Body: For thus we say, with∣out
difficulty, that they may compare one thing with
another, that they Conceive the Nature of Bodies
by pure Intellection, by which they form Universal
Notions; from whence they draw Consequences, and
frame Ideas; but these Ideas do not cause us to Be∣lieve,
that the Body and the Soul can be united like
two Liquors, or like two Metalls, which are melted
<PB N="55" REF="29"/>
one with the other, which are made either by an Un∣ctuous
or Viscous Humor, which binds the Parts of
them together, nor by Nails, Pegs and Joynts. We
may not imagine here any thing material, for we
are to cut off every thing that presents it self Corpo∣real
to our Spirits, for we are to conceive precisely
only a mutual and necessary Dependance, in such a
manner, as God has directed and disposed; which is
the way to conceive the manner how our Souls are
in our Bodies, as well as we are capable to compre∣hend:
They are not in us by a Local and Corporeal
Circumscription, they are not there as Liquor is in a
Vessel, or as a Bird is in the Nest or Cage, or as the
Body is in the Air, which environs it; but they are
in us as God is in the World, in which we must con∣ceive
him, as saith St. <HI>Augustin, Much more contain∣ing
than contained;</HI> for we may remember, that tho
the Nature of the Soul is a Spiritual Nature, which
doth as Essentially exclude Local extention, and by
Consequence all sorts of Ideas of Local Presence,
such as we commonly conceive under Corporeal
Images of Immediation, of Preportions, and of Co∣extention,
of Substances, as it doth Essentially include
the Grounds and the Acts of the knowing Faculty.
Bodies have their proper Fashion of being within
Places, and Spirits have theirs likewise; there is no∣thing
of likeness betwixt one and the other, for to
think otherways, were to subvert and destroy both
Corporeal and Spiritual Nature; for it is with the
manner how the Soul is in the Body, as it is with the
Soul it self: We cannot comprehend it as oft as we
conceive it by Imagination, what Corporeal Image
so ever we make of it, or under what material Form
soever we may conceive of it; for the manner how
the Soul is in the Body is altogether as Spiritual, as
is the Substance of the Soul; if it be demanded af∣ter
this, in what Part of the Body the Soul is, or
whether she is in all the Body; the Question will
<PB N="56" REF="30"/>
be difficult to resolve: However, the Learned say,
that all the Soul is in all the Body, and all of it in
the Essential and Integral Parts of it, as God is in
all the World, and in all the Parts of the World;
not by that Co-extension and Local Chimerical Pre∣sence,
which gross Spirits do imagine, but by the in∣timate
Presence of his Essence, Essentially operating
in all the World. We must say the same of the
Soul, that it is in all the Body, by relation of its
dependance and activity; but this does not hinder,
but that we may say she is more properly, and more
particularly in the Brain, since it is by that Part,
that the action of the Soul upon the Body imme∣diately
Commences; and that all the actions of the
Body upon the Soul termin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tes wholly in that Part,
as it sensibly appears, by that which interrupts and
suspends the action of the Soul upon the Body, and
the action of the Body upon the Soul; for as often
as it happens that the action of the Body upon the
Soul is interrupted, it is because there is some relaxa∣tion,
or some obstruction in some of the Nerves,
which hinders the motion from being continued in
the Part affected of the Body, as far as the Brain,
which is the Seat and Organ of the Senses, because
the impression have some palpable let or hindereance,
and cannot be carried, or arrive through the exterior
Senses of the Brain, which are called Internal. But
our Souls Naturally, like other-Created Spirits, ought
not to have any dependance upon our Bodies, for to
have the Ideas of things, they ought only to have
immediately dependance upon God, and by Conse∣quence
ought only to have Union with him; but this
Supreame Spirit having been pleased, for the reasons
we have said, and for many others which we con∣ceive,
and for more, yet apparently, perhaps, which
we do not conceive, that our Souls should have their
Thoughts and their Sentiments, their Desires and Af∣fections
upon the occasion of the Body, to the end,
<PB N="57" REF="30"/>
that they should be a continual Subject of Victory,
and Meritorious Exercise, by the assistance of Divine
Grace, which is of it self Victorious over the Im∣pure
delectation of Concupiscence; whereof it invin∣cibly
suspends the Charm, by the Heavenly and in∣ward
Taste, which it gives us of God, of our Duty,
and of Eternal Happiness; for Divine Grace causes
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to love Order and Duty, in spight of our selves,
making us sensible that we owe to God an infinite
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ve of Complacency, wholly disinteressed, and whol∣ly
pure; for which we ought to love his Eternal and
Sovereign Beauty, with all the strength and motions
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> our Hearts; for this alone will convey to us true
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>asure, for this will furnish us with Order, Truth
and Justice, which will undoubtedly prevent all Irre∣gularity.
Which Order is to be beloved by all Spi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>its,
and all upright Hearts in all the Parts of the
World; for this have some affinity to the Sovereign
Beauty of Nature, and of the Supreame Essence, who
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s the Lively and Eternal Source of Order, Equity
and Duty, the Eternal and Substantial Truth, which
do not discover it self but by Rays, by degrees escaping
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut from God, clearing the obscure Clouds of our
disorderly Desires, that we may Love and Adore our
Sovereign Creator, who gives us the weak glimmer∣ing
of his Ineffable Beauty, in that Virtue and Duty
which he causes us to Love; which is as it were, the
Charm of the Supreame Being. For all that we love
in the abstracted Idea of our Duties, or in the real
Charms of the Creatures, is nothing but the Splendor
and the Rays, or the Shadow of that Charm of Sove∣reign
Beauty and Perfection, which Gloriously shines
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n the Supreame Nature; from whose Beams it is,
that Nature Commences equally in us the love of
Complacency, and the love of Union; that we may
be filled with Contentment, with Pleasure and Love,
Truth, Justice and Equity, and all other Graces and
Virtues whom we love invincibly, under the Ideas,
<PB N="58" REF="31"/>
and under the Names of Truth, of Justice, of Beau∣ty,
of Virtue, of Duty, or of Equity, which shine
in all Places of the World, and makes it self seen
loved and adored invincibly by all Hearts, in all Ages
for these all preceed from the glimmering and glan∣ces
of Gods Original Beauty, which is so amicable
by it self, that as Corrupt as we are, we cannot hin∣der
our selves from loving it, because it flows from
the Sovereign Nature of God.</P>
<P>2. The Soul of Man have no Power of giving i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
self, neither the Idea, nor Knowledge, nor Sentiment
of any particular thing, but it is God, who hath al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Perfections dwelling in him, that Instructs and In∣lightens
the Souls of Men; for his Majesty alone
is the Life of every thing that Lives, and the Light
of every thing that is Enlightned; who gives us all
the Sentiments and all the Ideas which we receive, or
have from the occasion of our particular Bodies, and
from others which environ us. Tho to clear this point <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
be obscure and difficult; and, yet is very Important
and Necessary, in Order to make us comprehend our
dependance upon God, who is alone the All-know∣ing
Being by himself, as he is an existent Being by
himself: For it's God alone who hath Essentially of
himself, and by himself, his Eternal and Subsistent
Idea, by which he can distinctly see all things pos∣sible,
present and to come. The Created Spirits who
are not Thinking Beings of themselves, much less
Spirits knowing by themselves, or in themselves, the
things which are exterior to them; and, therefore
they have need to receive the Ideas of particular
things from God, that they may have a knowledge
of them: For if they had the Idea of one sole parti∣cular
thing out of themselves, there would not be
any Idea which they might not have; neither would
the Soul of Man have been Ignorant of any thing,
if she had had a Power by her self to Form and Idea
of the least thing, but by Consequence would have had
<PB N="59" REF="31"/>
the Idea of all things: But since, of her self <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
cannot form any one Idea; by Consequence she cann<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
form many: For to imagine she could, would be no
sensical and trivial. Our poor Soul goes grop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
through all the Bodies, who environs it, searching <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
a Pleasure and Contentment, which should satisfie i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
but no Pleasure nor Treasure can give the Soul tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
satisfaction, but God, who is the alone Soverei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Pleasure, which makes the Soul thus search after hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and him allone it is we ought to regard, with all o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Strength, Might and Motion, seeing his Majesty r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>¦gards
our Soul by all the Rays of his Infinite Essen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
For his Wisdom, it is who is our Satisfaction, our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
and Contentment, yea, our Sovereign Felicity. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Bodies then are, but as it were, our Souls burden,
at best but a House upon the Road of Eternity: Whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
fore we ought to seek for a lively Idea of our d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>dance
upon this Supreame Being, and upon all
Divine Attributes, that we may the better apprehe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
his Sovereign Perfection whose Nature is Supream
and yet is graciously pleased to operate continual
in us, and rules over us in all our ways, and in
divers operations. Our Souls do not make the dig∣s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion
in us, the Circulation of the Blood, the Natu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and pure<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y Animal Respiration in us; the Soul bei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
altogether Spiritual, have no Power to act this wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
but there is nothing which we certainly know, b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
the Soul is the active cause and principle of it,
which she have gain'd the Empire, either to do
not do, as she pleases; we may therefore reflect up
her Faculty, which she have of thinking, of willin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and determining her self, which are the two o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
active Faculties that we know in her, for the oth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
passive and receptive Faculties, of which she ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
essentially the Empire, as well as the certainty of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
double Faculty, and of all the Acts that precee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
there from; and we may see that she suspends <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
Thoughts, and her Reasonings puts them by determ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
<PB N="60" REF="32"/>
and applies them as she pleases to new Matters, which
always present themselves; and thus she is Mistress of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>er Will, without the motion that carries her to∣wards
God in general. If she be not preoccupy'd
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd transported with some Passions or other, but the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oul can by no means be the formal or physical Cause
of the heat which is in our Bodies, for it is impossi∣ble
to conceive that a Spirit should produce heat; yet
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y their Virtue and Operation they make the Body
move, by Empire and by Will, and yet this the Soul is
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aid to do out of it self; but whatsoever is done in us
Physically, is done by the act of our Body and its
Life, for there is in us a material principle of vegeta∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion,
or a vegetative Life, which the Soul doth not
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ause; so there is likewise a certain kind of acts of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eeing, of Hearing, of Tasting, of Smelling, of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouching, of Self-moving, or of Sensibility in the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ody, in which the Soul hath not any part, to which
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e doth not Influence any thing, and to which she
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ath not so much as a Sentiment.</P>
<P>3. To think and know is the Life of Spirits, who
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eceives Being from the first of Beings, or the prin∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ple
of Beings, the Great Almighty, from whom
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ery thing that is, receiveth without ceasing its
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eing, by a perpetual and never interrupted Communi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n
of the Supreame Essence, by reason that he is the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rinciple of Life, or the Essential and Original of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ife: It must needs be that every thing that Lives,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eceives continually a Life from him by a like In∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uence,
and by a like Communication of Life, and by
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onsequence every thing that thinks and knows,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hinks and knows by him, since to think and know
the Life of Spirits. This is the solid Metaphysick
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f St. <HI>Augustin,</HI> and the Theology of others, who
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith, agreeeble to the Scriptures, that an Angel and
Man differ without doubt; for an Angel is a Spirit
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hich God makes tryal off out of the Body, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hose Thoughts and Affections he hath not subjected
<PB N="61" REF="32"/>
to the dispositions of a Body; and a Man is a Spirit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
which God makes tryal off in the Body, to which he
subjects it before he Crowns it with Eternity: But the
Soul of Man if God had not disposed of it, after that
manner, would have had no need of a Body, where∣fore
the Union of Souls with Bodies is a hard and
difficult Empire, which God doth exercise over them,
and which if his Majesty would not sweeten the rigo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and difficulty of it, by the Pleasures of agreeable Sen∣timents,
which he hath annexed to the Acts and
Operations of Souls in Bodies. It could not be a tryal,
but a Misery; nay, the Fathers maintain, that if God
should not Spiritualize Bodies, that is to say, take
away from Souls the dependance which their present
State gives them upon Bodies, they could not have so
firm a hope of being raised again, as now they have,
because he would not put the Just Souls, whose ap∣proved
Fidelity deserves to be Crowned into Bodies
that should constrain them, and which enslaved their
Thoughts; which is what Spiritualized Bodies can∣not
bear, because Spiritualization of Bodies will con∣sist
in this precisely, that they should no longer exer∣cise
an Empire over the Souls, and that they should
be no longer a Charge, an Obstacle and an Incum∣brance
to them; for the Body cannot in any manner
act upon the Soul, so as to Illuminate it, or Affect
it Physically, or Immediately by it self; for the Body
cannot subject the Soul to be United to it, nor can
the Soul be willing to submit to the Body, which
humbleth and constraineth it. It is therefore God
the Author of universal Nature, that is the Immedi∣ate
and Efficient Principle, and Cause of the Union of
Souls and Bodies; for his Wisdom acteth as universal
Cause in the whole frame of Nature; 'tis evident then
that none but God alone can give the Soul the Sen∣timents
and Ideas which she hath, from the occasi∣on
of the Impressions which are made upon the
Body, for 'tis the Author of Nature which enlightens
<PB N="62" REF="33"/>
us, by the Ideas which we receive upon the occasion
of the Impression, of exterior Objects; and who af∣fectionates
to the Conversation of the Body, by the
agreeable or disagreeable Sentiments which he gives
us, to make us know by way of instinct, that which
is profitable or hurtful, for the Conver<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ation of our
Bodies and of Humane Species. This action he joyns
to that, by which he moves our Bodies, when our
Thoughts and Wills require it, and is properly the
action, by the which he Unites our Bodies to our Souls,
and our Souls to our Bodies. This is the active or
actual Union, which the Schools call the Unitive
action of God, which is joyned to the Immutable De∣cree
and Will▪ by the which he hath determined to
continue it, so long as the structure of the Body
shall subsist, and makes in the Soul and▪ in the Body
that Estate of Union, which is called Passive and
Formal Union; and this the Almighty doth by the
Essential act of his Supreame Nature, for his Essence
and Nature is infinitly pleased to act thus continually,
esteeming it his Pleasure and his Glory, by which,
also he is the occasional Cause of all the Eneffable
Ple<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sure of Holy Souls, and so much the rather, be∣cause
the Analogy of the Divine conduct Inspires us
to acknowledges an occasional Cause of all our Joy and
F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>icity. As there is an occasional Cause of the Tor∣ments
of the Reprobates, for each of these he is pleased
to make tryal off in the Body, by their Obedience or
Disobedience, annext to each of which, is Felicity or
Misery, for these shall go into Life Eternal, but the
Wicked into endless burnings.</P>
<P>4 Our Body is a Structure full of Harmony, where∣by
all the Parts are United to one common Center,
which is the Brain wrapt up in Membranes, and di∣stributed
and divided into divers Compartments, pro∣per
to receive and retain the Traces and Impressions
which the Divine Image shall in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>amp upon it: We
say, also that the Soul is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n the Body, but we take
<PB N="63" REF="33"/>
care not to conceive it. For all that as truly and pro∣perly
contain'd in the Body, it is United to the Body;
but we may not conceive her as poured into, and
mingled with the Body; or, as adjusted to its extent
by a co-extention and immediation of Greatness, of
Figure, or of Substance; but they have the greatest
part of their Thoughts, and of their Ideas, and of all
their Sentiments of Pleasure, and of Pain, by the oc∣casion
of their Body, because they act upon the Body
by the action of the Will, which removes them and
moves them, in the manner as have been already said.
The Learned say, that they are no otherways in the
Body, therefore every thing we conceive beyond this,
will be false, contradictory and extreamly dubious.
That which we call good Sense and Judgment, is
nothing but the Power and Faculty which the Soul
hath, to Order and Regulate our Thoughts, to sus∣pend
and stay them, that she may consider and main∣tain
their Connexion and Dependence: But she is said,
sometimes to loose this Faculty and Power, when
the Motion of the Blood, Humours, and of the Ani∣mal
Spirits, or of the Fibres of the Brain, which is
the Organ of the Internal Sense, which are annexed
the Species of things, that is to say, the Impressions
which remains of the Objects, are disordered and em∣broiled
in such sort, that the Natural Order and Con∣nexion
of these Species cannot be observed and kept,
but are confusedly and tumultuously excited and stir∣ed
up, by a tumultuous and irregular agitation of the
Organ, in which they reside; from whence comes
necessarily, that kind of Folly which consists in a
disorder and a fantastick Confusion of Thoughts,
without Order and Dependance, or Connexion, be∣cause
the Fibres of those Parts of our Bodies ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
scorched up, on which the Soul usually acts; and to
say this may not shake a Truth so well Establishe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and Proved, that it needs no further Illustration
therefore let it be our Care and Study to seek th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="64" REF="34"/>
Kingdom above, rather than to puzle our selves in the
nicities of Nature, or the manner how our Soul acts
in our Body; for better it is that the Soul and Body be
free from pollution, than to understand all the know∣ledge
our Nature is capable of being enlightned with;
for 'tis not he that understands al Myst<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies or all Se∣crets,
but he that is Obedient and Dutiful to the Di∣vine
Laws, that shall be filled with Joy in the Heaven∣ly
<HI>Ierusalem,</HI> that Place of spotless Purity, where no
Impure thing can dwell: Wherefore our Lord chose
rather to Suffer any Indignity, than that we should
continue in the Guilt of Sin; because any pollution
unquallifies us for his Kingdom, and Robs us of the
Happiness of being meet to be Citizens thereof. For
since Fruition is the end of Knowledge, it is of great
moment to us so to demean our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as not to be
unfit for the Union of Glory; and amongst other
aspiring Knowledge, the due Knowledge of a M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>s self
is highly conducive to attain to this Happiness, for
such a Knowledge shews him the Humility of the
Frame he ought to be in, to qualify him, to be wor∣thy
to enter into this Glorious City, where every Holy
Soul will be beloved of Ang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ls, and admired of Men:
Such qualified Persons be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>g the true Friends of God,
seeing they have defined to W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ship God in the in∣ward
Court of their Souls, as well as in the out Court
of his Sanctuary, and in the admiration of him in all
his Works of Wonder; for there is nothing of more
concern to us, than to be truly sensible of his ex∣ceeding
Mercy, which ought to be deeply It graven
in all ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Minds, so as to raise our Sons to a high
pitch of Gratitude, for all the benefits we have mo∣mently
received from him, the rememberance of
each of which are reviving Comforts, and are able to
cheer the Hearts of the most dejected Penitents; for
the true Sense of this assures them that they shall be
for ever Blessed, even to such a Perfection, as to be
Perfect Sovereigns in his Glorious Kingdom, where
<PB N="65" REF="34"/>
every one will be a Sovereign Prince, being Blessed
with infinite Injoyments, such as the beholding the
unvailed Vision of God, and the sweet Society of
Saints and Angels, where God Essence and Works
will satisfie all Holy desires, all Blessed wishes and
eager Thirst after Purity, and every Heavenly In∣joyment.</P>
<P>5. <Q>The Will which is that Invincible and Insur∣mountable
movement, which pusheth on all knowing
Natures towards God, is without doubt, and Operates
perpetually in Just Souls, and in Reprobated Souls;
but it is there, and Operates there very diversly. The
Just Souls have found the good they sought, they
are arrived to the term they have so long persued;
they imbrace it; they possess it; they lose them∣selves;
they plunge themselves; drown and ingulph
themselves in it.</Q> When they are arrived to the
Place of their repose, to the Center of their Desires,
to the port of their Wishes, they have nothing more
to follow, to search after in this Fortunate State they
p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssess, because they taste with an inexplicable Tran∣quility,
and an incomprehensible Satiety the Sove∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eign
good, and therefore are fully satisfied, content
and quiet: But this Tranquility and this Satiety does
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t lull them to Sleep, nor ever cloy them the Will
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atisfied, and arrived to its term does not cease pro∣ceeding
on always. It Operates and Sturs up it self
Eternally; in a most happy repose these Holy Souls
are always satisfied, and always a Hungary, always at
quiet, and always sturred up they Will and Desire
always, that which they have and would always
have more; for they are immediately United to the
Sovereign good, and to all his Joys, and are always
till vehemently desirous of being more United to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>im. Thus the Will hath its Excellency and Per∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ection
in Holy Souls, without any of the Imper∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ections,
it is at present subject to; for now it's not
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble to ballance it self betwixt True and False good,
<PB N="66" REF="35"/>
for at present it's sotting and wavering betwixt the
False Images of good, which the Immagination and
the Senses presents to it in the present State, and be∣twixt
the true and solid goods which Instinct and
Reason, Philosophy and Religion preposses to it: It
is happily drawn in by the Presence and Injoyments
of the Sovereign good, whose Immensity draws them
and carries them by force, and fastens them to his
Sovereign Beauty and to his Soverig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Delights; for
it's his Wisdom in whom they see the Source of good
and as it were, all the true Treasure and Foundation
of Life giving Excellencies, and, therefore cannot be
turned aside by any False good; but there is a vast
difference betwixt these happy Souls, and the Souls o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
the Reprobate, as to their final State; for as to the
latter of these, the Fountain of good repulses
them, and throws them back from the Vision o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Glory, and in the same time, wounds and transperce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
them with a Thousand deadly Darts; they are Et<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rnal∣ly
thirsting after Pleasure, but have Eternally nothing
but Grief, Pain and Dispair, for their Portion: So
that the Will placed in them, to be the beginning
and seat of their happiness, is found to be the Eternal
principle and seat of their unhappiness and dispair;
for as all the agreeable Passions will be in Holy Souls
so all the Afflicting ones will be in Reprobate Souls. The
Dispair of the Soul lies in the seeing and perceiving
the Impossibilities of a voiding Evil, and the not be∣ing
able to attain the good she persues, which must
needs be a dejection and a discouragement, accom∣panied
with profound sadness, because of this crue
Sentiment of Privation, and yet by some is called
truly and properly Voluntary, because the Will is tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Motion, by which the Soul is driven on invincibly to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wards
God, to Unite her self, and to be United to
him, which is the Love of God in general, and ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
be called properly Voluntary; for when the go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
which is aspired after cannot be acquired, Dispair b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="67" REF="35"/>
consequence succeeds; for the resentment of the Ap∣petite
preceeds from the dismal Thoughts, that 'tis
impossible to acquire the good so much wished for;
for we should not be afflicted, penetrated and over∣whelm'd
with the Privation of good if we did not
Love it, which made St. <HI>Augustin</HI> say, <HI>That the
Eternal Dispair of the Reprobates in Hell, is a true
Love of the Sovereign good;</HI> but this being a nicity that
concerns us not, we may not with saifty dive into it,
or amuse our selves about it; but strive to be Cloath∣ed
with the true Love of God, whereby we are sure
we may be qualified to enjoy the full Bliss of Heaven;
the true hopes of which fills every Holy Soul with
exceeding Joy, even such reviving Joy as may give
him some small glimmerings, even in this Life; of
what hereafter will undoubtedly be his Portion in those
Glorious Regions above, where every true Penitent
will be a Favorite of that great tremendious King,
who is the searcher of every Heart and observer of
every Action here, and the Infinite rewarder of every
Virtue hereafter. To him therefore be Glory and
Praise, Might, Majesty and Dominion ascribed by us,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd all the whole Creation, now and for ever.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="summary">
<HEAD>A Recapitulation of the moral con∣sequences,
drawn from what have been
established concerning our Souls, and for
the Conviction of our Duties, and the
Condemnation of Disorder.</HEAD>
<P>NO Man of Reason can believe that Ingratitude is
an Ornament to Nature; or, that Injustice Me∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s
a reward, nor that Treachery is a Virtue, or an
<PB N="68" REF="36"/>
Honest and Commendable Quality; nor on the con∣trary
that Justice, Fidelity and Gratitude are things
Condemnable and Wicked. Men make Laws according
to their Fancy, they make themselves Obey'd, for
fear of Punishment, when they have the Power in
their Hands. But it's remarkable, that Men who
make Laws cannot make themselves Obey'd, nor be
Beloved or Beleived, when they act things disagree∣able:
For Unjust and Tyrannical Laws, People pay
only an exterior Obedience to their Commands; but
the Heart and the Spirit cries out and demand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Justice, from him whom all Men naturally feel over
their Heads, as a Protector of Justice, and an avenge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of Oppression and Unjust Authority. We sometime
receive Unjust Laws, but we do not believe them to
be Just for all that; but, as to the natural Laws o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Duty and Consciences all Men receive them, and be
lieve by an invincible Determination of a Superio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Light, which equally perswades them alike; for Na∣tural
Light convinces us with invincible force; and
this is an Infallible Character of Natural Light. Con¦science
is then in us undoubtedly Natural, and as cer∣tain
as it is an Essential Companion of our Nature
and a Propriety inseparable from our Soul: From
hence arises in us, by the help of Grace, all Mora<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and Christian Virtues; because it is impossible to con¦ceive
that Corporeal Nature can be the subject o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Magnanimity, of Justice, of Fidelity, of Continenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and of Truth; for a Corporeal Nature alone canno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
have the Light of Order, or of Duty, or the Inclina¦tion,
or Determination of Duty, or the Pleasure o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Performance, or the Pain of the Violation of Duty
for Duty, Order and Justice have no Bodies, they ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
things totally Spiritual and Intelligible; and, there
fore without the assistance of the Soul cannot hav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
the Idea or the Sentiment of them, because it is by
the Soul that they are Ingrafted, and poured into ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Corporeal Nature. God having assembled togethe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="69" REF="36"/>
both these in one single whole, not as one; but act∣ing
by this Indubitable Method God have prescribed,
by reason of their dependance one upon another, or
to say better, the Union betwixt each other, and are
all animated with one and the same Influence of Di∣vine
Life, and marked with one and the same re∣semblance,
and equally Impelled by the same Love of
Duty: For which reason we are obliged to Love and
to Accomplish all the extents of Justice, of Truth,
of Charity, and of Civility, and of Mutual or Reci∣procal
respect towards all Men, upon the considera∣tion
that this Life is short and troublesome, and all
things in it are frail and perishable, and the noblest
Pleasures in it are essentially false, as well as empty;
they leave the Heart, even during this Life, Sick and
Famished, and if not retired from before Death, they
will leave the Soul Eternally, deceived by a cruel Pri∣vation,
and an insupportable desolation of regret. For
the best injoyments of this Life are a perpetual al∣ternativeness
of real Cares and Torments, all things
here being but false shadows of Repose and lucid In∣tervals
of Reason, a Theater of Eternal Mutations, a
Chain interlinked with short and transitory Felicities,
and long and durable Miseries, a vehement and impe∣tuous
Whirl-wind of Hurry and Ambition, which af∣ter
having much tormented and agitated the Body
and Soul, having raised a Thousand snares in the
Heart and Spirit, it disappears into Air and Smoak;
for so it is that this Life doth not exercise it self, but
upon the false and perishable Objects of Time, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s deceitful and deceiving Oeconomy; whereas the
n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ture Life exercises it self upon Objects wholly
True, and wholly Solid; because the future Life is
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut, as it were, one Day, all Uniformity; for there
very Holy Soul will Eternally be United to ever∣sting
Triumphs and Felicities, for there every Soul
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill be Essentially Living, infinite Happy and Joyous;
no here it have been exercised in Trouble, in the future
<PB N="70" REF="37"/>
Life it shall rest in Glory and endless Felicities, as the
Apostle saith, <HI>Such as Eye hath not seen, nor Ear heard,
nor Heart conceived,</HI> 2 Cor. 12. 4. Much less can the
feeble Eloquence of Man express, by any description
that his Idea or Sentiment can conceive to put into
Method to declare, or so much as describe.</P>
<P>Our Soul is said to commence when it goes out of
the Body. That which we call time is taken either
by relation to the duration of the abode of every
Soul in its Body, or by relation to the duration of
the whole present Oeconomy of the visible World,
destined to the Tryal of the Souls in the Bodys;
and in whatsoever signification we take Time, in op∣position
to Eternity, it signifies precisely a State of
Instability, of Change and Vicissitude, <HI>i. e.</HI> a State
which ought to have an end; for these are two
things which enter Essentially into the Idea, which
is called Time Vicissitude, and End; the space of the
duration that our Souls are in our Bodies, is called
Time, for these two Reasons. First, because it is to
have an end. And Secondly, because in the interim,
so long as it endures, it holds us exposed to a Thou∣sand
Chainges and Vicissitudes; and, which is to be
lamented, that Vicissitude of being obnoxious to pass
from Good to Evil, from Virtue to Sin, to Crimes
or Vice; but on the contrary, Eternity is Immutable
and an Interminable State and Order of things: As
much as Time includes Instability and End, so much
does Eternity excludes both; Time speaks Change<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and End, Eternity speaks the Being always the same
and never ending. Thus as our present State in the
Body is Time, so our future State out of the Bod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
is Eternity, the due consideration of which ought to
Penetrate us, and cause a General and Universa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Change in our Ideas, that now in time we may s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
prepare for Eternity, that we may be Eternally hap∣py
when Time shall be no more. Now of these tw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
States, the one appears infinitly Precious and Essen∣tial,
<PB N="71" REF="37"/>
and the other infinitly despisable: We ought
therefore earnestly to endeavour, to render our selves
worthy of being rewarded by him, to whom the se∣crets
of all Hearts are at present unclosed; and now
immediately relate our selves to him, by our Confes∣sion
of our dependance upon his Supereminent ex∣cellency
over us, and over all the World, that we may
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>el indubitably the Pleasures and Delights which he
contains; for his Goodness is ready to discover the
Charms and Beauty of his Sovereign Nature, to all
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ho desire to be united to him, by shewing Love and
Charity to all their Christian Brethren; that when God
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall make up his Jewels, they may be found worthy of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eward at the end of the present Oeconomy, when his
M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>jesty shall put an end to the Vicissitudes of Time, when
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e shall fix all things in an immutable and an eternal Or∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er,
when he will give a beginning to the New World,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd when he will re-establish all the Bodies, and re∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nite
every Soul to that Body which she animated,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pring this present life; this will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e do who calls
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>mself the Resurrection and the Life, the first born
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mongst the dead, the Father of Ages to come, he
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> whom we are all raised up again, in a Mistery and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> a Figure, and will undoubtedly raise us effectually <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
the last Day: For then we shall be even in our
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>odies like Angels, disfranchised from the businesses,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d the inclinations which we have upon the occa∣ons
of the Body. St. <HI>Paul</HI> also teaches us, that our
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>odies shall be Spiritualized, and we may upon this
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>inciple decide with certainty, that the re-union of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>odies doth not at all change the Foundation of that
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ate of the Soul out of the Body; the manner and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> cumstances, whereof we have been illustrating:
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r when our Bodies shall be Spiritualized by the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>surrection, they shall be no more a charge to the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; tho the Learned say, That the Nature of our
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dies shall not be chainged, so as to become know∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Natures, or cease to be extended Substances;
<PB N="72" REF="38"/>
but that the Body shall be no more an obstacle, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
hinderance in any thing to the Soul; but our Bodies
will serve to do Honour and Glory to the God of Nature
Our Bodies after they are raised, will have a perfect
and sovereign agility, that is to say, an intire indiffe∣rence
for all sorts of motion, which will cause them
without any resistance to be carried every where
whether the Souls would have them; for then they
will have neither Levity nor Gravity, but will be a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
light as the Air, and as swift as a Thought; th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Bodies of themselves have not either lightness <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
weight, so as to ascend or descend; but being afters
they are raised from the Grave Spiritualized, the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
will by the Almighty Power be able to do this, whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
our Bodies shall be replaced with our Souls; and ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
whole Man will be replaced in a much purer stru∣cture
than ever it was at first, before it was defile
by Sin. From whence we may see the excellen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
train of the Divine System of Religion, which
without doubt clear and certain, that the Univers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Resurrection will be a Circumstance of that Glorious
Solemnity of Justice, which God will make at th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
consummation of Ages, for the consecration of h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Eternal Temple, for the overture and commenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>¦ment
of his Immortal Reign, for the solemn Corona∣tion
of his Royal Majesty, and for the compleat Tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>umph
of Man-God, for the justification of his Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣vidence,
and the full Declaration, and Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>festatio
of his Glorious Will, at the end of this prese<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Oeconomy of Time. The Scripture speaks of Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>Souls,
as if they had the Pleasure of walking on th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Globes of the Heavens, and to be in the midst of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Stars, to walk upon the Sun and the Moon after t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
manner of Spirits; it accommodates it self to o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
ross manner of speaking, and of conceiving t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
most Spiritual things under Corporeal forms, whic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
may be called a clear distinct Idea of the visib<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
World, which God gives to Just Souls; they wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="73" REF="38"/>
after their manner upon the Arches of Heaven; they
are capable of being at the same time at both the
Poles of the World; they are said to fill its whole
extent; they are in both the Hemispheres. Their Ho∣rizon
is not at all a limited Horizon, which never per∣mits
us to see here but a little portion of the Universe;
it is not bounded. But by the bounds of Nature, We
do not at present see these Heavenly Bodies, but only
these parts of them, which reflects the light upon us:
We do not see the Sun, the Moon, the Stars, and the
Terraqueous Globe of the Earth and the Seas, but only
one side of them. But the pure Souls immediately
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nlightned by God, as they are, they see at the same
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ime the whole Globe of the Sun, all the Face of the
Moon, both the Hemispheres of the Earth; there is
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Antipodes to them, they all see at one view all the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>air prospects of Nature, and all the beautiful Table of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he visible World; for besides that, their Knowledg,
universal in this respect; so it is not at all successive,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut all full and clear at once, so that they see all things,
least by reflection, by which we compare one
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hing with the other, to observe diversities and sin∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>arities,
by which we pass on, from that we know
that we do not as yet know, which may be called
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e proper species of reasoning, which brings into the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orld all the Arts and Sciences as proper means to
tend Knowledge, as is an effort and agitation of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hought; but this is to be understood of the pre∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
Life; But what we spake before, we spake of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> future Life, <HI>i. e.</HI> of pure Souls made Glorious by
Majesty on high, who presides over all our Know∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ge,
and over all our Sentiments, and causes them
us, in spite of us; and all this by the assistance of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> admirable and illuminating Wisdom, which are
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ess<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntial Character and Attributes of that which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
call Divinity, or Supreame Nature, so that a re∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e
and an attentive Man cannot be ignorant of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> excellent Truths, by the assistance of the pro∣vident
<PB N="74" REF="39"/>
Wisdom of our great Creator; for he it is
that teaches us, that the Luminous Body of the Sun
with the Firmament shews perpetually his Glory;
every thing sympathysing with each other in the
mistaken Miseries, which Men call good, till their Spi∣ritual
Eyes are open, and they see they are deluded
by great mistake, when the sensation, by which one
Man doth see and understand an other, is made with
a confus'd sentiment of Pleasure, and with a certain
agreement which carries a desire of being united to
him, and which makes one Man pleased with another,
that is called sympathy. And, when on the contra∣ry,
this sensation is made with confused sentiments o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
disagreement and straingeness, that is called antipa∣thy.
And this is the general Idea of sensation, which
are the Knowledges that we have by the determina∣tion
of present Objects, by which we are able to
chuse to do Acts free and voluntary, tho there is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
distinction to be made betwixt free Acts and volu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tary
Acts; for every thing that is free is voluntary
but every thing that is voluntary is not free; but no
thing is voluntary in us but what is made by the de¦termination
of the Will; for this is a necessary and i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>vincible
motion of our Souls towards God, causing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
invincibly to love Good in general, with a full dete<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣mination
of our Mind and Will, by the which also w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
shun Evil, and every thing that hurts and afflicts <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
and we persue some times one particular Good tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
an other, as they more or less immediately concer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
us; for Liberty is always accompanied with the Wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Now Liberty is precisely that Empire which we ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of being able to determine our selves, which to chu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
and which to refuse, when the Objects are present<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
to the perceptive faculty of the Soul. We m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
easily shut our Eyes, and not let that reflective Lig <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
to enter in, from the superficies of the Object, whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Ingraves it in our Retina: But, yet we cannot hind <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
the Impression of Light, if once it be entred into <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="75" REF="39"/>
Eyes, nor that ordor of savor, if they have affected
those Nerves which are proper to carry the Impressi∣on
of them to the Brain. But our Soul cannot see
the Objects in those passages of the Brain, nor the
species, as in Pictures as we have endeavoured to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llustrate in our former presuppositions: This is a
thing which we know by an indubitable sentiment.
We may then presuppose that it is not all these Ta∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les,
whereon the Soul sees the Object; she being for∣mally
knowing, having in her self a lively representa∣tion,
or an inward sentiment of the Objects which
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ders themselves present by the material Impression,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hich is received in the Body by the assistance of the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctive faculty of Thinking, which is sometimes cal∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d
the faculty of Reasoning; for by these the Ob∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cts
which strike the Senses are lively represented to∣be
passive, or the active faculty of the Thinking Soul,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hich come from the diversity of the temperament,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd from the material Structure and Harmony of the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ody, by which the Understanding, the Judgement,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d the Memory, with all the other Natural Quali∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
receives advantage, to act every one its part
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen occasion shall present in its proper season; for
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Soul is inclined to all great and transcendant
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ings: The Mind is sometimes said to be the Soul,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>erting its Power into Heroick Actions, wherefore
great Soul is Magnanimous in effect, <HI>i. e.</HI> when our
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd is applied to mighty Objects; and such a one
said to be the Son of Eternal Power, and the Friend
infinite Goodness, a Man whose inward State is
raculous, and his Complexion Divine, because he
lights in the Celestial way of true Bliss, he turns his
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mporeal Riches into Obligations, by wining Souls
God, and thus gaining the Affections of the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se. For to be rich in the Hearts and Affections
Good People can be no deformity, and every such
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n is, as it were, his own end, while he considers it
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; for nothing is more conducive to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="76" REF="40"/>
Honour of the Holy Man, than to be bountiful and
munificient; for this proves true Riches to his own
Soul, and puts a double lustre upon that noble
Jewel, for this beautifies it, and makes it truly aimable
and Praise worthy; all these being shut up in Good∣ness.
For these Men make themselves truly great
by Enriching others, for the Eccho of their Works
are sweet, and pleasing in the Ears of all that are
surrounded with them; and may be said to be like
the Sun in the Rays of his Glory, and Reigns like a
King by the sole Power of Virtue, and thus beau∣tifies
their Religion; for these delight in the felicity
of all that accost them, and thus puts Embroiderie
on Religion by the chearfulness of their Spirits, and
the Heroick Actions of their Souls, and thus carries
a Light wher<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ever they go, and attracts the esteem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of every Good Person; so that these Men move in
a Sphere of Wonders; their Lives are a continua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
strem of Miracles, for they are always sacrificing
their Persons and Possessions to the benefit of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
World. Benifits and Blessings are their Life-guard, fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
that they live Holy and Temperate, and strive to i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>mediate
the Wisdom of Angels, whose guardian Sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
is never wanting to their assistance; so that their i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ward
House is a Habitation of Joy and Felicity, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
so brightens their outward behaviour, that almost a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
their Actions yields a spectacle of Contentment <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
every beholder: There is a generous confidence d∣coursed
in all their Actions, and some glimps of He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ven
in all their Behaviour: Therefore a Life beautifie
with Virtues is the greatest Gift that can be give
to Man. For the return of it in Holy Actions is a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ceptable
to God: For when all things shall be r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vealed,
the Life of these secret Persons shall perfect
appear in all their perfections. May we therefore
careful to adorn our Persons and Palaces with th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
kind of Riches, seeing they are so Delectable a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Pleasant: For these Men have a Love within the
<PB N="77" REF="40"/>
Souls, that is willing to impart all these incompre∣hensible
Treasures and Glories to every Soul, for such
a Mind and such Affections must Perfume and E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rich
our Sacrifices: For the Greatness and Goodness of
our Souls consists in such inlargements; for a Will
inlarged with an infinite Fancy is a prodigious depth
of Goodness; for infinite Desires and Intentions of
pleasing God are real Objects to his Eye, for such a
Soul being all Love, would do Millons of things for
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts Object: For infinite Love puts an infinite value on
the Gift, wherefore it must needs be Magnificence to
give a Gift of infinite value; and infinite valuable
every Good and Pious Action, in the Eyes of him,
who have told us, that no Thought or Action shall
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>emain uncovered, but every Thought, Word and
Action shall be seen clearly by all for ever: And all
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall be admired for their inward Piety and Holiness,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd every discovery of Virtue in one shall be an oc∣casion
of Joy in each other; so that every secret Vir∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e
that have been long concealed, but only to those
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ho have enjoyed the benefit of it, shall be a new
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ause of Eternal Joy to all, when in Heaven it shall
clearly discovered. For our Actions in passing, pass
ot away, but in the Sphere of our Life abideth for
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; so that a Good Man's Life all at once is a My∣erious
Object, interwoven with many Thoughts,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ccurrences and Transactions; and ought to be pre∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ted
to God like a Ring, a Garland, or a Jewel to a
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>agnificent Benefactor: Therefore we had need to be
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry choice in the mixture of our Flowers, and cu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ous
in the enammel of so rare a Present, that it may
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ove to us a Royal Diadem, to adorn our Souls for
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>: Therefore to let any dirt or blemish be in it,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ould be inconsistent to our Felicity: Therefore
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight and clear apprehensions, Divine, and Ardent
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffections are highly necessary to this Compleatment,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eing upon the sincerity of the affections and inten∣ons
depends the Honour of the Work, it concerns
<PB N="78" REF="41"/>
every one therefore to cleans his Heart from all Im∣purity
and Insincerity, that his whole Man may be
an acceptable Present to God, that his infinite Im∣mensity
may graciously accept him, and all his Works;
for his Wisdom never rejected the sincere, but endews
them with inward and outward Ornaments, such
as an infinite clesi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and delight in Goodness, enabling
them always to Love his Eternal Majesty, with an in∣finite
Love, and Deiight, greatly Thirsting to be fully
satisfied with him, and him only; for the Soul is to
Noble a thing to be satisfied with any thing less than
his Transcendent Majesty, whose Goodness extends to
all, even to the Unthankful: But he is most the
Friend of those who delight most in him, for infinite
Love and eternal Blessedness are near ally'd; for all
Delight springs from the satisfaction of violent de∣sires,
for which cause, when the desire is forgotten
the Delights are abated. <Q>The coming of a Crown<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and the Joy of a Kingdom, is far more quick and
powerful in the surprize and novelty of the Glory,
than the length of its continuance.</Q> The greate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
part of our Eternal Happiness consist in a greatfu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
recognition, not only of our Joys to come, but o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Benefits already received. True contentment is th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
full satisfaction of a knowing Mind, <HI>i. e.</HI> a long habi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of solid Repose, after much Study and serious Consi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>deration,
or a free and easie Mind attended with Plea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sure,
that naturally ariseth from ones present Cond<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tion;
yet to be content without a true Cause, is t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
fit down in our Imperfections, and to seek all on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Bliss in ones self alone, and, as it were, to scorn a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
other Objects, which is in it self a high piece of Pride
that renders a Man good for nothing, but makes him
Arrogant and Presumptious in the midst of his Blind<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ness;
whereby he leads a living Death by shuting u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
his Soul in a Grave, in that it tramples under Fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
the Essence of his Soul, which in Truth turns his F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>licity
to Malevolence and Misery, or in other Word
<PB N="79" REF="41"/>
Disorder and Confusion: Therefore Man is an unwel∣come
Creature to himself, till he can delight in his pre∣sent
Condition, provided his Condition be such as is plea∣sing
in the sight of God; for this must be the Con∣dition
that can make our pleasure exquisite: For
otherways we shall be tormented with the contriety
of our desires. The happiness of a contented Spirit
consists not only in the fruition of its Bliss, but in the
Fruits and Effects it produceth in our Lives, which
makes every Virtuous Man truly Great within, and
Glorious in his retirements, Magnanimity and Con∣tent
are very near aly'd, they spring from the same
Parents, but are of several Features. Fortitude and
Patience are Kindred too, to this incomparable Vir∣tue,
for these fill a Man with true Pleasure and great
Treasure, which makes him Magnanimous and truly
Great, not in his own Thoughts but in the sight of
God: The Magnanimous Soul is always awake, the
whole Globe of Earth is but a Nut-shel in comparison
of his Injoyments; for God alone is his Sovereign
delight and Supreame complacency: So that nothing
is great if compared to a Magnanimous Soul, but the
Sovereign Lord of all Worlds. But Man divided from
God is a weak and inconsiderable Creature: But every
Soul united to God is a Transcendent and Celestial
thing, for God is its Life, its Greatness, and its Pow∣er,
its Blessedness and Perfection; for he that is joyn∣ed
to the Lord is one Spirit, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 6. 20. His Omni∣presence
and Eternity fills the Holy Soul, and makes
it able to contain all heights, and depths, and lenghts,
and breadths whatsoever. In a Word, it's the desire
of every such Soul to be filled with the fulness of
God. Magnanimous desires are the Natural results of
a Magnanimous Capacity, the desire of being like
God, of knowing Good and Evil. But in a grosser
sence, this was the destruction of the Old World:
Not that it is Unlawful to desire to be like God, but
to aspire to the Perfection in a forbidden way, by
<PB N="80" REF="42"/>
Disobedience and following our own Inventions, by
seeking to the Creatures in opposition to the great
Creator. A Magnanimous Soul if we respect its Capa∣city,
is an immovable Sphere of Power and Know∣ledge,
far greater than all Worlds, by its Virtue and
Power that it passeth through all things, the Centre
of the Earth, and through all existencies; and all∣such
Creatures as these he counteth but Vanity and
Trifles in comparison of his true Object, the great
Almighty, whose Transcendent Goodness desendeth
in full Showers upon all Men, by his communitive
Goodness which is freely extended to every Man.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="quotations">
<HEAD>The Seven last WORDS our
Saviour spoke upon the Cross.</HEAD>
<P>I. FATHER forgive them, for they know not
what they do.</P>
<P>O Lord, forgive me, wherein I have forgot thy
Presepts, and done that which is Evil.</P>
<P><HI>To the good Thief,</HI>
II. This Day shalt thou be with me in Paridise.</P>
<P>O God, say to my Soul, in the Day when thou
takest it from my Body, This Day shall thou be
with me in Heaven.</P>
<P>III. Woman behold thy Son.</P>
<P>In Futurity let me behold the Vision of Bliss.</P>
<P>IV. Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani? <HI>that is to say,</HI>
My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me.</P>
<P>Forsake me not in my greatest Afflictions.</P>
<P><PB N="81" REF="42"/>
V. I thirst.</P>
<P>Grant that I may thirst for thee the Fountain of Li∣ving
Waters.</P>
<P>VI. Father into thy Hands I commend my Spirit.
Receive my Soul when it is returning unto
thee.</P>
<P>VII. It is finished.</P>
<P>Finish my Course with Joy, and grant O Jesus,
that I may be worthily qualified to receive that sweet
Voice of thine, <HI>Welcome to the Kingdom prepared by
my Father.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="meditation">
<HEAD>Meditation for the Sick.</HEAD>
<P>THEY that Glory in their Ancestors, in the
Nobleness of their Birth and Blood, must make
their Beds in the dark, and acknowledge Corruption
for their Father, and the Worm for their Mother
and Sister, they that are already Dead, and crumble
away, to make room from us that must come after them,
are secluded from Men, but live with Angels: <HI>Dust
thou art, and to dust thou shalt return,</HI> Gen. 3. 19.
<HI>What Man is he that liveth, and shall not see Death,</HI>
Psal. 89. 48. <HI>Our Bodies shall return to the Earth
from whence they were taken, but our Spirit shall return
to God that gave it,</HI> Eccl. 12. 7. <HI>It is appointed for
all Men once to die,</HI> Heb. 9. 26. <HI>We must needs
dye, and are as Water spilt upon the Ground that can∣not
be gathered up again,</HI> 2 Sam. 14 41. Then let
not the place of thy Death trouble thee, for the
Earth is the Lords, and the fulness thereof; Death
lost her Sting in the Side of our Saviour: The Day
<PB N="82" REF="43"/>
of Death is the Day of Jubilee, and frees us from all
these Evils; <HI>God kisseth the Righteous in their Deaths,
and, as it were, sucks in those Souls, which he breathed
into them,</HI> Deut. 34. 15. It is certain that the Soul so
soon as it is separated from the Body, is presented to
God, and receives an irrevocable Doom, either of
Woe, or Weal; <HI>Those that Honour me, I will Hon∣our,</HI>
saith the Lord, 1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 2. 30. Blessed and hap∣py
is he that hath part in the first Resurrection, on
such the second Death hath no Power, but they shall
be Precious with God and Christ, and shall Reign
with him. The Angels which kept not their first
Estate, he hath reserved in everlasting Chains of
Darkness, unto the Judgment of the great Day,
<HI>Iude</HI> 6. The Joy of our Heart is ceased, and the
Crown is fallen from our Head, <HI>Lam.</HI> 5. 15 16. In the Days
of his Flesh, when he had offered up Prayers and Sup∣plications,
with strong Crying and Tears unto him
that was able to save him from Death, and was heard
in that he feared, <HI>Heb.</HI> 5. 7. The Heavens shall be
opened, and those everlasting Doors shall be lift up
that the King of Glory may go forth with his An∣gels
to Judge the World, and return back again
with his Saints, when he hath Judged it. In the
Day of Judgment a good Conscience will stand us
in more stead, than a Mint of Treasure; therefore
with St. <HI>Ierome,</HI> let us make it our business, That
whether we Eat or Drink, or whatsoever we do, we
may think we hear the last Trumpet sounding in
our Ears, saying, Arise ye Dead, and come to Judg∣ment;
let us therefore appeal from the Bar of Gods
Justice, to the Bowels of his Mercy, beseeching him
in that Day to deal with the Souls of his Servants,
not as a severe Judge, but as a Merciful Jesus.
<HI>Amen.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prayer">
<PB N="83" REF="43"/>
<HEAD>Prayers for the Sick.</HEAD>
<Q><P>O Lord, look down from Heaven, behold, visit
and relieve this thy Servant, look upon him
with the Eyes of Mercy, give him Comfort and
sure Confidence in thee, defend him from the Dan¦ger
of the Enemy, and keep him in perpetua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Peace and Safety, through Jesus Christ our Lord
<HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<P>HEar us Almighty and most Merciful God and
Saviour, extend thy accustomed Goodness t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
this thy Servant who is grieved with Sickness
Sanctifie we beseech thee this thy Fatherly Correcti¦on
to him, that the sense of his Weakness may ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
Strength to his Faith, and Seriousness to his Repen¦tance,
that if it shall be thy good Pleasure to re¦store
him to his former Health, he may lead th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
residue of his Life in thy Fear, and to thy Glory
or give him Grace so to take this thy Heavenly visi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tation,
that after this painful Life ended, he may
dwell with thee in Life everlasting, through Jesu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Christ our Lord. <HI>Amen.</HI></P></Q>
<P>O Father of Mercyes, and God of all Consola¦tion,
lay no more upon him (or her) ther<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
thou wilt inable him to bear with Patience
Courage, and Contentment; either asswage his Pain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
or increase his Patience; bless all those means tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
have been, or shall be used for his recovery; eithe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
shorten his Sickness, or else give him Grace, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Strength to bear it; deliver him from the bitte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Pangs of Eternal Death, and from the Gates of Hel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
take from him the Sting of his Consciences, and th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
extremity of Sickness, Anguish, or Agony, that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="84" REF="44"/>
withdraw his mind from thee, through Jesus Christ
our Lord. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<P>DEliver him from all Dangers and Distress, from
Pain and Punishment Bodily and Ghostly, and
from all the Sins and Misdeeds, which by the Ma∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ice
of the Devil, or his own Frailty he have at any time
committed against thee. That it may please thee not
to lay to his Charge what in Concupiscence of the
Eye, Pride of Life, Vanity, or Superfluity, he hath
committed against thee. That it may please thee not
to lay to his Charge what in the Fierceness of his
Wroth, or in the eagerness of an Angry Spirit he hath
committed against thee. That it may please thee
not to lay to his Charge what in Vain and Idle
Words, in the Looseness and Slipperiness of the
Tongue he hath committed against thee. That it
may please thee to make him Partaker of all the
Mercies, and Promises in Christ Jesus. That it may
please the to vouchsafe his Soul the Estate of Joy,
Bliss, and Happiness with all thy blessed Saints in
thy Heavenly Kingdom. That it may please thee to
give him Peace, and a part in the blessed Resurrecti∣on
of Life and Glory; we commend his Soul into
thy Hands beseeching thee that it may be pretious
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n thy sight. O let not the Blood of Christ that was
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>shed for all Men, be spilt in vain to any, but let it be
effectual to the Salvation of every Soul, for thy own
Bowels and Compassion sake. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<P>IN the midst of Life we are in Death, Of whom
then may we seek for Succor, but of thee O Lord?
Who for our Sins are most justly displeased with us;
yet O Lord most Holy, O God most Mighty, O Holy
and most Merciful Father, deliver us not over to the
bitter Pains of Eternal Death. Thou knowest Lord
the Secrets of our Hearts, O shut not up against us
the Ears of thy Mercy, but spare us O Lord most
<PB N="85" REF="44"/>
Holy, O Saviour most mighty, O Immortal and mos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Merciful Redeemour. Thou most Worthy Judge
Eternal, suffer us not in our last Hour, for any Pains
of Death to fall from thee, though he hath Sinned,
yet he seeketh thee; and thou Lord never failest them
that seek thee. Let not the Guiltiness of a Sinne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
more prevail to condemn, than the Gracious Good∣ness
of a most Merciful Father, to Aquit and to Par∣don.
O let not the Unrighteousness of Man make th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Goodness of God of none effect, O Lord, no not
so remember not the Unkindnesess of this thy Child
so as thereby thou forgottest the Compassion and
Kindness of a Father. Do not so think on our Sins▪
that thou thereby forget thine own Nature and Pro∣perty,
which is always to have Mercy and Forgive.
Do not so remember our Sins, that thou thereby re∣member
not thy own Name, which is Jesus a most
Loving and Kind Saviour. Lord is thy Life in our
Life hath not sufficiently appeared, yet let not thy
Death lose the full Power and Effecacy thereof. Suf∣fer
not, O Lord, in both so great a price to perish,
lose not that O Lord which thou hast redeemed since
thou comest to redeem that which was lost, that
which was so dear to thee to redeem, suffer not to
be lost as a thing of no Value.</P>
<P>OH! Most Merciful and Blessed Saviour, have
Mercy upon the Soul of this thy Servant; re∣member
not his Ignorance, nor the Sins of his
Youth; but according to thy great Mercies remem∣ber
him in the Mercies, and Glories of thy King∣dom.
Thou, O Lord, hast opened the Kingdom of
Heaven to all Believers; let the Everlasting Gates be
opened, and receive his Soul; let the Angels who
Rejoyce at the Conversion of a Sinner, Triumph <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd
be Exalted in his Deliverance and Salvation, make
him partaker of the Benefits of thy Holy Incarnation,
Life, and Sanctity, Passion, and Death, Resurrection,
<PB N="86" REF="45"/>
and Assension, and of all the Prayers of the Church,
of the Joy of the Elect, and all the Fruits of the
Blessed Communion of Saints; and daily add to the
number of thy beatified Servants, such as shall be sa∣ved,
that thy coming may be hastned, and the ex∣pectation
of the Saints may be fulfiled, and the Glo∣ry
of thee our Lord Jesus be advanced; all the
whole Church Singing Praises to the Honour of thy
Holy Name, who Livest and Reignest ever one God,
World without end. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<P>OH! Most Merciful Jesu, who didst die to re∣deem
us from Death and Damnation, have Mer∣cy
upon this thy Servant, whom thy Hand has
visited with Sickness, of thy Goodness be pleased to
forgive him all his Sins, and Seal his hopes of Glory
with the refreshments of thy Holy Spirit. Lord
give him Strength and Confidence in thee, asswage
his Pain, repel the assaults of his Gostly Enemies,
by thy Mercies, and a Guard of Holy Angels pre∣serve
him in the Unity of the Church, keep his Sen∣ses
intire, his Understanding right, give him a great
measure of Contrition, true Faith, a well grounded
Hope, and abundance of Charity, give him a quiet
and a joyful departure, let thy Ministring Spi∣rits
conveigh his Soul to the Mansions of Peace and
Rest, there with certainty to expect a joyful Resur∣rection,
to the fulness of Joy at thy right Hand,
where there is pleasure for evermore. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prayer">
<HEAD>A Prayer for a Penitent.</HEAD>
<P>O Thou who still remainest the same Richfulness
in thy self, and the same bright Glory to all the
Blessed, have Mercy upon me, and all Mankind, in the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and full Pardon, and forgiveness of all our Sins that
<PB N="87" REF="45"/>
ever we have committed, from our Infancy to this
present Moment; and indue us with thy preventing
and assisting Grace, that we never fall into those Sins
of the which we have Repented; but fill us with
thy Holy Spirit, that we may increase in all Goodness
in the Spirit, of Might, of Wisdom, and Counsel,
Knowledge, Piety, and thy Holy Fear, that we may
do all such good Works as thou hast prepared for us
to walk in, by the assisting Power and Might of thy
Holy Strength, which we beseech thee constantly to
afford us to our last Breath, that when we shall breathe
out our Souls, they may be received instantly to Glo∣ry:
And this we begg for thy sake, who didst begin
to Bleed and Suffer for our Sin, even thee O Blessed
Jesus, who tookest that Heavenly Name, thy Blessed
purpose to Proclaim. Oh! may we bow our Heart<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and Knee bright King of Names to Glorious thee
who thus beginest our Bliss, thus carriedest on our
Happiness, to thee all Praise be paid, O Great
Misterious Three for ever Live, and ever be Obeyed▪
Beloved, Adored by Men, and Angels all abroad▪
Hallelujah.</P>
<P>O Lord, make us eminent Examples of Per∣fect
Christianity; and kindle in our Hearts
Zealous Emulations of thy Grace, that here immi∣tating
thy Life O Christ, we may be constant in the
Truth to our last Breath, that in our Mouths there may
not at any time be found a lie, that we may be
worthy to be presented without spot, before thy
Throne O God; and thou maiest exalt us to thy
Kingdom, and there admit us to tast of thos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Glorious Joys which incurcel thy Blessed Thron<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
above, to which we are Intituled by the Suffering o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Christ our Lord. Oh, give us true Repentance, that w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
may not fail of attaining of them, though I have no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
been strong enough to be perfectly Innocent: Yet mak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
me Humble enough to be truly Penitent, make m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="88" REF="46"/>
Heartily sorry that ever I have done amiss, and never
again dare to do that for which I am sorry; but per∣petually
Watch, and Change my Thoughts, to more
diligent and concerning Cares, how to redeem my
mispent Time with Sighs, and Tears, and Prayers;
and prepare our Understanding to assent to thy Truths,
and our Wills to follow thy Divine Inspirations; that
thou O God maiest fill our Memories with innumera∣ble
Mercies, and our whole Souls with the Glory of
his adorable Atributes; that thy Blessed Spirit may
come and breathe thy spacious Odor into our Hearts,
in these dull Regions here beneath, to fill our Souls
with thy sweet Grace, and Inspire us to give all pos∣sible
Glory to that secret Three, One ever Living So∣vereign
Lord, as at the first still may be, Beloved
Praised, Feared and Adored. Hallelujah.</P>
<P>O Lord, open the Eyes of our Understanding, and
shew us thy clear and supernatural Light, even
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thou didst to the Apostles, together with the
whole Army of Martyrs; that we may confidently
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffirm to others what we know so Infallibily cer∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ain
our selves: And be pleased to infuse into all
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ens Hearts the fulness of thine own Divine Charity,
that every one may instruct his Family; and with
Courage and Patience overcome their Oppressors,
that being thus Illuminated with a pure and clear
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ight, and inflamed with the ferver of Grace,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey may mightily shew forth thy Glory, and Con∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ert
many Souls to thee, that thy Grace may run
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd be Glorious over all the World, and thy Holy
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pirit be aimable in the Hearts of every Creature,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat all dulness may be removed from them, and they
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nay with swift Glances understand the sweet Will
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> their Divine Master, that they may Daily more and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ore increase in Virtue, and be inebriated with thy
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eavenly Wine, and filled with an Heroick Spirit,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>at may keep alive in their Hearts the Primitive
<PB N="89" REF="46"/>
Grace. Grant this O God who art still the same,
and with an equal Spirit Governs the World; re∣plenish
us all we beseech thee with the Holy Ghost,
which warms without scorching, and shines without
dim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ess, and inlightens without consuming: Kindle
in every one of our Hearts this Holy Spirit of Meek∣ness,
Peace, and Unity, that all the World may know
that we belong to thee. That exercising those
Virtues of Meekness, Long Suffering, Patience, Con∣tentedness
and Charity; thou maiest difuse thy Holy
Joy into our Breast, that may fill our Hearts with
Strength and undaunted Courage, that may duly
qualify us to ascend to those satisfing Joys above,
where all our Faculties shall be exercised in Adoring
and Worshiping thee O Lord our God, who wilt fill
our Souls full of Joy, and Ravish our Hearts with over∣flowing
Pleasures, and make us ever give Glory to
Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, the undivided Three
One equal Glory, one same Praise, from henceforth
and for ever be. Hallelujah.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prayer">
<HEAD>A Prayer for the Rich and Noble.</HEAD>
<P>O Lord, I beseech thee, make the Great and Hon∣ourable
become Good and Just, O suffer them
never to consent, nor combine with the Counsel of the
Wicked, but teach the Rich and Noble to lear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
to wait for thy Kingdom, cause them to im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ploy
their Wealth and Power in Piety, for Religio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and Charity, for the Poor; let them not loos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
their Courage in thee O King of Kings, for any diffi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>culties
they meet with in their way, but increase thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Faith, and support their Hope, that they may go o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
cheerfully in their Duty, firmly trusting in thee with<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>out
being removed from the Hope of a Blessed acce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tance
and a sure Reward. O make them diligent <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="90" REF="47"/>
all their indeavours, by removing all lets and hinde∣rances
of Piety, cause them Religiously to trust in thy
never failling Goodness, which will rather work a Mi∣racle,
which thy Power can do: Then forsake or slight
thy Servants which thy Goodness cannot, let the firm
assurance of this support them in every Centre of their
Lives, that they may always dedicate themselves to thy
Service, striving to be beneficial to the Poor, that so at
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ength both Poor and Rich may meet together in the
Kingdom of Glory, to Praise the Eternal King for ever
and ever. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prayer">
<HEAD>A Charitable Prayer for the Conversion
of all Hereticks.</HEAD>
<P>O Thou all-knowing Being, have Mercy upon the
Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> bless her with the choicest and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he richest of thy Blessings, power on her a double
Portion of thy Spirit, illuminate her with thy Truth,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urge out of her all Errors, Heresie and Superstition,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd whatsoever is contrary to Truth; make her such
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s she once was, a Pure, Spotless, and Holy Church,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ee her from all those Abominations which now she
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> involved in, illuminate her once again with the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>right Beams of thy pure Truth, that she may see
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er Errors, and forsake them, and cleave only to thee,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> God, that she may become such as thou canst not
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>huse but love, and be delighted with; take from her
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hatsoever displeaseth thee, make her Pure, Spotless
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd Innocent, full of Charity and good Fruits, free
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er from all those Superstitions and Corruptions she
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ave of late imbrac'd. With her, be merciful to all
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ther Churches, which differ from the Ancient Truth,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ake us all one Sheepfold, under one Shepherd Christ
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sus, that we may all give thee Honor and Praise
is most justly due; compleat that Promise of gi∣ving
<PB N="91" REF="47"/>
thy Son the Heathen for his Heritage, and the
utmost parts of the Earth for his Possessions. Bless
the King's Most Excellent Majesty, <HI>JAMES,</HI> by thy
Grace, of <HI>Great Brittain</HI> and <HI>Ireland,</HI> Supream
Governor, bind up his Soul in the Bundle of
Life, give him a long and prosperous Reign, with
abundance of Peace and Plenty, and when, at
length, it shall please thee to gather him to his Fa∣thers,
Crown him with Immortal Glory. And with
him, bless his Queen, with Queen Dowager, their
Royal Highnesses <HI>William</HI> and <HI>Mary,</HI> the Prince and
Princeses of <HI>Orange,</HI> and the Princess <HI>Anne</HI> of <HI>Den∣mark,</HI>
make them Instruments of much Good to
the Church of <HI>England,</HI> and these Nations, and give
them a Crown of Immortal Glory in thy Heavenly
Kingdom. Bless all the Nobility, the Judges, and the
Gentry, with the whole Commonalty of these Nations,
give them all True Faith and Fear to thee their God,
Loyalty to our Gracious Sovereign, and Brotherly Love
and Charity one towards another; and Bless with
the choicest of thy Blessings the Clergy of this Nation,
the Most Reverend the Arch-Bishops, and the Right
Reverend the Bishops, with all Priests and Deacons:
Grant, we beseech thee, that thy Grace may illustriously
appear in them, that by the Holiness of their Lives, and
the Soundness of their Doctrine, they may bring many
Souls to the Obedience of our Most Holy Faith; and be∣cause
no Man's Greatness or Wisdom can secure him
from the Grave. We beg thee, bless all Schools and
Nurseries of Piety and Learning, especially the two
Universities of our Land, that from thence may pro∣ceed
Men able and willing, to tell <HI>Judah</HI> of her Sins
and <HI>Israel</HI> of her Transgressions, and be mindful o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
those who suffer Affliction with <HI>Joseph;</HI> comfort all
those who in this transitory Life, are in Trouble, Sor∣row,
Need, Sickness, or any other Calamity, suppor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
them under, and give them a happy Issue out of al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
their Troubles, bind up their Souls Wounds, and fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
<PB N="92" REF="48"/>
their Spirits with Joy and Gladness; be with all those
that are going through the Valley of the Shadow of
Death, let thy Holy Angels conduct them safe to thy
Eternal Kingdom, let the Blood of Jesus bespeak their
Peace with thee, appoint those blessed Spirits to bring
their Souls safe into Bliss and Glory; make us all, we
pray thee, mindful of our Departure, that from thence∣forth,
we may be for ever happy: Mean time, make
us all truly thankful to thee, for all Spiritual and
Temporal Mercy to us, for the blessed Use of thy
Word and Sacraments, for Food and Nourishment,
and for all the Blessings we daily injoy, Health, Peace
and Liberty, for all the Conveniencies of this Life, and
for the Means and Hopes of a better. O impress in
our Minds, the lovely Idea of thy Majesty, that we
may seek to worship and adore thee according to thy
excellent Greatness, who art infinitely worthy of all
Praise, Honour and Glory. O inlarge our Souls to
pay thee such Praises, as may be in some degree wor∣thy
of thee, or at least, such as thou wilt be graci∣ously
pleased to accept. These Mercies we beg of
thee, for Jesus Christ's sake: To whom with thee,
O Father, and the Eternal Spirit, be all Honour, Glo∣ry,
Power and Praise, Might, Majesty, and Dominion,
now henceforth and for ever. <HI>Hallelujah.</HI></P>
<P>O Lord, I beseech thee, to magnify thy Power in
my Preservation, that my feeble Knees fains not;
preserve me from all unconstancy and deceitfulness of
Heart, that I may be presented to thee, pure and un∣blamable:
Be not wroth with us very sore, neither
remember our Iniquities for ever; but cause thy Face
to shine upon thy Sanctuary, which is in danger of
being desolate. Give Ease to those that are in Pain,
Supplies to all that are in Want. Give presumptious
Sinners a deep Sense of their Sins, and a true Sight of
thy Mercies to all that are in despair, that they may
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ot cast away their Confidence in thee, nor place it any
<PB N="93" REF="48"/>
where but in thee: Abhor them not, nor cast them
away in displeasure; but wean all our hearts from the
love of this World, and dispose of us as thy all-wise
Counsel have determined, but c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>use us to set our Af∣fections
above, where thou, O King of Glory, seteth
at the Right Hand of thy Father, to interceed for us,
that all our Weaknesses may be pitied, our Sins par∣doned,
our Graces strengthened, and our Souls eter∣nally
saved. In all our Pains of Body, and Agonies
of Spirit, give us thy refreshing Comforts, endew us
with Patience and Courage, Fortitude, and a full mea∣sure
of Faith, to bear, to undergo and to overcome;
Look, with Compassion, upon all poor Creatures that
draw near the approaches of Death, open the Gates of
thy everlasting Mercy to them, and receive them to thy
Favour; cause Death to be to them a Joyful Gate of
Glory, and an Entrance into everlasting Bliss, for
thine own bowels and compassion sake. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prayer">
<HEAD>A Prayer for a Member of the Church of England.</HEAD>
<P>O Lord take not off thy afflicting hand, till I am
reformed, and my Sins consumed; suffer me ne∣ver
to receive the least check against, nor disaffection
to the True Religion Established in (the Church of)
<HI>England:</HI> Let me return an humble denial to all that
shall propose such an unreasonable Question to me; but
if my denial will not suffice in this case, give me cou∣rage
rather to part from my Life, than to forsake my
Faith; and if my case be so happy, give me Grace,
with chearfulness, to pray for my Persecutors, though
dying by their Cruelty, that I may deeply impress
constancy and true courage in the hearts of all my
Spectators, that we all may sacrifice our Wills to God
before our Bodies, and both, whenever it shall please
him to require them at our hands; assist us in the do∣ing
this, by the powerful Operations of thy Divine
Grace, which we beseech thee, always plentifully to
supply us with, for thy Mercy sake. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="94" REF="49"/>
O Lord have Mercy upon our Parents, let th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Souls be bound up in the bundle of Life
grant them Grace to live a quiet and peaceable,
just and honest Life here, that when they come t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
die they may live with thee, and thy Christ in th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Heavenly Kingdom. Look not upon their Merit
but pardon their Offences, for thy Bowels an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Compassions sake, to whom be all Honour and Glor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
World without end. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prayer">
<HEAD>A Prayer at receiving the Holy Sacrament.</HEAD>
<P>O Lord and Heavenly Father, we thy humble Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>vants
beseech thy Fatherly Goodness to loo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
down from Heaven, thy Holy Habitation, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Throne of thy Glory, with an Eye of Pitty and Com¦passion
upon us thy Servants, let not our Sins hinde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
our Prayers from ascending up unto thee, or preven<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
thy Mercies coming down upon us; but come we
pray thee, and Sanctifie these Souls and Bodies o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
ours, and make them fit Habitations for thy Holy Spi∣rit
to dwell in; and come Sanctifie these thy Crea∣tures,
to the end, for which we receive them, that the
receiving the Blessed Sacrament may be unto us, for
the Conformation of our Faith, for the Strengthning
our Hope, and for the Pardoning of all our Sins, and
for the increase of all thy Graces in us, that the Pal∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate
of our Souls may be so changed thereby, that we
may relish nothing besides thee; but Hunger and
Thirst after this Bread of Life, and Cup of Salvation,
till we change this place of Misery, to enjoy thy Pre∣sence
in thy Heavenly Kingdom, for ever and ever.
<HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<HEAD>ERRATA.</HEAD>
<P>PAge 1. line 6. for whose, read what. p. 7. l. 21. r. the
Judge of. p. 24. l. 2. r. nor repine. p. 70. l. 29. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.
exclude.</P>
<PB REF="49"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

