<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The author and subject of healing in the church set forth in a sermon preached before the Right Honorable the Parliament of England at St. Margarets Church in Westminster, on Wednesday, April 25, 1660, being the day of their assembly / by Dr. Edward Reynolds ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Reynolds, Edward, 1599-1676.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A57130</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing R1239</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R36785</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">16016204</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 16016204</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">104769</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A57130)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104769)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1155:39)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The author and subject of healing in the church set forth in a sermon preached before the Right Honorable the Parliament of England at St. Margarets Church in Westminster, on Wednesday, April 25, 1660, being the day of their assembly / by Dr. Edward Reynolds ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Reynolds, Edward, 1599-1676.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 37 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Tho. Newcomb for George Thomason ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1660.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Imperfect: tightly bound, with loss of print.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</TERM><TERM>Bible. --  O.T. --  Malachi IV, 2-3 --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A57130">
<STC T="W">R1239</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">16016204</BIBNO>
<VID>104769</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
THE <HI>AUTHOR</HI> and <HI>SUBJECT</HI> OF HEALING IN THE CHURCH Set forth in a SERMON Preached before the Right Honorable The PARLIAMENT of <HI>England,</HI> at St. <HI>Margarets</HI> Church in <HI>Westminster,</HI> on Wednesday <HI>April</HI> 25. 1660. Being the day of their Assembly.</P>
<P>By <HI>Edward Reynolds</HI> D. D. and Dean of <HI>Christ-Church, Oxon.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>Tho: Newcomb</HI> for <HI>George Thomason,</HI> at the Rose and Crown in St. <HI>Pauls-</HI>Church-yard. 1660.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Right Honorable the LORDS &amp; COMMONS Assembled in PARLIAMENT.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Right Honorable,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Hen I was com∣manded by the Council of State to Preach before you on the day of the Parliaments Assembling, I could not but reflect on the woful and never-enough to be lamented con∣fusions, under which these Na∣tions
<PB REF="3"/>
were ready to sink and perish, till the Lord was pleased, as it were <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, to raise up an Honorable Instrument, by his Wisdom and Valor to put a <HI>stop</HI> to the <HI>progress,</HI> and to open a way, that you by your Counsel and Authority, might put a <HI>period</HI> to the <HI>Being</HI> of them. In order whereunto, I thought it my duty, as a Minister of the Gospel of Peace, and a Servant to our <HI>Great Lord,</HI> whose work it was to <HI>heal</HI> and <HI>recover, Luke 4. 18.</HI> Humbly to set before you the <HI>Au∣thor</HI> and the <HI>Object;</HI> and on the Monday following, before the Right Honorable <HI>House of Peers,</HI> the <HI>means</HI> and <HI>method</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
of <HI>Gods healing</HI> a Sick Nation: And thereupon to be seech you, so to imitate the example of Christ, who is <HI>the Lord that healeth us,</HI> so to promote the <HI>fear of his Name,</HI> and the great works of <HI>Humilia∣tion, Supplication,</HI> and <HI>Re∣formation</HI> amongst us, as that you might comfortably plead his pro∣mise, to <HI>hear, forgive, and heal the Land:</HI> For the <HI>Lord</HI> will be with you while you are with him; and if you seek him, he will be found of you.</P>
<P>And for this work of setting up the <HI>fear of God,</HI> and <HI>real conversion</HI> unto him, though god∣liness have as many enemies, as there be Devils in Hell, or wick∣ed
<PB REF="4"/>
men in the World; yet pro∣faneness is in it self so shameful, and holiness so amiable, that en∣deavors in this most weighty work, will, I am confident, meet with no prevalent opposition or ob∣struction among you. All sober men of every perswasion, how so∣ever otherwise divided, acknow∣ledging the necessity, and pro∣fessing their desires, that the Name of the <HI>Lord</HI> may in <HI>pu∣rity of Doctrine,</HI> and in <HI>holi∣ness of life,</HI> be magnified amongst us.</P>
<P>You have made an <HI>happy en∣trance</HI> unto this <HI>healing work,</HI> (for certainly the great <HI>suffer∣ings</HI> of our <HI>Princes,</HI> have had a
<PB REF="4"/>
strong causality upon our distracti∣ons, it can never be well with the <HI>Body,</HI> while it is ill with the <HI>Head,)</HI> and you have hereby blasted the projects and attempts of any, whose ambition might ani∣mate them, to awaken old, or to kindle new flames amongst us.</P>
<P>If together with this noble act of <HI>Justice</HI> and <HI>Loyaltie,</HI> you pro∣ceed to secure the Interest of <HI>Jesus Christ,</HI> by establishing the <HI>True Reformed Religion,</HI> an <HI>Orthodox,</HI> learned and painful <HI>Ministry,</HI> pure <HI>Worship,</HI> and the <HI>Power of godliness,</HI> sup∣pressing and putting to shame all profane practises, whereby the wrath of the <HI>Lord</HI> may be again
<PB REF="5"/>
kindled against us, you shall there∣by greatly blast the desires of <HI>li∣centious</HI> and evil men; and comfort the hearts, and give e∣vidence of the answer of <HI>God</HI> to the prayers of good men. Which that you may be enabled and as∣sisted to do by the power of <HI>Divine grace,</HI> is the most earnest prayer of</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE>May 5. 1660.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Your Honors most humbly devoted in the Lord ED. REYNOLDS.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>THE AUTHOR and SUBJECT Of Healing in the Church. <HI>Set forth in a</HI> SERMON Preached before the Right Honorable the PARLAMENT of <HI>England,</HI> at St. <HI>Margarets</HI> Church in <HI>Westminster,</HI> on Wednesday <HI>April</HI> 25. 1660. Being the day of their Assembly.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Mal. 4: 2, 3.</BIBL>
<Q><P>But unto you that fear my name, shall the Sun of Righteousness arise with healing in his wings, and ye shall go forth, and grow up as calves of the stall.</P>
<P N="3">3. And ye shall tread down the Wicked.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">O</SEG>Ur Prophet was the last of all the Prophets of the Old Testament, after which they were not to look for any o∣ther, till <HI>Elias</HI> the forerunner of the Angel of the Cove∣nant (who was the great Prophet of all) should come unto them. The Church ap∣pears 
<PB N="2" REF="6"/>
in his time to have been wofully cor∣rupted, by those sharp reprehensions of Priests and people, for corruption of wor∣ship, for violation of Covenant, for con∣t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>macy against God, for reproaching his ways, and passing an hard and false charge against his services as if they were vain and fruitless. In the midst of this Hypocritical people, the Lord had an <HI>Holy remnant</HI> who feared his name, and <HI>spake often to one another.</HI> Both these seemed to call for the <HI>coming</HI> of Christ, and to delight in the promise of the <HI>Angel of the Covenant. chap.</HI> 2: 17. 3: 1. And accordingly here is a promise of his <HI>coming speedily.</HI> But though desired by both, he should come with great difference to the one and the other; to the one after a terrible manner, <HI>with refineing fire and fullers sope,</HI> with <HI>fanne,</HI> and <HI>sword,</HI> with a <HI>spirit of Judg∣ment and burning</HI> to consume the stubble, to gather the body of that wicked people in∣to <NOTE PLACE="marg">Math. 3: 12. Math. 10: 34. Isai, 4: 4.</NOTE> <HI>Jerusalem</HI> as into an <HI>Oven</HI> and furnace, and there with a final and absolute <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> to dissolve the judaical politie, and leave them <HI>neither root nor branch,</HI> no visible hope of restitution again, <HI>chap.</HI> 4: 1. which was done by the army of the Romans under <HI>Titus.</HI> To the other with a promise of Com∣fort and Reviving. <HI>chap.</HI> 3: 17. <HI>They shall be mine, in that day when I make up my Jew∣els,</HI>
<PB N="3" REF="6"/>
<HI>and I will spare them as a man spareth his own son that serveth him.</HI> And that so remark∣able, that the reproach cast by the wicked Hypocrites upon the ways of God, <HI>ver.</HI> 14, 15. <HI>Ye have said it is vain to serve God: What pro∣fit is it that we have kept his Ordinance, and that we have walked mournfully before the Lord of Hosts? And now we call the proud happy</HI> &amp;c. should be clearly confuted, by the conspi∣cuous difference which the Lord would make between the righteous and the wicked, <HI>ver.</HI> 18. the one <HI>jewels</HI> and <HI>sons</HI> to be preserved and spared, the other <HI>stubble</HI> to be burnt and dis∣solved; the one to be <HI>healed</HI> and restored, the other to be <HI>troden down</HI> and despised. Concluding all with an awakening precept, that since they were not to expect any other Prophet, till <HI>Eliah</HI> and Christ should come, they should therefore <HI>remember the Law of Moses,</HI> and thereby fit themselves for the en∣tertainment of their <HI>Messiah.</HI></P>
<P>The words contain a <HI>gracious and discrimi∣nating mercy</HI> unto an holy remnant that fear∣ed Gods name, for their supportance and comfort against the terror of the foregoing threatning, that unto them the <HI>Sun of Righte∣ousness,</HI> the promised <HI>Messiah,</HI> should arise in <HI>his Incarnation</HI> with <HI>healing in his wings;</HI> and when <HI>grosse darkness did cover the people,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Isai. 60. 2. Isai. 9: 2.</NOTE> and they did sit even in the <HI>shadow of death,</HI>
<PB N="4" REF="7"/>
not only veiled over with the <HI>Shadows</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the Law, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mis∣led by the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> glosses of S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ibes and Pharisees, sold and devoured by their own shepherds, wofully oppressed under <HI>Alexan∣der,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Zach. 11: 5.</NOTE> <HI>Janneus, Hircanus, Aristobulus,</HI> sub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>u∣ed by <HI>Pompey</HI> into the form of a Roman Pro∣vince, and then sorely afflicted under the Tyranny of <HI>Antipater and Herod;</HI> that after such a night of darkness and distress, the pro∣mised <HI>Messiah</HI> should come to break the <HI>yoke</HI> and <HI>rod of their oppressor,</HI> and assert his peo∣ple <NOTE PLACE="marg">Isah 9. 4 10: 27.</NOTE> into Light and Liberty again. That he should come as the warm and welcom beams of the Sun, after a dead winter, or a gloomy and tempestuous night, to heal and remove all the sins and sorrows of his people.</P>
<P>In the words we have these particulars considerable. 1. The <HI>discriminating grace</HI> of God between a Remnant that feared his name, and the body of a co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>upt and pro∣phane people. 2. The <HI>supposition</HI> of a State of <HI>sickness</HI> and soreness, of sin and sorrow, under which even this Holy Remnant did lie; with a gracious promise of <HI>healing</HI> unto them. 3. The Author of this <HI>healing,</HI> ex∣pressed metaphorically by the name of the <HI>Sun of Righteousness,</HI> as before by the name of the Angel or <HI>Messenger of the Covenant.</HI> 4. The <HI>means</HI> of deriving this healing from
<PB N="5" REF="7"/>
this Sun of Righteousness. 1. His <HI>rising.</HI> 2. His <HI>wings</HI> or beams, which are the <HI>Vehi∣cula</HI> of all the light and vertue which flow eth forth from him 5. The proper and peculi∣ar <HI>Subject</HI> of this <HI>Healing,</HI> singled out by way of gracious <HI>compellation, unto you that fear my name.</HI> 6. The <HI>effects</HI> and fruits of this <HI>Healing,</HI> and they are three, 1. <HI>Going forth,</HI> as recovered men use to do out of their bed or chamber when the Sun shineth in a warm and beautifull day, to take the aire and refresh themselves. 2. <HI>Grewing up,</HI> in sta∣ture, in strength, <HI>speedily,</HI> as fatted C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lves, <HI>luxuriating</HI> in a full and pleas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt pasture. 3. <HI>Treading down</HI> and crushing the wicked as <HI>Grapes</HI> in the Press, as <HI>ashes</HI> under their Feet, in a full and triumphant victory.</P>
<P>I shall handle the words thus distribu∣ted after a double manner. 1. In the <HI>spi∣ritual,</HI> proper, and <HI>theological</HI> sense of them as they are a promise of Christ, and H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>al∣ing by him to an afflicted remnant of men that fear Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s name. 2. In an <HI>Applicatory</HI> and particular sense, as they are suitable to the present solemnity and occasion.</P>
<P N="1">1. The <HI>Church</HI> of God was at this time in a most defaced and corrupted condition, Gods worship prophaned, his name blasphemed, his treasuries robbed, his Judgments que stioned, his reproofs despised: yet in the midst
<PB N="6" REF="8"/>
of all this rubbish there is a <HI>Remnant</HI> accor∣ding to the Election of Grace. Though the Church be not alwaies visibly Glorious, yet in the most collapsed state thereof, in the worst times, it is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ever without visible pro∣fessors who have stood up to beare witness unto persecuted Truth. The Lord had Seven thousand in <HI>Israel</HI> that had not bowed the <NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Reg. 19. 18.</NOTE> knee to <HI>Baal.</HI> When our adversaries challenge us to shew where our Church was besore <HI>Lu∣ther,</HI> we answer, That in the midst of the greatest darkness and superstition, there were such <HI>fundamentall</HI> truths of faith and re∣pentance, and holy Life r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tained, as the Lord no doubt did sanctifie to the Salvation of many, who lived in the body of the <HI>Roman</HI> Church, and were by their very <HI>Ignorance</HI> preserved from the <HI>dangerous superstructions</HI> which the Doctors of that Church built upon that foundation, as the Renowned Bishop <NOTE PLACE="marg">Sermon of the unity of the Church.</NOTE> <HI>Usher</HI> hath observed. 2. There were in no age wanting Holy and zealous men who did boldly appeare against the prevailing Erro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of the times, as our learned men have large∣ly proved in their <HI>Historico-polemical</HI> writings, and large volumes have been written of the <HI>Catalogues</HI> of such witnesses in every age of the Church, who have declared against many Corruptions of the times wherein they lived. But that there hath alwaies been a <HI>visible</HI>
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
<HI>conspicuous Glory</HI> in the maine Body of the Church, is evidently disproved by the <HI>perse∣cutions</HI> which prevailed from time to time a∣gainst it. How did the <HI>Arian Heres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e</HI> over∣spread the world, when such glorious lights is <HI>Athanasius and Hilary</HI> were persecuted for professing the truth? <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ngemuit totus orbis</HI> saith <NOTE PLACE="marg">Hieron: ad∣verse Lucife∣rianos.</NOTE> <HI>Hierom, &amp; Arianum se esse miratus est.</HI> It is not less easie for us to finde out our Religion and the professors thereof in the corrupt ages of the Church, then for them to find out theirs in the pure and primitive.</P>
<P>Sure we are in the worst times the Lord hath ever <HI>had a people</HI> that feared his name, whose hearts he hath by select promises and Comforts supported, <HI>against</HI> the <HI>terror</HI> of those curses which he hath denounced against the corrupt body of the people. <HI>Say to the Righteous, it shall be well with them,</HI> Isai. 3. 10. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>inde the Testimonie, seale the Law among my Disciples,</HI> Isai. 8. 16. <HI>There is a remnant ac∣cording to the election of grace,</HI> when the rest are blinded, <HI>Rom.</HI> 11. 5. 7.</P>
<P>Hence that usuall intermixture of <HI>Threats</HI> and <HI>Promises</HI> in the Prophets, as a president <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nto Preachers of the truth in all ages, who ought with such prudence and tendernes to manage this part of their Ministry, as neither to <HI>harden</HI> the wicked in their sins by undue application of mercy, nor to <HI>make sad</HI> the
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
hearts of those whom the Lord hath not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ade sad, by a promis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uous denunciation of wrath, but <HI>righ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ly to divide the word of truth,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd <HI>to give to every one their own portion.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. Nor must we here pass by unobserved that <HI>discriminating Grace</HI> of God, whereby the <HI>Jewels</HI> and the <HI>Stubble,</HI> the Godly for <HI>healing,</HI> and the wicked for <HI>burning,</HI> are distinguished the one from the other. The Lord indeed doth most righteously dispence both <HI>healing</HI> to those that feare him, according to the <HI>Grace</HI> of his covenant; and burning to those that hate him, according to the <HI>Justice</HI> of his Law. And it is true, the <HI>wicked</HI> make thems<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lvs fit for the burning, for their <HI>de∣struction is of themselves,</HI> Hos. 13. 9. <HI>Their way and their doings have procured it,</HI> Jer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>. 4. 18. it is a <HI>choice</HI> of their owne making, <HI>Isai.</HI> 66. 3. But they that are <HI>healed,</HI> are not the Authors or originall procurers either of the <HI>grace</HI> whereby they fear God, or of the <HI>merc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> wherby God heales them; God alone by his <HI>free Grace</HI> makes the difference between those that serve him and those that serve him not. He <HI>reveales to babes, what he hides from the wise and prudent,</HI> and that because it <HI>seems good to him. Math.</HI> 11. 25. 26. <HI>To you it is given, to them it is not given. Math,</HI> 13. 11. I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> is <HI>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of him that willeth, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nor of him that runeth, but of God that sheweth mercy, Rom.</HI> 9, 16
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
If I be one of that Remnant that feare Gods name, I have no reason to glory in my selfe, it is God that <HI>gives me an heart and away to feare him,</HI> Ier. 32. 39. It is <HI>by his grace that I am what I am,</HI> 1 Cor. 15. 10. It is he that <HI>works in me to will and to do of his own good pleasure,</HI> Phil. 2. 13. It is he that <HI>makes me to differ,</HI> 1 Cor. 4. 7. <HI>ut Totum Deo detur, qui Hominis voluntatem bonam et praeparat adju∣vandam,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Aug. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nchirid: c.</HI> 32.</NOTE> <HI>et adjuvat praeparatam,</HI> as the in∣comparable Champion of the Grace of God St. <HI>Austin</HI> speaketh; That the whole work may be ascribed unto God, who both pre∣pareth the good will of man that it may be holpen, and helpeth it being prepared.</P>
<P>And againe <HI>Certum est nos velle cumvolu∣mus</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Aug. de Grat. &amp; lib. Arb. c</HI> 16. <HI>contra dua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Epist <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>elag. lib.</HI> 4. <HI>c</HI> 6. <HI>&amp; de d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> perse∣ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>at. cap.</HI> 13. <HI>de praedestinat: Sanct. c.</HI> 10</NOTE> <HI>sed ille facit ut velimus.</HI> It is certain, that we will when we do will, but it is he that maketh us to will. And again, <HI>nos volumus, sed Deus in nobis operatur &amp; velle, nos operam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r, sed Deus in nobis operatur &amp; operari;</HI> we will, but God worketh <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n us to will; we work, but God worketh in us to wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>k also. And again, <HI>Ille facit ut nos faciamus quae praecepit, nos non facimus ut ille faciat quae promisit;</HI> He maketh us to do the things which he commandeth, we make not him to do the things which he promiseth. O that the wanton and proud wits of men would leave the Lord <HI>to do with his owne what it pleaseth him,</HI> (as he will certainly
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
do notwithstanding all their passionate alterca∣tions, <HI>Mat.</HI> 20. 15.) and would let the <HI>difference</HI> between him that feareth the Lord, and him that feareth him not, be ascribed only unto the gift of grace, without the which, no man would feare him; which rich grace, <HI>a nullo duro Corde respuitur, ideo enim datur ut cordis duritia</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Aug de prae∣dest. Sanct. c.</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>primitus auferatur,</HI> as the same Father speakes, is not refused by any hard heart, for it is therefore given that hardness of heart may be taken away. Though man be <HI>free to resist</HI> grace, yet he is <HI>not free to conquer</HI> it; Gods mercy is victorious as well as his justice, <HI>That which cometh into your mind, shall not be at all, that ye say, we will be as the Heathen, as the Families of the Countries, to serve wood and stone, as I live saith the Lord God, surely with a mighty hand, and with a stretehed out arm, and with fury poured out, will I rule over you;</HI> Ezek. 20. 32, 33. Where the Lord threatneth to conquer them with his mercy, he will have mercy on whom he wil have mer∣cy, <HI>Si Deus miseretur etiam volumus, ad eandem quippe misericordiam pertinet ut velimus.</HI> I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ad Simplie. lib.</HI> I. <HI>qu.</HI> 2.</NOTE> men would be but contented that God should use his free will in <HI>giving</HI> his grace, as well as they contend for <HI>their owne free will</HI> to <HI>accept</HI> it; if the time which is spent in dis∣puting for free will, were spent in begging it: or if when we beg free will of God, that we
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
may accept grace and not refuse it, we would but allow it consonant to Gods power and goodnes, to grant us our petition, and to cause us not to refuse it, (and certainly <HI>lex supplicandi legem statuit Credendi,</HI> as <HI>Celesti∣nus</HI> speaks, we may beleeve that God will g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ant, what we pray for according to his will) the world would not be so continually troubled with the hot and passionate disputes in these arguments as we finde it is, certainly every humble and holy man will not onely think it his duty to praise God for that he gave him a <HI>power</HI> to convert, but that he gave him Conversion it selfe, and the very work of willing and turning unto God.</P>
<P N="3">3. We may here observe the double most different effect of the Gospell of <HI>Christ</HI> upon <HI>proud</HI> and <HI>penitent</HI> sinners, a <HI>savour of death</HI> to one, <HI>of life</HI> to the other, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 2. 15. 16. <HI>fire</HI> to the one, <HI>balsome</HI> to the other; as the same <HI>perfume</HI> kils the <HI>vulture,</HI> which revives the <HI>Dove;</HI> the same <HI>Red Sea</HI> a passage to <HI>Israel,</HI> a grave to <HI>Egypt;</HI> the same <HI>pillar</HI> light to one, and darknes to the other; the same <HI>sun</HI> makes the <HI>Garden</HI> smell sweet, and the <HI>Dunghill</HI> stink.</P>
<P>Great therefore must our care be what af∣fections we bring to hearing the word. <HI>It</HI> is given for life, but we may find it u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>to death, according to the disposition of heart we
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
bring with us thereunto, <HI>an honest and good Heart,</HI> a meek and quiet Spirit, a melted <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oul ready to be cast into the mould of the word, is the best preparation to meetwith Christ in his Gospel.</P>
<P N="2">II. We see here <HI>Healing</HI> promised to those that <HI>fear Gods name,</HI> and thence we may cer∣tainly conclude, that the <HI>Holiest men do want healing.</HI> 1. As we are like unto Christ, <HI>per pri∣mitias Spiritus,</HI> by the first fruits of the spi∣rit, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Aug. depeccat Me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>it &amp; Re∣miss. c.</HI> 8 E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> 7. 20. Jam. 3: 2.</NOTE> so we are unlike unto him <HI>per reliquias vetustatis,</HI> by the remainders of corruption; There is <HI>not a just man that liveth and sinneth not.</HI> Though the guilt of sin be removed in our <HI>justification,</HI> and the <HI>power subdued</HI> in our sanctification, yet the <HI>sickness</HI> and remain∣ders of it are <HI>not abolished</HI> till our dissolution. <HI>Ista vitia gratiâ dei medicante curantur, prius</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Aug. contra Julian. Pelag. lib 5. c. 7.</NOTE> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t reat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> non teneant, deinde ut constict<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> non vincant, postremo ut omni ex parte Sanata, nulla omnino remaneant,</HI> as St. <HI>Austin</HI> speaks. These Evils are cured by the Grace of God, first that they may not hold us by their guilt, next that they may not conquer us in the conflict, and lastly that being through∣ly healed, none of them may remain. And these remainders of corruption the Lord here leaveth in us to be matter of <HI>daily <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>on∣slict,</HI> of deep <HI>humbling,</HI> of earnest <HI>Prayer, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t sit quod pet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ntibus largiter adjiciat quod confi∣tentibus</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Aug. de spir. &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. cap u't.</NOTE>
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
<HI>clementer ignoscat,</HI> that he may bountisully give the things for which we pray, and graciously pardon the sins which we confess. 2. Besides our sins, we are sur∣rounded with <HI>Enemies,</HI> and beset on every side with <HI>Temptations,</HI> and though we have a promise of <HI>victory</HI> over them, and <HI>sufficiency</HI> of grace against them, yet we have no pro∣mise of absolute immunity, that we shall be invulnerable by them. The experience of our own Lapses, and of the Holiest and greatest Saints sufficiently evidence unto us what poor and fraile Creatures we are when the Lord leaves us, to t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y us, as he did <HI>Hezekiah,</HI> 2 <HI>Cron.</HI> 32. 31. 3. <HI>Sorrow</HI> is the naturall Off-spring of sinn and temptation, a sick and a wounded man cannot but feel the paine of that which weakneth him. There are not any men, more men of sorrow and acquain∣ted with grief, then they whose eyes are most open to see, whose hearts most tender to feel the weight of sinn, the terrors of God, and the Assaults of temptation. Being there∣fore subject to <HI>sins,</HI> to <HI>wounds,</HI> to <HI>sorrows,</HI> no wonder if they stand in need of <HI>healing.</HI></P>
<P>And indeed <HI>none call</HI> out so importunately for <HI>healing,</HI> either for themselves or for the Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ch of God, as they that feare <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>is name. <HI>Jer.</HI> 8. 22. <HI>Psal.</HI> 51. 8. 18. <HI>Psal.</HI> 38. 3<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>9. He that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hall read the dolefull complaints of <HI>Job,</HI> of
<PB N="14" REF="12"/>
<HI>Heman,</HI> of <HI>Hezekiah,</HI> and others mourning under the weight of sin and wrath; of <HI>Je remy, Daniel</HI> and <HI>Nehemiah</HI> bewailing the breaches and desolations of <HI>Sion,</HI> will finde it one principall evidence of a Godly man, to poure out his complaint before the Lord when he is overwhelmed. <HI>Psal.</HI> 102. 1. no desires so strong in t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>m as to have their eyes opened, their hearts purged, their sin re∣moved, their peace enlarged, the truth of God vindicated, his worship restored, his ordinances preserved, his presence continued in the midst of his people. <HI>Promises</HI> of healing in God, do awaken <HI>prayers</HI> for healing in them. <HI>Isai.</HI> 19. 22. <HI>Jer.</HI> 31. 8, 9, 10. 33. 6. <HI>Hos.</HI> 6. 1. <HI>Isai.</HI> 57. 15.</P>
<P N="3">III. The Au<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hor of this <HI>healing</HI> is here <NOTE PLACE="marg">Luk. 4. 18. Act. 4. 30. Isai. 30. 26.</NOTE> the <HI>Sun of Righteousness,</HI> who came pur∣posely, <HI>to binde up the broken hearted,</HI> to ap∣point to them that mourn, beauty for ashes &amp;c. <HI>Isai.</HI> 61: 1, 2, 3. Concerning him let us consider 1. The reason of his Appellation, 2. The manner of his <HI>healing.</HI> For the Ap∣pellation, he was called by <HI>Balaam,</HI> a <HI>Star,</HI> one that was to have dominion, <HI>Num.</HI> 24, 17, 19. A <HI>great Light. Isai.</HI> 9. 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, the day Spring or Sun rising, <HI>Luke</HI> 1. 78. A <HI>Bright Star</HI> of the morning, <HI>Rev.</HI> 22. 16. an <HI>everlasting</HI> light that never goes down, <HI>Jsai.</HI> 60: 20. That takes away all night, <HI>Rev.</HI> 22. 5.</P>
<P><PB N="15" REF="12"/>
The Apostle tells us, that by <HI>Christ</HI> the <HI>Worlds</HI> were made, <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>b.</HI> 1. 2. The old <HI>visi∣ble world,</HI> wherein is the natural Sun; and a <HI>New heaven</HI> and earth wherein dwelleth <HI>Righteousness,</HI> 2 <HI>Pet.</HI> 3. 13. unto which belongeth this <HI>Son of Righteousness.</HI> And therefore the time of the Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>el, is called <HI>a day of Grace and Salvation,</HI> 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 6. 2. <HI>Rom.</HI> 13: 12, 13. And Beleevers <HI>children of the light and of the day,</HI> 1 <HI>Thes.</HI> 5: 5. W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>erein darkness of Error and Ignorance is dispelled, and glorious things, which had been hidden from ages and generations manifested unto the World.</P>
<P>Christ is the <HI>Light</HI> of the <HI>World to come</HI> (as the Evangelical Church seemeth to be called, <HI>Heb.</HI> 2: 5.) That <HI>Light, John</HI> 1. 8. 3: 19. An <HI>heavenly</HI> Light, so Evangelical Doctrines are called <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Heavenly things, <HI>John</HI> 3: 12, 31. <HI>Heb.</HI> 9: 23.</P>
<P>A <HI>full</HI> Light, <HI>John</HI> 1: 14. In him did all fulness dwell, <HI>Col.</HI> 1: 19. An <HI>Indeficient</HI> light which endures for ever, as a faithful <HI>Witness</HI> in Heaven, <HI>Psal.</HI> 89: 36. <HI>Isai.</HI> 60: 19. A <HI>primi∣tive</HI> Independent Light, which deriveth not his righteousness f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>om any o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>her fountain, he <HI>sanctified himself</HI> by his own spirit, <HI>John</HI> 17, 19. A <HI>diffusive</HI> light which sheddeth it self on every other Vessel of Light <HI>of his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ess we all receive. He silleth all in all,</HI>
<PB N="16" REF="13"/>
<HI>John</HI> 1: 16. <HI>Eph.</HI> 1: 23. A <HI>moveing</HI> Light, which goes through all the Earth, to the ends of the world, <HI>Psal.</HI> 19: 3. 6. <HI>He came and preached peace to those afar off, and to them that were nigh Eph.</HI> 2: 17. An <HI>Operative,</HI> influential, and be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gne Light, which cometh with Life, as well as with Lustre, and therefore it is called the <HI>womb</HI> of the morning, <HI>Psal.</HI> 110: 3. 3. reviving, restoring, ripening the fiuits of the Earth. <HI>Psal.</HI> 36: 9.</P>
<P>The <HI>means</HI> and <HI>manner</HI> of his <HI>Healing</HI> is by his <HI>Arising</HI> unto us. There is a Sun extant at midnight, as well as at noon, but he com∣forts not us but by his rising. Now this rising not<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th,</P>
<P N="1">1. His <HI>Incarnation,</HI> the word which is translated <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Oriens,</HI> the day-spring or sun-rising, <HI>Luke</HI> 1: 78. is in the original <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a <HI>Branch, Zach</HI> 3. 8: And as here a <HI>Sun</HI> of righteousness; so elsewhere a <HI>Branch</HI> of Righteousness, <HI>Jer.</HI> 23. 5. 33: 15. A <HI>Sun</HI> of Righteousness, so he is the Lord <HI>from Hea∣ven,</HI> the Lord of <HI>David:</HI> a <HI>Branch</HI> of Righte∣ousness, so he is the son and the <HI>Off-spring of David.</HI> This is our comfort, that he is as well <HI>Germen,</HI> springing out of the Earth, as <HI>Oriens</HI> looking down from Heaven, <HI>Psal.</HI> 85: 11.</P>
<P N="2">2. His <HI>manifestation</HI> in spirit and power, by the Gospel to the consciences of his peo∣ple, 
<PB N="17" REF="13"/>
by the beauties of his Grace and Holi∣ness, illightning the mind, inclining the will, healing the affections, converting the con∣s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ience, discovering to the Soul the deep things of God, which is called the <HI>rising of the Day-star in the heart.</HI> 2 <HI>Pet.</HI> 1. 19.</P>
<P N="3">3. His rouzing men out of ignorance and security, unto the businesses of an holy life, for the sun riseth that men may <HI>go forth to their labours,</HI> Psal. 104. 22, 23. <HI>The light saith, awake thou that sleepest,</HI> Eph. 5. 14. <HI>Rom.</HI> 13. 11.</P>
<P N="4">4. His Heavenly conduct and direction, shewing us the way wherein we should walk, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 143: 8. Psal. 5. 8. Isai. 30: 21.</NOTE> and leading us therein, discovering Enemies and temptations behinde us, precipices, gulfs, snares, and pits before us, <HI>Luk.</HI> 1. 79. whereas he who walkethin darknes, knoweth not whither he goeth, <HI>Joh.</HI> 12. 35.</P>
<P>The Sun of Righteousness thus rising doth heale us by his <HI>light,</HI> and by his <HI>influ∣ence.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">John 16. 8. 11.</NOTE> 1. By the <HI>light</HI> of his Heavenly Do∣ctrine whereby he <HI>convinceth of sin,</HI> and so discovereth our disease: and then of <HI>Righ∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>snes</HI> in him to pardon our sin, and of <HI>Judgment</HI> to rescue us out of the dominion and power of Satan 2 By the <HI>Infuence</HI> of his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lessed <HI>Spirit</HI> efficaciously enforcing the word, an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>educing that vertue out of it, by which it restoreth health and beauty to the
<PB N="18" REF="14"/>
Soul, This is called the <HI>revealing of the arme of the Lord, Isa,</HI> 53. 1. and the <HI>hand of the Lord</HI> being with the word. <HI>Act.</HI> 11. 23.</P>
<P N="4">4. But Christ is in Heaven, and we in Earth, how shall we bring these together, that the <HI>Medicine</HI> may be applied to the disease. <HI>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne agens agit per Contactum,</HI> and this must be either <HI>Immediatione suppositi</HI> or <HI>Immediatione virtutis,</HI> as Philosophers speak. And we have both here, his <HI>person</HI> being Divine is <HI>Immense &amp; omnipresent.</HI> He <HI>filleth All in All.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Eph. 1. 23.</NOTE> His <HI>vertue</HI> is further conveyed unto us by his <HI>Wings,</HI> the <HI>Beams</HI> of this sun of Righteous∣nes, most swiftly and suddenly flying with <NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 139. 9.</NOTE> his truth and grace into the Soul. And these Wings are;</P>
<P N="1">1. His <HI>word and ordinances</HI> in which <HI>Christ</HI> is <HI>present</HI> with his Church, <HI>Math.</HI> 18. 20. and <HI>presented</HI> to it. <HI>Gal.</HI> 3. 1. The holy <HI>Doctrines</HI> of the Gospell, and duties of wor∣ship, (are if I may so speak) the <HI>Drugs</HI> and <HI>Materials,</HI> the <HI>Balme</HI> of <HI>Gilead,</HI> whereby spirituall diseases, sinn and sorrow are cured. As we find usually in the Gospell, he did but <HI>speak the word</HI> and <HI>diseases</HI> were gon. H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> cures were <HI>Commands.</HI> His ordinances ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the Leavs of the Tree of Life, which are fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth. 8. 8, 9.</NOTE> healing of Nations. <HI>Rev.</HI> 22. 2.</P>
<P N="2">2. Any Illustrious <HI>providence</HI> sent down <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it were from Heaven, when he doth <HI>terr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Isai. 64. 3.</NOTE>
<PB N="19" REF="14"/>
<HI>things which we looked not for.</HI> Thus he healed the fears of <HI>Israel</HI> by opening <HI>a way in the Red Sea,</HI> and their murmurings in the wildernes by giving them <HI>Waters out of the Rock.</HI> Thus he strengthned the faith of <HI>Constantine</HI> newly converted by the signe of the name of <HI>Christ</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Euseb d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Constantin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> lib 1. c. 22, 25. Raynolds Con∣ference with Hart. cap 8 divis 4. pag. 503.</NOTE> in Heaven, with this inscription, <HI>in hoc vinces. Wonderfull providences</HI> which bring any <HI>healing</HI> to discomposed and dilacerated Nations, are as so many <HI>beames of the Sun of righteousnes,</HI> who as Lord of all Creatures orders them all for his Churches good. The <HI>Wheels</HI> in <HI>Ezekiels</HI> Vision of living. Crea∣tures, whereby I understand the various and perplexed revolutions of all affairs in the World, were <HI>full of Eyes,</HI> noteing the guid∣ance <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezek. 1. 16, 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></NOTE> of Divine wisdome ordering them all to the welfare of his Church and People.</P>
<P N="3">3. Any speciall <HI>servants and officers</HI> of his whom he commissionateth and sendeth forth for the good of his people, whether the <HI>Angels of Heaven,</HI> as we read of an <HI>healing Angel, Joh.</HI> 5. 4. Or the <HI>Angels of the Church</HI> to whom belongeth the dispensation of <HI>wholsome</HI> and healing Doctrines, 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 6. 3. <HI>Tit.</HI> 2. 1. To open the eyes, and to turne them from darknes to light, <HI>Act.</HI> 26. 18. Or any other renowned instruments and mes∣sengers of help and comfort to an afflicted people. These are, if I may pursue the <HI>Meta∣phor,</HI>
<PB N="20" REF="15"/>
the <HI>Apothecaries,</HI> to weigh out, mix and temper and prepare the drugs according to the direction of Christ, which the Apo∣stle expresseth by the word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>Rightly to divide the word,</HI> 2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 2: 15. And our Sa∣viour by <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>To give the due portion of meat,</HI> Luke 12. 42. which some <NOTE PLACE="marg">S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ckins de con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>iv. l. 1. cap. 23.</NOTE> would have to allude unto the custom of measuring out daily or monthly unto Ser∣vants their allowances of diet.</P>
<P N="4">4. His own <HI>holy Spirit,</HI> who in <HI>Tertullians</HI> expression is <HI>vicarius Christi,</HI> as the beam is <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Tertul: de prae∣scriptionibus.</HI> John 16: 15. Rom. 5: 5. Cant. 4: 16.</NOTE> of the Sun, who taketh from Christ, and <HI>sheweth</HI> unto us; making report to the Souls of beleevers of the favor of Christ un∣to them, <HI>sheading abroad</HI> his love into their hearts, <HI>blowing</HI> upon his Garden, that the spices thereof may flow forth, as a <HI>Witness,</HI> a Seal, an Earnest, a Seed, bringing Christ and all his healing graces and comforts unto the Souls of his Servants, in their sins and sorrows to revive them.</P>
<P N="5">5. Here is the Subject of this healing; where observe. 1. The gracious and speci∣all <HI>compellation,</HI> the Lord speaks <HI>by name</HI> to his sick and sorrowfull servants, with a pe∣culiar favour as to his own sheep, <HI>John</HI> 10: 3. keeps a <HI>matricula</HI> and publick Register wherein t heir names are enroled, <HI>Mal.</HI> 3: 16. <HI>Psal.</HI> 87: 4-6. They are <HI>engrauen</HI> on the 
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
breast of our High Priest, <HI>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d.</HI> 28: 9. He takes exact notice of their wants, their com∣plaints, their tears, their desires, and shines in with <HI>particular comfort</HI> and healing up∣on them; so to <HI>Mary, John</HI> 20: 16. So to the <HI>Woman</HI> of <HI>Syrophaenicia, O woman great is thy Faith, be it unto thee as thou wilt,</HI> Mar. 15: 28. So to <HI>Peter,</HI> go tell his Disciples <HI>and Peter,</HI> poor mourning <HI>Peter,</HI> comfort him by name, <HI>Mark</HI> 16: 7.</P>
<P N="2">2. The immediate preparation and pro∣per <HI>disposition</HI> unto healing, to fear Gods name. There is a double vertue of Christ towards men.</P>
<P N="1">1. A <HI>Quickning</HI> vertue, and the Subjects of this vertue are those who are dead in Trespasses and Sins, <HI>Eph.</HI> 2. 1, 5.</P>
<P N="2">2. An <HI>healing vertue</HI> towards those who though they <HI>be alive,</HI> are yet in a <HI>weak,</HI> wounded, languishing condition, looking out after help and recovery. No such way for a sick and wounded nation to be <HI>healed as to fear Gods name,</HI> see <HI>Solomons</HI> Prayer to this parpose, 1 <HI>Reg.</HI> 8. 33-39. and the Lords gra∣cious <HI>answer</HI> unto that payer, 2 <HI>Chron</HI> 7. 13, 14. <HI>If my people that are called by my name shall humble themselves, and pray, and seek my face, and turn from their wicked ways; then will I hear from Heaven, and will forgive their sin, and will heale their Land.</HI> They are <HI>his</HI> 
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
<HI>people,</HI> his <HI>Sons,</HI> his <HI>Jewels,</HI> they call upon him, mourn towards him, turn to him, seek his face, they sink under the burden of cor∣ruptions, they cry out under the <HI>buffets</HI> of Satan, under the ravishments of temptation, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 7. 23. 2 Cor. 12. 7, 8.</NOTE> they pine away under the Judgments of God, they know not what to do but to look <NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Chro. 20. 12.</NOTE> up unto him: How can the bowels of an heavenly Father but yearne over a sick, a mourning, a weeping, a praying, a returning child. See <HI>Ephraim</HI> bemoaning himself, turn∣ing, repenting, smiteing upon his Thigh, and the Lord presently relenting over him, and resolving to have mercy upon him, <HI>Ier.</HI> 31. 18, 19, 20. <HI>Is Ephraim my dear Son? is he a pleasant child? for since I spake against him, I do carnestly remember him still; My bowels are troubled for him, I will surely have mercy upon him saith the Lord.</HI> It is not murmuring and repineing in our afflictions, bit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ing the stone which hath hurt us, breaking out into <HI>com∣plaints</HI> and revengeful <HI>animosities</HI> against one another, <HI>fretting our</HI> selves, <HI>cursing our King</HI> and our God, as the Prophet speaks, <HI>Isai.</HI> 8. 21. <HI>Gnawing our Tongues,</HI> and refuseing to repent, <HI>Rev.</HI> 16: 9-11. that is the way to healing. To be humbled, to accept <HI>of the punishment of our sins, to bear the indignation</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Levit. 26, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>1. Micah 7. 9.</NOTE> <HI>of the Lord,</HI> to seek his sace, to fear his name, to <HI>convert</HI> unto him, this only is the way to healing, <HI>Isai.</HI> 6: 10.</P>
<P N="6"><PB N="23" REF="16"/>
6. We should here proceed to consider the <HI>effects</HI> and consequences of this healing, which I must only name, and no more.</P>
<P N="1">1. <HI>Going forth,</HI> Leaping, Exulting, pre∣pared with joy and vigour, with courage and enlargement of Heart, unto duty and ser∣vice, as John, Christs forerunner is said to <HI>make ready apeople prepared for the Lord, Luk.</HI> 1: 17. It noteth that <HI>Spiritual Joy and Peace,</HI> which is the strength of Gods Servants in duty, when he shines with Light and Healing upon them. <HI>Healing and Holiness</HI> is a <HI>foun∣dation of Joy, Psal.</HI> 33: 1. 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 1: 12. and Joy back again a <HI>principle</HI> and preparation <HI>unto Holiness, The joy of the Lord is our strength, Nehem.</HI> 8: 13. The Servants of the Lord, the <HI>trees of righteousness,</HI> are ever so much the fuller of <HI>fruit,</HI> as they are of <HI>comfort,</HI> the more the <HI>Sun</HI> of Righteousness with his Light and influence doth <HI>shine</HI> upon them, the more they abound in duty and service.</P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>Growing up,</HI> in light, in st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ture, in strength, in knowledge, in grace, to more and more perfection, the <HI>most healthy</HI> are the <HI>most thriving</HI> christians. As many times when persons are recovered out of a fit of sicknes they visibly shoot up, and grow more in a few months then in some years before. So is it with Gods servants, when they have been delivered from any sore Temptation, like
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
<HI>Antaens</HI> they gain by their falls, when they are no more Children, when they cease to be weake, then they grow. <HI>Eph.</HI> 4. 14. 15.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>Victory and security</HI> against their proudest Enemies, whom the God of peace will <HI>tread down</HI> under the feet of his servants, as <HI>Joshua</HI> made his Captains to <HI>tread</HI> on the necks of the Kings of <HI>Canaan, Luk. 10. 19. Rom. 16. 20. Jos. 10. 24. Even for the bruized Reed,</HI> and for the <HI>Smoaking Flax</HI> will the Lord bring forth <HI>judgment unto victory. Matth.</HI> 12. 20.</P>
<P>Now from these many <HI>Metaphors</HI> seting forth Christ unto us, by whose <HI>light</HI> our blindnes is cured, by whose <HI>righteousnes</HI> our guilt is covered, by whose <HI>wings</HI> our cor∣ruptions are healed, and we enabled to <HI>go forth</HI> with Joy, to <HI>grow up</HI> in duty, to <HI>tread downe</HI> our Enemies, we learn,</P>
<P N="1">1. The <HI>freeness</HI> of his grace, nothing on Earth can deserve the shining of the Sun, nothing in us can deserve the grace of Christ, it shines most <HI>freely,</HI> without preceding merit, without consequent re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ibution, who <HI>bath first given to him, and it shall be recom∣penced to him again, Rom.</HI> 11. 35.</P>
<P N="2">2. The <HI>fulness</HI> of his Grace, he is a Sun. If we want <HI>wisedome</HI> there are Treasures in him, <HI>Col.</HI> 2. 3. If <HI>Spirit,</HI> it is without measure in him, <HI>Joh.</HI> 3. 34. If any spirituall
<PB N="25" REF="17"/>
<HI>Grace or Gift,</HI> there is unsearchable riches, an inexhausted Fountain in him, <HI>Ephes.</HI> 3. 8. <HI>Col.</HI> 1. 19. <HI>Zach.</HI> 13. 1. And he hath it all as a <HI>Magazin</HI> and <HI>Officer</HI> for the <HI>supply of his servants.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. The communion and dependance of the Church upon this his <HI>fulness:</HI> our <HI>light,</HI> our <HI>righteousness,</HI> our <HI>grace,</HI> our <HI>comfort,</HI> come from the influence, and depend upon the presence of Christ with us. The House doth not receive a stock of <HI>light</HI> to stay in it, though the Sun were gone, but hath it by immediate dependance on the light of the Sun: So every measure of <HI>Grace</HI> in us de∣pendeth in <HI>esse &amp; operari</HI> upon the influence, concurse, and presence of Christ by his Spirit with us. Every good work of ours hath its <HI>beginning, continuance,</HI> and <HI>consum∣mation</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Hierom. ad Ctesiphontem adversus Pela∣gianos.</NOTE> in him. <HI>Non mihi sufficit quod semel donavit, nisi semper donaverit,</HI> saith <HI>Jerome.</HI> He that <HI>begins, perfects, Phil.</HI> 1. 6. gives <HI>will and work, Phil.</HI> 2. 13. <HI>Heart and way, Jere.</HI> 32. 39. is the <HI>Author</HI> and the <HI>Finisher, Heb.</HI> 12. 2. Without him we can do nothing, in all things we must <HI>grow up in him, Joh.</HI> 15. 5. <HI>Ephes.</HI> 4. 15. <HI>From him is all our fruit found, Hos.</HI> 14. 8. We must pray with <HI>David, Take not away thine holy Spirit from me, Psal.</HI> 51. 11. We must take heed least by our quenching or grieving of him, we provoke him to with∣draw himself.</P>
<P N="4"><PB N="26" REF="18"/>
4. The conjunction between the <HI>Righte∣ousness</HI> of <HI>Christ</HI> and his <HI>healing;</HI> where he <HI>re∣ceives into grace,</HI> he <HI>takes away iniquity,</HI> and healeth backsliding, <HI>Hos.</HI> 14. 2, 4. He came not onely to <HI>pardon sin,</HI> but to <HI>destroy it,</HI> 1. <HI>John</HI> 3. 8. His <HI>Mercy</HI> is never without his <HI>Grace,</HI> his <HI>Offices</HI> go together, his <HI>Sacrifice</HI> and his <HI>Scepter</HI> cannot be divided. This is one of the greatest comforts that a believer hath, that at length <HI>his lusts shall be consumed.</HI> Even Heaven it self would not be a place of glory, if a man were to carry his sin along with him thither.</P>
<P>I have thus done with the General and Theological Tractation of the words: I now proceed very briefly unto such an Applica∣tion of them, as may come closer, and be more seasonable and suteable to this Honor∣able Solemnitie.</P>
<P>That this great <HI>Council</HI> and <HI>Colledge of Physitians</HI> hath a dangerously <HI>sick Patient</HI> to look after, <HI>Three Nations,</HI> and the <HI>Church of God</HI> in them, like the man between <HI>Jerusa∣lem</HI> and <HI>Jericho,</HI> wounded and hal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> dead, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 10. 30.</NOTE> we have had these many years the best, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> rather worst assurance that may be, by feel∣ing the sickness; so that there need be n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> further proof of it. We have seen and fel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> with sorrow and amazement, the <HI>honor</HI> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
the <HI>Parliaments</HI> of <HI>England</HI> shamefully as∣saulted, <HI>Princes</HI> bleeding out their Souls, <HI>sojourning in Mesech, and in the Tents of Kedar; Peers</HI> and <HI>Patriots</HI> secluded from <NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 120. 5.</NOTE> their Honorable and Rightful Trust; the <HI>great Council</HI> of the <HI>Nation</HI> sesquidimiated; a learned and faithful <HI>Ministry</HI> reproached, ready to be sacrificed, brought to the brow of the precipice; Ordinances decried, Er∣rors, and Heresies cumulated, the <HI>Publick worship</HI> of God interrupted, the <HI>Assemblies</HI> of his people on his own day, profanely af∣fronted by <HI>Mechanicks,</HI> working their ordi∣nary works in our <HI>Churches</HI> and <HI>Pulpits:</HI> We have seen and felt <HI>our Laws</HI> and our <HI>Founda∣tions</HI> threatned, our <HI>Ships</HI> broken, our <HI>Trade</HI> obstructed, our <HI>Treasures</HI> exhausted, our <HI>Merchants</HI> discouraged, our <HI>Religion</HI> crum∣bled, our <HI>Church-Congregations</HI> shamed and defiled with the impure and obscene intrusion of naked persons, cloathed with nothing but dung and impudence. We have heard of families raised upon the ruines of others, and of families ruined by perjurious crimina∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ons. Indeed, we have seen and heard of more <HI>evils</HI> and <HI>confusions,</HI> then the hour of a Sermon, or the length of an <HI>History</HI> can well enumerate. If sins, if sorrows, if shame, if fear, if dangers, if frenzies, if quakings, if convulsions, if breach upon breach, if
<PB N="28" REF="19"/>
change upon change, if divided mindes, if dis-joynted hearts, if inconsistent interests, if incoherent designs, if vicissitudes of <HI>Go∣vernment</HI> as mutable as the courses of the <HI>Moon,</HI> if Altar against Altar, Doctrine a∣gainst Doctrine, Worship against Worship, <HI>Post by post, threshold by threshold,</HI> be symptoms of a sick body; certainly this <HI>great Colledge</HI> of <HI>Physitians</HI> hath a very sick patient to look <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezek. 43. 8.</NOTE> after.</P>
<P>Nay, which is much to be bewailed, even they who fear the name of the Lord one∣very hand, of every perswasion, if they will impartially review their own ways, will finde that by their mutual jealousies, breaches, disaffections, distances, animosities, <HI>affecta∣tions</HI> of preheminence and domination, <HI>pursu∣ance</HI> of interests, preserving of stations and new raised estates; and many other the like miscarriages have contributed a great share to the sicknesses and sorrows of the <HI>common body,</HI> and caused the name of God, and the honor of Religion to be evil spoken of.</P>
<P>Your proper work, <HI>Right Honorable Pa∣triots,</HI> is to be <HI>Healers</HI> (so <HI>Rulers</HI> are call<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, <HI>Isai.</HI> 3. 7.) <HI>Healers</HI> to these three Nations. <HI>We have looked long for peace, and there came no good; and for the time of healing, and be∣hold</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Jer. 14. 19.</NOTE> <HI>trouble.</HI> If the Lord have reserved you for such a time, for such a work as this, to
<PB N="29" REF="19"/>
be <HI>eyes to the blinde, feet to the lame, Fathers to the poor, as one that comforteth the Mourners,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Job. 29. 15, 16. 25</NOTE> as <HI>Job</HI> speaks, the <HI>ear</HI> that hears you shall bless you, the <HI>eye</HI> that sees you, shall bear witness to you. <HI>It shall be written for the gene∣ration to come, and the people which shall be cre∣ated,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 102. 18.</NOTE> <HI>shall praise the Lord for you.</HI> The Lord shall make you the <HI>head,</HI> and not the <HI>tail,</HI> you shall be above onely, and not beneath, <HI>Deut.</HI> 2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>. 13. It is a weightie enterprise; the cure difficult, the disease complicate, great skill and wisdom, great Love and Caution, great Patience and tenderness is required unto it. There may be danger of miscarri∣age by clashing of Councils, by partialitie of Interests, by mis-judging of Cases, by the acrimonie of Purgatiyes, by the heighth of Cordials, by inequalitie and dispropor∣tionate Applications, by minding the parts asunder, as divided from the whole.</P>
<P>O come with none but <HI>healing Resolutions,</HI> with none but <HI>closing</HI> and <HI>uniting affections;</HI> let one <HI>Heart,</HI> one <HI>Soul,</HI> one <HI>End,</HI> one <HI>Spirit,</HI> animate your whole <HI>Body.</HI> If this precious ointment of <HI>unity</HI> and <HI>peace</HI> be first upon you i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> will fall down to the skirts of the Nation. The <HI>Patients</HI> will not fall out, if the <HI>Physicians</HI> be agreed.</P>
<P>Think with your selves, that you hear the <HI>life</HI> and <HI>being,</HI> the <HI>ancient honor</HI> and <HI>renown</HI>
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
of these <HI>Nations,</HI> call aloud unto you for <HI>Healing. England</HI> sometimes a <HI>terror</HI> to her proudest enemies, a <HI>ballance</HI> to all the Inter∣ests of <HI>Christendom,</HI> now a supplicant to her own Children to keep her alive.</P>
<P>Think that you hear the concurrent cry of the <HI>Protestant Churches,</HI> which are greatly concerned in our <HI>Weal,</HI> or wo, (the <HI>Protestant Religion,</HI> being the <HI>Interest of England,</HI> as the Duke of <HI>Rhoan</HI> hath gravely observed) calling upon you to <HI>heal</HI> us, that they may be whole.</P>
<P>Think that you hear the importunities of all the people of the Land, and all orders therein call unto you for <HI>Healing. Princes</HI> and <HI>Peers</HI> long <HI>dethroned</HI> and <HI>eclipsed</HI> in their <HI>ho∣nor</HI> and <HI>splendor. Citizens</HI> long decayed in their <HI>trade</HI> and <HI>commerce. Countrey-men</HI> long exhausted with heavy <HI>expences</HI> upon <HI>narrow estates. Ministers</HI> long discouraged by <HI>swarms</HI> of dangerous and corrupt <HI>opinions,</HI> by that abundance of Atheism, Scepticism, Neu∣tralitie, Indifferencie, Profaneness, Contempt of <HI>Ordinances,</HI> which the looseness of these times, like an opened <HI>sluce,</HI> or a breach in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>bank,</HI> hath let in as a deluge upon the <HI>Church of God</HI> amongst us.</P>
<P>Think that you hear your <HI>own families,</HI> your <HI>wives,</HI> your <HI>children, Et natos natorum, &amp; qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣nascuntur ab illis,</HI> the generations yet unborn,
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
calling unto you to lay up <HI>Healing</HI> for them, and like the man of <HI>Macedonia</HI> to the Apostle, saying, <HI>Come and help us.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts 16. 9.</NOTE></P>
<P>And if you will give me leave to tell you where you must begin; you must begin at this <HI>Sun of Righteousness;</HI> you must be <HI>wings, beams, Angels, Emanations</HI> from him, if you will bring <HI>help and healing</HI> to his people. From him all your <HI>Wisdom</HI> and <HI>Counsil,</HI> all your <HI>Love</HI> and <HI>Zeal,</HI> all your <HI>Fidelity</HI> and <HI>Sufficiency</HI> is derived. <HI>We are not sufficient of our selves to think any thing as of our selves; but our sufficiency is of God,</HI> who alone makes able <HI>Counsellors</HI> in the State, as well as Mini∣sters in the Church.</P>
<P>And as he is the <HI>Father</HI> of all your <HI>Light</HI> and <HI>Counsel;</HI> so by <HI>his blessing alone,</HI> they operate. Without him <HI>you can do nothing:</HI> As man liveth <HI>not by Bread alone,</HI> so he re∣covereth <HI>not by Physick alone, but by every word which proceedeth out of the mouth of God.</HI> He is <HI>the Lord that healeth us, Exod.</HI> 15. 26. He that gave <HI>his Disciples power</HI> to cure dis∣eases, <HI>Luke</HI> 9. 1. must do the same for you, if you be our <HI>healers:</HI> And therefore you must begin at him, and say as the <HI>Prophet</HI> did, <HI>Heal me, O Lord, and I shall be healed; save me, and I shall be saved, for thou art my praise,</HI> Jer. 17. 14.</P>
<P>And as you have his <HI>sufficiency</HI> to enable
<PB N="32" REF="21"/>
you, and his <HI>blessing</HI> to give success unto you, so you have him as a <HI>great Exemplar</HI> to lead and teach you, whom you may imitate in this great work; for he went about teaching and healing, <HI>Matth.</HI> 4. 23. And he <HI>healed,</HI></P>
<P N="1">1. <HI>Freely,</HI> and so he commanded his Dis∣ciples to heal, <HI>Matth.</HI> 10. 8. He did not in∣rich himself by any of his cures and miracles; by how much the less of <HI>reward,</HI> by so much the more of <HI>honor,</HI> for a <HI>free cure:</HI> Not but that it is worthie the bountie of a <HI>Parliament</HI> to acknowledge great and noble <HI>services,</HI> with proportionable returns of favor; but the less <HI>internal</HI> and <HI>domestical</HI> those returns are, they will appear the <HI>more noble. Tu ci∣vem patremque geras tu consule cunct is: No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> tibi, nec tua te moveant, sed publica damna</HI> Claudian.</P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>Bountifully,</HI> he was at cost and charges to heal others, <HI>his blood was our balsome;</HI> he was content to be <HI>smitten, that we might be healed, Isai.</HI> 53. 5. He looked not on his own things, but on <HI>the things of others, Phil.</HI> 2. 4, 5. <HI>He gave his life for his sheep, John</HI> 10. 11, A good man is willing <HI>to spend and to be spent,</HI> for the good of those unto whose service he is devoted, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 12. 15. <HI>Nec sibi, sed toti genitum, se credere mundo.</HI> It is recorded for the honor of <HI>Nehemiah,</HI> that though former Governors had been chargable to the people,
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
yet he and his brethren <HI>did not eate the bread of the Governor, Nehem.</HI> 5. 14, 15. and of <HI>He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er</HI> that she would <HI>venture perishing</HI> for the service of her people. <HI>Esther</HI> 4: 16.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>Universally,</HI> without expectation, he <HI>healed all</HI> that came to him for healing, <HI>Matth.</HI> 12. 25. <HI>Luke</HI> 4. 40. &amp; 6. 19. He is an ill <HI>Physician</HI> that will cure his patient of a sore Finger, and use no means against his <HI>Feaver</HI> or <HI>Consumption,</HI> for an <HI>akeing heart,</HI> or a <HI>bruised head.</HI> We may say of <HI>England,</HI> is the Prophet of his people, <HI>Isai.</HI> 1. 5, 6. That our <HI>sickness is from head to foot;</HI> some parts sick with <HI>sorrow</HI> and <HI>sufferings,</HI> others sick with <HI>sin</HI> and <HI>wickedness:</HI> Let <HI>your endea∣vors</HI> of <HI>cure</HI> be impartial. Any one part un∣healed will create pain and danger to the whole: And as you may not neglect any <HI>integral,</HI> so let <HI>your principal care</HI> be for the <HI>Vital</HI> and <HI>Architectonical parts,</HI> to reduce them unto <HI>health</HI> and <HI>safety.</HI> But let <HI>your pro∣vidence</HI> extend to all; the least and lowest <HI>Member</HI> hath a <HI>right</HI> in the <HI>common Soul,</HI> in the <HI>good</HI> of the whole. <HI>Render to all their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es, tribute, custom, fear, honor,</HI> are due to <NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 13. 7.</NOTE> some; <HI>love, libertie, propertie, safetie, pro∣tection, peace,</HI> are due to others. Ballance all <HI>interests</HI> with so equal and righteous a <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ize,</HI> that <HI>Rulers</HI> may govern a <HI>free people,</HI> and the people obey <HI>Illustrious</HI> and <HI>Noble</HI>
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
<HI>Governors;</HI> that the <HI>people</HI> may be comforted by the <HI>Jusstice</HI> and <HI>Clemency</HI> of their <HI>Princes,</HI> and <HI>Princes</HI> honored by the <HI>loyaltie</HI> and <HI>obedi∣ence</HI> of their people: That <HI>Love</HI> may be the <HI>Soul</HI> of the <HI>Body Politick,</HI> the <HI>Bond,</HI> the <HI>Joynt,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Col. 3. 15. Eph. 4 15, 16.</NOTE> the <HI>Sinew</HI> that holds together all the <HI>Members</HI> in the <HI>Unitie,</HI> and for the good of the whole.</P>
<P N="4">4. Meekly, humbly, compassionately, there is a <HI>fained meekness</HI> as that of <HI>Absolom</HI> and <HI>Otho, omnia serviliter pro Imperio,</HI> but Christ was <HI>meek and lowly in heart,</HI> Math. 11. 29. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Tacit. Hist.</NOTE> We read of the <HI>gentleness of Christ,</HI> 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 10: 1. So Christ <HI>taught</HI> men, <HI>as they were able to hear,</HI> Mark 4. 33. So he <HI>healed them,</HI> took the <HI>Lambs</HI> into his bosome, and gently lead the rest, <HI>Isai.</HI> 40. 11. Considers our mould, <HI>Psal.</HI> 103. 14. Will not break <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>bruised reed, Math.</HI> 12. 20. <HI>Stays</HI> with a poo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> blinde begger in the way, <HI>Mark</HI> 10. 49. 5<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>. And thus he requireth <HI>us to heale</HI> and resto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> disjointed Members with a spirit of meek∣ness, <HI>Gal.</HI> 6. 1. <HI>Phil.</HI> 4 5. Shew all <HI>possible tenderness</HI> and indulgence towards the infi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣mities, especially the <HI>consciences</HI> of men <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> humble and sober, of quiet and peaceab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Spirits, the <HI>strong</HI> are taught to bear the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣firmities of the weak, <HI>Rom.</HI> 15. 1. Be <HI>care<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> to secure and settle</HI> the <HI>Fundamentals,</HI> the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> tals</HI> and <HI>Essentials</HI> of Doctrine, Worsh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
and Dutie, that you may be sure of sound and <HI>Orthodox Ministers,</HI> to go in and cut be∣fore the <HI>flock;</HI> and if in <HI>smaller</HI> and <HI>more pro∣blematical things,</HI> men cannot be all of one minde, (as we never shall have perfection of Judgment till we come to Heaven) <HI>Let not the strong despise the weak,</HI> nor the <HI>weak judge the strong:</HI> Whom <HI>God</HI> receives into his favor, let not us shut out of ours, <HI>Rom.</HI> 14. 3.</P>
<P N="5">5. <HI>Perfectly,</HI> As many as touched him in order unto <HI>healing,</HI> were <HI>perfectly cured, Matth.</HI> 14. 36. Endeavor as much as is pos∣sible, such a <HI>total oblivion</HI> and <HI>obliteration</HI> of our sad divisions, and the distempers arisen there-from, that no <HI>dregs</HI> of the disease, no <HI>sears</HI> of the wound may remain; but that all the <HI>Members</HI> may coalesce into a perfect <HI>unitie</HI> and <HI>frat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rnitie</HI> again.</P>
<P>And as this must be your first care to be∣gin at the <HI>Sun of Righteousness,</HI> and to imitate him; so you must be careful of the <HI>Two wings</HI> which are the <HI>Vehicula</HI> of <HI>Healing,</HI> be sure that the <HI>Wings</HI> of the <HI>Sun of Righte∣ousness</HI> do carry him into all places of the Land.</P>
<P N="1">1. The <HI>Wing of Light, sound Doctrine, pure Ordinances.</HI> The more the people agree in <HI>divine truths,</HI> the more they will be dis∣posed for <HI>moral</HI> and for <HI>civil unity. Religion</HI>
<PB N="36" REF="23"/>
is a cementing thing, <HI>Lactantius</HI> and <HI>Jerome</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Lactant Instit. lib.</HI> 4. <HI>cap.</HI> 28. <HI>Hieron. in</HI> A∣mos 9.</NOTE> derive it a <HI>Religando, Quòd ea quasi in fas∣cem vincti sumus.</HI> Discourage and discounte∣nance, dangerous and false doctrines, bear up, speak comfortably to an able, Orthodox, Faithful and Learned Ministrie; procure <HI>brotherly reconciliation</HI> amongst men of <HI>sober mindes,</HI> but <HI>different judgments:</HI> The breaches I hope are not so wide, but that if animosi∣ties and prejudices were removed, they might by amicable and fraternal debates be closed up again.</P>
<P N="2">2. The <HI>Wing of Righteousness,</HI> able, faith∣ful, <HI>Religious Judges</HI> and <HI>Magistrates,</HI> whole∣some, healing, and <HI>Righteous Laws,</HI> are the <HI>Vehicula</HI> of <HI>Justice,</HI> by the sanctitie and pru∣dence of these, <HI>your healing</HI> will shed it self abroad into all parts of the Land.</P>
<P>In one word, <HI>Go forth,</HI> have your eyes i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> in every place, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: <NOTE PLACE="marg">Xenophon By∣rop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d.</NOTE> Let the <HI>Wheels</HI> of <HI>your Pro∣vidence</HI> have eies on them. <HI>Grow up</HI> into splendor and perfection, and restore the col∣lapsed <HI>honor</HI> of this <HI>august Council</HI> in all the parts of it: <HI>Tread down wickedness,</HI> make stronger Laws then ever against <HI>impietie</HI> and <HI>profaneness,</HI> against <HI>iniquity</HI> and <HI>unrighteous∣ness. Keep Christ</HI> and his presence; keep <HI>godliness</HI> and the fear of his <HI>Name</HI> in the mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st of the Land: Endeavor not a meere
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
<HI>formal and superficial,</HI> but a <HI>substantial</HI> and <HI>spiritual Reformation,</HI> and then assuredly the Lord will honor you, and make you his <HI>In∣struments</HI> of performing this gracious pro∣mise, <HI>Unto you that fear my Name, shall the Sun of Righteousness arise with healing in his Wings;</HI> and <HI>these wings</HI> shall carry <HI>your names</HI> and <HI>memories</HI> with splendor and renown unto all succeeding ages. <HI>For they that honor him, the Lord will honor.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 2. 30.</NOTE></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

