<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Mr. Pryn's good old cause stated and stunted 10 years ago, or, A most dangerous designe in mistating the good by mistaking the bad old cause clearly extricated and offered to the Parliament, the General Council of Officer's, the good people's and army's immediate consideration.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Rogers, John, 1627-1665?</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A57539</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing R1812</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R34004</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13657983</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13657983</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">101052</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A57539)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101052)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1045:21)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Mr. Pryn's good old cause stated and stunted 10 years ago, or, A most dangerous designe in mistating the good by mistaking the bad old cause clearly extricated and offered to the Parliament, the General Council of Officer's, the good people's and army's immediate consideration.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Rogers, John, 1627-1665?</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 20 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by J.C. for L. Chapman,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1659.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Signed at end: I.R.</NOTE><NOTE>Attributed to John Rogers by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</NOTE><NOTE>Numerous errors in paging.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Prynne, William, 1600-1669. --  Good old cause.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A57539">
<STC T="W">R1812</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13657983</BIBNO>
<VID>101052</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Mr. <HI>PRYN</HI>'S Good Old Cause Stated and <HI>Stunted</HI> 10. years ago. Or, A most dangerous DESIGNE, In <HI>Mistating</HI> the <HI>GOOD,</HI> By <HI>Mistaking</HI> the <HI>BAD Old Cause</HI>; Clearly Extricated and offered to the Parlia∣ment, the General Council of <HI>Officer</HI>'s, the Good People's and <HI>Army</HI>'s imme∣diate Consideration.</P>
<Q><BIBL>Prov. 1.17.</BIBL>
<P><HI>Surely in vain the Net is spread in the sight of any bird.</HI>Hebr. <HI>begnene Col bagnal Canaph,</HI> in the eyes of every Winged one; or, Vulg. Lat. <HI>ante oculos pen∣natorum,</HI> before them that have Wings.</P></Q>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>J. C.</HI> for <HI>L. Chapman,</HI> 1659.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Mr. <HI>Prin's</HI> Good Old Cause Stated, and <HI>Stunted,</HI> 10 year ago.</HEAD>
<P>MR. <HI>PRINS</HI> Parts I much respect, (for Learning I love as my life) yet his Principles and Spirit I must reject, which render him (<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh rib</HI>) litigi∣ous. It is a true Rule i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Nature, that (<HI>omne invalidum est Natu∣ra querulum</HI>) a thing weak and unsound is ever quarrelsome: yet for that a little m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tter, (as things now are) even a <HI>Wisp</HI> of <HI>Straw</HI> may kindle a great <HI>Conflagration</HI>; I would lend my hand (with∣out any need I hope of other Art or Engine) to put out THIS, if it m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y but be accepted.</P>
<P>What <HI>Silenus</HI> once said of an evil man, I may as fitly apply to this <HI>evil m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tter</HI> of Mr. <HI>PRINS</HI> PAMPHLET; <HI>That it had been best of all to have never been born; or next to that, not to live at all, or to dye as soon as may be:</HI> and I suppose the <HI>Gentle∣man</HI> (if he be not like the <HI>Bustard</HI> in a <HI>Fallow,</HI> that cannot raise it self (<HI>sine Viturbinis</HI>) without the help of a <HI>Whirlwind</HI>) will be contented to let his SHEET pass for a WINDING-SHEET; seeing it is so well stitched and seamed along the side, and knotted at the head, with the flourishing Title of <HI>The Good Old Cause stated,</HI> &amp;c. although the matter contained therein is but the <HI>Ghost</HI> or unsavory <HI>Corps</HI> of that <HI>Cause,</HI> which hath been sentenced to death, and buried long ago; but is now anew conjured up to <HI>haunt</HI> us (we hope not to <HI>hurt</HI> us) with.</P>
<P>The Preface (out of D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <HI>Bensons</HI> Serm. in 4<SUP>o</SUP>. on <HI>Hos.</HI> 7.7· p. 84 where it is better applyed) is the <HI>Proper Face</HI> of them who do use the u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>most of their <HI>Black Art</HI> in the Nation, to raise up those evil <HI>Spirits</HI> once more (if the Lord prevent not) which have before put us into the highest Broyls. But for all thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> his new-facing of the <HI>Old Garment</HI> (Rotten as durt, re∣jected long agone, for a Thread-bare, Base, and <HI>beggerly Thing,</HI> that would not hide our <HI>Nakedness,</HI> much less honour our <HI>Nation,</HI> or satisfie the best affected and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oundest <HI>Integrals</HI> of it)
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
I say, for all this it doth appear, that they are <HI>wily Gib<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o∣nit<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</HI> who by their wonted <HI>Stratagems</HI> (in City and Country, in <HI>Parliament</HI> and <HI>People</HI>) had now anew laid the <HI>Plot</HI> appa∣rently, to beguile the Commonwealth (and our <HI>Israel</HI> in it:) yea, that they might the better effect it, they have brought out their mouldy <HI>Bread,</HI> Filthy, Nasty, Musty Food, in their <HI>late Books</HI> and <HI>Pamphlets</HI>) yea, their <HI>Old Shooes</HI> and <HI>Garments</HI> too, to delude the poor plain people with, in the sinister and <HI>Sophisti∣cated Reports,</HI> which they make of the <HI>Good Old Cause,</HI> prepa∣red for those <HI>palats</HI> that like that <HI>bread</HI> best, that is most <HI>moul∣dy</HI> and worm-eaten: but if Mr. <HI>PRIN</HI> will yet maintain his <HI>Preface</HI> as his <HI>fancy</HI> applies it, let him but remember with it, that the <HI>Gibeonites</HI> were, for <HI>peace</HI>; came in <HI>peace,</HI> and submit∣ted themselves chearfully to <HI>Jehovah</HI> (and his <HI>Joshu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>) in the Government of the <HI>Commonwealth,</HI> as God's Institution; and then the Stone that he hath thrown at our <HI>Roch,</HI> (which is not as their <HI>Rock, Deut.</HI> 32.31.) will certainly Rebound upon his own <HI>Pate,</HI> and pain him more then us. But to the matter.</P>
<P>The Project or Design that is on foot to conjure up those <HI>Malignant Spirits</HI> again in the <HI>Nation</HI> (that have been so long, and (by the good hand of <HI>Jehovah</HI>) so wonderfully and hap∣pily allayed) shews it self in six several <HI>parts,</HI> by this one <HI>Pa∣per</HI> dispersed abroad in Mr. <HI>Prin's</HI> Name.</P>
<P N="1">I. His <HI>first designe,</HI> is to insinuate to the world, that our <HI>En∣glish Commonwealth-Government,</HI> is but a Conspiracy <HI>hatched</HI> and <HI>egged</HI> by the <HI>Jesuites</HI> and <HI>Romish Gibeonites</HI>; to use his own words in several places in that one <HI>Pamphlet,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> p. 1. <HI>This poli∣cy has for many years past b<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en pursued by Jesuites and other Gibeo∣nites of Rome—Whether this be not the present stratagem of some Instruments or Fraternity, under the disguise of their</HI> main∣taining <HI>the Good Old Cause</HI> (which in the margin he <HI>banks</HI> up with these words: <HI>If they mean by this Good Old Cause their new Commonwealth, it was begotten but in March,</HI> 1648.) No Rati∣onal Man can question what he means. The present Out∣cry, for the <HI>Good Old Cause,</HI> i. e. the <HI>Commonwealth-Government,</HI> declared and proclaimed in <HI>March</HI> 1648. he impeaches as the <HI>project</HI> of <HI>Jesuitick Instruments,</HI> Romish Gibeonites, or of that Fraternity; which he undertakes to demonstrate in the subsequence of his discourse. So p. 7, 8. <HI>It is the old way which wicked men, the old Gunpowder Traytors, have formerly troden; or
<PB N="18" REF="3"/>
finally, because at first set on foot and promoted, by certain crept in unawares into the Army and Nation from Jesuiticall Se∣minaries.</HI> Now what can be said more to render the <HI>Common-wealth</HI> most contemptible, odious, and Worthy of utter de∣struction? And that this <HI>Seed</HI> is not sown onely by Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> in the Nation, to male-content, ran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd incense the people, and Rank the Well-affected with the <HI>Jesuites</HI> and <HI>Papists,</HI> as their Pupils (that the people might beat out their <HI>Brains</HI> in the streets) see another <HI>Champion</HI> for this <HI>ill Old Cause</HI> mounted bravely, and more eminent in the Nation for the Ministry; one who not only <HI>England,</HI> but other <HI>Lands</HI> may be apt to credit, or take upon trust the <HI>Report</HI> that he makes; he has inlarged (what is here asserted) in his <HI>Book</HI> called a <HI>Key for Catholicks, (viz.</HI> Mr. <HI>Baxter</HI> of <HI>Kederminster</HI>) wherein he takes great pains to traduce and asperse the <HI>Common-wealth,</HI> and the most renowned <HI>Patriots</HI> of the Nation: it is a second <HI>Gangrena,</HI> worse then <HI>Edward</HI> hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Chap. 45. in the 36. <HI>detection</HI> of <HI>Papists</HI>; (which being too large to transcribe) I must referre to; as in p. 321, 322. <HI>To vindicate</HI> (saies he) <HI>the Protestants o∣p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nly before all the world, and to all posterity, from that fact,</HI> i. e. the ODIUM of KINGKILLING in <HI>England, which</HI> (he saith) <HI>was the JESUITES PLOT: it is most publickly known, that both houses of Parliament in their Protestation, ingaged themselves and the Nation to be true to the King.</HI> 2. <HI>Managed the War for K. and Parl.</HI> 3. <HI>Took the Covenant to be true to the King.</HI> So in p. 322. <HI>In that it was known that the Army was quite altered, not only by a new-modeling, but by an intestine Jesuiticall corrupting of multitudes of the Soldiery, before this odious fact</HI> (of King-kil∣ling) <HI>could be done.</HI> 7. <HI>And it is known the Iesuited part (that afterwards so many of them turn'd Levellers) drew into th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m the Anabaptists, Libertines, and other sects, upon a Conjunction of In∣terests; and by many sly pretences, especially tying all together by the predicated Liberty for all Religions,</HI> &amp;c. Who can read it without blushing and amazement! that such a Man as Mr. <HI>Bax∣ter</HI> (whom I have ever valued) should so little value himself or his Calling! Was there no war waged since that for K and Parliament? no Cause afoot for the People of God? or hath the Army and all been <HI>Jesuited</HI> since the New Model? and was that <HI>Act of Justi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> such an <HI>odious Fact</HI> in Mr. <HI>Baxter</HI>'s eyes? why then did he hide it all this while? But he will pay
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
it now it seems, for in p. 323. <HI>I do therefore leave it here to Po∣sterity, that it was utterly against the Mind and Thoughts of Pro∣testants, and of those they called Puritans, to put the King to death: and</HI> 12. <HI>evidences forementioned, are undeniable Arguments, that it was the work of Papists, Libertines, Vanists, and Anabaptists.</HI> So p. 355, 356. <HI>Really, if you take either Vanists or Levellers, who were the chief Agents, for Protestants, you may as well say Papists are Protestants.</HI> Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h abundance more of such abominable stuffe, as makes it not onely a <HI>Scandalum Magnum,</HI> but a SCANDALUM MAGNATUM, very unsavory, and unsuffer∣able for a Minister (that should be a <HI>Teacher</HI> of others) to abuse the dearest and highest WORTHIES of our Nation so, (seeing it is written, <HI>Exod.</HI> 22.28. <HI>Thou shalt not revile the Gods, nor curse the Rulers of the people</HI>) and this to the great Reproach of the <HI>Common-wealth,</HI> the Army, the <HI>Parliament,</HI> and well-affect∣ed People (or of all that are against the <HI>Bad Old Cause,</HI> and for the <HI>Good.</HI>) Can a higher spirit of Malignity appear in men? or is it probable they would presume so, if their expectations were not high? and with what confidence or credulity can this M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n affirm, that no <HI>Protestant</HI> had a hand in that <HI>Act of Justice?</HI> Was there not a Protestant of them all (above six score) ap∣pointed to sit upon him? or if he means no <HI>Presbyterian,</HI> and accounts none else for <HI>Protestants</HI>) yet it is a most strange in∣discretion, and thick emotion of passion, that impedes his eye from seeing the most of that judgement, and of the largest size and Character too, that fate in that Court. Or what proof can he produce to make good the charge of <HI>King-killing</HI> (much lesse (I presume) that it was of the <HI>Iesuites</HI> laying?) or if he cannot, how will he expiate and compensate for the injury, obloqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and publick <HI>Infamy?</HI> Could common sense or civility take this Liberty, but upon some design or other presupposed, able to indemnifie for all? Seeing the <HI>Parliaments</HI> Act was in open justice, but Jesui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es Act in <HI>Plots,</HI> and Clandestinely; yea, they indeed murther, but the <HI>Parliament</HI> executed judgemen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; they do it by inferiour hands, but the <HI>Parliament</HI> by superiour: they sneakingly and perfidiously, but the <HI>Parl.</HI> honourably and after Conquest; they do it for confusion and disorder, but the <HI>Parliament</HI> did it for peace and publick safety: They to destroy, but the <HI>Parliament</HI> to keep the good and ends of Government. So that with what forehead can any m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n (or malice it self)
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
suggest, that this was a thing laid by the <HI>Iesuites,</HI> but with an intent to write indeed after their copy, in as bloudy <HI>Chara∣cters,</HI> if he can? at least let us suspect i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, seeing Mr. <HI>Baxter</HI> saies, p. 341. <HI>I confesse, I think an ingenuous open Papist should have a great deal more gentle dealing from our Magistrates then these. For my own part, I must confesse, I feel a great deal of chari∣ty in my heart for a conscientious plain dealing Papist, and I would never be guilty o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cruelty or rigour to them.</HI> Thus far have these two <HI>Champions</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> op<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n faced, in this first <HI>Design</HI> of <HI>Fa∣thering</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he highe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI>Acts</HI> of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he <HI>Commonweal</HI> upon the Jesuites and that Fraternity: but let <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> judge, and the Lord de∣cide, <HI>who judgeth righteously,</HI> Psal.</P>
<P N="2">II. The second <HI>Design</HI> is, to p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssesse (if the People will but take a <HI>new edition</HI> of it) with this▪ that the <HI>Government</HI> by <HI>King,</HI> Lords, and Commons, is the Very <HI>Contignation</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rue State of the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI>; and that the <HI>Common-wealth Go∣vernment</HI> is but a new <HI>Oglio,</HI> Toads-stool, and not worth the naming, the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI>; in <HI>Pamphlet,</HI><NOTE PLACE="inter"><HI>Exact. Coll.</HI> Printed by Husbands.</NOTE> pag. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <HI>&amp;c.</HI> for this he quotes the <HI>Votes,</HI> Orders <HI>Ordinances,</HI> Remonstrances, and <HI>Declara∣rations</HI> of <HI>Lords</HI> and <HI>Commons</HI> in Par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iament (and because he will not hear, or own the Cause of <HI>Parliaments</HI> since, I shall deal with him out of them) all the <HI>Commissions</HI> of the Lord <HI>Generals</HI> of the <HI>Armies</HI>; and the <HI>Scotish Cove∣nant</HI>: but miserably misapplying them with <HI>Fallacious conse∣quences,</HI> and conclusions upon them, both as <HI>to the</HI> ORIGI∣NAL and MERIT of the Cause.</P>
<P N="1">1. He is very Remote from an Honest, Ingenuous, and Right stating the <HI>true Good Old Cause,</HI> in its ORIGINAL; when he sayes, <HI>p.</HI> 2. the first <HI>Original was the Kings coming into the Parliament,</HI> Jan. 4. 1641. <HI>to demand the five Members; and that upon this breach of priviledge, the Houses required the power of the Militia.</HI> True, this might ini<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iate that part of the <HI>quarrel</HI> with the King, (for breach of <HI>Parliament-Priviledges</HI>) but was this all? or all the Cause? With his leave, we finde (even in his own <HI>Book</HI> of <HI>Coll.</HI>) the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI> (for substance) asserted before that, and by <HI>both Houses</HI> of <HI>Parliament</HI> (which he might have seen wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hout <HI>Spectacles,</HI> had it pleased him:) <HI>For depriving the Bishops of Votes in Parliament: For abridging their usurped power: For the taking away all oppressions in matters of Religion;
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
For tendernesse to weak consciences; For the due excuting those good Laws made for the securing the</HI> LIBERTY <HI>of the subject.</HI> So on that fifteenth d. in the <HI>Remonstrance</HI> of the State of the <HI>Kingdom</HI>: Against <HI>Bishops, High</HI>-Commission-Courts, Prero∣gatives, forced Loans of Money, <HI>Injustice</HI>: and further, <HI>p.</HI> 20. <HI>for the better preservation of the Laws and LIBERTIES of the Kingdom: that all Illegal grievances and exactions be presented and punished,</HI> &amp;c. Also, that the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI> for our <HI>Liber∣ties Civil</HI> and <HI>Religious,</HI> was asserted before this <HI>Breach</HI> of <HI>Par∣liament-priviledge,</HI> may be seen by the <HI>King's</HI> own <HI>Reply</HI> too; Sayes he, <HI>The fears and jealousies which may make some impres∣sion in the mindes of our people, we will suppose may be of two sorts: Either for Religion, or Liberty, and their Civil Interest,</HI> &amp;c. Now, This—may easily obviate Mr. <HI>Prin</HI>'s <HI>fallaciam</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; first, for that this <HI>breach</HI> of <HI>Parliament-priviledge</HI> (by demanding <HI>the five Members</HI>) was not the <HI>onely Cause</HI> of the Contest (or of requiring the <HI>Militia</HI>) much lesse of the Warre between <HI>King and Parliament</HI>; (which he saith, ended in the <HI>mutual destruction of each other,</HI> pag. 2. l. 13, 14. But it is our mercy that it is no such matter; and that the <HI>Parlia∣ment</HI> did, and doth survive, do what they can that would not have it so) but withall, the <HI>Salui Populi,</HI> the <HI>Safety,</HI> and <HI>Liberty</HI> of the people (both in <HI>Spirituals</HI> and <HI>Civils</HI>) was the <HI>Cause</HI> of the Contest.</P>
<P N="2">2. That breach of <HI>Parliament</HI> was not the first <HI>Original</HI> (neither) of the differences betwixt the <HI>King</HI> and <HI>Parliament,</HI> which we find were very <HI>Wide</HI> and <HI>High</HI> before that: And all indeed upon the account of the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI> (as to sub∣stance, though indeed but an <HI>Embryo,</HI> unformed <HI>substance,</HI> to what it arose up to after.) But Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> gives the <HI>Go-by</HI> to all this, and puts in at another <HI>Port,</HI> or indeed <HI>part</HI> (and that mista∣kenly too) for the WHOLE; besides, 3<SUP>d</SUP>. even in that <HI>Decla∣ration</HI> he refers us to (pag. 38, 39, 40.) the <HI>Parliament</HI> for the Vindication of their worthy <HI>Members</HI>) do assert the <HI>Liberties</HI> and <HI>Rights</HI> of the people (before mentioned) as much as the <HI>Priviledges</HI> of <HI>Parliament.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. In the <HI>Matter</HI> or <HI>Merit</HI> of the <HI>Cause,</HI> by the <HI>Declarations</HI> of the <HI>Lords</HI> and <HI>Commons,</HI> Jun. 10 1648. he thinks to Win all at one throw; because the raising of the <HI>Militia,</HI> and after that an <HI>Army</HI> (by the <HI>Propositions</HI> for Money, Plate, Horse,
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
Arms, and men, was, for <HI>King and Parliament; and for the sup∣pressing of the Traiterous designe of his wicked and Malignant Counsellors, and to maintain the Protestant Religion, the Kings Au∣thority and person in Royal Dignity: the free course of Justice and Laws of the</HI> LAND, <HI>Peac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of the Kingdome, and Priviledges of Parliament</HI>: and here (saith he) you have the <HI>Good Old Cause, truely, clearly, and fully stated by both Houses of Parliament, in every particular branch thereof.</HI> But let us a little unravel and Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ricate the <HI>matter</HI> and <HI>ground</HI> of the quarrel between us and the King, from his Fallacies, (<HI>Extra Dictionem,</HI> as well as <HI>in Di∣ctione</HI>;) we do not deny but here the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI> appeared; Yet not so fully, truely, and every <HI>Branch</HI> thereof stated (as Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> affirms) or as it grew up unto afterward, both in Par∣li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ment, Army, and Nation; yet in a sense (or <HI>secundum quid</HI>) it did appear thus.</P>
<P N="1">1. For <HI>King</HI> and <HI>Parliament</HI> together; as the <HI>Supream Counsel</HI> of the Nation; And yet at the same time too A∣GAINST <HI>the King</HI> so f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rre as he was inseparable from his <HI>Evil and</HI> wicked <HI>Malignant Counsellours</HI>: the reason is this, be∣cause the <HI>Majestas Realis,</HI> or <HI>Tutilari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> the Protecting Real <HI>Au∣thority</HI> and <HI>Majesty</HI> of the <HI>King</HI> was with the <HI>Parliament</HI> all a∣long; though the <HI>titularis</HI> was with his own <HI>person</HI> and evil <HI>Counsellors.</HI> So that they must needs carry on All in the <HI>Name</HI> (and Authority too) of <HI>King and Parliament</HI>; so long a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> King∣ship lasted. Therefore when the <HI>King</HI> in person entred the <HI>Parliament,</HI> and demanded the five <HI>Members,</HI> the Parliament declared, <HI>Jan.</HI> 17. 1641. <HI>the same was a Traiterous Designe a∣gainst King and Parliament.</HI> For indeed they were both (in the Authority and Majesty Real) so long as the King adhered to his <HI>Evil Counsel.</HI> They fought not against his Real <HI>Majestie,</HI> but denied that he had it with his <HI>Evil Counsellors</HI> whom they engaged against, (and so against all that could not be separated therefrom.) See the <HI>Declaration</HI> of <HI>Lords and Com∣mons</HI> (for I must meddle with no other to Mr. <HI>Prin's</HI> Cause) they close it thus: <HI>So that it rests onely,</HI><NOTE PLACE="inter"><HI>Exact. Coll.</HI> p. 464.</NOTE> <HI>that the FREE-BORN English do consider whether they Will adhere to the King and his Parliament, by which they have so long enjoyed all that is dear to them; Or to the King seduced by Jesuitical Counsel and Cavaliers, who have designed all to slavery and confu∣sion; which by Gods bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssing, and our joynt endeavours, may be timely prevented.</HI></P>
<P N="2"><PB N="8" REF="6"/>2. To <HI>maintain Religion,</HI> the Kings <HI>Person</HI> and <HI>Authority,</HI> Both Houses of <HI>Parliament,</HI> the Laws and <HI>Liberties of the people, i. e.</HI> so farre as they could consist, or be kept together, was the CAUSE: but when that was impossible, and could not be effected; no, not by all the <HI>Remonstrances,</HI> Intreaties, Messa∣ges, Treaties, or Means used (day and night) for that purpose; Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n their <HI>Work</HI> was to maintain what they could of it, <HI>viz.</HI> the <HI>Liberties</HI> of the people and their <HI>Representatives</HI>: and this was the GOOD OLD CAUSE. To sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>isfie Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> (if it may be) by the <HI>Resolves</HI> of <HI>Parliament,</HI> when both Houses sat, 20 <HI>May</HI> 1642. Resolved, <HI>That whensoever the King ma∣keth Warre upon the Parliament, it is a breach of the trust Repos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d in him by his people, contrary to his Oath, and tend∣eth to the dissolution of this Government, i. e.</HI> Ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gly Go∣vernment; and Was not this the <HI>Good Old Cause,</HI> I pray? Even in Mr. <HI>Prin's</HI> own account, <HI>Anno</HI> 1642. (though it be not now.) The Consequent of the Argument is obvious to every eye: If the King made the Warre upon the <HI>Parliament,</HI> it tended to the Dissolution of his (Kingly) Government; But the King made the Warre upon the Parliament, by Mr. <HI>Prins,</HI> (and Mr. <HI>Baxter's</HI>) own Concession, (who say, the <HI>Parliament</HI> w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re on the <HI>Defensive</HI>) and by their own Argument it must be then the <HI>Good Old Cause,</HI> which stands upon the dissolution of that <HI>old Government</HI> (viz. King, Lords, and Commons;) and which maintains now (<HI>in sensu Composito</HI>) all the Rights and Liberties of People and Parliament, though the <HI>Kingly Govern∣ment</HI> be lost, and dissolved by his own Wars.</P>
<P N="3">3. And although there be a truth (yet it is not all the truth) that Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> sayes, but with <HI>fall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ciâ Accidentis,</HI> and impro∣perly, seeing the predicated Liberty and Rights of the People require neither a House of <HI>Lords</HI> nor <HI>Court</HI> (I mean of King) to the Essence of them. This form of Government (by <HI>King, Lords, and Commons</HI>) being laid in the thick of Popery by King <HI>Henry</HI> 1. (for the <HI>Popes</HI> Interest as well as his own, Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> cannot deny,) which merits the denomination of his <HI>Good Old Cause</HI>; This indeed was hatch'd and laid by the <HI>Romish Gibeo∣nites,</HI> but not ours of the <HI>Commonwealth.</HI> And the truth is, if we desire to be reduced to <HI>dark</HI> Popery, and <HI>stark Slavery,</HI> Mr. <HI>Prin's Good Old Cause</HI> is then the best. But will he weigh <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he <HI>Grounds</HI> upon which the most <HI>Honourable Parliament</HI> that
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
ever went before it, declared the <HI>House of Lords</HI> dissolved (as well as <HI>Kingship?</HI>) March 19. 1648. <HI>The. Commons of England Assembled in Parliament, finding by too long experience the House of Lords is use∣lesse and dangerous to the People of England.</HI><NOTE PLACE="inter"><HI>Vid. Scob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l. Coll.</HI> 2. part. pag. 8. Chap. 16.17.</NOTE> So upon <HI>March</HI> 17. 1648. <HI>Whereas by the Abolition of the Kingly Office, a most happy Way is made for this Nation, (if God see it good) to return to its just and Antient Right of being Governed by its own Repres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntatives, National Meetings in Council from time to time,</HI> &amp;c. This was all upon the account of the <HI>Good Old Cause,</HI> and is indeed the <HI>True Old Cause</HI> first contended for (in the more <HI>inform substance</HI> of it) now in a better excrescence of <HI>Beauty,</HI> and Perfection above what before appeared. And if Mr. <HI>Prin,</HI> or Mr. <HI>Baxter</HI> can make it appear, this was plot∣ted by the <HI>Jesuits</HI> (as we can theirs by <HI>Papists</HI>) I shall become their <HI>Proselyte</HI> in the <HI>state of the Case</HI>; but if that yet he will maintain the <HI>House of Lords</HI> in the foundation of them, I must desire him to reconcile himself to himself, or his <HI>present Ar∣gument</HI> with their <HI>former Action</HI> of expelling the Bishops <HI>(Lord's Spiritual</HI>) out of that <HI>House</HI>; since they were also from the <HI>first foundation</HI> of it, and had an equal right to sit in it (by all the <HI>Laws,</HI> Customes, and <HI>Statutes</HI> of this Nation for it) with the <HI>Lords Temporal</HI>; (and yet this was accounted an <HI>Act</HI> of the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI> by himself at that day;) Also whether indeed (<HI>Secundum jus</HI>) the <HI>Lords</HI> did not dissolve their <HI>Own House,</HI> (as to the <HI>f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>undation</HI> of it) then? and by that <HI>Act</HI> of both Hou∣ses? and so to continue until another <HI>Bellum Episcopale,</HI> or <HI>Pres∣byteriale</HI> do alter the Case, and so the Cause? or raise up their Reverend <HI>Father-h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ods</HI> upon the <HI>Wool-packs</HI> again, to usher <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>N their <HI>Lordships Temporal,</HI> as they did them OUT? but,</P>
<P N="4">4. That this his <HI>Cause</HI> is the <HI>Old Cause,</HI> (and that which <HI>Delinquents</HI> and <HI>Malignants</HI> have so long strugled to keep alive) we cannot deny; But that it is the GOOD <HI>Old Cause,</HI> and not the BAD, yea, the VERY BAD (and the Worse, for that like <HI>Runnet,</HI> the longer it stands the stronger it smells; An <HI>old Ser∣pent</HI> has most poyson, an <HI>old Dog</HI> bites deepest, an <HI>old Thorne</HI> rankles most, and an <HI>old Dotard</HI> is hardest to please; for <HI>quo magis senescit, eo magis stultescit,</HI> as 'tis said of <HI>Braband</HI>) I say, that ours is <HI>not the Bad Old Cause,</HI> as Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> doth <HI>state</HI> it, We can,
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
and do deny. Nor can he prove by all the help of his <HI>Concor∣dance</HI> upon the Word <HI>Old</HI> (which his seventh <HI>p.</HI> is so full of) that HIS is the <HI>Good Old Cause,</HI> or written in the <HI>Grand Chara∣cter,</HI> (but by a surreptitious applying of the <HI>Letter,</HI> and a <HI>beg∣ging of the Question.</HI>) Neither think I that he intended his Idolized <HI>Idea,</HI> (of <HI>King, Lords and Commons</HI>) to be meant the <HI>New Creature</HI> (though he saith that ours is of the O<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>D MAN, pag. 7.) I suppose his <HI>Divinity</HI> is better then hi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alect,</HI> unless it be, that he has an expecta<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion of having it BORN AGAIN: Which, how <HI>impracticable</HI> (as well as improbable) it is, let all <HI>Good men</HI> judge; not so much for this, <HI>How can a Man that is OLD be born again?</HI> as for this, How can <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Rotten corrupt Car∣cass</HI> (of the Cause) so long since exploded, condemned, <HI>defunct,</HI> and laid in <HI>dust</HI> where it stinketh, (and there let it lye until the Resurrection) be <HI>born again</HI> in this Nation? But thus for the second <HI>Design.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. DESIGN, is to represent the <HI>Commonwealth-Cause,</HI> a Monster, <HI>of a New Breed</HI>; or, as Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> says in the M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rgin of his 1. p. <HI>It was begotten but in</HI> March 1648. <HI>How then can they call it</HI> OLD? <HI>or the good old Man, or Cause, without a con∣tradiction and absurdity?</HI> (the like in <HI>p.</HI> 7.) To which We An∣swer.</P>
<P>1. <HI>Ex Opposito,</HI> or in opposition to the late (the last) <HI>Apo∣stacie</HI> since <HI>Anno</HI> 1653. mistaked for the Cause; it is called the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI> without absurdity, or contradiction. 2. <HI>In sensu Composito,</HI> (as I said before) or so far as it comprehends all that ever was contended for, by <HI>Parliament,</HI> People, or <HI>Army,</HI> in the sense, End, and equity thereof, (<HI>viz.</HI> all those <HI>Ordinan∣ces</HI> of <HI>Parliament,</HI> 10 Junii, <HI>&amp;</HI> 5. Julii, <HI>&amp;</HI> 14 Martii 1642. <HI>&amp;</HI> 3 Aug. 1643. <HI>Earl of Essex</HI> his Commission, 14 Aprilis, 1643. and my Lord <HI>Fairfax</HI> his Commission, 15. <HI>Febr.</HI> 1644. and the <HI>Covenant,</HI> all (quoted by Mr. <HI>Prin:</HI>) to <HI>keep up Religi∣on in purity, Reformation according to the Word of God, the Li∣berty and safety of the people, the Priviledges of Parliament, and the Authority of the King</HI> (which is yet up in <HI>Parliament,</HI> and more too) and the <HI>Person of the King IN</HI> (mark that) <HI>IN the defence of the true Religion and Liberties of the People,</HI> &amp;c. these are the express words, in the Letter of them; now so far as ANY of these, or ALL these could stand together, the <HI>Common-wealth</HI> doth preserve them; but where any of these (in the
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
Letter, and forms) be incompatible, the ENDS of them are kept (if the <HI>Forms</HI> at that time in being, be lost, or altered;) and has Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> forgotten when the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI> (even in his Own Account) <HI>Anno</HI> 1642. was glad to keep up this very <HI>Method</HI> and <HI>Kernel,</HI> to justifie it (then) as well as now, <HI>viz.</HI> when the <HI>Question</HI> rose about the <HI>Militia</HI>? vid. <HI>Exact. Coll.</HI> pag. 150. and how Laws are to be understood, and obedience yeilded, the King claiming the <HI>Militia</HI> by Law; which was thus resolved: <HI>There is in Laws an</HI> EQUITABLE, <HI>and a</HI> LITE∣RAL <HI>sense; When there is a Grounded suspition that the Letter of the Law shall be improved against the Equity of<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et,</HI> (i. e. <HI>the PUB∣LICK GOOD, whether of the Body Real, or Representative) it gives a Liberty to disobey the Letter, and to obey the Equity of it.</HI> These are the very <HI>words</HI> of the <HI>Good Old Cause,</HI> when Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> so accounted of it.</P>
<P>3. <HI>A Deposito</HI> (it is the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI>; and so called dis∣criminatively from that (<HI>Bad Old Cause</HI>) which Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> states, and is depos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d; which is proved was founded by the <HI>Papists</HI> (viz. <HI>King, Lords and Commons.</HI>) Bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> let me ask him, if like the Fowl <HI>Ibis</HI> (in <HI>Aegypt</HI>) he had his Liberty to remove all, that he ac∣counts <HI>Garbidge</HI> and filth in the <HI>Commonwealth-Cause,</HI> yet would he not (by this) leave a <HI>Worse</HI> behind him then ever he found? Convince us of that, and then cry up Mr. <HI>Prin's Good Old Cause,</HI> &amp;c. But,</P>
<P>4. A <HI>Posito,</HI> or from the <HI>foundation</HI> of our <HI>Good Old Cause:</HI> we call it so, for that it is laid in the LAW of God, of <HI>Nature,</HI> and in the <HI>fundamental Rights</HI> and Reason of this Nation; in the <HI>Liberties</HI> of the people, and Priviledges of Parliament their Repr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sentatives; which are of long standing, and were before ever the <HI>Government by King, Lords and Commons,</HI> came into this Land. These were contented for not onely against the <HI>late King,</HI> but his <HI>Predecessours,</HI> and hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ted at in Parliaments many years ago; called (in <HI>Declaration</HI> of <HI>Lords and Commons,</HI> July 12. 1642.) <HI>the Birth-right of the Subjects of this Land,</HI> &amp;c. which lately rose up to more <HI>Maturity,</HI> and to such as the <HI>King</HI> takes notice of, in's Complaint to the Parliament, (<HI>vid. Exact. Coll.</HI> p. 470.) in these words; <HI>He sees every day Pam∣phl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts published against his Crown, and against Monarchy its self.</HI> So that on all sides We see this was, and is the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI>; nor can Mr. <HI>Prin,</HI> with any colour deny it; onely
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
by his fallacy of <HI>non Causae pro Causâ,</HI> p. 2. endeavours to evade it.</P>
<P N="4">4. <HI>DESIGN,</HI> is to make us believe that the <HI>Common-wealth is the most ignoble</HI> and spurious <HI>issue of Apostacie</HI>; his Words are, <HI>p.</HI> 3. ult. <HI>Those who were first raised and C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mmissio∣ned by Parliament for its just defence, yet are at last degenerated into the greatest Apostates from, and violentest Enemies against it.</HI> VVhereas indeed the contrary would be most evident, <HI>viz.</HI> if after all this Blood and Treasure spent, we should recede again to <HI>King, Lords, and Commons,</HI> laid aside so nobly by the People, Army, and their famous <HI>Representatives</HI>; yea, so highly to the <HI>glory of God,</HI> Renown of this Nation, <HI>Terror</HI> and dread of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll our Enemies at home and abroad, who like <HI>Bores</HI> were w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et∣ting their <HI>Tusks</HI> in their own foame, (<HI>Corruptio optimi <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>essima est.</HI>)</P>
<P>2. Hath not experience taught it all along, that nothing is more obnoxious to Parliament-Priviledges, or ready to invade them, then a Kingly <HI>Prerogative,</HI> and a Negative Voyce in him∣self, and his supercilious scowling Lords? was not Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> of this opinion at the <HI>Kings</HI> demanding the five <HI>Members?</HI> and if the <HI>Sword</HI> be kept in its proper place, for the service of the <HI>Commonwealth,</HI> it will be far from over-awing the <HI>Freedom of Parliament,</HI> or enervating of their just Authority in the Na∣tion.</P>
<P>3. But the truth is, if the <HI>Commonwealth</HI> were Mr. <HI>Prin</HI>'s <HI>Client,</HI> or took his Counsel, it would quickly come to that; As the <HI>Fable</HI> sayes, Whiles <HI>Actaeon</HI> had his own and proper <HI>shape,</HI> he had all his <HI>Currs</HI> at his own Command; but when he did degenerate (or turn into a Beast) he was made a prey to his own <HI>Dogs</HI>; and so would the Commonwealth to he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> veriest Enemies, and we should soon see a <HI>Trowt</HI> to be deerer then an <HI>OX.</HI> But to prove that it is so, <HI>p</HI> 4. <HI>l.</HI> 1. he affirms, <HI>that the blindest eyes may most cleerly discern it:</HI> and I think so too; the truth is, he had need to deal with such as have had their <HI>right ears</HI> cut off (with <HI>Malchus</HI>) or their <HI>right eyes</HI> put out. He puts me in minde of a Man who was much taken with a Horse, both for make and <HI>colour</HI>; and after he had <HI>bought</HI> him, asked the fault of him, (which he should have done before:) but the <HI>Courser</HI> told him (for his incouragement) he had no fault but this, that he was a DARK <HI>Grey:</HI> and so he was a <HI>Grey,</HI> b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t as <HI>blinde</HI> as a
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
Beetle, <HI>dark</HI> indeed; it is but a folly to like the COLOUR that he puts upon his Cause, if <HI>the blindest Man may best dis∣cern it.</HI></P>
<P N="5">5. <HI>Grand DESIGN,</HI> is to revive the <HI>Memory of the late King's Death, with such circumstances as may set it out for the most Odious Act that ever was done in England:</HI> thereby, the more highly incensing the <HI>Commonwealth's Enemies,</HI> and colour their cruelty to the <HI>Commonwealth's friends,</HI> if ever they fall in∣to their fingers, or if they may sit but as <HI>Coroners</HI> upon it. Mr. <HI>Baxter</HI> of the Two, is most open-faced: for <HI>p.</HI> 317.318. of <HI>'s Key for Catholicks,</HI> he first forges a <HI>story,</HI> or unlocks a Ca∣binet full of <HI>Dilemma's</HI> to finde out the <HI>Plot,</HI> (which he calls the Jesui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es Plot, that they might bring upon this Nation the <HI>Odium</HI> of <HI>King-killing,</HI> and <HI>p.</HI> 321, 322. by twelve undeniable <HI>Arguments</HI> (as he calls them) he is pleased to say the Fact to be so odious, as that no <HI>Protestants</HI> had a hand in it; and <HI>the World</HI> (sayes he) <HI>knowes they</HI> (the Army) <HI>were fain to Master London, the Parliament; to imprison and cast out the Members, be∣fore they could accomplish it</HI> (here he <HI>refers to Mr.</HI> Prin) and sayes, <HI>It is well known to All</HI> England, <HI>that before, and since the doing of it, the thing is disowned and detested by the main Body of the</HI> Eng∣lish <HI>Nation, Nobility, Gentlemen, Ministers, and People. And that the Protestant Ministers so opposed the Kings Death, that they drew upon them the Odium of the Corrupted part of the Army. And that the London-Ministers unanimously concurr'd in an Addresse to prevent it, printed their Abhorrence of it to the World, and many of them were imprisoned, Mr.</HI> Love <HI>beheaded, and many others put to death about it. And that the Kingdom of Scotland</HI> (as he calls it) <HI>disowned it from first to last,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>Now what means all this ran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acking in the Tombs of the <HI>Dead,</HI> but to raise up <HI>evil Spirits?</HI> for if they had done it but like <HI>Alexander</HI> when he had opened <HI>Cyrus</HI>'s Tomb, to set a <HI>Crown</HI> upon his Hearse, and so as silently have shut it up again; it had been tolerable, and the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> had left room for more Chari∣ty, at least to think that excessive Love to their Persons gave the vent of these Passions; but as they handle the matter, it makes us doubt whether Love to them, or hatred to others did help most in the Obstetrication of this hurtfull matter, and un∣worthy Accusation, which the Lord convince them of, and humble them for. Mr. <HI>Prin,</HI> p. 6. mentions the <HI>Declaration</HI> of
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
the Army <HI>for settling his Majesty in his just Rights, the Par∣liament in their just Priviledges, and the Subject in their Li∣berties and Freedome.</HI> All which was effected; for his <HI>Maje∣stas Tutilaris &amp; realis,</HI> had its just right in the Parliament, and in our obedience thereto, (and his <HI>Majestas Titularis &amp; perso∣nalis,</HI> say they, had his right too, with his evil Counsellors:) in the Commonwealth also, the Parliament have their just Privi∣ledges, (which they are deprived of in and by the Kingly Go∣vernment) and the People have their due and just Liberties Civil and Religions; and is not this the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI>? but without doubt the Design is to make the <HI>Dead Body</HI> bleed a∣fresh (by Sympathy) if they can, and then to condemn the Worthiest Assertors of our <HI>Free State,</HI> for Murtherers and <HI>King-killers</HI> (the Lord shew them more mercy! we see what quarter they will give us, if they catch us:) far be it from me to aggravate their evil, and much more to excite any in Power or Army against them, whom I have had a very worthy esteem of, (but in this matter;) and truly, I hope, I would rather <HI>me potius periturum quam perditurum,</HI> die then destroy; onely I must be faithful <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o warn of the Danger. What need we won∣der now that the Exchange was so full of the Lists of them late∣ly that sat in the high <HI>Court of Justice,</HI> as if the Popes <HI>Taxa Camerae</HI> had been sent over, with the rates of all sins Venial and Mortal? Sure then 'tis time to look about us, lest SHEBA be too forward for us; <HI>Who</HI> 2 Sam. 20.1. <HI>blew the trumpet, and said, We have no part in David, neither have we inheritance in the son of Jesse: every man to his Tents, O Israel!</HI></P>
<P N="6">6. DESIGN, that Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> and his Brethren seem to have, is to disaff<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ct People with that Parli<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ment, if they can, (as being the most terrible of any to the Enemies of the Common∣wealth) th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t fixed the <HI>Government</HI> in (or the Balance of) a <HI>Free-State,</HI> af<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er the Dissolution of <HI>Kingship,</HI> and <HI>House of Lords</HI>; and to possesse the Nation with this, that there is no visible Authority in it, but the meer power and force of the Sword, <HI>the onely Good Old Cause now</HI> (sayes <HI>Mr. Prin</HI> p. 6.) <HI>cryed up.</HI> The truth i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, that <HI>Parliament</HI> was interrupted (we do not say <HI>dissolved</HI>) by a sudden recoil, we say not a total or intentio∣nal alienation of the <HI>Militia</HI>; yet so, as their <HI>Seats</HI> (it seems) in <HI>Parliament</HI> could neither fit, suit with, nor hold any other m<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n in them to this very day (after many an <HI>Essay</HI>) which is
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>
observable. And so, as that the Army are made the more sen∣sible of those <HI>Malign suffluences</HI> and Effects that <HI>Interposition</HI> had, which did of late eclipse both <HI>Parliament</HI> and good <HI>Peo∣ple</HI>; which will make them a thousand times the more to wel∣come and value the Lustre and Blessing of their restored Light and Liberty; and as liberally to Compensa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e it by their very faithfull return to their good <HI>old Trust,</HI> and proper Stations, so as to preserve the <HI>Parliament</HI> (for future) from the like Proreption or Perpetration of any. Besides, this we have learn'd by it, that if any Project do deprive them of our hands, yet it cannot be with the depredation of our hearts, so long as they keep up the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI> with life, fortitude, and fidelity. And this also we learn, that when those <HI>Arms</HI> do fail us, we can exercise other <HI>Arms</HI> and Artillery, that (through grace) hath never fail'd us, <HI>viz. Faith</HI> and <HI>Prayer.</HI> Yea, this the <HI>Parliament</HI> may learn, that when P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ovidence doth permit so high attempts upon their Priviledges or Per∣sons, it is in order to an edition of an <HI>higher Trust</HI>; that they may be taken off of an <HI>Arm of flesh,</HI> or carnal confidence, and conclude, that in the presence of the Almighty, and Glory of his precious Name, in the Affections and Prayers of his poor People, and in their own <HI>Innocency</HI> and faithfulnesse, is <HI>Protection,</HI> Ammunition, and a <HI>Life-guard</HI> to be found, suffici∣ent for them. Their enemies too may learn this, that no <HI>Mi∣litia</HI> diverted (or rather perverted) can confiscate us of God's favour, or keep off <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hem from his anger, that are perti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate to persist in their <HI>bad old Cause.</HI> But in a Word, there be so many and weighty Reasons for the sitting of that <HI>Parliament,</HI> both for the satisfaction of the Nation, for the maintaing and fur∣ther managing the most excellent <HI>Good Old Cause,</HI> the blessed Interest of <HI>Christ</HI> and of the <HI>Common-weal</HI> yea, for the keep∣ing up of the face of Authority (in the <HI>Majestate tutilari</HI>) to the dread of all <HI>Foes,</HI> and the more endearing of all <HI>Friends</HI>; healing the Wounds and Divisions of our old acquaintance in <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>my,</HI> people, and <HI>Councils;</HI> raising of money to supply pre∣sent Necessities, Straits, and Exigents, in Army and State; and indeed, to make them some mends for the <HI>Interruption</HI> they had in <HI>An.</HI> 1653. (this being the most united and loud call of the <HI>Well-affected,</HI> who doubtlesse will welcome them into their places with great <HI>Rejoycings</HI>;) I say, these <HI>Cinside∣rations</HI>
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>
can qui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kly wipe off those <HI>Aspersions</HI> the enemies would bespatter their <HI>Recalling</HI> with; and if Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> will be dash∣ing in the puddle, he will cause but the <HI>dirt</HI> to fly about his own ears.</P>
<P>But now READER, it must be left to thy judgement, upon the Argument between us, which is the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI> con∣tended for, and who indeed are the Wily <HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>beonites</HI> that come in with their clouted <HI>shooes</HI> and <HI>musty stuff,</HI> to deceive with; Worm-eaten <HI>Matter,</HI> or food fitter for MAGGOTS (such Gentils) then for MASTERS of Reason. The Dung∣hill-fly (sayes the Story) bragg'd of his descent, as more ex∣cellent then the <HI>Painfull Bees,</HI> because he came of a Horse; whereas indeed he rose but from the <HI>Horse</HI>▪ Dung; the Appli∣cation is easie, for theirs arose in the thick of Popery, from the Excrements of the times, and must we keep it up? Me∣thinks this <HI>Antiquary</HI> and his Consociates, might act the part of the old <HI>Arcades</HI> the next time, who boasted of their <HI>Anti∣quities</HI> (forsooth) as two dayes older then the <HI>Moon.</HI> I can inculcate his CALL to all, that are not under the Jewish Curse of <HI>hearing and they will not hear, or seeing and they will not per∣ceive,</HI> to examine accurately and find out, (if they can) any o∣ther <HI>Good old Cause,</HI> but that which we have <HI>asserted,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> hath <HI>deserted</HI> above these ten years. Yea let <HI>All Officers,</HI> Souldiers of the <HI>Army,</HI> Friends or Foes, Any or All that have their Wits about them, Grace in their hearts, or Honesty in their lives, and a good Conscien<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e left them, consider and duely perpend, which is the <HI>Imposture</HI> or spurious off-spring of <HI>Apostacy</HI>! (the <HI>Common-wealth-Government,</HI> and a Free-state; or a <HI>Kingly Government</HI> and slavery again;) for I do professe, if he or they will yet dote upon his <HI>Old Idea,</HI> I will cease to wonder at <HI>Caligula</HI>'s folly for falling so in love with his Horse <HI>Inci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atus.</HI> But to his exhortation out of <HI>Bernard</HI> (misquoted by him, p. 8. for it is in <HI>Lib.</HI> 4. <HI>de Consid.</HI> so <HI>lib.</HI> 8. <HI>Florum, Cap.</HI> 51. but not so fit for his or this purpose) <HI>Spiritualis ille homo qui emnia d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>judicat, ut ipse à nemine judicetur omne opus suum tri∣na quâdam consideratione praeveniet,</HI> 1. <HI>Quidem an liceat.</HI> 2. <HI>de∣inde an deceat.</HI> 3. <HI>Postremo an expediat,</HI> &amp;c. The spirituall Man is he that judgeth All things; and that he himself may be judg∣ed of no man, he forestals every thing he does with a <HI>three-fold</HI> consideration.<NOTE PLACE="inter">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 2.</NOTE> 1. <HI>Whether it be</HI> LAWFUL?
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
Now indeed what course else can be taken that is <HI>Lawfull</HI> be∣fore God and Man? or that can free from the Bloud that has been spilt. And besides, as it is in the case of a Wife, 1. Cor. 7.39. <HI>She is bound by the Law so long as her Husband liveth, but if her husband be dead,</HI> what then? must she keep up his <HI>dead</HI> shape? or his <HI>Corps</HI> above the ground for her onely hus∣band? must that lie by her, putrifying and infecting the air? at bed, at board, and in her bosome? (as Mr. <HI>Prin</HI> would have his <HI>Old cause,</HI> so long defunct and gone?) No! no! this is <HI>not Lawful; but if her husband be dead, she is at Liberty,</HI> and this is Lawfull. 2. <HI>Whether it be comely and amiable</HI>? I am sure, a Commonwealth was so in <HI>Israel,</HI> Numb. 24.5. <HI>How goodly are thy tents, O Jacob! and thy tabernacles O Israel!</HI> Jer. 6.2. Ezek. 16 14. and their degenerating from it was as great reproach to them, <HI>Isay</HI> 1.21, 22. 1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 8 7. and as sure am I in <HI>En∣gland,</HI> that it would be little becoming us to keep up any monstrous or most ugly declension▪ by setting up one or other mish<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pen <HI>Hydra, Chimae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a,</HI> or Creature after Mr. <HI>Prin</HI>'s old <HI>Cause,</HI> which puts God and the Devil together in the Balance. 3. WHETHER IT BE EXPED<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ENT? Sure, circumstances consider'd, no other <HI>Expedient</HI> can be found so practicable, and desireable; so lawfull and so amiable in the eyes of God and good men. But a few words</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>To the Honourable Council of Officers: our Army, and friends to the <HI>Good</HI> Old Cause.</HEAD>
<P>I Am a poor WORM (a despised dust) who am now come ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of my HOLE, where I have lay'n lamenting for these four or five years <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast past, under the dark and cloudy <HI>dis∣pensation</HI> that past upon us; but therein have seen so much of the Grace, Wisdome, and Faithfulnesse of our dear God, (<HI>JEHOVAH <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>IREH) Grace</HI> to Refine us! <HI>Wisdome</HI> to Try us! and his <HI>Faithfulnesse</HI> (O now!) at last to save us! (as we hope) and with such spirituall advantages to our poor Souls; that we we may conclude upon what <HI>Themistocles</HI> once said
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>
to's sons in banishment, PERISSEMUS NISI PERIISSEMUS, <HI>We had been</HI> (certainly) <HI>undone, if we had not been undone,</HI> (thus uncertainly) praised be the Lord for it. And therefore as <HI>Jo∣seph</HI> said unto his <HI>Brethren,</HI> Gen. 45.5, 7, 14, 15. (over whom he wept for joy, and kissed <HI>them all,</HI> and thus would we over you) <HI>Now be not grieved nor angry with your selves, for it was the Lord that appointed it, that we might be</HI> PRESERVED, (ver. 5. <HI>to preserve life</HI> (or Lemicojah) <HI>unto a Reviving,</HI> so Septuag. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or as it is in Arab. <HI>Magoutahan</HI> (where the <HI>Mim</HI> is Causal) that we might be kept to your help and assistance) <HI>this is the Lord's doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes!</HI> This is such <HI>a</HI> VICTORY as you never had before, your former was a Victory over your <HI>enemies,</HI> but this is a <HI>Victory</HI> over your selves; in the first you conquer'd like Souldiers, but in this like Chri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tians; in the first way was <HI>Alexander</HI> a famous <HI>Con∣querour,</HI> but in this last way was he miserably <HI>Conquered.</HI> Wherefore pursue your <HI>Victory</HI> in the name of the Lord, and preponderate the weight of the Work before you, with the danger of delaying that which is expected from you: <HI>Nequam &amp; Nequaquam</HI> are near neighbours, both enemies to the <HI>Good Old Cause</HI>; rout them out of your <HI>Councils,</HI> and take your March (as <HI>Numb.</HI> 33.29.) from <HI>Mitchah</HI> (which signifies sweetness) to <HI>Chashmonah</HI> (which signifies) <HI>Swiftnesse</HI>; there pitch your <HI>tents</HI> for present, and the Lord prosper you. Now if my mite may be but accepted, I shall offer you the Sense of your <HI>Old Friends,</HI> in seven or eight sentences, wherein (I hope) have the mind of God, I am sure I have of some hundreds of his ser∣vants, after most solemn seeking of his face.</P>
<P N="1">1. That there must be a full <HI>Remove</HI> of that old <HI>Carcasse</HI> (which Others call their <HI>Good Old Cause</HI>) that has put us to a stop, as <HI>Amasa</HI>'s corps did to the People, 2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 20.12, 13. till it was quite removed out of the way, <HI>and then all the Peopl<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> went on apace.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. Every unsound Body mu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t be soundly and seasonably <HI>purged,</HI> that the <HI>Vitals</HI> and Animals thereof may be restored and setled.</P>
<P N="3">3. The speedy <HI>Restitution</HI> of the faithfull Officers of the Army, of the Parliament, and of All, is a probable means to prevent the <HI>Destitution</HI> of ANY of the <HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od Old Cause.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4. Remember also that your <HI>Old Friends</HI> can do you
<PB N="19" REF="11"/>
as much good as your <HI>Old Swords,</HI> when you need them.</P>
<P N="5">5. And that your <HI>Opportunity</HI> is seconded with their <HI>impor∣tunity.</HI></P>
<P N="6">6. Also, remember to set your <HI>Christian-Names</HI> before your <HI>Sir-Names</HI> in every service.</P>
<P N="7">7. And when we drink of the <HI>Brook,</HI> let us think of the <HI>Spring.</HI></P>
<P N="8">8. If any amongst you touched with the late <HI>Defection</HI> must be retain'd, let it be without danger of the like <HI>Infection.</HI> And for others <HI>satisfaction</HI> as well as their own <HI>Sanctification,</HI> let us subject unto you this one consideration; Whether they might not be prepared (like the <HI>Captive-woman,</HI> Deut. 21. who <HI>was set a mourning fourty dayes, her Haire cut, and her Nailes pared,</HI> &amp;c.) We mean, by some deep <HI>Humiliation,</HI> and <HI>Demon∣stration</HI> of a Real <HI>Change?</HI> By this means you will work out all jealousies, and wonderfully knit our hearts unto you, as well as oblige our <HI>Persons,</HI> Purses and <HI>Prayers</HI> for you, with as mutual indearments between us (as ever were) <HI>to live and die</HI> together for Christ, and the <HI>Good Old Cause.</HI> Trusting to see the PLANT of RENOWN in this Nation yet, and the most excellent FOUNDATION <HI>of Many</HI> GENE∣RATIONS. Even so! <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

