<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Christs napkin: or, A sermon preached in Kirkcubright at the Communion, May 12. 1633. By that flower of the Church; famous, famous, Mr. Samuel Rutherfurd. Never before printed</TITLE><AUTHOR>Rutherford, Samuel, 1600?-1661.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A57965</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing R2373A</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 21465</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S116297</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99851514</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99851514</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">16789</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A57965)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16789)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1255:6)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Christs napkin: or, A sermon preached in Kirkcubright at the Communion, May 12. 1633. By that flower of the Church; famous, famous, Mr. Samuel Rutherfurd. Never before printed</TITLE><AUTHOR>Rutherford, Samuel, 1600?-1661.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>23, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[Scotland? :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>ca. 1660]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Imprint from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A57965">
<STC T="W">R2373A</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99851514</BIBNO>
<VID>16789</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>CHRISTS NAPKIN:
OR, A
SERMON
PREACHED IN
<HI>KIRKCVBRIGHT</HI>
AT THE
COMMUNION,
<HI>May</HI> 12. 1633.</P>
<P>By that Flower of the <HI>Church;</HI> Famous, famous,
Mr. <HI>Samuel Rutherfurd.</HI></P>
<P>Never before Printed.</P>
<Q><BIBL><HI>Revelation 21: Chapter 4▪ 5, 6, 7▪ 8, Verses.</HI></BIBL> 
<P>And GOD shall
Wipe away all Tears, and there shall be no more Death,
neither Sorrow, nor Crying, neither shall there be any
more Pain: For former Things are done away.</P>
<P>And He that Sate upon the Throne, said, behold, I make all
Things New. And He said unto me, write: For these
Things are Faithfull and True. <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P></Q>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE
TEXT.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>Revelation 21. Chapter, 4. 5, 6, 7, 8, Verses.</BIBL>
<Q><P>And GOD
shall Wipe away all Tears, and there shall be no more
Death, neither Sorrow, nor Crying, neither shall there
be any more Pain: For former things are done away.</P>
<P>And He that Sate upon the Throne, said, behold, I make
all Things New. And He said unto me, write: for
these Things are Faithfull and True, &amp;c.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>THIS <HI>Text</HI> contains Three Things. First, <HI>The State of
the Glorified,</HI> verse 4. Secondly, <HI>A part of</HI> Christ'<HI>s
Office,</HI> verse 5. Thirdly, <HI>A Description of His Na∣ture.</HI>
Fourthly, <HI>The Promises.</HI> As, 1. Drink to satisfie the
Thirsty. 2. An Inheritance to the Overcomers, or Over∣coming
Souldiers. The 3. is a Threatning of Eternal Wrath
to Offenders against the First and Second <HI>Table</HI> of the <HI>Law.
And GOD shall Wipe away all Tears.</HI> When Friends meets,
they give the Stranger his Welcome Home. Here the Pil∣grims
Welcome Home that our Friend <HI>Christ</HI> gives us: This
was spoken from Heaven, and therefore it is True Doctrine.
Then we see that the Sufferings and Tears of the Saints shall
be wiped away and removed, but not fully, while the Life
to come; For here is <HI>Christ</HI>'s Welcome Home to Poor Sin∣ners:
For they come all to <HI>Him</HI> with Wet Faces, and blear∣ed
with Tears for Sin, and the manifold Troubles in this
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
Life; And <HI>Christ</HI> meets them in the Door with a fair <HI>Soft
Napkin</HI> in <HI>His Hand,</HI> and puts up <HI>his hand</HI> to their Faces,
and says, Hold your Tongue, My Dear Bairns, ye shall never
Weep again. And indeed in my Judgement it is a <HI>Speech</HI>
borrowed from a Mother that has a Bairn with a broken Face,
all Bloody, and all bleared with Tears, and it comes to her,
and woes her Heart to see him so, and she sits down, and
wipes the Tears from his Eyes, and lays her Hand softly on
the Wound, and lays his Head in her Breast, and dights away
the Blood, and lays her two Arms about him, and there is
no end of Fair Words. So when <HI>Christ</HI> and we shall meet in
Heaven, <HI>He</HI> will Huss us, and wipe away all Tears, and lay
our Heads in <HI>his</HI> Bosom: See how <HI>he</HI> alludes to this Place,
Isaiah 54. <HI>O thou afflicted and tossed with Tempest and not
comforted: behold, I will lay thy Foundation with Sa∣phires,</HI>
&amp;c. It is there to speak so, our <HI>Lord</HI> is Rewing that
ever <HI>he</HI> had handled <HI>his</HI> Saints as <HI>he</HI> did Isaiah 65. 18. <HI>Be
Glad and Rejoice for evermore in that which I Create;
for behold, I Create Jerusalem a Rejoicing, and his People
a Joy.</HI> Verse 19. <HI>And I will Rejoice over Jerusalem, and
Joy in My People, and the Voice of Weeping shall no
more be heard in her, nor the Voice of Crying.</HI> If ever there
was a Blyth Meeting betwixt Two, it must be betwixt the
<HI>Bridegroom</HI> and the <HI>Bride</HI> in the <HI>Marriage-day.</HI> And what
a Meeting there is of Joy betwixt such a <HI>Bridegroom</HI> and
<HI>Bride</HI> cannot be conceived: For <HI>Christ</HI> that <HI>Day</HI> will have
on all <HI>his</HI> Best Cloaths, and such a <HI>Bride</HI> as the <HI>Lamb</HI>'s <HI>Wife,</HI>
What a <HI>Welcome</HI> will <HI>She</HI> get? To get a Drink at our first
Meeting, and Incoming to Heaven of the <HI>Well</HI> of the <HI>Water</HI> of
<HI>Life,</HI> O Strong Comforting <HI>Water.</HI> When we shall be cloath∣ed,
and not a Wrong Pinn on us. A Fair <HI>Bride</HI> in Silks and
Purple of <HI>Christ</HI>'s own Busking; And <HI>Christ</HI> our <HI>Lord</HI> shall
Present <HI>his Bride</HI> to <HI>his Father,</HI> and our <HI>Father-in-law</HI> the
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
<HI>Father</HI> of our <HI>Husband</HI> shall take us by the Hand &amp; Lead us
benn the House to the Dinning-hall, and set us down at a Ta∣ble
to feast our fill upon <HI>the Tree of Life.</HI> O! Strong Com∣forting
Water, <HI>the Well of Life,</HI> to feast upon the <HI>Trinity</HI>
for evermore. Now Mock and Scorn the Way to Heaven as
ye please, ye never heard of True Happiness till now: Here
is a <HI>Banquet of Joy</HI> for evermore. <HI>He shall wipe away all
Tears: Christ</HI> our <HI>Lord</HI> here wipes the Tears from <HI>his</HI> Bairns
Faces; Yet after that they weep New Tears: <HI>He</HI> never wipes
away all Tears till now. Here shall be our <HI>Last▪ Good-Night</HI>
of Death: <HI>Good-Night</HI> Mourning and Crying, and Sorrow:
We shall be on the other Side of the Water, over beyond the
Black River of <HI>Death,</HI> and shall Scorn <HI>Death:</HI> For <HI>Christ</HI>
(Rev. 20. 14.) <HI>shall take Death and Hell, and cast them
in Prison: Former Things are done away.</HI> The Mother
that lost her Bairns shall get them; All the <HI>Lord</HI>'s Widows shall
get their Husbands: The Old World which was the Mourn∣ing
World shall be away: And therefore, never while now shall
all Tears be wiped away; for it is the Way. The <HI>Kirk</HI> is
half a <HI>Widow</HI> here; Her <HI>Lord</HI> is in an uncouth Countrey,
far from her here, and ilk Lown round about plucks at this
<HI>Silly Widow,</HI> while she is in the Valey of <HI>Baca,</HI> wherein is
no Water. The <HI>Watchmen</HI> stricketh her, and taketh her Vail
from her; And <HI>Christ</HI> writes a <HI>Love-Letter</HI> to her, and af∣ter
she has read it, she rejoiceth and wipeth her Face; But
when the <HI>Letter</HI> grows old, and she has lost the <HI>Letter,</HI> New
Troubles comes on, she sheds New Tears, and she comes un∣der
New Persecutions, and her <HI>Lord</HI> for her <HI>Sin</HI> goes in behind
the <HI>Wall,</HI> and hides <HI>himself,</HI> and lets her Mourn her fill:
But in that Day <HI>He will wipe away all Tears from her Eyes.</HI>
See then how it goes here in this Life: First a Fair Day, then
again a Foull Day, while at last that Fair Day Dawn that all
Shadows shall flee away; and there shall never be a Foull
Day after that; but ay the long lasting Summer Day for ever∣more.
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
Ye see a Man Travelling to his Home, here is a Wa∣ter,
then a Dry Land, then another Water, then Dry Land,
then a Water, and only Dry Land between and his Home;
Then he goes Home to his Wife and his Bairns, and has no
moe Waters: But all our Tears are never dryed till we come
to Heaven; For the <HI>Saints</HI> have a <HI>Liferent-Tack</HI> of the
<HI>Cross</HI> of <HI>Christ,</HI> while we are here, and ay Ill Weather, <HI>Mat∣thew</HI>
16. ever the <HI>Cross.</HI> See <HI>John</HI> 16. Our <HI>Lord</HI> compares
our Troubles to the Pains that comes upon a Woman Travell∣ing,
now a Showre, and then some Ease, a Showre again, and
then Ease, ay while the last Showre that she be Delivered,
and then no more Showres; She remembreth no more Pain
for Joy that a Man-Child is born into the World. We must
be in Pain ere our Birth be Born; but we will be Delivered of
our Birth.</P>
<P><HI>Vse</HI> 1. Let us prepare, for Tears will follow us to Heaven▪
unto the very Entry of the Door, our Face shall be wet, for we
go out of this Life Sad and Groaning for this Miserable Life,
and to thrust throw the last Port, and to wade throw the hin∣dermost
VVater, it is a sore set: But be blyth <HI>Christians,</HI> and
Grip to the <HI>Promise:</HI> But ye that Laugh now (and so are
far from Tears, that Mock the <HI>Mourners of Zion)</HI> ye may
Sigh and close the <HI>Bible,</HI> and say alas! I never shed a Tear
for <HI>Christ,</HI> yon <HI>Text</HI> is not for me; It may be <HI>Christ</HI> shall that
Day gar you VVeep and shed Tears for Evermore. This Soure
Laughing World will away; There is a Day of Tears coming
on you, Greeting and Gnashing of Teeth. And when a Man
Gnasheth his Teeth one against another, he has no mind of
Laughing: But I would not have your Mirth for a World; be
doing, we will see who will Laugh fastest yon Day.</P>
<P><HI>Vse</HI> 2. There is an Ill coming on this Land; Sin is not come
to a full Harvest. <HI>GOD</HI>'s <HI>Bairns</HI> that can now Mourn for
their own Sins, and the Sins of the Land, Rejoice in Heaven;
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
there is never seen a Greeting Bairn there: GOD has a <HI>Nap∣kin</HI>
to dight their Faces. It is the Laughing, Rejoicing Peo∣ple
that GOD Destroys.</P>
<P><HI>He that Sate upon the Throne. John</HI> heareth more of
<HI>Christ,</HI> a Sweet Speech. Here Three Things, 1. <HI>A Speak∣er.
2. A Speech. 3. A Direction to keep the Speech.</HI>
Who spake the <HI>Speech</HI> is not told; whether an Angel or an
Earthly King; For they sit on Thrones also: But it is <HI>He</HI> of
whom it is said, Rev. 4. 2. <HI>And a Throne was set, and one sat on
the Throne. John</HI> tells not his Name. But he thinketh so
much of <HI>him</HI> that he takes it as granted, that there is none Wor∣thy
to be a <HI>King</HI> but <HI>He,</HI> and to sit upon a Throne but <HI>He.</HI>
The <HI>Saints</HI> measures all the Affections of others by their own
Affections; As if one speared at <HI>John</HI> who is <HI>He</HI> that Sits u∣pon
the Throne? He would have answered, what needs you
spear, Is there any in Heaven or Earth in my Estimation Wor∣thy
to be a <HI>King</HI> but <HI>He?</HI> and to Sit upon a Throne but
<HI>He?</HI> and to take a Crown but <HI>He</HI> upon <HI>His Head?</HI> The
<HI>Saints</HI> sets ay <HI>Christ His</HI> alone, they set <HI>Him</HI> ay above all:
Speak of Kings to them, but <HI>Christ</HI> is out of play. So <HI>Cant.</HI>
2. The <HI>Kirk</HI> Meeting with the <HI>Watchmen,</HI> saith, <HI>Saw ye
Him whom my Soul loveth?</HI> What kend the <HI>Watchmen Him
whom her Soul loveth?</HI> For she might have loved a Lown,
or a Harlot, or an Idol-god, or the World: But she measur∣eth
the <HI>Watchmen</HI> by her Self; there was none in her Mind
but <HI>Christ:</HI> And therefore she needed not to tell them as she
thought. So <HI>Mary Magdalen,</HI> John 20. 15: says to the <HI>Gar∣diner</HI>
(as she thought) <HI>Sir, if ye have born Him hence, tell
me where ye have laid Him:</HI> She tells not what <HI>Him;</HI> tak∣ing
as granted, none was so much in her Mind as <HI>Christ,</HI>
Nay, I pray you, let the same Mind be in you that was in
<HI>John.</HI> Let <HI>Christ</HI> be to your Soul the Pearl of the Ring. A∣mongst
all Kings, to us <HI>Christ</HI> should be made High and Esteem∣ed
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
as <HI>He,</HI> the Only <HI>He,</HI> that is Worthy to Sit on the Throne.
So <HI>Canticles 5. He</HI> is to the Kirk <HI>the Chief among ten thous∣and.</HI>
Gather all the Angels, and all the Saints in Heaven and
Earth together, <HI>Christ</HI> is too Good to be their Captain; And
indeed what is all that sits on a Throne? It must be In∣finitly
more in <HI>Him:</HI> And what Glory is in the World, is far
more in <HI>Him?</HI> Take all the Roses in the Earth, and put them
all in one, that would be a Dainty Thing and Sight; Now
what are all these to <HI>Christ?</HI> No more than a Nettle to the
fairest Rose; Fy upon the Tasteless Love of Men that never
Loveth <HI>Jesus Christ,</HI> and yet falleth in Love with Lusts:
They Love Gold, Riches and Honour, and puts <HI>Christ</HI> to a
Backside; ay <HI>Christ</HI> gets not <HI>his</HI> own amongst us, we Com∣mend
<HI>him</HI> not, neither will we match with <HI>him.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, <HI>I will make all Things New.</HI> This is as much
as all Things were Old: Sinhath made all things Old, <HI>Rom.</HI> 8.
They are like a Woman Groaning in Child-birth with Pain
and Vanity, because of our Sin; All the Creation are sickned
because of Sin; Because of our Sin, Vanity came on the <HI>Sun,
Moon,</HI> and other Creatures, they Sigh under this, and Pray
in their kind a Mallison, and a Wo to Man, for Sin has made
us all Miserable, The Heavens that are the fairest part of the
Great Web of the World, waxes Old as an Garment. The
<HI>Prophet</HI> saith, they are like an Old Clout▪ The <HI>Water</HI> saith,
Let me drown Sinners, they have sinned against my <HI>Lord:</HI>
The <HI>Fire</HI> saith, Let me Burn him, let me Burn <HI>Sodom,</HI> for
they have sinned against my <HI>Lord.</HI> All Things has lost their
Glory that they got in their first Creation. <HI>Jesus</HI> seeth all
Things gone Wrong, and quite out of Order: And Man fallen
from his <HI>Lord;</HI> and <HI>He</HI> did even with the World, as a Pylot
once with an Untentive Man at the Rudder, stirring the Ship
on an Sand-Bank, he stept in quickly and turned Her inconti∣nent,
or else, all would have gone to Confusion. So our <HI>Lord</HI>
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>
steped in when the Great Ship of this World was running
on a Sand-bed; The <HI>Sun</HI> and <HI>Moon</HI> looked Sad like, and
said, They would not Serve us; Our <HI>Lord</HI> Renewed them
by <HI>his</HI> Death, and made them all Laugh on the <HI>Elect</HI> again,
and gave them all a Suite of New Cloaths Drunkards, <HI>Christ</HI>
gave <HI>his</HI> Blessing to the Wine that ye Spew on the Walls. Ye
that Dishonours your <HI>Maker</HI> with your Vain Apparel, ye
know not what it Cost <HI>Christ;</HI> Our <HI>Lord</HI> bleed to buy a
Right of them that ye abuse in Vanity. All that sets the
World in their Hearts where the <HI>Lord</HI> should be, forgets that
<HI>Christ</HI> bought the World to be their Servant, and not to be as
their Darling and Wife that lyes in their Bosom: Ye that
makes the Earth and the broad Aikers of it your Souls Portion,
so as ye Desire no more but Land, ye forget <HI>Christ</HI> that bought
the World, and made it New to be a Foot-stool, and not a
Chair for your Souls to sit down upon: And if <HI>Christ</HI> has this
Art to make all Things New, come to <HI>Him</HI> all ye that are
Old, ye that has Old Hearts come. Indeed <HI>Christ</HI> may get
<HI>his</HI> Craft among us, if we would go to <HI>Him,</HI> for <HI>He</HI> makes
all Things New. The <HI>Devil</HI> borrows another Man's Heart
for <HI>Covetousness,</HI> and he has crooked it with the Thorny-Cares
of this World and holled it, and dung the Bottom out
of it. O if ye would put it in <HI>Christ</HI>'s Hand, <HI>he</HI> would put
it in <HI>his</HI> Furnace and Melt it again, and by <HI>his</HI> Art bring it out
a New Heart for <HI>himself</HI> to Dwell in: Alas! <HI>Christ</HI> gets not
<HI>his</HI> Trade or Calling amongst us: But why are not our Old
Hearts mended? Because we handle them as a Foolish Mo∣ther
doth a Datted Bairn; She will not let him go to School
to Learn, and why? Because she dow not want him out of
her Sight; She will therefore never let him do well, but feed
him to the Gallows. We dow not give away our Souls to
<HI>Christ</HI> who would fain have them, and easily Mend them;
but Lust keeps them like the Foolish Mother out of <HI>Christ</HI>'s
<PB N="10" REF="6"/>
Company. And <HI>Pride</HI> keeps another Man's Heart, and <HI>Co∣vetousness</HI>
another Man's Heart, that, that Dear Craftsman
<HI>Christ</HI> that made the Heart and made the Earth under our
Feet New, and the Mountains New, yet we will not let <HI>Him</HI>
make our Old Hearts New; Our Souls are all hinging in
Tattars, Worn and Old, with Sin, and we dow not put them
in <HI>Christ</HI>'s Hand that would make them Whole and Cleanse
them. Fy upon thee that thy <HI>Garden</HI> was Cursed in <HI>Adam</HI>'s
Days to bring forth Nettles and Thorns, and is Blessed to
bring out Fruit in <HI>Christ,</HI> and thy Soul gets not so much Good
of <HI>Christ</HI> as thy Yard; It is made New, and thy Soul remains
Old, and <HI>Christ</HI> gets not <HI>his</HI> Craft among us. <HI>He</HI> bids <HI>John</HI>
write these Things about the State of the <HI>Glorified,</HI> and calls
them <HI>Faithfull and True. He</HI> would not Intrust <HI>his</HI> Word to
Man's Memory and Conscience; <HI>He</HI> will have it written.
<HI>Blasphemous Papists</HI> laugh not at this, nor call the <HI>Pope</HI>'s
<HI>Breast</HI> the <HI>Bible;</HI> Here a Warrand for the written <HI>Scrip∣ture.</HI>
But indeed it tells us that Mans Falshood wore
his Conscience, had his Conscience been a Faithfull <HI>Register,</HI>
there should have been no need of a written <HI>Bible:</HI> But now
the <HI>Lord</HI> has lippened more to Dead Paper than to a Living
Mans Soul. Our Conscience now under Sin has not been a
Good <HI>Bible:</HI> Because Man is ready to run away from his Con∣science;
because what is written on our Conscience as that
there is a GOD, a <HI>Judgement,</HI> a <HI>Heaven,</HI> or <HI>Hell: Satan</HI>
and <HI>Sin</HI> comes in as Two <HI>False Witnesses</HI> and blots our that,
and writes that in the Fool's Heart, that says, <HI>there is no
GOD.</HI> And there is many Holes in our Souls, the Word of
GOD comes in and runs out again at back spouts, except <HI>Je∣sus</HI>
make their Soul Water-fast, so that the Word of GOD may
Dwell in them plentifully, <HI>Colos.</HI> 3. 16. Is not our Hearts com∣pared
to a <HI>Field,</HI> wherein the Preacher sows the <HI>Seed,</HI> Mat.
13. and the <HI>Black Spirits</HI> of <HI>Hell</HI> comes and gathers up
<PB N="11" REF="6"/>
<HI>Christ</HI>'s <HI>Wheat.</HI> O but there are many running out Souls,
and much need we have of a <HI>written Bible;</HI> and therefore
make much of the <HI>written Word,</HI> and pray GOD to Copy
<HI>his Bible,</HI> and to write a New Book of <HI>his</HI> Doctrine in our
Hearts, and put it in the Conscience as <HI>he</HI> directs, <HI>Jer.</HI> 31.
1. <HI>Of his Prophesie. 2. A Description. 3. A Promise
of Matter. Christ</HI> says to <HI>John, It is done.</HI> That is Ex∣poned
in <HI>Rev.</HI> 16. and 17. The World is ended, so speaks
<HI>Christ</HI> of the World, and Glory of it passeth away in the
Twinkling of an Eye, and <HI>Christ</HI> cryeth to those that has the
World in both their Arms, <HI>It is done;</HI> It is a past Thing, there
is no more of it. It is but a word to our <HI>Lord, he</HI> said, <HI>Let
all Things be,</HI> and they were. <HI>He</HI> said, <HI>Let all Things be,</HI>
and they are at an end. And we are beginning with the
World, as if it would be evermore ours; and our <HI>Lord</HI> says,
in a Moment, let it be plucked from them, and it is done. It
is no for nothing that the taking down of this Inns of Heaven
and Earth is touched in so few words. <HI>It is done:</HI> For it is
an Easie Thing for the <HI>Almighty</HI> to take the Staffes in <HI>his</HI> own
<HI>Hand</HI> that holdeth up this Fair Tent, and when <HI>he</HI> pulleth it,
<HI>he</HI> Garreth it come down with a Titt. So <HI>Rev.</HI> 4. 7. Four
<HI>Angels</HI> is brought in holding the four <HI>Winds</HI> in their Hands,
as if they had the World in their Hands, and as if they had it
ready to Fold it up as a Sheet. And O! what a fighting and
business do they make to get a Clout of this Sheet; He star∣ring
out his Eyes, and he setting out his Neck, for a piece of
this Hollie Clout and Sheet, and for a Gloib of the Earth.
But see <HI>Rev. 6. 14. The Heavens shall depart away like a
Scroll</HI> of Parchment that is rolled together, and the Fair
Stories thereof are like Figs, with the shake of the <HI>Almighty</HI>'s
Arm they shall fall together to the Ground; and what more,
with a Touch of the <HI>Almighty's</HI> Hand, or a Put of <HI>his</HI> Little
Finger, with the Blast of <HI>his</HI> Mouth, saying, <HI>It is done.</HI> The
<PB N="12" REF="7"/>
Cupples of the Walls of the House cometh down. Now I
cannot but speak of Fools that has their Heads full of Wind-Mills,
and crys it is beginning, <HI>and to Morrow shall be as
this Day, and much more abundant,</HI> Isaiah 56. And there
is no end of Buying and Building; I came not here to bide any
Body be Unthrifty; but not to be like Bairns building San∣dy
Bourocks at a Water-side, when presently a Speat of Water
comes and spills all their Sport, or a Showre chases them in
from their Play. Men are even bigging Castles in the Air. In
very deed we are like Bairns holding the Water at a River-side
with their Hand, they think (Daft Things) they hold the
Water, while in the mean time it runs throw their Fingers. And
what says GOD of Honour, Riches, Pleasure, Lands, Fair
Houses, Sums of Money? Even that in a word, <HI>all is done.</HI>
Ask of them that had the World once at Will, and had broad
Lands, and what is to the fore? And what is to the fore of
so many Thousands? Nothing but their Name; And what if
their Name he Lost too? What has the World of them but their
Name? And what is that? Ten or Eleven or Twelve Letters
of the <HI>A, B, C;</HI> and for their Bodies, howbeit they were
Living, Kingdoms would not content them, and yet the Clay
in which the Bodies are Dissolved, would not now fill a Glove.
I think that a True Word, and a Strange spoken Word, Isa:
40. 22. <HI>GOD sits in the Circle of the Heaven, and all the
World are as Grashoppers.</HI> We even Creep like Grashoppers
up and down the Globe of this Earth, and cry to Men of the
Vanities of all Things, while <HI>Death</HI> come like a Little <HI>Com∣mon
Thief</HI> without any Dinn or Feet, and plucks them away,
and there is no more of them, and then they say, <HI>it is done.</HI>
All Men will say, it is True that I say: But I think to be Dead
ere they believe it, or be brought to Hate the World. I think
the World is the <HI>Devil</HI>'s Great <HI>Herry-water-net</HI> that has
Taken Thousands and Slain them: Ye say ye are sure of it.
Then I say ye are a Dyeted Horse for Heaven.</P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="7"/>
The <HI>Second</HI> Thing that is in the <HI>Verse,</HI> is a Description
of <HI>Christ, I Am Alpha and Omega, the Beginning and the
End.</HI> Our <HI>Lord</HI> here being to make an Offer of the <HI>Water
of Life: He</HI> first sheweth what <HI>He</HI> is, even the first &amp; the last
Letter of the <HI>A, B, C; The Ancient of Days, the Eternal
Son of the Eternal GOD.</HI> It Teaches us that we may Crack
more of our Old Holding, and Old Charter, nor all the VVorld
can do: For why? VVhen began <HI>Christ</HI> to bear a Good-will to
a <HI>Sinner?</HI> Even when <HI>he</HI> began to be <HI>GOD;</HI> and <HI>he</HI> was <HI>GOD</HI>
from all Eternity. Suppose the <HI>Sun</HI> in the Firmament were
Eternal, the Light of it behoved to be Eternal: For the Light
of the <HI>Sun</HI> is as Old as the <HI>Sun.</HI> Love is a Beam of Light,
and Heat that comes from <HI>Christ</HI> the <HI>Sun of Righteousness:</HI>
Therefore Ever-living <HI>Christ</HI> and Ever-living <HI>Love;</HI> For <HI>Love</HI>
comes not on <HI>Christ</HI> the Day which was not in <HI>him</HI> Yesterday.
Man's Love, and a King's Love are hunted for very much,
and yet they die, and their love dies with them, and often
their love dies before themselves: But who seeks <HI>Christ</HI>'s
<HI>Love</HI> that Changes not? Yea this is a Matter of Admiration
and VVonder that <HI>Christ</HI> should have thought on us VVorms
of Clay ere ever we were, and that our <HI>Salvation</HI> is as <HI>Old</HI>
as <HI>Evermore,</HI> and as <HI>Old</HI> as <HI>Christ,</HI> and <HI>Christ</HI> is as <HI>Old</HI> as
<HI>GOD:</HI> For indeed if <HI>GOD</HI> should begin at any Point of
Time to <HI>love Sinners, his Love</HI> should have had a Begin∣ning;
and if <HI>his love</HI> should have had a Beginning, <HI>Christ him∣self</HI>
should have had a Beginning; Because <HI>love</HI> with <HI>him</HI> is
one with <HI>his Essence</HI> and <HI>Nature:</HI> But it may be said, Can
the <HI>love</HI> of <HI>GOD</HI> be <HI>Older</HI> than the <HI>Death</HI> of <HI>Christ? An∣swer.
Christ</HI>'s <HI>Death</HI> doth not make <HI>GOD</HI> properly a <HI>Hat∣er</HI>
or <HI>Lover</HI> of <HI>Man;</HI> for then both <HI>his Will</HI> should be <HI>Chang∣able</HI>
and <HI>his Love</HI> have a Beginning. How then? <HI>Christ</HI>'s
<HI>Death</HI> doth not only let that <HI>GOD</HI> may kyth the <HI>Fruits</HI> of
<HI>his</HI> Eternal <HI>Love</HI> out upon us, but after such a VVay as <HI>he</HI>
<PB N="14" REF="8"/>
thought convenient for <HI>his Justice;</HI> and therefore, we are said
in Scripture to Reconciled to be GOD; and GOD is not said
to be Reconciled to us: <HI>His love</HI> is Everlasting; because by
order of Nature it is before the Seed, before we had done
either Good or Evil; So that <HI>Sin</HI> should not Change GOD's
Mind, but only by the order of <HI>Justice; Sin</HI> stood in the
Way to hinder us of <HI>Life Everlasting</HI> which is a Fruit of <HI>his
love:</HI> yea more, GOD with that same <HI>love</HI> in <HI>Christ, loveth</HI>
the <HI>Elect</HI> before and after Conversion: And therefore, we
have to Rejoice in feeling any of God's <HI>love</HI> to us in <HI>Christ.</HI>
It is Old Acquaintance betwixt <HI>him</HI> and us; and therefore,
as it is Folly in Man (as <HI>Solomon</HI> saith) to cast off his Old
Friend, and his Fathers Friend: So let us think it Madness to
cast off such an Old Friend as <HI>Christ,</HI> and let our Faith hold
fast by this under Temptations and Desertions; <HI>Alpha and
Omega</HI> Changeth not, the Change is in us.</P>
<P>The <HI>Third</HI> Thing in the Words is a <HI>Promise</HI> of the <HI>Water
of Life</HI> to the <HI>Thirsty,</HI> Isaiah 55. 1: <HI>and</HI> John 13. 7. <HI>Christ</HI>
at the Mercat-Cross crys the <HI>Well</HI> free; But Learn, 1. The
<HI>Thirsty</HI> and <HI>Hungry</HI> Souls are meetest for the <HI>Water of Life▪</HI>
What, (ye will say) are not all Thirsty? all wants the Life
of GOD and the Sap of Grace, and are burnt and withered
at the Root: But all knows not their own Want: But indeed
a special Comfort for the Weak Ones to say, O say they, I
know <HI>Christ</HI> doth Good to Believers, to Repenters, and to
such as love <HI>Him;</HI> But I dow not nor cannot win to Faith and
Repentance, Hope &amp; Patience; I have too short an Arm to Rax
so High. Then say I, Have ye a Desire, a Hunger for Faith
and Repentance and Love? now upon your Conscience speak
the Truth; I trow ye cannot deny it. Then your <HI>Lord</HI> bides
you come, the <HI>Well</HI> is open unto you; for Hunger and Thirst
being next to Motion, and are the Two Properties that begins
first with Life. So every Thing that is New Born is Lively
<PB N="15" REF="8"/>
and hath a Stomack for Meat and Drink. O but say ye, I
am many Times in my Soul even at Deaths Door; I have nei∣ther
Faith nor Feeling: I am even at this, <HI>GOD loves</HI> me not,
and the <HI>Well</HI> is not ordained for me at these Times. Would
ye fain be at the <HI>Well?</HI> Now in my Mind ye cannot win away.
The Children of <HI>GOD</HI> when at the lowest Ebb, even when
Faith, Comfort, Joy, Love, and Disposition to Pray is away,
Is there not a longing for a Presence? I speak to the Consci∣ence
of <HI>GOD</HI>'s Child, Lye not. No, <HI>David,</HI> Psalms 6. when
he thought <HI>GOD</HI> strake him in <HI>his Wrath,</HI> was at <HI>how long
LORD?</HI> A cutted word. I think that he looked like a Poor
Hungry Beast, looking ov'r the Dyke, who would fain have had
a Mouth-full; he was even going about to seek a Slapp to
break ov'r the Dyke of his Doubtings And so it is with
<HI>GOD</HI>'s <HI>Bairns</HI> under their <HI>Thirst</HI> for the <HI>Well of Life.</HI> See
<HI>Cant.</HI> 3. when the <HI>Kirk</HI> can get no spearing of <HI>Christ,</HI> and
has no smell of <HI>Him,</HI> and cannot find the Print of <HI>His</HI> Foot;
yet <HI>she</HI> is at this, <HI>Saw ye Him whom my Soul loveth?</HI> and
Chap. 2. <HI>I charge you tell Him that I am Sick of Love.</HI> Then
let me now speak to Weak Ones, and I will tell you who are
<HI>Christ</HI>'s Companions that Drinks with <HI>Him,</HI> and shall get their
Heads and Hearts full <HI>of the Water of Life;</HI> even the Ten∣der
Christian that is ay seeking; The Bairn in <HI>Christ</HI>'s House
that is most Cumbersome, and makes most Dinn for his Meat,
is the best Bairn that <HI>Christ</HI> has; The Bairn that is Greeting
ilk hour of the day for a Piece and a Drink: We say of such
a silly Thing <HI>he</HI> would fain love. Ay the Cumbersomer that
<HI>Christ</HI>'s Bairns be, they are ay the Welcomer. Na, <HI>He</HI> loveth
the Bairns best that has no shame, and is ay crying, alas black
Hunger, Dear <HI>Lord Jesus,</HI> I am burnt with <HI>Thirst;</HI> O for an
open Cold Fountain. O it is a sweet thing ay to be whing∣ing,
and crying, and seeking about <HI>Christ</HI>'s Pantry Doors, and
to hold ay an Eye upon <HI>Christ</HI> when <HI>he</HI> goes into the House
<PB N="16" REF="9"/>
of <HI>Wine,</HI> into <HI>His Fathers</HI> fair Luckie <HI>Wine-Celler</HI> where
there are many <HI>Wines,</HI> and bout in at <HI>Christ</HI>'s back. But in
a word, Have ye a Good Stomack? Much <HI>Hunger</HI> &amp; <HI>Thrist:</HI>
Well, ye shall get much Satisfaction of Grace in <HI>Christ.</HI> Now
who are they that are Debarred from <HI>Christ</HI>'s <HI>Well?</HI> Answer.
These who has gotten an Ill Drink from the <HI>Devil,</HI> full of
Lusts, Pride, and Covetousness, full of Love of the World;
Such are they that has no Stomack for <HI>Christ:</HI> Alas and woes
me, <HI>Christ</HI> standeth at the <HI>Wells</HI> side, and cryeth, the back
of <HI>My Hand</HI> to you. The <HI>Lord Jesus</HI> give you a Vomite-Drink,
that you may grow Wholsome and Hungry again for
<HI>Christ;</HI> For while then, ye are never meet for <HI>Christ.</HI> Is
there not a Time when you cannot get Presence, and ye have
no pith to put up the Door and bout in, but puts it half up,
and blinks in? Love ye to Pray, or desire ye but a Desire of
Prayer? Hold on then there, ye are Right; The True Desire
is Absolute, and not Conditional; Not like the Sluggard that
wad have a Crope upon Condition he might have a Feather-bed
to ly on for fear of Cold: Even so they would have Hea∣ven
upon Condition they might keep their Lusts, and take
their Lusts with them. But, <HI>Secondly,</HI> Hunger is ay seek∣ing
throw the whole House, for the Belly can hardly play the
Hypocrite. The Natural-Man is in Darkness, he is in a Sleep;
it is Night with him, and he is like a Cumbersome Bairn
Greeting in the Night for a Drink, and crying, Psal. 4. <HI>Who
will shew us any Good Thing?</HI> and <HI>Satan</HI> is ready at his
Elbow with his Dishfull of the Dirty Myrie-Matters of Lust to
the World, and he Drinks while he Sweats and Tynes Breath,
and Tynes a Sight and Desire of <HI>Christ,</HI> the Fountain of the
<HI>Water of Life,</HI> John 7. 37. It is true this Fountain of Life
is said to proceed <HI>out of the Throne of GOD, and from the
Lamb:</HI> But it is all one, for the Streams of the <HI>Water of Life,</HI>
proceed from the <HI>Fountain Christ▪</HI> How then is the <HI>Water
<PB N="17" REF="9"/>
Christ? Christ-Man</HI> Dying and sending out <HI>His</HI> Heart-blood
for Quenching of the Thirst of such Poor Sinners as fi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>deth
the Fire of Hell at the Stomack of their Soul, burning them
up with the Fire of the <HI>Wrath</HI> of <HI>GOD</HI> for Sin; this is the <HI>Well,</HI>
Why <HI>He</HI> is called <HI>a Fountain of the Water of Life.</HI> As,
1. Because a Man burnt with Thirst, nothing can quench him,
no, not a World of Gold is so Good as a drink of Pure cold Clean
Fountain-Water. In a word, a Soul wakened under Sin, find∣eth
nothing in the World Satisfactory to the Souls Appetite,
but in <HI>Christ.</HI> Tell me, art thou a Thirsty Sinner after <HI>Christ,</HI>
thy Soul is Dead Sick, while thou get <HI>Him.</HI> Lay a Man down
on a Soft Bed, dry the Sweat off him, give him a Cold Re∣freshing
Drink: Now ye cannot speak such a word to a Soul
bursten thing under Sin, as to lay it upon a Crucified <HI>Christ;</HI>
O that is a Soft Bed; his sinfull Soul being stretched upon the
open warm flowing Blood and Wounds of <HI>Christ;</HI> O that
is a Soft Bed. O but a part of <HI>Christ<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>s Blood is a Refreshing
Cooling Drink to him. To know a Slave of Hell that he is
made a Free Heir of Heaven, O that is Sweet: Hence it is that
those that are wakened with the Furies of Hell, howbeit they
know not yet what <HI>Christ</HI> is to them; Yet this World cannot
Calm their Conscience, because for Men that are Soul-sick, and
Sin-sick, there is no Physick, but one only a Drink <HI>of the Well
of Life;</HI> and because they ken not the gate to <HI>this Well of
Life,</HI> they loup out of this Life out of Despair into the Fire
of Hell, throw the Madness of an awakened Conscience. For
a Thirsty Sick-soul finds Two Things in <HI>Christ,</HI> never to
be found in all the World, or any Thing else. 1. <HI>Christ</HI>
takes off the Hardness of Sin: None has Power to do this but
<HI>He:</HI> All the Pardons of Sin are in <HI>Christ</HI>'s keeping, &amp; of <HI>Christs</HI>
making; It is <HI>His Office</HI> to forgive Sin. 2. Besides they find
in <HI>Him</HI> an Influence and Abundance of Happiness in <HI>Him;</HI> So
as what they sought before in the Creature, they find no
<PB N="18" REF="10"/>
where else but in <HI>Him;</HI> Then speak to them of Gold, it is no∣thing
to <HI>Christ;</HI> Speak of Lands and Lordships a Saviour, &amp;
such a Saviour has and is another Name to a Sinner that is
wakened.</P>
<P>Again, The <HI>Text</HI> calls <HI>Him, The Water of Life.</HI> We see
here, there is some Water that is Rotten and Ill Tasted; Will
a Thirsty Man Drink of it? he shall not be the better: But
the Wholsomest Water is the Running Spring: So all that
Sinners can get beside <HI>Christ</HI> is Standing-water. Let them
Drink in Gold, and Kingdoms, and Lands. they shall never be
Satisfying to a Sick Soul as <HI>He</HI> will be; And who have drunk
in these at Death, they would be content to Spue them out a∣gain,
they ly so heavy upon their Stomack; But <HI>Christ</HI> is the
Coolling Wholesome Spring, <HI>the Well of Water springing
up to Eternal Life.</HI> Now to make our Use of this: See∣ing
<HI>Christ</HI> is such <HI>a Living Well of Water,</HI> How is it in the
Gospel that there are so many withered dryed Souls? I An∣swer,
for <HI>GOD</HI>'s Part, indeed <HI>GOD</HI> has not put an <HI>Iron-Lock</HI>
upon the <HI>Well of Life;</HI> But <HI>Christ</HI> by <HI>His Word</HI> and
<HI>Sacraments</HI> opens the <HI>Well</HI> in the midest of us, and for Se∣venty
Years and more in this <HI>Kingdom</HI> the <HI>Well</HI> has been O∣pen:
<HI>Christ</HI> and <HI>His Messengers</HI> has been Crying to Dry
Souls: But now for ought we see, <HI>He</HI> will Close the <HI>Well</HI> a∣gain;
for <HI>He</HI> has been setting out the Means of Life, and open∣ing
<HI>His</HI> Booth-doors to give us freely, even to such as will
take it, but <HI>He</HI> gets no Sale: Therefore <HI>He</HI> must put up <HI>his</HI>
Wares and go away, for Men are not <HI>Thirsty</HI> for <HI>his Waters;</HI>
but Thirst for Court and Honour; Another for Lust and Mo∣neys;
A Third Lusts after Sinfull Pleasures. 1. There be
few Stomacks gapping for <HI>Christ.</HI> 2. They have not a Vessel to
cast down in the <HI>VVell,</HI> and take up the <HI>VVater:</HI> This is a
Fruitless Generation. Oh we loath <HI>Christ,</HI> and <HI>Christ</HI> loaths
us. We need speak no more of the Call of the <HI>VVord;</HI> All
the <HI>Land, Court, King, Noblemen</HI> and <HI>Kirkmen</HI> has spew∣ed
<PB N="19" REF="10"/>
the <HI>Waters;</HI> by Despising <HI>Mercy,</HI> and Contemning the
<HI>Gospel:</HI> And in very deed, when we cast in Clay and Mudd
in <HI>Christ</HI>'s Well, and mixes <HI>His VVorship</HI> with the Poyson
<HI>of the VVhores VVell of Rome.</HI> What do we else, but Pro∣vock
the <HI>LORD</HI> to Close the <HI>VVell.</HI> I will give it freely:
So are all <HI>Christ</HI>'s <HI>Mercies</HI> given of <HI>Grace; His Mercy</HI> is
for Nothing, and of free <HI>Grace.</HI> I grant the <HI>VVell</HI> is Dear to
<HI>Christ; GOD</HI>'s <HI>Justice</HI> digged it out of <HI>his Side,</HI> and <HI>Heart,</HI>
and <HI>Hands,</HI> and <HI>Feet:</HI> The <HI>Man Christ</HI> got not this <HI>VVater</HI>
for Nothing; Yet <HI>He</HI> gives it to us for Nothing; Because <HI>He</HI>
minds not to make a Gain of us: We live upon <HI>Christ</HI>'s Win∣ning;
For know ye that <HI>Christ</HI> Redeemed many, do so by the
Rule of Justice, since <HI>He</HI> gave <HI>Himself,</HI> and has bought all
<HI>with His own Blood:</HI> So that in this Sense <HI>Christ</HI> was bought
to us with Blood, else we could not get <HI>Him,</HI> for <HI>He</HI> was
both the <HI>Price</HI> and the <HI>VVares:</HI> So that as far as we can see
by Order of Justice, it is Decreed by the <HI>Lord</HI> that <HI>Christ</HI>
could not have lived, and given to us the <HI>VVaters of Life.</HI>
It was Dear Water to <HI>him;</HI> for in the <HI>Garden GOD</HI> Deserted
<HI>him,</HI> and <HI>Blood</HI> came out on the <HI>Cross▪ GOD</HI> Bruised <HI>him,</HI>
and <HI>Blood</HI> came out, and that is the <HI>VVell</HI> we have here:
And we have here a Great Impediment removed. We think
we would have something to give to <HI>Christ</HI> for the <HI>VVater of
Life,</HI> some of our own Righteousness, some of our own Wor∣thiness.
But that is plaistered Humility, watered Copper;
and in doing so, we Refuse <HI>Grace,</HI> and makes <HI>Grace</HI> to be
no more <HI>Grace;</HI> for if it be given for any Worth in us, it is
no more <HI>Grace:</HI> And therefore let Men here see then, that
the <HI>Kingdom</HI> of <HI>Grace</HI> is a Good Cheap World, where the
Best Things are gotten for Nothing: And therefore I think
in this Dear World, wherein all Things goes for Money; when
Court cost Expences, Lands are Dear, and Gold is not gotten
for Nought, and Laws are Dearer than ever they were: yea,
<PB N="20" REF="11"/>
Papet and Ink are now Dearer than Jewels; and Gold Rings
were long syne Nothing, now is bought for Nought: Yet
<HI>CHRIST</HI> for all that, will not Change <HI>his VVorld;</HI>
but all Things with <HI>Him</HI> are given <HI>Gratis,</HI> and ye
are Welcome when all is done. We get no Garments for
Nought; No Physick for Nought. <HI>Christ</HI> gives <HI>VVhite Ray∣ment,
Eye Salve,</HI> and all for Nought, without Money▪ <HI>Sin∣ners</HI>
says, LORD, <HI>VVhat take ye for the VVater of Life?
He</HI> Answers. <HI>Even Nothing, and yet VVelcome. Christ</HI> plays
not the <HI>Merchant</HI> with <HI>his VVares, he</HI> makes no Gain, but
Crys, the <HI>VVell</HI> is free. No, says the <HI>Pope,</HI> not a Drope,
till ye tell down Money. That <HI>Bloody Beast</HI> would Sell the
Water of <HI>Rome</HI> for Gold, as meikle Money, as meikle Gtace
and Forgiveness. Want ye Money? He answers, Ye shall
not come here. Nothing in <HI>Rome</HI> without Money. Fy, fy,
the stink of the <HI>Devil</HI>'s World. Nay, but CHRIST is for
Nothing. Nay, Justice giveth Money, and Officers give Mo∣ney;
it is a Dear World: But CHRIST and <HI>his VVorld</HI> cares
no more for Money nor before.</P>
<P>Verse 7. <HI>He that overcometh shall Inherit all Things.</HI>
Still in this Book, <HI>John</HI> urgeth Fighting and Overcoming for
Heaven. We wonder much that GOD will not have Poor
Men going to Heaven, but by <HI>Fighting,</HI> seeing <HI>he</HI> might have
sent us to Heaven by a second Heaven; But this is but a thought
of Men, that would have made a New Back-gate of their own
to Heaven: But GOD advised well, when <HI>he</HI> made this Causay
to it, and ordained all <HI>his Saints,</HI> and <HI>his own Sons</HI> to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o
that Way; But it is easier for us to Complain on GOD's <HI>De∣cree</HI>
than to Obey, and to Dispute than Believe. Men has
too Thin Skins, and for Health they will cut a Vein, or let
a Leg or an Arm be cut off for fear of a Feaster, and yet for
<HI>Life Everlasting,</HI> they are so that they dow not Venture a
<HI>Moments Pain.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="21" REF="11"/>
<HI>Secondly,</HI> There are <HI>Excellent Promises</HI> made to the <HI>O∣vercomers;</HI>
To him that taketh Heaven with Stroake of
Sword and Blood; For Heaven is a besieged <HI>City</HI> or <HI>Castle:</HI>
Armies of <HI>Sin</HI> with all their <HI>Armour,</HI> and the Deceiving and
Malicious <HI>VVorld;</HI> The <HI>VVorld</HI> has <HI>Evah</HI>'s <HI>Apple</HI> in the
one Hand, and <HI>Fire</HI> and <HI>Sword</HI> in the other, and the <HI>Devil</HI>
is the <HI>Captain</HI> of the <HI>Army.</HI> Now here is a <HI>Price</HI> set, and
an <HI>Offer</HI> made to him that <HI>overcometh,</HI> to him that will mount
up by <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Hope,</HI> and leap up in CHRIST's <HI>Chariot,</HI>
and betide him <HI>Life,</HI> betide him <HI>Death,</HI> he will go throw:
But they are <HI>Cowards</HI> that take a <HI>Backside,</HI> and lets the <HI>De∣vil</HI>
coup them in a <HI>Gutter.</HI> But yet to lead Men on, here
is a <HI>Promise</HI> of Two Things.</P>
<P>First, <HI>He shall Inherit all Things.</HI> Then ye see, that the
<HI>Christian</HI>'s <HI>Captain</HI> is a Man of a Fair Rent, 1 Cor. 3. 21. <HI>For
all Things are Yours, whether</HI> Paul <HI>or</HI> Apollos, <HI>or</HI> Cephas,
<HI>or the VVorld, or Life, or Death: Things present, or Things
to come.</HI> And to let us see <HI>he</HI> bides by the thing <HI>he</HI> has said;
<HI>He</HI> says again, <HI>All Things are Yours.</HI> Ye see then, one has
a <HI>Kingdom</HI> as <HI>Asa,</HI> but wants Health, and is Sick of his Feet,
he has not <HI>all Things.</HI> Another has Strength of Body above
any Living, yet had many Troubles, and wanted his Eyes as
<HI>Sampson;</HI> and therefore had not <HI>all Things.</HI> O the Business
<HI>Adam</HI>'s <HI>Sons</HI> are at for <HI>Inheritances:</HI> Here a <HI>Mealline,</HI> there
a <HI>Lairdship,</HI> there a <HI>New Lordship,</HI> that they call their <HI>all
Things.</HI> I think this is a Greedy Stile, and Proud like, <HI>Lord∣ship,</HI>
or <HI>Lairdship,</HI> that they call <HI>all Things:</HI> Yet Greedy
<HI>Adam</HI>'s <HI>Sons</HI> has more Greediness here than Wit. They run
all upon their <HI>Lordships,</HI> that they call the <HI>Lordship</HI> of ma∣ny
Things, Luke 10. <HI>Martha, Martha, thou art troubled.
VVorldlings,</HI> ye are ay troubled about this, to be called <HI>my
Lord</HI> of many Things. But we shall see if the <HI>Text</HI> be True.
<HI>I Am Alpha and Omega;</HI> Then, <HI>First,</HI> The Apostle here
<PB N="22" REF="12"/>
puts in <HI>Death. Death is the Wages of Sin.</HI> I think <HI>Death</HI>
an <HI>Ill Mealline;</HI> better want it out of the <HI>Charter. How
then have they all Things?</HI> I Answer, <HI>Death</HI> is also a part
of the <HI>Lordship</HI> this way; because it is <HI>my Lord of all Things,</HI>
and a <HI>Coatch</HI> to Glory; CHRIST <HI>Himself</HI> being the <HI>Coatch-man,</HI>
and Driving the <HI>Horse; Death</HI> is the <HI>Servant;</HI> as the
<HI>Wind</HI> serveth to bring the <HI>Sea-man</HI> Home; So <HI>Death</HI> serv∣eth
him that hath the <HI>New Lordship. Death</HI> is CHRISTs
<HI>Ferry-Boat</HI> to Carry us Home; For in CHRIST he sets his
Foot on <HI>Death</HI>'s Neck; It is a Bridge o're the <HI>River</HI> of <HI>Hell</HI>
that he walketh on to <HI>Heaven,</HI> and it is his: The <HI>Christian</HI>
is advanced in CHRIST<HI>'s Court,</HI> and gets the New Stile, to be
<HI>my Lord of all Things,</HI> the <HI>Prince,</HI> the <HI>Duke of all Things.</HI>
Yet I shall get you a <HI>Lordship</HI> beneath them all; but much
sought for: The <HI>Lordship</HI> of <HI>Vanity</HI> or <HI>Nothing,</HI> Prov. 23. 5.
<HI>Wilt thou set thine Eyes on that which is Nought: For
verily Riches has Wings;</HI> He that is <HI>Rich</HI> has <HI>Nought.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, <HI>If he Inherit all Things,</HI> Then the whole <HI>World</HI>
in his, and so he wanteth <HI>Nothing.</HI></P>
<P>A <HI>Third</HI> Question, <HI>How is it then that the Saints are
Hungry and Poor?</HI> Answer, This <HI>Promise</HI> is so taken from
them, 2 Sam. 3, 14. Psal. 89. 27, 28. <HI>I will set His one
Hand on the Sea, and His Right Hand on the River.</HI> Then
see how broad CHRIST<HI>'s</HI> Two <HI>Arms</HI> are. <HI>His</HI> one <HI>hand</HI> u∣pon
all the <HI>Sea,</HI> and <HI>his</HI> other <HI>hand</HI> upon the <HI>River,</HI> and
that <HI>Promise</HI> is made to CHRIST as <HI>Principal-Cautioner</HI>
of the <HI>Covenant:</HI> For it is said, Verse 26. He <HI>shall say un∣to
Me, Thou art My Father and My GOD, and the Rock
of My Salvation.</HI> Verse 27. <HI>Also I will make him My First-born
Higher than the Kings of the Earth.</HI> Which is Ex∣poned
of CHRIST, Heb. 1. 5. Rev. 10. 2. <HI>He has his right
foot on the Sea, and his left foot on the Land.</HI> Put these
Two together, and see how Wide <HI>his Arms</HI> and <HI>Legs,</HI> or
<PB N="23" REF="12"/>
<HI>Feet</HI> are, they go over the whole <HI>World</HI> as <HI>his Inheritance</HI>
which <HI>he</HI> Wan to <HI>himself,</HI> and <HI>his Heirs</HI> after <HI>him</HI> with <HI>his
Blood.</HI> Now CHRIST got <HI>Land</HI> not to <HI>himself:</HI> What needs
<HI>him Land</HI> to give <HI>his Blood</HI> for <HI>Clay?</HI> But <HI>he</HI> wan it to us,
and took <HI>Infeftment</HI> in the Earth in Name of <HI>his Friends.</HI>
And now it is True, they are not <HI>Possessors of all Things.</HI>
But, <HI>Secondly,</HI> For Peoples <HI>Wants,</HI> ye see their Interest is in
and over <HI>all Things;</HI> Yet their <HI>Tutour</HI> lets them go with a
Toom-<HI>purse;</HI> He knows the <HI>Heir</HI> is a Young one, and can∣not
keep <HI>Gold,</HI> and therefore he gives them <HI>Food</HI> and <HI>Rayment</HI>
for their present Necessity; but keeps the <HI>Lordship</HI> for the
present. Our <HI>Tutour</HI> CHRIST is made of GOD our <HI>Tutour,</HI>
our <HI>Purse-Master:</HI> It is all one whether we have it in our
<HI>Chist-neuk,</HI> or if it be in CHRIST's <HI>Purse</HI> to keep while we
need it, providing we want not:</P>
<P><HI>Thirdly,</HI> A Third <HI>Question,</HI> and a Third <HI>Doubt</HI> is, at least,
<HI>Seeing they are under so many Troubles in this Life, and
has no Ease, they have not all Things?</HI> I Answer. Yet I
must Defend it, and say, if they have the <HI>Inheritance,</HI> that
they have <HI>all Things;</HI> because the Sweet of the <HI>Comfort</HI> and
<HI>Troubles</HI> are theirs.</P>
<P>A <HI>Fourth</HI> Question or Objection. <HI>They have not Heaven
and Glory, at least, in this Life, and therefore they are
not Inheritors of all Things?</HI> I Answer. The <HI>Promise</HI> is
not fullfilled in this <HI>Life:</HI> Yet when a Man has shorn a Stouk
or two of <HI>Corn,</HI> we say he has gotten <HI>Harvest</HI> and <HI>New Corn.</HI>
So the <HI>Believer</HI> gets <HI>Joy, Hope, Faith, Assurance</HI> of <HI>Heaven</HI>
and the <HI>First Fruits</HI> of the <HI>Spirit,</HI> are <HI>New Corn.</HI> So in the
beginning he gets <HI>all Things.</HI> 2. Having GOD and CHRIST
they have <HI>all Things:</HI> For ye see the Great-<HI>Ship</HI> Trailleth the
<HI>Cock-Boat</HI> after her: So the <HI>Great</HI> CHRIST bringeth <HI>all
Things</HI> after <HI>him</HI> at <HI>his Back:</HI> So I say, having CHRIST,
they have <HI>all Things;</HI> They have the <HI>Father,</HI> and the <HI>Spirit,</HI>
the <HI>Word, Life</HI> and <HI>Death. Amen. Let us Pray▪</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

