<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The triumphs of London performed on Tuesday, Octob. 29, 1695, for the entertainment of the right honourable Sir John Houblon, Kt., Lord Mayor of the city of London, containing a true description of the several pageants, with the speeches spoken on each pageant : all prepared at the proper costs and charges of the worshipful Company of Grocers : to which is added, a new song upon His Majesty's return / by E.S.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A59354</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing S2726</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R41718</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">31355821</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 31355821</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">110697</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A59354)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110697)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1752:26)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The triumphs of London performed on Tuesday, Octob. 29, 1695, for the entertainment of the right honourable Sir John Houblon, Kt., Lord Mayor of the city of London, containing a true description of the several pageants, with the speeches spoken on each pageant : all prepared at the proper costs and charges of the worshipful Company of Grocers : to which is added, a new song upon His Majesty's return / by E.S.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>16 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Jer. Wilkins, and are to be sold by Richard Baldwin ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1695.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Houblon, John, --  Sir, d. 1712.</TERM><TERM>Festivals --  England --  London.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A59354">
<STC T="W">S2726</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">31355821</BIBNO>
<VID>110697</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
<HI>Triumphs of London.</HI>
Performed on <HI>Tuesday, Octob.</HI> 29. 1695.
FOR THE
Entertainment of the Right Honourable
S<SUP>R.</SUP> John Houblon, K<SUP>T.</SUP>
<HI>LORD MAYOR</HI> of the City of
LONDON.</P>
<P>CONTAINING
A True Description of the Several Pageants; with the Speeches
Spoken on each PAGEANT.</P>
<P>All Prepared, at the proper Costs and Charges of the
WORSHIPFUL COMPANY
OF
GROCERS.
To which is added,
<HI>A New Song upon His</HI> Majesty'<HI>s Return.</HI></P>
<P>By E. S.</P>
<P>Published by Authority.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by <HI>Jer. Wilkins;</HI> And are to be Sold by <HI>Richard Baldwin,</HI>
at the <HI>Oxford-Arms</HI> in <HI>VVarwick</HI>-Lane, 1695.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE
RIGHT HONOURABLE
Sir Iohn Houblon, Kt
LORD MAYOR
OF THE
City of London.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>MY LORD,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IN this Dedication to the Right Honou∣rable
Sr. <HI>John Houblon,</HI> One of the
<HI>Lords</HI> of the ADMIRALTY,
Governour of the <HI>Royal</HI> BANK of
<HI>England,</HI> and now the great <HI>Lieutenant Royal</HI>
of this <HI>Metropolitan City;</HI> methinks, I am en∣terd
into so spacious a Field, with such vari∣ous
attracting Prospects before me, as even di∣vide
my Veneration. The Homage is on all
<PB REF="3"/>
Sides so equally Due, that I know not Where
to Kneel first. For Your <HI>Lordship</HI> by an
<HI>Accumulation</HI> of <HI>Glories,</HI> has, perhaps, so far
out-run the Common Race of <HI>Honour;</HI> that
in Your Accession to the <HI>CHAIR,</HI> as
considerable a Triumph as it gives you, in∣stead
of being Your Highest <HI>Ascendant</HI> of
<HI>Renown,</HI> is only an <HI>Addition</HI> to Your more
ample Pile of <HI>Trophies;</HI> whilst You have so
far out-stript the <HI>Candidates</HI> of <HI>Dignity</HI> before
You, that You <HI>bring</HI> the <HI>Right Honourable</HI>
to Your <HI>Praetorian Seate,</HI> not come to <HI>find</HI> it
there.</P>
<P>Not that this publick Address, I now make
Your <HI>Lordship,</HI> is intended for any Piece, ei∣ther
of <HI>Panegyrick,</HI> or <HI>Herauldry,</HI> to Illustrate
or Blazon the High Promotions to which
Your <HI>Lordship</HI> has so eminently Arrived: No,
my <HI>Lord,</HI> I have a fairer Theme, a Specula∣tion
above them. For 'tis not <HI>Preferment,
Titles,</HI> or <HI>State:</HI> 'Tis the <HI>Virtue,</HI> the <HI>Merit,
Principle</HI> and <HI>Integrity,</HI> that both mount and
<PB REF="3"/>
fill the Seats of <HI>Power</HI> and <HI>Trust,</HI> are the <HI>embo∣dyed
Mass;</HI> when the others are but the meer
<HI>Drapery</HI> of HONOUR.</P>
<P>'Tis in this last Capacity, (not the <HI>Pomp</HI> and
<HI>Splendour</HI> of Advancement,) but Your <HI>Lord∣ships</HI>
Double Qualifications of <HI>Fidelity</HI> and
<HI>Ability</HI> to <HI>Execute</HI> in those Exalted Posts, that
render You the Subject of an Universal Ap∣plause.
And though my present Address is
chiefly to Congratulate Your <HI>Lordship's In∣auguration</HI>
into this <HI>August Magistracy,</HI> in which
both the Pride and Gratitude of the <HI>Honoura∣ble
Company</HI> of GROCERS make their
profoundest Tenders of Respect to so Con∣spicuous
a Member and Ornament to their
<HI>Society:</HI> Yet all this is but an inconsiderable
Tribute, compared to what the World has
yet to Pay You; For, Your <HI>Lordship</HI> has
taken Care for a more lasting <HI>Triumph;</HI> so
vast is the Difference betwixt Glittering for a
Day, and Shining for a Life.</P>
<P><PB REF="4"/>
I should dwell longer upon this inviting
Theme, were I not not sensible that, to all
Your other Accomplishments, Your <HI>Lordship</HI>
has that innate <HI>Modesty,</HI> that You rather stu∣dy
to <HI>deserve Encomiums</HI> than to <HI>hear</HI> them;
which only Consideration shall check my Pen,
and make me the sooner hasten to Subscribe
my self,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>MY LORD,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED>Your Lordships
Most Obedient and Dutiful Servant
E. SETTLE.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To the Worshipful Company of
GROCERS.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>GENTLEMEN,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IT is now but Three Years since I had this Ho∣nour
before; and If I am come so soon again to
tender my new Service to my Worthy old <HI>Masters,</HI> I
have only this to say, That You live in a Warm
Sun and a Fruitful Soyl; where <HI>WORTH</HI> and
<HI>VIRTUE</HI> spring up apace amongst You, when you
have so often the Pride of Filling the <HI>CHAIR</HI> from
a <HI>Member</HI> of the <HI>Honourable COMPANY</HI> of
<HI>GROCERS.</HI></P>
<P>Your <HI>Griffons</HI> are truly a Bird of Wing, when they
Fly so <HI>High</HI> and Mount so <HI>Fast:</HI> But indeed it is less
to be wondred that <HI>Growing HONOUR</HI> should
<HI>Root</HI> so <HI>Strong</HI> and <HI>Flourish</HI> so <HI>Eminently</HI> with You,
when the very <HI>ROYAL-FOUNTAIN</HI> of it,
makes <HI>One</HI> amongst You; whilst not only the <HI>Lord</HI> of
it, but likewise the <HI>SOVERAIGN</HI> of the <HI>Chair</HI>
too, <HI>Great WILLIAM</HI> himself if a <HI>Member</HI> of
Your <HI>SOCIETY:</HI> And though, it's true, so many
<HI>Crown'd Heads</HI> before had so often Blest Your Happy
<HI>Roof:</HI> Yet let it suffice, that this last <HI>Glory</HI> consum∣mates
Your whole <HI>Renown:</HI> And whilst You stand
thus highly Graced with that <HI>Illustrious</HI> and <HI>Adorable
Name</HI> Inrolled amongst You; As by the Reach of Your
<PB REF="5"/>
<HI>Charter</HI> the whole <HI>Spicy-Nest</HI> was all Your own before,
I may now add this Prouder <HI>Blazon</HI> to Your <HI>Scutcheon,</HI>
that You have the <HI>Phaenix</HI> too.</P>
<P>Dic quibuscum sis, &amp; dicam quis es.
(Worth is known by the Company it Keeps.)
Was a Celebrated True Adage of Old, which you Gen∣tlemen,
have amply Veryfied: For it is sufficient for
the truly Honourable <HI>G R O C E R S,</HI> to their Noblest
Reputation, to tell the World, that the Darling of
<HI>Britain,</HI> the Champion of <HI>Christendom,</HI> and the Pride
of <HI>Europe,</HI> the <HI>English LYON</HI> Herds with You:
And the particular Inclination of the <HI>Albion CAESAR</HI>
in Electing Your <HI>SOCIETY</HI> His <HI>Favourite Choice,</HI>
is an ample Demonstration, that His Encouragement
for such an Election, was, that undoubtedly he found
those Virtues amongst You, <HI>Nearest</HI> His <HI>Own;</HI> and
<HI>Worthiest</HI> such <HI>Royal Favour.</HI></P>
<P>And, <HI>Gentlemen,</HI> whatever other Conspicuous
<HI>Merits</HI> You challenge, 'tis enough that this single <HI>Plume</HI>
in Your Fair <HI>Crest,</HI> shall Entitule You to no common
Share of <HI>Fame;</HI> and 'tis with my Congratulation of
This, and all your Other <HI>Happiness,</HI> I subscribe my
Self,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>GENTLEMEN,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED>Your most Devoted Humble Servant
E. SETTLE.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="triumph">
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>The Movements of the Morning.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Between Seven and Eight in the Morning the whole
Company designed for the Duty of the Day, meet
at Grocers Hall.</HEAD>
<P>1. THE Master, Wardens, and Assistants, in Gowns
Faced with Foins, and their Hoods.</P>
<P>2. The Livery in their Gowns Faced with Budg,
and their Hoods.</P>
<P>3. Forty Foins Batchelors in Gowns and Scarlet Hoods.</P>
<P>4. Forty Budge-Batchelors in Gowns and Scarlet Hoods.</P>
<P>5. Forty Gentlemen Ushers in Velvet Coats, each of them
a Chain of Gold about his Shoulders, and a White Staff
in his Hand.</P>
<P>6. Several Drums and Fifes with Scarfs, and the Colours
of the Company in their Hats, Crimson and White.</P>
<P>7. The Serjeant Trumpet, and Twenty Four Trumpets
more, whereof Sixteen are His Majesties, the Serjeant-Trum∣pet
wearing Two Scarfs, a Crimson and a White.</P>
<P>8. The Drum-Major to the King, wearing a Shoulder-Scarf
of the Companies Colours, with others of His Maje∣sties
Drums and Fifes.</P>
<P>9. The Two City Marshals each of them Mounted on
Horse-back, with Rich Furniture, Hoosings, and Crupper,
all Embroider'd; Six Servitors likewise Mounted to Attend
with Scarfs, and Colours of the Companies.</P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="6"/>
10. The Foot-Marshal with a Scarf, and Six Attendants
in Colours.</P>
<P>11. The Master of Defence, with the same Scarfe and Co∣lours,
Eight Persons of the same Science to attend him.</P>
<P>12. Twenty Pensioners with Coats and Caps employed in
carrying the Standards and Banners.</P>
<P>This Ordered, and accomodated, they are committed to
the management of the Foot-Marshal, who distributes them
in Seven Divisions, and ranked all Two by Two, begining
with the inferior part of the Standard-Bearers. In the Head
of them are placed Two Drums, One Fife, and One Gentle∣man
bearing the Companies Arms.</P>
<P>In the Rear of them, Two Gentlemen bearing Banners,
containing the Arms of the Deceased Benefactors.</P>
<P>In the Center of them, fall Two Drums.</P>
<P>In the Rear of them Three Drums, One Fife, and Two
Gentlemen in Plush-Coats, bearing Two Banners, One of His
Majesties, the Other of the Companies. After them Six
Gentlemen-Ushers, followed by the Budg∣Batchelors.</P>
<P>The next, Two Gentlemen bearing Two Other Banners.
After them Six Gentlemen Ushers, succeeded by the Foins
Batchelors.</P>
<P>In the Rear fall in Two Drums, and a Fife. Then Two
Gentlemen One bearing my Lord MAYOR's, the Other
the City Banners. Then Twelve Gentlemen-Ushers,
and after them the Court of Assistance, which makes the last
Division</P>
<P>The Right Honourable the LORD MAYOR, with
the Principal Aldermen and Sheriffs, Mounts his Horse, with
the Aldermen Two by Two, the Sheriffs in the Rear.</P>
<P>In this Equipage of Two and Two the whole Body move
toward <HI>Skinners-Hall,</HI> where the <HI>Lord Mayor</HI> Elect, attended
from his own House, joyns with the Old <HI>Lord Mayor</HI> and
his Retinue; whence all of them, in this Order, March
<PB N="11" REF="6"/>
through <HI>King-street</HI> down to <HI>Three-Grane-Wharfe,</HI> there en∣tring
into their several Barges, which are gloriously adorn∣ed
with Flags and Pendants, His Lordship, and this Gallant
Company all Landing at <HI>Westminster,</HI> is conducted to the
Exchequer-Bar; there having performed several Ceremo∣nial
and Customary Duties, and taken the Oaths to His
Majestie, he returns again by Water to <HI>Black-fryers-Stairs,</HI>
with Drums Beating, Trumpets Sounding, Musick Playing,
&amp;c.</P>
<P>There his Lordship, and the several Companies Landing
from their Respective Barges, the rest of the Attendants
that went not to <HI>Westminster,</HI> waiting for his Reception,
the whole Body moves in Order before him to <HI>Cheap-side,</HI>
where his Lordship is Saluted with the First Pageant.</P>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="pageant">
<HEAD>The First Pageant, of FAME.</HEAD>
<P>ON a large Stage are Erected Four Antique
Pedestals, upon which are planted Four
Urnes of Gold, from which issue forth Four Trees
sprinkled with Golden-Nutmegs. In the Center is
planted a large Camel of Gold, being the Creft of
the Honourable Company; on which rides a beauti∣ful
Figure, richly and properly Drest, representing
<HI>Fame;</HI> Below, on each fide of the Stage, are placed
Four Figures more, <HI>viz. Justice, Mercy, Equity,</HI> and
<HI>Law.</HI></P>
<DIV3 TYPE="part">
<PB N="12" REF="7"/>
<HEAD>Fame thus Addresses His Lordship.</HEAD>
<L>IF <HI>Monarchs</HI> in their Soveraign Command,</L>
<L>In no less Post than <HI>Heav'ns</HI> Vicegerents stand;</L>
<L>And, in the Second Sphear of <HI>Government,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Magistrate</HI> dos the <HI>Crown'd-Head</HI> Present;</L>
<L>Hayl then, My <HI>LORD,</HI> to Your <HI>Praetorian Seat,</HI></L>
<L>Where both the <HI>Caears</HI> and <HI>Heav'ns</HI> Image meet:</L>
<L>And here 'twixt <HI>Justice, Equity,</HI> and <HI>Law,</HI></L>
<L>So near the Life Your Great <HI>Originals</HI> draw;</L>
<L>Till Your <HI>Augusta</HI>'s Heart, so all Your Own,</L>
<L>You fix the <HI>CHAIR</HI> the Copy af the <HI>THRONE:</HI></L>
<L>Whilst 'twixt her Ecchoing <HI>Praise</HI> and Bended <HI>Knee,</HI></L>
<L>You make Your Happy Year a <HI>Jubilee,</HI></L>
<L>Thus shall You Eternize Your Hononour'd <HI>Name,</HI></L>
<L>And never want the loudest Trump of <HI>Fame.</HI></L>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="pageant">
<HEAD>The Second Pageant.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">The Chariot of VICTORY.</HEAD>
<P>A Large Chariot splendidly Imbellished with all
manner of Enrichments of Silver, as Lyons
Heads, Large Shields, Noble Festoons, and Em∣bossed
<PB N="13" REF="7"/>
Goloss; The Wheels likewise are Silver. Be∣neath
the Chariot Wheels are Piles of Trophies, all
of Silver, <HI>viz,</HI> Helmets, Targets, Armory of all
sorts, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> This Chariot is drawn by Two stately
Griffons, the Companys Supporters, on whose Backs
are seated Two Princely Figures, Representing <HI>Asia</HI>
and <HI>America;</HI> as being those Parts of the World
whence the Spicery and other Grocery are Import∣ed.
In this Chariot fits a Figure Representing
<HI>Victory,</HI> Attended by Six more Figures Personating
<HI>Wisdom, Policy, Labour, Industry, Vigour,</HI> and <HI>Vigilance.</HI></P>
<DIV3 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>VICTORY Speaks.</HEAD>
<L>WHilst Victory, with all her ecchoing Praise,</L>
<L>Dos the Great <HI>WILLIAM's</HI> Deathless Honour raise,</L>
<L>Is it the <HI>Heroe</HI>'s only Crown'd? And grows</L>
<L>The <HI>Laurel</HI> only for the <HI>Warriour's</HI> Brows?</L>
<L>No! <HI>Peace</HI> her Trophies has, as well as <HI>War:</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Lordship</HI> with Great <HI>Caesar</HI> shares thus far;</L>
<L>He in his <HI>Martial,</HI> You Your <HI>Justice</HI> Seat;</L>
<L>Whilst He in Foreign Fields in Fame so Great,</L>
<L>His <HI>Sword</HI> and <HI>Shield</HI> his Glittering VVreath Secures,</L>
<L>Your <HI>Sword</HI> and <HI>Scales</HI> at Home shall Plant You Yours.</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="8"/>
This Difference, 'tis true, Your Toyls attends;</L>
<L>His Foes He Conquers, You shall win his <HI>Friends.</HI></L>
<L>Thus both the <HI>Prince</HI> and <HI>Magistrate</HI> shall joyn,</L>
<L>Both Glories Tune One Harmony Divine:</L>
<L>Your <HI>Olive-Garland,</HI> with his <HI>Bays</HI> shall Shine.</L>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="pageant">
<HEAD>The Third, the Plantation Pageant.</HEAD>
<P>IN the Center of a very large Stage is Erected
a Magnificent Pile, as the Shrine of <HI>St. Antho∣ny,
Patron</HI> to the Honourable Company; In this
Pile, under Four Arches fits <HI>St. Anthony</HI> and Three
more Attendants, Representing <HI>India, Persia,</HI> and
<HI>Arabia;</HI> The whole is Environ'd with Twelve Pe∣destals,
bearing as many Large Golden-Urnes, from
whence Issue <HI>Cinnamon-Trees,</HI> Richly Ornamented
with Flowers, Blossoms, Golden-Fruit,<HI>&amp;c.</HI> With∣in
the Body of this <HI>Pageant</HI> are several Persons in
Rural Habits, as <HI>Negroes, Tauneys, Virginia-Plan∣ters,
&amp;c.</HI> All exercised in Imitation of their seve∣ral
Employments. The whole <HI>Pageants</HI> all Adorn'd
with <HI>Flags</HI> and <HI>Streamers.</HI></P>
<DIV3 TYPE="part">
<PB N="15" REF="8"/>
<HEAD>St. ANTHONY's Speech.</HEAD>
<L>WHilst Proud St. <HI>Anthony,</HI> in his Spicy Plains,</L>
<L>The Honourable <HI>Grocers Patron</HI> Raigns;</L>
<L>'Tis here my <HI>Aromatick</HI> Odours spring;</L>
<L>And my Rich Fruits their fragrant Harvest bring.</L>
<L>But hold!—From my poor Throne, I must remove,</L>
<L>'Tis You're the <HI>Lord</HI> of all my <HI>Balmy Grove:</HI></L>
<L>'Tis from Your Smiles alone each kind Perfume,</L>
<L>And all my <HI>Oriental</HI> Sweets must Bloom.</L>
<L>Sweets did I say! You've Sweets yet more Refin'd;</L>
<L><HI>Virtue</HI> and every <HI>Grace</HI> that decks Mankind.</L>
<L><HI>Virtue</HI> a Plant of <HI>Paradice</HI> may boast,</L>
<L>Th' Original Offspring of the <HI>Eden</HI> Coast:</L>
<L>Nor let the Famous <HI>Bird</HI> of the Fair <HI>East</HI></L>
<L><HI>Vaunt</HI> her Proud <HI>Urne</HI> of that <HI>Rich-Mass</HI> possest;</L>
<L>'Tis <HI>Virtue</HI> only Builds the <HI>Spicy Neft.</HI></L>
<DIV4 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>A SONG.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>I.</HEAD>
<L>GRin <HI>Malice,</HI> burst <HI>Envy,</HI> cheer <HI>Albion,</HI> sing Fame.</L>
<L>'Tis all a just Tribute to NASSAU's Great <HI>Name;</HI></L>
<L>He comes! And, hark, round</L>
<L>The <HI>Hosannas</HI> resound.</L>
<L>In his Chariot Triumphant the Heroe dos move,</L>
<L>Whilst His own Grateful Thunder salutes our dear <HI>JOVE.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<PB N="16" REF="9"/>
<HEAD>II.</HEAD>
<L>The Virgins strew <HI>Flowrs,</HI> and the Matrons they <HI>Pray,</HI></L>
<L>The Nymphs on the Plains, and the Shepherds they <HI>Play.</HI></L>
<L>The Groves they all Ring,</L>
<L>Whilst the Nightingales Sing</L>
<L>And the Lark to the Skies the sweet Harmony bears,</L>
<L>Till the Gods joyn ith' <HI>Chorus</HI> and new Tune their Sphears.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>III.</HEAD>
<L>He comes, yes he comes, but more strong to Return:</L>
<L>His Friends they Rejoyce, but His Foes they must Mourn.</L>
<L>His bold Pen of Steel,</L>
<L>Has yet Volumes to fill;</L>
<L>For the brave <HI>British</HI> LYON the <HI>Lillies</HI> must Win.</L>
<L>He began at the <HI>Boyne,</HI> and shall end at the <HI>Seine.</HI></L>
</LG>
</DIV4>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

