<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A short memorial of the sufferings and grievances past and present of the Presbyterians in Scotland particularly of them called by nick-name Cameronians.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Shields, Alexander, 1660?-1700.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A59965</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing S3434</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R25753</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">09102270</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 09102270</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">42451</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A59965)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42451)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1295:3)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A short memorial of the sufferings and grievances past and present of the Presbyterians in Scotland particularly of them called by nick-name Cameronians.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Shields, Alexander, 1660?-1700.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 56 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[Edinburgh? :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1690.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Church of Scotland --  History.</TERM><TERM>Covenanters.</TERM><TERM>Scotland --  History --  1660-1688.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A59965">
<STC T="W">S3434</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">09102270</BIBNO>
<VID>42451</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A SHORT
MEMORIAL
OF THE
<HI>Sufferings</HI> AND <HI>Grievances,</HI>
PAST and PRESENT
OF THE
PRESBYTERIANS
IN
SCOTLAND:
Particularly of those of them called by Nick-name
<HI>Cameronians.</HI></P>
<P>Printed in the Year, 1690.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE
READER.</HEAD>
<P>IT is not needful in the entry to give a Deduction, either of the Excellent
Establishments of Religion and Civil Liberties, and Provisions made
for security of both, that our Fathers obtained and Enjoyed, by the
<HI>Mercy of GOD,</HI> under the Patrociny of Righteous Rulers; Or of the deplorable
Demolishments of these Invaluable Intersts, since the unhappy Re-introduction
of <HI>Prelacy</HI> and <HI>Tyranny,</HI> which brought <HI>Poperie</HI> to the very Birth in this
Land, had it not pleased the Most <HI>High GOD,</HI> by the interposition of the pre∣sent
<HI>King,</HI> as an Instrument, to make it abortive. But it is very useful and plea∣sant,
to remember that the <HI>Reformation of the Church of Scotland,</HI> was some∣times
as far Celebrated among all the Churches, as now it is Depreciated incontempt
and Obscurity: Among other peculiar Eminencies of it above many other Church∣es,
she had this very early for the subject of her Gloriation, through Grace;
that at once and from the Beginning, both, Doctrine, Worship, Discipline and
Government were Reformed, according to the Pattern of the Institutions of
Christ, to that degree of Purity, that our very first <HI>Reformers</HI> could assert, to
the praise of Grace, that no Corruption was left in this Church, that ever flow∣ed
from the <HI>Man of Sin.</HI> Which, through the Blessing of <HI>GOD</HI> upon the
Faithful and earnest Labours and Wrestling of His Servants in the Ministry,
made such progress in a short time; that not only the <HI>Doctrine</HI> was perfectly
purged of the Leaven of <HI>Popery, Arminianisme, Socinianisme &amp;c.</HI> and
all other <HI>Heresies;</HI> the <HI>Worship,</HI> of all Idolatry and Superstition: but the
<HI>Discipline</HI> was impartially exercised, and the <HI>Government</HI> Reformed from
<HI>Diocesan Prelacy, Sectarian</HI> Confusions, and <HI>Erastian</HI> Supremacy of the
Civil Powers, and framed in the nearest Conformity to the Primitive Aposto∣lick
Pattern, according to the Word of GOD, and example of the best Refor∣med
Churches, in the <HI>Presbyterial</HI> Order, of <HI>Congregational, Classical,
Synodical,</HI> and <HI>National</HI> Assemblies. In the Preservation and Observation
of which Beautiful Order, making our Church Beautiful as <HI>Tirzah,</HI> Comely
as <HI>Jerufalem,</HI> Terrible <HI>as an Army with Banners.</HI> This was also her
Priviledge and Praise, which is the Fruit of this Government wheresoever it
hath Place, that she was Once and for a long time, as much admired for <HI>Union,</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
as of late for <HI>Divisions</HI> since these Corruptions made a Breach upon Vs: Her
Name was once called <HI>Philadelphia</HI> among all the Reformed Churches; and
twas long since attested at that unhappy Convention at <HI>Perth,</HI> which attemp∣ted
the Introduction of some <HI>Popish</HI> Novations, in the Year 1618. That from
that backward, to the Year 1558. there had been neither <HI>Schisme</HI> nor <HI>He∣resie</HI>
in this Church; as also from thence forward, the same might have been
said, excepting the Contentions which the <HI>Prelates</HI> and <HI>Malignants</HI> occasioned,
until the fatal <HI>Catastrophe.</HI> No Church on Earth had more Purity, Order,
or Vnity, and was freer of Corruption, Defection and Division, that this
Church. This our Renowned <HI>Reformation</HI> in Doctrine, Worship, Discipline
and Government, as it was Founded on the Law and the Testimony of the GOD
of Heaven; so it was Confirmed by all the Sanctions, Ratifications and Securi∣ties,
that any Right can be capable of among Men: Not only by many <HI>Laws,
penal,</HI> and <HI>Statutory,</HI> Established as Bulworks, for Preserving and Defen∣ding
it against all the forementioned Adversaries; by many <HI>Constitutions</HI> and
<HI>Acts</HI> of <HI>General Assemblies,</HI> ratified by <HI>Parliaments:</HI> But by many, again
and again Renewed National and Solemn <HI>Covenants,</HI> sworn to the most High
<HI>GOD</HI> by all Ranks, from the King to the Beggar, in all Capacities and Con∣ditions.
This Testimony, for this <HI>Covenanted Reformation,</HI> so Confirmed
and Established; as it hath been Transmitted to Vs, through a long continued
Tract of many Wrestling and Sufferings, from our worthy Ancestors, and
sealed by much Precious Blood and the Bonds and Bondage of many Faithful
Martyrs and Confessors of Christ, adhering to the same in our day; so, as it
was then and now Stated and Sealed, hath been and is thought by all the Asser∣ters
of our <HI>Reformation,</HI> to have such a near and clear Connexion with the great
Concern of the Crown-Prerogatives, and Imperial Dignities of the Prince of the
Kings of the Earth, as Head of His visible Kingdom, whose incommunicable
Glory it is, without Competitoor Co-partner, either Coordinate or Subordinate,
to Institute his own Government, prescribe His own Laws, appoint his own
Ordinances (which He will have observed without addition, dimunition or alte∣ration,
until His second coming) and to constitute His own Officers, Cloathed
only with His Authority, and to be regulated only by His Instructions in their
Ministerial Function without any Dependence on, Subordination to, or In∣dulgence
from any Man or Angel, in the exercise thereof, under their Master
Christ alone; to whom it belongs as properly to Rule the Church his own free
Kingdom, according to the good pleasure of His own Will, as it belongs to Him
to save his Church by the Merit of his own Sufferings; that our Famous Fa∣thers,
and such of their Children as have been faithful in following their foot∣steps,
have judged it a <HI>Testimony</HI> worthy to Sacrifice all their Interests upon,
<PB REF="3"/>
in opposing and contending against all the Invasions and Vsurpations made upon
these Prerogatives of Christ, and Priviledges of His Church, by <HI>Poperie Prelacy,</HI>
and <HI>Erastian Supremacy,</HI> all condemned in the Law of GOD, diseharged
by the Laws of the Land, and Abjured in our <HI>Covenants National and
Solemn League;</HI> As being highly derogatorie to the Glory of Christ, contra∣dictory
to His revealed will, offensive to His People, obstructive to the Power,
and destructive to the peace, purity and Liberty of His precious Gospel.</P>
<P>Now for adbering to this complex <HI>Testimony,</HI> what have been the Sufferings
and Grievances of <HI>Presbyterians</HI> in general, and ours in particular since <HI>Anno</HI>
1660: from the <HI>Popish; Prelatical</HI> and <HI>Malignant Party,</HI> is more fully de∣monstrated,
(with the Principles and Testimonie contended for by us, vindicated) in
<HI>Naphtali, Jus populi, the Hind let loose,</HI> our <HI>Informatory Vindication,</HI>
&amp; the <HI>Testimony against the Toleration,</HI> given in by that faithful &amp; zealous
Minister of <HI>Christ, Mr. James Renwick;</HI> and here summarly Remonstrated. We
had once a Resolution, at the first appearance of the <HI>Prince of Orange;</HI> who,
under GOD, was the Honoured Instrument of our begun enlargement from them,
To have Addressed his <HI>Highness</HI> with this same <HI>Memorial:</HI> But that failing,
after this long suspence in expectation of some Redress of Grievances, whereof we
and many others have been in a great measure disappointed; We have been in∣duced
to publish it in this Iuncture, with an <HI>Appendix</HI> of our present complaints
of somethings that we understand to be wrong in the <HI>Church, State, Army</HI> and <HI>Country,</HI> at the time of the writing thereof; which was in the time, and
upon occasion of the many Adjournments of Parliament: Wherein perhaps some∣thing
will occur, which may seem obliquely to reflect upon the Government, when
we complain of the ill Administrations of many Malignants in power: But as
they are sad Truths which cannot be denyed, and tho we may be charged with
Imprudence in speaking so freely what many Thousands, and those of the surest
Friends the Government hath, do think: So, however we be neither Politicians nor
Flatterers, we think Conscience and Loyalty both, doth oblige us to speak what
concerns the King and Country both to hear. We do not blame the King for de∣laying
the satisfaction that his People have long waited for, further than for
permitting some into Trust, who have abused him with misinformations of what
they waited for, and with counsels to delay their satisfaction. Nor are we jea∣lous
of his Majesties sincere intentions to perform what he hath promised, and
the Estates Demanded, as necessary for settling the Church, securing Laws, re∣storing
Liberties, and Redressing Grievances; Albeit many here complained of,
have laboured to suggest grounds of such Iealousie. We have got already so
much Advantage by the success of his Heroick Expedition; And so many re∣peated
<PB REF="4"/>
Assurances of his Royal Resolutions to fulfill his <HI>Declaration</HI> and <HI>Pro∣mises</HI>
to our satisfaction; none of which we can charge him with the breach of
tho many of them are not yet accomplished; that we should be very unworthy to
Iealouse his Integrity. We consider his Majestie, stated in very Difficult and
Dangerous Circumstances, since he interposed himself in our Gap, between an
angry God and a sinful Provocking People; Wherein he hath to do with a potent
Enemy without, and many undermyning Enemies about his Hand, seeking to en∣snare
him in sin and expose him to ruine; and hath in his two Kingdoms of <HI>Britain</HI>
People of different Interests and Inclination, whom to Govern will require great
deliberation, and consequently occasion delayes: But we lay the blame where it
should lye, on the Malignants at <HI>Court, Council</HI> and <HI>Parliament,</HI> who are
seeking to betray him and us both. If some of these be exposed, and their old
pranks discovered, and the Grievous effects of their being so much in Power hinted
at; We hope the Candid Reader will think it no ill service either to King or
Country.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="errata">
<HEAD>ERRATA</HEAD>
<P>Reader before thou peruse these Sheets be pleased to help these Escapes of the PRESS (omitting
these of less Note) <HI>Page 15. Line</HI> 34. Read encouraged. <HI>P. 17. 19. R.</HI> superadded by
<HI>L. 25. R.</HI> equaling <HI>P.</HI> 34. Col. 1. 9. <HI>R.</HI> 21 Men and 5 Women. <HI>P.</HI> 35 Col. 2. <HI>L.</HI>
11. for <HI>Douglas R. Dundass. P.</HI> 36. Col. 1. <HI>L</HI> 5 for Mouat <HI>R. Mewae.</HI> Col. 2. <HI>L.</HI> 20 R.
<HI>Dundass,</HI> and <HI>L. 26. R. Dundass. P. 39. L.</HI> 36. for Orders <HI>R.</HI> Order <HI>P. 48. L.</HI> 18.
<HI>R.</HI> flowing.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A SHORT
MEMORIAL
OF THE
GRIEVANCES and SUFFERINGS
Of the
PRESBYTERIANS in SCOTLAND,
Since the Year 1660.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Particularly of those of them called
CAMERONIANS.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>FTER King <HI>Charles</HI> returned from his Exile, the first Device,
which the Malignants then advanced to the highest places of
Trust fell upon,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 1.</NOTE> for overturning our Religion, Laws, and
Liberties, was to prevent and obstruct all access either to
Justice or Mercy for such as they had a mind to destroy,
and preclude all Applications for a Redress of Grievances. Hence,
when some faithful Ministers were drawing up a Monitory Supplica∣tion
to the King, congratulating his Return, and minding him of his
Covenant Engagements and promises to promote and preserve the
work of Reformation; the Committee of States then siting, caused
apprehend, and without hearing incarcerate them, for no other cause
but that Supplication: against which at that time there was no Law;
and which all Law and Reason of the World will justifie, as the most
innocent expedient of getting their just complaints heard and redres∣sed,
and the common priviledge of all men, which slavery it self can∣not
take away. Yet as all Men, and they themselves, could not but,
see this a manifest subverting of the Subjects Liberty: So, in procure∣ing
a Law to approve it afterwards, they made it worse and more ille∣gal,
in declaring Petitions to be unlawful and seditious, <HI>Carol. 2.
Parl. 2. Sess. 2. Act</HI> 2. Hence no Petition or Remostrance of publick
Grievances, Oppressing, and enslaving Church or Nation, either
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
durst be offered, or could find Access or Acceptance, being interdict∣ed
and also punished very severely; as in the instance of the Grie∣vances
given in against <HI>Lauderdale.</HI> Nor durst Prisoners tender the
most innocent Supplication, even for release or a more easie Confine∣ment,
in any terms that seemed either to reflect on their severity, or
represent the illegality of their prosecutions, or in the least to vindi∣cate
the cause they were suffering for; which caused many afterwards
to decline all petitioning, and choose rather to ly under the most
unsupportable bondage, for fear of having it made more miserable.</P>
<P>The next succeeding Devices, to undermine and overturn our Re∣ligion
and Liberty,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 2.</NOTE> were the Mischiefs framed into Law by the <HI>first
Session of the first Parl: Charles</HI> 2. held by the Earl of <HI>Middletoun</HI> 1661.
Wherein by the very first Act thereof, all the Members were invol∣ved
in a Conscience Ensnaring and Enslaving Oath of <HI>Absolute</HI> and <HI>Im∣plieite
Allegiance</HI> and <HI>Supremacy,</HI> (without the former usual Limitati∣ons
then standing unrepealed) not only wronging Parliaments in
their Priviledges, and the Church in her Liberties, but the Lord Je∣sus
Christ in his Prerogative of Supremacy, and Headship over the
Church; making the King a Pope, and not only a Church Member
(as a Magistrate) or Church Officer, but the <HI>Supreme Architectonick
Head of the Church.</HI> For refusing this afterwards, many Ministers and
others were banished; several of them made to subscribe a Bond to
remove out of all his Majesties Dominions within a moneth, not to
return under the pain of Death; And many kept in prison by the Ar∣bittary
Power of the Council, beside the tenor and extent of their own
wicked Act thereupon.</P>
<P>In the following Acts of that same Session of Parliament, they ad∣vanced
the Kings <HI>Prerogative</HI> to the highest pitch of <HI>Absoluteness:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 3.</NOTE> and
the acknowledgement of this vast and unlimited prerogative, in all
particulars, was formed and imposed, <HI>Charl: 2: Parl: 1. Sess. 1. Act 2,
3,</HI> 4, 5, 11. This was the foundation of all the succeeding Tyranny,
and source of the Nations slavery; and in it self a head of sufferings
to several Gentlemen and others, who could not in Conscience sub∣scribe
or make that acknowledgement of such a <HI>prerogative;</HI> which
would manifestly have imported an approving of the first audacious
and presumptuous effect and attempt of its power, exerted in rescin∣ding
and annulling at one blow all the Righteous and Legal Establish∣ments
of the <HI>Covenanted Reformation,</HI> and all the Acts made in favours
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
thereof in all the Parliaments and Conventions of Estates from the
year 1640. to 1650. even those that the then King <HI>Charles</HI> 1. approved,
owned, and called.</P>
<P>They rested not here, in a general or gradual unhinging of Legal
Constitutions,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 4.</NOTE> made for security of our Religion and Liberty; but
then took advantage of the universal silent Submission of the Nation,
to break down at once the carved work of the whole Fabrick of the
Reformation as with Axes and Hammers, in that insolent effrontry
and indignity against Heaven, in making void the <HI>National and Solemn
League and Covenants:</HI> which the Church and State both in their Re∣presentatives
and Members, did most solemnly Swear and Subscrive,
for themselves and Posterity: which, for the matter of them perpe∣tually
obliging, for the manner so Religiously engaged into, and for
their ends so Glorious, no power on Earth can dispense with, disan∣null,
or disable: which not only the Lord from Heaven did ratify,
by the Conversion of many Thousands, and vouchsafing his presence
gracious in Ordinances and propitious in Providences at the subscriv∣ing
of them; But in this Land, at the Inauguration of the King <HI>Charles</HI> 2.
(being the condition upon which he was admitted to the Government)
the latter of these Covenants was Ratified and Established, as the great
fundamental Law of the Kingdom, whereon all the Rights and Pri∣viledges
either of King or People are principally bottomed and secured,
and as the very <HI>Magna Charta</HI> of our Reformation. Yet this not only
they did break in Heaven-daring boldness; but to flatter the King in
making way for <HI>Prelacy, Tyranny,</HI> and <HI>Popery,</HI> and to indulge the licen∣tiousness
of some debauched Nobles, who could not endure the Yoke
of <HI>Christs</HI> Government according to his Institutions there Covenanted
to be preserved; they enacted and declared, it should have no Obli∣gation
or binding Force any farther; and that none should henceforth
require the renewing of it <HI>Carol. 2. Parl. 1. Sess. 1. Act.</HI> 7. And after∣wards,
that the <HI>National Covenant</HI> and <HI>Solemn League and Covenant</HI> were
in themselves Unlawful Oaths: and therefore annulled all Acts and
Constitutions Ecclesiastical or Civil approving them, <HI>Parl. 1. Sess. 2.
Act.</HI> 2. And not only so but in contempt of Heaven, they caused burn
them by the hand of the <HI>Hangman.</HI> For adhering unto these Sacred,
Inviolable, and Indispensible Engagements, the sufferings of <HI>Presby∣terians</HI>
have in a great measure been stated since that time.</P>
<P>The next wicked project was,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 5.</NOTE> to remove out of the way all who
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
were eminent Instruments, in promoting that work of Reformation
now about to be razed, and whom they feared would obstruct their
Antichristian and Tyrannical designs, both in the State and in the
Church. Accordingly the Noble Marquess of <HI>Argyle</HI> was beheaded for
no other alledged cause but for his complyance with the <HI>English,</HI> when
they had made a Conquest of our Land, Wherein also the Judges that
condemned him were <HI>Socii Criminis.</HI> And afterwards, the Lord <HI>Wa∣riston</HI>
upon the same pretence: And for the same pretended cause, ma∣ny
other Gentlemen, above 800 were Arbitrarly and Exorbitantly
fined; some under divers stiles twice over. Such of the Ministry
also as had been most faithful &amp; servent for the interests of their Ma∣ster
and of his Church were cruelly and most illegally removed; some
by Death, as famous Mr. <HI>Guthrie,</HI> for asserting the Kingly Preroga∣tive
of Christ in opposition to the <HI>Erastian Supremacy</HI> encroaching
thereupon; others by Banishment, for giving faithful warning, and
protesting against the defection of that time, thereby only contraveen∣ing
a wicked Proclamation discharging them to speak against the Pro∣ceedings
of the State; others <HI>Indicta causa,</HI> without access to give in their
defences, or to get so much as an extract of their sentence.</P>
<P>After they had thus prepared their way,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 6.</NOTE> by the very first Act of
the second <HI>Sess of the first Parl. anno</HI> 1662. They reestablished and re∣dintegrated
their <HI>Dagon</HI> of Episcopal <HI>Prelacy,</HI> with all its inseparably
concomitant retinue of Pride, Perjury, Simony, Sacriledge, and in∣tollerable
Usurpations and Corruptions; And wreathed again about
our Neck that Yoke which neither our Fathers, who wrestled much
against it, nor we were nor ever shall be able to bear: which as it is
insupportable to, and hated of all the Godly (and desirable to none,
but dissolute &amp; debauched Persons, who cannot endure Christs disci∣pline
impartially exercised, and do find incouragement under the
wings of <HI>Prelacy</HI>) being in its original both the Mother and Daughter,
Root and Off-spring, Cause and Effect of <HI>Popery;</HI> a device which ad∣vanced
the Man of Sin to his hight in the World, and the only re∣maining
support of his hopes of recovering these Kingdoms, by Christs
conquest rescued from his Tyranny; in its nature, evidently eversive
of the very nature of <HI>Gospel Church Government;</HI> in its ends only adapted
to bring the Church into a slavish dependence on &amp; subordination to
an usurped Supremacy of the Magistrate, which is a change only of
the <HI>Pope</HI> not of the Popedom; And in its effects, alwayes found to be
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
most deplorably destructive to the purity and power of Religion, and
peace of its sincere profession, and that which hath introduced and en∣couraged
Impiety, Error, Schism, and Persecution in these Lands:
So by all the sober and judicious that have known the Case of this
Church and Kingdom it hath been acknowledged to be the source and
spring of all our Sorrows and Grievances, under which we have groan∣ed
these 28 Years. This abjured <HI>Prelacy,</HI> as it was introduced by ma∣nifest
Perjury and Persidy, so it was at first erected and hitherto ad∣vanced
and supported on such a Foundation, as might bear out and
justify the Contrivers and Promoters of it, as well in all attemprs to set
up <HI>Popery</HI> it self: the Act establishing it <Q>Declaring, the disposal of the
Government of the Church doth properly belong to his Majesty as an
inherent Right of the Crown, by vertue of his Royal Prerogative
and Supremacy in causes Ecclesiastick;</Q> An usurpation upon the King∣dom
of Christ equivalent to any that ever the <HI>Papacy</HI> it self durst as∣pire
unto over the Government of the Church. The first effect where∣of
was by another Act 1 <HI>Sess. 2 Parl. Carol.</HI> 2. <Q>the restoring the old
exploded bondage of Parronages;</Q> another old Relict of <HI>Popish</HI> Sla∣very,
depriving the Church of the freedom of Calling and Choosing
their own Pastors: And dispossessing all the Ministers, who entered
since the Year 1640. of their Churches and Benefices, possessed with∣out
the presentations of <HI>Patrons</HI> After which, by the instigation of
the <HI>Prelates,</HI> the Council passed an Act <HI>October</HI> 1662, whereby above
300 Ministers were violently put out of their Charges, and their Con∣gregations
laid desolate, without all Legal Procedure, without either
Accusation or Citation, Conviction or Sentence, or a hearing allowed
to them. And therefore for <HI>simple Nonconformity,</HI> and refusing subjection
to and taking Collations from the <HI>Prelates,</HI> the rest of the Ministers,
in great numbers, were, with cruelty more beseeming <HI>Turks,</HI> thrust
from their Labours and banished, with a nice and strange confinement;
20. Miles from their own Parish Church, Six Miles from a Cathedral,
and three Miles from a Burgh. In whose room succeded, a swarm of
Ignorant and Scandalous Apostates, the <HI>Prelates</HI> and their Mercenary
Substitutes the <HI>Curats:</HI> against whom such Charges might alwayes have
been adduced, and to this day such Accusations are in readiness to be
produced, to any competent ludicatories, that shall be called to cog∣nosce
upon them, of the pernicious Errors of <HI>Popery, Socinianisme,</HI> and
<HI>Arminianisme</HI> maintained by many of them, Abominable Adulteries
committed by others of them, the Profanity, Sensuality,
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
and Debauchery, Oppression and Persecution of Godliness and
good Men chargeable on the generallity of them, and Perjury in
breach of <HI>Covenant,</HI> and <HI>Schismatical intrusion</HI> without consent of the
Church owned of all of them, and Ungodliness by them transfused
over all the Land; as could not but make them detested of all, as the
greatest stain to be suffered in a <HI>Reformed Church.</HI></P>
<P>Upon the back of this, by the instigation of the <HI>Prelates,</HI> who scorn∣ed
to be and one,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 7.</NOTE> no not by <HI>Iulian</HI> the Apostate, in surpressing Reli∣gion,
they proceeded to poyson all the Seminaries of Learning: Or∣daining,
in <HI>Act. 9. Sess. 2. Parl. 1. Carol.</HI> 2. <Q>That none be Masters
in any University, except they both take the Oath of Supremacy,
and submit to and own Prelacy; or be so much as a Pedagogue to
Children, without the Prelates Licence.</Q> By which course Honest
and Learned Men were brought to considerable Straits and Sufferings;
and Ungodly and Unsound Masters had access and encouragement,
to corrupt the Youth with perverse and Malignant Principles, to the
great and observable Detriment and Decrement of Religion, Lear∣ning,
Sobriety, and Morality in the Nation.</P>
<P>The next Contrivance was, to corrupt all the Fountains of Judica∣ture.
And for this End it was enacted,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 8.</NOTE> <HI>Act 5. Sess. 2. Parl. 1. Carol. 2.
That all Persons, in any publick Trust or Office whatsoever, should subscribe
the Declaration, renouncing and abjuring the Covenants;</HI> And that not only
under the Certified penalty of <HI>Forefaulting the Priviledges of Magistrates;</HI>
But also of all the <HI>Priviledges of Merchandizing, Trading, and others, belong∣ing
to a Burgess, Act 3. Sess. 3. Parl 1. Carol.</HI> 2. Whereby Perjury was
made the chief and indispensable Qualification, and <HI>Conditio sine qua
non</HI> of all that were capable of Exercising any power in Church or
State; contrate to known Laws yet unrepealed, which make them
that are guilty of Perjury, incapable of being intrusted with any pub∣lick
Administration in the Kingdom.</P>
<P>The Parliaments thus corrupted, and instigated by the <HI>Bishops</HI> and
<HI>Curates,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 9.</NOTE> Establish wicked Laws pressing Conformity. And in the ve∣ry
first of them, made such a streach, beyond all bounds of Charity,
Justice, Reason, or Humanity, that they made all Addresses to God
or Man, remonstrating such Grievances and reflecting on such pro∣ceedings
to be Criminal; <HI>Declaring Petitions to be Seditious,</HI> And <HI>dis∣charging
all Writing, Printing, Remonstrating, Praying, or Preaching, shewing
any dislike of the Kings Absolute Prerogative and Supremacy in Causes Ecclesi∣astick,
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
or of the Government of the Church by Bishops, Act 2. Sess. 2. Par. 1.
Carol.</HI> 2. And <HI>Act 4 ibid.</HI> They not only prohibited any to Preach
in publick, or so much as in Families without the <HI>Prelates</HI> Licences
but Discharged all Private Meetings in Houses for Religious Exercise,
of such as could not in Conscience give their Countenance to the <HI>Cu∣rats</HI>
Service in Churches.</P>
<P>Then in the 3 <HI>Sess. Act.</HI> 2.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Grie∣ance 10.</NOTE> <Q>They Declare, that all Non conform∣ed
Ministers, that shall presume to Exercise their Ministry, shall
be punished as Seditious Persons: And Require of all, in acknow∣ledgement
of and Complyance with his Majesties Government Eccle∣siastical,
that they give their concurrence and countenance to the <HI>Cu∣rates,</HI>
and attend their Meetings for Worship: Ordaining, that
whosoever shall withdraw, shall incur, each Nobleman, Gentleman,
or Heretor, the loss of a fourth part of their Years rent, every
Yeoman the loss of a fourth or under of his Moveables, each Bur∣gess
the loss of his Burge-ship, with the fourth of his Moveables,
with a reference to the Council, for farther punishment, and more
effectual Execution:</Q> Which the Council very vigorously Prose∣cuted,
in emitting most rigorous Proclamations after that: Some
requiring all to keep their Parioch Churches under the pain of 20.
<HI>shil. toties quoties;</HI> Some discharging all Preaching, Praying, or Hear∣ing
in Families, where three or some more then the <HI>Domesticks</HI> were
found, as unlawful <HI>Conventicles;</HI> Others Certifying, that all such
Meetings, not Authorised, shall be punished by Pecunial and Cor∣poral
pains, at the Arbittement of the Council; Other Command∣ing
all Masters of Families, Heretors, Landlords, and Magistrates of
Burghs, ro cause their Servants, Dependents, Tennents, Taxmen,
Cottars, and all under their Charge, to submit and conform to the
<HI>Curates</HI> their Ministry.</P>
<P>For putting these Laws in Execution,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 11.</NOTE> the King erected a <HI>High Com∣mission
Court;</HI> consisting of some Prelates, Noblemen, Magistrates of
Burghs, and some Souldiers, impowered, by vertue of his Prero¦gative
Royal and Supremacy, to suspend, deprive, and Excommuni∣cat,
As also to punish by Fining, Confining, and Incarcerating, all
keepers of Conventicles, and all Non Conformists: A Hotch-potch
mongrel Monster of a Judicatory, Authorized by the Prerogative
against the Laws of GOD and Man, meddling with Causes and Cen∣sures
Ecclesiastick and Civil, most Illegal and Arbitrary, both for its
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
Constitution and Procedure: Whereby persons brought before them
were made to answer <HI>super inquirendis,</HI> contrare to express standing
Law <HI>Ioc. 6. Parl. 10. Act. 13. Anno.</HI> 1585. without either Libel or Ac∣cuser,
or admitting Legal Defences except they take the Oaths; and
sentenced with Stigmatizing, Scourging, Banishment, Deportation
and Slaverie to <HI>Barbados,</HI> &amp;c. By orders from this Court, especially
from the <HI>Prelates,</HI> whose country sides were in a great measure Depo∣pulate
for Non-conformity, by Souldiers; Sometimes besetting the
Churches, where honest Ministers were not yet ejected, and forcing
all within to pay fines; Sometimes going to the <HI>Curates</HI> Churches, and
Amerciating all the Absents in such fines as they pleased; Sometimes
by force driving all to Church, beating, wounding, and binding the
Reousants; Sometimes exacting exorbitant fines by Plunder, to the
Harassing and making Havock of whole Country sides; sparing
sometimes Complyers no more then Recusants; And punishing Hus∣bands
for their Wives, Parents for their Children; Yea doubling and
tripling the same exactions after payment; yet compelling them some∣times,
to subscribe an acknowledgement that the Captain had used
them civilly and discreetly; Then after all, Apprehending, Impri∣soning,
Scourging some, Stigmatizing others, and sending them to
Forreign parts, that would not for all this conform.</P>
<P>Hereupon, being outwearied with intollerable oppressions, a small
party of Dissenters were partly compelled, and party by a surprise of
Providence engaged,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 12.</NOTE> to run together for their own defence, at <HI>Pentland
Anno</HI> 1666. Where, after the defeat, <HI>The Prisoners that were taken up∣on
Quarter and solemn parol to have their life spared, were treacherously given
up to be Condemned, the very manner of their Execution being first determined
and described before Arraigment, and cruelly hanged; their Heads being set
up at</HI> Edinburgh, Glasgow, Air, Dumsreis, <HI>and at</HI> Hamiltoun; <HI>Turks</HI>
would have blushed to have seen the like. Among the rest one emi∣nent
Minister, Mr. <HI>Hugh Mckail,</HI> for having but a Sword tho not pre∣sent
at the Fight, was first cruelly tortured with the Iron boots, and
afterwards execute to the death. At their Executions Drums were
beat that they might not be heard; a Barbarity never known in <HI>Scot∣land</HI>
before; and rarely heard of except in the Duke <HI>d' Alvas</HI> mur∣dering
the <HI>Protestants</HI> in the <HI>Netherlands;</HI> But frequently used almost
at all the Executions since of our Martyred Brethren in this Land.
Immediatly hereafter Souldiers were sent out on free Quarter, to ex∣amine
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
men by Tortures, threatning to kill or rost alive all that
would not delate all they knew Accessary to that rising: Who ac∣cordingly,
by fire Matches and other tortures, forced Women to
discover their Husbands and other Relations, although they knew
not it they were there; stripped them who Reset the Fugitives, and
thrusted them in crouds to Prisons in cold and nakedness; And some
they murdered without Process, that would not, because they could
not, discover those persecuted people; Yea and drove away the
Goods of the Country, without respect to Guilt or Innocency. In
the mean time, such as were in Armes, and some that were not,
were Intercommuned, and interdicted of all Reset, Harbour, Hid∣ing,
Corresponding, or Comfort, under pain of Rebellion and of be∣ing
counted guilty of the same Crimes, wherewith the Intercommun∣ed
were charged. And many Gentlemen, Ministers, and others,
were Forfeited of their whole Estates very illegally: Yea some that
were not present at that Appearance in Armes, nor Legally Convict,
nor cited to answer according to Law, were yet Forfaulted before the
Act of <HI>Parl. 2. Act 11. Carol.</HI> 2. contrate to express standing Statutes.
And further all Dissenters, and such as did not joyn in suppressing
that Expedition, were by order from the Council robbed of their
Armes and Horses fit for service; their guilty Consciences puting them
in Fears, and dictating their desert of greater opposition.</P>
<P>After all these Cruelties,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 13.</NOTE> murdering the Persons and oppressing the
Estates of poor Dissenters; what they could not do by Law, nor
Force, nor Futy, they contrived to effectuate by Craft, under the no∣tion
of Clemency; but such a Clemency, as was a greater Cruelty
then any former Persecution. The poor People that had nothing left
them but a good Conscience, must have that robbed from them like∣wise:
Therefore these wicked Councellers and <HI>Prelates,</HI> still stirred up
by the <HI>Curates,</HI> having none or a seared Conscience of their own, con∣trived
to take away from People all Remainders of Conscience, or to
make them pliable to comply with every corruption they should in∣troduce,
by imposing Conscience-debauching and ensnaring <HI>Oaths</HI> and
<HI>Bands</HI> most Deceitfully and Ambiguously framed, most Illegally im∣posed,
and Insolently pressed▪ and more numerous since that time than
ever was heard of in any Nation in one Age: there being scarce one year
since that time, wherein several of these Oaths and Bonds have not
been vented and imposed, contradictory to one another, contrary to
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
our sworn Covenants and work of Reformation, impossible to keep,
and unlawful to take.</P>
<P>Yet finding they could not yet suppress the persecuted Meetings for
Gospel Ordinances,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 14.</NOTE> but that the more violence was used the greater
and more frequent they grew; They fell upon a more crafty device,
to divide and destroy the Remnant, to overturn what remained of
the Churches Priviledges undestroyed, and to settle Ministers and
People into a silent and stupid Submission to all the Kings Usurpations
upon the same, by giving an <HI>Indulgence, Anno</HI> 1669. to some outed
Ministers, with Restrictions and Instructions, clearly homologatory
of the Supremacy whence it flowed, establishing the height of <HI>Erastia∣nism,</HI>
prejudicial to the freedom of the Ministry, injurious to the
Priviledges of the Church, contrary to <HI>Presbyterian</HI> Principles, and
contradictory to the <HI>Covenants:</HI> The Grant and Acceptance whereof
hath been the bane of the Church of <HI>Scotland,</HI> and a Bone of Con∣tention
rending and ruining the Remnant of Ministers and People
Unite before. The end of it was to advance the Supremacy; as upon
this occasion they enlarged and explained it: And because it was
against Law, therefore, that the Kings Letter might be made the Su∣preme
Law afterwards, at least Law enough for the Council to pro∣ceed,
enact, and execute what the King pleased in matters Ecclesia∣stick,
The <HI>Parl. 2. Act 1. Carol.</HI> 2. held by <HI>Lauderdale,</HI> Asserts and
Declares, <Q>That, by vertue of the Supremacy, the ordering of
the Government of the Church doth properly belong to his Majesty
and Successors, as an Inherent Right to the Crown; and that he
may enact and emitt such Constitutions, Acts, and Orders, con∣cerning
Church Administrations, Persons, Meetings, Matters, as
he in his Royal Wisdom shall think fit, Which Acts, Orders, <HI>&amp;c.</HI>
Are to be observed and obeyed by all Subjects, any Law, Act or
Custom, to the contrary notwithstanding.</Q></P>
<P>But now as before,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 15.</NOTE> faithful Ministers that were not thus Indulged,
sensible of the indispensable necessity of Preaching the Gospel, and of
the Peoples great necessity calling them to it from several quarters,
after they had undergone and endured many hazards and hardships
of Villany and Violence, Imprisonment and Banishment, for meeting
in the Houses, where they were easily Intraped, Interrupted, and In∣sulted
over, were forced to go to the Fields, and Preach in places most
convenient, secret and safe; whither the People, being tyred of their
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
cold and dead Curates, and wanting long the Ministry of their old Pa∣stors,
resorted in great numbers, on the greatest of hazards: the Coun∣cil
then, at the instigation of the Bishops and Curates, raised Troops
of Horse and Dragoons to pursue them as Traitors and Rebells, for
their following that Necessary and Signally blessed Duty; Im∣powred
and Encouraged to apprehend, and bring Dead or Alive,
some Ministers, with prices put upon their Heads, and to incarcerate
all they could find, either at the Meetings, or suspected to be coming
to or from them. Hence Prisons were filled; some were sent to the
<HI>Bass;</HI> some Banished; and many hundreds driven from their Dwel∣lings,
Outlawed, and Intercommuned.</P>
<P>For Legalizing such Mischiess,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 16.</NOTE> the second <HI>Sess.</HI> of the second <HI>Parlia∣ment,
Anno</HI> 1670. held by <HI>Lauderdale,</HI> made many wicked Laws, causes
of many Grievances following. As <HI>Act</HI> 2. <Q>Ordaining all of every
quality or sex, called to depone upon Oath their knowledge of such
Meetings and Persons therein, to declare the same in all particulars
interrogate, under the pains of Fining, Imprisonment, or Banish∣ment,
and Deportaion to the <HI>Indies,</HI> as the Council shall think fit: ob∣lidging
People thereby to betray their own Neighbours. <HI>Act</HI> 5. De∣claring
all outed Ministers, found Preaching or Praying, in any
House except in and to their own Family, shall be Imprison∣ed,
till they find Caution under the pain of 5000 Marks, not to do
the like again; and every Hearer shall be <HI>toties quoties</HI> fined, each
Tennant in 25 Pounds Scots, each Cottar in 12 Pounds, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> And
that all that Preach in the Fields, or in any House where any of the
People are without Doors, shall be punished with DEATH; and
any that shall seise and secure any of them, dead or alive, shall have
500 Marks reward.</Q> <HI>Act</HI> 6. Imposing most I yrannically exorbitant
and grievous. Fines, upon any that shall offer their Children to be Bap∣tized
by any but Curats and Indulged Ministers; which were after∣wards,
by <HI>Act 11. Sess. 3. Parl.</HI> 2. laid upon all who shall keep their
Children Unbaptized, for Thirty dayes together. <HI>Act</HI> 9. Imposing
intolerable Fines on all that shall three Sabbath dayes together with∣draw
themselves from their own Paroch Churches. <HI>Act 9. Sess▪</HI> 3.
Declaring all Ordinations of Ministers, since the Year 1661. which
have not been by Bishops, to be Null and Invalid; and that they are
no Ministers that are otherwise Ordained: encroaching hereby on
the most Intrinsick and formally Ecclesiastick Powers of the Officers
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
of Christs Kingdom. These wicked Acts were followed with cruel
Executions, whereby many were made to endure such Havock, as
harder could not be found in the Reign of <HI>Caligula</HI> or <HI>Nero,</HI> both in
their own Houses, in Prisons, and at Sea in Deportations.</P>
<P>Hereafter, thinking the ordinary Forces not cruel enough in exe∣cuting
these enacted Mischiefs,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 17.</NOTE> they brought from the wild <HI>Highlands</HI>
a Host of 10 or 11000 Barbarous Savages, and poured them in upon
the <HI>Westeren</HI> Shires (all peaceable at the time, none so much as moving
a Finger against them) on design, as would seem, utterly to lay them
desolate: with Orders to press a Bond of Conformity, wherein every
Subscriber was bound, for himself and all under him, to frequent the
Paroch Church, and never go to House or Field Meetings, nor reset
any that went to them, but to informe against, pursue, and deliver
up all outed Preachers to Judgement. Many Houses and Families
were then left desolate. the Inhabitants being made to flee in the Win∣ter
Season: many left their Cattel, and in seeking to recover them
lost their Lives.</P>
<P>Yet the Innocent Country was made to pay for all this Service, and
hire them to do more,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 18.</NOTE> by paying the imposed <HI>Cess,</HI> enacted and ex∣acted
professedly, by the Act of the Convention of Estates holden by
<HI>Lauderdale, anno</HI> 1678. to raise and maintain more Forces, and to main∣tain
the Supremacy as now Asserted and Established, and to suppress
Field Meetings called <HI>Rendezvouses of Rebelion</HI> And, for the same
Causes, and to suppress the Propagation of the Principles then suffered
for, continued by <HI>Act 3. Parl.</HI> 3. held by the DUKE of <HI>York</HI> Com∣missioner.
And by <HI>Act 12. Parl. 1. Iac.</HI> 7. holden by <HI>Queensberry,</HI>
continued and prorogued, during all the Terms of his Lifetime:
which, because of the Illegality of its imposition, the nature of its
Exaction, being an Obedience to a wicked Law, a help to the Un∣godly
to make Havock of the Church, a hire to the Souldiers to de∣stroy
what remained of Religion and Liberty, and because of its ends
so expresly Declared in the Narratives of the Acts, to suppress the
persecuted Gospel and destroy its Followers, many <HI>Presbyterians</HI> durst
not justify by Obedience, in paying the required Moyetie; but chose
rather to suffer joyfully the spoyling of their Goods, and all the force
and fury they could exert against them. Whereby many tho' poor
yet honest and honestly provided Families, were laid waste, and ex∣posed
to the Miseries of uncertain Wanderings.</P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="10"/>
At length, upon occasion of <HI>Graham</HI> of <HI>Claverhouse,</HI> his assaulting a
meeting near <HI>Loudoun-hill,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 19.</NOTE> carrying about with him a Minister and se∣veral
Countrey men bound as Beasts, and getting a repulse in the ran∣counter
with the meeting; Another Insurrection, for our Lives, Li∣berties,
and Religion, was undertaken, and discomfited at <HI>Bothwel∣bridge,
anno 1679:</HI> and at the defeat several hundreds were killed on
the Field, and 10. or 1100. were taken Prisoners, stript, and carried
to <HI>Edinburgh,</HI> where, after two of our Ministers were martyred for that
Appearance, Mr. <HI>Iohn King</HI> and Mr. <HI>Iohn Kid:</HI> And after the rest of
the Prisoners were kept several weeks in a Church yard without a co∣vert
either from cold or heat in the open Air; a bond was tendered,
seeming to offer Life and Liberty, on terms that clearly condemned
the cause, <HI>never to rise in Arms against the King, on any pretence whatsoever,
&amp;c.</HI> Which many took, and the rest of us that refused, and even
many that did take it, were sent away in a Ship bound for <HI>America,</HI>
between 2 and 300 in all: who were all murdered in the Ship, being
shut up under the hatches, when it split upon a Rock in the North of
<HI>Scotland,</HI> excepting 50: some of which are yet alive to give this account.</P>
<P>After this, the grand Design of subverting and utter everting our
Reformation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 20.</NOTE> tho' from the beginning of this Fatal Catastrophe pro∣jected,
and by all the forementioned Methods prosecuted hitherto, was
more and more discovered, and beyond all denial demonstrated,
that nothing less was intended then the gradual introduction of <HI>Po∣pery</HI>
and <HI>Slavery,</HI> and that by all the ordinat <HI>Iesuitical Rules,</HI> observed
in the seduction of Churches into the <HI>Roman Tyrannie:</HI> The chiefest of
which have alwayes been to foment all Quarrels among <HI>Protestants,</HI>
and to strengthen the Party readiest to comply, to make and execme
rigorous Laws against the most tenacious, and to load the <HI>Protestant</HI>
Opinions that are more obnoxious with all odious constructions.
Accordingly in the first place, to propagate Defection and promote
Division, a Proclamation was emitted <HI>anno</HI> 1679 inveighing against
and resolutely interdicting all Field-meetings; and granting Liberty
to Preach in Houses upon terms of a <HI>cautionary Bond,</HI> binding and ob∣lieging
the People for their Ministers living peaceably, and in Order
thereto to present him before his Majesties Privy Council, when they
should be called so to do; And in caise of falizie in not presenting him,
to be lyable to the sum of 6000 <HI>merks.</HI> Yet excluding all these <HI>Ministers,</HI>
who were suspect to have been at that insurrection of <HI>Bothwel;</HI> And
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
all those who should afterwards be admitted by <HI>Non conformed</HI> Mini∣sters:
Whereby those that durst not comply were exceedingly di∣vided,
and more easily destroyed.</P>
<P>For their Courts of cruel Inquisition went by Circuit through the
Country,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 21.</NOTE> pressing the Bond of <HI>Peace,</HI> denying the Principle and re∣nouncing
the Priviledge of Defensive Arms; And taking up <HI>Portuous
Rolls</HI> of all that were suspect to have been at <HI>Bothwel</HI> insurrection; where∣of
they reputed all to be convict, who being summoned did not ap∣pear,
or were delated by Oath <HI>super inquirendis</HI> to have been seen or
heard to be in Armes, or did not go to the Kings Camp, about that
time. Whereby, not only upon the account of that Appearance
were many executed to the Death, by packing bloody Juries and As∣sises,
as might conduce and be for their murdering ends, besides more
than can be reckoned that were kept to perish in Prisons, or Deporta∣tions
to Banishment; But many Gentlemen and others were Indy∣ted,
Imprisoned, and some condemned to Death, others Forefaulted
or Fyned above the value of their Estates, for having seen or spoken
with some of those called Rebels; or because they did not discover
or apprehend them, even when they did not and could not know
whether they were called or counted Rebels or not.</P>
<P>And some poor People, when they could not be reached any way
for this insurrection at <HI>Bothwell,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 22.</NOTE> nor any other overt Act or Trans∣gression
against even their wicked Laws, were condemned for their
simple declared Opinion of it: Which the Council, and Court of
Justiciarie, particularly Sir <HI>George Mackenzie</HI> Advocate, did extort
from them by terrible menacings of Death and Torture. For, being
interrogate, <HI>Whether the rysing at Bothwel-bridge was Rebellion, and a sin
against GOD:</HI> Many, for saying it was not, yea, for not saying it was,
and waving the Question, as reckoning themselves not oblieged to
Answer, were cruelly condemned and executed, tho they declared
and were known to be as free as the Child unborn of these Actions they
were examined upon.</P>
<P>In Fine, After our Patience had been long outwearied with insup∣portable
Slavery, and under such intollerable Oppressions in our Con∣sciences,
Persons and Estates; so universaly extended, that in the pre∣sent
circumstances we had more reason to hope, that past miseries,
present Pressures, and future Dangers of greater Encroachments, then
foreseen by all men that did not willingly shut their Eyes, should
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
have incited and invited all, that had any regard to the great Interests
of Religion and Liberty, to concur in an Essay to emancipate them∣selves
and posterity from that Yoke of grassant &amp; growing Tyrannie,
Than to fear the condemnation of any under these Oppressions, or
the clamour and out cry of those that were at ease against the Informa∣lity,
Illegalily, Unseasonableness, or Unfealableness of such Revolt:
We were Enduced and Enforced at length, when we could do no
more to preserve what remained of these Interests, or save
our Consciences innocent from all participation of the sin of the de∣stroyer
of them; To declare for our parts a Revolt from, and dis∣own
Alleagiance to King <HI>Charles</HI> the Second, as being no longer to be
accounted our Supreme Magistrate, but <HI>ipso jure</HI> devested of that
Office and Trust, Reposed and Devolved on him by express Com∣pact
and Covenant: When he broke all these conditions, where∣upon
his Authority and our Alleagiance were founded; in his utter
violating and making void the Covenant and Coronation Oath,
whereby our Subjection to him, limited to those provisions, was ex∣plicitely
disingaged and remitted; when he did unhinge and insringe
all the Legal Establishments of our Religion; and subverted all our
Religious Liberties, by usurping a Blasphemous Sacrilegious Supre∣macy
over Ecclesiastical Ordinances instituted by Christ; And when
now he had overturned all Fundamental constitutions of the State
as well as the Church, subverting the Peoples Rights, Liberties, Laws,
and all securities of our Life and Enjoyments whatsoever, by claim∣ing
and taking an Absolute Tyrannical Civil Prerogative, paramount
to all Law, inconsistent either with the Freedom or Safety of the
People: Whereby no shadow of Government was left, but Arbi∣trary
Absoluteness, making the Kings Letter the Supreme Law of
<HI>Scotland;</HI> while Innocent and Honest People for Conscience were grie∣vously
oppressed, and Perjuries, Adulteries, Idolatries, and all Im∣pieries,
were not only Indemnified and past without punishment, but
encouraged as Badges of Loyalty. For which causes, we openly
proclaimed our Revolt from the Government as it was then Admi∣nistrate.
And in the same Declaration, we reckoned our selves ob∣lieged
to protest against the Reception of the Duke of <HI>York</HI> in <HI>Scotland;</HI>
And against his succeeding to the Crown, who was then declared in∣capable
of Succession of the Government, by a Vote of the
two Honourable Houses of the Parliament of <HI>England.</HI> For
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
For owning,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 22.</NOTE> and not daring to disown, which Revolt, it is im∣possible
to enumerate our Kinds and Degrees of Sufferings: for this
we had our Ministers and Brethren Murdered, both in the Fields, and
Scaffolds, and Prisons, and Seas; Besides those that were slain at <HI>Airds∣moss,</HI>
where <HI>Bruce</HI> of <HI>Earleshall</HI> attacked us, and slew Mr. <HI>Richard
Cameron</HI> a Faithful and Zealous Minister with many of our Bre∣thren.
After this it was generally imposed on Prisoners, even such
as could not be charged with any Accession to the forementioned De∣claration,
to give an account of their Thoughts and Consciences about
the Lawfulness of the Kings Authority: which if they could not own,
or declined to declare their Thoughts, as judging it the common In∣terest
of Mankind to plead for the Freedom of Thoughts from all
humane Jurisdiction, or if any answered with such innocent Qualifi∣cations,
as that they owned all Lawful Authority <HI>In the Lord,</HI> or, <HI>Ac∣cording
to the Word of God;</HI> then they were punished as Traitors, exe∣cuted
to the <HI>Death,</HI> and some at their first apprehending Tormented
with <HI>Fire-matches,</HI> then laid in <HI>Irons,</HI> afterwards Tortured with the
<HI>Boots</HI> or <HI>Thumbkins,</HI> and after all executed in a most Barbarous man∣ner
without suffering them to speak their dying Words for beating of
Drums. Thus a great number of innocent People have been destroyed,
without respect to Age or Sexe; some meer Boyes have been for this
hanged; some stouping for Age; some Women also hanged, and
some Drowned, because they could not satisfy the Council, Justitiary
Court, and the Souldiers, with their thoughts about the Goverment.</P>
<P>In the Year 1681. the Duke of <HI>York,</HI> as Commissioner from his
Brother,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 23.</NOTE> held a Parliament, (Auspicated with the Blood of Mr.
<HI>Donald Cargil</HI> a Godly and Faithful Minister, which was
shed at the <HI>Cross</HI> of <HI>EDINBURGH,</HI> the day before the sitting
down of the Parliament) wherein he not only presided against all
our Righteous Laws, that Make a <HI>Papist</HI> incapable of such a Trust,
and against their own Laws, without taking the Oaths of Admini∣stration,
but procured an Act to be made recognizing his Succession to
the Crown notwithstanding all standing unrepealed Laws against <HI>papists:</HI>
wherein also many Acts were contrived that have been great causes of
the desolation and depopulation of the Country that ensued: As <HI>Act</HI>
4. dowbling the Fines imposed by former <HI>Laws</HI> for Fieid Conven∣ticles;
And ordering Heretors and Masters to put away their Tennants,
Cottars, or Servants, at any time of the Year without any warning or
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
process of removing, notwithstanding of any Tacks or Terms to run;
And to retain their goods, <HI>&amp;c. Act</HI> 18. Declaring, <Q>that all Jurisdicti∣on
doth so reside in his Majestie, that his Majesty may, by himself
or any Commissionated by him, take Cognizance and Decision
of any cases or causes he pleases.</Q> Hereby a foundation was laid for
overturning all Civil and Criminal Justice, and for erecting the Ty∣ranny
of the <HI>Popish Inquisition,</HI> whensoever matters were ripe for it, and
for commissionating Souldiers to take away the lives of Innocents,
without all Process of Law, as was frequently exemplified afterward
And <HI>Act</HI> 6. and 25. Framing and Imposing on all in Trust a dete∣stable
and self contradictory Test, which turned out of all places of
Trust any that retained any measure of common Honesty. For ex∣plaining
which, the late Earl of <HI>Argyle</HI> was arfaigned and condemn∣ed;
and escaping prison, forced to flee to forraign Lands: As many
others, both Gentlemen and Commons were constrained to leave the
Land; where for multiplied, illegal, and ensnaring impositions, they
could neither live like Men nor like Christians, but as Asses couch∣ing
under all burdens.</P>
<P>These and the like Acts, with many others Arbitrarly superadded
<HI>Proclamations</HI> (which have been multiplied every year beyond all
reckoning, and stretching the designs of the Court beyond all Mea∣sures,
no only of Legality, but of Humanity, expecting at the next
Parliament to have them either justified or Indemnified and pardon∣ed)<NOTE PLACE="marg">Grie∣vance 24.</NOTE>
were with Tyrannous Rigor executed by Circuit Courts of Inqui∣sition
(some way equally if not exceeding the <HI>Spanish,</HI> for illegality
and inhumanity) pressing Conformity, submission to Prelacy, Im∣possing,
enslaving and ensnaring Oaths and Bonds, contradictory to
Reason, and contrary to Religion; and Oppressing of all Ranks,
Qualities, and Vocations, with such Arbitrary Acts of Intercom∣munings,
Finings, and other intollerable Impossitions, that they
seemed to drive at no less than the overturning what remained un∣destroyed
of Religion, Liberty, Law; or Conscience in the Nation.
For not only the Poorer sort were many wayes Oppressed, Plundered,
Pillaged, Impoverished, and Destroyed; but Gentlemen also were
extremely vexed, for alledged converse with Intercommuned Suffer∣ers,
being Fore faulted, Fined, and incarcerate, till they should pay
Summs, which neither they were obliged nor able to pay. And not
only were the formerly persecuted Ministers, lurking in the Land,
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
forced to leave it; or Cited and Compeared at their Courts were Im∣prisoned:
But even the Indulged Ministers, who by the Kings Supre∣macy
were Authorized to Preach in Churches alloted to them, were
as Arbitrarly Discharged, Summoned to their Circuits, and Impri∣soned.
Especially we, who durst not comply in less or more with
any of their Impositions, nor own their Usurpations and Tyranny,
whom therefore they represented in all their Edicts, as Enemies to all
Government and Humane Society, were exposed to, and made to en∣dure
the utmost of their rage.</P>
<P>Our Families were harassed, pillaged and laid waste, our Persons
were intercommuned,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance. 25.</NOTE> driven out of our own and all other habitari∣ons
into the Wilderness, being interdicted of all Harbour, Supply,
Comfort or Converse, by barbarous Edicts; and incestantly pursued
by numerous Forces, Horse, Foot, and Dragons powered into all
parts of the Country, Impowered and Commissioned to plunder and
pillage all houses where they heard we were seen; And not only to
search, hunt, &amp; chase us through all Towns, Villages, Cottages, Woods,
Moors, Mosses, and Mountains, forcing us us to flee to the remotest
Recesses in the wildest Deserts; But to Shoot, Hang, Drown, Mur∣der,
and make Havock of us, where ever they could apprehend us,
without Tryal or Sentence. Proclamations one after another were
Emitted, commanding all to raise the <HI>Hue</HI> and <HI>Cry</HI> after us, and not
only to advertise the Souldiers, but to concur with them in pursu∣ing
us, and to seek us out of all our Dens and Caves in the most re∣tired
places of the Mountains, which we digged under ground,
when we could not find a hiding place above the face of the Earth:
Whence we were redacted to many incredible hardships and hazards,
being exposed to the cold blasts of Winter, and the pinching straits
of Hunger, when we could neither have Sustenance with us, nor
durst we go abroad to seek it but in the peril of our Lives, and being
forced to hide from Country People as well as Souldiers: Whence
many of us could not escape falling into their bloody hands, who,
in obedience to their murdering Mandates killed many instantly in
the Fields; And such as obtained the favour of being spared for exe∣cution
upon Scaffolds, tho without any colourable shadow of a for∣mal
procedure, or were imprisoned, Tortured, or Banished to be
Slaves, were thought to have been very mercifully dealt with. Where∣upon,
being driven to such a paraxisme of Danger and Despair, that
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
neither, were we able to endure the extremities of inexpressible mise∣ries
then lying and growing upon us, nor had hope to escape in Hu∣mane
probability the utter destruction intended, enacted, declared,
and indefatigably pursued against us by our Enemies, the <HI>Popish,
Prelatieal</HI> and <HI>Malignant</HI> faction; When so many of us were daily taken
and murdered, and the rest of us could neither escape by flight out
of the Land, (Orders being given to stop all passages by Sea and Land,
and catch us wheresoever we could be deprehended making any such
Essay) nor by lurking and hiding in the Land, through the Vigilance
and Diligence of Intelligencers, who were suborned and encouraged
to use all endeavours to intrap and inform of us, wheresoever we
could be heard of; No other expedient was left under our Delibe∣ration
to try for preventing our utter extermination, than to publish,
by affixing on the Church-doors in the night season, an <HI>Apologetick
Declaration,</HI> avowing our Adherence to former Principles and Testi∣monies,
and warning our Enemies to surcease from their wickedness
and severity against us, under certifications that it should be reveng∣ed:
Designing hereby mainly to restrain and deter these insolent In∣telligencers.</P>
<P>Hereupon followed a most violent Proclamation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 26.</NOTE> Ordaining all
that owned or refused to disown the Declaration, and the principles
therein specified, should be execute to the Death; Commanding
all the Subjects to concur in the pursute of us; And for their encou∣ragement,
offering 500 Merks for each of us; Requiring also, that
none presume to offer to travel in the Country without Testificates of
their Loyalty, by taking the Oath of <HI>Abjuration,</HI> otherwise they should
be holden as concurrers with us, and therefore that none shall be
lodged without these Certificates. Hence the Trade and Commerce
of the Countrey was much interrupted and prejudged, by prohibiting
all to travel without a Pass in time of Peace. And to the reproach
of all Order and Government: Hostlers and common Inn-keepers
were made Judges impowered to impose Oaths upon all Passengers &amp;
Travellers, that their Passes were not forged and seigned. This Oath of
Abjuration was pressed universally, on pain of Death, (in some places
from house to house) upon Men and Women, Young and Old; who
were pressed upon the penalty of Death, without time to advise upon
it, to give their judgement of the said Declaration, and of the Kings
Authority; which contributed very much to make it more and
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
more questioned by many, and rediculous to all. Hence many of
us that stood out and aloof from this complyance, were shot in the
Fields; some brought in Prisoners, Sentenced, and Executed all in
one day; and some early in the morning, that People might not be
affected with the pitiful sight of such bloody severities; Yea, some∣times
the Spectators were commanded by Captain <HI>Graham</HI> in <HI>Edin∣burgh,</HI>
to give their judgement, and declare their Opinion, whether
they were justly put to Death or not.</P>
<P>In process of time, the late King dying, and the Duke of <HI>York</HI> as∣cending
the Throne;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 27.</NOTE> It would have been thought, that such Revo∣lutions
then occurring would have required and produced some Ces∣sation,
Relaxation, or Relentment of our persecution: being in our
selves, and in our persecutors esteem, persons of so mean a Figure in
the World, scarce worthy to be the Object of the indignation of a
new installed Prince; And his late Proclamations would make the
World believe, that the beginning of his Government had put an end
to all these troubles upon the account of Conscience. But on the con∣trare,
the Acts and Executions against us in a manner did then but
begin to be cruel; And all the power of the Forces was imployed to
destroy us, so much already destroyed. For then, more cruelly than
ever, not only the standing Forces, but another Host of savage <HI>High∣landers,</HI>
inured to Rapine and Murder, brought from the North,
were ordered and impowered to Act against us the greatest Barbari∣ties,
in butchering and slaughtering us in the Fields where ever we
could be found, without all colour of Justice, only for not satisfying
them in their impertinent as well as wicked impositions on the Con∣science,
or form of Law, even the worst of their own Laws. Accord∣ingly
some of us at Labour, same traveling in the Road, were cut off
without pity; Some surprised in Caves, and Murdered there; without
time given to Pray to God for Mercy; some were taken first to Prison,
then surprised with execution, without a Triall or definite sentence,
not knowing when or if at all they should be execute; Some had their
Ears cutt, &amp; then sentenced to be transported to <HI>Iamaica,</HI> and yet some
of these were kept, and again sentenced with Death, and Executed:
others were sent to an old ruinous Castle <HI>Denotter,</HI> and kept in Vaults,
in such crouds and Numbers, that they had no room either to sit or
lie, and so cruelly treated, as would make Savages blush to hear of
it, and then banished to <HI>America,</HI> and in the Voyage about 60 died.</P>
<P><PB N="21" REF="14"/>
But as those cruelties were Monstrnous for Illegality and Inhuma∣nity;
so the ensuing Laws made in the first Parliament, <HI>Iames</HI> 7th.
1685. held by <HI>Queensberry</HI> Commissioner, Approving and Ratifying
the same, do far exceed all former for unparalelled Attrociousness:
As <HI>Act</HI> 3. Allowing Pannals already in prison, and indicted for Trea∣son,
to be cited on 24 houres. <HI>Act</HI> 4. Statuting, That such as being
cited to be witnesses as in cases of Treason, Field or House Conven∣ticles,
do refuse to depone, they shall be lyable to be punished as
guilty of these Crimes respectively, in which they refuse to be wit∣nesses.
<HI>Act</HI> 5. Declaring, That the giving or taking the <HI>National Co∣venant</HI>
or the <HI>Solemn League and Covenant,</HI> or writing in Defence there∣of,
or owning of them as Lawful, or Obligatory on themselves or o∣thers,
shall infer the crime and pains of Treason. <HI>Act</HI> 6. Declar∣ing
the usual procedure of Fyning Husbands for their Wives with∣drawing
from the Church, to have been Legal. <HI>Act</HI> 7. Statuting,
That the concealing and not revealing of any supply given to such,
as are Forefaulted for Treason (<HI>to wit,</HI> the most innocent contend∣ing
for the <HI>Covenants</HI> and Work of <HI>Reformation,</HI> against Popery, Prela∣cy,
or Tyranny, and tho the supply should be given to their nearest
Relations so foresaulted) is Treason, and to be judged accordingly.
<HI>Act</HI> 8 Statuting, That all that shall hereafter Preach at House or Field
Conventicles, and all Hearers also at Field Conventicles shall be pu∣nished
by Death and Confiscation. <HI>Act</HI> 13. Reinjoyning, and fur∣ther
extending the Imposition of the Self-contradictory Test. <HI>Act</HI> 17.
Ratifying, Confirming, and Approving what hath been done by the
Privy Council, Justiciary, or those commissionated by them, in Ba∣nishing,
Imprisoning, and Fyning such as refused to take the Oath of
Allegiance, (which includes the blasphemous Supremacy) with as∣serting
the Prerogatives; And under the same pains, Ordaining all
Subjects so to take the said Oath when required. <HI>Act</HI> 23. Ratifying
and Approving the Opinion of the Lords of Council and Session, ad∣judging
it Treason to refuse the Oath of Abjuration, confirming all
the illegality of procedure thereupon. <HI>Act</HI> 24. Statuting, That all
Masters, Heretors, Liferenters, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> shall insert in all Tacks to be set
by them to their Tennants, in Burgh or Landwart, an express clause,
oblieging the Tennant for his Wife and Family to Conformity, un∣der
exorbitant penalties. <HI>Act</HI> 25. Ratifying a Proclamation against
us, as bearing the effect of an Act of Parliament; Requiring all the
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
Subjects, upon knowledge or information of any one or two or moe
of us in any place, to give information thereof to the Chancellour, and
to the nearest Commanders of the <HI>Forces,</HI> within the space of an hour
at most for every three Miles distance, and all Sheriffs, &amp;c. To call the
Subjects to search and apprehend us; And on our flight, to acquaint
the Magistrates of the next Shire, and so from Shire of Shire, till we be
apprehended, or expelled from the Realm; with Certification, that
whosoever fails in pursuing us whether Magistrats or Subjects, or in
not giving timeous Information within the space forsaid, shall be held
as Art and Part, and undergo the same Punishment with us. In which
Act and Proclamation, we are called only 80 Runnagats, Traitors and
Fugitives, tho` in pursuance of this cruel Edict, they have Multiplied
that Number many times over and over, in imprisoning, banishing,
and butchering our Dear Brethren; And yet all the Prisons they could
fill, and Shipt they could fraught with us, and Gibbets they could hang
us on, could never either exhaust or lesson our Number: For the more
we were afflicted the more we grew; And the design to destroy us, by
the mercy of our GOD counteracting it, proved alwayes a burden∣some
Stone to the Destroyers, and an help to the Destroyed. Yet
tho they pretended to have us expelled out of the Realm, they shut
up all possible access to attempting to depart out of it: For, as Forces
were lying on each side the Borders to catch us if we should escape by
Land, so they prevented all probability of going by Sea, by <HI>Act</HI> 27.
of this same Parliament, Forbidding and Prohibiting all Masters of
Ships to export any Passenger till he be brought before the next Magi∣strates:
which none of us durst venture upon for fear of our Lives.</P>
<P>This was an unhappy Specimen of the Kings Commenced Govern∣ment,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 28.</NOTE>
and a very unprecedented Policy of his Counselors, to reconcile
male contented Subjects to a Loving and Consienciously Loyal Sub∣jection
to him, being in effect the same with the Advice of the Young
men to <HI>Rehoboam,</HI> and productive of the same effect with that: When
practically in their Acts and Actings it was declared to us, that where∣as
the former King had made our Yoke heavy; This would add
thereto: The former had <HI>chastised us with Whips, but he would chastise
us with Scorpions:</HI> Whereof having felt the smart so sharply, we could
not be easily induced to a kindly acknowledgment of Allegiance out
of Conscience unto him, who came not in as a Father to rule us, but as a
Lyon to devour us. Wherefore, tho much pressed by all the Tyran∣nical
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>
force, that could be exercised to enslave us under that Yoke, or
destroy us for refusing, we could not in Conscience own or acknow∣ledge
his Lawful Authority. And in pressing it they gained little, af∣ter
all the blood they shed on Scaffolds and Fields upon this account,
but to ridicule the Government, and make it more contemptible, when
they required every poor Lad &amp; Lass in the Country to give their Opi∣nion
of the <HI>Government,</HI> a Question very unusual to be proposed to pri∣vate
Subjects. Men really invested with Authority do think, their
Laws and Power to execute them on Offenders may well enough se∣cure
the Peoples subjection, and will disdain such a suspicion of the
questionablenss of their Authority, as to make it a Question to the Sub∣jects:
The more it was made a Question to us, the more it became
questioned and suspected: And the more we were made to enquire
into it, the further we were from deprehending or recognoscing in
him either the Characters or Constitution of a Magistrate to be
owned. We considered the many righteous Laws, established by our
worthy Ancestors, for the preservation of the True Religion and Li∣berties
of the Kingdom, insert in the <HI>National Covenant</HI> (which every
Soul in the Kingdom under the Bond of that Covenant, is bound, to
maintain according to their Capacities;) As <HI>Act 8 Parl.</HI> 1. King <HI>Ia:
6:</HI> repeated and ratified in many Acts afterwards, expresly providing
and ordaining, <Q>that all Kings and Princes, at their Coronation and
Reception of their Princely Authority, shall make their faithful
promise by Oath, and that they shall profess and maintain the <HI>Pro∣testant</HI>
Religion, and shall abolish and gainstand all false Religion
contrary the same, and shall rule according to Law, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></Q> Which
Oath of Coronation he did not take, would not take, could not take,
while a Papist; and therefore we could not look on him as our King
by Law. We considered likewise, that in our Covenants the Alle∣giance
that we must own to the King is expresly limited and qualified
thus, <HI>In the preservation and defence of the True Rellgion, Liberties, and Laws
of the Kingdom:</HI> Of which Qualification, Allegiance to him, a destroy∣er
of Religion and Liberty, is nor capable. We remembred the
Principles and Sentiments of our Fathers upon the Admission of King
<HI>Charles</HI> 2. to the exercise of his Royal Power, Declared in their sea∣sonable
and necessary Warning, <HI>Gen: Assem. Iuly 27: Sess: 27:</HI> 1649.
Wherein they tell us, <Q>That a boundless and illimited Power is to
be acknowledged in no King nor Magistrate; that there is a mutual
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
Stipulation and Obligation between the King and the People, as
both of them are tyed to GOD, so each of them are tyed to one
another: Accordingly Kings are to take the Oath of Coronation,
to abolish Popery and maintain the <HI>Protestant Religion:</HI> As long
therefore as the King refuses to Engage and Obliege himself for se∣curity
of <HI>Religion,</HI> and safety; of his People it is consonant to <HI>Scripture</HI>
and Reason and Laws of the Kingdom, that he should be refused:
And that in the Covenant, the Duty of owning the King is subordi∣nate
to the Duty of preserving Religion and Liberty. And there∣fore,
without security of these, it were a manifest breach of Gove∣nant,
and a preferring the Kings Interest to the Interest of Christ, to
bring him to the exercise of his power.</Q> And consequently, for us
to give such a consent to it, as such an owning of him as required
would amount to. Accordingly also the Commission of the <HI>General
Assembly</HI> in their Act of the <HI>West-Kirk,</HI> Declared, <Q>They would not
own the King nor his Interest, otherwise than with a subordination
to GOD, and so far as he should own and prosecute the Cause of
GOD, and disclaim his and his Fathers opposition to the Work of
GOD and the Covenant.</Q> We called to mind likewise, what our
Renowned Reformers gave out, as the case of their Revolt from the
Government of <HI>Mary</HI> Qu: <HI>Dowager, anno</HI> 1559. her persecuting the Pro∣fessors
of the True Religion, and oppressing the Liberties of the True
Lieges, her intruding of Magistrates against all Order of Election, her
Adultering and Subverting the Old Laws of the Realm, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Which
all Men know were as applicable to King <HI>Iames</HI> 7th: as to her: And
therefore we had their Reason to obliege us, and their example to en∣courage
us to say with them; <Q>We own and promise to our Lawful
Soveraign all due Obedience, provided we may have our Religion
and Liberty secured, without which we firmely purpose never to be
subject to Mortal Man.</Q> For which and many other Reasons, we
reckoned our selves under Obligations to decline the imposed owning
of his Authority; and took the opportunity in the time of the Expe∣dition
of the Earl of <HI>Argyle</HI> against him, to Publish in a Declaration
our Reasons why we could not acknowledge it.</P>
<P>In the mean time,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 29.</NOTE> the late Earl of <HI>Argyle,</HI> with some other Noble∣men
and Gentlemen, Associating with the Duke of <HI>Munmouth,</HI> to
essay some Diversion and Opposition to the Kings designs, of advan∣cing
and establing Tyrannie and Popery: All the Forces, Militia
<PB N="25" REF="16"/>
Troups and Companies, and the whole Army of Heretors were
powred in upon those Places of the Kingdom, where most of us were
sojourning. Who, besides all the blood shed upon the account of that
Expedition, the Blood of the Earle himself, and others of both
Nations engaged with him, and many of his Wassalls in the High∣lands
cruely put to Death by the Marq. of <HI>Athol,</HI> had in Commission,
and put in execution the Bloodiest Orders we think readily Men could
ever receive or obey. The greatest employment, that that great
Army had in hand and in heart, was to wreck and exert all their fury
and force upon the poor <HI>Mountain-Men</HI> as they called us: Which
they did by ranging and spreading themselves many miles in breadth,
every one within sight of another, and searching for us through all
the Rocks, Woods, Mountains, and Mosses of the Country, where we
were hiding, with such Vigore, Violence, and dilligence, as if they
had been hunting for <HI>Hares</HI> or <HI>Foxes.</HI> And the greatest ambition and
emulation of their Leaders and Champions, <HI>Graham</HI> of <HI>Claver-house,</HI>
&amp; Liev. Gen. <HI>Douglas</HI> Brother to the Duke of <HI>Queensberry,</HI> Col. <HI>Buchan,</HI>
with others of their inferiour Officers, Maj. <HI>Balfour,</HI> Liev. <HI>Creightoun,</HI>
and Liev. <HI>Livingstoun,</HI> &amp;c. was, who should be most skilful and succes∣full
in destroying us. And all this, for no other Cause, then because
we could not Answer to their satisfaction the Questions they proposed,
without any warrant of Law, and against the Common Interest of
Mankind, which frees all Men from being obliged to discover their
secret thoughts; Namely because we could not obtain of our Consciences
to declare that we would own and acknowledge that Authority which
enacted, and by which they acted, all these mischiefs. Yet, to the
commendation of GODS Clemency, and condemnation of Mens
cruelty, we may say, when they had shot all their bolts, after they
had hanged, shot, tortured, or banished for slaves, all they could catch
of us, they were further from their purpose than when they began; our
Numbers and Mettings for Gospel ordinances, Administrated in Purity
and power, encreased more and more.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Grie∣vance 30.</NOTE></P>
<P>But at length, tho' our Persecution continued, the King was pleased
to change his Methods with other Dissenters. He multiplied many
Favours to such of them as he called <HI>Moderate:</HI> And, by these means
intending to advance the Mysterie of iniquity, by stoping the mouths,
and binding up the hands of all from whom he might expect Control
or Contradiction, and laying them by from all open opposition to
<PB N="26" REF="17"/>
the introduction of Poperie and advancement of Slaverie, he purposed
and proposed the repealing of the <HI>Penal Statutes</HI> against Papists, at the
Parliament held by the Earl of <HI>Murray:</HI> Against which, when af∣terwards
some of the Common sort of people, and of the Souldiers,
spoke some what freely, and for shewing their dislike of setting up the
Idolatrous Mass, and for speaking against Poperie, and the designs of
the King, they were put to Death in a most Despotical and Arbitrary
manner. The Persecution the mean while still continuing against
us, and growing more dangerous, and worse to bear that we had all
the brunt of it to sustain; while the Forces had few other to Persecute
but us: which they did in great fury, murdering in Fields and Scaf∣folds,
such as they could catch of us.</P>
<P>At length, what could not be obtained by Law, at the formentio∣ned
Parliament for taking off the Penal Statutes, was effectuate by
Prerogative, in a Proclamation, <HI>Feb: 12:</HI> 1687. Granting, by the Kings
Soveraign Authority,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Grie∣vance 31.</NOTE> Prerogative Royal, and Absolute Power, <HI>which
Subjects are to obey without Reserve;</HI> a <HI>Toleration,</HI> under certain conditions,
Restrictions, and Limitations, to all sorts of Perswasions, excepting
us who are left to the full vigor and utmost rigor of the Laws made
against us: Suspending, Stoping and Disabling all Laws, or Acts of
Parliament, customs or constitutions against any <HI>Roman Catholick</HI> Sub∣jects;
giving them freedom in all respects, as much as any <HI>Prtoestant</HI>
Subjects, whatsoever, not only to Exercise their Religion, but to
enjoy all Offices, Benefices, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> which he shall think fit to bestow u∣pon
them in all time coming. Hence Papists were put into places of
highest Trust, both Civil and Military: And Popish Magistrates
without any Election established in Burghs, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> contrare to the known
Laws of the Kingdom, admitting none to be <Q>Magistrates, or so
much as a Procutator, Notar, or member of Court, who professes
not the Protestant Religion, <HI>Act 9. Parl: 1. Iames</HI> 6. Declaring all
Papists infamous, and unable to sit or stand in Judgment, pursue,
bear Office, or to be admitted as proves, Witness, or Assisors a∣gainst
Protestants.</Q> <HI>Act 45: Parl: 3: Iames 6:</HI> which is extended to all
and whatsomever Office, without any Exception or Restriction in
all time coming. <HI>Act 5: Parl: 20: Iames 6:</HI> Hence also the Idolatrous
<HI>Mass</HI> was set up in the most publick places of the Kingdom; and Po∣pish
Seminary Priests suffered and encouraged to preach, and set up
Schools, to seduce the People, especially the Youth: contrate to
many express standing Laws, <HI>Act 3: Parl: 1: Iames 6:</HI> and <HI>Act 5: ibid:</HI>
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
<Q>Ordaining all layers or hearers of Mass to be punished, with im∣prisonment
for the first fault, banishment for the second, and justi∣fying
to the Death for the third fault. <HI>Act 122: Iarl: 12: K: Iames 6:</HI>
Decerning, That, in all time coming, the saying of Mass, resetting
of Jesuites, Seminary Priests, Traffiquing Papists, shall be just cause
to infer the pain and crime of Treason. <HI>Act 196: Parl: 14: Iames 6:</HI>
Ordaining in all time coming,</Q> all wilfull hearers of Mass, and con∣cealers
of the same, be execute to the Death: Ratified in the 1 <HI>Act.
Parl. 19. Iac.</HI> 6. And in 5. <HI>Act. Parl: 20: Iac:</HI> 6. Hence Papists have
erected Schools, and made, sold, and dispersed their Heretical Books,
tending to seduce the People from the true Religion: contrary to
express Laws, <HI>Act. 106. Parl: 7: Iac: 6: Act</HI> 24, and 25: <HI>Parl: 11: I:</HI> 6.
This Popish Toleration, was neither extended to us; all the three
Proclamations thereof expresly providing, that Field Conventicles, &amp;
all Preachers and Hearers thereat, be prosecuted according to the ut∣most
Severity and Rigor of the Lawes made against them, left in
their full Force and Vigor, with a Command to all Judges, Magi∣strates
and Officers of <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orces, to pursue us with all Violence; Nor
could we in Conscience and Duty, directly or indirectly, suffer our
selves to be involved, by any participation therewith or acceptance
thereof, in the sin of it against the Laws of GOD and Man: Since
it appeared evidently to flow from a Blasphemous fountain of Abso∣lute
Power; through a Treasonable Channel of stoping, Suspending,
and disabling the Penal Statutes made against the Enemies of GOD,
and of the Kingdom; and to be designed for the wicked ends of sub∣verting
the Protestant Religion, and the peaceable introduction of
Popish Idolatrie and Heresie; And to offer, not the establishment of
our Religion, but the Tolerating of it, under the scandalous notion
of a thing to be suffered for a while; and with such shameful securi∣ties,
as robbed the Church of all her Legal Charters of Laws and Co∣venants
establishing her Reformation, leaving her nothing in lieu
thereof but a blind precarious promise of One, whose principles ob∣lieged
him to keen no Faith with those to whom he promised it. But
against all these indignities done to Christ, and injuries to the Church,
intended and effected by this Toleration, our Ministers thought
themselves oblieged to bear witness and Testimony: And with re∣spect
both to necessity and duty, to continue to keep their Meetings
in the open Fields, whether the Tyranny of the times had driven
them: Since they durst neither seem to Homologate the Toleration,
<PB N="28" REF="18"/>
by coming under the sconce of such a protection; Nor durst they give
such advantage to such as were insatiably thirsting after their Blood,
and were impowered to shed it, as they were seeking and would have
found, if they had shut up themselves within houses, that could neither
hold their Friends, nor be hid from their Enemies. This we looked
upon as a Testimony, for the interest of the Protestant Religion, for
our Covenanted Reformation, for the Laws &amp; Liberties of our Coun∣try,
all undermined and sought to be subverted by that Toleration.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griev∣ance 32.</NOTE></P>
<P>In the prosecution of this Device, when others were killed with
Popish kindnesses, we were left to feell the sweet effects of Popish
Crueltie. Some of our Bretheren were Murdered in Fields and Scaf∣folds,
since that pretended Toleration; Many both Men and Women
have been banished and Sold for Slaves in <HI>Barbados:</HI> Other severe Pro∣clamations
were issued against our Ministers, Intercommuning, &amp; set∣ing
a pryce upon their Heads, to encourage all to apprehend them
Dead or alive: One of them, Mr. <HI>Iames Renwick</HI> a painful Minister
being <HI>Feb.</HI> 1688. was Executed to the Death in <HI>Edinburgh,</HI> the Drums
beating all the time of his Praying and speaking upon the Scaffold.
And after this, not only was the Country oppressed with Souldiers, free
quarterings, and frighted with their searches, and Insolences in their
ryding up and down the Country, challenging peaceable Travellers
upon the Road, about their Opinions of the Kings Authority, and
if this and that was Rebellion; and threatning present Death to such
as did not satisfie them: But the City of <HI>Edinburgh</HI> vexed with uni∣versal
searches, and the impositions of these impertinences, whereby
many were taken and examined by <HI>Claver-house,</HI> who required them
to renounce the Covenant, imprisoned the Recusants; Whereby the
Prisons were crouded: And yet, notwithstanding of an Indemni∣ty,
<HI>October 2:</HI> 1688 alledged as ample as Absolute Power could make
it, tho not expresly excluded, they were detained Prisoners until the
Report of his Highness the Prince of <HI>Orange,</HI> now King of <HI>Brittain</HI> his
prevailing, and fear of his Victorious Arms did move them not to
keep any longer any that might be evidences and Witnesses of their
Arbitrary cruelty. As the same reason also it seems did constrain
them, to take down and bury the heads of those they murdered, for
fear lest these monuments of their cruelty standing, might occasion
the Question to be moved, by whom and for what they were set up?
<PB N="29" REF="18"/>
Than which nothing shall be more confounding to them, when in∣quisition
shall be made for blood.</P>
<P>Thus these Enemies of the Country, the encroaching Privy Coun∣cil,
and the Prelates in special, now universally contemned since the
Toleration, were going on in their Designs to enslave the Nation,
and to prevent and suppress all Essayes to retrive or revive any hopes
of recovering any Liberty;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Grie∣vance 33.</NOTE> Multiplying their searches, not only for
us, but for any that were suspected to favour their present Majesties
Cause, and undertaking, so soon as it began to be surmised here; and
laying up in irons and closs prison some Gentlemen, upon suspicion
of their being privy to it. And, as soon as they had certain intelli∣gence
of King <HI>William</HI> his great and generous Resolutions, in order to
the Restauration and Preservation of Religion, Laws, and Liberties,
in these three Kingdoms, They made such vigorous preparations for
opposition, and issued out such virulent Proclamations inveighing a∣gainst
his Highness, under such severities of certifications, requiring
all from 60: to 16: to concur under their displayed Banner for Arbi∣trary
Government, as if they had feared an Invasion from <HI>Turks</HI> or
<HI>Tartars.</HI> Yet in the mean time, tho there were suspicions then, and dis∣coveries
since, of an intended <HI>Popish Massacre,</HI> they disarmed the <HI>Western</HI>
Shires, and sent Orders to the Officers of Forces, especially imploying
such as were professedly Popish, to go through the Country, and take
all their Armes, leaving them nothing to defend themselves withal,
and causing the People to swear that they had no other Armes than
such as they got. And in their march, meeting with some of our
number, they threatned to shoot them presently if they would not
own King <HI>Iames,</HI> pray for him, and for confusion to all his Enemies:
which they refusing at first were appointed to be shot, and had their
faces covered with Napkins, and with great difficulty escaped by com∣plying.</P>
<P>By the former Summary and abridged Abstract and compendious
Deduction of our many and manifold Grievances (the Truth where∣of
can be evidenced by many demonstrative Evidences) it may ap∣pear
what have been our sufferiugs since that fatal Revolution, <HI>anno
1660:</HI> from the Popish, Prelatical, and Malignant Party; and what
have been their Attempts, Machins, and Methods to overturn our
Religion, Laws, and Liberties, and subject us to meer Arbitrary and
Absolute Tyrannie; At least what have been their capital Devices,
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
whereby they have ruined and sought to raze us; And what have
been the principal causes and kinds of our Sufferings, in their prose∣cuting
the same: The particular Relation of which, so far as can be
collected, is intended (GOD willing) afterwards in due season to be
published. Only here it may not be inconvenient to subjoyn, by way
of specimen, a short Recapitulation in bulk of some instances of our
several kinds of Sufferings, with a touch at some of the most principal
Instruments thereof in the five <HI>Western</HI> Shires</P>
<P>First, For <HI>Fines,</HI> and other Exorbitant and Illegal Exactions of
Money, the particular summs cannot be here enumerated; but their
vastness, when together calculate, may be easily collected by the scraps
already gathered, of some poor Families of Farmers, Cottars, Ser∣vants,
<HI>&amp;c.</HI> and many of these omitted, or not known, which would very
considerably augment the summ) in some few Shires; <HI>viz. Clidsdale,
Renfrew, Air, Galloway, Nithsdale,</HI> and <HI>Annandale,</HI> only for but a few
years, to wit, since <HI>Bothwel bridge</HI> insurrection, amounting to above
288000. pounds <HI>Scots</HI> Money.</P>
<P>Besides the many honest Families, which have been casten out of
their houses, harassed and spoiled of their <HI>All:</HI> Some of their houses
being thrown down, some Burnt, some shut up, their goods and
moveables seized upon, their Crop and Cattel also disposed of, at the
will of their Persecuters, in the forementioned Shires amounting to
above 200: of all which we have a particular account in readiness to
instruct.</P>
<P>The immediate Authors, Actors, and Instruments of these oppres∣sions,
were principally the <HI>Curates</HI> instigating the <HI>Privy Council,</HI> which
impowered the Forces, and Noblemen and Gentlemen of the Coun∣try,
to prey upon the poor People. All cannot be here expressed, but
some of the most noted in the <HI>Western</HI> Shires shall be named, who were
the greatest Persecuters and Oppressors by Finings and other Ex∣actions.</P>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="list of oppressors">
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Of Officers of the Forces.</HEAD>
<P>Col. <HI>Dowglas,</HI> now Liev: Gen.
<HI>Dowglas,</HI> Brother to the Duke of
<HI>Queensberry,</HI> exacted above 2000
Pounds Scots Money, in <HI>Galloway,
Nithsdale, Shire of Aire,</HI> and other
Places.</P>
<P>Liev. Gen. <HI>Drumond,</HI> besides the
Forefaultries of Gentlemen, did
also exact moneys of the poor in
the Shire of <HI>Air.</HI></P>
<P>The Earl of <HI>Lithgow,</HI> and his
Souldiers, spoiled much in <HI>Gal∣loway.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="31" REF="19" MS="y"/>
The Earl of <HI>Airly,</HI> and his
Troup, in the same Shire</P>
<P>The Lord <HI>Balearras,</HI> a great
Oppressor in <HI>Galloway,</HI> besides all
the Robberies he committed in
<HI>Fife.</HI></P>
<P><HI>—Graham</HI> of <HI>Claverhouse,</HI> after∣wards
Viscount of <HI>Dundee,</HI> with
his Brother, and subaltern Officers
in <HI>Galloway, Nithsdale,</HI> and <HI>Anan∣dale,</HI>
exacted by Fines and other∣wise,
above 13500: pounds <HI>Scots</HI>
money.</P>
<P>Col: <HI>Buchan,</HI> a most violent
persecuter, in <HI>Galloway</HI> and Shire
of <HI>Air,</HI> by Robberies took from
the People upwards of 4000:
pounds <HI>Scots.</HI></P>
<P>Major <HI>Cockburn,</HI> a great op∣pressor
in <HI>Galloway.</HI></P>
<P>Major <HI>White,</HI> in <HI>Clidsdale</HI> and
shire of <HI>Air,</HI> exacted by Fines and
otherwise, above 2500. p: <HI>Scots.</HI></P>
<P>Major <HI>Balfour,</HI> now called Liev:
Col; <HI>Balfour,</HI> a great persecuter
and Oppressor in <HI>Clidsdale.</HI></P>
<P>Captain <HI>Strauchan,</HI> with his
Troup, oppressed and spoiled
much in <HI>Galloway,</HI> &amp; other places.</P>
<P>Captain <HI>Inglis</HI> with his Troup,
did dispossess many Families, and
got much spoil in <HI>Galloway,</HI> shire
of <HI>Air,</HI> and <HI>Clidsdale.</HI></P>
<P>Captain <HI>Dowglas,</HI> in <HI>Galloway,</HI>
committed much outrage and
spoil.</P>
<P>Captain <HI>Dalzel,</HI> harassed much
in <HI>Anandale.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Captain</HI> Bruce <HI>in</HI> Nithsdale.</P>
<P>—<HI>Meldrum</HI> in <HI>Clidsdale,</HI> in several
Inroads uplifted from poor Fami∣lies
upwards of 2300 Pounds; besi∣des
the vast summes he exacted in
<HI>Mers</HI> and <HI>Tiviotdale;</HI> with the Earle
of <HI>Hume, Ker</HI> of <HI>Gradown,</HI> Laird of
<HI>Hayning,</HI> and <HI>Blindlee;</HI> and in <HI>Twed∣dale,</HI>
with the Laird of <HI>Possa,</HI> all
great Persecuters.</P>
<P>Liv. <HI>Winram,</HI> in <HI>Galloway,</HI> a very
vigilant Persecuter and Spoyler.</P>
<P>Liev. <HI>Barns</HI> also, in the same
Shire took much Spoyl.</P>
<P>Liev. <HI>Iohn Living stoun,</HI> a most
violent Persecuter and Exacter.</P>
<P>Liev. <HI>Lauder,</HI> in the Shire of
<HI>Air,</HI> a most outragious Persecuter
and Oppressor.</P>
<P>—<HI>Bonshaw,</HI> a Borderer, a High∣way
Man, afterwards an Officer
of Dragoons, robbed much from
the poor People in <HI>Clidsdale.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Duncan Grant,</HI> a Creple with a
Tree Leg, a very outragious Per∣secuter,
exacted in <HI>Clidsdale</HI> from
poor People, above 1500 pounds.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Of Noblemen, Gentlemen,
and Others, in the above-mentioned
Shires, the grea∣test
Oppressors and Perse∣cuters
of the people, were;
In Clidsdale.</HEAD>
<P><HI>—Sommervail,</HI> of <HI>Spittel</HI> Sheriff de.
pute. who, besides his other wayes
of Persecution wherein he was
most Active, drew from the poor∣est
People above 1200 pounds.</P>
<P><PB N="32" REF="20" MS="y"/>
The Laird of <HI>Halyards,</HI> who up∣lifted
more then 8500 pounds.</P>
<P>The Laird of <HI>Lachop,</HI> a great
Persecuter and Oppressor.</P>
<P>The Laird of <HI>Bonnytown,</HI> and
Laird <HI>Symme,</HI> both violent Perse∣cuters
and Exactors.</P>
<P>In the City of <HI>Glasgow,</HI> Provest
<HI>Iohnston,</HI> Prov. <HI>Barns,</HI> Bail. <HI>Iohn An∣derson,</HI>
Bail: <HI>Yuil,</HI> Bail. <HI>Graham, Wil∣liam
Sterling</HI> Baron Baylif, great
Persecuters, exacted above 20000
pounds.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>In Renfrew.</HEAD>
<P>The Earl of <HI>Glencairn,</HI> by Fines
and dispossessing of Families, ex∣acted,
partly there, and partly in
<HI>Clidsdale</HI> and <HI>Nidsdale,</HI> above 2400
pounds.</P>
<P>Lord <HI>Semple</HI> a <HI>Papist,</HI> a persecuter.</P>
<P><HI>Alexander Hume</HI> in <HI>Eglshome,</HI> a
most violent and vigilant Persecut∣er
and Exactor, with many others.</P>
<P>Mr. <HI>Ezechiel Montgomery</HI> a great
Fine-Monger.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>In the Shire of Air</HEAD>
<P>The Earle of <HI>Drumfries,</HI> exact∣ed
above 1000: pounds.</P>
<P>The Lord <HI>Craigy,</HI> a great perse∣cuter
and oppressor.</P>
<P><HI>William Creighton</HI> Sheriff depute
very violent and active.</P>
<P><HI>Crawford</HI> of <HI>Ardmillan,</HI> a
wicked persecuter and spoiler.</P>
<P>Mr. <HI>William Crawford, Montgo∣mery</HI>
of <HI>Bozland,</HI> Laird of <HI>Broyche,</HI>
Clark <HI>Ogilbie,</HI> all great persecu∣ters,
who sought to make them∣selves
up with the spoils of the
poor people.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>In Galloway.</HEAD>
<P>The Laird of <HI>Lag Grierson,</HI> a
most wicked persecuter there, and
in <HI>Nithisdale,</HI> exacted above 1200:
pounds.</P>
<P>The Laird of <HI>Elie, Lidderdale,</HI>
and <HI>Canon</HI> of <HI>Merdrogat,</HI> all
diligent persecuters and Intelli∣gencers,
together with the then
Collectors.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>In Nithsdale.</HEAD>
<P>The Duke of <HI>Queensberry</HI> and
his Sons oppressed much.</P>
<P><HI>Iohn Alison</HI> Chamberlain to the
Duke of <HI>Queensberry,</HI> who when
dying, said, <HI>He had damned
his Soul for the Duke his
Master.</HI> And <HI>George Charters,</HI> an∣other
of the Dukes Factors, who
vaunted, he had made 26: jour∣neys
in one year in pursuite of the
Whiggs.</P>
<P><HI>Iohn Dowglas</HI> of <HI>Sten-house,</HI> a
Papist, exacted above 5000: p:</P>
<P>The Laird of <HI>Closburn,</HI> above
700: pounds.</P>
<P>Sir <HI>Robert Dalzel,</HI> upward of
400: p: of a few poor Families.</P>
<P>Sir <HI>Robert Lawrie</HI> of <HI>Maxweltoun,</HI>
an oppressor and persecuter.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>In Anandale.</HEAD>
<P>The Lord <HI>Anandale,</HI> disposses∣sed
and harassed many Families,
and persecuted much in <HI>Galloway.</HI></P>
<P>The Laird of <HI>Westerhall,</HI> a great
Per: exacted upwards of 1000: p:</P>
<P><PB N="33" REF="20"/>
Sir <HI>Patrick Maxwel</HI> of <HI>Sprinkell</HI> a
very active and violent persecu∣ter
and oppressor.</P>
<P><HI>The Lairds of</HI> Powdeen, Castle∣milk,
Robert Caruthers <HI>of</HI> Rama∣skells,
Thomas Kennedy <HI>of</HI> Heybeiths,
<HI>most violent persecuters of poor
People.</HI></P>
<P>The Summes here charged up∣on
these Gentlemen, are collected
from the Minutes the Writer had
by him, which he is certain are
computed within the extent of
the several Summes. The rest
here named did also extort Con∣siderable
Summes, to their own
gain and the poor Peoples loss; but
because the forsaid Minuts do not
give a Particular account of the
<HI>Quotas</HI> therefore they are not sup∣plied.</P>
<P>Next for the <HI>Forefaulted</HI> Gentle∣men
and Heretors, we shall not
meddle with them: Hoping they
shall give a good account of them∣selves.</P>
<P>And as for the number of such
as have been forced to a <HI>Voluntary
Exile</HI> to Forreign Countries, we
think it Impossible to come to any
reckoning of them: Nor of these
that have been <HI>Imprisoned</HI> these 30.
Years for Nonconformity, of
whom it cannot be told how many
have died in Prison, or contracted
their Death in Prison, which spedi∣ly
did follow upon their Libe∣ration.
Nor of the many extorted
vast Sums, and Robberies of pri∣soners
by <HI>Iaylors.</HI></P>
<P>Of the <HI>Banished,</HI> deported into
other Countries, for the Cause of
Adhering to the Covenant and
Work of Reformation, it may
suffice to give this account Besides
the 6. or 7. Ministers that were
banished, and went to <HI>Holland:</HI> and
7. or 8. Country People to <HI>France;</HI>
Several others to <HI>Barbados,</HI> before
<HI>Pentland.</HI> Since the Year 1678.
there have been banished and sent
away Slaves, of Men and Wo∣men,
for the same Cause, 700.
viz. <HI>anno.</HI> 1678. To <HI>Virginia,</HI> 60.
whereof 3. or 4. were Ministers,
who were all by the Mercy of God
delivered at <HI>London.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Anno.</HI> 1679. Of the Prisoners
taken at <HI>Bothwel,</HI> were banished
to <HI>America, 250:</HI> who were taken
away by <HI>Paterson</HI> Mer∣chant
in <HI>Leith,</HI> that transacted for
them with Provost <HI>Milns,</HI> Laird of
<HI>Barntown;</HI> the Man that first did
burn the Covenant; whereof 200:
were drowned by Shipwrack, be∣ing
shut up within the hatches,
50 escaped.</P>
<P>Afterwards were banished to
<HI>Flanders,</HI> 7. men.</P>
<P>Thereafter were taken away in
Banishment, by one <HI>Robert Maloch,
14.</HI> men.</P>
<P>Then by <HI>Walter Gibson,</HI> Late
Provest in <HI>Glasgow,</HI> to <HI>Corolina</HI> 30.</P>
<P><HI>Anno.</HI> 1685. in the time of <HI>Queens∣berries</HI>
Parliament of Men and
Women were sent to <HI>Iamaica</HI> 200.</P>
<P><PB N="34" REF="21"/>
That same Year, of the Prison∣ers
in <HI>Dinotter</HI> with others were
taken away by <HI>Pitlochie,</HI> to <HI>New∣gersie</HI>
100. whereof 24. were Wo∣men.</P>
<P>That same Year, 13. more were
sent to <HI>Barbados.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Anno.</HI> 1687. after the Toleration
21. Men and Women were sent
to <HI>Barbados.</HI></P>
<P>As for the Number of the slain
at the several Skirmages at <HI>Pentland
Bothuel, Airdsmoss, &amp;c.</HI> They a∣mount
too about 400. and some
odds.</P>
<P>The Number of such as have
been executed to Death on Scaf∣folds,
under collour of Law, from
Mr. <HI>Iames Gutherie</HI> the first, to Mr.
<HI>Iames Renwick,</HI> is about 140,
whereof some were Women.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="list of victims">
<HEAD>The list of those that were killed in
cold Blood, without Tryal, Con∣viction,
or any colour of Law,
by the persons under writ∣ten,
followeth.</HEAD>
<P>Omitting the account of
<HI>Finlay,</HI> murdered by General <HI>Dal∣zels</HI>
orders at <HI>Air,</HI> because he could
not discover who was at the ap¦pearance
at <HI>Pentland,</HI> in the year
1666; And of <HI>Iames Davie</HI> in <HI>Bath∣gate</HI>
paroch, and several others, at
several times, in several places,
whose blood was mingled with
their sacrifice at Sermons in the
Fields, before <HI>Bothwel-bridge;</HI> And
of <HI>Thomas Ker</HI> of <HI>Heyhope,</HI> brother
to the Laird of <HI>Cherrie trees,</HI> who
was forced to flee for shelter into
the <HI>English</HI> Borders, and there kil∣led
by Col: <HI>Struthers, anno 1678;</HI>
And of <HI>Henry Hall</HI> of <HI>Haughead,</HI>
apprehended at <HI>Queensferrie</HI> by
<HI>Midletoun</HI> Governour of
<HI>Blackness,</HI> and after several wounds,
at length knocked on the head by
<HI>Tho: George</HI> Waiter at <HI>Queensferrie.</HI></P>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>A short hint of those that have been
Murdered since the Year 1682. may
suffce.</HEAD>
<P><HI>Iohn Graham</HI> of <HI>Claver house,</HI> Vis∣count
of <HI>Dundee,</HI> in the Year 1682.
with a party of his <HI>Troup,</HI> pursued
<HI>William Graham</HI> in the parish of
in <HI>Galloway,</HI> making his escape
from his Mothers house, and o∣vertaking
him, instantly shot him
dead.</P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said <HI>Claver house,</HI> to∣gether
with the Earl of <HI>Dumbar∣ton,</HI>
and Liev: Gen: <HI>Dowglas,</HI> caused
<HI>Peter Gillis, Iohn Bryce, Thomas
Young,</HI> (who was taken by the
Laird of <HI>Lee,) William Fiddison,</HI>
and <HI>Iohn Buiening,</HI> to be put to
Death upon a Gibbet, without
Legal Tryal or Sentence, suffer∣ing
them neither to have a <HI>Bible,</HI>
nor to pray before they died, at
<HI>Mauchlin, anno</HI> 1685.</P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said <HI>Claverhouse</HI> com∣ing
to <HI>Galloway,</HI> in answer to the
Viscount of <HI>Kenmures</HI> Letter, with
<PB N="35" REF="21"/>
a small party surprised <HI>Robert Stu∣art,
Iohn Grier, Robert Ferguson,</HI>
and another, and instantly shot
them dead, at the water of <HI>Dee,</HI>
in <HI>Gallaway, December</HI> 1684. Their
Corps being buried, were at his
command raised again.</P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said <HI>Claverhouse</HI> in
<HI>May, 1685:</HI> apprehended <HI>Iohn
Broun</HI> in <HI>priest-hill,</HI> in the parish of
<HI>Moorkirk,</HI> in the Shire of <HI>Air,</HI> be∣ing
at his work, about his own
house, and shot him dead before
his own door, in presence of his
Wife.</P>
<P><HI>Item.</HI> the said <HI>Claverhouse</HI> Autho∣rised
his Troop to kill <HI>Matthew
Mckel wrath,</HI> without any Exa∣mination,
in the Paroch of <HI>Camo∣nel</HI>
in <HI>Carrick, Anno</HI> 1685.</P>
<P>Col. <HI>Iames Douglass,</HI> now <HI>Liev.
General,</HI> Brother to the Duke of
<HI>Queensberry,</HI> together with <HI>Liev:
Iohn Livingston,</HI> and a Party with
them, surprised 5: men in a
Cave at <HI>Inglestoun,</HI> in the parish of
<HI>Glencarn,</HI> being betrayed by <HI>An∣drew
Watson</HI> now prisoner in <HI>Drum∣freis;</HI>
their names were <HI>Iohn Gib∣son,
Robert Grierson, Robert Mitchel,
Iames Bennoch,</HI> and <HI>Iohn Edgar,</HI> all
which were at the command of
the said Col: <HI>Dowglas</HI> brought
forth &amp; immediately shot dead,
without giving them so much
time as to recommend their Souls
unto GOD. One <HI>Iohn Ferguson,</HI>
sometimes a profest Friend, thrust
one of them through; supposing
he was not dead: This was done
in the Year, 1685.</P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> the said Col: <HI>Iames Dou∣glas</HI>
and his party, shot to Death
<HI>Iohn Hunter</HI> for no alledged Cause,
but running out from the house
at <HI>Corchead,</HI> the same year, 1685.
<HI>Item,</HI> The said Col: or Liev: Gen:
<HI>Iames Dowglas,</HI> with Liev: <HI>Living∣ston,</HI>
and Coronet <HI>Iames Dowglas,</HI>
surprised six Men at Prayer at the
<HI>Calduns,</HI> in the parish of <HI>Minigaf;
viz: Iames Dun, Robert Dun, An∣drew
Mickale, Thomas Stevenson, Iohn
Macklude</HI> and <HI>Iohn Stevenson,</HI> in
<HI>Ianuary</HI> 1685.</P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said Col: or Liev:
Gen: <HI>Iames Dowglas</HI> caused take
<HI>Adam Macquhan</HI> out of his bed, sick
of a Fever, and carry him to <HI>New∣toun</HI>
of <HI>Galloway,</HI> and the next day
shot him dead, the foresaid year,
1685.</P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said Col: or Liev: Gen:
<HI>Dowglas</HI> commanded <HI>Thomas Rich∣ard,</HI>
an old Man of 70: years, to
be shot in the time of prayer; (he
was betrayed and taken by <HI>Peter
Ingles) anno</HI> 1685. at <HI>Cumnock</HI> in <HI>Kyle.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said Col: or Liev:
Gen: <HI>Iames Dowglas,</HI> together
with the Laird of <HI>Lag,</HI> and Capt:
<HI>Winram,</HI> most illegally condemn∣ed,
and most inhumanely drown∣ed
at Stakes within the Sea-mark,
two Women at <HI>Wigtoun;</HI> viz: <HI>Mar∣garet
Lauchlan,</HI> upward of 60: years
<PB N="36" REF="22"/>
and <HI>Margaret Wilson,</HI> about 20:
years of age, the foresaid fatal
year, 1685.</P>
<P>Captain <HI>Dowglas</HI> finding one
<HI>Mowat,</HI> a Taylor, meer∣ly
because he had some pieces of
lead belonging to his Trade, took
him, and without any further tri∣al
shot him dead, between <HI>Fleet</HI>
and <HI>Dee</HI> in <HI>Galloway.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said Captain <HI>Dowglas</HI>
and his Men finding one
<HI>Auchenleck,</HI> a deaf man, for not
making answer, through defect of
his hearing, instantly shot him
dead off Horseback, near <HI>Carlin∣wark,
anno</HI> 1685.</P>
<P>Sir <HI>Robert Dalzel</HI> and Liev: <HI>Stra∣toun,</HI>
having apprehended <HI>Daniel
Mackmichel,</HI> and detained him 24
hours Prisoner, took him out and
shot him at <HI>Dalveen,</HI> in the parish
of <HI>Durisdeer</HI> in <HI>Nithsdale, Ian: 1685:</HI></P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said Captain <HI>Dalzel,</HI>
and Liev: <HI>Stratoun,</HI> with their men,
found <HI>William Adam</HI> hiding in a
Bush, and instantly killed him,
at the <HI>Walwood</HI> in <HI>Kyle, Feb:</HI> 1685.</P>
<P>Captain <HI>Bruce,</HI> Capt: of <HI>Dragoons</HI>
apprehended <HI>Iames Kirko,</HI> at the
intelligence of one <HI>Iames Wright,</HI>
carried him to <HI>Drumfreis,</HI> detained
him prisoner one night, next day
brought him forth to the water∣sands,
and without any process,
shot him dead. The dying Man
desired a little time to make his
peace with GOD; The Captain
answered, oftner than once or
twice, <HI>Devil a peace ye get
more made up.</HI> Some Gentle∣women
coming to beg his Life,
were hindred by one <HI>Iohn Craik</HI> of
<HI>Stewartoun;</HI> the foresaid <HI>Dalzells 2d.</HI>
son was one of them that shot him,
tho without command, <HI>Iune</HI> 1685.</P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said Captain <HI>Bruce</HI>
surprised in the Fields, and in∣stantly
shot three Men in the pa∣rish
of <HI>Kirk-patrick</HI> in <HI>Galloway,
viz. Iohn Wallace, Edgar,</HI>
and another, <HI>Feb.</HI> 1685.</P>
<P><HI>Item.</HI> The said Captain <HI>Bruce</HI>
and his Men, took out of his bed
<HI>Thomas Mckhaffie,</HI> sick of a Feaver
and shot him instantly, in the
Paroch of <HI>Strat<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>un</HI> in <HI>Carrick, Ian.</HI>
1686.</P>
<P><HI>Iames Dowglass</HI> Coronet of
<HI>Dragoons,</HI> commanded to shot
<HI>Iohn Semple,</HI> Eslaying to escape
out of his Window, in the Pa∣roch
of <HI>Dellie, Anno 1685. Kilkerron</HI>
shot him.</P>
<P><HI>Item.</HI> The said Coronet <HI>Dou∣glass</HI>
Apprehended <HI>Edward Mck∣cen,</HI>
and by search finding a
Flint stone upon him, presently
shot him, without any further
Tryal, <HI>Feb:</HI> 1685.</P>
<P>Liev. Gen. <HI>Drummond</HI> com∣manded
without any Process or
Tryal <HI>Iohn Murchie,</HI> and <HI>Daniel
Mckilwrick,</HI> to be immediatly
shot, after they were taken, in
the Paroch of <HI>Camonel</HI> in <HI>Carrick,
Anno,</HI> 1685.</P>
<P><PB N="37" REF="22"/>
At the same time, his Soul∣diers
did shoot dead <HI>Alex. Lin.</HI></P>
<P>Captain <HI>Inglis,</HI> and his <HI>Dragoons</HI>
pursued and killed <HI>Iames Smith,</HI>
at the Burn of <HI>Ann</HI> in <HI>Kyle,</HI> 1684.</P>
<P><HI>Peter Inglis</HI> his Son, killed one
<HI>Iohn Smith</HI> in <HI>Cunningham,</HI> 1685.</P>
<P><HI>Item.</HI> The said <HI>Peter</HI> or <HI>Patrick
Inglis</HI> killed one <HI>Iames White,</HI>
struck off his head with an Ax,
brought it to <HI>Newmills,</HI> and plaid
at the Foot ball with it, he killed
him at <HI>Little-black wood,</HI> the fore∣said
year, 1685.</P>
<P><HI>Item.</HI> The said <HI>Peter Inglis</HI> shot
<HI>Iohn Barrie,</HI> with his <HI>Pass</HI> in his
hand, in <HI>Evandale, April,</HI> 1685.</P>
<P>Major <HI>Balfour,</HI> together with
Captain <HI>Maitland</HI> and their Party,
Apprehended at their Work, <HI>Ro∣bert
Tam, Iohn Vrie,</HI> and <HI>Tho: Cook,</HI>
and instantly shot them. at <HI>Poma∣dee,</HI>
near <HI>Glasgow, May,</HI> 1685.</P>
<P><HI>Col. Buchan,</HI> with the Laird of
<HI>Lee,</HI> and their men shot <HI>Iohn Smith,</HI>
in the Paroch of <HI>Lesmahago, Feb:
1685.</HI></P>
<P>Liev: <HI>Lauder</HI> shot to death <HI>Wil∣liam
Shillilaw,</HI> at the <HI>Wood head</HI> in
the Water of <HI>Air,</HI> Anno, 1685.</P>
<P>Liev: <HI>Nisbet</HI> and his Party shot
to death <HI>Iohn Ferguson, George
Whiteburn,</HI> and <HI>Patrick Gemmil</HI> in
the parish of <HI>Finnick,</HI> in the said
year, 1685.</P>
<P>Liev. <HI>Murray,</HI> now Prisoner in
<HI>Edin.</HI> with his party, Shot one <HI>Iohn
Broun,</HI> after quarters given at <HI>Black∣wood</HI>
in <HI>Clidsdale,</HI> Mar. 1685,</P>
<P>Liev. <HI>Crichton,</HI> now prisoner in
<HI>Edinburgh,</HI> did most barbarously
after Quarters, shoot <HI>David Steel,</HI>
in the parish of <HI>Lesmahego, Decem:
1686.</HI></P>
<P>The Laird of <HI>Stenhouse,</HI> Sir <HI>Ko∣bert
Laurie</HI> of <HI>Maxueltoun</HI> and <HI>Iohn
Craik</HI> of <HI>Stewartoun,</HI> did instigate
and urge Coronet <HI>Bailie</HI> his party
of Dragoons to shot <HI>William Smith</HI>
in <HI>Hill,</HI> after he had been prison∣er
one night (it was the day of
<HI>Maxueltouns</HI> daughters Marriage,)
who also refused to let him be bu∣ried
in the Church-yeard.</P>
<P>Sir <HI>Iames Iohnstoun</HI> of <HI>Westerhall,</HI>
caused apprehend <HI>Andrew Hislop</HI>
in the parish of <HI>Hutton</HI> in <HI>Anandale</HI>
delivered him up to <HI>Claverhouse,</HI>
and never rested untill he got
him shot by <HI>Claverhouse</HI> his Trou∣pers;
<HI>Claverhouse</HI> would have de∣layed
it, but <HI>Westerhall</HI> was so ur∣gent,
that <HI>Claverhouse</HI> was heard
say, <HI>This Mans blood shall be upon
Westerhall,</HI> May 1685.</P>
<P>Sir <HI>Robert Grierson</HI> of <HI>Lag,</HI> hav∣ing
the command of a part of <HI>Cla∣verhouses</HI>
Troop &amp; <HI>Strauchans</HI> Dra∣goons,
surprised <HI>Io. Bell</HI> of <HI>Whiteside,
David Haliday</HI> portioner of <HI>May∣field,
Andrew Macrabeit, Iames Cle∣ment,</HI>
and <HI>Robert Lennox</HI> of <HI>Irlintoun,</HI>
and barbarously killed them after
Quarters, without time allowed
to pray; when <HI>Iohn Bell</HI> of <HI>White∣side</HI>
begged a little time to pray,
<HI>Lag</HI> answered, <HI>What Devil have you
<PB N="38" REF="23"/>
been doing? Have you not prayed e∣nough
these many years in the hills?</HI>
and so shot him presently in the
parish of <HI>Tongland</HI> in <HI>Galloway,
Febr.</HI> 1685.</P>
<P><HI>Item,</HI> The said Laird of <HI>Lag</HI>
having <HI>Alexander Mellubie</HI> and
<HI>Iohn Gordon</HI> Prisoners, at the Mil∣toun
of <HI>Orr,</HI> without any Assiise
or Tryal, caused them to be
hanged on a tree at the Kirk of
<HI>Irongray,</HI> and there left them
hanging.</P>
<P><HI>Item</HI> the said Laird of <HI>Lagg,</HI> with
the Earle of <HI>Anandale,</HI> having
Command of some Troups of He∣retors,
pursued another <HI>David Ha∣lyday</HI>
and <HI>George Short,</HI> and appre∣hended
and shot them, under the
cloud of Night, in the Paroch of
<HI>Wynhame</HI> in <HI>Galloway, Anno,</HI> 1685.</P>
<P>The Laird of <HI>Culyean,</HI> for that
time Captain of a Troup of <HI>Mili∣tiae</HI>
and Heretors, killed <HI>William
Mckergur</HI> at <HI>Blairquhan Milne, An∣no,
1685.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Item</HI> the Laird of <HI>Culyean,</HI> with
the Laird of <HI>Ballochmilne,</HI> shott
<HI>Gilbert Mcadam,</HI> in the Paroch of
<HI>Kirkmichel, Iuly,</HI> 1685.</P>
<P>A party of <HI>Highlanders</HI> killed
<HI>Ioseph Wilson, David Dun, Simeon
Paterson,</HI> and other two, near the
Water of <HI>Kill,</HI> in a Moss in <HI>Kile,
Anno</HI> 1685.</P>
<P>The Laird of <HI>Ironkeple</HI> comman∣ding
a party of <HI>Highlandmen,</HI> killed
<HI>Robert Lochart</HI> and <HI>Gabriel Thomson,</HI>
about that time also.</P>
<P>Likewise, <HI>William Paterson</HI> was
shot ot <HI>Strevin,</HI> uncertain by whom,
1685.</P>
<P>Also <HI>Iohn Mclorgan</HI> was killed
at <HI>Drummellians</HI> House in the night
time not known by whom.</P>
<P><HI>Iohn Reid</HI> belonging sometimes
to <HI>Craigies Troup,</HI> who was this
last Summer in Rebellion in the
<HI>Highlands,</HI> did under Cloud of
Night, kill by a Shot, one <HI>George
Wood,</HI> about 16 Years old, with∣out
asking one Question at him,
at <HI>Tinkhorn</HI> hill in <HI>Kyle, Iune</HI> 1688.</P>
<P>In summ their Number a∣mounts
to 78.</P>
<P>The chief Contrivers and Au∣thors
of all these Slaughters and
Mischiefs were, they that enacted
and Subscribed the Edicts for
them in Council, principally the
E. of <HI>Perth</HI> Chancellour. Duke
of <HI>Queensberry,</HI> Marq. of <HI>Athol,</HI> and
particularly the <HI>Viscount</HI> of <HI>Tarbat,</HI>
who invented this Murdering De∣vice,
wherein yet he carried so
Cunningly, that he procured the
dispatch of the Act to the King,
with such suddenness, that he
found a way to shift his own Sub∣scribing
of it.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P>Having thus, in a Compendious and Cursory Glance, given this
short <HI>Memorial</HI> of our <HI>Grievances</HI> and <HI>Sufferings</HI> under the former Go∣vernments,
with a particular Specimen of some Instances, discover∣ing
<PB N="39" REF="23"/>
some, and but a few of the Actors and Instruments of these Evils;
whom we have specially mentioned, selected out of the Copious store
of many others of that Character that might be specified, not out of a
Principle of Revenge, or humor of Reproach, but from a Principle
of Zeal for Justice, the Honour of the King, and Happiness of the
Kingdom; We desire (in the sense of the Necessity, and in the Hope
that the King and Parliament will see the Expediency of removing the
former Tools of Tyranny from Power and Trust under this Govern∣ment,
and from a Capacity of driving their old Trade) that among
others a Remark may be put upon the abovementioned Persons. We
shall in the next place Condesend upon some of our present <HI>Grievances,</HI>
which, instead of the Redress of the former, we are of new made to
Groan under; whereby our Expectation have been in a great Mea∣sure
disappointed, and the Comforts of our present Quiet and reviving
in our Bondage (which yet we desire to be Thankful to God for, and
to the King as his Honoured Instrument) are much Imbittered.</P>
<P>We are but a poor People, and therefore our Grievances are the
less regarded: Nor were they indeed to be so much respected, if they
were peculiar to us, but being of Common Extent, and Grievous to
the greatest Body of the Nation (tho' a great part are so accustomed,
<HI>Issachar-like</HI> to Couch under all Burdens, in silent and stupid Submis∣sion,
that their Grievances are heavier than their Groaning; and o∣thers
through frequent disappointments are become so heartless in
their hopes of Redress, that they have given over Complaining, ex∣cept
in their private Murmurings, or secret Mournings before the
Lord of Heaven and Earth) we have the more Confidence to speak out
what others think, and Choose rather (if it shall come to that) to suf∣fer
<HI>Once</HI> for speaking than to <HI>Continue Languishing</HI> under growing Grie∣vances
for not speaking. For our former Grievances we do
not plead merit to obtain a Redress: Yet we take the Con∣fidence
to say, that as our former Sufferings, under the former
Governments, should have Conciliated Compassion; so what we have
endeavoured to do in evidencing our Zeal for this; might have had
some Consideration. We are represented by the Viperous <HI>Curates,</HI>
and other Malignants, who alwayes sought our Ruine, as <HI>Antipods</HI> to
all Mankind, Enemies to Government, and incapable of Orders:
But as their Order and Cause is <HI>toto Diametro</HI> opposite unto the Insti∣tutions
and Cause of Christ, and it were the Interest of all in this <HI>He∣misphere</HI>
to have such a Generation of Viperous Reproachers; and their
<PB N="40" REF="24"/>
lying Lybells Banished to the <HI>Antipods;</HI> so they must have little witt,
and less Honesty, who will entertain their Reproaches, who are as
great Rebells to this Government, as we avowed our selves to be to
the former. Our Sufferings for declining the Yoke of Malignant
Tyranny and Popish Usurpation are before hinted and generally
known; and all that will be pleased to know, and consider our Car∣riage
since the King did first appear in his Heroick Undertaking, to
Redeem these Nations from, Popery add Slavery, will be forced to
acknowledge we have given as good Evidence of our being willing to
be Subjects to King <HI>William,</HI> as we gave proof before of our being un∣willing
to be Slaves to King <HI>Iames.</HI> For upon the first Report of the
Prince of <HI>Orange</HI>'s Expedition we owned his H. Quarrel, when as the
Prelatick Faction were in Armes to Oppose his Coming to Help Us.
We Prayed openly for the Success of his Armes, when in all the
Churches the Prayers were for his Ruine. We Associated our selves
to Contribute what we could to the promoting of his Interest; and
were with the first that Declared a desire to Engage for him, and un∣der
him at our Renewing the <HI>Covenants,</HI> when they were Associating
with and for his Enemies. Accordingly for that effect, after we had
gone to Armes, upon the noise of <HI>Kircudbrights</HI> Burning, we modelled
our selves in Companies; whereby we were in Readiness to offer, and
had the honour to be admitted to guard and defend the Honourable
Meeting of Estates, against all Attempts of the D. of <HI>Gordoun,</HI> Vi∣count
of <HI>Dundee,</HI> or other Enemies. And thereafter understanding
the Government required the raising of Forces, for the defence there∣of
against the intestine Insurrections, and Forreign Invasions of the
Late King <HI>Iames,</HI> his Complices within or without the Land: Upon
the first occasion, we were the first that offered to furnish a Regiment
for his Majesties Service, and accordingly made up the E. of <HI>Angus</HI>'s
Regiment, all in one day, without beat of Drum, or expence of Le∣vy
money; having first concerted with the Liev: Colonel <HI>Clevland</HI>
such Conditions and Provisions, as we thought necessary for securing
and clearing our Conscience, Liberty and Safety; <Q>That all the Of∣ficers
of the Regiment should be such, as in Conscience and Pru∣dence,
might with cordial confidence be submitted unto &amp; followed;
Such as had not served the Enemy in destroying, nor engaged by
Oaths and Tests, to destroy the cause, now to be sought for and
defended; But that they should be well affected, of approven Fide∣lity,
<PB N="41" REF="24"/>
and of a sober conversation. Having also declared, That the
cause they were called to appear for, was the service of the Kings
Majesty, in the defence of the Nation, Recoverie and preservation
of the Protestant Religion, and in particular, the work of Refor∣mation
in <HI>Scotland,</HI> in opposition to Popery, Prelacy and Arbitrary
Power, in all its Branches and Steps, until the Government of
Church and State, be brought to their Lustre and Integrity esta∣blished
in the best and purest times.</Q> Upon these terms, we offer∣ed
to compleat two or three more Regiments, if it had been accepted.
But, before we offered to be <HI>Souldiers,</HI> we had first made an offer to
be <HI>Subjects;</HI> And because we did not look upon our selves as Subjects
to the Late King, who treated us as Enemies, We made therefore a
voluntary Tender of our Subjection, in a peculiar Petition by our
selves▪ which we purposed to have given in to the Meeting of Estates
at their first sitting down. We shewed it to several Honourable Mem∣bers,
but by their Advice it was delayed, until the Meeting prevent∣ed
the purpose of it, by Proclaiming the <HI>King</HI> and <HI>Queen.</HI> The Tenor
whereof here Follows.</P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="petition">
<HEAD>TO THE
MEETING of ESTATES
Of the Kingdom of SCOTLAND.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">THE NOBLEMEN, BARONS and BVRGESSES, Law∣fully
Called and Chosen, now Assembled at Edinburgh, for
Establishing the Government, Restoring and Securing the
True Religion, Laws and Liberties of the said Kingdom.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">The Humble PETITION of the poor People who have Suffered Grie∣vous
Persecution, for their Revolt from, and disowning the Authority of
James the VII, Pleading for the devolving the Government upon the Prince
of Orange, now King of England.</HEAD>
<OPENER>SHEWETH,</OPENER>
<P>THat the sad effects of the Late Arbitrary and Tyrannical Course
of Government, which these Nations, and we in a special man∣ner
<PB N="42" REF="25"/>
have been groaning under these years past; From which to Re∣lieve
them, the Most Serene and Illustrious Prince of <HI>Orange</HI> was in∣duced
by the Propitious Conduct of a very Glorious Providence, to
Undertake this Noble and Heroick Enterprise, And for Redressing
which, This Honourable <HI>Convention</HI> is Called and Conveened: To∣gether
with the revived hopes, since His <HI>Highness</HI> Auspicious Arrival,
that all honnest men have begun to conceive and entertain, of get∣ting
their <HI>Grievances</HI> freely Represented and Redressed; The denyal
whereof, these several years, hath been to us, and many others, a
Grievance very grievous: Have necessitate, incited, invited and en∣couraged
us among others (tho of the meanest Figure, and lowest
Interest in this great Affair; Yet, as persons pressed to declare, and
oppressed for declaring their Consciences, Sentiments and Resent∣ments
of the Late abused Government) to take the Boldness, now
to open our hearts to this Great and Honourable <HI>Meeting;</HI> And with
all humility, as becomes, to Represent to Your <HI>Honours,</HI> That, as
we conceive, we wanted not Right and Reason upon Consciencious
Grounds, to decline the Illegally extorted, and Arbitrarly impos∣ed
acknowledgement of our Allegiance unto <HI>Iames</HI> the VII. Whose
Authority we could never own, because of his Illegal Investiture,
without taking, or being in Capacity to take the Oath of Coronation
(while addicted to Poperie) contrare to the Laws of God and Man,
because of his Advancing the Prerogative, unto an Illimited and
most Despotical Absolutness, <HI>which all were required to obey without Re∣serve;</HI>
And because of his Arbitrary abusing it, to the undermining
and overturning our Religion, Laws and Liberties, and intended In∣troduction
of Poperie and Slaverie, at the opened gap of the <HI>Prelatical
Hierarchy, Erastian Supremacy,</HI> and the Late vastly extended <HI>Toleration.</HI>
And because we could not own it, our Sufferings have been very great,
known to this and other Nations, and we are confident will not now
be condemned by any that have espoused the Cause, and have been
honoured to concur in the Enterprise of Rescuing these Nations from
the Unsupportable Yoke of the Late Popish Domination, upon the
same, or equivalent grounds on which we durst not own it: So we
prostrate ourselves, yet sorrowing under the smart of our still bleed∣ing
wounds, at your <HI>Honours</HI> Feet, who have a Call, a Capacity,
and we hope a good mind to cure them; And offer this our <HI>Petition,</HI>
enforced by all the formerly felt, presently seen, and for the future
<PB N="43" REF="25"/>
feared Effects and Efforts of this Throne of Iniquity, and the mis∣chief
thereby framed into Law, and practised or projected against all
Law, by the Cry of the Blood of our murdered Brethren, by the sla∣very
of the banished free born Subjects of this Realm, by all the mi∣series
that many forefeited, disinhereted, harassed and wasted honest
Families have been redacted to (their Estates and Lives being at the
mercy of incensed Souldiers) for adhering unto the Ancient Cove∣nanted
Establishments of Religion and Liberty; And by all the Ar∣guments
of Justice, Necessity and Mercy, that ever could conciliate
Commiseration among Men of Wisdom, Piety and Vertue; humbly
Beseeching, Requesting and Craving of your H: Now when GOD
hath given you this opportunity to Act for His Glory, the good of the
Church and Nation, your own Honour, and the Happiness of Poste∣rity,
Now when this Kingdom, the Neighbouring, and all other
Nations of <HI>Europe,</HI> have their Eyes upon you, expecting
you will acquit your selves like the Representatives of a free Nation,
in redeeming it from Slaverie, otherwise ineluctable, following the
Noble footsteps of your Renowned Ancestors, and the present Pre∣cedent
and Pattern of this Honourable Convention and Parliament
now sitting in <HI>England;</HI> That you will proceed, without any farther
Procrastinations (alwayes, especially now Dangerous, when Papists,
and other Malignant Enemies are openly attempting to raise a Rebel∣lion
against the State) to declare the late Iniquous Government dissol∣ved,
the Crown Vacant, and <HI>Iames</HI> VII, whom we never have, and
resolve with many Thousands, never again to owne, to have really
Forfeited, and rightly to be deprived of all Right and Title, he could
ever pretend thereunto: And to provide, that it may never be in the
Power of any succeeding Governour, for the time to come, to aspire
unto or arrive at such a Capacity of Tyrannizing. Moreover since <HI>A∣narchy</HI>
and <HI>Tyranny</HI> are equally to be detested, and the Nation cannot
subsist without a Righteous Governour, and none can have a nearer
Right, nor fitter Qualifications, than his Illustrious <HI>Highness,</HI> whom
the Most High hath signally Owned and Honoured to be our delive∣ror
from Popery end Slavery; We Cry and Crave that King <HI>William,</HI>
now of <HI>England,</HI> may be Chosen and Proclaimed King of <HI>Scotland,</HI> and
that the Regal Authority be devolved upon him, with such necessary
Provisions, Limitations and Conditions of Compact; as may give
Iust and Legal Securities of the Peace and Purity of our Religion,
<PB N="44" REF="26"/>
Stability of our Laws, priviledges of Parliaments, and Subjects Li∣berties
Civil and Ecclesiastick, and make our Subjection both a clear
Duty, and a comfortable Happiness. And because Kings are but Men
mortal, mutable, and fallible; particularly, We crave, that he be bound
in his Royal Oath; not only to Govern according to the Will and
Command of GOD, and Ancient, Laudible and Righteous Laws, in
the Ministration of Justice, punishment of Iniquities, Redressing of
just Grievances, and preservation of true Liberties: But above all,
that he and his Sucessors, profess persevere in, Protect and maintain
the true <HI>Protestant Religion,</HI> abolish <HI>Poperie</HI> and all false Religion, <HI>Heresie;
Idolatrie</HI> and <HI>Superstition,</HI> revive the <HI>Penal Lawes</HI> against the same, re∣establish
and Redintegrate the Ancient <HI>Covenanted Work of Reformation</HI>
of this Church, in Doctrine, worship, discipline and Government, ac∣cording
to the <HI>Word of GOD, Confession of Faith; Covenants National</HI> and
<HI>Solemn League;</HI> upon its old foundations, as Established from the Year
1638. and downward to 1650; And that he restore and Confirme, by
his Princely Sanction, the due Priviledges of the Church, granted to
her by▪ JESUS CHRIST, her only Head and Supreme, and never
assume to himself an Erastian Supremacy over the Church in Causes
Ecclessiastick, or Unbounded Prerogative, in Civils, above Law; but,
as the Keeper of both Tables of the Law of God, in a way Compe∣tent
to Civil Authority, interpose his Power, for the Ejecting out of
the Church, the Prelats, the main Instruments of the Church and
Nations Miseries. And from all Administration of the Power and
Trust in the State, such Malignant Enemies as have promoted the
Ruine thereof: Upon these or the like Termes, We tender our Al∣legiance
to King <HI>William,</HI> and hope to give more pregnant Proof of
our Loyalty to his <HI>Majesty,</HI> in Adverse, as well as Prosperous Provi∣dences,
than they have done or can do, who profess Implicite Sub∣jection
to Absolute Authority, so long only as Providence preserves
its Grandure.</P>
<P>MAY IT THEREFORE PLEASE YOUR <HI>HON.</HI> To
take the Premises into Your serious Consideration, and put a
Favourable Construction on this our Humble and Earnest Re∣quest,
which sense of Duty, in desire to Exoner our Consei∣ences,
and in Complyance with, and at the Solicitation of the
Cries of many Thousands in the Nation, moved and craved,
<PB N="45" REF="26"/>
We take the Confidence to present to Your <HI>HON.</HI> In
the Hope, that Zeal for GOD and his Church, regard to
Iustice and Mercy, Care of Your own, as well as the Coun∣tries
Interest, dutiful Love, Loyalty and Gratitude to King
<HI>William,</HI> and even Pity to us, will prevail with Your <HI>Wis∣dom</HI>
to grant in with all convenient Expedition. And Your
<HI>Supplicants</HI> shall ever Pray <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>FROM what is above hinted, it may appear, that We are not Ene∣mies
to <HI>Government;</HI> but, that as we have had Occasion, We have
given more Evidences of true Loyalty, than any of our Traducers, and
of true Zeal to have this Government fixed, on such a Foundation, as
may make it Secure and Stable, and Subjection thereunto to be not
only a Duty, but a Comfort. And with the same inviolable Zeal,
Affection and Fidelity, since others will not, We cannot forbear to
Remonstrare those Grievances, that are as well hateful to GOD, and
hurtful to the Government, as Grievous to Us.</P>
<P><HI>First,</HI> As to the <HI>Church,</HI> tho' all Honest Subjects have been impatient∣ly
expecting the settlement thereof, from the Kings <HI>Declaration,</HI> his
Promises at the Acceptance of the Crown, and his Instructions to D.
<HI>Hamiltoun;</HI> Yet, to this Day, it is neither Settled, nor Purged, nor
Planted, but kept in uncertain suspense what to fear, or what to
hope. <HI>Popery</HI> indeed is much suppressed, in a way, wherein much of
GOD, and little of Man is to be acknowledged and admired; yet
the Ancient Laudable Laws against <HI>Papists, Seminary Priests, Sayers</HI> and
<HI>Hearers of Mass</HI> are not Revived, Reinforced, nor put in Execution,
while many of these Idolaters, and Intycers to Idolatry, are connived
at, past without punishment, and favourably Intreated, when some
of us have apprehend them, and delivered them into Custody. Whence
they are much encouraged where they Cohabite in great Numbers;
especially in the Sea Coast of <HI>Galloway,</HI> where they may open a Door
and free Ingress to the <HI>Irish,</HI> whenever they have a mind to Invade;
whereby the Country about, is contiunally Tormented with fears of
their Massacres and Murdering Attempts. We can never be freed
from the hazard of the Return of Popery, so long as Papists are so
much Tolerated, and are bragging of their hopes of getting a <HI>Tolera∣ration</HI>
established, Suspending and Dispensing with the <HI>Penal Statutes</HI>
against them; which will defile the Land with Idolatry, and expose
us to the Judgement of GOD.</P>
<P><PB N="46" REF="27"/>
We desire also to be thankful, that <HI>Poperies</HI> eldest Daughter,
the <HI>Episcopal</HI> Hierarehy, or <HI>Prelacy,</HI> hath got such a knock on the head,
that it is abolished by Law, &amp; its return so far <HI>Legally precluded,</HI> that the
removal thereof, being one of the <HI>Stipulations</HI> &amp; <HI>Artieles of Compact</HI> with
his <HI>Majesty,</HI> at the <HI>Disposal and Acceptance of the Crown,</HI> it cannot be restored
without asignal Violation of the Regal Covenant; the native Conse∣quences
whereof, may beforeseen to be so dangerous, that we hope,
the Kings Wisdom and Justice, will be proof, against all the Insinua∣tions
and Perswasions of the Church of <HI>England,</HI> to hazard it; yet it
is a very burdensome Grievance, that the settlement of the Church
Government, is so long suspended, and the Nation kept in Suspense,
not knowing what shall be settled in stead of <HI>Prelacy</HI> abolished; where∣by
the Land is left to settle in nothing, but to rest and rott in old
Crying sins, and new provocations are daylie Multiplied without
control; Scandals and Disorders, to the dishonour of GOD, reproach
of Religion, stumbling the weak, hardening the perverse, and offend∣ing
all are not restrained, but much encouraged, and different factions
much fomented; while Church Government and Discipline (the only
Preservative and restaurative Medicine for such Distempers) is neither
established, nor any rule determined, by which it shall be Established,
except the <HI>Inclinations of the People;</HI> which are in themselves very vari∣able,
and must be ruled by, and not a Rule unto the Institutions of
<HI>IESVS CHRIST:</HI> And as they are variable, so they are as Various
and diverse, as there are Numbers of Persons or Parties, that prefer their
own Humours and Interests to the Supreme Law, the <HI>revealed will of
Christ:</HI> Some are for <HI>Erastianisme;</HI> Some for a constant <HI>Moderatorship;</HI>
some for a <HI>Superintendency;</HI> some perhaps for <HI>Independency;</HI> some for a <HI>To∣leration</HI>
of all; some are for a <HI>continuance of the Curates;</HI> either without any
Accommodation with them, and secluding them from a share of the
Government, but suffering them still to Exercise their Ministry; Or
by an Accommodation and Coalition with them in the Government
also; some again are for the continuance of <HI>Patronages,</HI> how ever it be.
We and many Thousands are against all these things, as being contra∣ry
to the Word of GOD, abjured frequently in our <HI>COVE∣NANTS
NATIONAL</HI> and <HI>SOLEMN LEAGVE;</HI>
condemned in the confession of this, and all other best Refor∣med
Churches; And in the doleful experience of former times, known
to be inlets to many wicked inventions, innovations and corruptions
in the Church; And in process of time productive of Prelacy again:
Which, in the Lords strength, We, and many Thousands, do intend
<PB N="47" REF="27"/>
never to submit to, tho for our Recusancy, we should suffer the great∣est
persecution from Men. We are for the Restauration and Re∣establishment
of this Churches Ancient <HI>Covenanted Reformation,</HI> in its
<HI>Doctrine, Worship, Discipline</HI> and <HI>Government</HI> (according to the <HI>Word of God,
Confession of Faith, Catechisms</HI> Larger and Shorter, National and Solemn
<HI>Covenants</HI> and <HI>Acts</HI> of General Assemblies) in all its Legall Immunities,
Securities and Sanctions, as before the Year 1650. These <HI>Different In∣clinations,</HI>
cannot be a Rule of Government and order, but of Ataxie
and Confusion; Nor can they be determined by a <HI>Lesbian rule,</HI> uncon∣stant
and uncertain; But somewhat, to which all must vail and and
submit, and which must claim the last Appeal. Tho we might, with as
great Confidence as others, Venture the success of our Plea for <HI>Presby∣terie,</HI>
upon the decision of a Poll and Plurality of Votes, providing
(which could not be denied) none be admitted to Vote, but such as
are well affected to the Government of King <HI>William</HI> and Queen <HI>Marry.</HI>
Yet we cannot subject the determination of that Plea, to any other
Rule, than he <HI>Institution of CHRIST;</HI> considering, that either the Lord
<HI>IESVS,</HI> who is anointed only King and Head of his Church, and is
faithful in all his House, must not have appointed any Government
or order thereof at all (which would exceedingly Reflect upon His
Wisdom and Faithfullness and the Perfection of his Law) or this Go∣vernment
which he hath appointed, must not be Arbitrary and Am∣bulatory,
indifferently determinable▪ by the will and inclinations of
Men, no more than others of His Institutions can be. We plead for
no Government, and for nothing in this of Presbyterie, but what we
have the Lawes of <HI>CHRIST</HI> in his Word, the Ancient Lawes of the
Nation, the Constitutions of the Church, never yet repealed, by any
subsequent Authority Ecclesiastick, and the Covenant Eengagements
of all ranks in the Land, of Indespensible obligation, for: Nor do we
plead for any exercise, or extent of this order, further then is necessary
for the <HI>purging of the Church,</HI> of every <HI>Antichristian,</HI> or <HI>Erastian</HI> Corrup∣tion
and Invention, Defection or Schism, Error or Scandal in
Officers or Members impartially; And for the Planting of the Church
with Godly, able and Faithful Ministers, for the Instruction, conviction
conversion, Edification and Consolation of the Members thereof. But
now, not only is this Government not established, but even that of
Prelacy is not effectually, nor can be abolished, while the many ini∣quous
Laws against <HI>Presbytery,</HI> and pressing submission to <HI>Prelacy</HI> are not
rescinded; And while our <HI>National and Solemn League Cevenants</HI> for
<PB N="48" REF="28"/>
Preserving and Promoting Reformation, are so far forgotten and
trampled upon, that the Acts Antiquating and Discharging them to be
owned, are not only not Abrogated, but so far yet observed, that it is
hardly allowed they should be publickly mentioned: While also, the
Ecclesiastical <HI>Supremacy,</HI> a feather likewise of <HI>Antichrists</HI> wing, and a
Blasphemous and Sacrilegious Encroachment upon Christs Preroga∣tives,
and His Kingdoms Priviledges, is not revocked, nor declared
void, whereby it stands declared by wicked Laws, to be the inherent
Right of the Magistrate, to Order, Dispose, Alter or Innovate the
external Government of the Church, and to plant, or transplant
Ministers, and give them Instructions, to Regulate them in the Ex∣ercise
of their Function; which, if not Abolished, will not only o∣ptn
a Door to the Introdnction of <HI>Prelacy</HI> or <HI>Popery</HI> again: But if the
<HI>Protestant</HI> Religion be never so well Established, this will in process of
time, unhinge all possible Settlements thereof. There is nothing
more the Interest of the Church, than to seek that this Mountain in the
way of its Reformation, be removed; and all Acts confirming the
same repealed; and <HI>Indulgences</HI> following therefrom, be declared
to be Usurpations. Another Pillar of <HI>Prelacy,</HI> the constant support of it,
and stop to Reformation, does yet continue, while the burden∣some
Bondage of <HI>Patronages</HI> is not removed; whereby the Church is
Robbed of the Liberty of choosing her own Guides intrusted with her
greatest concerns, &amp; the <HI>Great-men</HI> have open access Implicity to impose,
and Prey upon, and Pester the Church with Corrupt Teachers: But
if all these things were Rectified, it is impossible the Church can ever
be settled, or purged, or planted, as long as the Episcopal <HI>Curats,</HI> in∣truded
by the Prelats Collation and Patrons Presentation, contrare
to the Institutions of Christ, and the Constitutions of this Reformed
Church, without the Call, and contrare to the Inclinations of the
People in many places, but every where the Bane of the Nation, the
Scandal of the Church and the cause of all our Confusions, are conti∣nued
in the Churches. How can the Church be settled, when those
that unsettled it continue in the same Capacity to oppose all Righ∣teous
Settlements of Reformation? How can the Church be purged,
when the greatest Corrupters, and the most corrupted Members, re∣main
in Power? Either they must be looked upon, and Subject them∣selves
as Members of the <HI>Presbyterian</HI> Church, and then Discipline
cannot but strike against them, in such a measure of Severity, as may
<PB N="49" REF="28"/>
be some way proportioned to the greatness of their Scandal, their
Obstinacy, Impenitency, and Continuance in it as long as they could,
and the hazard of their Leavening the whole Lump; or they must
be looked upon as Pure and Perfect Schismaticks, seting up a distinct
Church, and seperate Communion, within a well Constitute Natio∣nal
Church, and as such they ought to be Censured and Restrained.
How can the Church be planted, when those Plants that the LORD
never planted, fill so much of His Vineyard, and continue in so many
Paroches, either to sterve them with the hungry Husks of Ethick
Homilies and Harangues of Moral Vertues, instead of Gospel Holi∣ness
(not knowing to Preach the Mystery of the Covenant of Grace,
or declare the Counsel of GOD, to the Conversion of Sinners unto
CHRIST or so poyson them with points of <HI>Popery, Arminianisme, So∣cinianisme:</HI>
Yet many of them do yet Peaceably possess the places they
were intruded into; and others dispossessed, are reponed by Force,
contrare to the inclinations of the Paroch, and notwithstanding their
opposition in some places, as for instance in <HI>Colintown</HI> and in <HI>Peebles,</HI>
where great Insolences were committed, affronting the Magistrates,
and disturbing the <HI>Presbyterian</HI> Meeting, which have been overlooked;
but the least Accession to any Opposition that was made, hath been
severely punished, one <HI>Francis Beatie</HI> upon this account being for these
many weeks kept in prison, and his <HI>Petitions</HI> for Liberty ejected. This
hath discouraged many, and opened their mouths to reflect; That
tho this Government be as much admited for Acts of Mercy to Re∣bells,
as the former was for Cruelty, yet wherever any <HI>Presbyterian</HI>
can be apprehended in any fault, he must expect the rigour of Seve∣rity.
We do not justifie illegal Tumults, nor do we approve that peo∣ple
should transgress their Line and Station in endeavours of Refor∣mation,
when there is a Magistrate to be applied unto: But as Magi∣strates
ought to interpose their Power for extruding, and easing the
people of Intruders; so when they abuse it, to the re inforcing of these
intrusions, honnest and zealous people can as hardly be restrained
from resisting such Invasions and Impositions against the Laws of <HI>GOD</HI>
and Man, as they can be kept from withstanding a violent Invader of
their Property, or Intruder on their Heritage. For our part, as we
thought it a seasonable duty, to take the opportunity of the <HI>Interreg∣num,</HI>
before the settlement of a Government that we could subject
our selves to, for cleansing the <HI>Western Shiers</HI> of these <HI>Creatures</HI> (which
<PB N="50" REF="29"/>
was done with all the discretion that the confusions of that time, and
the feared shortness of that opportunity could admitt. And whatever
clamour they make of their Persecutions, in their Late Printed Ac∣count
and Information to the Church of <HI>England,</HI> stuft with Lies, we
defy them to give an instance of any hurt done by us to any of their
Persons or Families, or to charge us with one <HI>Six-pence</HI> worth of their
Goods: If any have, let it be proven and punished) which, if others
in other places had imitated, in that season, with the like discretion,
the Nation might have been much eased, and the Government pre∣vented
of a great deal of trouble: So, tho we are not for Persecut∣ing
them who were our greatest Persecuters, nor rendering them any
evil for their evil, farther than to restrain them from coming back a∣gain
to Persecute us, and from Intruding, where they have no Right;
Yet we are resolved, through Gods Assistance, to endeavour by all
approven means, to hold them out now when they are out; And
sooner to die, and venture the loss of all things temporal, than to
suffer any of them to repossess themselves of the Churches, whence
they are thrown out; or any other within our reach, untill after suf∣ficient
Evidences of their remorse they shall come in at the door of
<HI>CHRISTS</HI> Appointment. If in this we Offend the Malignants in the
<HI>Parliament</HI> or <HI>Council,</HI> we cannot help it, it is not the first time, nor
perhaps the last: But for the <HI>Noble</HI> &amp; <HI>Honoured Patriots</HI> among them, who
are well affected to the Cause of <HI>Reformation</HI> the Nations good, and his
<HI>Majesties</HI> Honour and Happiness, we are confident they will construct
of our ingenuity in good part; as flowing from conscience and Candor.
And we are hopeful his Majestie will Compassionat us in this matter;
and consider the Case, that it is more for his Honour and Interest; to
have respect to the Consciences of so many People, than to the humor
and haughtiness of a few debauched Lords and Gentlemen, who de∣light
in these vexations, and who by Custom, as it were, have it for
their Element to impose upon poor Peoples Consciences. And we
hope his Majesty will think upon the Redressing of this Grievance, of
the Continuance of these Episcopal <HI>Curates,</HI> who took notice of this, as
one of the Grievances, in his <HI>Declaration,</HI> that he came to relieve the
Nation from.</P>
<P>In the netxt place, as to the <HI>State,</HI> tho we desire to be more abstract
from these Administrations that are above our reach; yet it is obvious
and Grievous to all that desire the Establishment thereof in Righteous∣ness
<PB N="51" REF="29"/>
and Peace, that the settlement of Church and State both is Re∣tarded
and Obstructed, by the frequent Adjournments of Parlia∣ments,
in so Critical a Season when the Government is not well
settled, the Enemies thereof are prevailing, the Friends thereof are
sore discouraged and devided, and the Forces have no Maintenance.
If ever there <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of Parliaments, now it must be when the great∣est
Interests, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> King and People, are in so eminent Hazard:
And yet it is more Grievous, that when they Conveen, and have op∣portunity
to Act for the good of the Nation, the settlement of the
Church Government, and the Redress of Grievances, the Disputes of
divided Factions, about things of lesser Moment, do hinder their E∣stablishing
of those things, that all agree are Absolutely necessary. Time
might be afterwards spared for many of these Debates, with which the
present precious opportunity is wasted, and they might with more
Advantage and Facility be Adjusted and Composed afterwards, if
once the Establishment of the Church, and the Security of the Na∣tion
were provided for, and these things, for which they have his
Majesties <HI>Instructions,</HI> were Settled and Enacted: But we fear these
Differences are much Fomented by Self-seeking Malignant Incendia∣ries,
who love to Fish in troubled Waters, and to pursue their selfish
and sinistrous ends of Undermining the Church, supplanting the
King's Interest, and betraying the Countries Liberties, from whom
these Disorders and Grievances have proceeded, which are now desi∣red
to be Rectified and Redressed, and from whose Influence all these
Retardments and Disapointments do flow, which the Nation so
much complains of. For as the open and avowed Enemies of the
King and Country, owning the late King <HI>Iames</HI> his Interest (all con∣sisting
either of the Popish or Prelatical and Malignant Faction, not
so much as one <HI>Presbyterian</HI> being among them) are very many, In∣solent
and Prevalent; not only in the <HI>Highlands,</HI> but in all the hires
of the Kingdom; and no doubt have their Active Agents, Corre∣spondents
and Abetters in the Parliament, Council and all the Su∣preme
Judicatories of the Kingdom; so there are far moe secret un∣dermining
Enemies, who for the time are not appearing in opposi∣tion
to the Government, that are as great Enemies to the King and
Country, and all Righteous Interests, as any that do most appear,
who are now desiring Places, and ingyring themselves into publick
Trust, not to serve King <HI>William,</HI> whose Advancement to the Throne
<PB N="52" REF="30"/>
they opposed, with all the Power and Policy they had; nor simply
to satisfy their Insatiable Ambition, but to put themselves in better
Capacity to serve King <HI>Iames,</HI> in Retarding all Righteous Establish∣ments,
Rending the Parliaments, and Ruining Us all: Yea, how∣ever
some may account it Policy, it is not only a Grievance, but a
Sin dishonouring God, and destructive to the Nation, and a dangerous
Politick, threatning hazard to Religion and Liberty and the Go∣vernment,
that many wicked Malignants, Enemies to Reformation,
are admitted &amp; imployed in the publick Administrations, as <HI>Officers of
State, Members of Council &amp; Parliament,</HI> and other Judicatories and places
of Trust; who not only were our cruel Persecuters, and Murderers of
our Bretheren, whose Blood cries for Vengence against them; but
were the professed and sworn Tools of the late Tyranny, and Instru∣ments
of the Nations Slavery, Ministring to King <HI>Iames,</HI> and coope∣rating
with him in all his Encroachments upon our <HI>Religion, Laws</HI> and
<HI>Liberties,</HI> as absolute Vassals of his Despotical Will, under Oaths and
Pensionary Obligations to obey without reserve, and to this day, are
either evil Counsellours to perswade the King to some degrees of Ar∣bitrariness,
or very disaffected to the Government, Counsellers to, En∣couragers
of, or Connivers at Rebellion against it. It had been wor∣thy
Service to the Nation, to have at first exposed these Men in their
own Colours, and represented the danger of trusting them, to the
King; who being much a Stranger to Men, at his first coming over,
might be easily deceived in the choose of such as were to be Imploy∣ed;
and then it had been easier to keep out, then now to put out of
Places: But it is never too late to seek to be Rid of these that were,
and are like to be Instruments of our Ruine; whose Exclusion from
Trust and Power to play their old Tricks, is necessary for the King's
Interest as well as the Kingdoms, which are inseperable. And since
the King declared against these evil Counsellours; and on their Crimes
and Mal-administrations, founded the Righteousness and Necessity
of his Expedition, neither King nor Parliament can justly offend at;
or refuse the Nations Demands, to be eased of them, nor find it con∣venient,
that the Betrayers of our Laws, and Robbers of our Privi∣ledges
under the last Government, be excluded from all share of
Administration in this. We have experience of their Conduct and
Administration already, wherein we found nothing but Tyranny, Ra∣pine
and Violence, and such Justice and Law as is discovered above;
<PB N="53" REF="30"/>
and therefore can never beleive while only <HI>Interest</HI> hath made them
change their way, that ever they shall Administer Righteous Judge∣ment.
And whatever Confidence others may have, we cannot be
without fears, while we are under the power of our old Persecuters.
But above all; it is most offensive to God and all Good men, that
Murderers of innocent People, without and against all Law, particu∣larly
several of these above Named, should not only be Connived at,
and past without punishment, but Encouraged and Intertained in Fa∣vour
and Trust; some of them Discovered and Apprehended as Trai∣tors
to the present Government, are notwithstanding over looked and
suffered to escape Justice, and Liberate upon <HI>Bale,</HI> as Major or Lieu.
Col. <HI>Balfour,</HI> and Lieu. <HI>Nisbet;</HI> others of them are Members of Par∣liament,
as the <HI>Commissioners</HI> for the Shire of <HI>Nithsdale</HI> and Stewartry of
<HI>Anandale,</HI> Sir <HI>Ia. Iohnstoun</HI> of <HI>Westerhal,</HI> and <HI>Iohnstoun</HI> of <HI>Corehead,</HI>
who is notourly known to have of late several times in Caballs with
<HI>Iacobines</HI> drunk the late King's Health. Blood is a crying Sin, defil∣ing
the Land, which <HI>cannot be cleansed but by the Blood of them that shed it.</HI>
We thirst for the Blood of none, nor crave the sheding of any, but
of these who are so guilty of Blood, that they are Condemned to the
punishment of Murderers, by the Law of God and all Nations, hav∣ing
shed the Blood of War in Peace, without all shaddow of Law.
But as for those that Murdered our Bretheren, without all Process,
Accusation, Trial, Conviction, Assise or Sentence, as is observed in
his <HI>Majesties Declaration for Scotland,</HI> We should not be free of the Guilt
of their Impunity, if we did not seek Justice against them. Yet we
wonder the less at this, that such Criminalls as were Authorized under
the former Government, by Arbitrary orders, tho without Law, to
perpetrate their Crimes, are not Punished, when open avowed Traitors,
Speakers of Treason, and Rebells against the Present Government,
taken in ovett Acts of <HI>Lese-Majestie,</HI> discovered in Plots and Projects,
and Apprehended in Armes against his Majestie, are Indemnified,
Connived at, let out of Prisons and Tolerated, and thereby Encou∣raged
and Tempted to go on in their Conspiracies, and return to the
same Crimes, when ever they find Opportunity; for they will not
ascribe this to his Majesties Clemency, but to the weakness of the
Government, that dare not draw its Sword of Justice. In the former
Government, there was nothing but Severity against those that in the
least Discented from it: In this there is nothing but Mercy to Rebels;
<HI>both these are Extremes.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="54" REF="31"/>
In the Third place we cannot but have sad Reflections upon the
bad success of the War: Which we think is not so much to be imputed
to the bad Conduct of those to whom it is intrusted, as to the Wicked∣ness
and Malignancy of the Army, laying them and the Land open
to the danger of the wrath of GOD; while the Abominations of <HI>Swear∣ing,
Cursing, Profaning the Sabbath, Whoredom, Drunkenness,</HI> and all debau∣cheries
(which are severely interdicted by Military Lawes, if they
were put in execution) and are so abounding among Officers and
Souldiers, that the honest hearted among them, whom only Conscience
did prompt to engage in the service, are exceedingly discouraged, &amp;
all the fearers of GOD affrighted, to whom the abounding of, and
continuance in these sins is a greater terror, than all the Numbers of
Enemies. This is the more to be adverted, that all that acknowledge
GOD, are astonished with His signall and stupendous stroks, so ob∣servably
wasting many Thousands of the <HI>English</HI> Army in <HI>Ireland,</HI> with∣in
these few Moneths past for these same Abominations. But not only
are our Armies filled with the Profane end Profligate Skum of Man∣kind;
But to the great Reproach of the Cause, wherein Religion is so
nearly concerned, to the dishonour of GOD and offence of all the
Godly, many Malignant Enemies to Reformation, avowed Adver∣saries
and Persecuters of Truth and Godliness, are encouraged, imploy∣ed
and intrusted for the defence of the Interest, which, within this short
time, they professedly opposed, and by many Dreadful <HI>Oaths</HI> were en∣gaged
to Suppress. For the old Dragoons, the Late Kings <HI>Lieveguard</HI>
and others, after by Executing their old Masters cruell and Arbitrary
Orders, they had enriched themselves with the spoylls of the oppressed
Country, and imbrewed their hands in the Blood of innocent and
Righteous People, when they saw the Prince of <HI>Orange</HI> like to prevail,
forsook their King and crouded into his <HI>Highness</HI> Armies: Not for love
to his Cause, which with the greatest keenness they contended against,
as long as they could; But to prevent the just Vengance of his Victori∣ous
Armes, then threatened. Hence they are yet intertained among the
Forces, and there tho they have not occasion to exert their fury, as for∣merly;
Yet they cease not to express their Malice against us, in boast∣ing
that they hope yet to Persecute us as much as ever; And bragg∣ing
they are, and shall be for Prelacy as long as they Live, not fear∣ing
to impugn the Act of Parliament against it. It is certainly a Land∣sin
to be witnessed against, as well as a Grievance, that such Enemies
<PB N="55" REF="31"/>
of Truth and Godliness, should be admitted unto, or continued in
Power and Trust in the Army, or imployed and intertained therein.
It is dangerous that the Royal Standart should be a Sanctuary to them,
whom Divine Justice will pursue; And absurd, that the Army should
be polluted, and in danger to be infected with the Contagion of such
an unhappy conjunction and unholy Association. It were more pro∣fitable
and promising like, that the Tears and Cries of the many Wi∣dows
and Orphans, whom their bloody Sword have beraved of their
Husbands and Parents, might prevail with the Justice of the Go∣vernment,
to find them out and give them their reward. It were no
loss, but a great advantage to the King and Countrey both, that the
Army were throughly purged of those who betray the Interest in stead
of serving it, and whose carriage declares they are in the interest of
the Enemy, and were filled up with such as have another principle
prompting them to serve, than the prospect of <HI>Pay,</HI> which will make
them venture their dearest Blood in the Cause, with Resolution and
Confidence, when those that are pursued with a guilty Conscience are
afraid to look Death and Hell in the face. Hereby, as his Majesty
would be far from all fears of the like Treasons and Treacheries, in
some discovered already; so all Honest Men having no other Interest
or End, but the Glory of God, the Peace and Prosperity of their
Country, and the Honour and Happiness of the King, would be ex∣ceedingly
Encouraged and Engaged to be Zealous and Resolute in the
Service, when they should know they have none to Associate with,
but such as are of Aproven Fidelity and good Affection to the Cause.
It is yet the more Grievous, that not only so many wicked and Trea∣cherous
Men are intertained in the Army; but Men of Principle and
Conscience, who are willing and Zealous to serve in the Warrs with
the utmost Fidelity, can find little Encouragement; and some are
put out of Trust and Employment in the Army, who had given
Good proof of their Zeal, fidelity and courage, by the Malignants
procurement, to the end they might be rid of the fears and Iealousies
they had of their opposing their sinistrous designs: Some there are we
acknowledge in several Regiments and Troups, that are Men of prin∣ciple,
Conscience, Courage and Honour; but these labour under very
many Discouragements, being very much Maligned by the rest. Par∣ticularly,
we cannot but complain of the Treatment of the E. of <HI>Angues</HI>'s
Regiment, which was sent to <HI>Dunkeld</HI> (as would seem) on design by
<PB N="56" REF="32"/>
some to be betrayed and destroyed; For, being there posted alone in the
mouth of the <HI>Highlands,</HI> the whole body of <HI>Canons</HI> Army marched to∣wards
them, the very day they came thither, and within three days
gave them a <HI>general assault:</HI> where that Regiment was left in the chock,
denuded of the success that my <HI>Lord Cardross</HI> brought them, who were
recalled; and denyed the assistance they sought from <HI>Col. Ramsey</HI> lying
at <HI>Perth▪</HI> After which, getting the honor of that Victory, <HI>by the goodness
of GOD,</HI> they were more then ever envyed, by the remaining malice
of their old enemies; who, when they durst do no more to destroy
them openly; &amp; their Arts failed them to get them destroyed by the
<HI>common enemy,</HI> sought by all means <HI>to break</HI> them, or to <HI>blast their Reputation.</HI></P>
<P>Finally, <HI>The</HI> Country <HI>is much languishing in their jealousies, think∣ing
their sufferings cannot be over, as long as not only the instruments,
of their oppression, their Persecuters are in so much power: but the</HI> Laws
and Acts of Parliament, <HI>&amp;c. impowering them, &amp; condemning the</HI> grounds
<HI>of former sufferings, are</HI> yet standing unrepealed. <HI>Yea, they complain their</HI>
sufferings still continue, <HI>while</HI> Forefaultries <HI>&amp;</HI> Fines <HI>are not redressed; while
many are impoverished by loss of</HI> Law suits, <HI>and</HI> Decreets <HI>past against
them, through their</HI> Non-appearance in their own defence, <HI>in</HI> times of hazard▪
<HI>to their persons; while many</HI> Widows <HI>and</HI> Orphans <HI>of those that lost their</HI>
Lives in Fields and Scaffolds, <HI>and of those that</HI> died in banishments, <HI>are in
great distress, having none to provide for them; and while many are
yet</HI> in servitude in forraign Plantations, <HI>whither they were banished &amp; sold
as</HI> Slaves, <HI>who are not yet</HI> partakers of this reviving, <HI>we have got</HI> in our bondage.</P>
<P><HI>Moreover,</HI> As the unrestrained debaucherie and dissoluteness of Country
People is very grievous, occasioned by the want of Church Government and Disci∣pline;
So the insolence of many Gentlemen, professedly <HI>Jacobins,</HI> owning the Au∣thority
of K▪ <HI>James,</HI> drinking his health, and forcing others to it where they are
numerous, impugning the present Authority, and openly speaking Treason, is an
intollerable Affront to the Government: For the Honour of which, Zeal for our
GOD, Loyalty to the King, and Love to our Country; observing the deficiency of
others that could do it better, we could not forbear to suggest these complaints; In
the hope that such as are not sensible of them, may open their eyes and see their di∣stempers
and dangers; And those that are sensible of them, may be moved to re∣present
them to those that are in Authority, to redress and remove them. But
whether Men will hear, or not hear; we are confident there is a GOD that ruleth
in <HI>Jacob, to the ends of the Earth,</HI> who will hear the<HI>cry of the Humble,</HI>
in His own time.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="32"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

