<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The Siege of Mentz, or, The German heroin a novel.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A60224</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing S3771</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R20903</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12294600</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12294600</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">58987</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A60224)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58987)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 160:5)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The Siege of Mentz, or, The German heroin a novel.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Belon, P. (Peter)</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 151, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Sam. Briscoe ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1692.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Dedication signed: P.B. [i.e. Peter Bellon?, translator]. Cf. BM.</NOTE><NOTE>Advertisement on p. [1] at end.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Robyn Anspach</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A60224">
<STC T="W">S3771</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12294600</BIBNO>
<VID>58987</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE SIEGE OF MENTZ. OR, THE German Heroin, A NOVEL</P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI> Printed for <HI>Sam. Briscoe,</HI> over against <HI>Will</HI>'s Coffee-House, in <HI>Rus∣sel-Street, Covent-Garden,</HI> 1697.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the ever Honoured, <HI>Adam Felton,</HI> Knight Barronet.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><HI>I</HI> Had no sooner dress'd this <HI>German Heroine,</HI> in an <HI>English</HI> Habit, and taught her our Dialect, but that my high Obligations to you, brought you fresh into my Memory, with all the re∣quisite Accomplishments, for the Prote∣ction of so brave a Stranger, against the most severe Insults, that Malice, and Envy, could produce; in which choice, Sir, I have been further encou∣raged by that singular Affability and Bounty, which renders you the Delights (of the most ingenious) of both Sexes. And tho I was somewhat ashamed to pre∣fix
<PB REF="3"/>
your Name to so mean a Subject, as these Results of some hours of my lei∣sure; yet, I thought it much better, to take this opportunity, to write your Pa∣negyrick, having so large a Field, as your Merits to exercise in, then to ap∣pear wholly insensible of your generous Favours, till something more sutable to your noble Genius should offer it self. But then, reflecting on your Avertion, to all Encomiums (tho never so justly due) obliges me to lay aside all other thoughts, than of craving your favoura∣ble Acceptance of this trifle, and of subscribing my self,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>Your most Humble Servant,
P. B.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="novel">
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE SIEGE OF MENTZ. A NOVEL</HEAD>
<P>THERE is so great a disparity betwixt <HI>Mars</HI> and the God of Love, that one would ima∣gine where the first did ap∣pear, the last should not presume to shew his head: The one is all Fierceness Va∣lour, and Undauntedness, which scorns all Advantages▪ but what are gained by Bravery and Courage: And the other is of so soft and delicate a F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame, that it
<PB N="2" REF="4"/>
uses nothing but Policy and Stratagems to bring about its Amorous Intrigues and Designs. Yet, notwithstanding this vast difference, <HI>Mars</HI> is seldom seen to take the Field, but that Love is perceived to follow in the Rear, not without hopes of obtaining as considerable Conquests there, as the other can hope for in the first ranks of Honour. We are not without divers examples of this kind; but this which I here present to the publick, is of so mo∣dern a date, and so remarkable in our days, that I thought I should not a little oblige the World in giving it this Piece of Gallantry, in which one of our own Nation, was one of the principal Heroes, both as to War and Love.</P>
<P>We will disguise him under the Name of <HI>Peregrine,</HI> of a considerable Family in the <HI>North</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> though a younger Brother, who being come to <HI>London,</HI> (that famous place for framing of Youth to Virtue, as well as to Vice,) there he sell in Company with some Officers of the Consederates, who had left their <HI>Ger∣man</HI> Winter-Quarters, to spend some days in seeing the <HI>English</HI>-Court.</P>
<P><PB N="3" REF="4"/>His natural tendency to Arms put him on the design of seeing a Campaigne, or two; and though he had some thoughts at first, to make his first Essay in <HI>Flan∣ders,</HI> yet the Friendship which he con∣tracted with these <HI>German</HI>-Officers, made him to proffer to accompany them back, to serve with them in quality of Volun∣tier in the Army of the Allies, in hopes they would continue their Friendship to∣wards him. They readily imbrac'd his offers, with assurances of not only their Services out of their Friendship; also, e∣specially Count <HI>Zinzendorf,</HI> who had a considerable Post, took him into particu∣lar Protection, assuring him, That he would write to him, and send him word where he should find him at the opening of the Campaigne.</P>
<P><HI>Peregrine</HI> having laid so good a Foun∣dation, to build his war-like Resolution upon, thinks of no more but getting, a∣gainst the Season, such an Equipage as might sute with his Designs, and the quality of those that honoured him with their Friendship; wherefore so soon as these <HI>German</HI> Gentlemen had satisfied their Curiosities, in all that was remark∣able in this great City, and the adjacent
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
places to it, (in which <HI>Peregrine</HI> did assist them, not only with all his Interest, but that of his Friends also,) they took leave of him, and imbarked for <HI>Holland,</HI> in or∣der to their return in their own Coun∣try.</P>
<P>Now is <HI>Peregrine</HI> busied to the utmost, to get himself provided with Horses, Ser∣vants, Monies, and other necessaries, to appear like a Gentleman, being resolved to signalize himself by some brave action to render himself worthy of the honour of these brave Strangers, who had so free∣ly taken him into their Friendship.</P>
<P><HI>Peregrine</HI> had left in the Country, a young Gentlewoman, who was deeply in love with him; but his Mind having been for a considerable time, before he could perceive her affections, possest with the desires of Travelling, he had avoid∣ed, as much as he could, her Company, for fear of being diverted by her from his beloved design. This Gentlewoman hearing of <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s suddain leaving of <HI>England,</HI> writ to him a Letter, which was extraordinary full of Passion, which he received the day before his departure; the contents of which I shall have occa∣sion
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
to deliver, in the Thread of this fol∣lowing Discourse.</P>
<P>There is nothing like a willing mind to dispatch Business; his desires were so great, that in a short time he had got ready an Equipage suitable to his worth; with which, after having taken leave of his particular Friends, in the Month of <HI>March</HI> he set forward for <HI>Harwich,</HI> where having found the Pacquet-Boat ready for sail, he went in it for <HI>Holland;</HI> where he safely arrived the third day after <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Netherlands,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> where nothing happened to him▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> able, 'till he was got within a day <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣ncy of the City of <HI>Mentz,</HI> which was then in the possession of the <HI>French,</HI> who put all the Country thereabouts under Contribution, &amp; took up such considerable Hostages as they could find, for security, which they carried with them into that place, threatning them with Death if the Contributions were not duly brought in.</P>
<P>There had fallen such a vast quantity of Rain, during a whole day and night, that all the Roads were covered with Waters, and the small Rivers swollen in∣to
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
Torrents: He was to pass on through a Ford that was at a small distance from an ancient Castle, by whose Walls the River run, taring up, and hurrying a∣long with its Streams, Trees, and pieces of Rocks.</P>
<P>There was a Lady on the other side of the River, who leaning over some Rails on the Banks, beholding the strange con∣susion which this medly of things made; <HI>Peregrine</HI> having made an halt, while he had sent one of his Men for a Guide, he, mean time, had leasure to consider that Person, who with her sumptuous Dress, and delicate Beauty, had fix'd his Eyes in admiration of her; when on the suddain, the Earth she stood upon, gave way, and she, with the Rails, fell head∣long into the Torrent; she gave a most vehement out-cry, which was seconded by <HI>Peregrine,</HI> and his Servants. He Pre∣sently set Spurs to his Horse, and having gon beyond where she was floting on the Currant, being buoy'd up by her Cloths, and the rapidness of the Stream, he plung'd into the River, and with much ado, got hold of her; but finding his Horse might hurt her, while he dragg'd her along, he quitted him, not without
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
receiving a hurt in the Leg, which made it the more difficult for him to reach the shore, with his drowning Prize: At last he got hold of some Roots of Trees, by which he hung, 'till he had recovered Breath, holding the Lady's Head, as much as possible he could, above Wa∣ter, 'till his Man reaching some Branches to him, which they had hastily lopp'd off of Trees; he got hold of them, and was pulled to shoar, with the Lady: She laid for dead, on the Grass; and he with small signs of life.</P>
<P>By this time, the out-crys that had been made at the Lady's fall in the Wa∣ter, had brought some of the Servants of the Castle to the Rivers side, where ha∣ving beheld the sad Spectacle, they re∣newed the out-crys; but above all, <HI>Ma∣riana, Clarinda</HI>'s Kinswoman, transpor∣ted beyond her self, at the sight of her dead Friend, did fling her self violently upon her Body, making the greatest La∣mentations imaginable; at the shock of these two Bodies, <HI>Clarinda</HI> coming a lit∣tle to her self, open'd her Eyes, and fetch∣ing a short sigh, gave visible signs that there was some Life in her. <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who was come to himself a little before,
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
began to give advice, (in <HI>French,</HI> for he could not speak one word of <HI>German,</HI> though his Groom could) That the La∣dy should instantly be carried into her Chamber, and there laid with her head downwards, to let out of her Stomach as much. Water as they could: This Lan∣guage being understood by her who was come to them, it was presently done, with the assistance of two of <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Servants▪ who told them all the circum∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ces of that sad accident.</P>
<P><HI>Clarinda▪</HI> by these▪ and other means <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 lines" DISP="〈3 lines〉"/> fallen into the River▪ but was wholly ig∣norant of all that had happened to he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> after? <HI>Mariana</HI> took upon her to satisfie her dear Friend in that point, as well as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he could, with the relation she had re∣ceived from <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Groom. And what is become of my Deliverer? said <HI>Clarinda.</HI> Is he alive? We left him, re∣ply'd <HI>Mariana▪</HI> sitting on the Bank over the River. An ill place, answered <HI>Cla∣rinda,</HI> for a Person that has taken somuch pains to lave my Life, with so great an hazard of his own: Go, continued she,
<PB N="9" REF="7"/>
let him be invited in, and provide a Chamber, and all things necessary for his reception: Let me not appear un∣grateful to a Person so deserving my care, the rather to, because he is a Stranger, who has done these great <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="apex" EXTENT="5+ letters" DISP="•••••…"/>gs for me. This said, was soon obey'd, she being absolute Mistress in that Castle, by her Father's detention, her Brother's absence in the Wars of <HI>Hungary,</HI> and the Death of her Mother; 'tis true, there was an old Aunt liv'd with her, but so antiqua∣ted, that she was rather a burden, than an aid. <HI>Peregrine</HI> was presently laid in a good warm Bed, in a decent Apartment; great excuses made for having defered so long the performance of those things, so justly due to his Merits, laying the whole fault on the care they had taken of their young Mistress's recovery. Then inquiry was made how he felt his Leg: He told them, that he found he should want the use of some expert Chyrurgeon, because he felt the pain to increase, and to spread it self upwards: there was presently a Chyrurgeon sent for; as also a Physician to look to <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s, as well as to <HI>Pere∣grine</HI>'s Health; they were both blooded▪ to <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/>reyent Fevers; and with the <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/>
<PB N="10" REF="8"/>
some slight Remedies, <HI>Clarinda</HI> was in a short time perfectly recovered; but it was not so with <HI>Peregrine;</HI> for what with having his Contusion so long bathed in cold Water, at a Season when the Air was something sharp, there was some apprehension of a Gangrene, which shew'd it self by the lividity, and insensibility of the part. So soon as <HI>Clarinda</HI> understood the danger, she doubled her diligence in attending him: She was no longer con∣tented to let him have all that the Castle and Neighbourhood could afford of com∣fort and refreshment, but she thought her self oblig'd to administer them her self: while <HI>Peregrine</HI> dy'd for Love of <HI>Clarinda,</HI> and slighted his own illness.</P>
<P>It is an old saying, <HI>That Love will creep where it cannot go;</HI> and it is as true as an∣cient. At first <HI>Clarinda</HI> did all these pieces of service to her Deliverer, as in∣cumbent Duties on those Obligations she was ingag'd to him for her Life. But little, by little, she found that there was some other motive, though she knew nor what, that led her on; she was more concern'd, and more inquisitive after <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI>'s well-fare, every day, though he daily increased in health: She would fre∣quently
<PB N="11" REF="8"/>
find her self in his Room, yet forget how she came there, and for what purpose; which would sometimes so dis∣compose her, that <HI>Peregrine</HI> could not but observe it, and she perceiving his ta∣king notice of it, that would put her in the greater disorder. Once, amongst the rest, <HI>Clarinda</HI> having entred his Cham∣ber, with a preserving Pan, with young Chickens in it, did not know that she had mistaken his Room for hers, 'till <HI>Peregrine</HI> ask'd her aloud, Whether she had brought him a Pan full of Caudle for his Brakefast? That indeed put her into such a confusion, that not having a ready excuse, she speedily went▪ out of the Chamber again, without replying one word: whereupon <HI>Peregrine</HI> offered to rise, and run after her, but found he had attempted beyond the power of his Leg: I cannot follow you Madam, cry'd he, but it shall be for the next time. When she was got to her own Chamber, she be∣gan to consider her condition, and how insensibly Love had drawn her into his Net, was very much troubled at it, but much more, that she had given <HI>Peregrine</HI> so great an insight into the affairs▪ of her Heart: She endeavoured to frame some
<PB N="12" REF="9"/>
excuses a thousand ways, but all to no purpose; she could not find any thing in the whole Magazine of her Wit, that could attone for that Error▪ because she knew that <HI>Peregrine</HI> had taken particular notice of it, and that her suddain, and silent retreat, had confirmed him but too much of her mistake. In this great perplexity she abstain'd from visiting him all that day▪ and when it began to grow duskish, in hopes to conceal the disorders she should be in, at the sight of him, she adventured into his Chamber, not being able to abstain any longer from the sight of a Person who had made a greater pro∣gress in her Heart, than she expected. I come, Sir, said she, not to make an Applogy for entring your Chamber this Morning, but for my obrupt return, without shewing you those pretty little Creatures I had in my Pan, and not so much as making any excuse for my rude∣ness. I had forgot to say something of moment to that Person who had presen∣ted me with them. Madam, reply'd <HI>Pe∣regrine▪</HI> who had a mind to reclaim her; It would be a great <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="bleedthrough" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in me to con∣troul your Actions; all that I have to say, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="bleedthrough" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="bleedthrough" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>y that you had any occasion
<PB N="13" REF="9"/>
oblig'd you to so suddain a return, to deprive me of your most charming Conversation; I have passed this re∣dious long day like an Hermit in my self, or rather like a condemn'd Per∣son, after the hopes of a Reprieve. Upon the fear, I have been in all this day, of having given you some distaste. Sir, you might, or you might nor, she replied, according as you may censure my Actions. I am all respect, Madam, said he, and if I had any thought in me otherwise, I should soon destroy them, as Rebels to my Heart. There she inter∣rupted him, saying; Take heed, Sir, what you advance, for should it at any time, be contradicted, by Words or Acti∣ons, that would be sufficient to debase you in my good Opinion. These Words check the brisk thoughts which <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s late Action, had raised in his mind, fear∣ing that it was his offer to go after her in the morning, that had deprived him of her presence all that day; so that he pre∣sently turned the design he had made to rally her, into a profound respect. And silence, which gave opportunity to <HI>Cla∣rinda,</HI> thus to continue, I know that you Men, are but too apt to flatter your selves▪
<PB N="14" REF="10"/>
and to construe the least of our inconside∣rate Actions, to your best Advantages, though they were intended quite contrary. There he interrupted her, saying, when I look on all these Accomplishments of body and mind, which spake you the most admirable Creature in the World, or that I turn back my Eyes on my own Unworthiness: How is it possible for me, Madam, to do more, than admire; and with trembling, frame answers to your demands, for fear of breaking that respect that is due to you from the whole World? Nay, Sir, she said, then I can take no∣tice of what I owe you, which I must acknowledge to be great, being oblig'd to you for no less than my Life, with the addition of the great hazard you put yours in, in that worthy Action; and I am not so destitute of Gratitude, as not to own that I have nothing to present you with, proportionable to so signal a piece of Ser∣vice; but when all is done, I can but of∣fer you those small means that I have at present at my own disposal, being yet un∣der the Tuition of a Father, and a Bro∣ther, both unfortunately absent now that I want them here, to add their Acknow∣ledgments, where mine are deficient Oh!
<PB N="15" REF="10"/>
Madam, What have you named? Or rather, what have you endeavoured to conceal? Answered he, Are not you Mi∣stress of the richest Jewel upon Earth? And can all the Fathers, Mothers, or brothers, in the World, dispose of the Treasure of your Heart? That, Ma∣dam, is certainly at your own disposal. That, Sir, replied <HI>Clarinda,</HI> what price so ever you are pleased to set upon it, is not of so much value in my esteem; though, I must confess, I should be unwilling, on the other hand, to cast it away; especi∣ally,—she was going on, when she was interrupted with the entring of a Gentleman of the Neighbour-hood, who had the consent of her Father to Court her for a Wife, whom I shall call Count <HI>Mansfielt.</HI> Madam, said he, at the first news of your late disaster, I come to of∣fer you my most humble Service, even with the hazard of my Life. Sir, an∣swered <HI>Clarinda,</HI> I have no Enemy to fight, to take you for my Second, except you would call the two Elements of Earth and Water to an account, for ha∣ving together conspired against my Life. But here's a Gentleman, continued she, presenting him to <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who has
<PB N="16" REF="11"/>
done that already, and rescued me from both their furies, to the hazard of his Life; at this the Count and <HI>Peregrine</HI> saluting one another, the first said, I envy your Happiness, Sir, in having been thought, by Fate, a worthy Instrument in the Pre∣servation of this Lady; I might have challenged a Prerogative in that, even by the consent of those that may claim an Authority over her; but Fortune is blind▪ Sir, you know, and—I can not call her blind, Sir, upon these fortunate Oc∣casions, said <HI>Clarinda,</HI> seeing that when I was destitute of all other helps, from Friends, she called this worthy Stranger <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my rescue. Madam, then, said <HI>Peri∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ne,</HI> if there is any thing, in this late <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tion, that is worthy your Record, I <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> attribute it, but to my good Fortune, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> guided me hither; where the same <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4+ letters" DISP="••••…"/>g, might have been performed by <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wortheir Person, as this Gentleman, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>e like: Yes, Sir, replied the young <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, as being doubly engaged for my <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Interest as well as that Ladies. I hope, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ered <HI>Clarinda,</HI> in a little heat) that <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> will not say, I ever gave you any In∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4+ letters" DISP="••••…"/> me? And I am of Opinion, that <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3+ letters" DISP="•••…"/>ever my Parents may have done▪
<PB N="17" REF="11"/>
without my consent, of this nature, may be, by me alter'd as I shall▪ think <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> not so fast, Sir, she continued, lest you leave me behind; after which; she <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>∣ed a side, which being observed by <HI>Pere∣grine,</HI> it▪ put a new Life; into his d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣ing Spirits, which he ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> almost lost <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> this young Count's confident▪ App<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> which made him venture to say▪ that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Lady was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the right, and th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eved most Persons would be of her <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> adding▪ There <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> a force▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Count, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>wed to give their Advices a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Right Sir, answered <HI>Clarinda,</HI> and▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> that we ought to receive them with Re∣spect, as coming from them. You say well, Madam, said the young Count, and that was the Motive that induced me to proceed after the manner I have done, towards the honour of pleasing you. My Father and Mother, you mean, Sir, who from me are distinct Persons, so that you might apply your self to them, and pour your whole Soul into their Bosoms▪ make them wholly yours, with your
<PB N="18" REF="12"/>
great Eloquence; and yet I might still be the same indifferent Person in all re∣spects: Yet, Madam, replied the Count, I have had the Happiness of finding a fa∣vourable Reception at your Hands, which there <HI>Clarinda</HI> interrupted him, saying, In Obedience to my Mothers Advices; but she is no more, and what power soe∣ver she might have, as a Parent, yet she could not, nor never did offer, to have a Jurisdiction over my Mind, and Incli∣nations. You have a Father still, Ma∣dam, who was pleased to encourage my Adresses to your fair self; I'll plead his Authority, and Favour. Here <HI>Peregrine</HI> could not forbear, saying, With this La∣dies leave, I'll venture to say, That durst I raise my Thoughts, towards so much Happiness, I should trust rather on For∣tune, though blind, and my own Me∣rits, though never so mean and unwor∣thy, than on any other Cause whatsoever; Assidious Services, and a most Submissive Obedience, are great Advocates in mat∣ters of this weight. Pardon me, Sir, if I must tell you, added <HI>Clarinda,</HI> adres∣sing to the Count, that this Gentleman has named, two of the chiefest means, to which I may add Fidelity and Perse∣verance:
<PB N="19" REF="12"/>
In opposition to all Trials▪ Madam, whatever you say, must be as∣sented to, replied the Count, you are a Party concerned; but for this Gentleman to give his un-ask'd for Advice, I think it very unnecessary. With that the Count look'd very frowningly towards <HI>Perigrine;</HI> which Action, and Words, having the more netled <HI>Clarinda,</HI> she in some kind of Emotion, returned, Sir, This Gentle∣man I look upon as the Preserver of my Life, which may have intitled him to some share▪ in the Care of me, as well as he may be in my Esteem. Though blind Fortune, said the Count, has brought this Gentleman to do you a piece of Service, of that Nature; yet I, with Justice, claim such a considerable Interest in you, as I must not suffer any Stranger to equal, or come near, without declaring him my Enemy. I am not an Enemy to any one, replied <HI>Peregrine;</HI> but I will die in main∣taining, that all the World, ought to ad∣mire this Ladies Perfections, and not without vehement Desires. <HI>Clarinda</HI> finding, that the heat increased, betwixt those two Rivals, as she felt Love to glow more fiercely in her Breast, towards the worthy Stranger; she broke off the Di∣scourse,
<PB N="20" REF="13"/>
or Dispute rather, by saying, the Count would oblige her much more, in letting fall that Discourse, which was ve∣ry unpleasing to her, and to exercise his Talient on any other Subject; and turn∣ing towards <HI>Peregrine,</HI> she added, I fear, Sir, that my too long visit, may have caused some Disorder, which may retard your Health, towards which I ought ra∣ther to contribute. Then, turning again towards the Count, If you please, Sir, continued she, you and I will retire into <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> his Hand.</P>
<P>What various and different Motions did animate those three Persons Breasts: <HI>Peregrine</HI> was all Respect and Love; the Count Interest and Revenge, mixt with some grounds of Affection; and <HI>Clarinda,</HI> full of Gratitude, which was almost all turned into Passion. <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who be∣fore had had divers opportunities to ob∣serve a worthy Gratitude in <HI>Clarinda's</HI> Breast, was ravish'd to find that by de∣grees it grow up into an Affection: That Noble Vigour, with which she had main∣tained his Interest against the Count, had
<PB N="21" REF="13"/>
almost wholly convinc'd his Modesty, that he was perfectly happy in her Bo∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome? but still he feared he had reason to: apprehend the Opposition of a powerful Rival, but then he hop'd that the Count's own Rashness would work him out a shorter way to his Happiness, than he might expect, by the due Methods in Love. He therefore contributed all he could towards his Recovery, and in that Resolution, his Spirits being rais'd above their ordinary pitch, by the thoughts of Conquest, he forc'd himself out of his Seat, by the aid of a Staff, and getting into the Room, where he expected to have found <HI>Clarinda</HI> and the Count to∣gether. He was strangely, surprised to find <HI>Clarinda</HI> alone, imerg'd in Tears▪ under a gale of Sighs, which she was not able to suppress so suddainly, but that <HI>Peregrine</HI> over-heard; he found of some of them, she had covered her Face all over with her Handkerchief, so that <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI> came up close to her, and stood some time before her, ere she could per∣ceive him; besides, she little expected his coming, and knew no Body but her dear <HI>Mariana</HI> was permitted▪ to enter where she was; if she heard any noise,
<PB N="22" REF="14"/>
she believed it to proceed from her: Wherefore, as soon as her Sighs would permit her to make use of her Speech, remaining still in the same posture, Let us, dear <HI>Mariana,</HI> said she, Let us pre∣vent, if we can possible, the dangerous effects of the Count's fury and power, o∣ver a Stranger, to whom I owe so much, and whom thou knowest I love. With that uncovering her Face, and perceiving <HI>Peregrine</HI> standing before her, she gave a shriek, and presently clouding her Coun∣tenance with some marks of Displeasure, in another Accent, she said; It was not fair, Sir, thus to intrude upon my Re∣tirement, and become a spie to my most secret Actions; it must needs lessen you in my thoughts, and that which mere Gratitude had made me to express to your Advantage, may by such proceed∣ings tu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n to your Prejudice. <HI>Peregrine,</HI> perceiving his Error, flung himself on his Knees before her, saying, I own my fault, Madam, and thus so I beg your pardon, but be so just as to hear my excuse; I have accus'd my self of a Crime, which I have committed without design, therefore I hope the easier to be pardon'd; but if I must incur your Displeasure, doom
<PB N="23" REF="14"/>
me to Death, command my Rival to chastise that Presumption, which lead me to inquire after his Behaviour towards so much worth; 'twas the Apprehensions of his want of respect towards you, that forc'd me out of my Chamber, to be a bridle to his ruggid Temper, which I fear, Madam, has been the Cause of these Disorders, I unhappily find you in. The Count, who <HI>Peregrine</HI> had thought to be gone, was returning again upon his steps, but was met by <HI>Mariana</HI> at the Chamber Door, who having seen the posture of these two Lovers, judg'd it convenient to prevent the Count from the same Specta∣cle; but yet not so well but that he had time to perceive, as she was shutting the Door, how Courteously <HI>Clarinda</HI> was raising <HI>Peregrine</HI> from the Floor. Hell and Confusion, cried the Count, Can I see this tamely? It must not, it shall not be, one of us two must yield to the other, by a suddain Death; with that he went hastily out again, grumbling to him∣self. <HI>Mariana</HI> did attempt to appease him, and called to him, but he had no Ears left but for revenge, which press'd him forward to some fatal Enterprise.</P>
<P><PB N="24" REF="15"/>The noise the Count had made, had reach'd the Lovers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>s; and <HI>Peregrine</HI> was earnestly persuading <HI>Clarinda,</HI> to per∣mit him to go and correct his Insolence; but she retain'd him by the Hand, telling him she knew better how to allay his pas∣sion, as being better acquainted with it▪ I'll take my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to do it, continued she, mean time, I must dissuade you, from so much Presumption as to believe that if <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mention'd Love, as you have intimated, I thought then of you; I must confess you have a great share in my Gratitude, and some Progress you may have made in my Esteem, by your obliging Behaviour; yet not so firmly establish, but that, the least, Presumption in your very▪ Thoughts, would beat down all the Fabrick, your modesty had raised, should it come to my Knowledge▪ Madam, replied <HI>Pere∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ne,</HI> I am nothing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> what you would have me to b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and I will never presume to think▪ to speak, or to act, but what shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> correspondent to your Will and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> replied <HI>Clarinda,</HI> I will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> believe that I ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> some <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> you, but let that be the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of your Ambition. I am all Obedience, Madam, replied <HI>Pe∣regrine;</HI>
<PB N="25" REF="15"/>
and in order to bring my self to this frame of Temper, I will have the vilest Thoughts of my self, and the most honourable of the Count, that I can con∣ceive in my Imagination: as for your Excellencies, I am already satisfied, that they put you above the aspiring of the most accomplished Monarchs on Earth. <HI>Mariana</HI>'s coming in to acquaint them with what the Count had seen, and said, made them to change their Discourse; and some time after, <HI>Peregrine</HI> seeing it grow late, took his leave of <HI>Clarinda,</HI> in order to go to his Bed; at which <HI>Clarin∣da</HI> thought fit (to sweeten his relish after the bitter Potion she had given him,) with some kindnesses, to say, that she had a great desire to see his Leg, which she fear'd was not so well as she could wish, by his favouring it so much. I have attained, added she, to some skill in Wounds and Bruises, from some ob∣servations which I have made in my Mother's, and my Aunt's charitable pra∣ctise amongst the Poor of the Neighbour∣hood. <HI>Peregrine</HI> would have excused himself from giving her that trouble.</P>
<P><PB N="26" REF="16"/>But <HI>Clarinda,</HI> who design'd to sweeten him again, ordered <HI>Mariana</HI> to send for those things with which he dress'd his Leg, that she might see it opened her self.</P>
<P><HI>Peregrine</HI> must have been more than blind, not to discern that all <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s pretended actions of gratitude, were the meer effects of Love. But notwithstand∣ing all his knowledge, he was to seem ignorant: He therefore consented to all her desires, and permitted his Leg to be dress'd by his two new Chyrurgeons. <HI>Clarinda</HI> perceiving some blackness still remaining on the bruised part, appeared much concerned at it, and said, she fear'd very much that he was not yet past all danger. <HI>Peregrine</HI> protested all was well; that he felt no other inconveniency at that present, but a little weakness which attended his Ankle, which he attributed to the want of using his Leg, and the fall of some humours upon that part. <HI>Maria∣na,</HI> who knew it would please <HI>Clarinda,</HI> did second her in what she said, and ad∣ded, it was fit to send for the Chyrurgeon very early in the Morning, before he should be gone forth: so that <HI>Peregrine,</HI> for fear of offending, had not a word to
<PB N="27" REF="16"/>
reply. This being concluded on, and <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI>'s Leg swadled up again, he took his leave once more of his two Doctres∣ses, and by the aid of one of his Servants, retir'd to his own Chamber.</P>
<P><HI>Peregrine</HI> was no sooner got thither, but <HI>Clarinda</HI> went into hers, attended by her Faithful <HI>Mariana;</HI> where, while <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI> was undressing, they had a large discant upon that Evenings Transactions; wherein <HI>Mariana</HI> endeavoured to con∣vince <HI>Clarinda,</HI> That seeing she her self was grown to that pass, as not to be ca∣pable of concealing her Passion towards <HI>Peregrine,</HI> she ought to take other me∣thods with him, and not deny so abso∣lutely, that which she could not conceal from him in the day, and from her at night, in her Dreams and passionate Transports, at her awaking. <HI>Clarinda</HI> confess'd, that she could not well palliate her Passion much longer, it was grown to such a heighth, but that she was resolved not wholly to declare in favour of <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI> neither, 'till she had got her Fa∣ther's consent to disingage herself from the Count; and that she would lose no time, nor leave no means unattempted to ac∣complish her designs; wherefore she had
<PB N="28" REF="17"/>
design'd the next Morning to send an Ex∣press to her Father about it. These Re∣solutions being taken, they went to their repose,</P>
<P>The young Count, who had but very little rest all that Night, and that found himself the next Morning very indis∣posed, designed to prevent a Fever, by a bleeding in the Arm; he thereunto im∣ploy'd the same Chyrurgeon that had been sent for that very Morning by <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI> to <HI>Peregrine,</HI> because he liv'd near him, and was constantly made use of on any occasion by the whole Family, as those kind of Persons affect to make themselves busie in their employ: he told the Count, that he was presently to go to the Lady <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s, to look on a strange Gentleman's Leg, who he had in hand before, and had left, as believing him quite out of danger. The Count hearing of this, caused the Chyrurgeon to bleed him in the left Arm; after which he took the opportunity of this Messenger to convey a Challenge into <HI>Peregrine's</HI> hand, and to receive an answer by the same way, unknown, and unsuspected by any Person of the Castle. He then writ as follows.</P>
<LETTER>
<PB N="29" REF="17"/>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>MY Right to fair <HI>Clarinda</HI> is so sub∣stantial and solid, that you must re∣solve to quit all your imaginary Claims to her, under your hand, or be ready to main∣tain your weak pretensions, with your Sword in hand, to Morrow, at Five in the Morn∣ing, in the <HI>Gravel Pits,</HI> about the mid∣way, betwixt the Castle and the Habitation of</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Humble Servant
Count <HI>Man<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>▪</HI></SIGNED>
The least Child will shew you the place.</CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P>He delivered this Paper, sealed up, to the Chyrurgeon, giving him strict charge to convey into that Gentleman's own hands, unperceived of any Person what∣soever, and to require an answer, and bring it as secretly back to him again. The Chyrurgeon promised to perform his commands to a tittle, and upon that went his way to the Castle. He was presently admitted into <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Cham∣ber,
<PB N="30" REF="18"/>
where, not long after, <HI>Clarinda</HI> and <HI>Mariana</HI> appear'd also; they inquir'd af∣ter his Health, which he own'd to be perfect, and that it was meerly to con∣descend to others desires, that he admit∣ted of this unnecessary visit from the Chy∣rurgeon. The Chyrurgeon did not think fit to deliver the Letter, while they were in the Room, wherefore he im∣ploy'd himself in pulling out his Pocket, all the Instruments he had, which were not a few, though he had no occasion for any; and with searching all his Poc∣kets, he at last let drop the Letter by ac∣cident, which being perceived by <HI>Mari∣ana,</HI> she took it up, and convey'd it in∣to <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s hands, who went out to read. Mean time, the Leg was taken in∣to Examination, and after all adjudg'd by the Leech-Oracle, to be as the owner of it had certified. Now he had no more to do, but to deliver the Letter, but still is very uneasie at the Women's presence; he tumbles all over himself, to have it in readiness to deliver, with the first op∣portunity; frets within himself that he cannot find it, at last perceives it on the Table, where <HI>Clarinda</HI> had laid it, after she had read, and seal'd it up again:
<PB N="31" REF="18"/>
He greedily snatches it up; and <HI>Clarinda</HI> perceiving he had found it, retires with <HI>Mariana,</HI> to give him the opportunity of delivery: He presently conveys it in∣to <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s hands, and waits for an an∣swer: <HI>Peregrine</HI> reads it, and instantly sends him back with these following Lines.</P>
<LETTER>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>HAD you said, That neither you, nor I, nor none else, had any right in that Lady, more than she is pleas'd herself to dispose of to any Person she judges wor∣thy of that Honour, I had join'd with you▪ in opposition to all Contradictions. But be∣cause I am of Opinion, you ground your right on a false bottom, I am willing to in∣form you, I shall not fail to meet you, at the time and place appointed▪ with my Sword in hand, to let you know <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> what right I ground my pretensions in that fair person; 'till then, I am</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Humble Servant
Peregrine.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P><PB N="32" REF="19"/>
Now are all parties very well pleas'd with their cunning contrivances, though every one in a distinct respect; <HI>Peregrine</HI> appear'd all that day more gay and plea∣sant than ever, walking up and down, and would willingly have taken the Air out of Doors, but that he could not ob∣tain of his courteous Guardian; when he found that by no means he could not get out, to see himself where was the place of Rendezvous, being so narrowly watch'd by all the Family, he sent one of his Servants to inquire the way to the Count's, and then to follow that Road, 'till he found some Gravel Pits about the mid-way; after that, he gave order to another of his, to keep all the Horses, and all things else, in a readiness, as if to depart the next Morning; but that they should do it very privately, and not go about it 'till all the Servants were in Bed. After this, he apply'd himself to the composing of this following Letter.</P>
<LETTER>
<P>I <HI>Fly, Madam, to inform the Count, with the point of my Sword, that you are a fewel I can yield to no Man, but ac∣companied with my Life; not Madam, that I dare presume to think any thing in me,</HI>
<PB N="33" REF="19"/>
<HI>worthy so rich a prize. But I am so vain as to assert, That none can love you better, and that none dare do for you more, then I am ready to perform at all times, and yet attribute to my self no Merits in the least, on that account. I go with that confidence, that I repose on the advantage of your E∣steem and Friendship, that makes me sure of the Victory. If I live, it will be but to continue your Slave all the days of my Life. If I fall, and you afford but one kind thought to accompany me to my Grave, I shall rest in peace; but either in Life or Death, I am, and shall ever be</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your most humble Servant
Peregrine.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P>This Letter was to be left, seal'd up, on his Pillow, that it might not so readi∣ly be sound, and that he might first have time to dispose of himself, according to the Event of the Combat; he still, by in∣tervals, mixt himself with <HI>Clarinda</HI> and <HI>Mariana,</HI> who had other Thoughts in their Heads, and <HI>Peregrine</HI> perceiving them to be something more pensive than ordinarily, did all he could to divert
<PB N="34" REF="20"/>
them; all this did but still more, and more insnare <HI>Clarinda,</HI> who could not but be highly pleas'd at her Lover's great Passion and Bravery, which very much ficted her Masculine Spirit; but she had design'd to prevent all mischief, for this time, with a resolution to give her self to him, so soon as the Messenger she had sent to her Father, were return'd, what answer soever he brought, in order to prevent all future quarrels, in the opini∣on, that being once his, all other pre∣tensions would be at an end, and fall of themselves,</P>
<P>The Day drawing to an end, <HI>Clarinda</HI> pretended her self somewhat indisposed, that she might the sooner retire to perfect the design, which she, and <HI>Mariana</HI> had laid, to disappoint <HI>Peregrine</HI> of his Inten∣tions: <HI>Peregrine</HI> also, to take time to pack up all things, without noise, was glad of that opportunity to retire.</P>
<P>He had not been long alone in his Chamber, but he thought he heard the sound of some Instrument, at a distance, which made him give an Attention to it; he shifted to all sides of the Room, to find from whence it came; at last, hav∣ing opened a Closet Door, he was sensi∣ble
<PB N="35" REF="20"/>
that it proceeded from behind that Wall: He laid his Ear as close as he could to it, and discern'd 'twas a Lute; after which he heard some body say, Here, take this Instrument, it suits not now my too distracted Thoughts, come lets to rest: I think 'twill be convenient, answer'd another, that we may not fail of encoun∣tring the Count early enough, to defeat his Designs. 'Twill be a strange Surpri∣sal, answer'd the other, to him, and to our Guests, who little think how fast he is secure. After this, there was a silence which made him give over hearkning, to break their Measures, not doubting but 'twas <HI>Clarinda</HI> and <HI>Mariana,</HI> who had had some Intelligence of the Duel: He was alone in his Chamber, having order∣ed his Servants to their rest; he went to open his Chamber-Door, to call one of them, but found he was double lock'd in. This made him to distrust the more, but knew not how to remedy it; in this per∣plexity walking up and down, he at last thought of getting out at the Window; he takes what he thought fit with him, looks every where for his Sword, but finds it not; so gets out of the Window without it, and finds himself near to the
<PB N="36" REF="21"/>
Stable-Yard, he makes towards the Sta∣bles, where he finds his Man getting the Horses in a readiness, according to order, inquires after his Sword, but no News of it, so was forc'd to take one of his Servants Weapons, and that he might not be fol∣lowed by <HI>Clarinda,</HI> causes his Servants, to turn all the Horses loose, out of the Sta∣ble, except his own, believing it too far a Journey for her to walk. Now, he grows very impatient, thinks the time long, re∣turns not to his Chamber, but waits for the tedious hour by his Horses; and so soon as day began to peep, he gets his Horses sadled our, without noise, and he follows himself, without being discover'd. That Servant who had been sent to find where the Gravel pits were, leads the Van, <HI>Peregrine</HI> followed; after Five or Six Miles riding, the Guide told his Ma∣ster, that they were within half a Mile of the Pits; there <HI>Peregrine</HI> makes a halt, and perceicing a thick Wood, on the right, commands his Men to go wait for him there; after which, he rides on with his Guide, who leads him to the Pits; there he orders his Man, that so soon as he should see a Gentleman appear, he should retire homewards, in the Road,
<PB N="37" REF="21"/>
at some convenient distance, a little out of the way, not to be seen, and there wait his coming.</P>
<P><HI>Clarinda,</HI> full of Thoughts and Fears, could not Sleep, nor suffer <HI>Mariana</HI> to take rest; but so soon as Day began to ap∣pear, they did arise, and calling up some Servants, gave Orders to have three Hor∣ses sadled, her own, and <HI>Marianas,</HI> and another for a Groom, and they went a∣bout to get themselves ready. The Mes∣senger presently returned, saying, That there was not an Horse in the Stable; this did alarum <HI>Clarinda:</HI> What, said she, are not our Guest's Horses there neither? The Person answered, that there was not one; this put <HI>Clarinda</HI> in a great plunge, and <HI>Mariana</HI> was sent immediately down, with the Key of <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Chamber-Door, to see after him; she passing by that Window, out of which <HI>Peregrine</HI> had got, perceiving it open, and some∣thing white lying on the ground, she took it up, and feared he had got out that way, she hastily run to his Chamber-Door, and having opened it, found that the Bird was flown; she immediately run back to acquaint <HI>Clarinda</HI> of it, and both in great surprise, run to the Stables,
<PB N="38" REF="22"/>
half dressed, and half undressed; there <HI>Clarinda</HI> met a Groom, leading her own Pad, who said, He, nor his Fellows, could find no more Horses, as yet, she caused him immediately to be saddled, mean time, sends <HI>Mariana</HI> for <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Sword, which she had laid out of the way; and so soon as her Horse was ready, gets up, orders <HI>Mariana</HI> to follow her, so soon as possible she could, and rides towards the Pits, as fast as her Horse could carry her.</P>
<P>By this the Count was come, <HI>Pere∣grine</HI> had left him for dead, and at his fall, having perceived a blue Ribbon hang out of his Pocket, he had the Cu∣riosity to pluck it out, at the end of which, he found a Picture, which per∣ceiving to be <HI>Clarindas,</HI> he put it in his own Pocket, and run back to find his Man and Horse, to make his escape. He had not gon far, before he met with an Horse, on which hung <HI>Clarinda,</HI> by the Foot in the Stirrup, and her Head drag∣ging on the ground, crying out for help. He presently knew her by her voice, and perceiving that the Horse was fright∣ed, he gently drew near him till he got hold of the Bridle; and by that means
<PB N="39" REF="22"/>
was a second time the Preserver of his dear Mistresses Life. He disingaged her, and knowing he could not be far from his Servant, he whistled, at which he presently came: <HI>Clarinda</HI> had been cruel∣ly bruised, all about the Head and Shoul∣ders, and receiv'd a dangerous Wound, on her Arm, with a tread of the Horse, which caused her to swound, so soon as she had been layd in <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Lap, who with both his Hands, hill'd her Head, and endeavour'd to stop the Blood which ran very fast. He was in this posture, when <HI>Mariana</HI> came full speed, who per∣ceiving the Disaster, leapt off of her Horse, and ran to <HI>Clarinda,</HI> who she found coming to her self; and who be∣gan to return thanks to <HI>Peregrine</HI> for his timely Assistance. He presently enquir'd how she found her self, which was secon∣ded by <HI>Mariana. Clarinda,</HI> not sensible then of her pain, told them, She hop'd it would be nothing, and that the fright was the most: But <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who knew better than her self, in what a Condition she was, desired that she should immedi∣ately be carried back to her Bed, and Chirurgeons sent for to take Care of her Wounds, and Bruises; she would not
<PB N="40" REF="23"/>
consent to be remov'd, till she had in∣quir'd whether <HI>Peregrine</HI> had any hurt? And what was become of the Count? He answer'd, He was perfectly well, except the grief that he conceiv'd at her disaster; she ask'd him again earnestly, What is become of the Count? You have not kill'd him, I hope? Added she, I know not what he is, Madam, replied <HI>Pere∣grine,</HI> I left him unable to persue my re∣treat. If he's in danger, replied <HI>Clarinda,</HI> there's no staying here; he has powerful Friends, that will revenge his Death: Flie <HI>Peregrine,</HI> added she, and preserve that Life, which twice has sav'd mine: This is no place for us to stay in any longer; Let us, at least, retire from the Road: And are you sure, you are not hurt? Continued she, looking on <HI>Peragrine</HI> with a passionate air. With that, not staying for his Answer, she made offer to rise, which with the aid of <HI>Peregrine,</HI> and <HI>Mariana,</HI> she perform'd: They led her into a thick Wood, which was close by, where they set her down; and she having once more inquired whether <HI>Peregrine</HI> was not hurt, and he assured her no; she related, how galloping down a Hill, her Horse had stumbl'd, flung her over his
<PB N="41" REF="23"/>
Head, and dragg'd her all along, and had undoubtedly kill'd her, had not the Heavens sent him to her Relief. <HI>Pere∣grine</HI> knew well in what danger he stay∣ed there, but could not leave his dear <HI>Cla∣rinda,</HI> all wounded as she was, which made him very Restless; she soon per∣ceiv'd it, and dreading the worst; I fear, said she, you have more cause to flie, than to stay here; 'twas my Misfortune, and your too great Rashness, has brought you into danger: Flie, Sir, to save that Life, which I must prize above my own Content. Where e'er you go, think of <HI>Clarinda,</HI> Sir; She's yours by Acquisition, The Heavens will have it so; but when you're safe, fail not to let me know where e'er you are; my Prayers to Heaven shall be to keep you safe, as safe as I shall keep you in my Thoughts. <HI>Peregrine</HI> was go∣ing to reply, but hearing a great noise of Horse passing by; and <HI>Mariana</HI> having perceiv'd some of the Count's Liveries, they guest it was in pursuit of <HI>Peregrine;</HI> he therefore had no longer time, then to kneel, take her Hand, and kiss it; Adieu sweet Angel, said he to <HI>Clarinda,</HI> Death only shall drive thee out of my Thoughts; I am, forever thine: Adieu, kind <HI>Mari∣ana,</HI>
<PB N="42" REF="24"/>
added he, supply my place in the Preservation of this fair one, I may live to return to see you both. This Farewel drew Tears from all their Eyes; he got on Horse-back, and with his Man, went to seek after the rest of his Equipage, still looking behind him, going with a slow pace, and heavy Heart, till he had lost the sight of them. He met with his other Servants, with whom he got into a cross Road, with all the speed he could.</P>
<P>Those who had pass'd by in such haste, were pursuers of <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who having found the Count, as they thought, expi∣ring, followed him, while the rest were conveying the poor Count home, in whom, they had found some signs of Life. They were running with all speed towards the Castle, where not being contented to inquire after the Stranger (whom they believ'd had done the Deed, by what they had gather'd from the Chirurgeon, who had began to suspect the Contents of those Letters he had carried,) they also search all over the Castle, but finding no∣thing, were returning home; (not know∣ing which way to go,) when they were met by <HI>Clarinda,</HI> on her Horse, support∣ed by <HI>Mariana,</HI> on one side, and by the
<PB N="43" REF="24"/>
Groom, on the other, who had follow'd as fast as he could get a Horse, and make him go; they knew her, though muffl'd up, and all in Blood; but the Business they had been about, and their rude Be∣haviour in the Castle, made them unwil∣ling to take notice of her, so they posted by, without any further notice.</P>
<P>Poor <HI>Clarinda</HI> was thus brought home, laid in her Bed, her Heart more full of Grief for <HI>Peregrine's</HI> Absence, though ne∣cessary for the safety of his Life, than her Body was of pain, by the Wounds she had receiv'd; they were soon made whole again, by the Care and Diligence of her Physicians, and Chirurgeons; but it was not so with that of her Heart, no Phy∣sician was capable of curing those Wounds which <HI>Peregrine's</HI> Dangers and Absence had made there; nothing but time, and his dear Presence, could be a fit Salve for those great Evils. As she lay pensive in her Bed, after she had been dress'd, a Servant brought in the Letter which she had found upon <HI>Peregrine's</HI> Pillow; she bid <HI>Mariana</HI> open it, and read it to her, which drew Tears from her Eyes; and this having put <HI>Mariana</HI> in mind of the Papers she had found in the morning,
<PB N="42" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="43" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="44" REF="26"/>
she pull'd them out of her Pocket, told <HI>Clarinda</HI> how she had found them, and then read as follows,</P>
<LG>
<HEAD>Verses for a Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><HI>WHile Beauteous </HI>Cloris,<HI> on the Wa∣ters lay,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Panting for Life, </HI>Damon<HI> wandred that way;</HI></L>
<L><HI>He 'spi'd, plung'd, seis'd, and to the de∣sir'd Shore,</HI></L>
<L><HI>His expiring fair Prize, in triumph bore;</HI></L>
<L><HI>But when his Purchase, he had laid,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And saw no signs of Life, he said,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Why made I not more hash, to set thee free?</HI></L>
<L><HI>Or, being too late, Why died I not with thee?</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>The charming Nymph, after some moments rest,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Gave signs, some Life still harbour'd in her Breast;</HI></L>
<L><HI>She sigh'd, she groan'd, she open'd both her Eyes,</HI></L>
<L><HI>She struggl'd hard, but yet, she could not rise,</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="45" REF="26"/>
<L><HI>Till </HI>Damon<HI> giving her some ease,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Her helpless Hand did gently cease;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Which having warm'd with Kisses, down he laid,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And cried, Heaven pity this poor dying Maid.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>At this her Eyes, which she again had clos'd,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Were lifted up; on his Breast she repos'd</HI></L>
<L><HI>Her wearied Head, look'd gashly on the Youth,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Not knowing whither 'twas a Dream, or Truth;</HI></L>
<L><HI>'Till he be sought her to declare,</HI></L>
<L><HI>How she, within her self did fare;</HI></L>
<L><HI>To which, with languid Looks, she did reply,</HI></L>
<L><HI>'Tis too late Shepheard, </HI>Cloris,<HI> now must die.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>These Words did so transpierce the poor Youth's Heart,</HI></L>
<L><HI>(Who first had wounded been with </HI>Cupid's<HI> Dart,)</HI></L>
<L><HI>That to cold Death he was resigning all,</HI></L>
<L><HI>When the fair Nymph, from Death thus did him call,</HI></L>
<L><HI><PB N="46" REF="27"/>Do not die, said she, and I'll live,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And streight her gentle hand did give;</HI></L>
<L><HI>So were they heard no longer to complain;</HI></L>
<L><HI>But liv'd to Love, and lov'd to live again.</HI></L>
</LG>
</LG>
<P>These things did but add fuel to that amorous Fire, which flam'd in the af∣flicted <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s Brest. Why were the Heavens so kind, said she, to provide so worthy a Preserver of my Life, and so cruel again, as to snatch him from me, before I could let him know the grati∣tude of my Heart! His first brave action had sufficiently engag'd me to him, with∣out being twice made beholden for my Life; but, as if that was not yet enough, to make me his Debtor beyond hopes of redemption, he also cruel proves in his passionate Expressions, and brave Perfor∣mances. <HI>Mariana,</HI> who did all she could to divert her from those Reflections, told her, that she had a great fancy to give the Verses to set, to her Master of the Lute, the next time he should come, that she might sing and play them both toge∣ther. <HI>Clarinda</HI> said, that would but in∣crease her sorrow for the absence of the Composer; yet do, continued she, since I cannot have his sweet presence, let me
<PB N="47" REF="27"/>
injoy what I can, of the Fruits of his Love; my greatest comfort, in all my afflictions is, to find he loves me. No, said she again, that is rather grief upon affliction; as circumstances are, it had been better had he prove unkind. Thus was poor <HI>Clarinda</HI> afflicting her self, and her dear <HI>Mariana</HI> comforting of her, when news were brought, her Musick-Master waited in the Parlor. <HI>Clarinda</HI> would have him sent back, saying, she was not in condition to hear Musick; but <HI>Mariana</HI> did so strongly plead, in hopes it would aid to compose her Spirits, that he was sent for up, and part of the accident that had befallen her, related to him, as it had been to the rest of the Houshold, to put a stop to their over∣curious Inquisitions. He took up her Lute, which having tun'd, he plaid on it such Lessons as vs'd to delight her most; but she seem'd not to hearken to them. Ask of <HI>Mariana</HI> the Verses which she began to read; then returning them to her again, there, said she, do what you will with them. <HI>Mariana</HI> taking this as a <HI>tacit</HI> consent, to what she had propos'd, shew'd them to the Musick-Master, and desir'd him to set them to a Tune, so as that they
<PB N="48" REF="28"/>
might be sung, and play'd upon the Lute; he promised so to do, and to bring them with him the next day; and having play'd two or three Tunes more, he took his leave, and retired.</P>
<P>Then had <HI>Mariana</HI> leasure, and not before, to unfold the other Paper which she had taken up; but she found it writ∣ten in a Language she did not understand. Here is, I know not what, said she to <HI>Clarinda,</HI> giving her the Paper; (which was that Letter which <HI>Peregrine</HI> received from that Lady I mentioned before, the day before he left <HI>England:) Clarinda</HI> was as far to seek, as <HI>Mariana;</HI> she fancied it to be a Woman's hand, and was con∣firm'd in that Opinion, so soon as she had read at the bottom of it, the word <HI>Isabella;</HI> her Heart started at it, as a pre∣sage of the sorrows which it would cause her; she dreaded the contents, yet was impatient to know them; she doubted not but this was a Letter to him from some <HI>English</HI> Woman, writ in that Lan∣guage, and therefore was the less in hopes of having it decyphered: they both beat their Heads very much about it, but to no purpose; 'till at last it came into <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI>'s mind, that she had heard her old
<PB N="49" REF="28"/>
Aunt say, That presently upon the death of her Husband, who had died at <HI>Lon∣don,</HI> she had been forc'd to go thither, to recover some considerable Sums of Mony, that were due to her Husband, which she could not recover but by long and costly Suits at Law, which had caus'd her to remain in that Kingdom, near two years, in which time, she had got some imper∣fect knowledge of that Language. <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI> sent <HI>Mariana</HI> immediately with the Letter to her Aunt, to desire her that she would Translate it for her, as well as she could possible. The old Gentlewo∣man was very unwilling to undertake such a Task, pleading her long discon∣tinuance in that Tongue; but being over∣persuaded by her Neice's, and <HI>Mariana</HI>'s Importunities, she writ out of it that which follows, pick'd out here and there, as well as she could gather it, without any coherence.</P>
<LETTER>
<P>The despair of ever seen you more, has—my Passion was too great, not to be—to bestow on others, that which by my—so Cruel to one, who never—but in loving you—my
<PB N="50" REF="29"/>
Death a salve to all—Peregrine hear—of the unfortunate</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Isabella.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P>The old Lady had required time, 'till Night, for the unravelling of those My∣steries, which <HI>Mariana</HI> was forc'd to al∣low her, but through <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s Impa∣tience she was frequently interrupted by <HI>Mariana,</HI> which caus'd the old Lady to lock her self up, 'till she had done, to a∣void any further Disturbance; at last, the Business was Accomplish'd, as well as could be done by her, and <HI>Mariana</HI> cal∣led up, to whom it was delivered, not without being ask'd by the old Gentlewo∣man, how she had come by that Letter, adding that that was all she could make of it▪ <HI>Mariana,</HI> told her she had found it by chance, so run down immediately to shew it to the impatient <HI>Clarinda.</HI></P>
<P>Heavens, What do I see? Said <HI>Clarinda,</HI> after she had read a little. How's this? Cried she again, reading on; What read I more? Continued she, here is his Name, and that also of that unfortunate Wo∣man, whom he has render'd Miserable; See, see <HI>Mariana,</HI> continued she, <HI>Pere∣grine</HI>
<PB N="51" REF="29"/>
is false; Oh Heavens! What will become of me? <HI>Mariana,</HI> having read <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, said, I perceive a complaint made by one <HI>Isabella;</HI> at <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s depart, she <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eems to tax him with cruelty, and owns <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he loves him, but in all this, I do not find that she calls him Unconstant, Infi∣del, Perjur'd, Deceitful, or the like: No, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eplied <HI>Clarinda,</HI> but all that, and a great deal more does follow. Those Inferences may easily be drawn from what I have seen; Oh! Unfortunate <HI>Clarinda,</HI> and False <HI>Peregrine;</HI> with that she gave her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elf over to Unconsolable Grief. <HI>Mari∣ana</HI> did all she could to comfort her, but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll in vain, she represented to her, that though all was true which she but surmi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed at most; yet, this was before he had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>een her, and that she believ'd the very Heavens had contributed by strange Ac∣cidents to make him constant to her. A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alse Man minds not Heaven, answered <HI>Clarinda,</HI> Oh! that I had seen but this before he had gone, I had commanded him never more to see my Face. In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hort, <HI>Clarinda</HI> was in such a fury, that <HI>Mariana</HI> thought it Prudence, not to in∣sist any longer on <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Justification, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t that present, but rather to divert her
<PB N="52" REF="30"/>
from the Thoughts of him, by raising of some other Discourse, not questioning but that in time <HI>Peregrine</HI> would be able to justifie himself; for <HI>Mariana</HI> had en∣tertained so good an Opinion of him, that she would believe all things else, ra∣ther than that he should be false. The Messenger, which <HI>Clarinda</HI> had sent to her Father at <HI>Mentz,</HI> being just at that time return'd, he brought her the sad News of her Father's desperate Illness. This Addition of Grief, made her resolve to leave the Castle, that place which had lately prov'd so fatal to her, and to go and tend her Father in the Town of <HI>Mentz,</HI> without any further Desires to hear of <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s safe Retreat. She be∣gan from that time, to gather all that she thought convenient to carry with her, as Money, Plate, and Jewels, the rather to, because the Servant had told her that there was great Apprehensions in <HI>Mentz,</HI> of the Confederate Troops speedy Approach∣es, and that no doubt they would ravage the Country: Wherefore, partly her own safety, and partly in a dispair, she took that Resolution, designing to put in Ex∣ecution, with the earliest haste, and to leave <HI>Mariana,</HI> in the Castle, to attend
<PB N="53" REF="30"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er old Aunt, who kept continually Cloi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter'd up in her Chamber, and to send <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er News, by some means or other, of that Perfidious Man, in Case she had any to send, that she might inform him, she now knew him: This was a hard Pill for <HI>Ma∣riana</HI> to swallow, but finding she might <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o <HI>Peregrine</HI> a great piece of Service, in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ending <HI>Clarinda</HI> News of him, from whom she did not question but to hear, so soon as he was got in a place of security; she consented to <HI>Clarindas</HI> request.</P>
<P>The earnest Desires <HI>Clarinda</HI> had to be gone, hastened in some measure her Cure; so that the third day, after her Disaster, she was fit to get on Horse back; but ha∣ving been further informed that all the Roads were full of the Confederate's For∣ces, she thought it would be dangerous for her to adventure in her own Aparel, for fear of being met by some rude party▪ she therefore put on one of her Brother's Suits, assuming his Name, and being fit∣ted with all things else, to make her a compleat Cavalier; she set forward in the close of the Evening, with three of her Men Servants, designing to be so near <HI>Mentz</HI> by Morning, that the Confeder∣ates should not prevent her getting in▪</P>
<P><PB N="54" REF="31"/>Fortune did so favour her Enterprise, that by the next Morning, she got safe in∣to <HI>Montz,</HI> but it was not without riding very hard, having been pursued for two Miles, even to the very Gates of the Town; there (for Addition to her Grief) she learnt the Death of her Father, and that he had been buried the day before her coming: Those who had seen the Servant that had been sent before, retur∣ning with her, who now went under the Notion of <HI>Frederick,</HI> (which was her Brother's Name,) and Son and Air to the Deceased, did not in the least que∣stion the truth thereof; wherefore, they delivered to <HI>Frederick,</HI> all that his Fa∣ther had left; but he disliking his Lodg∣ings, he took one up in a more convenient place, and presently sent back all three of his Servants, giving them charge to put his dear <HI>Mariana</HI> in mind, of what she had promised to do.</P>
<P><HI>Peregrine,</HI> mean time, as he was ma∣king his escape, fell into a Party of the Consederates, who took him Prisoner, and brought him where he was most de∣sirous to be, in the Absence of his charm∣ing <HI>Clarinda.</HI> He presently made inquiry after his worthy Friend, Count <HI>Zinzerdorf,</HI>
<PB N="55" REF="31"/>
and was not long after brought to his Quar∣ters, where he was receiv'd with all the Caresses imaginable. He came into the Camp, about the beginning of <HI>July,</HI> ha∣ving been taken by a Party of Foot, the Evening before, who were Convey to the Baggage and Artillary. The Camp being on one Line, and the Regiments of Horse and Foot being intermix'd, it was late the next Morning, before he was sur∣render'd into the Count's Hands. He being thus safe, his next Care was to give notice to <HI>Clarinda</HI> of his safety, which he conceiv'd in these Terms.</P>
<LETTER>
<P>If there was any perfect felicity to be had, where the charming <HI>Clarinda</HI> is not, I might think my self not far from attaining it. I am with my Friends, in an Army that fronts, and threatens the Enemy's De∣struction; and I have that particular and vast Advantage over the rest, of having you, Madam, for my Guardian Angel; but when I reflect on the Condition, in which my hard Fate, forc'd me to leave you; especi∣ally, considering that I am to place all your Misfortunes on the account of my perverse Stars, all my great prospect of Contented∣ness is reduc'd into a black Cloud of Dispair;
<PB N="56" REF="32"/>
I earnestly intreat the most obliging <HI>Maria∣na</HI> to let me know whether I stand for Life or Death, for both depend so absolutely upon <HI>Clarindas</HI> State, that according to my In∣formation, I am prepared to live, or die an eternal Votary to that fair Saint.</P>
</LETTER>
<P>With this Letter he dispatch'd one of his Servants, who spoke <HI>German,</HI> to con∣vey it to the Castle, and got a Pass that he might not be hindred in his going or co∣ming back. This Messenger, who was his Groom, made a shift to loose himself, in the dark of the Evening, betwixt the Camp and the Town, in a Vale, near a Mill, where some of the Army of <HI>Loraine</HI> had orders to post themselves. This made the Groom to avoid them (not knowing who they were) to get betwixt them and the Town, with a Design, so soon as any light did appear, never so little, to get from amongst them as fast as ever he could, and so inquire out the way to the Castle: But he fail'd in his Measures, for the <HI>French</HI> sallied out, which gave an ala∣rum to the <HI>Germans,</HI> who soon drove back the Salliers, who took but one Man Prisoner, that prov'd to be <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Groom. He was brought into the Town,
<PB N="57" REF="32"/>
and some would have made him pass for a Spie, but that the Fellow had so much wit as to call himself a Deserter, who being sent with a Letter, from a Gentle∣man, came but the day before into the Camp, of the Confederates, to a Lady that liv'd in a Castle, about a days Jour∣ney from thence, he had taken that op∣portunity of escaping into the Town, and that he was waiting for some opportunity of doing so, when he was luckily brought in; this and the Fellow's Readiness to pro∣duce the Letter, soon gain'd Credit, so that he was releas'd, and the Letter, after read, return'd to him.</P>
<P>Amongst those who were present at the Fellow's Examination; a person who li¦ved in the same House where <HI>Frederick</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay, had been a Spectator, and being ask'd, at his return, what news from the Party that had sallied out that Night, he said, they had lost three or four Men, but had got but one Prisoner, who it seems was a Deserter, then he told them the whole Story; this having been related just by <HI>Frederick</HI>'s Chamber Door, so that he had over heard all; he began to fancy, that he might be something concern'd in this Business more than ordinary; he there∣fore
<PB N="58" REF="33"/>
inquir'd, where he might see this De∣serter, and what Livery he had on? But could learn neither, he only was offer'd by the Fellow to go seek after him, and bring him to him, if he would consider him for his pains; <HI>Frederick</HI> having pro∣mis'd the Fellow a good reward, and gi∣ven him a small advance, he went his ways to seek after <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Groom, who he found about some two Hours after drinking with some Soldiers; but he scarce knew him again, because the Soldiers had taken the pains to ease him of his upward Garment, which was <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Livery. But hearing him say that the Lady must excuse him, if he made bold to light his Pipe, with some of these Compliments which his Master sent to her; that made the Fellow confident it was the same Per∣son, he stopt his Hand, and told him there was a young Gentleman, in the Town, that had something to say to him: The Groom presently put up the Letter again, with his Pipe, and said, he was ready to follow him, desiring his Com∣rades to forbare drinking the rest of his Coat, 'till he return'd to have his share of it; with that he follow'd his Guide, who soon brought him to <HI>Frederick.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="59" REF="33"/>The Groom having never seen <HI>Frede∣rick</HI> before, no not in his former Aparel, nor <HI>Frederick</HI> him; he was oblig'd to in∣terogate him the more strictly, and the Groom gave <HI>Frederick</HI> such satisfactory Answers, that when he was presented with the open Letter, all rompl'd, he soon knew the Character, and remained well satisfied of the truth of all the rest; he gratifi'd both the Fellows, and bid the Groom come to him the next day, then he retir'd to his own Chamber, to read with the greater leisure, and privacy, that which he thought most concerned him in this World; he could not but reflect at Fortune's figaries, who had mis-lead this Fellow, by which means he had come the sooner to hear of that false Man, to whom he was resolv'd to send a severe Epistle. <HI>Frederick</HI> read, but did not; kiss'd those Lines which <HI>Peregrine</HI> had writ, an Hundred times over, as he had done before, when he was still <HI>Clarinda,</HI> and finding so much Passion in them, he thought he could not dispute them too much. He was impatient of the Groom's return, that he might further examine him, and find whither he might intrust him with his Designs; in the mean time,
<PB N="60" REF="34"/>
he busied himself in reading all <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Writings; after which, he took his Lute, Play'd and Song to it those Verses, which his Musick-Master had given him, that same day he had set forth for <HI>Mentz,</HI> which he had got very perfect, with re∣peating them continually, as he daily did, but not with that pleasure he had former∣ly done. Of Truth, this had been the greatest of his Diversion ever since his coming to that place, where he had liv'd retire, without any Communication even at his Meals, so that he passed under the Notion of the Woman hater, because there were divers Gentlewomen in the same House, Boarders, whose Company <HI>Frederick</HI> did avoid, as if they had had the Plague; and when any one came to make his Bed, or clean his Chamber, he would all that time retire into a Closet, at the further end of his Chamber, which contained all his Trunks, Boxes and Chests, and where he would frequently retire to play on the Lute, or to medi∣tate on those Writings once so precious to him, that he might still be the less heard, and thought on. There he be∣gan to think in what perplexities <HI>Pere∣grine</HI> would have been in, had he been
<PB N="61" REF="34"/>
true, at his not hearing any News from him, which made him think the time very long before the Groom's return, who at last came. <HI>Frederick</HI> brought him in∣to his Closet; after he had shut the Cham∣ber Door, where he examin'd so closly the Groom, that he confest to him, he had pretended to be a Deserter, when he had been taken by the Enemy, only that he might have the better opportunity to get to that Castle, where they had been made so much on by the good Lady of that place, on his Masters Account, he was sure; for he had heard his Fellow-Servants, who were oftner within Door, than he, whose whole Business was in the Stable, talk strange things of them: And do they believe, said <HI>Frederick,</HI> that your Master does really Love that Gentlewo∣man? Love her, answered the Groom, doats upon her, ay, and will e'en run statk-staring Mad for her, to, it's believ'd; for a does neither eat, drink, nor sleep; but all Night he's a sighing and sobbing, as if his own Hearts Blood and Guts, would burst asunder: By'r Lady, I could not live so, for my part, continued he. Well, honest Friend, replied <HI>Frederick,</HI> since thou hast been so faithful to thy Master,
<PB N="62" REF="35"/>
and dost design to continue so, here is to encourage thee to go on, in serving him truly; and now I will tell thee that I am nearly related to that Lady, to whom thou were going with the Letter, and that if thou wilt venture to carry back a Letter to thy Master, I shall reward thee well for thy pains: Odds-buds, Master, answered the honest blunt Groom, I did fancy so much so soon as I saw you, though I never saw her, and might my Girdle never hold, if I do not venture my Whi∣zle, at any time for any of you Three; trie me else, continued he, do ye but con∣trive, and drive me forwards, and trie if I don't go. This hearty proffer from so blunt a Fellow, could not but highly please <HI>Frederick,</HI> who resolved to take this opportunity to make a Trial of <HI>Pere∣grine</HI>'s Constancy, beginning to hearken to his Love, who very much inclined him to clear <HI>Peregrine</HI> in his Thoughts, ever since he had, without passion or prejudice read over and over, those broken Frag∣ments which did pretend a passionate Love, from the Woman, but no Perfi∣diousness in the Man, who after all might never have lov'd her. However, he was resolved to put <HI>Peregrine</HI> on very se∣vere
<PB N="63" REF="35"/>
Trials, that should throughly con∣firm him of his constancy towards him, before he would admit him again, to the same place, he before that discovery pos∣sess'd in his Heart; to that purpose, <HI>Fre∣derick</HI> resolv'd to conceal himself, under the Character of a Friend of the Counts, and in that Humour, writ the following Lines.</P>
<LETTER>
<P>If all the Men in your Armies were as expert as you are, at killing of both Sexes, we should have reason not to fear for our selves only, but for our Wives and Daugh∣ters also; you are not contented with those Murthers which you have committed at home, but wearied there, with Blood, you are come to exercise your Talient amongst us, also; we have had but too woful Examples of it, in the late unfortunate Count <HI>Mans∣fielt,</HI> and since that, in the much to be la∣mented <HI>Clarinda,</HI> whose knowledg of your Domestick Perfidiousness, has untimely snatched away from us. As a Friend to both these, I declare my self your Mortal Enemy, who will never have quiet till I have washed, with your Blood, those stains which must render you odious to all Mankind.</P>
</LETTER>
<P><PB N="62" REF="36"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="63" REF="36"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>

<PB N="64" REF="37"/>
This short but smart Epistle being seal'd up, he gave it without Superscription to the Groom, with some Gold, and bid him to get himself in a Readiness, to Sal∣ly out the next Night with a Party that was appointed to that purpose, and gave him one of the Soldier's Coats to conceal himself under, which he might well e∣nough do in the dark; then giving him an handful of Silver, he thus dismissed him.</P>
<P>The following Night, the Garrison made four false Sallies, in one of which, the trusty Groom made a shift to get out of the Town, and return to his Master, to whom, having given the Letter, he related all that had happened to him since his Absence. You may imagine into what surprising terrour, a Letter so fill'd with horrour, did put him; he was for a long time mute, and as stiff as a Stake, without the least Motion, out of which he suddainly starred, asking the Groom if he had brought him e're a Letter? There 'tis in your hand, said the Fellow, Thou liest, Villain, replied distracted <HI>Peregrine;</HI> then looking on the Letter, See, added he, Is this directed to me? Holding it to the poor trembling Fellow;
<PB N="65" REF="37"/>
Alack, Sir, I cannot read, not I, said the Groom, but I am sure that he who gave it me, bid me to deliver it into your own hands. Why, who am I, Dog? Said poor <HI>Peregrine;</HI> my Master, Sir, I think, answered the Fellow, but I think strange∣ly chang'd. I'll go ask what is the mat∣ter, added he, with that he slipt out of the Chamber, and left <HI>Peregrine</HI> alone, to descant upon that severe Letter, where we will leave him for some small space, to inform you of what was become of the Count, and of <HI>Mariana.</HI></P>
<P>As for the Count he had been so care∣fully look'd after, that he was perfectly recovered of his Wound, but not of that extream Weakness, which that vast quan∣tity of Blood he had lost, had brought upon him; he, and his Friends, were re∣solved not to give over that Business so, but to have a full revenge, so soon as they could but hear where <HI>Peregrine</HI> was retired; to that purpose, they had made all the inquiries they could possible, from the Servants at the Castle; as also, of the Chirurgeon. They had learnt, that he was an <HI>English</HI> Man, <HI>Peregrine</HI> by Name, that he design'd to pass the Campaign, in the Confederates Army, and they belie∣ved,
<PB N="66" REF="38"/>
that without doubt, he was retired there; but they would not attempt any thing against him, to the prejudice of the Count's Honour; wherefore, they but staid till the Count was in Condition to call <HI>Peregrine</HI> to an Account himself.</P>
<P>As for <HI>Mariana,</HI> she had been so afrigh∣ted, and the old Lady also, by a Party from the Confederates, who had com∣mitted a world of Rudeness, that they were retired, Servants and all, to a place Twenty Miles off of the Castle; <HI>Mariana</HI> having concluded that it would be as im∣possible to send any News to <HI>Clarinda,</HI> as she fear'd <HI>Peregrine</HI> had found it difficult to send to her, at the Castle; she still con∣tinuing in that Confidence, she had of <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI>'s Virtues; wherefore, was willing to attribute his silence, to any other Cause than his Inconstancy.</P>
<P>Things were at that pass, amongst the Lovers Conserns, when that the Confe∣derate's Army had made their Approaches, very near to the Town, at 450 Paces from the Counterscarp, where the Saxons, (a∣mongst which, <HI>Peregrine</HI> was a Volun∣tiere) had taken their Post, on which the Enemy did Fire continually all that day; and one of their Shot, out of a Falcon,
<PB N="67" REF="38"/>
unfortunately killed, the Prince Palatine, <HI>Frederick William,</HI> who was come, as a Voluntiere, in the Camp; and was, that day, with <HI>Peregrine,</HI> at the head of the <HI>French;</HI> where, also, were the Prince Elector, his Brother, and the Grand Ma∣ster of the Tutonick Order. The Body of that unfortunate Prince was carried to <HI>Francfort,</HI> there to be embalmed.</P>
<P><HI>Peregrine,</HI> who notwithstanding all his Afflictions and Grief, would not let pass any opportunity of shewing that he was not come so far only to see, and to be seen, did not omit this occasion of wait∣ing on the Prince, at the head of the <HI>French,</HI> but did wish, a thousand times, that the Bullet had met with his Head, in liew of the Princes; since he had recei∣ved that fatal Letter, there had not been any dangerous Enterprise, but he had been in it, with a purpose Design of not out-living his dear <HI>Clarinda,</HI> whom he concluded Dead, of which, he counted himself the Cause; but still he did come off with Honour, his better Fortune reser∣ving him to injoy his Hearts Desires: How often did he call himself negligent Fool, for not having burnt that fatal <HI>En∣glish</HI> Letter, to which he attributed all
<PB N="68" REF="39"/>
his Misfortunes, as was intimated, in that which he had received, from an unknown Hand? He was resolved, with the first opportunity, to get into the Town, to inform himself, more at large, and to find out that unknown Person, who had been so severe in his Censure of him. That, of Truth, had been the Occasion of his going on all Parties; but, as yet, he had not met with any opportunity, of accomplishing his Design, which still did distract him more, and more, in so much, that his Friends, and especially, the Count <HI>Zinzendorf,</HI> had divers times inquired what was the matter with him? What Cause of Discontent he had had, which appeared so visibly in his Countenance? And that made him so desperately throw himself into all kind of Dangers? Desi∣ring him to manage himself a little better? But to all these Interrogatories, and Ad∣vices, he would make no Answer, nor give his Friends (who were really high∣ly concerned for him) any Satisfaction, so that they were forced to let him take his own Course, giving him over for a lost Man. He still continued deaf, to all their Advices; and he, most impatiently, watch'd for an opportunity of deserting,
<PB N="69" REF="39"/>
with a Resolution, in case he found <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI> gone, to throw himself head long, amongst the Enemies, and there be sacri∣ficed, a Victim to her Memory.</P>
<P><HI>Clarinda,</HI> or <HI>Frederick,</HI> rather, on the other hand, had a thousand times wish'd he had not sent so severe a Letter, which he feared would produce <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s death, his Innocence daily getting ground over <HI>Frederick</HI>'s Indignation; at last, not hear∣ing from him, it brought <HI>Frederick</HI> into such an impatiency, that he could no long∣er rest, without learning something of his once so dearly beloved Preserver; he had been brought into that violent desire by the frequent Reflections he had made, on <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Bravery; concluding with himself, that it was impossible so gallant a Person, who had done so much for him, could be guilty of so horrid a Crime, as he had taxed him with, in his Passion: He had tried all means imaginable to send some body to him, but had found it im∣possible, which had made him take up the brave Resolution to join in the next Party that should go out, and to get over to the Army, or perish in the attempt. To accomplish this, he went a Voluntiere, and joined himself to the Horse-Guard,
<PB N="70" REF="40"/>
that the Town had sent forth to front that of the Confederates; and there being no other Action, on that time, on the Con∣federates side; <HI>Peregrine,</HI> rather then do nothing at all, was got amongst their Horse Guard. Towards Night, there were some Pickeerings, in which divers were killed, on both side, amongst which was one <HI>D' Andlau,</HI> Captain in <HI>Palfe</HI>'s Regiment, and divers made Prisoners, on both sides, amongst which, <HI>Frederick</HI> was the best pleased.</P>
<P>It proved luckily for <HI>Frederick,</HI> that he was the Prisoner of one of <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s in∣timate Friends. For this Gentleman, ha∣ving not heard what was become of <HI>Pe∣regrine,</HI> had sent to inquire after him; News was brought that he was supposed to be killed, for his Horse was found dead, which was known again by his own Groom, but his Body was not yet to be found; so it was concluded, that he had quitted his Horse, and having fought on Foot, and that he might be dropt amongst the Enemies. This hav∣ing been told in the presence of <HI>Frederick,</HI> it caused such a suddain change in him, that notice was taken of it; and presently after, he retired into that Room which
<PB N="71" REF="40"/>
had been allotted for him (for his Ran∣som had already been set to an hundred Pistols, to which he had readily agreed,) where having flung himself upon a Couch, he gave way to all that passion could move in a sensible Breast. He called himself, a thousand times, a Murtherer, in having writ that cruel Letter, which doubtless, was the cause of his becoming so Careless of his Life, as he was reported to be; some Servants having taken notice of this great passion, in the young Priso∣ner, they went and acquainted the Offi∣cer with it, who, coming near to the Tent Door, heard <HI>Frederick</HI> say, unfor∣tunate Woman. The Officer entered hastily, and going to the Bed, What Wo∣man do you mean? Said he, And what is the cause of that great Passion you have fallen into, since the News of my wor∣thy Friend's Death?</P>
<P><HI>Frederick</HI> thought himself now abso∣lutely ruin'd, and remained silent for a considerable time, not knowing what to say. This made the Officer to add, were you acquainted with him? If so, let me know it? If he was a Friend of yours, I assure you, you shall fare the better for it? <HI>Frederick,</HI> that desired no
<PB N="72" REF="41"/>
longer to live, now he thought <HI>Peregrine</HI> was dead; with a design to urge the Of∣ficer to do him some Mischief, thus an∣swered, If you was <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Friend, you can not do his Memory a greater piece of Service, than to Sacrifice me to it? For, I declare, I was his mortal Enemy, that I writ to him a Letter, which put him into that Dispair, which made him so little to manage his Life, to which I add, that I let my self be taken Prisoner, (as the posture I was found in, might ea∣sily shew), being alighted, and amongst your own Party, that I might have his Blood, for having been the Death of a Gentlewoman to whom I am related. Now, Sir, continued he, If you have any respect for your Friend's memory, do what he himself would have done to me, or I had been his Executioner? And seeing the Officer stand as amazed, he ad∣ded, If it is the loss of my Ransome, de∣tains you from doing that piece of Justice, to your Friend, here is that which will be worth better than an 100 Pistols to you? And with that drew a Jewel out of his Bosome, which he presented to the Officer, but he refused it; and being still more and more surprised, at these strange
<PB N="73" REF="41"/>
things, knew not what to think, and af∣ter he had remained a little silent, he thus said, I know not, Young Man, what to think of you; I find you are in a kind of Despair, which makes you seek for relief, in Death, but I am not a Person to take Advantage of any-one's Misfortunes. I do not know but that my Friend may have been taken Prisoner, seeing, that though his Horse has been found slain, his body has not been yet discovered; where∣fore, I would have you manage your self, till we have a certainty of the matter; not doubting, but that if my Friend lives, he will give you all the Satisfaction that you can receive from a gallant Person: forbear but speaking ill of my worthy Friend, and injoy here all the conveni∣encies that my Quarters will afford; I will leave you to your self, a dieu, with that the Officer went out of the Tent.</P>
<P>Thus was the poor afflicted <HI>Frederick</HI> left, a Prev to all his Sorrows, with the only small glimpse, which <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Friend had left him, by saying, he might be made a Prisoner; <HI>Frederick,</HI> resolv'd to know the truth of it, out of hand, by escaping into the City, though with the hazard of his Life; with a firm Resolu∣tion,
<PB N="74" REF="42"/>
to die, if he found not <HI>Peregrine</HI> there a live; he began to be extraordinary sen∣sible of the evil Effects of his Rashness, in sending that fatal Letter, which had been the certain cause of all the Evils that followed upon it, so accounted himself the Murtherer of him, who had twice pre∣served his Life, and whom he now veri∣ly believed to be true, and constant, by the strange effects which those cursed Lines had wrought in him, which made him so carelessly to prostitute his Life, in the greatest dangers, as believing it not worth preserving, after the loss of his <HI>Cla∣rinda;</HI> thus did <HI>Frederick</HI>'s Bosome de∣clare in favour of the unfortunate <HI>Pere∣grine,</HI> which made him to conclude to kill himself, if he found him not in <HI>Mentz,</HI> designing to get thither the next Night, or to die in the attempt; but the Heavens had ordained otherwise of him, as I am going to relate.</P>
<P>The Confederates did throw abundance of Bombs, every Night, into the City, which fired many Houses; that in which poor wounded Prisoners lay, having been set on Fire, they were forced to be removed, as fast as they could, and they put a wounded Gentleman into a Cham∣ber,
<PB N="75" REF="42"/>
at the very next House, which pro∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed to be in <HI>Frederick</HI>'s own Chamber, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill they had found some other conveni∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ncy for him. <HI>Frederick</HI> having given <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut, when he left his Lodgings, that he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hould not return in three or four days, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecause he was to go to the other end of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Town, about earnest business; he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad taken the Key of his large Closet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith him, but had left his Chamber <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oor open; and this Fire happening in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Night, they had carried the wounded Gentleman in there, as being nearest at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and, with a design to remove him a∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ain, so soon as the owner of the Cham∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er should return. That Night divers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eserters got into the Town, and <HI>Frede∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ick</HI> heard that two or three <HI>French</HI> Offi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs had gotten in at noon day, that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ave him hopes of having as good a suc∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ess in his attempt; in these hopes he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alks out to take a little Air, as he pre∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ended, but it was to observe which way <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e should attempt to put in Execution his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esign.</P>
<P>As he was thus walking pensive alone, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> perceived a small Party, riding up to∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ards him; he, who had no mind to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en, stept a little out of the way, that
<PB N="76" REF="43"/>
they might pass him unregarded; but, as the company▪ was got close to him, he thought he knew one of their Voices, he looked suddainly up, and perceiving that it was Count <HI>Mansfeilt,</HI> he presently tur∣ned his Head another way, and observed which way they were marching, and saw them go into that Tent which be∣longed to the Officer that had taken him. The Count being now perfectly recover∣ed of his Wounds, and Weakness, and having learnt where <HI>Peregrine</HI> was enter∣tained, had been with his Kinsman, Count <HI>Zinzendorf,</HI> to demand Justice of him, against a Stranger, who had wrong∣ed him, and taken something from him, whom he protected. The Count, who was related to <HI>Mansfeilt,</HI> received him very Courteously, and assured him of all the Services that lay in his power; but told him, withal, that he had had so ma∣ny Proofs of that Gentleman's bravery, and generous Temper, whom he accus'd, that none but his Kinsman could suspect, without offending him; that he hoped he was mistaken in the Person, and that to be satisfied in that, he himself would conduct his Kinsman, to his Friends Quar∣ters, having not heard of him in two
<PB N="77" REF="43"/>
days: They were going to seek after <HI>Pe∣regrine,</HI> when <HI>Frederick</HI> did take notice of them. It enter'd into <HI>Frederick</HI>'s Head, that the Count came not there for any good to <HI>Peregrine,</HI> which made him (though <HI>Peregrine</HI> was far from thence, if he was at all) to have a Desire of knowing the nature of the Count's Busi∣ness. He therefore walks back, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ly af∣ter, and getting in by the back way of the Tent, waited to hear what would be said.</P>
<P>He had looked on the young Count, as the first Cause of all his, and of <HI>Pere∣grine</HI>'s Misfortunes, and even of his Death, if he was slain: This had bred such an hatred in his Breast, rowards the Count, that he wished he could be the Death of him; wherefore, very far from ever receiving him into Favour again. Being thus prepossest, he heard the Officer re∣late how <HI>Peregrine</HI> had been lost, and that he had a young Prisoner, who he had taken that Night, that had declared he had permitted himself to be taken, but to be brought where <HI>Peregrine</HI> was, that he might kill him, for being the Death of a Kinswoman of his. He is very desperate, added the Officer, and
<PB N="78" REF="44"/>
Careless of his Life, expresses much Cou∣rage, though very young. Upon this, the Count said, That it was not he alone who complained of <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Unwor∣thiness; and that besides that Gentlewo∣man, for whose Death he was accused, he believed, that the Death of another Lady might be laid to his Charge also, of whom no News was to be had, and who doubtless he had made away, it may be, after he had had his Pleasure of her. Here, <HI>Frederick</HI> could not any long∣er forbear, but rushing into the Tent, a∣dressed himself to the Count, with a stern Countenance, and his Hand upon his Sword. Thou liest Count, cried he, a∣loud, in the Relation thou givest of <HI>Pere∣grine,</HI> and because he is not here to ju∣stifie himself of those base and false Ac∣cusations, I come to vindicate him in the presence of all these; therefore draw, added he, and with that, drew his Sword, and run at the Count: The Count had but time to draw, and making a pass, gave a slight Wound to <HI>Frederick</HI>'s Hand, and disarmed him, before any could come into them. They were parted, and <HI>Fre∣derick</HI> put out of the Tent, and every Body remained in a maze, at the rash,
<PB N="79" REF="44"/>
and desperate Actions, of so young a Youth; but, above all, the Officer was strangely surprised to see one who had declar'd was come to kill <HI>Peregrine,</HI> e∣spouse, with so much fierceness, his Inte∣rest, in so rashly exposing his Life to main∣tain <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Reputation.</P>
<P>Mean time, <HI>Frederick</HI> was glad he had been put out, before he had been disco∣vered by any there; and for fear of being called to an account, for this Action, be∣fore the Count, who might, at last, know him, he went his way, telling some Ser∣vants, he met, that he was going to seek some Chirurgeon to dress his Hand. Of Truth, the Count began to entertain some Ideas of that Face, which persuaded him he had seen it somewhere before; and up∣on that he had desired that Person should be brought in again, that he might have a more full view of him; but he was gone, and was not found by any at that time. All this did still breed more Suspi∣tion in the Count, and Wonders in the Beholders; he, at last, with pondring much upon the knowledge of that Face, did really conclude, that this was none but <HI>Clarinda,</HI> in a Disguise; but, on what account, could not imagine; he had but
<PB N="80" REF="45"/>
too well found that <HI>Peregrine</HI> had render∣ed himself absolute Master of <HI>Clarindas</HI> Heart, he fear'd, beyond all the Art he had to reclaim it again; yet, he was loth to absolutely give over the pursute; he found he still had the same Love and Affection for her, but had great reason to believe she hated him, witness her late Action; in this Agitation of Spirit, he knew not what to resolve, nor indeed, what to say to his Friends: He thought that if he could but once more set his Eye upon her, he would haunt her Day and Night, rather than not receive some fa∣vourable answer from her: In this Reso∣lution, he takes his leave of Count <HI>Zinzen∣dorf,</HI> and of the other Officer, and with those Friends that he had brought along with him, returns, with a design to se∣parate, and all go in search after her, se∣veral ways, and in case <HI>Peregrine</HI> was dead (as it was believed) never to aban∣don her, till he had gained her good Will; but in case he should still be living, either to kill, or be killed, by him, finding it impossible for him to live, without the Possession of <HI>Clarinda.</HI> He thus sent his Friends several ways to seek her, amongst her own Relations, and at the Castle, but
<PB N="81" REF="45"/>
reserves to himself, to search the whole Camp after her.</P>
<P><HI>Frederick</HI> having got as far as the <HI>Lor∣rain</HI> Attack, he perceived a <HI>French</HI> Party, of about 400 Foot, that appeared within a mile of the Trenches, he designed, at first, to have run amongst them, but they presently disappeared again, so remain'd frustrated of that design; some time after, it rained very hard, which made <HI>Frede∣risk</HI> to seek for some shelter; as he was so doing, he perceived a Woman, at some distance, that crept on all four, whom he concluded to be some Spie, or some Carrier of Intelligence; he, after the same manner, got to her, before she had espi∣ed him; when, finding it was too late for her to endeavour her escape, she tur∣ned towards him, fell on her Knees, and besought him to spare her Life, promising that she would never more stir out of the Town; this she did, believing verily that she was discovered to be a Spie, and that <HI>Frederick</HI> had come that way, and had ventured so near the Shot of the Town, but to seize on her. Some few Shots, in∣deed, were made at them, while <HI>Frede∣rick</HI> bid her not to fear, that he would do her no hurt. So soon as she had his pro∣mise,
<PB N="82" REF="46"/>
she called to a black Dog of hers, that was not far from thence, which be∣ing perceived by those on the Ramparts, that had Shot at them before, they pre∣sently ceased firing. <HI>Frederick</HI> asked the Woman how he might get into the Town, she judging, by that, that he was some Deserter, plucked up a good Heart, and told him, that if he pleased to have patience a while, he should see her get in, and-that he might after do the like, if he pleased; all this time they being got into a little hollow, that covered them from the Camp, though not from the Town; she told him that she had used this Trade daily, ever since the Town had been Besieged, and that she had ne∣ver been surprised; that in case she should be at any time taken, that nothing might be found about her, that could prejudice her, she roll'd up her Intelligence, in a piece of Parchment, and put that Parch∣ment in a piece of Gut, which she gave to her Dog to carry, and that he had been used to follow her, at a great distance; that when she came near the Gate, she would slip her self into her little H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, that was close by the Centry, by the back Door, and open the fore Door, in which
<PB N="83" REF="46"/>
her Dog would come; that so soon as he was got in, she would lock him up, feed him well, and then would go, and deli∣ver her Intelligence to the Governour; and that, by so doing, she had got the Character of being a Witch, that used to go in, and out of the Town, in the shape of a black Dog; that she had a Pi∣stol every time, and that all that mount∣ed the Guard, had Orders not to Shoot any Dog. Not long after this, at a sign that was given, she went sidling towards the Town, her Dog still remaining in the same place; she bid <HI>Frederick</HI> to follow the Dog, who would not go fast, so soon as he should see him move. It proved as the Woman had said, when she was got about an hundred yards, from the Dog, the Dog took up the piece of Gut, which lay by him, and followed the Woman, still keeping the same distance behind her. <HI>Frederick,</HI> perceiving this, began to follow the Dog, thereby, expo∣sing himself wholly to the Towns Shot, but there was not one made at him; thus little by little, taking a small compass, still tending towards the Gate <HI>Gaw;</HI> where, at last, being come, they were both let in; at the Foot of the Rampart, she had
<PB N="84" REF="47"/>
made a halt, at which the Dog had done the like; but <HI>Frederick</HI> advanced, after she had given him a sign. Thus did <HI>Fre∣derick</HI> get into the Town again, without any great hazard; he gave the Woman a Pistol, and then went towards his old Lodgings, which were almost at the other end of the Town: They had seen six or seven <HI>French</HI> Officers, well mounted, who had endeavoured to get into the Town, at a considerable distance from them; <HI>Frede∣rick,</HI> at first, though on Foot, wish'd him∣self amongst them, but seeing two of them drop, he took the Woman's Advice, and did not follow the rest, who got safe in.</P>
<P><HI>Frederick,</HI> after his wonted Custom, so soon as he got into that House, where he lodged, was going into his Chamber, without speaking to any body; but his Landlady called, and told him, that his Chamber was taken up, by such an Ac∣cident, which she related to him, but that the Party should presently be remo∣ved; mean time, a Servant was gone to bid the wounded Gentleman prepare to be removed, which News he received with much disgust, fearing the prejudice which another disturbance would pro∣duce
<PB N="85" REF="47"/>
to his Wound; he desired therefore, that he might first speak with the Gentle∣man that owned the Chamber; <HI>Frederick,</HI> hearing that, went in▪ Sir, said the Sick Man, to him, You see, a poor wounded Pri∣soner; I am a Gentleman, continued he, and if, besides the Ransom I am to pay, I can purchase my stay here, till I am in a better Condition to remove, spake but your demands, and I will procure it you. <HI>Frederick,</HI> pittying the poor Gentleman's Condition, whom he guest to be very ill, by the faintness of his Voice, made answer, that he knew how to be civil even to his Enemies, that he should re∣main there so long as he pleased, and trouble himself no further; with that, <HI>Frederick,</HI> shutting the Bed-Curtains close, bid him take his rest, and went immedi∣ately out of the House again, in the design of employing some Persons, to go in eve∣ry part of the Town, and inquire after a Gentleman Prisoner, taken such a day, and supposed to be brought in wounded, his Horse having been shot under him. <HI>Frederick</HI> having resolved to remain in the Closet, all that day, and the next, where there was a little Couch; he got
<PB N="86" REF="48"/>
a Bottle of Wine, another of Water, and some Bisket, with which he retired into the Closet, without having been percei∣ved of any Body, no not so much as by the Sick Man, who knew of no Closet, and when he heard any noise, supposed it to be some Servant, who was going in and out; thus did <HI>Frederick</HI> lock himself into his Closet, for that time, having told the Persons whom he had employed, on the search after <HI>Peregrine,</HI> that he would meet them, at such a certain place, two days after.</P>
<P>In the Night time, as <HI>Frederick</HI> lay on his Couch, he heard great complaints, and having hearkened to them, he found it was the Sick Man, who was lamenting his hard Fate. What vast difference, said he, do I find, betwixt the Wounds of the Body, and those of the Mind! How insensible I am of the first, when, my Miseries present themselves to my thoughts! And, what Balm have I to allay the smart of the last, but this poor Relick of that fair Saint, which my Soul did Adore! How dare I look on it? What Advan∣tage can I expect from it? After what I have made the Original to suffer; Thou sweet representer of all my past Joys, I
<PB N="87" REF="48"/>
would not part with thee for less than the Original; the whole World is of less value to me, than this dead Idea of that which with me was all in all. Why do I live still, so long as she's no more? Well, a short time shall put an end to all my Miseries; I will follow in death, she who I have sent before, by my inconsiderate∣ness; and seeing I am deprived of her dear Conversation in this Life, I will en∣deavour to injoy it in the next, so soon as my slight Wound will but permit me to sacrifice my life to those dear Ashes; mean time I must continue miserable. Oh Heavens! After this there was a great si∣lence, which continuing, <HI>Frederick</HI> o∣pen'd the Closet Door, without the least noise, and approaching little by little, to∣wards the Bed, and finding that the Gen∣tleman was fallen fast asleep, he ventur'd to search upon it for the Picture that had lately been mention'd; but hearing some noise at the Chamber-Door, that made him to retire again, to lock himself up, and to defer his curiosity, till some other convenient time.</P>
<P>It was that Officer who had taken <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI> Prisoner, who having learnt that day, by a Deserter, that the Besiegers
<PB N="88" REF="49"/>
designed very suddainly to give a general Assault, was come to bid his Prisoner provide the 100 Pistoles for his Ransome: To which the Chyrurgeon that was with him, added, That now he was almost well, he desired he should also send for Money to pay his Charges. This was something surprising to <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who made no answer; which made the Quar∣ter-Master say, That he did not know how Fortune might order the day; and that he was loath to lose so much Mo∣ney, which might serve for a Ransome for himself, should he have the Fortune to be made a Prisoner; and bidding <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI> imploy some body about it, the next day at the farthest, he went huffing out of the Chamber. <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who had not spoke one Word all the while, but answered with Sighs, then said, Here is some comfort yet, this want of a Ran∣some may invite this greedy man to send me to my dear <HI>Clarinda.</HI> Oh! that Name has still such Charms in it, that it puts life in me when I hear it sound: She was too forward, too credulous, too—Ah! Fatal <HI>Isabella;</HI> Thou hast carried home thy Revenge against me, for slight∣ing of thy Love; my time to Love
<PB N="89" REF="49"/>
was not yet come; <HI>Clarinda</HI> was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> to gather the first Fruits of my Affections; but how dear she has paid for it, is the subject of my eternal Grief. After these, and divers others regrets, he remained si∣lent.</P>
<P><HI>Frederick,</HI> who had heard all, being now intirely convinced, that this Person was her dear <HI>Peregrine,</HI> and that he was blameless, and never lov'd any other but him, he resolved to put an end to both their Afflictions in a short time, but would do it with the greatest surprize that could be imagined, having so fair an opportu∣nity to do it; and to begin, he roll'd up two several Papers, containing each an hundred Pistoles, then writ what follows.</P>
<LETTER>
<P>Your good Angel, to preserve your Life, and compose your Spirits, has provided what Gold you have occasion for; and in requital of it, has deprived you of the renewer of your grief. Still live in hope it is <HI>Clarin∣da's</HI> Ghost will have it so.</P>
</LETTER>
<P>After this, having watched till he was asleep, he came softly to the Bed∣side, and having laid the two Papers of Gold close to his Pillow, was groping for
<PB N="90" REF="50"/>
the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>tu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, he selt him to move, then heard him sigh, which had put him by from seeking any farther, for fear of be∣ing discovered; but as he was taking up his hand, he found his Fingers intangled, which prov'd to be the Ribbon belonging to the Picture; he presently took it up, and retired softly, unperceived, and just as he was getting into the Closet, he heard <HI>Peregrine</HI> say, Divine <HI>Clarinda;</HI> at which he could not forbear answering, in a low voice, Constant <HI>Peregrine.</HI> Ha! What's that I hear? cry'd out <HI>Peregrine,</HI> in a strange surprise, having he knew not how got sitting in the Bed, which he had not done e'er since his Wound before; the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> he hearkned very attentively for a time; after which he laid himself down again, saying, with a great sigh, 'twas but a Dream, but very pleasing to me; after which, he again remain'd silent. So soon as Day began to permit him to see, he was again at his exercise of sighing, and go∣ing to order his Pillow, he felt something heavy, lye close to his Head; he laid his hand upon it, took it up, and found it to be the rolls of Gold, lapt up in a sheet of Paper, in which <HI>Frederick</HI> had writ those few Lines. <HI>Peregrine,</HI> in great sur∣prize,
<PB N="91" REF="50"/>
open'd the sheet of Paper, and there read what had been writ: This did won∣derfully amaze him; he could not ima∣gine how this relief should come so unex∣pected to him; he busied his Thoughts a thousand ways to find out the right cause; and all he could imagine that came nea∣rest to it was, that Count <HI>Zinzendorf,</HI> ha∣ving sound out that he was a Prisoner in <HI>Mentz,</HI> had (he knew not how) convey'd that Relief to him: But then, how should he come to the knowledge of his concerns with <HI>Clarinda,</HI> and that he had her Picture, he having never discovered to any Person one title of the whole Tran∣saction, that he could not dive into; he only conjectur'd that <HI>Mariana</HI> might have sent a Letter to him, which men∣tion'd all those particulars; and that in his absence his Friends might have open'd it, to learn how far it concern'd him: then feeling for the Picture, and finding it gone, he was in as great a concerne at all these surprising things unknown to him, ad∣miring how it was possible he should be seiz'd with so profound a Sleep, as not to be awaken'd; then sure, said he, these People will come again when I am not asleep, and give me some Information of
<PB N="92" REF="51"/>
the whole Event: He was thus canvassing the business in his Mind, when he heard the tuning of an Instrument, as it were in some other Room of the House; he listened, and was surprised more than ever, to hear those Verses he had made on his accidental saving of <HI>Clarinda,</HI> sung to a Theorbo-Lute. These were all In∣chantments to him; and the most pro∣bable conjecture he could make of it, was that certainly it was <HI>Mariana</HI> who had done all this; but how she should come there, find him out, learn his particular wants, and all the rest, was a Miracle to him. So soon as the Song was ended, he strove so much that he reach'd a Shooe, with which he made a shift to knock so loud, that some of the Servants came to him. He ask'd them who had been there? They answered him, they were certain no body had been in the Chamber since the Quarter-Master and the Chyrur∣geon had been there; because the last go∣ing out had double-lock'd the Door, and given the Key to his Mistress, from whom he had just now received it, to come in∣to him.</P>
<P><PB N="93" REF="51"/>This could not but strangely disorder <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who ask'd the Fellow whether there was not some other way into his Chamber. The Fellow, who was but newly in that service, answered, he knew not, that he did not believe there was, and that he would see: with that he walk'd round the Chamber, then told him he could see no other Door: with which answer poor <HI>Peregrine</HI> was forc'd to rest satisfied; and the Servant having ask'd him what he wanted; <HI>Peregrine</HI> told him, He wanted now the Quarter-Master to pay him his Ransome, and the Chy∣rurgeon also, to discharge him, and all the rest of his Ingagements; for I have been sufficiently supply'd this Night, con∣tinued he, but by what means. Then he pursued, Has no Gentleman been lately entertained in this House? No, answer∣ed the Servant; but there were two went yesterday away. So <HI>Peregrine</HI> finding himself, after all these Interrogations, as much in the dark as ever, he sent the Ser∣vant away.</P>
<P><HI>Frederick</HI> was once giving himself to be plainly discovered, and was in great fears when the Fellow walk'd about the Cham∣ber, but when he found he was gone, he
<PB N="94" REF="52"/>
resolved to pursue his design to the last: he, upon that, concluded to continue one Night longer in his concealment, though he began to be very weary of living on Bisket and Sweet▪Meats, which was all the Food he had had since his retirement, with the addition of a Glass of Wine, with which he sometimes refreshed him∣self.</P>
<P>Some time after, the Quarter Master return'd with the Chyrurgeon, and were encountred by the Mistress of the House, who giving them the Key of <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Chamber, told them, That now they needed not to fear the Prisoner, for he had Gold enough to satisfie all demands, as the Servant had informed her, but that no body knew how it came to him, see∣ing he had been lock'd up ever since they had last been there. The Quarter-Master began to prick up his Ears, and said, all that is mine; for when I took him, all he had was mine, and he must needs have concealed all that Gold about him: He must provide for another Ransome be∣sides this, continued he, for this I will seize on as my due. Hold there, reply'd the Chyrurgeon, I will not lose my share of it, be he ten times your Prisoner; while
<PB N="95" REF="52"/>
he has Money I will be satisfied for my Pains, Cares, and all the Charges I have been at. And why should I lose any thing, said the Landlady, he has had at∣tendance, and all the House could afford, I am sure, ever since he was removed here; and it is but reasonable I should be paid. The Quarter-Master, to avoid those broils, being greedy of the Money, went into <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Chamber, but was follow'd close at the Heels by the Chy∣rurgeon, and the Land-lady. I am glad, cry'd <HI>Peregrine,</HI> (seeing them come in,) that you are here, for now I have where∣with to satisfie you all. Hold a little, pray not so fast, said the Quarter-Master, all you have is mine, continued he, as being conceal'd about you, when I made you Prisoner. If you could prove that, said <HI>Peregrine,</HI> it were something, though not quite as you would have it neither; for there has an agreement past since be∣twixt us, that I should have my full li∣berty in paying you an hundred Pistoles, which I am now ready to do; but beside, I can assure you, that I have received it of late. You could not, since I was here, said the Quarter-Master; you did not mention yesterday that you had any such
<PB N="96" REF="53"/>
thing in readiness: How came you by this Money? To which <HI>Peregrine</HI> made Answer, that he had parted with a Rich Picture, for that Money, that he might be set at Liberty; which Picture, you have several times seen me sigh over, ad∣ded he, addressing to the Chyrurgeon, and which I prised much more than all this Gold. I remember, said the Chyrur∣geon, that I have often chid you, for put∣ting your self into passions, with gazing too much on it; and really, in my opi∣nion, seeing it was left you so long after you had been here, I think you may in Justice make the best Advantage you can of it. The Quarter-Master, perceiving that they were all against him, yielded, for the present, and was contented to re∣ceive the hundred Pistols, but not with∣out giving a Discharge to his Prisoner, which he did at last, with great difficulty; that being done, <HI>Peregrine</HI> paid off his Chyrurgeon, upon Condition, that he should, from time to time, visit him, and furnish him with such Plaisters and Salves, as he should want, till he was able to re∣turn to the Camp; this was freely assent∣ed to: Next, the Landlady was sattisfied, in all she demanded, and <HI>Peregrine</HI> inqui∣ring
<PB N="97" REF="53"/>
after the Gentleman, who had so ge∣nerously quitted his Chamber to him. The Woman told him, she had not heard from him since, but that she knew he would return again, because he had a great many Goods still in the House. <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI> said, he long'd to return him Thanks; and ask'd the Chyrurgeon how long it would be before he might rise, and set His Foot to the Ground. I was going to tell you Sir, reply'd he, That if you find your self without great pain when you move it in Bed, or when you feel it with your hand, you may venture to rise, and for some time keep it upon a Stool, some∣times resting it on the Floor. Very well, reply'd <HI>Peregrine;</HI> upon which they all took leave of him, and left him to him∣self.</P>
<P>I told you how the young Count <HI>Mans∣feilt</HI> had separated himself from all the rest of his Friends, in order to search the whole Camp after <HI>Clarinda;</HI> for he con∣cluded that she must needs be there; he thought she could not be far neither, be∣cause he had unfortunately wounded her. He therefore design'd to act as a Volun∣tier, and to ingage in some warm Action. He was in some despair also, since he had
<PB N="98" REF="54"/>
seen with what fierceness <HI>Clarinda</HI> had ta∣ken <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Interest; he was vext for having spoken ill of him before her. The hurt he had given her was not much to his advantage neither; he had no other hopes therefore, but in what the Officer had related; That his young Prisoner confess'd he hated <HI>Peregrine,</HI> and was come into the Camp, on purpose to kill him: He built his hopes barely upon that weak bottom, which in time he hoped might again reclaim her.</P>
<P>The whole Army was getting in a rea∣diness for a general Assault, which they design'd to begin at the covered way; the signal being given by the discharge of three Canons, and one Bomb that broke in the Air. The young Count took this opportunity to do some Action worthy himself, and the fair <HI>Clarinda;</HI> so he put himself amongst the Voluntiers: They all March to the Assault, with that un∣dauntedness end courage, that the Ene∣my not being able to endure the on-set, immediately gave way, at the Imperial, the Saxon, and the Bavarian Attacks. The Enemy, a while after, having ral∣lied, and taken new Posts on both sides, as well as in Front, their Firing was so
<PB N="99" REF="54"/>
great and continual, during some Hours, that it is impossible to apprehend the least Idea of it. The Confederate Army was near two Hours exposed to all their Ene∣mies Shot, without any covering on the Glacis, joining to the Pallisadoes, not being able to shelter it self, by reason of the Enemies continual Firing upon them, which they endured with a world of bra∣very; till at last, the Besieged being bro∣ken, and pressed upon on all sides, they were forced to give way, but not till they had sprung a Mine, which involv'd a great number of Men, and four Colours in its Mines; whereupon the Besiegers took their Post on the very brink of the Ditch.</P>
<P>All the following Night was taken up in continual Skirmishes; the Count had behaved himself so bravely, that parti∣cular notice had been taken of him, but he was not to be found neither amongst the living nor the dead: He was changing Ground to come where the warmest Skir∣mishes was, he over-took two Horse-men that were running from him towards the Gate <HI>Altmunster;</HI> he dismounted the one, and took the other Prisoner, who readily yielded upon Quarters for Life. The Count
<PB N="100" REF="55"/>
was going to deliver his Prisoner into Custody, that he might have some more Skirmishes, when he was surrounded with a small party of Horse, that were getting into the Town, who took him along with them, and his Prisoner also, and bestowed them both safe for the rest of that Night.</P>
<P>The Count had not been much trou∣bled, had he had the charming <HI>Clarinda</HI> with him: But the other Prisoner seem∣ed very much concerned, and did all he could not to be seen; they had a Room alotted them, with a Bed in it, and a Centry sat over them. The Count threw himself on the Bed, and asked his Fellow Prisoner, whither he would do the same, adding, that if he had not been retaken from him, he had found him a Generous Enemy; the other returned him thanks, saying, he had more a mind to sit up, still turning his Face, that the Count might not see it. The Count, a while after, cried out, ha! dear <HI>Clarinda,</HI> that you were but here safe and well. Those Words confirmed the other Prisoner, in the opinion, that he knew the Count, so that afterwards he was more shie than ever of shewing his Face; there we will
<PB N="101" REF="55"/>
leave them for a short time, to return to the amazed <HI>Peregrine,</HI> that could not yet reconcile himself to those surprising Ac∣cidents, that so lately had happened to him; still did his mind run on <HI>Marianas</HI> being there, concealed, unwilling he should know of her, concluding, that none but she, or his dear <HI>Clarinda,</HI> re∣turned from the dead, could act as had been done. <HI>Clarinda,</HI> dear <HI>Clarinda</HI> ▪ then cried he out, If it is thy Spirit that is still so Officious to me after Death, bless me but with one short sight of thee, I am sure thou canst not assume any shape can affright thy distracted <HI>Peregrine;</HI> but if I could behold thee with all those real Charms about thee, which thou once wore, though they were now but mere Delusions, I should die with Excess of Joy! Thus was he continuing in his Transports, when News was brought him that divers Prisoners had been taken in the last As∣sault, but that the Enemy had posted themselves very Advantagious, and had repulsed the besieged very far. <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who had given those Orders, that when they heard of any Prisoners, they should give him notice; sent the Servant to make inquiry of their Names, as well as
<PB N="102" REF="56"/>
he could, and that to oblige them to de∣clare their Names, they should say it was one <HI>Peregrine</HI> desired it.</P>
<P>Amongst the other places, that this Messenger was at, he came to that, where the Count was, with his Fellow Prisoner, where he found them both very unwil∣ling to tell their Names, till after he had named <HI>Peregrine,</HI> he observed the Count to rise off of the Bed, and say, how, <HI>Pe∣regrine?</HI> Where is that Person? Who answered, not far in the Town, and then began to tell the Count all that he knew of him, adding, that certainly he was a Devil, or some Conjurer, for, said he, when he was locked up in his Chamber, without one farthing towards his Ran∣some of an hundred Pistols. The next Morning, when the Door was opened, he had two hundred Pistols, with which he discharged all he owed, and now re∣mains full of Gold, which it is thought the Devil brings to him, by the Window, or down the Chimney. This did not a little trouble the Count, but the other Prisoner, was not less concerned at this Narrative, yet would not discover his Surprisal before the Count, but taking the opportunity, when the Messenger was
<PB N="103" REF="56"/>
going out, he desired him to tell the Gen∣tleman, that there was a Prisoner, who belonged to a Lady, named <HI>Clarinda,</HI> that would be glad to see him, if he could contrive it. The Messenger, well satis∣fied with what he had done, returned home, and gave <HI>Peregrine</HI> an Account of his discovery: <HI>Peregrine,</HI> had no sooner heard the charming word <HI>Clarinda,</HI> but he immediately sent back the Messenger, rewarding him well, and charged him to know what Ransome was set upon that Prisoner; he went, and returned not long after, to tell <HI>Peregrine,</HI> that fifty Pistols, payed presently, would set him free; they were immediately sent, and the Prisoner set at Liberty, to go where he pleased, who went along with the Messenger, to <HI>Peregrine's</HI> Lodging; and the Count ha∣ving lost his Companion, was left Dis∣consolate, all alone. The fear of having the Town taken by Storm, was the Cause of this Prisoner's going off with ready Money; for it was verily believed that such another Assault would certainly car∣ry it.</P>
<P>The late Prisoner being brought into <HI>Peregrine's</HI> Chamber, he got to his Bed∣side, and began to return him thanks,
<PB N="104" REF="57"/>
for the Ransome he had been so kind to pay for him; assuring him, that so soon as <HI>Clarinda</HI> should come to the knowledg of it, she would return it him with hear∣ty thanks, because he was a Servant, for whom <HI>Clarinda</HI> had always a particular Kindness. At this, <HI>Peregrine,</HI> fetching a deep sigh from the bottom of his Heart, answered, Then do your Office, repay me of your Ransome, in sending me im∣mediately to wait on that fair Saint, you just now named; and to invite you the more to do that piece of singular Service, to the Memory of your dear Mistress, know, I have murthered her, at that the Person started, and cried, Heavens forbid! Yes, replied <HI>Peregrine,</HI> I am an expert Murtherer, I need no Weapons, nor Poisons, to act with all, I can do it with a bare Letter, nay, even when I have no such Thoughts, Mischief is so natural to me. Pray recollect your self, replied <HI>Clarindas</HI> Servant, you speak as if you were not well, in your Mind; Whence do you derive that fancy of <HI>Clarindas</HI> Death? Is it because you have not heard from her lately? Or, do you believe that you are dead in her Heart, and that con∣sequently she may be counted dead as to
<PB N="105" REF="57"/>
you? If any such thing were, I yet might live and hope; <HI>Peregrine</HI> answered, but she is really: dead; Oh, unspeakable Grief! I have it from good Hands, a Friend of the unfortunate Count; therefore, an E∣nemy to me, has certified it to me; and, upon that, has vowed my Death, but is not so kind as to come and give it me; but now, you are here, do that which Justice, Revenge, and Duty, ought to prompt you to, Kill, kill, that miserable Wretch, that has had the Confidence to survive her so long. <HI>Clarindas</HI> Servant, at these Words, let himself fall upon the Bed, saying, in a low voice, unfortunate <HI>Clarinda,</HI> and miserable <HI>Mariana;</HI> Die <HI>Mariana,</HI> why shouldst thou live to hear such doleful News, with that, he sound∣ed quite away; at those last Words, <HI>Pe∣regrine,</HI> who was set up, in his Bed, look∣ing stedfast on the Person's Face, <HI>Maria∣na,</HI> said he, take a little of this to stay thee, till thou takest me along with thee, giving her a little Cordial, out of a Bot∣tle, which he had by him; after which, he did all he could besides, to recover her, without the Assistance of any body else, because of her Sex. <HI>Frederick</HI> had over-heard all, and was so moved at his
<PB N="106" REF="58"/>
dear <HI>Marianas</HI> Trouble, that he was co∣ming out to discover himself, when he heard her fetch a great sigh; after which, she came to her self again, saying, Pray Heavens you may have been abused; that Happiness cannot be hoped for, replied <HI>Peregrine,</HI> I should certainly have heard of her, I that have sought her in all pla∣ces. At this, <HI>Mariana</HI> did shed a flood of Tears, and <HI>Peregrine</HI> sent forth whole gales of Sighs; after which, <HI>Peregrine</HI> gave <HI>Mariana</HI> an Account of all his Acti∣ons, since his Absence; and how oft he had sought Death, but was not so happy as to meet with it: Heavens forbid, said <HI>Mariana,</HI> poor <HI>Clarindas</HI> Death, added she, is more to be attributed to her Pas∣sion, and Rashness, than to your Cruel∣ty; and I must confess, that my Impru∣dence, has been Instrumental also; with that, she gave him an Account of all that had happened to <HI>Clarinda,</HI> and to her self, since <HI>Clarindas</HI> departure. Thus, after a long Discourse, what with Grief, and Weariness, poor <HI>Mariana,</HI> fell a sleep, at <HI>Peregrine's</HI> Beds Feet, which obliged him to do the like, not long after.</P>
<P><PB N="107" REF="58"/>This silence did somewhat appease <HI>Frederick's</HI> disturbed Mind, at both those dear Friends Afflictions: He was very de∣sirous to Accomplish what he had begun, and did hope that they would continue their Sleep, till Night, at which time, he intended to perform the last act of his Tragicomedy; and from that time, he began to prepare himself for it, and it luc∣kily happened that they both did sleep, till there was Candles brought into the Chamber, that did awake <HI>Peregrine,</HI> who gave order that no noise should be made, and that a Fowl should be got ready for Supper; as for <HI>Mariana,</HI> she slept on till Supper was brought up, she having had no sleep, in two Nights before; and <HI>Pere∣grine</HI> would by no means disturb her, but let her awake of her self. He invited her to cat, but she excused her self, telling him, that she never more should enjoy her self; he could not so much as make her drink a Glass of Wine; thus they both sate, <HI>Peregrine,</HI> in the Bed, and <HI>Ma∣riana,</HI> on the side of it, looking doleful∣ly, on each other, not knowing what to say; Ah! That my dear <HI>Clarinda</HI> was here at last, said <HI>Mariana,</HI> then you would have no cause to invite me to eat,
<PB N="108" REF="59"/>
or drink; that is a bit she used to love, added she, pointing at some part of the Fowl; her Ghost, would suffice me, said <HI>Peregrine,</HI> or, at least, that sweet Picture, which is vanished from me. <HI>Frederick,</HI> hearing this, came softly, and laid the Picture upon the Bed; a little while after, <HI>Peregrine,</HI> having leaned towards <HI>Maria∣na,</HI> till his Arm ak'd, turn'd, to sit up, and saw the Picture lie before him; he takes it up, kisses it, and cried, see <HI>Mari∣ana,</HI> the Heavens grow kind, and have sent me my Desires: Heavens! How comes this to pass? Replied, poor <HI>Mari∣ana,</HI> as affrighted, sure, you had not look'd for it well! 'Tis like, it has never been off of the Bed, but ingaged in some of the foldings of the Bed-Cloths; none of all that, dear <HI>Mariana,</HI> replied <HI>Pere∣grine,</HI> this Paper left in the room of it, with the Gold, expresses otherwise, read it; he gave her the Paper, in which she read, as he had done before; then, she added, sure, this is her own hand, or I am the most mistaken in the World! Why may not her Hand be imitated, ad∣ded <HI>Peregrine,</HI> as well as Bodies be assu∣med by kind obliging Spirits, and appear? The one is as feasible, as the other; those
<PB N="109" REF="59"/>
are strange things, <HI>Mariana,</HI> continued he: they much surprise me, said <HI>Mariana,</HI> who stood in a kind of Amazement; How would you be then, said <HI>Peregrine,</HI> if her sweet Ghost, should instantly appear? Ah! would it would; yet, no, added he, it would affright you too much: No, I believe not, answered <HI>Mariana,</HI> I know not what it might do, if I was alone, but you being here:—Drink to me, <HI>Mariana,</HI> drink her Health, I'll pledg it, though 'twas Poison, said <HI>Peregrine,</HI>—He was going to proceed, when <HI>Clarinda,</HI> appeared, coming up close to the little Table, by the Bed-side, on which the Supper was laid.</P>
<P>She had put a Linnen Cloth, over her Head, which hung over her Face, down to her upper Lip; and she had put over that, a large white Sheet, which she had tied of a bunch, at the top of her Head, which covered her all over, but the Face; she had, besides, a Glass of Wine, in each Hand; she stood a while, without moving, before them, at which, <HI>Maria∣na,</HI> wrapt her self round, in the Curtain, making a great shriek; but <HI>Peregrine</HI> sat gazing, with a Countenance that expres∣sed a great disorder; after that, <HI>Clarinda,</HI>
<PB N="110" REF="60"/>
who had stood without motion, stooped towards <HI>Peregrine,</HI> offering one of the Glasses of Wine, which he refused to take, pulling himself back; with that, she sat one of the Glasses on the Table, then stan∣ding up streight, Is this the Man, said she, would drink my Health, in Poison? Why have I disturbed my sweet rest, in hopes to see such constancy, after Death, in one I loved, and be thus disappointed? I must return again, with this certain Truth, there is no Faith in Man; Adieu, fond Morrals, adieu, for ever more; at these last Words, as she was turning, Hold, cried <HI>Peregrine,</HI> Though thou canst not be <HI>Clarindas</HI> Ghost, for that would know me better, I will drink the Poison, give me the Glass; Ghost, stay, added he, and take me with you, or go tell Divine <HI>Clarinda,</HI> how thou seest me take that Pass which is to convey me to her; with saying this, he took the Glass from <HI>Cla∣rinda,</HI> and raising his voice, Here's to <HI>Clarinda,</HI> whom I still Adore, said he, and drank up the Wine. I should not have pronounced that Name, continued he, after drinking, it may prove an An∣tidote, beyond the power of the most virulent Poison, and prevent my flight
<PB N="111" REF="60"/>
to her; it has, for certain, much better'd the Taste. <HI>Clarinda,</HI>—added he, at which, she lifting off the Sheet, and Cloth, which covered her Face, she ap∣peared, in a Dress, which <HI>Peregrine</HI> had formerly seen. Constant, and Faithful, <HI>Peregrine,</HI> here is thy <HI>Clarinda,</HI> she is wholly thine, said <HI>Clarinda;</HI> with that, inclining on the Bed, she took him by the Hand, pressing it hard, and kissed his frighted Cheeks; feel, said she, I am thy warm <HI>Clarinda,</HI> living still, to die in thy sweet Bosome: But where's dear <HI>Maria∣na?</HI> Alas, poor Soul, frighted, I fear, too much; Come, my dèar <HI>Mariana,</HI> and enjoy, once again, thy poor <HI>Clarinda.</HI> Fear not, I am really she, with that, she unfolded the Curtains, which <HI>Mariana,</HI> held no longer so hard: <HI>Mariana;</HI> it is she, cried out <HI>Peregrine,</HI> the living <HI>Cla∣rinda;</HI> What Wonders do I see! What Joys possess my Heart! They crowd in here too fast, with that, he sunk down in a swoon: <HI>Clarinda</HI> having embraced her dear <HI>Mariana,</HI> and assured her of her life, with a thousand warm Kisses, which the still discomposed Girl, returned again, so well as her late fears would permit her: <HI>Clarinda,</HI> casting an Eye, on <HI>Peregrine,</HI>
<PB N="112" REF="61"/>
and perceiving him fallen backwards, with his Eyes closed, help, <HI>Mariana,</HI> cri∣ed she, assist me to preserve my second Life, <HI>Peregrine</HI> is not well; they both bu∣sied themselves, to raise him up again, at which, he came to himself: That Men should die, with too much Joy, said he.</P>
<P>I beg your Pardon my dear <HI>Peregrine,</HI> said <HI>Clarinda,</HI> for that great share I have had in producing all your Sorrows and Griefs, when you'l please to consider 'twas the effects of my Passions towards you, which plung'd me into a severe Jealousie, and deep Despair, at the sight of that fatal <HI>English</HI> Letter: You will, I know, be so good as to pardon the results of that Rage, which had so intirely pos∣sest me. <HI>Peregrine</HI> made answer, That his imprudence in keeping that Letter, (which he ought to have burnt, since he valued it not,) being the first cause of all those Miseries he had suffered since, he ought to pass by other lesser Errors. But, added he, How came you to the under∣standing of it? Who was your Interpre∣ter? I fear he did not do me Justice. <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI> answered, When I have eat and drank with you, to confirm you further
<PB N="113" REF="61"/>
I am no Ghost, (though I have almost liv'd like one these two Days,) then I shall give my <HI>Peregrine</HI> that satisfaction, with a full account of all has happened to me since you went from us: With that they sate themselves to eat, which <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI> did very heartily. They had seve∣ral little pickeerings of Wit with one a∣nother, which diverted them during Sup∣per; after which, <HI>Peregrine,</HI> contriving within himself how <HI>Clarinda</HI> and <HI>Mariana</HI> should be disposed on that Night, <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI> took notice of his musing; What possesses your Thoughts now? said she; To know where you and <HI>Mariana</HI> shall lye this Night; or rather where I shall retire, answered <HI>Peregrine,</HI> for i'll quit you my Bed, I find it now grows late. It does, said <HI>Clarinda;</HI> wherefore I shall leave my Narrative till Morning. <HI>Mari∣ana</HI> and I, will leave you to your Re∣pose, which I hope will now be sweet and long to you; and we will retire to that <HI>Elizium,</HI> where I kept, while thought dead; there is a little Couch will hold us both. Not so, reply'd <HI>Mariana;</HI> do you go into Bed, and i'll sit up: But where is this Inchanted place, so near, yet so invisible? Here, said <HI>Clarinda,</HI>
<PB N="114" REF="62"/>
(stepping towards the Closet, and taking up the Hanging,) within the reach of all you said: Come <HI>Mariana,</HI> added she, and see the Grave in which I was buried alive: They both went into the Closet, where after they had remained a while, <HI>Peregrine</HI> having slipt on his Gown, and leaning on a Stick, came halting in, say∣ing, He was resolved that Night to lye in <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s Grave: with that he laid himself down on the Couch, and by no intreats nor persuasions could be got off again; telling them, That he would pass the rest of that Night in that place. <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI> finding him obstinate, took out of the Closet all that was convenient for her and <HI>Mariana,</HI> that Night, with a Night-Gown for <HI>Mariana,</HI> and one of her Man∣tua's for her to put on the next Morn∣ing.</P>
<P>No Servants had come near them all that Evening and Night, because <HI>Pere∣grine</HI> had frequently given strict Orders that no body should come to him, except they heard him knock; so that they had no disturbance on that side; and having took leave of one another, they all com∣posed themselves to sleep.</P>
<P><PB N="115" REF="62"/>The next Morning, <HI>Clarinda</HI> and <HI>Ma∣riana</HI> being up, and in their Night-Dres∣ses, went to see how <HI>Peregrine</HI> had past the Night; they found by his chearful looks, and hearty answer, that he was much improved as to his Health and Strength. How could I do amiss, said he, having my Titular Angel so near me; and lying in my <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s sweet Monument? After a while, as they were returning into the Chamber, <HI>Mariana</HI> making a false step, fell down, but did not hurt her self; one of the Servants hearing the noise, and believing <HI>Peregrine</HI> knock'd, came into the Chamber, where espying no Man in Bed, and two Gen∣tlewomen dressing themselves, he pre∣sently run down again; telling the Mis∣tress, that certainly the Devil haunted that Chamber; for in lieu of finding a Lame▪Man in Bed, there was two fine Gentlewomen dressing themselves at their Glasses; let who will go there for me hereafter, added he, i'll not go to the Devil so often. A while after, the La∣dies wanting Water, knock in good ear∣nest, but no body came to them; they repeated the knocking, and finding it was to no purpose, <HI>Mariana</HI> stept to the
<PB N="116" REF="63"/>
Stair-head, and aloud ask'd, Whether there was no body in the House? At which the People below Stairs were all mute, but one Maid bolder than the rest, said, she would see these Hobgoblings, at what rate soever, so went up Stairs, and <HI>Mari∣ana</HI> returning into the Chamber, where the Maid following her, she was told they wanted Water, and desired they should be a little better attended, assuring her, the Servants should not lose their la∣bour. The Maid made her excuses, and laid the fault upon the impertinency of a silly Fellow in the House, who ever since the Gentleman that lay there before, had the Gold brought to him so strangely, did take all that was done in that Room for Inchantments; that he had run down Stayrs, so soon as he had peep'd into the Chamber, and said, he had seen there, he knew not how many Devils in Wo∣men's Apparel, dressing themselves: which made <HI>Clarinda</HI> smile to her self: Then did the Maid tell them, that at the least Call she would run up to wait on them, or the Gentleman either, if he was there still, as she supposed he was not, there being but one Bed. <HI>Clarinda,</HI> to unde∣ceive her, and to take away all suspitions,
<PB N="117" REF="63"/>
brought her to the Closet, where she shewed her <HI>Peregrine</HI> in Bed: This is the place, said she, out of which came the Gold, and all the other Inchantments, I being in it all that while, who came here at first, in the habit of a Gentleman, to pass with more safety through the Army, that then was gathering about this place: Pray satisfie your Mistress, and all other Persons of this Truth. The Maid, making a Courtesie, went away well satisfied, and did according as <HI>Clarinda</HI> had comman∣ded her; so that the next time they knock'd for any thing, they were waited upon by the Mistress of the House, who made a great many Apologies, and gave great Assurances of her future attendance. <HI>Clarinda</HI> informed her of all she thought fit she should know, and so dismist her.</P>
<P>The Confederates great advantage which they had got over the Besieged, in the late Assault, caus'd the Governour, who was the Marquess of <HI>Ʋxelles,</HI> to call a grand Council of War; in which it was concluded, That considering the great loss which they had sustained in this last Attack, the great Advantages with which the Enemies had posted them∣selves, which was very difficult to re∣gain,
<PB N="118" REF="64"/>
and the great want of Ammuniti∣on they were in, having not above 4 C▪ weight of Powder left, together with the great number of Sick and Wounded, and the small hopes of Relief, that the white Flag should be hung out, which was done that very Morning, about eight of the Clock, and a Parley was beaten, in order to Capitulate. Prince <HI>Albert</HI> of <HI>Saxe-Cornbourg,</HI> who Commanded that Day in the Trenches, on the side of the Imperial Attack, sent a Trumpet to the Besieged, to know their meaning. To which was answered, That the Gover∣nour was inclin'd to give up the Garison; that if the Duke of <HI>Loraine</HI> would be pleased to send the Governour a Lieute∣nant-Collonel, with an other Officer; to discourse with them about Conditions, he would send into their Camp Hostages of the same quality. Whereupon the Prince sent his aid Major to consult with the Duke of <HI>Loraine,</HI> and they agreed to the Governour's desires, upon condition, that he should first send his two Officers. Whereupon the Duke of <HI>Loraine</HI> sent in∣to the City the Prince <HI>de Commercy,</HI> and Lieutenant Collonel <HI>Princj;</HI> after which there was a Cessation of Arms betwixt
<PB N="119" REF="64"/>
both-Parties, and the Treaty fully con∣cluded before Night.</P>
<P>Count <HI>Mansfeilt</HI> all this while had not remained Idle, by the aid of divers Mes∣sengers he had found out <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Lodgings, and had got the Servant, who was with him before, to come to him again: He inquired of him how <HI>Peregrine</HI> did? What Company he had with him? And whether he stirr'd abroad yet? The Fellow, who was the same that had been so frighted, told him, That now all the Devils which haunted him before, were all turn'd into Gentlewomen, that were very tame and gentle indeed, wonderous fine and handsome; and that, that very Prisoner, whose Ransome he had paid, by the wounded Gentleman's Orders, was turned to a Gentlewoman also. This account gave the Count cause to consider, he apprehended that this was <HI>Clarinda,</HI> who he had taken, which he had not known in the dark; he began to think how shye that Person was of showing his Face, how he refused lying down with him, with abundance more; from all which he fully concluded it was <HI>Clarinda,</HI> that he had so tamely parted with, to his Mortal Enemy; this put him into
<PB N="120" REF="65"/>
such a rage, that he was almost distract∣ed; he lay continually sighing and groan∣ing on the Bed, and would neither eat nor drink. While the Fellow was still with him, the Person who had took him, came to tell him, He must find out a suddain way to pay his Ransome, which he resolved not to lose. To which the Count made no answer, but that he was his Prisoner, he might do what he plea∣sed with him. That gave but little sa∣tisfaction to the Officer, who was grum∣bling very hard; which made the Fel∣low run home as fast as he could; he told his Mistress, that the other Prisoner that had been taken with the Man-Gen∣tlewoman, that was above Stairs, was like to be kill'd by him who had taken him, for want of his Ransome. The Mistress of the House, fancying that he might be known by the Gentlewoman, went up Stairs to give notice of it: At which <HI>Mariana</HI> cry'd out, alas! this is the Count, who I told you was taken with me. How, a Count, said the Land∣lady, that will bring a good lump of Mony. No, no, reply'd <HI>Clarinda,</HI> it is a Voluntier, whose Name is <HI>le Count:</HI> so it was turn'd off, and the Land-lady
<PB N="121" REF="65"/>
was desired to know what Ransome was demanded for him. Mean time <HI>Clarinda</HI> and <HI>Mariana</HI> went into the Closet to con∣sult about it with <HI>Peregrine,</HI> saying, now you have a fair opportunity to rid your self of your Rival, the Count; so told him to what a sad condition he was re∣duc'd. Why sends he not to his Friends in the Camp, to let them know his con∣dition, said <HI>Peregrine.</HI> There's the mis∣chief of it, said <HI>Mariana,</HI> with what this Fellow has put in his Head, that the Per∣son he had taken was a Woman in man's Apparel, and believing it was you doubt∣less, (speaking to <HI>Clarinda</HI>) he is in a De∣spair, for having parted so tamely with you. Heavens forbid, that we should not assist him, if we can, said <HI>Peregrine;</HI> though he will not help himself, the more need has he of our aid. Still spo∣ken like generous <HI>Peregrine.</HI> He shall be releaved, and presently too, said <HI>Clarin∣da,</HI> since my dear Friend has said it. Some time after the Fellow return'd, saying, he refus'd all aid, assistance, or comfort, except he knew from whom it came. This made <HI>Peregrine</HI> say, unfor∣tunate Gentleman! There is nothing but this rich Jewel, but I would part with, ad∣ded
<PB N="122" REF="66"/>
he, taking <HI>Clarinda</HI> by the hand, to serve him with: But what is his Ran∣some? The Fellow said, The Office<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> had told him something was better than nothing; and that seeing the Article<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> would be signed that Night for the de∣livery of the Town, in which might be comprised the releasing of all Prisoners o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> both sides, he would be contented with what he could get. Then said <HI>Clarinda</HI> I must get you <HI>Mariana</HI> to go with For∣ty Pistoles, which I will give you; and give twenty for his Ransome, and give him the rest to defray his present Neces∣sities, as if all this came from your self, taking no notice in the least of us two▪ otherwise, peradventure he would refuse it. <HI>Mariana</HI> readily accepted the Com∣mission, and prepared to go with the Fellow, after <HI>Clarinda</HI> had given her the Gold. Mean time did <HI>Clarinda</HI> give <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI> an account of all her misfortunes, since they had been separated, not for∣getting his Friend's Civility towards her, and her Rancounter with the Count.</P>
<P>While she was thus relating her Story to him, News was brought that there was one below, who would spake with <HI>Pere∣grine;</HI> he ordered him to be brought up,
<PB N="123" REF="66"/>
and it proved to be his honest Groom. So soon as the Articles had been signed, in∣quiry had been made about the Prisoners of Note, and Count <HI>Zinzendorf,</HI> having notice thereof, had sent this Fellow to learn News of his Master: The Fellow being come, and perceiving his Master smile; 'Tis well you're found, at last, Master, said he, there has been a foul stir about you, no body knew what was become of you; and after I told your Friends how I had found poor Crop, meat for Crows, they all concluded you dead; dead, said I, he has other Fish to frie, I warrant you; D'you think that a Man has nothing else to do, that has a Sweet-Heart? He's gone to Ferret her out, I'll warrant you; and now I find I guest well, faith Master, or she has serrited you out. Well, I'm glad to see thee again, old Boy, answered <HI>Pe∣regrine;</HI> How does all things whence you come? With that, he gave him this Ac∣count; Your three Horses, and three Ser∣vants, are all well, as you see, at this pre∣sent, and all present their Service to you; and Count <HI>Zinzendorf</HI> send me to tell you, that you should send him word, whither you were dead or alive; is so, that he would order all your Trinckoms to be
<PB N="124" REF="67"/>
sent to you; for now the Rogues are wea∣ry of fighting, Honest Folks may go about their Business again: Well, continued he, I am woundely mistaken, if this Gentle∣woman-Gentleman, was not the same bo∣dy that gave me that plaguy Letter (a Pox on't) that made you run out of your Wits; if the truth was known, has play'd more tricks than are good, I'll warrant you, and I fear 'tis for no good he's here; pray let's search him, Master: <HI>Clarinda,</HI> and <HI>Peregrine,</HI> could not but laugh, at the Fellows Bluntness: Come, come, let's see your Hand, added he, I'll tell you your Fortune, she pulled off her Glove, and shewed the Palm of her Hand, thinking he would tell her Fortune; but the Fellow presently said, I'll a none of your tricks put upon me; let see the back-side of it? She having turned it, and he having espi∣ed the Plaster; there's the mark of the Beast, cried he, that's he (though now turn'd to a Woman) that let himself be taken, on purpose, as he declared, to cut your Throat, as I have been well infor∣med, by the Officer's Man; and for rage, he could not find you, had like to have made a Scieve, of a Count's Belly, but that a was a little too nimble for him, and
<PB N="125" REF="67"/>
gave him that Remembrance, which he carries yet; Pray Master, let's search him, I say? No, no, replied <HI>Peregrine,</HI> I'll en∣gage this Lady is no Man, but thou hast guest pretty right, as to the rest: Nay, nay, if you have searched her, you know better than I, I am sattisfied: Well then, added he, What shall I say to the Count, and the rest of your Friends: Tell them, answered <HI>Peregrine,</HI> that I am well; and that the desperate young Gentleman is well also, added <HI>Clarinda;</HI> at <HI>Clarindas</HI> speaking, let your betters be first served, said the Fellow, my Master began first; this was very pleasant to them: Well, go thy ways, added <HI>Peregrine,</HI> tell all my Friends, I hope to see them here▪ in good Health; and do you, and your Comrades, return to me again, presently, with my Equipage, if it will be permitted. You'll give me leave to drink a Pot of Wine first, said the Fellow; two and thou wilt, answered <HI>Peregrine,</HI> but be not drunk▪ There honest Fellow, said <HI>Clarinda,</HI> gi∣ving him Money, go drink thy Master's Health, and mine, I love thee for being honest and true to thy Master, with that, the Fellow made a Leg, and went his way, telling his Master, he'd go dispatch his Bu∣siness.</P>
<P><PB N="126" REF="68"/><HI>Mariana,</HI> mean time, was come to the Count, who was much surprised at the sight of her; he forced himself to be civil to her; she told him, she had heard of his Misfortune, and was come to offer him all the aid, and assistance, that lay in her Power; he thanked her, coldly, and told her, he should not be long there; for either, in the Capitulations, the Priso∣ners would be exchanged, or released, on both sides, or a Ransome paid for him; mean time, that he was resolved to suffer, for he did not care what became of him; this he concluded, with a deep sigh, which drew Tears from <HI>Marianas</HI> Eves. But, Sir, said she, I come with a Ransome, from the Person you had taken, who thinks it due to you, though he was after that retaken with you also: I know, I had <HI>Clarinda</HI> in my Possession, but not so fortunate as to keep her; the Crossness of my Stars, do still pursue me, and inter∣pose their fatal Influences, 'twixt me, and my Happiness. In that particular, you are mistaken, Sir, you never had her in your Power, 'twas I, Sir, you pursued, took, and then lost again: How! said the Count, and was it not <HI>Clarinda?</HI> No Count, answered <HI>Mariana,</HI> I can give
<PB N="127" REF="68"/>
you such an exact account of every parti∣cular of the Business (besides the killing of her Servant) as would convince you: And is she not in <HI>Mentz?</HI> Answer'd the Count: Sir, I say not so:—There he interrupted her, saying, and in my happy Rivals Possession: No, I assure you Count, answered <HI>Mariana,</HI> she is ab∣solute Mistress of her self still: If I was sure of that,—he there was inter∣rupted, by the insolent Officer, who had taken him, who came to insult over-him▪ with two or three more, like himself: I come for Money, Sir, said he, going up to the Count: Prithy Friend, take my Life, thou wouldst do me a Kindness, for 'tis a Burthen to me, so heavy, as I am not able any longer to bear: <HI>Mariana,</HI> seeing the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ere going to apply themselves to the Count, she pulled the Officer by the Sleeve; and having told him, it did not become him, nor those o∣thers, to insult so, over a Person in Af∣fliction: What will content you? Here, said she, take this, and deliver me your Prisoner: The Officer (having felt in his Hand the weight and bulk of twenty Pi∣stols) made no answer, but coming up to the Count, Sir, you are free, said he,
<PB N="128" REF="69"/>
and I am your humble Servant: Come, added he, to his Friends, I have no lon∣ger any concern with him; let us depart, and let him go where he pleases, with that they went their way. You, <HI>Maria∣na,</HI> are kind, said the Count, but much more you would be, in letting me have a sight of fair <HI>Clarinda.</HI> Sir, all that is in my Power, you may command, answe∣red <HI>Mariana; Clarinda</HI> is Mistress of her own Actions, and of so good a temper, that I'll engage, she will do you all the Justice she can possible, so soon as things are settled; mean time, Sir, I earnestly intreat you to take Care of your self; and, in order to that, be pleased to make use of those few Pistols; with that, for fear of farther Interrogations▪ she went her ways, giving the Count▪ Compassionate Look, and left the Pistols on the Table, and the Count to do what he pleased with them.</P>
<P>The Count, so soon as <HI>Mariana</HI> was gone, took the Gold, and with it went to an Inn, where he got a Messenger to go to Count <HI>Zinzendorf</HI> in the Camp. He after that, began to reflect with a more compos'd mind, than ever he had done before, on all his Concerns; he dwelt
<PB N="129" REF="69"/>
much on <HI>Mariana</HI>'s kindness to him; he believed that she had all along been his Friend; he fancied he could make that out from her Actions, and something in her looks: Of truth, <HI>Mariana</HI> was of a very compassionate Temper, apt to side with any Person in Affliction; she had look'd on the Count, when she left him, with a Countenance full of tenderness, in the Opinion that the Count had no hopes left now of ever possessing <HI>Clarinda;</HI> for though she had said true, that she was still at her own disposal, yet she knew her thoughts so well, that she was certain none but <HI>Peregrine</HI> would carry her. <HI>Clarinda</HI> and she were near related, had been brought up, and Educated together; and her Portion, which had been left in <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI>'s Father's hands, at the Death of her Father and Mother, while she was yet very young, had increas'd to very near the Sum of <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s, and her Beauty not much inferiour; so that she was as <HI>Clarinda</HI>'s Companion, and they lov'd one another intimately. All these things running in the Count's mind, he thought himself oblig'd to <HI>Mariana</HI>'s Bounty, and that he ought to requite all her Favours in an handsome manner, and
<PB N="130" REF="70"/>
in that resolution he remained, till the Town was Surrendered.</P>
<P>The Articles were;<HI> That the next day the Confederates should have possession given them of St. </HI>Jacob's<HI> Tower, and of the </HI>Gau-Gate;<HI> that they should send five thou∣sand Men to possess themselves of it; that the next Day after, early in the Morning, the </HI>French<HI> Garison should march out of the place, with six pieces of Cannon, two Mor∣tars, with the Arms of </HI>France,<HI> and as many Carts and Waggons as were necessary to carry their Baggage, with their Colours flying, Drums beating, lighted Matches, and to be guarded to </HI>Landau,<HI> with a Con∣voy of ten Thousand Men of the Imperia∣lists.</HI></P>
<P>These Articles did very much displease the Soldiers, who had all along been very desirous to take the City by Storm, to be reveng'd of those perfidious Incen∣diaries the <HI>French,</HI> as they term'd them.</P>
<P><HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Men were got into the Town, and had given an account of these things to him from Count <HI>Zinzen∣dorf,</HI> who had sent him word also, that he should be with him the next day:
<PB N="131" REF="70"/>
whereupon <HI>Peregrine</HI> fearing some Dis∣orders might happen, as there is usually in such Affairs, so soon as <HI>Mariana</HI> was returned, he caused the Chamber-Door to be continually locked, and his Three Men to be in constant waiting at it. He after that endeavoured all he could to stand upon his Leg, and he found that he gathered much strength by it, so that by the next day he was able to walk, with the aid of a Staff. Both he and <HI>Clarinda</HI> inquired of <HI>Mariana,</HI> how the Count did, and how he had received their Civilities, or yours rather, said <HI>Clarinda:</HI> very in∣differently, answered <HI>Mariana;</HI> I was for∣ced to leave the Gold on the Table before him, and to go abruptly from him, for fear he should have returned it me: How does he look? Said <HI>Peregrine;</HI> very dis∣mayed, answered <HI>Mariana,</HI> full of trou∣ble, so that I could not but pity him very much: I wish, said <HI>Clarinda,</HI> you had the Power, dear <HI>Mariana,</HI> to change all his Sorrows into Love, of thee I mean: I fear, said <HI>Peregrine,</HI> that who ever has once lo∣ved <HI>Clarinda,</HI> can never be capable of any other Love: I am of your mind, replied <HI>Mariana:</HI> I am not, said <HI>Clarinda;</HI> he never loved to an excess; and I believe
<PB N="132" REF="71"/>
there has been more of Obstinacy and Revenge, in his Conduct towards me, than o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sincere Affection, so that he will easily be diverted by some other Object, when he is once passed all hopes: Pray wave this Discourse, replied <HI>Mariana,</HI> and let us speak of other things: Agreed, said <HI>Peregrine;</HI> but first give me leave to say, that next to seeing my dear <HI>Clarinda</HI> in∣tirely mine, past all Disputes, I heartily could wish, the Count so happy as to be in full Possession of the obliging <HI>Mariana;</HI> from this they fell into various Discourses, with which they passed the rest of that Morning: After Dinner, they desired <HI>Ma∣riana</HI> to give them, in a continued Story, the Course of her Life, since they had been separated, which they had not heard yet, but by pieces; <HI>Mariana,</HI> having as∣sented to their Request, thus began.</P>
<P>After you had been two days gon, and that the Servants you had sent back, had assured me of your safe getting into the Town, and of your Father's Death, and Burial; I every moment expected, with great impatiency, to hear from <HI>Peregrine,</HI> in what place of safety he was retired, that I might send you word, if possible, which I much dispaired to do, when I heard how
<PB N="133" REF="71"/>
difficult it was for any one to get into the Town, since the Confederates had laid a formal Siege before it. I was out of all hopes of hearing from him also, and was very willing to lay the fault on any thing else, than on his neglect, though I believ∣ed it more easily to have heard from him, than to have sent to you; this made me apprehend that he might have fallen into some Disaster. I was in those fears, when a Party of the Imperialists, came to the Castle, where they acted a great deal of Rudeness, not only towards my old Aunt, and my self, but every one of the Ser∣vants were made sensible of their Insolen∣cies; and the worst was, that when I had made my Complaints to the Officer, under pretence of taking me into his Pro∣tection; he offered things to me, beyond what I could tamely endure, so that I was forced to Repulse him with fury: mean time: the Soldiers did ransack all the Ca∣stle, taking what they thought convenient to carry along with them, not sparing my poor Aunts Chamber, which put her into such a fright, that I verily believe much contributed to her Death presently after. They were not contented with that, but went to the Stables, where they exchang∣ed
<PB N="134" REF="72"/>
their worse Horses for ours, and took away the rest. When they had done all the mischief they could, except firing, they left us to condole our Misfortunes; I found my poor Aunt in so lamentable a Condi∣tion, that she looked then as if she had been dead; so soon as she was recovered from her fright, so much as would per∣mit her to speak, she said, Let us begon, good Niece, as far as we can from these merciless Devils, before another Party of them come to make an end of us; Where shall we go, dear Aunt? I answered her; to my Farm, said she, which is Twenty miles further from <HI>Mentz;</HI> I told her she would scarce be able to endure the fatigue of so long a Journey, especially on Horse∣back, and there was then no other conve∣niency to be had; but she said, she had ra∣ther chose to die by the way, than be a∣gain frighted, as she had been before, which would certainly procure her Death: We therefore, the very next morning, very early, set forwards, with all they had left us, that was carriable; but though we went but slowly, considering we fled, my poor Aunt was so much fatigated, that she fell sick of a Fever, of which she died, the day after we came to the Farm; she
<PB N="135" REF="72"/>
by her Will, parted all she had betwixt us two; she left to my Cousin, your Bro∣ther, a Legacy, in case he were alive, which, if he was not, was to return to us. I took Care to have her decently buried, according to her Quality, as well as I could; after which, I gave my self up to lament her loss, and your Absence. I remained so, till hearing no News of ei∣ther of you, and being in Despair of hav∣ing any, I inquired of all the Men Ser∣vants, which would be so Couragious, as to attempt the getting into <HI>Mentz,</HI> with me, to learn what was become of their young Mistress; your own Groom was the readiest to answer, but your Brother's Faulkner was the most forward to attend me; he only asked, When I would set forward? I told him, the next day; he said no more, but got all things in Rea∣diness, both for me, and himself, and co∣ming to me the next morning: Are you ready, Madam? Said he: Why? An∣swered I, Have you got every thing, as it should be? Every thing, answered he, even to one, of my young Master's Suits, which he was pleased to bestow on me, when he went into <HI>Hungary;</HI> for I believe it impossible for a Woman to get through
<PB N="136" REF="73"/>
so many rude Men, without receiving some Affronts: I readily accepted his Kindness, assuring him I should gratifie, him for that, and all his other Troubles and Civilities; and in Conclusion, I got∣on Horse-back, accoutred like an absolute Cadett, and he like my Servant, both well provided with Arms.</P>
<P>Our Design was to get into the Camp, where we were to inquire after <HI>Peregrine,</HI> and so to have conversed with him, how to have proceeded; but when, after a long search, we had no other News of him, but that it was believed he was kil∣led, because his Horse had been found dead, with a Shot; we then resolved to attempt the getting into the Town, as Deserters, so soon as possible we could; to that pur∣pose, we were in the Night time, getting as close as we could to the Wall, when we were espied by a single Horseman, who making after us, shot at us, and kill'd the poor Faulkner; I perceiving him fall, fea∣ring that my turn would be next, slack'd my pace, and turning my Horse, cried, I yield, save my Life, and you shall have a Ransome; my pursuer seem'd satisfied with that, and was going to secure me, from an escape, when we were presently
<PB N="137" REF="73"/>
surrounded with a Party of Horse, that was retiring into the Town, which took us along with them. You have heard since, how it proved to be the Count, that had taken me Prisoner, but how he hap∣pened on me, or what he was doing there, I am still to learn.</P>
<P>Thus did <HI>Mariana</HI> put an end to her Narrative; they spent the rest of the day, in contriving how <HI>Peregrine</HI> should meet with his Friends, and how they shall dis∣pose of themselves, after things were set∣iled again in the Town; <HI>Mariana</HI> said, That she long'd to see them all safe re∣turned to their own homes: What say you to it, Madam, said <HI>Peregrine,</HI> Must I return to my own home also? That would be too far a Journey for you to perform at once, replied <HI>Clarinda;</HI> you shall rest your self some time, at the Ca∣stle; and then I must begon, added <HI>Pe∣regrine:</HI> Goodness, cried <HI>Clarinda,</HI> you are such a troublesome Man, you shall stay there till you are sent away: That may be the next day after, Madam, an∣swered <HI>Peregrine,</HI> or so soon as your Bro∣ther returns, if you do not anticipate him in that employ: Shall I propose an expe∣dient, said <HI>Mariana,</HI> that will salve all?
<PB N="138" REF="74"/>
Let's hear it, answered <HI>Clarinda:</HI> Nay, will you stand to it, added <HI>Mariana,</HI> I as∣sure you, before hand, it shall be to both your Likings, and Advantages? I will stand to it, cried <HI>Peregrine,</HI> irrevocably: What say you, Madam? added he, to <HI>Clarinda:</HI> Upon <HI>Marianas</HI> assurance, I care not if I do: Give me your Hands to the Bargain, said <HI>Mariana;</HI> with that she took both their Hands, and joined them together, saying, Marry, without delay: Spoken like an Angel, cried out <HI>Peregrine,</HI> with Joy; and finding <HI>Cla∣rinda</HI> to pull back her Hand, and to look surprised: Nay, Madam, added he, it is too late to draw back, we have your consent: I did not think, said <HI>Clarinda,</HI> that <HI>Mariana</HI> would have served me so; I believed her more firm to my In∣terests: Can I be more firm to <HI>Clarindas</HI> Interest, answered <HI>Mariana,</HI> than to pro∣mote them to the outmost of my Power? What can be more your Interest, than to be inseparably united to what you Love; What is there more Advantagious for you, than to once be fixed in <HI>Peregrine's</HI> Arms? So fix'd, as not to be remov'd but by Death: All this is true, Madam, added <HI>Peregrine,</HI> If your Heart does not gain-say
<PB N="139" REF="74"/>
your Mouth, add the last of your Bles∣sings, in assenting to what our dear <HI>Mari∣ana</HI> has so justly proposed? Nay, she can∣not deny me for shame, said <HI>Mariana;</HI> of she should, I should for ever dis-own her for my Friend; but I know she will not, she has too much of Justice, of Sense, and of Love for me, besides what she has for you, Sir, to act against her own Satis∣faction, and Quiet; Come, I must have it so, added she, bringing <HI>Clarinda,</HI> near to <HI>Peregrine,</HI> and giving her Hand to him once more; Tell him, you are his, and that you will confirm it, by Marriage, with the first opportunity: Well, replied <HI>Clarinda,</HI> on Condition that you shall not refuse to do that which I shall propose to you, <HI>Mariana,</HI> I will: Then spake <HI>Clarinda,</HI> answered <HI>Mariana;</HI> spake to <HI>Peregrine,</HI> then next to me: Well then, said <HI>Clarinda,</HI> with a soft sigh, since it must be so, <HI>Clarinda</HI> is yours, Sir, here is my Hand to it, and so soon as opportu∣nity shall offer it self, I will be Married to you: I leave you to guess at <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s Transports, for I cannot express them: Now, added <HI>Clarinda;</HI> let me speak to you, <HI>Mariana,</HI> Love the Count, and endeav∣our to make him yours: Very well re∣partied,
<PB N="140" REF="75"/>
I'll swear, said <HI>Peregrine;</HI> and I add, may you by that means be the cause of our perfect Reconciliation: <HI>Amen,</HI> said <HI>Clarinda;</HI> nay, if you will all have it so, I say <HI>Amen</HI> too. After this, Supper was ser∣ved in; they cat and drank, and were merry; <HI>Peregrine</HI> walked about the Cham∣ber; and after they had tired themselves, with Mirth, <HI>Clarinda,</HI> at <HI>Peregrine</HI>'s re∣quest, took her Lute, and Sung those Lines, which <HI>Peregrine</HI> had made; and when it came to the two last, they all in Consort Sang,</P>
<LG>
<L><HI>So were they heard, no longer to complain;</HI></L>
<L><HI>But liv'd to Love, and lov'd to Live again.</HI></L>
</LG>
<P>Thus they concluded the Evening, after which, they went to their Re∣pose.</P>
<P>The next Morning, was the Day ap∣pointed for the Garrison to March out, and the Confederates to March in, accor∣ding to the Capitulation that had been made: The Imperiallists drew up their Army, in two Ranks, by Six in the Mor∣ning, to receive their Enemies; divers of the Imperial Cavalry, posted themselves, on the Right of the <HI>Gaw-Gate;</HI> on the
<PB N="141" REF="75"/>
Left side, were chiefly to be seen, the Guards du Corps, of the Duke of <HI>Bavaria;</HI> and next to them, those of the Duke of <HI>Saxony,</HI> with some other Troops of the Imperial Cavalry, and Dragoons; after which, the <HI>French</HI> began to March out of the City, to the number of 6690 Men, with 572 loaded Horses, 334 Carts, 31 Mules, 43 Light Horse-Men, 6 Chaires, 2 Coaches, 1 Litter, 36 Colours, and 10 Standards.</P>
<P>Besides, there were put into Boats, which had been sent from <HI>Strasbourg,</HI> with Ammunition for the <HI>French,</HI> 6 Pie∣ces of Cannon, 2 Mortars, 2 Hawbitz, and 1500 Sick, whereof, some died con∣tinually, which they threw over into the <HI>Rhine.</HI> As the Marquiss <HI>D'Ʋxelles</HI> mar∣ched out of the Garrison, he took his leave of the Duke of <HI>Lorrain,</HI> of the Elector of <HI>Saxony,</HI> and of that of <HI>Bavaria;</HI> as also, of all the rest of the Princes, and Generals; The <HI>French</HI> declared, that before the Siege, the Garrison consisted of 11000 Men. The time of their March out of the Gar∣rison, was from Seven in the Morning, till Three in the Afternoon; after which, the Allies took Possession of the City. Up∣on the <HI>French</HI> marching out, <HI>Peregrine,</HI>
<PB N="142" REF="76"/>
and the two Ladies, got at the top of the House, whence they could very distinctly see the whole Garrison March.</P>
<P>The Count, on the other hand, upon mature Considerations, had taken now Measures; he was resolved to slight those who slighed him, and to esteem those who vallued him; so that now his whole de∣signs were altered, which put him upon writing this Letter to <HI>Mariana.</HI></P>
<LETTER>
<P>It has always been counted an ill thing to strive against a too rapid stream; I have too long done so, while I might have swom down easily, with the currant; I have at last found out my obstinacy, in indeavouring to compel Love, not considering that it is as tameless as it is blind; henceforwards, I will endea∣vour to Love, where I have hopes to be belo∣ved again. I humbly require the beautious <HI>Marianas</HI> Advice, on this point, she being a Person, to whom I acknowledge my self infi∣nitely obliged, and of so sweet a Disposition, as not to refuse her Counsel, to the Ʋnfor∣tunate</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Count</HI> Mansfeilt.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P><PB N="143" REF="76"/>
This Letter was, by his Direction, pri∣vately conveyed into <HI>Marianas</HI> own Hands, by a Maid Servant of the House, who promised to return an Answer safe, if she pleased to give her one: <HI>Mariana</HI> was strangely surprised, at the reading of this Letter, she did not know well what to make of it, she was loth to flatter her self too much, and as unwilling to take advice of her best Friends, for fear they should think her too conceited of her self, and apt to receive Amorous Impressions; she therefore concluded to consider very maturely on the Business, and then send an Answer as suitable, as she could, to her Modesty, and her Desires; she fancied that her Kindness towards the Count, when abandoned of all, and the commi∣serating Looks, she cast on him, when she left him last, might have had some kind Influence over his Mind, that seeing he had resolved to take off his Affections from <HI>Clarinda,</HI> as he seemed to intimate, he might as well have some Thoughts of her, as he had had of <HI>Clarinda,</HI> to whom, she thought not her self Inferiour in Birth, nor not much in Estate, except her Bro∣ther should chance to die: These, and
<PB N="144" REF="77"/>
many more Thoughts, of the like nature running in her Mind, she resolved to send the Count an Answer, as Modest as she could, which she conceived in these Terms.</P>
<LETTER>
<P>I have always professed my self, a Friend to the afflicted, and so long as I have thought you so, I have been made sensible of your Troubles; but now I find you are in the right way of getting out of your Adversities, I withdraw my pity, you having no further oc∣casion for it; What need a Man ask the way that is in the right road? You have a suffici∣ent Esiate, not to confine you to Match for Riches only, and you want not Sense, to pre∣fer Discretion, good Nature, and Comeliness, to the bare shadow of Beauty. I can there∣fore contribute no more, than my Wishes for your Happiness, which I desire, as I do that of your humble Servant,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Mariana.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P><PB N="145" REF="77"/>
When the Count received this, he was in a great perplexity, as to the Nature of <HI>Marianas</HI> Answer, till he had read it; he opened it, and read, with that Satisfacti∣on, that made him repeat it over again, though he saw a world of good Nature in it; and he resolved by one Letter more to know the bottom of <HI>Marianas</HI> Heart; he was in haste, because he believed that his late Mistress, and his Rival, was so to; and he designed to be before hand with them, that his new choice might appear as a contempt; not doubting of <HI>Marianas</HI> Discretion, in keeping the Business Secret, at the least notice, that he desired it should be so; he therefore, gratifying well the Messenger for what he had already done, and promising him a farther Bounty, he sent him immediately back, with this Answer.</P>
<LETTER>
<P>If the obliging <HI>Mariana</HI> would but nomi∣nate any Person, whom she thought would be a proper Subject for my Love, I should think my self extremely obliged to her; but how surprised should I be, with a transport of joy, should she vouchsafe to name her self. My
<PB N="146" REF="78"/>
Design is to anticipate <HI>Clarindas,</HI> and my late Rivals haste, and to be fixt in my choice, before they have concluded theirs: Let my dear <HI>Mariana,</HI> be so kind, as not to delay sending me word, whether she will accept of my Person and Fortune, that I may thereby be in hopes of possessing her; this requires such haste, and secrecy, as beggs for a suddain definitive Answer, to the most impatient</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Count <HI>Mansfeilt.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P>This was sufficient to inform <HI>Mariana,</HI> in every particular Circumstance, of the Count's Design; she could not but see that this fit, was the effects of a Contempt and Revenge; she had no time to loose, know∣ing how forward <HI>Clarinda</HI> and <HI>Peregrine</HI> were in their Concerns; she was pleased with the Surprisal, and knew before-hand, that her dear <HI>Clarinda,</HI> would be exceed∣ingly pleased with it; she verily believed the Count to be Worthy and Just, where∣fore, she thought she had no more to do, but to throw her self on his Honour, and to readily embrace the offer; she there∣fore sent him presently back, this short Answer.</P>
<LETTER>
<PB N="147" REF="78"/>
<P>I put such Confidence in your Word and Honour, that though I might think my self, unworthy your choice, I wholly relie on them both; I therefore resign my self to be your Wife, when e're you shall think fit to bestow that Honour on,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Humble Servant,
Mariana.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P>The Count was so fully satisfied, with this short, but full Answer, from <HI>Maria∣na,</HI> that he now went about to contrive how he should make this Secret March break out to his greater Credit and Ad∣vantage, as well as to his Antagonists Sur∣prisal; so soon as his Kinsman▪ Count <HI>Zinzendorf,</HI> was marched into the Town, he repaired to him, and the better to dis∣guise his Intentions, he began to harp a∣gain on the Picture, which he believed <HI>Peregrine</HI> had taken from him; <HI>Zinzen∣dorf</HI> told him, that he had found out where <HI>Peregrine</HI> lay, that he would go and acquaint <HI>Peregrine</HI> with what he had said, and he would bring him back his
<PB N="148" REF="79"/>
Answer, being very desirous to make a thorough Reconciliation bet wixt them, as being Friend to both, telling him besides, he thought that the best expedient to ap∣pease all disputes, between them, concern∣ing <HI>Clarinda,</HI> would be to have them both stand to her Decision, in making choice of whom she liked best: The Count see∣med to give his consent, by saying, Do what you please: So Count <HI>Zinzendorf</HI> went immediately to find out <HI>Peregrine,</HI> and to discourse the business with him; he found his Friend in company with <HI>Clarinda</HI> and <HI>Mariana:</HI> After the first Embraces and Compliments to the Ladies, as well as to his Friend, who had ac∣quainted him with their Qualities, he took <HI>Peregrine</HI> aside, to let him understand what Count <HI>Mansfeilt</HI> had said to him. As for the Picture, said <HI>Peregrine,</HI> I own I took it from him, and shall restore it him again, when e'er he requires it; but I know of no wrong I ever did him; I had engag'd my Affections to this Lady, added he, before I knew any thing of his pretensions, and had had obliging returns from her; and therefore I find not in what I have incurr'd his displeasure; but if he is pleased to let the Lady decide our
<PB N="149" REF="79"/>
difference, I shall readily submit to it: If you please to press the Business to him, that our differences may be ended forth∣with, I shall be infinitely oblig'd to you. Count <HI>Zinzendorf,</HI> whose business in set∣ling his Quarters, call'd him another way, made what hast he could back to Count <HI>Mansfeilt,</HI> and acquainted him with <HI>Pe∣regrine</HI>'s Answer, and did further bring the Count to pitch on a certain Hour the next Day, to meet all together, and there make up all Discords. The Count, who thought himself sure of <HI>Mariana,</HI> agreed to all; whereupon Count <HI>Zinzendorf</HI> left him, to send an account to <HI>Peregrine</HI> of the Hour and Place the Count had nam'd for the Rendezvouz.</P>
<P>The next Day, at the Hour appointed, all Parties met at Count <HI>Zinzendorf</HI>'s Quarters, where <HI>Mariana</HI> was sure to make one. Count <HI>Zinzendorf</HI> broke the Ice, saying, That seeing both Parties were agreed to stand to the Lady's Decision, he humbly intreated her to determine, which of those Gentlemen she would please to make choice of for her Husband. At this Count <HI>Mansfeilt</HI> cryed out, Which Lady do you mean? And stepping up to <HI>Mari∣ana,</HI> taking her by the Hand, This is the
<PB N="150" REF="80"/>
only Lady I desire should speak that De∣cree. What say you Madam, will you make me so happy, as to make choice of me for your Husband? This he said, looking fixedly on <HI>Mariana,</HI> and expect∣ing her answer. Yes Sir, answered <HI>Ma∣riana,</HI> if you please to consent to my choice. With that, the Count kiss'd her, and said, Bear Witness all, that I take this Gentlewoman, my dear <HI>Mariana,</HI> to be my Wife; and that I will Marry her so soon as I can get any one to do that Office for us: And now Madam, said he, addressing himself to <HI>Clarinda,</HI> I have been before-hand with you, you may now make choice of whom you please. Count <HI>Zinzendorf,</HI> after this, said, All things go very well hitherto; I should be glad to see the rest prosper so well also: My Friend <HI>Peregrine,</HI> you are now to ex∣pect what that Lady will declare. He need not, Sir, answered <HI>Clarinda,</HI> I have al∣ready given my self to him; and now I ratifie it before all this Company. At which <HI>Peregrine</HI> return'd her his most humble Thanks.</P>
<P>There are but two things more to be done, said Count <HI>Zinzendorf;</HI> you Sir, are to make Restitution of that Picture, which
<PB N="151" REF="80"/>
once <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell to your Lot: Let him keep it, with the Original, now, if he pleases, said Count <HI>Mansfeilt,</HI> interupting him; I am intirely satisfied, with this Jewel, added he, pres∣sing <HI>Mariana</HI> by the Hand: Now, for the last, said Count <HI>Zinzendorf,</HI> I would glad∣ly see a through Reconciliation betwixt you, both my worthy Friends, such as may be as durable as your Lives: It shall not be my fault, I assure you, said <HI>Peregrine,</HI> of∣fering forwards, towards the Count: Count <HI>Mansfeilt,</HI> who would not be behind him, in point of good Nature, as the Cause of our Differences is now taken a∣way; I am desirous, that what has past be∣tween us, of Jars, and Animosities, should be forgotten; with that, they both em∣braced; and, after felicitating one ano∣thers Happiness, they all retired to <HI>Pere∣grine</HI>'s Lodgings, till they had time to get some more convenient for them all.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<PB REF="81"/>
<HEAD>Books newly Printed for <HI>Sam. Briscoe,</HI> over against <HI>Will's</HI> Coffee House, in <HI>Russel▪ Street,</HI> in <HI>Covent-Garden.</HI></HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. WIves Excuse, or Cuckolds make themselves, a Comedy, by Mr. <HI>Southern;</HI> with a Copy of Verses on the Play, by Mr. <HI>Driden.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. The Marriage-Hater matched; a Comedy, by Mr. <HI>Durfey.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Traytor, a Tragedy; newly re∣viv'd; Written by Mr. <HI>Rivers.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>4. The true Widow, a Comedy; Written by <HI>Thomaes Shandwell. Lauri.</HI>—</ITEM>
<ITEM>5. The Lives of the 12 <HI>Caesars,</HI> the first Emperors of <HI>Rome:</HI> Written in <HI>Latin,</HI> by <HI>C. Suetonius Tranquillius,</HI> and done into <HI>English</HI> by several Gentlemen of the Ʋni∣versity of <HI>Oxford.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>6. Advice to a young Lord; written by his Father, under these following Heads; Religion, Study and Exercise, Travel, Marriage, House-keeping and Hospitality, of the Court, of Friendship, of Pleasure, and Idleness, of Conversation.</ITEM>
<ITEM>7. Sir <HI>William Temple</HI>'s Essays.</ITEM>
<ITEM>8. <HI>Ovid</HI>'s Epistles, Translated by seve∣ral Hands, adorned with Cuts.</ITEM>
<ITEM>9. The Works of <HI>Horace,</HI> Translated by Mr. <HI>Creech,</HI> of <HI>Oxford.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>10. The <HI>London-Jilt;</HI> or the Female Cuckolds a new Novel.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<PB REF="81"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

