<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The spirit convincing of sinne opened in a sermon before the Honorable House of Commons, assembled in Parliament upon the solemne day of their monethly fast, Novemb. 26, 1645 / by Peter Sterry ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Sterry, Peter, 1613-1672.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A61475</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing S5483</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R34606</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">14522660</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 14522660</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">102509</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A61475)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102509)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1071:27)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The spirit convincing of sinne opened in a sermon before the Honorable House of Commons, assembled in Parliament upon the solemne day of their monethly fast, Novemb. 26, 1645 / by Peter Sterry ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Sterry, Peter, 1613-1672.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[6], 36 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Matth. Simmons for Henry Overton and Benjamin Allen ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1645.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>"Published by order of the House of Commons."</NOTE><NOTE>Imperfect: pages stained.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XVI, 8 --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Fast-day sermons.</TERM><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A61475">
<STC T="W">S5483</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">14522660</BIBNO>
<VID>102509</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
SPIRIT
CONVINCING
OF SINNE. OPENED
In a Sermon before the Honorable
HOUSE of COMMONS,
Assembled in Parliament upon the solemne
day of their Monethly Fast,
<HI>Novemb.</HI> 26. 1645.</P>
<P>By PETER STERRY, sometimes Fellow
of <HI>Emanuel Colledge</HI> in <HI>Cambridge.</HI> AND NOW
Preacher of the Gospel in LONDON.</P>
<P>Published by Order of the House of Commons.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by <HI>Matth. Simmons,</HI> for <HI>Henry Overton,</HI> and <HI>Benjamin
Allen,</HI> and are to be sold at their shops in
Popes-head Alley, 1645.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To THE
HONOURABLE
THE
KNIGHTS &amp; BURGESSES
OF THE
HOUSE of COMMONS
Assembled in
PARLIAMENT.</HEAD>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">G</SEG>OD</HI> hath promised his people to carry
them on the <HI>Eagles Wing.</HI> The
onely desire and humble endeavour
of your lowest servant in Christ, hath
been to work with God in this Ser∣mon;
that your Soules, Counsels,
Warres, may be carried on by the
Spirit of God; who in the language
of the Scriptures is not onely the <HI>Dove</HI> for <HI>Purity</HI>
and <HI>Peace;</HI> but also the <HI>True Eagle</HI> for <HI>Wisdome</HI> and
<HI>Power.</HI></P>
<P><PB REF="3"/>
Worthy Senatours, if you knew this Spirit, you
would ask <HI>Him</HI> of your Saviour; and Hee would be in
you a Fountain of Counsell and Strength springing up
to Everlasting Peace and Glory. But have you not
known <HI>The Spirit?</HI> His sound hath gone forth
into all your Eares. All the Scriptures speak of <HI>Him</HI>
as they doe of <HI>Jesus Christ.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Daniel</HI> was chosen by the King of Assyria to sway
the great affaires of that vast Empire; because the <HI>Spi∣rit
of the immortall God</HI> was found in him.</P>
<P><HI>David</HI> was a <HI>Statesman, Wiser then his Tea∣chers:
David</HI> was a <HI>Souldier;</HI> His fingers were
skil'd in fighting, his hands train'd up to Victory o∣ver
Wild Beasts, Giants, Armies of Men. was not
the <HI>Spirit</HI> the <HI>Lamp</HI> of God which shone thus glori∣ously
on <HI>David's</HI> Court and Camp, which made his
Throne so great? <HI>Thy Word,</HI> saith he, <HI>was a Light to
my Feet.</HI> The Word of God is the Spirit of God, saith
<HI>S<SUP>t</SUP>. Paul; The Sword of the Spirit,</HI><NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, as rela∣ting to <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> not <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, as relating to <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>which (Spirit,</HI>
not <HI>Sword) is the Word of God.</HI> This made <HI>Da∣vid</HI>
when hee had sin'd, cry: Take not thine Holy Spi∣rit
from me. When the Spirit of God once left <HI>Saul,</HI>
an evill Spirit came upon him, which vex't him,
which haunted him to the losse of his kingdome and life
together.</P>
<P>Honourable Fathers of your Countries, I humbly
move to know, By what Title you sit there and rule o∣ver
us. Is it not as <HI>Powers on Earth?</HI> But <HI>All
power on Earth</HI> as well as in Heaven, is given to
Iesus Christ. You are Substitutes and Vice-gerents to
the Lord Iesus. Look then to Iesus the Beginning and
End of your Authority. God hath laid the Government
<PB REF="3"/>
on his Shoulder. What is his sufficiency for it? The Spi∣rit
of the Lord resteth on him, and this is, A Spirit of
Counsell and Might in him.</P>
<P>You who sit at the right hand of the Lord Iesus, in
this Common-wealth, as the Lord Iesus sits at the right
hand of his Father in that Kingdome, which is over all:
pray, that the same Spirit, which was powred forth on
him, may be by him powred forth on you: So shall you be
<HI>Messiahs,</HI> anointed ones, and <HI>Saviours</HI> to this people.
Can <HI>You</HI> be able to rule over any spot of this earth;
when <HI>Jesus Christ</HI> was not fit for the government of
the whole; without the Spirit?</P>
<P>Do you put your whole trust in the promises of God,
and expect by them to be made partakers of every blessing?
Do you believe the promises made in the Word of God? I
hope, I may say, at least with as good confidence, as <HI>Paul</HI>
said it to <HI>Agrippa;</HI> I know you believe them.</P>
<P>This is the promise: <HI>The Spirit shall lead you into
all truth.</HI> You are now searching into the deep things
of God, which concern <HI>Religion;</HI> Live in the Spirit,
and the Spirit shall bring all into your minde, and shew
you the things of Iesus Christ. It behoves you to know
the method of Satan; the stratagems and dark deeps of
the Devill himself, in mysteries of <HI>State</HI> and <HI>Religi∣on.</HI>
Walk in the Spirit; hee shall lead you into their
chambers, as hee did <HI>Ezekiel;</HI> and let you see what
mischiefes they are there contriving in secret.</P>
<P>This is the promise: <HI>The Spirit of God and of glory
shall rest on his servants, in their conflicts and suffer∣ings.</HI>
Sit still in all humble resignation of your selves, to
the working of this Spirit; that hee may rest on you: so
shall hee manage your counsels, finish your wars; and
<PB REF="4"/>
end all your sufferings with <HI>glorie.</HI></P>
<P>I shall conclude my Epistle with an <HI>humble Petition
to</HI> your Honours: <HI>an hearty Prayer for</HI> you.</P>
<P>My humble Petition is, that You would ever remem∣ber
to converse as <HI>Doves,</HI> among <HI>Doves;</HI> with <HI>this
Dove;</HI> He is a tender Spirit, take heed of grieving
<HI>this Spirit,</HI> where ever hee dwels: For by him alone
can your hopes be sealed to a day of full accomplish∣ment.</P>
<P>My <HI>hearty Prayer</HI> is, <HI>that,</HI> as you sit debating in
Parliament, the appearances of the Holy Ghost may be
among you; as hee was with the Apostles, sitting over
them in the form of fiery tongues: <HI>that</HI> when you fight
in the field, the Holy Ghost may be as a two-edged sword
going forth from the mouth of the Lord Iesus into your
enemy's hearts: <HI>that</HI> you may never see upon the walls of
your house, that hand-writing which made <HI>Bel-shazzer</HI>
tremble; <HI>Your kingdome is divided;</HI> but in stead of
this, that uniting and building Principle; <HI>Not by
might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, saith the
Lord.</HI> This is the fervent, constant prayer of</P>
<SIGNED>Your Honours
humble servant in Christ,
<HI>Peter Sterry.</HI></SIGNED>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A
SERMON PREACHED
Before the honorable House of
COMMONS,
<DATE>Novemb. 26. 1645.</DATE> being the publike Fast.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>JOHN 16. 8.</BIBL>
<Q>When he shall come, he shall convince
the world of sin, &amp;c.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Will at once open to you the
publike scope of this place; and
the private sense of my Text,
as it lies imbodied in the Con∣text.</P>
<P>Our tender-hearted Saviour
is now cheering the hearts of his
Disciples, drooping with the sad
presages of their dear Master's death.</P>
<P>The Lord Jesus sweetly gives them for a revivall
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
of their fainting spirits, a gracious promise of his
own Spirit.</P>
<P>This Promise is threefold,
<HI>The Spirit's</HI><LIST>
<ITEM>1. Personall Comming,</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Particular Comforts,</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Universall Convictions.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>Pardon me, if I be somewhat larger in the Expli∣cation
of these. For this also will serve my purpose;
which is, to set before you the <HI>Spirit</HI> of the Lord
Jesus; that <HI>Spirit,</HI> by which we know those things,
which <HI>Reason</HI> cannot reach; and live, not<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 3. 3.</NOTE> as <HI>Men,</HI>
(<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) but as<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">2 Pet. 1. 4.</NOTE> <HI>Partakers of the Divine Nature.</HI></P>
<P>The first Promise is the <HI>Personall comming.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Pro.</HI> 1.</NOTE> This
hath two parts. <HI>The</HI><LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Person</HI> comming.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Comming</HI> of that Person.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><HI>Part</HI> 1<SUP>st</SUP>. The first part is the <HI>Person</HI> comming. It
appears to be a <HI>Person</HI> of whom our Saviour speaks,
by those demonstrative particles: <HI>Hee: Him.</HI> It
appeares to be some great One, a <HI>Divine Person,</HI> by
those workes, which are to be done by him: To com∣fort
hearts: To convince a world: To be in stead of
Christ; nay, to be a better Comforter then Christ
himselfe in the flesh.</P>
<P>Commentators, Common-placers, Controver∣siaries,
School-men; all sorts of Divines in general,
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
chuse this place, and such like places in this dying
discourse of our Saviour's; for principall proofes of
this fundamental point in Divinity; that, the <HI>Blessed
Spirit</HI> is not onely, <HI>The Power of the Godhead,</HI> but, <HI>A
Person in the Godhead.</HI> For, say they, Christ speakes
of him as of a <HI>Person; Hee; Him:</HI> and as of a <HI>Di∣stinct
Person</HI> in the Trinity, <HI>Joh. 14. 16. Another</HI>
Comforter. Another besides Jesus Christ.</P>
<P>Now these places with the same force prove it to
be the same Person, which was to come to the Dis∣ciples.
For Christ speaks of him not <HI>simply,</HI> but <HI>in
respect</HI> of his <HI>comming.</HI></P>
<P>Part. 2. <HI>The second part of this Promise is; The</HI>
comming <HI>of that Person. School-men call the</HI> com∣ming
<HI>of the</HI> Spirit: Novus modus Existendi &amp; Appa∣rendi:
A new way of the Spirit's Being in men, and Ap∣pearing
to men.</P>
<P>All that I shall say concerning it, amounts to this.
The Scriptures very often represent the <HI>Comming of
Christ</HI> in the flesh, &amp; this <HI>Comming</HI> of the <HI>Spirit</HI> in the
same formes of Expression. I have cul'd forth these
five: <HI>Comming, Sending, Giving, Dwelling, Appearing.</HI></P>
<P>1<SUP>st</SUP> <HI>Comming.</HI> You read of the <HI>Comming</HI> of Shi∣loh,
which is Christ: <HI>Hee, to whom. Gen.</HI> 49. 10. My
Text tells you of the <HI>comming</HI> of the Spirit. The
Divine and Humane Nature are, as it were, two
termes of reciprocall motion, for these two glori∣ous
Persons.</P>
<P>2<SUP>d</SUP>. <HI>Sending.</HI> The Father <HI>sends</HI> the Son, <HI>Joh.</HI> 3.
17. The Son sends the Spirit, in the verse going be∣fore
my Text. The Father's <HI>Love-token</HI> to man, is
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
<HI>his own Son.</HI> The Son's <HI>Love-token</HI> to his spouse, is
<HI>his own Spirit.</HI></P>
<P>3<SUP>d</SUP>. <HI>Giving.</HI> Christ is the <HI>Gift</HI> of God to the
world, <HI>Joh.</HI> 3. 16. S. <HI>Paul</HI> tells us that the holy
Ghost is <HI>given</HI> to us, <HI>Rom.</HI> 5. 5. In a <HI>Gift</HI> there is a
<HI>conferring of Propriety,</HI> and <HI>Possession.</HI></P>
<P>4. <HI>Dwelling.</HI> Joh. 1. 14. <HI>The Word was made Flesh,
and dwelt among us.</HI> 2 Tim. 1. 14. <HI>By the holy Ghost
which dwelleth in thee.</HI> These two Texts have this dif∣ference.
Christ dwels in Flesh, as in a <HI>Tabernacle,</HI> or
<HI>Tent,</HI> like a Pilgrim or Souldier. The Spirit dwels
in <HI>Timothy</HI> as at home, in his owne house.</P>
<P>5. <HI>Appearing.</HI> Christ is <HI>God manifested in Flesh,</HI>
1 Tim. 3. 16. Jesus speakes of the Spirit to his A∣postles,
<HI>You shall know him,</HI> Joh. 14. 17. These two
are distinct Persons in respect of their <HI>Appearances,</HI>
as well as <HI>Subsistencies.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</P>
<P>This concurrency of expressions seems to signifie
that these two <HI>Commings</HI> of <HI>Christ</HI> in the Flesh, and
of the <HI>Spirit,</HI> are <HI>True, Reall Unions</HI> of God with
Man; <HI>True, Reall Appearances</HI> of God to man; in
these two Persons of the Trinity, the Son, the Spi∣rit.
But with this threefold difference.</P>
<P>First, the <HI>Cōming</HI> of <HI>Christ</HI> in the flesh is a Union of
two Natures in one Person. This is that w<SUP>ch</SUP> we call
the <HI>Hypostaticall Union;</HI> where there is a distinction
of Natures without a distinction of Persons or sub∣sistencies.
The <HI>Comming</HI> of the <HI>Spirit</HI> is a union
between <HI>Persons</HI> as well as <HI>Natures.</HI> Here is a <HI>Distin∣ction</HI>
and a <HI>Union</HI> both at once, between <HI>Natures</HI> and
<HI>Persons</HI> joyntly. Compare those two places of
Scripture, 1 Cor. 6. 17. <HI>He that is joyned to the Lord,
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
is one Spirit.</HI> and <HI>Rom. 8. 16. The Spirit witnesseth
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith our spirits.</HI> The result of these will be; that
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Spirit of <HI>Christ,</HI> and of a <HI>Christian,</HI> are <HI>two spi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>its,
by distinction of persons, one by Union.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, the <HI>coming</HI> of <HI>Christ</HI> was into the broad
street of the same common nature of man; to be
<HI>with</HI> us; yet so, as to be <HI>without</HI> us. The coming
of the <HI>Spirit</HI> is into our particular persons as into
the same house with us. See this Opposition, <HI>Gal.</HI>
4. chap. 4. verse. <HI>He hath sent his Son, [made of a
woman];</HI> that is, made of the humane nature. Then,
vers. 6. <HI>He hath sent the Spirit of his Son into our
[Hearts].</HI> Christ came into our <HI>flesh.</HI> The Spirit
comes into our <HI>hearts;</HI> so as to be both <HI>with</HI> us,
and <HI>within</HI> us, <HI>John</HI> 14. chap. 16. verse. <HI>He dwelleth
[with] you, and shall be [in] you.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, the <HI>comming of Christ</HI> in the flesh, was
visible to all alike, to the eye of sense. But the <HI>com∣ing</HI>
of the <HI>Spirit</HI> is invisible to all the world; vi∣sible
only to those who receive him, <HI>Joh.</HI> c. 14. v. 16.
<HI>The world seeth him not, but ye shall know him, for he shall
be in you.</HI> To these he is visible <HI>inwardly,</HI> and after a
spirituall manner.</P>
<P>This is the first Promise, The <HI>Personall coming.</HI></P>
<P>The second Promise is,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prom. 2.</NOTE> The <HI>particular comforts</HI> of
the Spirit: He shall come as <HI>Comforter,</HI> saith the
verse immediately foregoing my Text.</P>
<P>But can any thing comfort a Spouse that mourns
for her beloved One, besides his own presence? ther∣fore
this makes the <HI>Spirit, a Comforter indeed;</HI> He
brings <HI>Christ</HI> for a <HI>comfort</HI> along with him. <HI>Christ</HI> was
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
to live again in the <HI>Spirit,</HI> 1 Pet. 3. c. 18. v. <HI>He was
crucified in the flesh, but quickened by the Spirit. Christ</HI>
was to appeare again to them in the <HI>Spirit,</HI> and to be
for ever with them, <HI>Joh.</HI> 15. chap. 26. vers. <HI>When the
Spirit come, he shall testifie of me.</HI> The <HI>Spirit</HI> was to
give them a <HI>second Sight</HI> of their Husband, in a more
true, divine, lasting way; as he was unvailed of flesh,
and in his own heavenly form.</P>
<P>Yea, this <HI>Comfort</HI> was to be <HI>doubled</HI> at the coming
of the <HI>Spirit:</HI> For the Father was to <HI>come</HI> along
with his deare Son, <HI>Joh.</HI> 14. c. 23. v. <HI>I, and the Fa∣ther
will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</HI>
But which way would these Persons of glory come
to lodge themselves in the humble Cottage of a
Saints heart? In the <HI>Spirit.</HI> This Person was to be
the Chariot for the other two. Therefore but two
verses after this Promise, <HI>Christ</HI> explains it by ano∣ther
Promise, that of the <HI>coming</HI> of the <HI>Comforter:</HI>
And S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>Paul</HI> tels us, that we have accesse to the
Father, by <HI>one Spirit,</HI> Ephes. 2. <HI>c. 18. v.</HI> Thus the
<HI>Father, Son, Spirit,</HI> and a <HI>Saint,</HI> dwell all together,
and converse: The <HI>Father</HI> and <HI>Son</HI> in the <HI>Spirit;</HI> the
<HI>Spirit</HI> in our hearts. This is that <HI>Unity</HI> of the <HI>Spirit,</HI>
which is the <HI>band</HI> of <HI>Comforts,</HI> Ephes. 4. <HI>c. 3. v.</HI></P>
<P>The third Promise is the <HI>Universall Convictions</HI>
of the Spirit.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prom. 3.</NOTE> Christ and his Disciples were singu∣lar
in the world; they saw those things whcih none
could see besides themselves: <HI>Blessed are your eyes, for
they see.</HI> They were as mad men; they fill'd the
world with a noise of things, as present, reall migh∣ty
in glory; they spake every where of a rising
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
Sun, of a wonderfull Light, which made all other
lights a deep darknesse; when all this while the
whole world of men round about them could dis∣cerne
no other Sun without them, save that which
had shined from the creation untill now; no other
Light within them, besides that which their own
reason had ever in an ordinary way supplied them
withall. <HI>Isaiah</HI> prophecied of Christ and his
Disciples, <HI>Es.</HI> 8. chap. 8. v. <HI>I, and the children which
thou hast given mee, are for signes and for wonders.</HI></P>
<P>Would our Saviour now leave his Disciples alone
in such a world as this? Therefore hee comforts
them with this; that his <HI>Spirit</HI> should come and con∣vince
the world, anoint the eyes of man-kind gene∣rally,
to see the same light of divine truth with them.</P>
<P>The Text reads it, <HI>Reprove,</HI> but the word in Greek
(<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) more properly signifies <HI>to convince,</HI> as the
margin hath it.</P>
<P>This <HI>Conviction</HI> is threefold:</P>
<P>First, of <HI>Sin; Because they believe not in me.</HI> The
<HI>Spirit</HI> should shew the world this as the <HI>Center,</HI>
where all sin met in one; from whence all sin flows;
their <HI>not believing</HI> in Christ, their neglect of the Per∣son
of Christ.</P>
<P>Secondly, of <HI>Righteousnesse, because I go to my
Father,</HI><NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">John 6. 62.</NOTE> By Christs returning thither, where he
was at first; by his going back to the Father, the
Spirit should teach the world; that he alone came
forth from the Father:<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">John 3. 13.</NOTE> <HI>For no one ascendeth up to
Heaven, but the Son of man, who came down from Hea∣ven.</HI>
And by this Argument shall the Spirit de∣monstrate
Christ alone to be the Righteousnesse
of God to man.</P>
<P><PB N="8" REF="8"/>
Thirdly, of <HI>Judgement, because now the Prince of
this world is cast out.</HI> The Spirit should reade this
Lecture upon the world; how, since the fall, the
whole frame, all appearances of things, had been
one great enchantment raised and maintained up∣on
the spirits of men, by the father of lies, the
Prince of darknesse; to hide their eyes from the
sight of God. But how Jesus Christ had by his
death cast down that old Magician from his Throne
and Power; and now the whole enchantment, the
fashion or show of this world was dissolving and
vanishing, till it should appeare no more.</P>
<P>Thus large I have been in the opening of the con∣text
and Text.</P>
<P>Now, without any further stay, or needlesse divi∣sion
of my Text;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Doctr.</NOTE> my Doctrine from it is this.</P>
<P>Rightly to convince of sin, is the proper work of the
Spirit.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Proof.</NOTE></P>
<P><HI>I shall give you only one place of Scripture to
prove it; but that, I hope, a fit and full one,</HI> Zach.
12. 10. I will powre out upon them the spirit of grace
and supplications, and they shall see him, whom they
have pierced, and mourn over him.</P>
<P>You have here two successive <HI>effusions:</HI> one of
the <HI>Spirit,</HI> and another of <HI>Tears.</HI></P>
<P>First, <HI>An effusion of Teares; They shall mourne.
Mourning</HI> expresseth true Repentance in all the
foure parts of it; conviction, confession, contri∣tion,
conversion. The force of the conviction here,
as in my Text, lies in a sight of Christ pierced;
in a sense of unbelief. Not to receive <HI>Christ</HI> for
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
your Husband and King, is to Pierce him. To take
away <HI>His Crown</HI> and <HI>Your Hearts</HI> from him, is to kill
him the worst way. But this is only a Consequent
and Secondary effusion.</P>
<P>Secondly, An <HI>Effusion of spirit.</HI> This is the Ante∣cedent
Effusion. The powring forth of the Spirit
is the cause of powring forth teares. But who? or
what is this Spirit? He is markt by a double cha∣racter:
<HI>A Spirit of grace</HI> and <HI>supplication.</HI></P>
<P>First, <HI>a Spirit of grace.</HI> There is a twofold grace.
The <HI>grace</HI> of <HI>loving-kindnesse</HI> in the heart of God.
The <HI>grace</HI> of <HI>divine lovelinesse</HI> in the heart of man.
If this latter be here meant, then the <HI>Spirit of grace</HI>
is he, whom S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>Paul</HI> calls the <HI>holy Spirit,</HI> Ephes. 1.
and wee generally know by the name of the <HI>Holy
Ghost.</HI></P>
<P>But this cannot be the sense: For in the Origi∣nall,
it is <HI>chen,</HI> not <HI>chesed: Grace,</HI> or <HI>loving-kindnesse,</HI>
not <HI>graciousnesse,</HI> or <HI>goodnesse.</HI></P>
<P>This <HI>Spirit</HI> of <HI>Grace</HI> then must be, either the <HI>Spi∣rit,
the spring</HI> of love in the bosome of the Godhead:
or, the <HI>Spirit,</HI> the diffuser, the discoverer of this love
in the bosome of man. Both these are that One Spi∣rit,
the <HI>Holy Ghost.</HI> Divines give to the third Person,
the name of <HI>Love;</HI> as they do to the second, that of
<HI>Wisdome:</HI> And wee reade from S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>Paul's</HI> mouth,
<HI>Rom. 5. 5. The love of God is powred forth in our
hearts, by the Holy Ghost, which he hath given us.</HI> This
is the first character.</P>
<P>Second. <HI>A spirit of supplication.</HI> You have a
<HI>Commentary</HI> upon this character, <HI>Rom.</HI> 8. ch. 26. vers.
<HI>The Spirit helpeth our infirmities, making intercession
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
for us by groanes unexpressible.</HI> This is the <HI>Spirit</HI>
which convinceth of sin, the <HI>Holy Ghost</HI> himself.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Reasons.</HEAD>
<P>The Spirit is truth.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Reason 1.</NOTE> These are the words of the
Holy Ghost himself, 1 <HI>Joh.</HI> 5. c. 6. v. <HI>The Spirit is
truth.</HI> Truth absolutely, that is, the Highest and
fullest truth; the Principle of all truth: the first
truth, and so the last measure of all truth.</P>
<P>Take two Distinctions upon this <HI>Reason.</HI></P>
<P>Threre are three Principles of truth.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Distin.</HI> 1.</NOTE>.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. Sense.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Reason.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Spirit.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>1. Princ. <HI>Sense,</HI> Prov. 20. ch. 12. vers. <HI>The seeing
eye, and the hearing eare, God hath made them both.</HI> God
hath made the <HI>senses, standards</HI> and <HI>judges</HI> of truth,
within their own <HI>circuit,</HI> in such things, as may be
<HI>seen</HI> or <HI>heard;</HI> as appertain to <HI>sense.</HI></P>
<P>2. Princ. <HI>Reason,</HI> Prov. 20. <HI>ch. 26. vers. The spi∣rit
of man is the candle of the Lord, searching out the
hidden parts of the belly.</HI> Though the <HI>candle</HI> of <HI>Rea∣son</HI>
excell in light the Glow-worms of sense; yet is
it but a <HI>candle,</HI> not the <HI>Sun</HI> it self; it makes not
day; only shines in the darknesse of the night. You
will more clearly see this Spirit of man to be the
<HI>Principle</HI> of <HI>Reason,</HI> planted by nature in man; if
you compare this expression of <HI>Solomon's</HI> with that
of S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>Paul,</HI> which seems to have some glance towards
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
this Proverb, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 2. ch. 11. vers. <HI>No man knowes
the things of a man, but the spirit of man, which is
in man. The things of a man</HI> are all the things of
this creation, visible, invisible;<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 6. 10.</NOTE> man is the summe
of them all; all are subject to man; God hath,
<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 3. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>set this whole world in the heart of man,</HI> to search
it out; these are the <HI>hidden things of his belly:</HI> And
thus farre the spirit of man, the <HI>candle</HI> of <HI>Reason,</HI>
spreads his beams, to enlighten this <HI>world</HI> of <HI>na∣ture.</HI>
This the Scripture calls <HI>Man's Day,</HI> which is
<HI>God's</HI> and <HI>a Saint's night.</HI></P>
<P>3. Princ. <HI>The Spirit</HI> 1 Cor. 2. <HI>c. 11. v. The things
of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God. The Spirit
searcheth out the deep things of God.</HI> Divine truths are
the <HI>depths</HI> of things; the rest are only the <HI>surface.</HI>
No plummet is strong, no line long enough to
sound these depths; save only that of the <HI>Spirit.</HI></P>
<P>These three different <HI>Principles of truth</HI> consti∣tute
the three different <HI>parts</HI> or <HI>states</HI> of <HI>life:</HI></P>
<P>First, <HI>the brute part</HI> of the world; it is that which
is acted by <HI>sense.</HI></P>
<P>Seconly, <HI>Reason</HI> makes <HI>man;</HI> or the <HI>rationall state.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Thirdly,</HI> the Spirit <HI>is the principle of a</HI> Saint
<NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Rom. 8. 1.</NOTE> As many as are the sons of God, are led <HI>(or</HI> acted) by
the Spirit of God.</P>
<P>I cannot leave this <HI>Distinction</HI> betweene these
three <HI>Principles</HI> of truth, before I have annext three
<HI>Rules.</HI></P>
<P>1. Rule. <HI>Every principle of truth is to be confin'd to
its own compasse, to its own object.</HI> To seek out spi∣rituall
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
things by the sent and sagacity of reason;
were to plough with an Oxe and an Asse. <HI>Sensus
non fallitur circa proprium objectum,</HI> Sense is not de∣ceived
in judging of its own proper object. If
sense and reason make no other report but this;
<HI>This is the state of things, according to our principles:
this is the appearance of things to us:</HI> Sense and
reason may be admitted for true witnesses. But if
they will be wise beyond what is written in their
book, and say: <HI>This is the only, absolute, true appea∣rance
of things; because this is the appearance which
things make to us.</HI> Now sense and reason become blind
guides, and will lead you into the ditch: 1 <HI>Cor. 2. 12.
Spirituall things are spiritually discern'd.</HI> By pro∣portion:
<HI>sensuall</HI> things are <HI>sensually</HI> discern'd: <HI>ra∣tionall</HI>
things are <HI>rationally</HI> discern'd. You cannot
reach the things of reason by the hand of sense,
though it be stretch't out like <HI>Jeroboam's</HI> towards
the Prophet. You cannot understand spirituall
things Rationally; that is, upon the grounds of
Reason.</P>
<P>2. Ru. <HI>Right Appearances of things to one Principle
of truth, may be directly contrary to those which are right
Appearances of the same things to another Principle of
truth.</HI> The greatest lights of this world, Angels and
Invisible things, are meere darknesse to the eye of
sense. The light of this life is darknesse in the lan∣guage
of the Scripture. Darknesse it selfe is as the
light before the face of God. 1 Cor. 2. 14. <HI>The wis∣dome
of the Spirit is foolishnesse to the Naturall man.</HI> The
Apostle distinguisheth betweene two men, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
&amp; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: Man, whose Principle is <HI>Rationall
soul:</HI> and Man, whose Principle is the <HI>Spirit.</HI> That
which is <HI>Wisdome</HI> to one, is <HI>Foolishnesse</HI> to the other.</P>
<P>3. Ru. <HI>Lower Principles of Truth cannot comprehend
the Higher; but they are comprehended and judged by
these.</HI> So Philosophers say, that <HI>Reason corrects the
errors of Sense.</HI> 1 Cor. 2. 15. <HI>The spirituall man judgeth
all things, but he is judg'd or discern'd by none.</HI> ver. 9. <HI>Eye
hath not seen, eare hath not heard, neither can the heart of
mā receive the things of the Gospel.</HI> See here both Prin∣ciples
of <HI>Sense</HI> and <HI>Reason.</HI> The senses are too super∣ficial:
the large heart of Man, the vast spirit of Rea∣son
in him is too narrow to take in any thing of the
spirit. But the spirit understands them with all their
wayes and workings <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; distinctly and criti∣cally.</P>
<P>These three Principles of truth are as three
Circles upon the face of the water; one within ano∣ther:
the lesser are infolded in the greater; but can∣not
extend themselves to the wide compasse of the
greater circle, unlesse they break and vanish in them∣selves,
<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 3. 18.</NOTE> that they may become one with it. <HI>If any man
be wise, let him become a foole that he may be wise.</HI></P>
<P>The soule shuts the windowes of sense when she
would have the room fill'd with the light of Rea∣son.
Reason's selfe must first be cast cast into a deep
sleep and die, before she can rise again in the bright∣nesse
of the Spirit. I have dispatch'd the first Di∣stinction.</P>
<P><HI>Dist.</HI> 2<SUP>d</SUP>. All three Persons in the Trinity are
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
<HI>Truth,</HI> but with their severall and distinct Idioms or
Characters. The Father is the onely <HI>True</HI> God, <HI>Joh.</HI>
17. 3. The Son is <HI>Truth, Joh.</HI> 14. 6. The Spirit is
<HI>Truth, Joh.</HI> 5. 5. But,</P>
<P>1. The <HI>Father</HI> is <HI>Truth</HI> in the Root: therefore hee
is call'd the <HI>Father of Lights,</HI> Jam. 1. 17.</P>
<P>2. <HI>The</HI> Son <HI>is</HI> Truth <HI>in the Image.</HI> He is the Image
of the Invisible God, <HI>Coloss.</HI> 1. 15.</P>
<P>3. The <HI>Spirit</HI> is <HI>Truth</HI> in the <HI>Irradiation</HI> or Dis∣covery:
therefore the Spirit is the <HI>witnessing Truth,
1 Joh.</HI> 5. The Spirit is the <HI>testifying Truth,</HI> Ioh. 15. 26.</P>
<P><HI>Nazianzen</HI> delivers the Doctrine of the Tri∣nity
to us from that place of Scripture, <HI>Psal. 36. 9.
In thy light shall we see light.</HI> 1. The Father is Light
in the Fountain. <HI>Thy Light.</HI> 2. The Son is Light in
the <HI>Face</HI> or <HI>Fulnesse: See Light.</HI> 3. The Spirit is
Light in the <HI>Flowing</HI> or <HI>Emanation</HI> of it: <HI>In light.</HI>
The Father is the Light, <HI>from which</HI> is all we see: The
Son is Light, <HI>which</HI> we see: The Spirit, the Light <HI>by
which</HI> we see.</P>
<P><HI>Sin is spiritually discern'd.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Reason 2.</NOTE> Privations and Habits;
Perfections and Defects, are judg'd by the same fa∣culty.
The eye discerns light and darknesse. Sin is
a privation or the absence of Divine Grace. Holi∣nesse
is frequently exprest by light; sin by darknesse.
Holinesse is a spirituall beauty: sin, deformity. Both
are perceiv'd by the same Spirit.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>VSES.</HEAD>
<P><HI>An Admonition.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Vse 1.</NOTE> You have dedicated this day,
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
and many such dayes, to a holy sorrow. I know
some, I beleeve many, I hope most of you carry <HI>bro∣ken
hearts</HI> in your bosomes thorough these dayes.
Indeed very nature in you cannot but relent; and
reason it selfe tremble, to see those things, which
your eyes see. Three Kingdomes stand before you
this day, like those three crosses on Mount <HI>Golgotha,</HI>
all laden with broken and bleeding carkasses. These
three doth your God take, as one Text, that hee may
preach sin to your soules from it, that he may con∣vince
you of sin by it.</P>
<P>Behold, <HI>Scotland</HI> comes with her thousands of
slain men; <HI>England</HI> with her ten thousands; <HI>Ireland</HI>
with her millions; besides innumerable multitudes
which no man can reckon up, of families, persons,
now undone, now famishing. These come crying to
every one of us, <HI>Our bloods be upon your heads, if you
weep not for us before our God this day whilest we bleed
and dye.</HI> Sure your <HI>hearts</HI> doe <HI>break</HI> at the representa∣tion
of these things; which your selves know to bee
at this present farre more sad in <HI>Fact,</HI> then they can
be made by any <HI>Relation.</HI></P>
<P>You that are the Fathers of your Countries over
all this Nation, doe you not often look back upon
your severall Countries with a tender and dropping
eye? Do you not find as much reason and sweetnesse
as once <HI>David</HI> did, to sigh and say within your selves,
<HI>Lord, we have sin'd, wee should have kept this people as
their shepheards: but we have procur'd their woe. Alas!
what have these sheep done?</HI></P>
<P>But now is it not pitie that <HI>broken hearts</HI> should
be worthlesse and uselesse? that God should say of
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
our <HI>Mourning,</HI> as <HI>Solomon</HI> sayes of <HI>Mirth: what
doth it?</HI> Yet so it will be, if it be your <HI>Reason</HI> one∣ly,
and not the <HI>Spirit,</HI> which by your sufferings con∣vinceth
you of your sins. If your convictions and
contritions be Rationall and no more; your groanes
will be to God as the unpleasing cry, the howling of
wild beasts when they are pinch'd with famine, or
caught in a toyle: He that sacrificeth with a heart
thus broken, will be as if he offer'd a <HI>Dog's Heart.</HI></P>
<P>Doth it not much concern you to know whether
your convictions be from a <HI>Rationall</HI> or <HI>Spirituall</HI>
Principle? Are you not eager to understand the
difference between these, that you may judge your
sorrows? As God shall assist me, I will assist you in
this enquiry, by which you are to examine your
selves.</P>
<P><HI>Rationall</HI> and <HI>Spirituall</HI> convictions differ in
their <HI>Perswasives,</HI> in their <HI>Principles.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Rationall Perswasives</HI> in conviction for sinne are
such as these.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Pers. Rat.</NOTE></P>
<P>First, <HI>Self-love.</HI> Will you heare the workings of
this? One man afflicted and oppress'd, laments af∣ter
this manner: <HI>I have blasted my reputation; wasted
my estate; brought my body into diseases; by my lusts:
and now I hang over a pit of flames by the thin, worn
thread of this life; in the same moment that this thread
is cut; I drop in, and am lost for ever. Wo is me!</HI> Thus
he cryes; then he runs to prayers, Sermons, Fasts,
in these he hopes for ease. Another, as he, lies rest∣lesse
all the night; hath these thoughts working like
a storm in his breast. <HI>I have expos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d my life to
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
the Censure of the Lawes, by Treacheries against my Coun∣trey,
and my God. If the Preacher's words prove true,
and there be a hell at last; there remaines nothing for me,
but a fearfull expectation of my share there.</HI> In these an∣guishes
this man breathes forth a groan, and cries to
God, to have mercy on him. So <HI>Pharaoh,</HI> so <HI>Ahab</HI>
were convinc'd. This is like weeping with an Oni∣on;
the eyes shed teares because they smart.</P>
<P>2. <HI>Sparklings of Naturall Worth.</HI> A generous
heart, if it be no more, when it hath done any thing
foulely dishonest, or dishonorable; will call aloud
for Seas of Teares; a Laver of Blood to wash it
clean.</P>
<P>The Jewes in the Wildernesse, when once they
had refus'd to fight at God's command, would purge
that blot with their blood, fighting though forbid∣den,
when they were sure to fall. This is not beyond
that Elephant, which reproach'd with the offer of a∣nother
Elephant to draw his burthen for him; drew
till he broke his heart, and fell down dead.</P>
<P>3. <HI>Naturall Religion</HI> heightned by temper, edu∣cation,
custome, formalities of Nation, age, in
which wee live. The Heathen Romanes wounded
deeply with the losse of an Army, or the pestilence;
sought reliefe in <HI>reforming</HI> their <HI>Religion:</HI> The Si∣byl's
books were search'd: <HI>Ludi instaurati:</HI> solemne
showes and pomps for devotion renew'd: Temples
set open. Cushions laid; Holy tables, seats, beds
made ready: the Matrons flock't in Troops, fill'd
the Churches, fell on their faces, with their haire
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
spred and torne; moystening the Marble pavement
with their plentifull teares at the feet of every I∣doll.</P>
<P><HI>In after-times the Heathens among whom the
Christians lived, on every sad accident, exclaimed:</HI>
The Christians are the cause of this, which joyn not with
us in the worship of our gods. Appease the gods, by the
suppression, or slaughter of these Christians.</P>
<P>Happy are our times, if some amongst us doe not,
upon no higher Conviction, then these of Natu∣rall
Devotion, call for <HI>dayes of Humiliation, Reforma∣tion
in Religion.</HI></P>
<P>But do I condemne these Convictions? No. God
commands and commends them from the example
of Brute Creatures: <HI>The Oxe knowes his owne; and the
Asse his Masters Crib.</HI> But this I say; These are no
better things then the <HI>Best of Beasts,</HI> the <HI>worst of Men</HI>
have attain'd unto. These indeed, if they be but <HI>Sin∣gle,</HI>
may procure <HI>Temporall, Temporary</HI> blessings. But
if they be not <HI>Subordinate</HI> to the Convictions of the
Spirit, they can doe your souls no good. You may
save the Kingdome by such teares, but alas! what
shall be done for Your souls?</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Spirituall Perswasives follow.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Perswa. Spir.</NOTE></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">First, Sense of Divine Love. Zach. 12. 10.</HEAD>
<P>First, a Spirit of Grace, or Love, is shed upon
the Heart; Then teares are shed. What an eye was
that which Christ cast upon <HI>Peter,</HI> when he went out
and wept bitterly? Was it not an Eye of love? a
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
Melting look? You have seen how a Sugar-loafe
dissolves, and weeps it selfe away, when it is dipt in
wine. So hearts dissolve, so they melt, dip't in the
sweet sense of Divine Love. Who knowes not
what a wound, abused love, a wronged Friend makes
upon a tender breast? How then doth the dearest
love, the sweetest friendship of the great God
wound a soule with the sense of Love and Sin.</P>
<P>Have you not sometimes read that place, and
drop't teares upon it? some have told me, that they
have done it often. The place is Es 43. 22. <HI>I have not
wearied thee with sacrifices; thou hast wearied me with thy
sins, O Israel. I blot out thy transgressions like a Cloud, &amp;
remember then no more.</HI> Give me the worst, the hard∣est
Heart in this great Assembly: how soft would it
grow on a sudden, if the Spirit of Christ should
whisper to it such words as these are: <HI>Many years hast
thou lived profanely; many a secret wickednesse hast thou
practis'd, which mine eye hath seen. Often I have set my
selfe before thee in the blood of my Manhood, in the glory
of my Godhead, in the love of both my Natures: Thou
hast wearied me with thy scornings:— But thou sha't be
mine, I freely forgive all thy sins, as if they never had been
committed. Come and see how much I love thee! how I
have ever loved thee!</HI> What temper would thy heart
be in when thou shouldst hear these words? Would
it not be like unto that, when <HI>Joseph</HI> revealed him∣selfe
to his brethren: Whiles thy Saviour falls on
thy neck to kisse thee, thou would'st fall at his feet
unable to speak any word for weeping.</P>
<P>I appeale to you that feel the love of your God,
how it works in the soules of men: doe you not of∣ten
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
in sweet pangs cry out? Ah! my God, the swee∣ter
thou art to me, the more sinfull still doe I appear
to my selfe. This is a Spirituall Conviction, a Con∣viction
by <HI>Love.</HI></P>
<P>2. <HI>Sight of Jesus Christ. They shall see him whom
they have pierced, and mourne over him.</HI> As the looking
forth of the Sun melts the Snow; so doe the shi∣nings
out of Jesus Christ melt the Soule. 'Tis
sweet when a Saint sayes; <HI>Mine eyes have seen
my Saviour, and now they powre forth teares.</HI> A Rain∣bow,
the Covenant of peace is then form<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, when the
Sun shines upon a watry cloud: When Christ puts
forth himselfe, and scatters his beams upon a mour∣ning
cloudy soule; then followes faire weather:
there is peace. This is a spirituall Conviction, a
Conviction by the Beames of Beauty.</P>
<P>3. The greatest sin, the not-beleeving in Iesus Christ.
<HI>In spirituall Perswasives the Person of our Saviour
is the</HI> Argument <HI>and</HI> Conclusion <HI>of all Convictions.</HI>
A sight of Christ, <HI>is that,</HI> by which <HI>Men are powerfully
convinc'd.</HI> Not-beleeving on Christ, <HI>is the grand sin,</HI>
of which <HI>they are convinc'd.</HI></P>
<P>They shall mourn over him whom▪ they have pierced.
Not to beleeve on Christ is to pierce him.</P>
<P>To beleeve Christ is to see him. So in those
Chronicles of Faith, Hebr. 11. c. 27. v. <HI>Moses</HI>'s
faith is exprest by his sight: <HI>He saw him who was invi∣sible.</HI>
But this sight is Inward, Spirituall, Divine:
a sight by no ordinery Light. S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Peter</HI> describes the
state of beleeving, the sight of faith, 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2. 9. Hee
<PB N="21" REF="14"/>
hath brought us into his (his own <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) marvel∣ous
Light. Hee that sees Christ, sees him in a
strange, wonderfull, in a divine Light, in God's own
Light. To believe, is thus to see Christ, and to live
continually by this sight of Christ; <HI>The life I live▪
is by the faith of the Son of God,</HI> Gal. 2. <HI>chap. ver.</HI> ult.</P>
<P>Paul <HI>was convinc'd</HI> by this sight <HI>of Christ; and</HI>
of this sin, <HI>that he had ever liv'd on any other sight.</HI>
Gal. 1. <HI>chap.</HI> 16. vers. When it pleased the Father to
reveale his Son in mee, I consulted not with flesh and
blood.</P>
<P>You may see by <HI>Paul's Conversion,</HI> what his <HI>Con∣viction</HI>
was. He had consulted with flesh and blood;
that is, with Principles of Reason, with the Spirit of
man; what should hee have consulted with? or
whom? with the Word, the immortall Word:
with the Wisdome of God; with the discoveries
of Jesus Christ in him.</P>
<P>Is this the Sin, you chiefly mourn for this day?
By this judge of your convictions. Do you grieve to
think; that the glory of God hath shined so long,
so sweetly from the face of Christ; filling all things
round about you: while you have been sitting un∣der
the shadow of humane wit and reason, as in the
shadow of death; That so bright a Day hath dawn'd
from the Person of the Lord Jesus; and yet you sit
spinning out your Counsels and Course▪ by the
candle-light of man's spirit, and policy, as in the
night? Do your hearts sigh-forth this sense? Lord,
we have sate in counsell concerning the great affairs
of many Kingdomes, Churches, Common-wealths▪
but not by thy Wisdome; by the shining forth of
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
thy Son in us. Many Principles of State, Reason,
Policy, have raigned over us; but the sight of thee,
O Jesus, in our hearts, hath not ruled us.</P>
<P>When the Spirit convinceth of sin; hee makes
this the great sin and folly; that the appearances
of Christ have not been our <HI>Sun</HI> and <HI>shield.</HI> No
such <HI>shield</HI> is there to defend us from the strifes,
contentions, conspiracies of men and things; as to
be hid in the light of our Saviour's looks. No
such advantage is there as to gain this <HI>Sun,</HI> to have
the beamings forth of our Husband-king on our
side: How do the glorious dartings of his presence
from among us, dazle the spirits of our enemies,
trouble their order, and make them unable to fight
against us, or hurt us?</P>
<P>When the Spirit convinceth of sin, hee shews
us, that the story of things in the Wildernesse, was
a Figure for us under the Gospel, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 10. c. 4. ver.
When the <HI>Jews</HI> were to passe over the river <HI>Jordan,</HI>
the Ark went before them; so they passed through
dry-shod. When they travelled through the De∣sart;
the Cloud, the Glory went before them: as
that moved, they marched on; when that rested, they
stood still.</P>
<P>Your Ark now is the spirituall presence of Je∣sus
Christ in your hearts; the Cloud, the Glory
now, is the appearance of your Saviour, resting
upon your spirits. You have waded through many
rivers of blood, have you seen the discoveries of
your Jesus going before you, and followed these?
You have made many Marches, many Rests; hath
the wel-pleased face of your Jesus, as your Leading-starre,
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>
been still in your eye? Have you march't
as this hath moved? Where this hath stood still,
have you stay'd?</P>
<P>The <HI>Jews</HI> sung of old; What ailed you, ye wa∣ters,
that ye fled? ye seas, that ye were driven back∣wards?
The waters saw thee, O God, and fled be∣fore
thee. If these things be thus with you, you
may go forth, and say in your songs: What ailed
you, ye mighty armies, at <HI>Keinton, Newbury, York,
Naseby;</HI> that ye fled, and were driven backwards?
What ailed you, ye strong treasons, close conspi∣racies,
that ye trembled, and fell, and your founda∣tions
were discovered, before you could take effect?
They saw thee, O Jesus! they saw thee appearing in
the midst of us; so they fled, so they fell before
thee.</P>
<P>If things have not been thus with you; behold
the sin, over which you are principally to powre
out your tears. Behold the sin, which troubles
you. Assure your selves; all your acts in Coun∣sell
and Camp will be <HI>Null;</HI> till the Lord Jesus be
as the shout of a King, in the midst of you. Vain
are all our hopes, sweet dreams of Peace; till our
Deare Saviour shew himself among you, as once
among his Disciples; <HI>Saying;</HI> Peace be with you;
<HI>Breathing</HI> Peace upon you.</P>
<P>These are the <HI>Perswasives,</HI> in which <HI>Rationall</HI> and
<HI>Spirituall</HI> convictions for sin differ; not all, but
some few, which I have chosen for you from among
the rest.</P>
<P>Now remains the difference between these <HI>Con∣victions</HI>
in the <HI>Principles</HI> themselves.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
<HEAD>Principles.</HEAD>
<P>The <HI>Principles</HI> themselves are the <HI>Spirit</HI> of <HI>Man</HI>
or <HI>Reason;</HI> the <HI>Spirit</HI> of <HI>God.</HI> But I can no more
convey a sense of this difference into any soule,
that hath not seen these two Lights shining in it
self: than I can convey the difference between <HI>Salt</HI>
and <HI>Sugar;</HI> to him, who hath never tasted <HI>Sweet</HI> or
<HI>Sharp.</HI> These things are discerned only by <HI>exercise</HI>
of <HI>senses;</HI> and are too hard for those, who have
not their own <HI>senses</HI> exercised in them, as S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>Paul</HI>
speaks, <HI>Hebr.</HI> 5. chap. 14. ver. When you shall see
the <HI>Sea</HI> of Truth, the <HI>Spirit;</HI> then you will know,
that the <HI>Great River</HI> of <HI>Reason</HI> was not the <HI>Sea.</HI></P>
<P>I can tell you, that as much as the complexion
of a face; the colour of a cloth or lace, seen by
Moon-light, and Sun-shine differ: So, and farre
more do the convictions or discoveries by <HI>Reason,</HI>
and the <HI>Spirit.</HI></P>
<P><HI>But still this is the difference in the</HI> Effects, <HI>not
in the</HI> Principles <HI>themselves. To give you, as I
may, some shadowie description of this; I will
commend to your most constant and serious medi∣tations
that place,</HI> 1 Cor. 15. chap. 45. v. The first man
was a living soule; the last man a quickening spirit,
<HI>Vers.</HI> 46. The naturall is first, and then the spirituall.
<HI>Vers.</HI> 48. As the earthy, so are they that are earthy; as
is the heavenly, so are they that are heavenly. <HI>Vers.</HI> 49.
As we have born the Image of the earthly man; so shall
we beare the Image of the heavenly.</P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="16"/>
From these places you may draw these <HI>Archi∣tectonick,</HI>
or commanding Conclusions.</P>
<P>1. A <HI>Living soule</HI> in her full glory, as she was
in the <HI>first man</HI> in innocencie, in Paradise, is not
the <HI>Principle</HI> of the second man, the new birth;
but the <HI>All-quickening,</HI> the <HI>Eternall Spirit.</HI></P>
<P>2. A <HI>Living soule,</HI> with the highest improve∣ments,
raised to the noblest actings of Wit, Rea∣son,
Worth, is <HI>naturall,</HI> not <HI>spirituall;</HI> the <HI>Image
of the first Adam,</HI> not the <HI>Image of the Lord Jesus.</HI></P>
<P>3. <HI>The</HI> naturall <HI>and</HI> spirituall <HI>man differ as much
as</HI> earth <HI>and</HI> heaven; corruption <HI>and</HI> immortality; flesh
<HI>and</HI> spirit.</P>
<P>You see the difference between these two sorts
of convictions; as I have been able to set it before
you. I will now conclude this Use with an <HI>Admo∣nition,</HI>
as I begun it.</P>
<P>An earthly Root may bring forth earthly fruit;
nothing can reach up to Heaven, and immortalitie,
but that which first comes from heaven, and that
immortall Spirit. If you see your sins this day,
and weep for them, though it be only by the Owle-light
of your own reason, (as the Philosopher him∣self
styles it) you shall not lose your <HI>reward,</HI> though
you may lose your soules.</P>
<P>But what will it profit you to save three King∣domes
by your sorrows; and in the mean time to
carry in your own bosomes, dying, perishing soules,
of which every <HI>single one</HI> is more worth than all
the world?</P>
<P><PB N="26" REF="17"/>
'Tis dreadfull to expresse; but I will speak it for
your sakes. If God should please to put the choice
into my hands; I had much rather, that all these
three Kingdomes should be consum'd at once, in
this very moment, with fire from heaven, by an
outward destruction; then that <HI>any one</HI> the meanest,
most miserable <HI>soule</HI> in them, should perish ever∣lastingly.</P>
<P>Draw then water out of that <HI>Well</HI> of salvation,
the <HI>Spirit;</HI> and powre it forth before the Lord. If
the <HI>Spirit</HI> be the <HI>Spring;</HI> your tears will quench <HI>both
flames,</HI> those that burn <HI>outwardly,</HI> and <HI>inwardly;</HI> so
you shall at once save these nations, and your own
soules.</P>
<P><HI>A Caution.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Vse 2.</NOTE> If it be the work of the <HI>Spirit</HI> to
convince of <HI>sin;</HI> then it is his work more especi∣ally,
to convince of spirituall <HI>Duties,</HI> and spirituall
<HI>Truths.</HI> Take heed of measuring divine things by
the modell of <HI>Reason.</HI> Take heed of rejecting what
<HI>Reason</HI> cannot receive. S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>Paul</HI> gives you a full ac∣count
of the <HI>Jews</HI> case and ruine, in a few words;
<HI>Rom. 10. 3. While they sought after righteousnesse by
the Law, they fell short; because they were ignorant of
the righteousnesse of God.</HI> Feare, lest you also fall
after the same example of unbelief; lest you fall
short of the knowledge of spirituall things; be∣cause
you seek it by <HI>Reason,</HI> and know not the
<HI>Spirit</HI> of God.</P>
<P>It is true; all grant, that some; some say, that
all truths which come by <HI>revelation</HI> of the <HI>Spirit,</HI>
may also be demonstrated by <HI>Reason.</HI> But if they
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
be, they are then no more <HI>Divine,</HI> but humane
truths: They lose their <HI>certainty, beauty, efficacy;</HI>
they become like the <HI>Name</HI> of Jesus in the mouth
of those <HI>counterfeit Exorcists,</HI> which made them not
the Devil's <HI>Masters,</HI> but his <HI>scorne. Spirituall truths</HI>
discovered by demonstrations of Reason, are like
the Mistresse in her Cook-maid's clothes. They
differ from themselves in their own true shape;
as those little plump boyes with wings, the pictures
of Angels in Churches, differ from the Angels in
Heaven. <HI>Spirituall things are foolishnesse to the na∣turall
man,</HI> 1 Cor. 2. <HI>chap.</HI> No visible shape is so
lovely, so full of Majesty, as that of <HI>Man:</HI> No
shape is so deformed, ridiculous, as the resem∣blance
of man in a beast, in the <HI>Ape.</HI> So heaven∣ly
things lose their majestie, become weak and con∣temptible,
when they are represented by <HI>Reason</HI>
only: For they are not the things themselves; but
an apish, mimicall imitation of them.</P>
<P>The Philosopher gives us this rule; that wee
should seek for sutable demonstrations in every
sort of truths; and not leape from one <HI>kinde</HI> to
another. The Apostle gives us this rule; to <HI>com∣pare
spirituall things with spirituall.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 2. 13.</NOTE> <HI>Spirituall Con∣clusions,</HI>
with <HI>spirituall Principles.</HI></P>
<P>You will reap both pleasure and profit from
this Observation; that the <HI>true Protestant</HI> differs
from all sorts of men and Religions, by making
the three Persons in Trinity, according to their se∣verall
properties, <HI>the foundation of all truth.</HI></P>
<P>1. He distinguisheth himself from the <HI>Atheists,</HI>
<PB N="28" REF="18"/>
by worshipping the <HI>Father</HI> as the <HI>Fountain</HI> of <HI>truth.</HI></P>
<P>2. He dissents from <HI>Mahumetans, Indians, In∣fidels,</HI>
while he sets up <HI>Christ</HI> in himself, for the on∣ly
<HI>Image</HI> of truth.</P>
<P>3. By seeking and imbracing the <HI>discovery</HI> of
truth in the <HI>Spirit,</HI> hee differs from all sorts of
<HI>Christians;</HI> especially three.</P>
<P>1. The <HI>Papists,</HI> a <HI>Faction of policy.</HI> These per∣swade
us to receive the testimony, not of the <HI>Spi∣rit,</HI>
but of the <HI>Church,</HI> for a Touchstone of truth:
And this <HI>Church</HI> is the <HI>Popes</HI> private <HI>Consistory,</HI> or
<HI>Generall Councel.</HI> Thus the <HI>Church's Authority,</HI> not
the <HI>Demonstration of the Holy Ghost</HI> shall be the light
of Faith to Truth. Thus not content with an <HI>An∣tichrist,</HI>
they set up their <HI>Consistory,</HI> or <HI>Councel</HI> for
an <HI>Anti-spirit.</HI> But wee need no visible Judge on
earth, to determine upon our consciences; <HI>What is
Scripture; what is the sense of Scripture.</HI> We have
an invisible Judge and Witnesse in our own breasts:
<HI>He that believeth, hath the testimony in himself,</HI> 1 Joh.
5. <HI>chap. 10. v.</HI> for he hath the Spirit.</P>
<P>2. The <HI>Arminians,</HI> a <HI>Sect of Moralists,</HI> who give
the over-perswading power of the Spirit, to strength
of Rhetorick and Reason, inward or outward.</P>
<P>3. A <HI>Party of wit and worth:</HI> so farre as the wit
and worth of man can go; if they would submit
the wit and worth of man to the Power and Wis∣dome
of God: The <HI>Socinians;</HI> the <HI>Principles</HI> of
<HI>Reason,</HI> are the <HI>pillars</HI> of <HI>Religion,</HI> and truth to
<PB N="29" REF="18"/>
these men. But Reason is a <HI>pillar</HI> of a <HI>Cloud;</HI> the
Spirit only is the <HI>pillar</HI> of <HI>Fire,</HI> which hath light
in it. Reason is that <HI>Gladius versatilis,</HI> that sword
in that hand of the Cherubim, that kept Paradise;
a sword that turns every way. It may keep men
from the tree of Life, but can never bring them to
it. Our faith is not in the <HI>wisdome</HI> of <HI>man,</HI> but <HI>power</HI>
of <HI>God,</HI> 1 Cor. 2. <HI>chap. 5. verse.</HI></P>
<P>Now, Worthy Senators, give me leave to make
my particular addresses to your selves. You have
commanded me to speak before you; how farre
so ever I finde my self below a sufficiencie for it,
I must speak; I would not seek to work upon you
by art or cunning, if I had any skill in these things.
My earnest desire is, with all humilitie and lowli∣nesse,
to speak the things of <HI>God,</HI> as a <HI>man;</HI> on whom
the earliest glimmerings of the Spirit have scarce
yet dawned. I have believed, so I will speak; to
you; those things▪ on which I fasten the immor∣talitie
of mine own deare soule.</P>
<P>Pardon mee, Honourable Patriots, if I speake
twice to you, once as <HI>private Christians,</HI> a second
time, as <HI>publike persons</HI> and Magistrates.</P>
<P>First, <HI>As Private Christians.</HI> If the words of a
weak, worthlesse man may have place in your large
hearts, I beseech you to lay up within you, and to
ponder frequently upon this short word which I am
now about to speak: <HI>Remember, Remember, not to trust
to the strength and wisdome of that Living soule, which
dwels in the Breast of Man.</HI> But, <HI>Have all your depen∣dance
upon that Spirit of the Immortall God, which comes
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
forth from our Lord Jesus Christ.</HI> I speak this to <HI>You,</HI>
who are Princes of Reason, in whom the Spirit of
Man is at a High pitch: Your Saviour died, that he
might send you this <HI>Spirit:</HI> He left you in his flesh∣ly
presence, that you might have this Spirit with
you. O wait <HI>for him</HI> constantly, till he come: Wait
<HI>upon him</HI> diligently, when he is come.</P>
<P>Saint <HI>Hierom</HI> thought hee ever heard the last
Trumpet sounding in his eares. How well should I
think my selfe rewarded for all the pains of this day,
if I could fix upon your spirits the constant sound
of two onely Sentences, as two blasts of the last
Trumpet? The Sentences are, <HI>Esa. 2. vers. ult.</HI></P>
<P>Cease from man whose breath is in his nostrils;
wherein is he to be esteemed of?</P>
<Q><BIBL>VERS. 17.</BIBL><P>The Lord alone shall be exalted in that day. The
great God make <HI>That</HI> day, <HI>This</HI> day, to every one of
your soules.</P></Q>
<P><HI>Thus much to Private Christians.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, As <HI>Publick Persons.</HI> Christ tells the
Jewes:</P>
<P>If any one sin against the Son of Man, it shall be for∣given
him: But if any one sin against the holy Ghost: it
never shall bee forgiven him. <HI>You will allow it, if I
shall make a little change in these words, and so re∣turn
them to you.</HI> If a State sin against the Sonne of
Man, it shall he forgiven: But if a State sin against the
holy Ghost, it shall never be forgiven.</P>
<P><PB N="31" REF="19"/>
<HI>Remember Hierusalem, Christ</HI> came in the flesh,
and was crucified, yet <HI>Hierusalem</HI> stood. The <HI>Spirit</HI>
of Christ came in the persons of the Disciples, in
the power of the Gospel, and was cast out; then <HI>Hie∣rusalem</HI>
fell. Divided into three Factions within, be∣leaguer'd
with a fourth enemy without; <HI>Hierusalem</HI>
miserably fell.</P>
<P><HI>O England! London! Remember Hierusalem.</HI> You
have had the first day of your Peace, and passed it.
<HI>Christ</HI> hath been preach'd among you; but as in the
<HI>Flesh;</HI> clouded with carnall rites and ceremonies.
Christ hath been pierc'd among us, that is, not be∣leeved
on: yet we <HI>live,</HI> though we <HI>bleed.</HI> You have
had the first day of your Peace, and pass'd it. Be care∣full;
Be carefull, to know the <HI>last day</HI> of your Peace;
the comming of the <HI>Spirit</HI> among you.</P>
<P><HI>You have set me on your Watch-Tower, and
made me your Watchman for the few sands of these
glasses; If you ask mee now;</HI> Watchman, what of
the Night? <HI>My humble answer is:</HI> The Nights is
almost past, the Day is at hand, if you will receive the
Spirit when he comes: If you shall refuse to heare, you
will look for day; but I feare, I feare, it will be Black∣nesse
of Darknesse, and Desolation.</P>
<P>But I bend my Knees to the Father of our Lord
Jesus, who hath hitherto made you tender in a very
great measure; that he would send the Spirit of his
Son into your hearts; that you may know him, that
he may be in you; that all this people may honour
the <HI>Spirits</HI> as they honour Jesus Christ.</P>
<P><PB N="32" REF="20"/>
<HI>A</HI> Vindication of the Spirit <HI>from those Who</HI>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. Pretend it to Profanenesse.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Vse 3.</NOTE></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Profane it under Pretentes.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>1. From those who <HI>Pretend the Spirit to Profane∣nesse.</HI>
Can any think they have the <HI>Spirit of Grace</HI> in
them, and yet sin, and yet not mourn for sin? Can a∣ny
man make that Spirit, whose work is to <HI>Convince</HI>
of sin, a <HI>Colour</HI> for sin? Can any man paint his foule
lusts with the specious name of this holy Spirit,
whose property it is to paint out lusts in their True
deformities, their Hellish shapes?</P>
<P>I read in Ecclesiastick Writers, that in the Pri∣mitive
times there were those that deserv'd the name
of <HI>Borboristae,</HI> or <HI>Coenosi:</HI> The <HI>Dirty Sect:</HI> and yet a
Branch of the <HI>Gnostiques.</HI></P>
<P>But I might perhaps feare this to be the <HI>Malice,</HI>
or <HI>Mistake</HI> of some in those ages; if I did not read
in the holy Scriptures of<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Jude 8.</NOTE> <HI>Filthy-Dreamers.</HI></P>
<P>Spirituall Discoveries are either <HI>Waking Sights,</HI>
or <HI>Dreames.</HI> Dreames are False Visions of sleeping
men, without connexion, full of absurdities, incon∣sistencies.
It is not strange for a filthy vile Person to
have fair Glorious Dreames. It is monstrous, that
Glorious Discourses, Notions and Apprehensions,
should be set upon vile Affections, Actions, and
conversations; as the Head of an Angel upon the
body of a Beast. But All is a <HI>Dream.</HI></P>
<P>If any man indeed have the <HI>Spirit,</HI> he hath a <HI>True
Dove</HI> in his Breast. The Dove's eyes are the Em∣blem
of Chastity; The Dove's song is in Grones.
<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
Who, so mourn for sin; who, so moane day and
night after their God, as those who live with this
<HI>Spirit?</HI></P>
<P>This is the first Part of the <HI>Vindication.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, from those that <HI>Profane the Spirit</HI> un∣der
<HI>Pretences</HI> of <HI>Fancy, Profanenesse.</HI></P>
<P>1. Under <HI>Pretences of Fancy.</HI> Why should <HI>Jo∣seph</HI>
be despised as a <HI>Dreamer</HI> among his brethren?
<HI>Paul</HI> as a Babler among the Athenians? The <HI>Spirit
as a Fancy,</HI> by men onely Rationall? That scurrilous
Comoedian in his Greek play call'd the <HI>Frogs,</HI> re∣proach'd
<HI>Socrates,</HI> as a Worshipper of <HI>Clouds,</HI> and
the <HI>Aire;</HI> because he neglected their Idols, and con∣vers'd
with the <HI>Invisible-God,</HI> So the workings and
Discoveries of the Spirit, often seem to Men of
Mighty Reason, <HI>Cloudy, Airy.</HI> Yet the <HI>Spirit</HI> is
<HI>Truth;</HI> the onely Solid and Weighty Truth, carry∣ing
the power of God for a demonstration along
with it.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 2. 4.</NOTE></P>
<P>Some learned men beare such a modest respect to
<HI>Nature,</HI> that they affirm it Probable, Some Beasts
may have a <HI>Sense</HI> more then we have, which wee can
neither judge of, or guesse at; because we have it not.
O! that the most Rationall Men, were so modest to∣wards
their Maker; as to suspect, that there may be
in him a <HI>Divine Sense,</HI> a <HI>Spirit of Light,</HI> above the
Compasse and Conjectures of their Reason; which
he may communicate to whom he pleaseth!</P>
<P>2. Under <HI>Pretences</HI> of <HI>Profanenesse.</HI> The Heathens
mingled with Christians, of old charg'd their secret
Meetings with the <HI>Beds</HI> of <HI>Oedipus,</HI> unnaturall In∣cests,
<PB N="34" REF="21"/>
the <HI>Feasts</HI> of <HI>Thyestes,</HI> monstrous cruelties.</P>
<P>The Late <HI>Protestants at large</HI> cloath'd the best men
with the name of <HI>Puritan,</HI> as with a Cap of Paper;
then they painted that Cap with Devils; they loa∣ded
that name with all the foule things of all Sects
or Persons; as before them the Papist did the Pro∣testant.</P>
<P>God grant that the Father of lies may not still
live between the Lips of Men by the same Art of
Names; representing the most spirituall men like
Christ on the Crosse, under the most carnall Titles
of Ambition, Lust, Falshood.</P>
<P>The Spirit is Holy, so are they that are <HI>His.</HI> This
Spirit cannot encourage to sin, comfort in sin; for
his work is to convince sin.</P>
<P>Beleeve it, 'Tis true as Gospel: No man that is
led by the law of the Spirit of Life; can walk con∣trary
to any Law of Nature, Common Honesty,
Civill Policy, or whatsoever is of good Report,
Praise-worthy.</P>
<P>If any man walk by any other rule; an evill Spirit
hath deceived him; only let not the reproach of
such fall upon them, who with humble and panting
hearts call upon the Name of this <HI>Holy Spirit.</HI></P>
<P>A <HI>Consolation.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Use 4.</NOTE> This Spirit, which convinceth of
sin, is the <HI>Comforter.</HI> If you have this day receiv'd
his conviction; you shall now go away full of his
comforts: with bosomes full of All comforts
of peace and joy in your selves; of peace and
love, one towards another.</P>
<P>Where the Spirit convinceth of sin, he commu∣nicates
<PB N="35" REF="21"/>
all contents in these two bundles of com∣forts;
Righteousnesse and Peace.</P>
<P>1. <HI>Righteousnesse.</HI> Have you seen your sins by
the light of the Spirit? by the same light you shall
see your righteousnesse. Humble your selves be∣fore
this Spirit; let him cover your faces with
shame; and he shall cloath your persons with glo∣ry.
He shall make you precious in the eyes of your
God, honourable in all the world: Nations round
about shall say, This is a wise and righteous people,
for the Spirit of the Eternall God is come down
among them.</P>
<P>2. <HI>Peace.</HI> Naturalists say, A wound is a separa∣tion
of parts in the whole. How full are all of
wounds? Alas, do we not begin to have wounds up∣on
our breasts, neer our hearts? And still we strive
to make that good in Civilitie, which is true only
in Nature; that the best Balsome for a wound is
its own blood: We would make up our divisions,
by making them more.</P>
<P>Who now shall restore Peace to our mourners?
This Spirit will restore peace to his mourners. This
Dove, though he come groaning, yet he brings an
Olive branch in his mouth. O ye! every one of you
in particular, give this Spirit your single hearts to
breake in pieces; and he will make them all one
heart. How happy should we live, if God would
do this!</P>
<P>If the Lord would powre forth his Spirit upon
our souls, and melt them; how sweetly would they
<PB N="36" REF="22"/>
run all into one piece, like gold?</P>
<P>Then should <HI>Righteousnesse</HI> and <HI>Peace</HI> kisse each
other in these Lands; and these three kingdomes
should mutually kisse and imbrace in this union.
The Lambs, <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Scotland,</HI> Presbyterians and
Independents, shall feed together in fat pastures.
The Lambs and the Lion shall live lovingly, and
converse one with another.</P>
<P>Then shall your Cattell go forth again in Herds
and Flocks: Your children in dances; Your Saints
in their assemblies; and the Lord Jesus shall be
known for a God in the midst of them.</P>
<P>Then shall after-ages call this Age, this Parlia∣ment;
<HI>The blessed of the Lord;</HI> and make it your
Motto for ever.</P>
<Q><L>Blessed are the Peace-makers in divided Common-wealths.</L>
<L>Blessed are the Peace-makers in divided Consci∣ences.</L></Q>
<P>Thus if the Holy Spirit set a crown of thorns by
conviction on your hearts; he shall crown you with
Righteousnesse and Peace: For;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rom. 14. 17.</NOTE> <HI>The Kingdome of
God is Righteousnesse, Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghost.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="22"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

