<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A true narrative of the proceedings at the Sessions-house in the Old-Bayly at a sessions there held; which began on Wednesday the 13th of this instant Decemb. and ended on Saturday the 16th, 1676. Setting forth the several facts and tryals of several malefactors. With the tryal of the maid that set her master's barns on fire at Harrow on the Hill, at Michaelmas last. With an account how many are condemned, burn'd in the hand, to be whipt, and transported. With allowance. Roger L'Estrange.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A63589</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing T2819A</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R222541</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99833700</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99833700</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">38178</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A63589)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38178)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2220:12)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A true narrative of the proceedings at the Sessions-house in the Old-Bayly at a sessions there held; which began on Wednesday the 13th of this instant Decemb. and ended on Saturday the 16th, 1676. Setting forth the several facts and tryals of several malefactors. With the tryal of the maid that set her master's barns on fire at Harrow on the Hill, at Michaelmas last. With an account how many are condemned, burn'd in the hand, to be whipt, and transported. With allowance. Roger L'Estrange.</TITLE><AUTHOR>England and Wales. Court of Quarter Sessions of the Peace (London)</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>8 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>printed for D.M.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1676.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Copy has print show-through.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Guildhall Library, London.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Trials --  England --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Crime --  England --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Criminals --  England --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Murder --  England --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A63589">
<STC T="W">T2819A</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99833700</BIBNO>
<VID>38178</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A true
NARRATIVE
Of the Proceedings at the
Sessions-house
IN THE
OLD-BAYLY,
At a Sessions there held;
Which began on <HI>Wednesday</HI> the <HI>13th</HI> of this In∣stant
<HI>Decemb.</HI> and ended on <HI>Saturday</HI> the 16th, 1676.</P>
<P>Setting forth the several
Facts and Tryals of several
Malefactors.</P>
<P>With the Tryal of the Maid that set her Master's Barns
on fire at <HI>Harrow on the Hill,</HI> at <HI>Michaelmas</HI> last.</P>
<P>With an Account how many are Condemned,
Burn'd in the Hand, to be Whipt, and Transported.</P>
<P>With Allowance. <HI>Roger L'Estrange.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI> Printed for <HI>D. M.</HI> 1676.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>A Narrative of the Proceedings
at the Sessions begun <DATE>the 13th of Decem∣ber
1676,</DATE> at the Oly Bayly.</HEAD>
<P>THe first person tried, was for making a∣way
her Bastard-childe; but upon
hearing the Evidence, and examinati∣on
both of the Midwife and Coroner,
it appeared to be onely a Miscarriage;
and by several circumstances there was reason to
judge that she had not gone above sixteen weeks,
and had never been quick, the abortive Infant be∣ing
not above eight inches long, and no symptoms
of Wounds or Bruises being to be seen on the body
to argue any violence used to it, the Jury thereup∣on
thought fit to bring her in not guilty.</P>
<P>A young man was arraigned for Murther, killing
an old man in St. <HI>James</HI>'s Park: Two fellows being
running together in the evening the poor ancient
man unlukily happen'd to be in their way, and one
of them tumbled him down and bruised him, of
which bruise the next day he died; but the Evi∣dence
testifying that it was done meerly by acci∣dent,
without any grudge or quarrel precedent, and
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
that the Prisoner as food as he perceived he had
done an injury, went immediately and call'd a Chair
to carry him home, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> There was no reason for
finding the Indictment, so that he was discharged.</P>
<P>A Servant maid was found guilty of stealing a
silver Tankard of the value of Five pounds: She
living at a publick house in the <HI>Old Jury,</HI> took an
opportunity to take it away; and having knock'd
off the Lid, brought it to a Goldsmith to sell, who
perceiving the Cover lately broke off, would not
buy it, unless she would shew it him; which after
much importunity she did, and upon that was engra∣ven
the name of the Owner, whose wife she then
pretended to be, and had the Goldsmith to a Con∣federates
house, who seemed to say as much: but
at last being trapp'd in their words by him, she con∣fess'd
the Felony to him, and afterwards on her ex∣amination
before the Justice, and acknowledg'd in
effect as much now at the bar, onely said that the
Tankard was delivered her to sell by a fellow ser∣vant;
but there being neither proof nor probabili∣ty
of any such things, she was convicted.</P>
<P>A woman was indicted for burning her Master's
Barns at <HI>Harrow on the Hill,</HI> in which a considerable
parcel of Wheat and other Corn was consumed on
<HI>Michaelmas</HI> day last. Her Master and his wife gave
evidence, but nothing of their own knowledge,
onely that she had confess'd the Fact, that in their
absence in the evening she took a Fire-brand, and
carrying it out of the house put it in at a hole in the
Barn amongst a Mow of unthrash'd Oats, whereby
that Barn, and another adjoyning were burn'd down,
<PB N="5" REF="3" MS="y"/>
and the Dwelling house with much difficulty pre∣served.
And this likewise appeared on reading her
Examination; for which mischievous act she could
alleadge no other provocation but that her Master
would not lend her money to go to a Wedding.
However the Justice that committed her, assuring
the Court from his personal knowledge, that the
Prisoners Father was a very m<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lanch<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly and dist<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m∣per'd
man, and that she her self had a defect in her
understanding, and many times at least not the use
of common Reason or Sense, and the Evidence a∣gainst
her in effect acknowledging as much, which
was confirmed by her present stupid carriage at the
B<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r. The Jury looking upon her as <HI>Non Compos
Mentis</HI> at the time of the Fact committed, could
not finde her guilty in the eye of the Law, of the
Crime for which she stood indicted.</P>
<P>Two Legerdemain Ladies of profound experience
in the mysteries of Shop lifting; one of them having
been whipt at the Carts tail but the very last Sessions,
were convicted for stealing two pieces of Callicoe,
under pretence of buying <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kerum. The Goods
were taken before they got out of sight in one of their
aprons, who alleadged a very civil excuse, assuring
the Court that she was drunk with Brandy, and
knew not what she did; but that Plea was over∣rul'd,
and both of them found guilty.</P>
<P>A French Gentleman, came in voluntarily
to take a tryal for killing a Marshal's man's fol∣lower,
in <HI>April</HI> last was two years, at the end of St.
<HI>Martins-lane.</HI> The Marshals man himself was gone
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
another way, and the party kill'd, and three or four
more seiz'd the Prisoner (as they subpose it was) but
without having any Warrant at that instant with
them; and besides, the Warrant their Master had
was wrong in the Christian name. Upon their ta∣king
the party, divers of his Companions drew their
Swords, and one of the Bayliffs lost his life in the
fray; but the Evidence could not say who kill'd
him, nor positively that the Prisoner at Bar was the
person they had arrested: so that he was acquitted
both of Murther and Manslaughter.</P>
<P>The next was a tedious tryal of a young fellow
for breaking open the house of a worthy Gentleman
his late Master, and stealing thence a Spanish Gun,
and other Goods, to the value of Fourty pound.
There appeared several violent presumptions of
Guilt, and a person where the Gun was found had
sworn directly before the Justice, that the Prisoner
was the man that sold it; and another, that he ve∣rily
believ'd him to be the man; but now neither of
them would say further, than that he was somewhat
like him. The Prisoner had a great number to speak
in his behalf, but few couln say any thing to the pur∣pose;
and the Court declared themselves sensible
of much practice us'd on the Prisoner's behalf, to
conceal the truth, yet on a full hearing, for want of
direct Evidence, the Jury brought him in not guil∣ty.</P>
<P>A Flemming born in the City of <HI>Antwerp,</HI> was in∣dicted
on the Statute for exercising the Trade of a
Gold-beater here, not having served seven years an
Apprentice; but it being prov'd by several witnesses
<PB N="7" REF="4" MS="y"/>
that he serv'd the said term to his Father of the same
Trade in the said City of <HI>Antwerp,</HI> and that he was
an excellent Artist. The Court considering the in∣tent
of the said Statute, which is onely to prevent
unskilful and insufficient Workmen; and that the
Art it self prohibi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s onely <HI>Those that have been Ap∣prentices,
or not serv'd as Apprentices:</HI> And though
he were not Apprentice in <HI>England,</HI> yet he had serv'd
<HI>as an Apprentice</HI> abroad; which they concluded to
be within the intent of the Statute: For otherwise
it would be too great a discouragement to Foreign∣ers
to instruct us in the usual Inventions; and there∣fore
the Jury found him not guilty.</P>
<P>An old Offender was convicted for stealing a bay
Gelding of Six pound price, a quarter of grownd
Mault and two Sacks: the Horse was taken out of
the stable on the 28th of <HI>Nov.</HI> and the two sacks of
Mault with it. The very next day the Owner co∣ming
to <HI>London</HI> met the Prisoner driving his Horse
along <HI>St. Gileses</HI>'s, with one of the Sacks empty on
his arm, and there seiz'd him, who now pretended
that the Sack was given him by two strangers, he
knew not who, for his pains to drive the Horse along
Tyburn road, but he knew not whether; and there∣fore
seeming onely a forged excuse, without any
proof to confirm it, he was found guilty, it being a∣vert'd
in Court that he had three times already been
burnt in the hand and convicted.</P>
<P>Two persons, one by his own Confession, and the other by
Verdidict, were Convicted for stealing a silver Tankard in the
<HI>Woolstaple Westminster,</HI> from a publique house, whence at once
they stole away themselves, the Plate and the Reckoning, but
were discovered by a Female Crony, upon a disgust, that
she was not allowed Snips in the prize, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="8" REF="5"/>
A Woman as principal, and a Man as accessary, were Con∣viicted
for stealing Plate, and other rich goods, to the value of
200 pound from a Frenchman at <HI>Westminster;</HI> whose servant
the woman being, to<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k the opportun<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y of his absence, and
ransackt several of his Rooms, and stole the said goods, Af∣ter
which the said other prisoner took her a Lodging, dispo∣sed
of a Watch, and some of the Plate; for which both
were found Guilty.</P>
<P>A Lighterman and his wife were Arraigned, for stealing of
about 40 pieces of Serge, out of a Lighter on the Thomes;
The Prosecuter produced several witnesses, and one very
roundly swore, that she saw two of the pieces of Serge in
the Prisoners house in the Cradle, and that his wife seemed
much afraid of a search; and threatned to fling them into
the house or office, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> But upon a full examination, it ap∣pearing
that there had been several suits and brangles be∣tween
the parties, that the Prisoner was sick at the time of
the Robbery, that it was two years ago, and no prosecution
all this while, that the husband prisoner was a person of good
Fame, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> They were both acquitted by the Jury.</P>
<P>There was great exbectation of the Tryal of one <HI>Lodowick
Muggleton,</HI> for spreading detestable opinions, and publishing
several impious Books; But the same was put off, till witnes∣ses
might be ready for a full discovery of his Villanies, and
therefore the reader is to take notice, that any Pamphlets
published concerning his Tryal, are faigned stories.</P>
<P>There were t<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nn burnt in the hand, seven allowed Trans∣portation,
ten to be whipt, and one to stand in the Pillory.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

