<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Anima magica abscondita or a discourse of the universall spirit of nature, with his strange, abstruse, miraculous ascent, and descent. By Eugenius Philalethes.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Vaughan, Thomas, 1622-1666.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A64761</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing V142</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R3720</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99872473</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99872473</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">124910</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A64761)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124910)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 174:E1302[3])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Anima magica abscondita or a discourse of the universall spirit of nature, with his strange, abstruse, miraculous ascent, and descent. By Eugenius Philalethes.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Vaughan, Thomas, 1622-1666.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[14], 56, [2] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by T.W. for H. B[lunden].,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1650.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Eugenius Philalethes = Thomas Vaughan.</NOTE><NOTE>Publisher's name from Wing V142A.</NOTE><NOTE>With a final leaf of verse to the author.</NOTE><NOTE>Probably not issued separately, but with his "Anthroposophia theomagica", since that work ends with F8, and the first quire of this work is signed G2, A3, G4, although the balance of the quires are signed B-D, E⁴. Thomason dates both works Jan. 9.</NOTE><NOTE>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 9".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (Early English books) and in the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Nature --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2000-00</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2001-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP Staff (Michigan)</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP Staff (Michigan)</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="fulc" R="UM" ID="A64761">
<STC T="W">V142</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99872473</BIBNO>
<VID>124910</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>ANIMA MAGICA ABSCONDITA;
Or A Discourse of the universall Spirit of Nature, With his strange, abstruse, miraculous Ascent, and descent.</P>
<P>By <HI>Eugenius Philalethes.</HI></P>
<BIBL><ABBR>Stapul:</ABBR> in <ABBR>Dion:</ABBR></BIBL>
<Q>Est autem Vniversum <HI>speculum Unum,</HI> ad <HI>Quod</HI> astans <HI>Amor,</HI> suum effor∣mat <HI>Idolum.</HI></Q>
<P>Dû a Digon: Hêb Dhû, Hêb Dhim.</P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>T.W.</HI> For <HI>H. B.</HI> 1650.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Reader.</HEAD>
<P>NOw God defend! what will become of me? I have nei∣ther consulted with the <HI>stars,</HI> nor their <HI>Vrinals,</HI> the Alma∣nacks. A fine Fel∣low, to neglect the <HI>Prophets,</HI> who are read in <HI>England</HI> every Day! They shall pardon me for this <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. There is a <HI>Mystery</HI> in their <HI>pro∣fession,</HI> they have not so much as heard of: <HI>Coelum stellatum Christianum</HI>; a <HI>new Heaven</HI> fansied on the <HI>old Earth.</HI> Here the <HI>Twelve Apostles</HI> have sur∣pris'd the <HI>Zodiak,</HI> and all the <HI>Saints</HI> are
<PB REF="3"/>
rang'd on their <HI>North,</HI> and <HI>South sides.</HI> It were a pretty vanity, to preach when Saint <HI>Paul</HI> is <HI>ascendent,</HI> and would not a <HI>Papist</HI> smile to have his <HI>Pope elected</HI> un∣der Saint <HI>Peter</HI>? Reader, if I studied <HI>these Things,</HI> I should think my self worst imployd then the <HI>Roman Chaucer</HI> was in his <HI>Troilus.</HI> I come out as if there were no <HI>Houres</HI> in the <HI>Day,</HI> nor <HI>Planets</HI> in the <HI>Houres</HI>: neither do I care for any thing, but that <HI>Interlude</HI> of <HI>Pe∣rendenga</HI> in <HI>Michael Cervantes: Let the old Man my Master live, and Christ be with us all.</HI> Thou wilt wonder now where this drives, for I have neither a <HI>Conde de lemos,</HI> nor a <HI>Cardinal</HI> to pray for. I pray for the <HI>Dead,</HI> that is, I wish <HI>him</HI> a <HI>fair Remembrance,</HI> whose <HI>Labours</HI> have <HI>deservd</HI> it. It happened in exposing my former Discourse to <HI>Censure,</HI> (a cu∣stom hath strangl'd many Truths in the Cradle) that a Learned Man suggested to me some bad Opinion he had of my Author, <HI>Henricus Cornelius Agrippa.</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
I ever understood, it was not <HI>One,</HI> but <HI>many</HI> in whose sentiment that <HI>miracle</HI> suffer'd. It is the Fortune of deep wri∣ters to <HI>miscary</HI> because of <HI>obscurity</HI>: Thus the <HI>Spots</HI> in the <HI>Moon</HI> with some Men are <HI>Earth,</HI> but 'tis more probable they are <HI>water.</HI> There is no <HI>Day</HI> so <HI>clear,</HI> but there are <HI>Lees</HI> towards the <HI>Horizon</HI>: so <HI>inferior Wits,</HI> when they reflect on <HI>higher Intellects,</HI> leave a <HI>Mist</HI> in their <HI>Beames.</HI> Had he liv'd in <HI>Igno∣rance,</HI> as most do, he might have past hence like the <HI>last yeares Cloudes,</HI> with∣out any more Remembrance. But as I believe the <HI>Trueth</HI> a maine <HI>Branch</HI> of that <HI>End,</HI> to which I was <HI>born</HI>; so I hold it my <HI>Duty</HI> to <HI>vindicate him,</HI> from <HI>whom</HI> I have receiv'd it. The <HI>world</HI> then being not able to <HI>confute</HI> this mans <HI>Principles</HI> by <HI>Reason,</HI> went about to do it by <HI>Scandal,</HI> and the <HI>first Argument</HI> they fastend on, was <HI>that</HI> of the <HI>Iews</HI> a∣gainst his <HI>Sviour: Thou art a Samari∣tan, and hast a Divel.</HI> The <HI>Chief</HI> in
<PB REF="4"/>
this <HI>Persecution</HI> is <HI>Cicognes,</HI> and after him <HI>Delrio</HI> in his Fabulous Disquisiti∣ons. But <HI>Paulus Iovius</HI> stirr'd in the <HI>Vomit,</HI> who amongst other mens <HI>Lives</HI> hath put my <HI>Author</HI> to <HI>Death.</HI> It is done indeed Emphatically betwixt <HI>Him,</HI> and his <HI>Poet,</HI> whom he <HI>hir'd</HI> (it seems) to stitch <HI>verse</HI> to his <HI>Prose,</HI> and so <HI>patch'd</HI> up the <HI>Legend.</HI>
<Q>Quis <HI>(sayth he)</HI> in Henrici Cornelii Agrippae sedato vultu portentosum Ingenium latuisse crediderit?</Q>
In his subsequent Discourse he states his <HI>Question,</HI> and returns my Authors <HI>best parts</HI> as a <HI>Libell</HI> on his <HI>memorie.</HI> But that which troubles him most of all is, <HI>That Agrippa</HI> should <HI>prove</HI> his <HI>Doctrine</HI> out of the <HI>Scriptures.</HI> Then he inculcates the solemn <HI>Crambe</HI> of his <HI>Dog-Devill,</HI> whose <HI>Collar Em∣blematically</HI> wrought with <HI>Nails,</HI> made the <HI>Ruffe</HI> to his <HI>Familiar.</HI> For a Close to the story, he <HI>kills</HI> him at <HI>Lyons,</HI> where being neer his <HI>Departure</HI> he un∣ravell'd his <HI>Magick</HI> in this desperat Dis∣mission,
<PB REF="4"/>
<HI>Abi perdita Bestia, qui me to∣tum perdidisti.</HI> This is the most <HI>grosse Lie,</HI> and the least <HI>probable</HI> in every <HI>cir∣cumstance</HI> that ever was related. <HI>Devils</HI> use not to <HI>quit</HI> their <HI>Conjurers</HI> in the <HI>day of Death,</HI> neither will they at <HI>such Times</HI> be <HI>exterminated.</HI> This is the <HI>hour</HI> wherein <HI>they attend</HI> their <HI>Prey,</HI> and from <HI>seeming servants</HI> become <HI>cruell Ma∣sters.</HI> Besides, is it not most gross, That any should <HI>dog</HI> this <HI>Devil</HI> from <HI>Agrippa's Lodging</HI> to <HI>Araris,</HI> where (sayth this Prelate) he plung'd himself? Certainly spirits passe away invisibly, and with that <HI>dispatch</HI> no mortall man can <HI>trace</HI> them. Believe <HI>this,</HI> &amp; believe all the <HI>Fables</HI> of <HI>Purgatory.</HI> Now Rea∣der, thou hast heard the <HI>worst,</HI> lend a just Eare, and thou shalt hear the <HI>Best. Io∣hannes Wyerus,</HI> a profest Adversarie to <HI>Ceremonial Magick,</HI> and sometimes <HI>sec∣cretary</HI> to <HI>Cornelius Agrippa,</HI> in his <HI>Dae∣monomania</HI> speaks thus. He wonders that some learned <HI>Germans</HI> and <HI>Italians</HI>
<PB REF="5"/>
were not asham'd to <HI>traduce his Master in their publick writings.</HI> That he had a <HI>Dog</HI> whose <HI>Call</HI> was <HI>Mounsieur</HI> he confesseth: and this <HI>Spaniell</HI> during his service he us'd to <HI>leade,</HI> when <HI>Agrippa</HI> walk'd abroad, <HI>in Loro ex pilis concin∣nato.</HI>
<Q>At revera <HI>(saith he)</HI> Canis erat Naturalis Masculus,</Q>
To which also <HI>Agrippa</HI> coupl'd a <HI>Bitch</HI> of the same colour call'd <HI>Madammoyscelle.</HI> It is con∣fest he was <HI>fond</HI> of this <HI>Dog,</HI> as some men are, and having <HI>divorc'd</HI> his <HI>first wife,</HI> would suffer <HI>him</HI> for a <HI>Sarcasm,</HI> to sleep with him under the sheetes. In his <HI>study</HI> too, this <HI>dog</HI> would couch on the <HI>Table</HI> by his <HI>Master,</HI> whence this <HI>great Philosopber, inter supellectilem Chartaceam certe insignem delitescens,</HI> sayth <HI>Wyerus,</HI> would not somtimes stir out for a <HI>whole week together.</HI> So studi∣ous was he for the <HI>good of posterity,</HI> who have but <HI>coldly rewarded him</HI> for his pains. I have observ'd also in his <HI>Epi∣stles,</HI> That when he was resident at
<PB REF="5"/>
<HI>Malines,</HI> his <HI>Domesticks</HI> us'd to give him an <HI>account</HI> in their <HI>Letters</HI> how <HI>his dogs Far'd</HI>; so <HI>fond</HI> was <HI>he</HI> of those <HI>Crea∣tures.</HI> But to come to the rest of the Legend; <HI>Paulus Iovius</HI> tells you he died at <HI>Lyons ignobili, &amp; tenebroso in diver∣sorio:</HI> But <HI>Wyerus,</HI> who had <HI>more Rea∣son</HI> to be <HI>inquisitive</HI> after his <HI>masters death,</HI> tells me he died at <HI>Granople,</HI> and that <HI>in Domino,</HI> not <HI>desperatly</HI> as his <HI>E∣nemies</HI> would have it. Here now was a <HI>Ioviall</HI> stride from <HI>Gratianopolis</HI> to <HI>Lugdunum:</HI> Sure this <HI>Paul</HI> was a <HI>scant Geographer.</HI> But Reader, it is not my Intention to conceale any thing in this <HI>matter,</HI> know therfore that <HI>Agrippa</HI> had another <HI>dog,</HI> his <HI>Filioli:</HI> and this <HI>last</HI> died in more <HI>respect</HI> then <HI>most</HI> of his masters <HI>Adversaries.</HI> For my <HI>author</HI> by some <HI>secret meanes</HI> having strangely <HI>qualified him,</HI> divers <HI>learned men</HI> writ <HI>Epitaphs</HI> upon him, whereof some have been <HI>published,</HI> and are yet <HI>extant.</HI> Out of this <HI>Fable</HI> of the <HI>Cerberus
<PB REF="6"/>
Baptista Possevinus</HI> pumpt these ver∣ses.</P>
<Q><L>Vivens quem cernis Tumulum, nè fertè meretur</L>
<L>Os placidum, stygii Rex fuit iste Lacus.</L>
<L>Quare etiam Custodē habuit, dū viveret, Orci,</L>
<L>Cui nunc in Tenebris praeda daret Comitem.</L>
<L>Ast Hic, st Ingeniū moderari scisset, ad Auras</L>
<L>Tantum isset, Quantum Tartara nigra subit.</L></Q>
<P>Thus have they <HI>all-to-be-divell'd him,</HI> but why may not <HI>Trueth</HI> run in <HI>verse,</HI> aswell as <HI>scandal</HI>?</P>
<Q><L>Sic <HI>Agrippa</HI> ingens, <HI>duplici</HI> quo{que} sufficit <HI>Orbi,</HI></L>
<L>Fractaque <HI>diversas</HI> Fabrica monstrat <HI>Opes.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Terram</HI> Terra capit <HI>Caeloque affinia</HI> Coelum</L>
<L>Possidet: <HI>Hoc</HI> vivus scripserat ante <HI>Sophos.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Naturam Natura trahit</HI>: similem{que} <HI>Supernae</HI></L>
<L>Hanc animam, agnoscit <HI>vita superna</HI> suam.</L>
<L>Sic vivens, Moriensque <HI>Docet</HI>: dumque altus in <HI>Astra</HI></L>
<L>Tendit, habet <HI>Magicas</HI> parca vel ipsa <HI>Manus.</HI></L></Q>
<P><PB REF="6"/>Now Reader, if thou wouldest be further satisfied in his <HI>distaste</HI> of <HI>Black Magick,</HI> I wish thee to read his most <HI>Christian Invective</HI> against the <HI>German Conjurer</HI> entertained in the <HI>French Court.</HI> Nay, so zealous, and <HI>nice</HI> of <HI>Conscience</HI> was <HI>he,</HI> that being solli∣cited by some Divines for a <HI>Comment</HI> on <HI>Trismegistus,</HI> he return'd them a <HI>very tart answer,</HI> referring all <HI>true know∣ledge</HI> to the <HI>Scripture.</HI> In a word, he did not onely hate <HI>impious,</HI> but <HI>vain Arts</HI>; For he lost the <HI>Favour</HI> of the <HI>Queen-Mother,</HI> because he would not be <HI>imployed</HI> by her in <HI>Astrologie.</HI> A <HI>science</HI> in whose <HI>true naturall part,</HI> which concernes <HI>Generation</HI> and <HI>Cor∣ruption,</HI> he was <HI>skill'd</HI> to a <HI>miracle</HI>: but <HI>he</HI> knew it was <HI>bootles</HI> to look <HI>fatal E∣vents</HI> in the <HI>Planets,</HI> for <HI>such</HI> are not <HI>written</HI> in <HI>Nature,</HI> but in the <HI>superior Tables</HI> of <HI>Praedestination.</HI> Having thus then sufficiently prov'd his <HI>Integrity,</HI>
<PB REF="7"/>
I will in a few words discover the <HI>grounds</HI> of his <HI>persecution.</HI> He was a <HI>man reform'd</HI> in his <HI>Religion,</HI> and had I the leysure to cite his <HI>workes,</HI> I could quick∣ly prove <HI>he was not of the Roman Church.</HI> For in his Book <HI>de vanitate scientiarum</HI> he allows not of <HI>Monks</HI> and <HI>Friars,</HI> but calls them Sects, <HI>Quibus carvit Ec∣clesia, cum fuit Optima.</HI> And certainly that <HI>notable Iest</HI> of <HI>his</HI> on the <HI>Cowle,</HI> nettles the <HI>Papists</HI> to this Day. He dis∣claimes also their <HI>Images,</HI> their <HI>Invoca∣tion</HI> of <HI>Saints,</HI> their <HI>Purgatory</HI> and <HI>Par∣dons,</HI> and would have the <HI>Laity</HI> com∣municate <HI>sub utraque specie.</HI> He <HI>corrects</HI> the <HI>Pope himself</HI> sufficiently, and is ut∣terly against the <HI>Inquisition Office.</HI> what also <HI>his Opinion</HI> was of <HI>Luther,</HI> is not hard to guesse out of his <HI>E∣pistles</HI>: For in a <HI>letter</HI> to <HI>Melan∣cthon</HI> he hath these words. <HI>Saluta∣bis per me invictum illum Haereti∣cum Martinum Lutherum, qui (ut
<PB REF="7"/>
ait Paulus in Actibus) servit Deo suo secundum sectam quam vocant Haere∣sin.</HI> Lastly, he was altogether for the <HI>written word,</HI> preferring it to <HI>humane Constitutions,</HI> which is <HI>contrarie</HI> to the <HI>Papist,</HI> who will not allow it to be the <HI>Iudge of Controversies.</HI> This is the Man, and <HI>thus qualified</HI> at <HI>Home,</HI> how∣soever the <HI>world</HI> hath <HI>rendred</HI> him <HI>a∣broad.</HI> Now for <HI>his more mysteri∣ous Principles,</HI> thou hast their <HI>Maine</HI> in this <HI>Discourse,</HI> which if thou canst apprehend, I know thou wilt <HI>style</HI> him in particular, as <HI>Trismegistus</HI> doth <HI>Man</HI> in <HI>Generall,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: or as <HI>Panaetius</HI> did his <HI>Plato, Hominem Divinum, Sanctissi∣mum, sapientissimum &amp; Homerum Philo∣sophorum.</HI> But this <HI>sluttish shuffle</HI> fits not his <HI>Memorie,</HI> and Things fall from me now as <HI>strictures,</HI> not <HI>Compo∣sitions.</HI> I shall say nothing more,
<PB REF="8"/>
but leave thee to thy <HI>studies,</HI> whiles I translate that <HI>Epitaph</HI> of <HI>Platina,</HI> to his <HI>Tom.</HI> 6.</P>
<Q><L>Quisquis es, si pius, Agrippam</L>
<L>Et suos ne vexes: Anguste</L>
<L>Iacent, &amp; soli volunt esse.</L></Q>
<BYLINE>E. P.</BYLINE>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="8"/>
<HEAD>ANIMA MAGICA ABSCONDITA.</HEAD>
<P>TO build <HI>Castles in the air,</HI> is a <HI>Common Proverb</HI> with all <HI>Men,</HI> but a <HI>Common Pra∣ctice</HI> with the <HI>Peripateticks</HI> onely. I have oftentimes admir'd, That the very end and Result of their <HI>Philoso∣phy</HI> did not cleerly discover its falsity. It is a meer <HI>Help to Discourse. Moode</HI> and <HI>Figure</HI> are their two pillars, their <HI>Non ultra</HI>: Their <HI>Heptarchie</HI> ends in a <HI>Syllogism,</HI> and the best professour amongst Them is but a scold well disciplin'd. Their seven years studie are seven years of Famine; They leave the <HI>Soul not satisfied,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen:</NOTE> and are more a Dream then that of <HI>Pharaoh.</HI> For verily if the stage, and Reign of Dreams be no
<PB N="2" REF="9"/>
where beyond <HI>Fansie,</HI> then the <HI>Fansies</HI> of these men being no where beyond their <HI>Authors,</HI> may rest on the same <HI>Pillow.</HI> This Sect then may be styl'd <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: Their Conceptions are not grounded on any Reason existent in <HI>Na∣ture,</HI> but they would ground Nature on Reasons fram'd, and principl'd by their own Concepti∣ons. Their <HI>Philosophie</HI> is built on <HI>generall em∣pty Maxims,</HI> Things of that stretch and <HI>latitude</HI> they may be applied to any Thing but conduce to the <HI>Discovery of Nothing.</HI> These are the first <HI>Lineaments</HI> of their <HI>Monster,</HI> and in reference to them they have many <HI>subordinate Errors,</HI> which praetend a <HI>Symmetrie</HI> with their Funda∣mentalls, but in trueth have none at all. These <HI>later Quillets</HI> are so minc'd with Divisions and Distinctions, That their very patrons are dubi∣ous how to state them. I could compare their <HI>Physiologie</HI> to a <HI>Chase in Arras,</HI> where there is much of similitude, but nothing of <HI>Truth.</HI> Tis the <HI>Childe of Fancie,</HI> a <HI>Romance</HI> in <HI>Syllogisms,</HI> a <HI>Texture</HI> of their <HI>own Brain,</HI> like that Cob-web <HI>Campagnia,</HI> which <HI>Lucians Spiders</HI> planted be∣twixt the <HI>Moon,</HI> and <HI>Venus. Nature</HI> in Gene∣rall (say They) is <HI>Principium Motus, &amp; quie∣tis.</HI> A Form is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, a definition they know not what to make of, and the soul is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or <HI>actus Corporis Organici.</HI> These Two last Descriptions (for they are no <HI>Substan∣tial
<PB N="3" REF="9"/>
definitions</HI>) are such <HI>Riddles,</HI> that I verily believe <HI>Aristotle</HI> made use of those words <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>&amp;</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> because he would not discover his Ignorance in these points. For why should a <HI>Form,</HI> be call'd <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or in what other Author can we find this <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>? But be∣cause Nature in Generall, that is, in her <HI>Active,</HI> and <HI>Passive</HI> portions, namely <HI>Matter</HI> and <HI>Form,</HI> together with the <HI>Soul</HI> of man, are the main Fundamentals wherein to build a <HI>Philo∣sophie,</HI> and that this <HI>Aristotle</HI> is so <HI>Sainted</HI> by his <HI>Clients,</HI> that the <HI>Divines of Collein</HI> tell us, He was <HI>praecursor Christi in Naturalibus, ut Iohannes Baptista in Gratuitis</HI>; I shall further examine these his Definitions, and acknow∣ledge the Benefit when I finde it.</P>
<P>In the first place then, it may be thought I am beholding to this Man for telling me, that Nature is a Principle. So I may tell the Rea∣der, The <HI>Magician's passive spirit</HI> is a princi∣ple, but if I tell him not what kind of sub∣stance it is, I will allow him ten years studie, and if the <HI>Sun</HI> went back every day <HI>ten De∣grees</HI> in his <HI>Diall,</HI> he shall not without a su∣pernaturall assistance know what, or where it is. But you will reply: He tells me further, it is a principle causet<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Bodies to move and rest. I thank him for his Nothing. I desire not to know what this Principle doth, for that is ob∣vious to every Eye; but I would know what
<PB N="4" REF="10"/>
it is, and therefore he may pocket his Defini∣tion. Again you will object, he tells me not onely that Nature is a Principle, but that <HI>Na∣tura est Forma,</HI> and by Consequence <HI>Forma est Natura.</HI> This is <HI>Idem per Idem,</HI> he retains me in a circle of notions, but resolves nothing at all <HI>Essentially.</HI> Besides, <HI>Forma</HI> in the <HI>genuine scope</HI> of the <HI>Language</HI> signifies the <HI>outward symme∣trie,</HI> or <HI>shape</HI> of a <HI>Compound.</HI> But the <HI>Peripate∣ticks</HI> who impose on <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oungs,</HI> as they do on <HI>Nature,</HI> render it otherwise in their Books; and mistake the <HI>effect</HI> for the <HI>cause.</HI> I shall therefore take it in Their sense, and be content for once to <HI>subscribe</HI> to their <HI>Com∣ments. Forma</HI> then in their Conception is the same with <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or <HI>vis Formatrix,</HI> which <HI>Aristotle</HI> defines <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. I must confesse I do not understand him, and therefore I shall take him upon Trust, as his Disciples expound him.
<Q>Est enim <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> (<HI>saith</HI> Magirus) quoniam absolvit, expolit, &amp; infor∣mat Rem Naturalem, ut per eam una ab Al∣terá distinguatur.</Q>
This is an expresse of the Office and Effect of Formes, but nothing at all to their Substance, or Essence</P>
<P>Now let us see what he sayth to the <HI>Soul of Man.</HI> The Soul (sayth he) is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> that is in plain Terms <HI>Consummatio,</HI> or barba∣rously but <HI>truely Finitatio,</HI> though his own fol∣lowers falsly render it, <HI>Actus Corporis Organici.</HI>
<PB N="5" REF="10"/>
But this definition is cōmon to beasts, &amp; plants, &amp; therfore he hath stumbl'd on another; <HI>Anima est Principium quo vivimus; sentimus; move∣mur, &amp; Intellîgimus.</HI> Now both these <HI>descri∣ptions</HI> concerne only the Operations and Facul∣ties which the Soul exerciseth in the Body, but discover not her <HI>Nature,</HI> or <HI>Originall</HI> at all. It was ingenuously done of <HI>Galen,</HI> who con∣fess'd his Ignorance concerning the substance of the Soul, but this Fellow who had not so much honestie is voic'd <HI>Prince of Philosophers,</HI> and the positions of more <HI>glorious Authors</HI> are ex∣amin'd by his <HI>Dictats,</HI> as it were by a Touch∣stone; Nay the Scripture it self is oftentimes wrested, and forc'd by his Disciples to vote a <HI>Placet</HI> to his Conclusions. It is a miserable task to dwell on this <HI>Ethnick,</HI> to gather his <HI>straw</HI> and <HI>stubble</HI> most of our Dayes, and after all to be no better acquainted with our selves, but that the <HI>Soul</HI> is the <HI>Cause of Life, sense, motion, and understanding.</HI> I pity our <HI>Customarie Fol∣lies,</HI> that we binde our selves over to a <HI>Prenti∣ship</HI> of <HI>Expence and study,</HI> onely to compasse a few superficiall Trueths which every <HI>plow-man</HI> knows without book. Verily Nature is so much a Tutor, that none can be ignorant in these Things: for who is so stupid as not to know the Difference between Life and Death, the absence, and presence of his Soul? Yet these very defi∣nitions,
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/><PB N="4" REF="11"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/><PB N="5" REF="11"/>
<PB N="6" REF="12"/>
though look'd upon as rare, profound, Philosophicall Determinations, instruct us in nothing more. Away then with this <HI>Peripate∣ticall Philosophy,</HI> this <HI>Vain Babling,</HI> as S. <HI>Paul</HI> justly stiles it, for sure inough he had some Ex∣perience of it at <HI>Athens,</HI> in his Dispute about the <HI>Resurrection.</HI> Let us no more look on this <HI>Olla Podrida,</HI> but on that Spirit which resides in the Elements: for this produceth reall Effects by the subsequent <HI>Rotations</HI> of corruption &amp; ge∣neration, but the spirit of Errour, which is <HI>A∣ristotl's,</HI> produceth nought but a multiplicity of Notions. Observe then, that this <HI>Stagirit</HI> and Nature are at a great distance, the One ends in works, the other in word: his Followers refine the old Notions, but not the old Crea∣tures. And verily the Mystery of their profes∣sion consists onely in their Termes: if their Spe∣culations were expos'd to the world in a <HI>plain dresse,</HI> their sense is so empty, and shallow, there is not any would acknowledge Them for Philosophers. In some Discourses, I confesse they have Nature before them, but they go not the right way to apprehend her, They are still in Chase, but never overtake their Game: for who is he amongst Them, whose knowledge is so intire and regular, that he can justifie his Po∣sitions by Practice? Againe, in some Things they are quite besides the <HI>Cushion,</HI> they scold and
<PB N="7" REF="12"/>
squable about Whymzies and Problems of their own which are no more in Nature then <HI>Lu∣cian's Lachanopters,</HI> or <HI>Hippogypians.</HI> Now the Reason of their Errours is, because they are Ex∣perienc'd in nothing but outward Accidents, or Qualities: and all the performance they can do in Philosophie is to pronounce a Body Hot, or Cold moyst, or drie; But if they minde the Es∣sentiall Temperament, they are grosly mista∣ken in stateing these Qualifications for it is not the Touch, or sight that can discern Intrinsecal, true Complexions. A Body that is outwardly Cold to the Sense, may be <HI>hotter in Occulto</HI> where the <HI>genuine Temperament</HI> lyes, then the <HI>Sun</HI> himself is <HI>in Manifesto.</HI> But they know not the Providence of Nature how she interpo∣seth a different resisting <HI>Quality</HI> in the Circum∣ference of every Thing, lest the <HI>Qualities</HI> of <HI>Ambient Bodies</HI> should conspire in too great a measure with the Center, and so procure a Dis∣solution of the Compound. Thus she interpo∣seth her passive refreshing Spirit between the <HI>Centrall Fire,</HI> and the <HI>Sulphur</HI>; Again she pla∣ceth the <HI>Sulphur</HI> between the <HI>Liquor</HI> of the <HI>Coelestiall Luna,</HI> and her <HI>outward Mercurie.</HI> A rare and Admirable <HI>Texture,</HI> infallibly pro∣ving, That none but <HI>God onely wise,</HI> who fore∣saw the Conveniencies and Disconveniencies of his Creatures, could range them in that sa∣ving
<PB N="8" REF="13"/>
Order, and <HI>Connexion.</HI> But to go further with these <HI>Peripateticks</HI>: Their <HI>Philosophy</HI> is a kinde of <HI>Physiognomy,</HI> They will judge of in∣visible, Inward Principles, (Formes as they call them) which are shut up in the Closet of the Matter, and all this in perusing the outside, or Crust of Nature. 'Twere a foolish presumption, if a <HI>Lapidarie</HI> should undertake to state the va∣lue, or Lustre of a Jewell that is Lockt up, be∣fore he opens the <HI>Cabinet.</HI> I advice them there∣fore to use their Hands, not their Fansies, and to change their Abstractions into Extractions; for verily as long as they lick the shell in this fashion, and <HI>pierce</HI> not <HI>experimentally</HI> into the <HI>Center</HI> of <HI>things,</HI> they can do no otherwise then they have done; they cannot know things sub∣stantially, but onely describe them by their out∣ward effects and Motions, which are subject, and obvious to every Common Eye. Let them con∣sider therefore, That there is in Nature a Cer∣tain spirit which applies himself to the matter, and actuates in every Generation. That there is also a passive Intrinsecal principle where he is more immediatly resident then in the rest, and by mediation of which he communicates with the more gross, materiall parts. For there is in Nature a Certain Chain, or subordinate pro∣pinquity of Complexions between Visibles, and invisibles, and this is it by which the superiour,
<PB N="9" REF="13"/>
<HI>spirituall Essences descend,</HI> and converse here be∣low with the <HI>Matter.</HI> But have a care lest you misconceive me. I speake not in this place of the <HI>Divine spirit,</HI> but I speake of a certaine <HI>Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> by which a <HI>particular Spirit</HI> may be uni∣ted to the <HI>universall,</HI> and <HI>Nature</HI> by conse∣quence may be strangely <HI>exalted,</HI> and <HI>multiply∣ed.</HI> Now then, you that have your Eyes in your Hearts, and not your Hearts in your Eyes, attend to that which is spoken, and that I may exhort you to <HI>Magick</HI> in the Magicians phrase, <HI>Intellectu Cordis Audite.</HI></P>
<P>It is obvious to all those whom Nature hath inrich'd with sence, and convenient Organs to to exercise it, That every body in the World is subject to a certain <HI>Species</HI> of Motion. Ani∣mals have their Progressive outward, and their Vitall Inward Motions. The Heavens are car∣ried with that <HI>species,</HI> which the Peripateticks call <HI>Lation,</HI> where by the way I must tell you, it proceeds from an <HI>Intrinsecall Principle,</HI> for Intelligences are fabulous. The <HI>Aire</HI> mooves variously, The <HI>Sea</HI> hath his Flux and Refluxe. <HI>Vegetables</HI> have their growth and augmentati∣on, which necessarily inferre a Concoction; And finally the <HI>Earth,</HI> with her Mineralls and all other Treasures, are subject to alteration, that is to Generation and Corruption. Now the Matter of it selfe being meerely Passive, and
<PB N="10" REF="14"/>
furnished with no motive Faculty at all, wee must of necessity conclude, that there is some o∣ther <HI>inward Principle</HI> which acts and regulates it in every severall <HI>species</HI> of motion. But veri∣ly it is not enough to call this <HI>Principle</HI> a Form, and so bury up the Riches of Nature in this narrow, and most absurd Formality. We should rather abstaine from Scribling, or study to publish that which may make something for the Authors Credit, but much more for the benefit of the Readers. To be plaine then, this <HI>Principle</HI> is <HI>Anima Mundi,</HI> or the uni∣versall <HI>spirit</HI> of Nature. This <HI>Anima</HI> is retaind in the Matter by certaine other <HI>Proportionate natures,</HI> and missing a Vent, doth <HI>Organizare Molem.</HI> She labours what she can to resume her former Liberty, frames for her selfe a Ha∣bitation here in the Center, puts her <HI>Prison</HI> into some good order, and brancheth into the seve∣rall Members, that she may have more roome to act and imploy her <HI>Faculties.</HI> But you are to observe, that in every Frame there are 3 <HI>leading Principles.</HI> The first is this <HI>Anima</HI> whereof we have spoken something already. The second is that which is called <HI>spiritus Mundi,</HI> and this <HI>spirit</HI> is the <HI>medium per quod Anima infundi∣tur &amp; movet suum corpus.</HI> The third is a cer∣taine <HI>oleous aethereall water</HI>: this is <HI>Menstru∣um, &amp; Matrix Mundi,</HI> for in it all things
<PB N="11" REF="14"/>
are framed and preserved. The <HI>Anima</HI> is a Compound <HI>ex aura tenuissima, &amp; luce simplici∣ssima.</HI> Hence that admirable Platonicall Poet stil'd it—<HI>Aurai simplicis ignem.</HI> Virg.</P>
<P>Neither should you wonder that I say it is a Compound, for there is no <HI>perfect specificall Nature</HI> that is simple and voyd of Compositi∣on, but only that of God Almighty. Trust not then to <HI>Aristotle,</HI> who tells you, that the Ele∣ments are <HI>Corpora simplicia,</HI> for the contrary hath been manifested by absolute, infallible Experience. The <HI>Passive spirit</HI> is a thinne ae∣real substance, the only immediate Vestiment wherein the <HI>Anima</HI> wraps her selfe, when she descends and applies to Generation. The <HI>Ra∣dicall Vitall liquor</HI> is a pure Coelestiall Nature, answering in Proportion and complexion to the <HI>superiour interstellar Waters.</HI> Now as soone as the Passive spirit attracts the <HI>Anima,</HI> which is done when the first link in the Chayne moves (of which we shall speake in its due place) then the <HI>aethereall water</HI> in a moment attracts the <HI>Passive spirit,</HI> for this is the first visible Re∣ceptacle wherein the <HI>superiour Natures</HI> are <HI>Concentrated.</HI> The Soule being thus confined and imprisoned by lawfull Magick in this <HI>Li∣quid Chrystall,</HI> the Light which is in her streams thorough the Water, and then it is <HI>Lux mani∣fest è visibilis ad oculum,</HI> in which state it is
<PB N="12" REF="15"/>
first made subject to the <HI>Artist.</HI> Here now lies the Mystery of the Magicians <HI>denarius,</HI> his most secret and miraculous <HI>Pyramid,</HI> whose first V∣nity or <HI>Cone</HI> is alwaies in <HI>Horizonte Eternita∣tis,</HI> but his Basis or Quadrate is here below in <HI>Horizonte Temporis.</HI> The <HI>Anima</HI> consists of three Portions of light, and one of the <HI>matter.</HI> The <HI>Passive spirit</HI> hath two parts of the Matter, and two of the Light, wherefore it is called <HI>Natura media,</HI> and <HI>Sphaera Equalitatis</HI>; The Coelestial Water hath but one portion of <HI>Light</HI> to three of the <HI>Matter.</HI> Now the Chaine of Descent which concernes the <HI>spirituall parts,</HI> is grounded on a similitude, or Symboll of Natures according to that Principle of <HI>Osthanes</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. For there being three Portions of Light in the <HI>Anima,</HI> and two in the Passive spirit, the <HI>Inferiour</HI> at∣tracts the <HI>Superiour.</HI> Then there being but one Portion in the <HI>Coelestiall Nature,</HI> and two in the Middle spirit; this solitary shining <HI>Unity,</HI> attracts the other <HI>Binarius</HI> to Fortifie and aug∣ment its selfe, as Light joynes with Light, or Flame with Flame, and thus they hang in a <HI>Vitall magneticall Series.</HI> Againe the Chayn of <HI>Ascent</HI> which concerne the <HI>Matter,</HI> is perfor∣med thus. The Coelestiall nature differs not in substance from the Aereall Spirit, but only in Degree and Complexion; and the Aereall spirit
<PB N="13" REF="15"/>
differs from the <HI>Aura,</HI> or Materiall part of the <HI>Anima</HI> in Constitution only, and not in Nature; So that those three being but one sub∣stantially, may admit of a <HI>perfect, Hypostati∣call Vnion,</HI> and be carried by a certaine intel∣lectuall Light in <HI>Horizontem Mundi super-su∣premi,</HI> and so swallowed up of <HI>Immortality.</HI> But me thinks Nature complaines of a Prosti∣tution, that I goe about to diminish her Ma∣jesty, having allmost broken her S<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ale, and ex∣posed her naked to the World. I must con∣fesse I have gone very far, and now I must re∣call my selfe: For there is a necessity of reser∣ving, as well as publishing some things, and yet I will speake of greater matters. The <HI>A∣nima</HI> though in some sence active, yet is she not so essentially, but a meer <HI>Instrumentall Agent,</HI> For she is guided in her Operations by a <HI>Spiri∣tuall Metaphysicall Graine,</HI> a Seed or Glance of <HI>Light,</HI> simple, and without any Mixture de∣scending from the <HI>first Father of Lights.</HI> For though his <HI>full-ey'd</HI> Love shines on nothing but <HI>Man,</HI> yet every thing in the World is in some measure directed for his Preservation by a <HI>spice</HI> or <HI>touch</HI> of the <HI>first Intellect.</HI> This is partly confirmed by the Habitation and Residence of God: For he is seated <HI>above all his Creatures,</HI> to <HI>hatch</HI> as it were, and cherish them with <HI>li∣ving Eternall Influences</HI> which daily and
<PB N="14" REF="16"/>
hourely proceed from him. Hence he is call'd of the Cabalists <HI>Cether,</HI> and it answers to <HI>Par∣menides</HI> his <HI>Corona Ignea,</HI> which he plac'd a∣bove all the <HI>Visible spheares.</HI> This <HI>Flux</HI> of <HI>Immateriall powers,</HI> Christ himself, in whom the <HI>Fullnesse</HI> of the <HI>Godhead resided,</HI> confirm'd, and acknowledged in the <HI>Flesh:</HI> For when the <HI>diseased</HI> touch'd his <HI>Garment,</HI> though the <HI>prease</HI> was <HI>great,</HI> he <HI>questioned</HI> who it was, adding this <HI>Reason, I perceive</HI> (said he) <HI>that vertue is gone out of me.</HI> But laying aside such <HI>Proofs,</HI> though the <HI>Scripture</HI> abounds in <HI>Them,</HI> let us consider the <HI>Exercise,</HI> and <HI>practise</HI> of <HI>Nature</HI> here be∣low, and we shall finde her <HI>Game such,</HI> she can not <HI>play it</HI> without this <HI>Tutor.</HI> In the first place then, I would faine know <HI>who taught</HI> the <HI>spider</HI> his <HI>Mathematicks</HI>? how comes he to <HI>lodge</HI> in the <HI>Center</HI> of his <HI>Web,</HI> that he may <HI>sally</HI> upon all <HI>Occasions</HI> to any part of the <HI>Circumference</HI>? How comes he to <HI>praemeditate,</HI> and <HI>forecast</HI>? for if he did not first know, and imagine that there are <HI>Flies,</HI> whereupon he must <HI>feede,</HI> he would not watch for them, nor spin out his <HI>Netts</HI> in that <HI>exquisite form,</HI> and <HI>Texture.</HI> Verily we must needs confesse, that <HI>he</HI> who <HI>ordain'd Flyes</HI> for his <HI>sustenance,</HI> gave him also some <HI>small light</HI> to know, and <HI>execute</HI> his <HI>Ordinance.</HI> Tell me if you can, who taught the <HI>Hare</HI> to <HI>Coun∣termarch,</HI> when she <HI>doubles</HI> her <HI>Trace</HI> in the
<PB N="15" REF="16"/>
<HI>pursuit</HI> to <HI>confound</HI> the <HI>sent,</HI> and <HI>puzzle</HI> her <HI>persecutors?</HI> who <HI>counsels</HI> her to <HI>stride</HI> from the <HI>Double</HI> to her <HI>Form,</HI> that her <HI>steps</HI> may be at a <HI>greater distance,</HI> and by cnosequence the <HI>more difficult</HI> to <HI>finde</HI> out? Certainly this is a <HI>well or∣der'd policy,</HI> enough to prove that <HI>God</HI> is not <HI>absent</HI> from his <HI>Creatures,</HI> but that <HI>Wisdom reacheth mightily from one end to another,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Wis.</NOTE> and that <HI>his Incor∣ruptible spirit filleth all things.</HI> But to speak something more immediatly apposite to our purpose. Let us consider the severall products that are in <HI>nature,</HI> with their admirable fea∣tures and <HI>symmetrie.</HI> We know very well there is but one matter out of which there are form'd so many different shapes, and Constitutions. Now if the Agent which determinates, and fi∣gures the matter, were not a <HI>discerning</HI> Spirit, it were impossible for him to produce any thing at all. For let me suppose <HI>Hyliard</HI> with his <HI>Pencill,</HI> and <HI>Table</HI> ready to <HI>pourtray</HI> a <HI>Rose</HI>: if he doth not <HI>inwardly apprehend</HI> the very shape, and proportion of that which he intends to limne, he may aswell do it without his eyes, as without his <HI>Intellectualls.</HI> Let us now apply this to the Spirit which worketh in Nature. This moves in the <HI>Center</HI> of all things, hath the matter before him, as the <HI>Potter</HI> hath his <HI>clay,</HI> or the <HI>Limner</HI> his <HI>colours.</HI> And first of all he
<PB N="16" REF="17"/>
exerciseth his <HI>chymistry</HI> in severall <HI>Transmuta∣tions,</HI> producing <HI>Sinews, Veines, bloud, flesh,</HI> and <HI>bones</HI>: which work also includes his <HI>Arithme∣tick</HI> for he makes the Joynts and all Integrall parts, nay, as <HI>Christ</HI> tells us, the very Hairs of our Heads, in a certain determinate Number; which may conduce to the beauty and motion of the <HI>Frame.</HI> Again in the outward <HI>Linea∣ments,</HI> or <HI>symmetrie</HI> of the <HI>compound,</HI> he proves himself a most regular <HI>Mathematician,</HI> propor∣tioning Parts to Parts, all which Operations can proceede from Nothing but a <HI>Divine, In∣tellectuall spirit.</HI> For if he had not severall <HI>Ideas</HI> or <HI>Conoeptions</HI> correspondent to his several <HI>Intentions,</HI> he could not distinguish the one from the other: And if he were not sensible, if he did not foresee the work he doth intend, then the End could be no Impulsive cause, as the <HI>Pori∣pateticks</HI> would have it.</P>
<P>The Consideration of these severall offices which this spirit performs in Generation, made <HI>Aristotle</HI> himself grant, That in the Seeds of all Things there were <HI>Virtutes similes Arti∣ficiis.</HI> We should therefore examine who weaves the flowers of Vegetables? who colours them without a pencill? who bolts the branches up∣wards, and threds (as it were) their Roots downwards? for all these actions include a cer∣tain Artifice, which cannot be done without
<PB N="17" REF="17"/>
Judgement, and Discretion. Now our Saviour tells us, <HI>My Father worketh hitherto</HI>; and in another place, it is <HI>God cloathes the Lilie of the Field</HI> &amp; again <HI>not one Sparrow fals without your Father.</HI> Verily this is the <HI>Trueth,</HI> and the <HI>Te∣stemony</HI> of Trueth, notwithstanding <HI>Aristotle</HI> and his <HI>Problems.</HI> Neither should you think the <HI>Divine Spirit disparag'd</HI> in being president to every generation, because some Products seem poor, and contemptible: For verily as long as they conduce to the Glory of their Author, they are noble inough, and if you reflect upon <HI>Egypt,</HI> you will finde the basest of his Creatures to ex∣tort a <HI>Catholik Confession</HI> from the <HI>Wizards; Digitus Dei est hic,</HI> The <HI>Finger of God is here.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod.</NOTE> That I may come then to the point, These invisible, <HI>Centrall Artists</HI> are Lights seeded by the first Light, in that <HI>primitive Emanation,</HI> or <HI>sit Lux,</HI> which some falsly render <HI>Fiat Lux.</HI> For <HI>Nature</HI> is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, not a meer sound or Command, but a substantiall active Breath, proceeding from the Creatour<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and penetrating all things. God himself is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; and this is the only sense wherein a Form may be de∣fined <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. I know this will seem harsh to some Men, whose <HI>ignorant zeal,</HI> hath made them <HI>Adversaries</HI> to <HI>God,</HI> for they <HI>rob him</HI> of his Glory, and give it to his Creature, nay
<PB N="18" REF="18"/>
sometimes to fancies, and Inventions of their own. I wish <HI>such Philosophers</HI> to consider, whe∣ther in the beginning there was any life, or wis∣dom beyond the Creator, and if so, to tell us where. Verily (to use their own Term) they can never finde this <HI>Ubi.</HI> For they are gratious con∣cessions, or Talents which God of his free will hath lent us, and if he should resume them, we should presently return to our first Nothing. Let them take heed therefore whiles they attri∣bute Generation to Qualities: lest the true Author of it, should come against them with that charge, which he brought sometimes a∣gainst the <HI>Assyrian. Shall the ax boast it self against Him that heweth there∣with?</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Isai.</NOTE> <HI>or shall the saw magnifie it self against him that shaketh it? as if the Rod should shake it self against them that lift it up, or as if the staffe should lift up it self, as if it were no wood.</HI> Let them rather cashier their <HI>Aristotle,</HI> and the Errors wherewith he hath infatuated so many Generations. Let them approach with confidence to the Almighty God, who made the world, for none can give a better account of the work then the <HI>Architect.</HI> Let them not de∣spair to attain his Familiarity, for he is a God <HI>that desires to be known,</HI> and will <HI>reveale him∣self</HI> both for the <HI>manifestation of his own glory,</HI> and the <HI>Benefit</HI> of his <HI>Creature.</HI> There is no
<PB N="19" REF="18"/>
reason then why we should decline this great, and <HI>glorious School-Master,</HI> whose very Invi∣tation speaks more then an Ordinary Incou∣ragement. <HI>Thus sayeth the Lord, the Holy One of Israel, and our Maker: Ask me of things to come concerning my Sons,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Is. xlv.</NOTE> <HI>and Concerning the Work of my Hands Command you Me. I have made the Earth, and created man upon it</HI>; I, <HI>even my hand, have stretched out the Heavens, and all their Hostes have</HI> I <HI>commanded.</HI> But it will be question'd perhaps, how shall we approach to the Lord, and by what means may we finde him out? Truely not with words, but with workes, not in studying ignorant, <HI>Heathenish Authours,</HI> but in perusing, and trying his Crea∣tures: For in them Lies his secret path, which though it be shut up with thornes and Briars, with outward worldly Corruptions, yet if we would take the pains to remove this luggage, we might <HI>Enter the Terrestriall Paradise,</HI> that <HI>Hortus Conclusus</HI> of <HI>Solomon,</HI> where God de∣scends to walk, and drink of the sealed Foun∣tain. But verily there is such a generall preju∣dice such a customary opposition of all Prin∣ciples which crosse <HI>Aristotle,</HI> That trueth can no sooner step abroad, but some <HI>Sophister</HI> or o∣ther flings Dirt in her Face. It is strange that none of these Schoolmen consider, how the se∣verall
<PB N="20" REF="19"/>
distinctions, and divisions translated from <HI>Logick</HI> to <HI>Divinity,</HI> have set all Christendom on fire: How they have violated the Peace of many flourishing Kingdoms, and occasion'd more sects in Religion, then there are opinions in Philosophie. Most seasonable then and Chri∣stian is that Petition of Saint <HI>Augustine, A Logicâ libera nos Domine!</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">In Gen.</NOTE> And here I must desire the Reader not to mistake me<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I do not condemn the Vse, but the Abuse of Reason, the many subtleties, and Fetches of it, which Man hath so applied, That truth and Errour are equally dis∣putable. I am One that stands up for a <HI>true Naturall knowledge,</HI> grounded as <HI>Nature is,</HI> on Christ Jesus, who is the true <HI>Foundation</HI> of all things visible, and Invisible. I shall therefore in this Discourse, touch neerly upon those my∣steries, which some Few have delivered over to posterity, in difficult, obscure termes; That if pos∣sible, the Majesty of trueth, and the Benefit they shall receive from it, may settle Men in a new way, and bring them at last from vain, empty Fansies, to a Reall, sensible Fruition of Nature.</P>
<P>You may remember how in my former dis∣course of the Nature of Man, I mention'd a certain triplicity of Elements according to their severall Complexions in the severall Regions of the world. I shall now speak of another tripli∣city
<PB N="21" REF="19"/>
much more obscure and mysticall, without which you can never attain to the former, for these three principles are the <HI>Clavis</HI> of all <HI>Ma∣gick,</HI> without whose perfect Knowledge you can never truely understand the least <HI>Idioms</HI> in <HI>Nature.</HI> The first Principle is <HI>One in One,</HI> and <HI>One from One.</HI> It is a pure, white <HI>Virgin,</HI> and next to that which is most pure, and simple. This is the first created vnity. By this all things were made, not actually, but Mediately, and without This Nothing can be made either <HI>Ar∣tificiall</HI> or <HI>Naturall.</HI> This is <HI>Uxor D<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i, &amp; stel∣larum.</HI> By mediation of this, there is a descent from <HI>One</HI> into <HI>Four,</HI> and an ascent from <HI>three</HI> by <HI>four</HI> to the <HI>invisible, supernaturall Monas.</HI> Who knows not <HI>This,</HI> can never attain to the <HI>Art,</HI> for He knows not what he is to look for. The second Principle differs not from the <HI>sirst</HI> in substance and dignity, but in <HI>Complexion</HI> and Order. This <HI>second</HI> was the <HI>first,</HI> and is so still Essentially, but by <HI>adhaesion</HI> to the <HI>Matter</HI> it contracted an impurity, and so fell from its <HI>first unity,</HI> wherefore the <HI>Magicians</HI> stile it <HI>Bi∣narius.</HI> Separate therefore the <HI>Circumference</HI> from the <HI>Center per Lineam Diametralem,</HI> and there will appear unto thee the Philosophers <HI>Ternarius,</HI> which is the third <HI>Principle.</HI> This third is properly no principle, but a product of <HI>Art.</HI> It is a <HI>various</HI> Nature, Com∣pounded in one sence, and Decompounded in
<PB N="22" REF="20"/>
another, consisting of Inferior and superior <HI>pow∣ers.</HI> This is the Magicians <HI>Fire,</HI> This is <HI>Mer∣curius Philosophorum, celeberrimus ille Mi∣crocosmus, &amp; Adam.</HI> This is the <HI>Labyrinth</HI> and <HI>Wild</HI> of <HI>Magick</HI> where a <HI>world</HI> of <HI>students</HI> have <HI>lost themselves</HI>: a <HI>thing</HI> so <HI>confusedly</HI> and <HI>obscurely</HI> handled by such as knew it, that it is altogether impossible to find it in their <HI>Records.</HI> There is no late writer understands the <HI>full La∣titude,</HI> and <HI>universality</HI> of this <HI>Principle,</HI> nor the genuine <HI>Metaphysicall use</HI> thereof. It moves here below in shades and <HI>Tiffanies,</HI> above in <HI>whites aethereall Vestures</HI>; neither is there any thing in Nature expos'd to such a <HI>publique pro∣stitution</HI> as <HI>this</HI> is, for it <HI>passeth</HI> thorough all hands, and there is not <HI>any Creature</HI> but hath the <HI>use</HI> Thereof. This <HI>Ternarius,</HI> being reduc'd <HI>per Quaternarium</HI> ascends to the <HI>Magicall Decad,</HI> which is <HI>Monas Unitissima,</HI> in which state <HI>Quaecunque vult, potest</HI>; for it is <HI>united</HI> then <HI>per Aspectum</HI> to the <HI>first<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> eternall, spiritu∣all unity.</HI> But of these Three, hear the <HI>Oracle</HI> of <HI>Magick,</HI> the great, and solemn <HI>Agrippa.</HI>
<Q>Quatuor itaque quae diximus sunt Elementa, sine Quorum notitiâ perfectâ nullum in Ma∣giâ producere possumus effectum: Sunt au∣tem Singula Triplicia, ut sic Quaternarius com pleat Duodenarium: &amp; per septenarium in Denarium progrediens ad supremam Uni∣tatem,
<PB N="23" REF="20"/>
unde omnis Virtus, &amp; mirabilis ope∣ratio dependet, fiat progressus. Primo igitu ordine Elementa pura sunt, Quae nec Compo∣nuntur, nec mutantur, nec patiuntur commix∣tionem, sed Incorruptibilia sunt, &amp; non a qui∣bus, sed per quae omnium naturalium rerum Virtutes producuntur in Effectum. Virtutes Illorum a Nullo explicari possunt, quia in om∣nia possunt omnia. Haec qui ignorat, ad nul∣lam mitabilium Effectuum operationem per∣tingere potest. Secundi Ordinis Elementa Composita sunt, multiplicia, &amp; Varia, &amp; im∣pura, reducibilia tamen per Artem ad puram simplicitatem, quibus tuno ad suam simplici∣tatem reversis virtus est super omnia comple∣mentum dans omnium operationum occulta∣rum &amp; operationum naturae: haec sunt fun∣damentum totius Magiae naturalis. Tertii or∣dinis Elementa, haec primò &amp; per se non sunt Elementa, sed Decomposita varia multiplicia, &amp; inter se invicem permutabilia: Ipsa sunt in∣fallibile Medium, ideoque vocantur media Natura, sive Anima mcdiae naturae: paucis∣simi sunt, qui illorum profunda Mysteria in∣telligunt. In ipsis per certos Numeros, gradus, &amp; ordines: est Consummatio omnis Effectus in quacunque re Naturali, Coelesti, &amp; super∣coelesti, miranda sunt<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> &amp; plena mysteriis quae operari possunt in Magiâ tam Naturali, quam
<PB N="24" REF="21"/>
Divina: per ipsa enim omnium rerum ligatio∣nes, etiam solutiones, &amp; Transmutationes, &amp; Futurorum cognitio &amp; praedictio, etiam Ma∣lorum Daemonum Exterminatio, &amp; Bono∣rum Spirituum conciliatio ab Illis descendit. Sinc his igitur Triplicibus Elementis, eorun∣demque cognitione, nemo confidat se in oc∣cultis Magiae, &amp; naturae scient<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is quicquam posse operari. Quicunque aurem haec in illa, impura in pura, Multiplicia in Simplicia redu∣cere noverit, Eorundemque Naturam, Virtu∣tem, potestatem in Numero, gradibus, &amp; or∣dine sine Divisione substantiae discernere scive∣rit: Is facile obtinebit omnium naturalium re∣rum &amp; coelestium secretorum sclentiam, &amp; o∣operationem perfectam.</Q>
This is He with the <HI>black Spaniell</HI>: or rather, This is he <HI>Qui ab in∣eunte aetate semper circa mirabilium Effectuum, &amp; plenas Mysteriorum operationes Curiosus, in trepidusque extitit Explorator.</HI> Now for your further Instruction hear also the <HI>Dark Disciple</HI> of the more dark <HI>Libanius Gallus.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ioan. Trith.</NOTE>
<Q>Primum principi∣um in uno consistit, non a quo, sed per Quod omnis mirandorum naturalium virtus produ∣citur in Effectum: per Quod diximus, quia Purum ab uno procedens non componitur, neque mutatur. Ad ipsum a Ternario &amp; qua∣ternario fit ad Monadem progressus, ut com∣pleatur
<PB N="25" REF="21"/>
Denarius: per, ipsum enim est Numeri regressus ad unum, simul descensus in quatuor, &amp; Ascensus in Monadem. Impossibile est compleri Denarium, nisi per ipsum: Monas in Triade laeta convertitur. Omnes hoc princi∣pium post principium Monadis Ignorantes nil in Ternario proficiunt, nec ad sacrum qua∣ternarium pertingunt. Nam etsi sapientum Libros omnes habeant, syderum cursus, virtu∣tes, potestates, operationes, &amp; proprietates per∣fecte cognoscant, ipsorumque imagines, Annu∣los, &amp; Sigilla &amp; secretissima quaeque ad plenum intelligant, nullum tamen mirandorum conse∣qui possent in suis operationibus effectum, sine hujus principii a principio cognitione, in prin∣cipium; unde omnes quotquot vidi in Magiâ Naturali Operantes aut nihil consecuti sunt, aut ad vana, frivola, &amp; superstitiosa, post lon∣gas &amp; inutiles operationes desperatione pro∣lapsi sunt. Principium vero secundum ordine non Dignitate quidem a Primo separatum quod unum existens facit Ternarium, est quod operatur miranda per Binarium. In uno est enìm unum, &amp; non est unum, est simplex, &amp; in Quaternario componitur: Quo purificato per Ignem in sole Aqua pura egreditur &amp; ipsum ad suam simplicitatem reversum, Complementum operanti monstrabit occultorum. Hic Cen∣trum est totius Magiae naturalis, cujus circum∣ferentia
<PB N="26" REF="22"/>
sibi unita circulum repraesentat inmen∣sus ordo in infinitum: Virtus ejus super Omnia purificata, &amp; simplex minor Omnibus, Qua∣ternario super gradu composita. Quaternarius autem Pythagoricus numerus Ternario sufful∣tus, si ordinem gradumque observat, purificatus purusque in uno, ad Binarium in Ternario mi∣randa &amp; occulta Naturae operari potest. Hic est Quaternarius in cujus mensurâ Ternarius Binario conjunctus in uno cuncta facit, quae mirabiliter facit. Ternarius ad unitatem re∣ductus per aspectum omnia in se continet, &amp; quae vult potest. Principium tertium per se non est principium, sed inter ipsum &amp; Binarium est finis omnis scientiae &amp; Artis mysticae, ac infal∣lible Medii Centrum: in alio quam in ipso fa∣cilius non erratur, quoniam paucissimi vivunt in Terris qui profunda ejus intelligant: Vari∣um est compofitum, &amp; per septenarium in Ternarium octies multiplicatum consurgens, &amp; manens fixum. In ipso est consummatio Nu∣meri graduum, &amp; ordinis: per hoc omnes Phi∣losophi, occultorum naturae veri Inquisitores mirabiles effectus consecuti sunt; per ipsum ad simplex Elementum in Ternario reductum su∣bito fiunt infirmitatum curae miraculosae, &amp; naturaliter omnium aegritudinum: opusque in Magia Naturali &amp; praeternaturali operantis consequitur Effectum per dispositionem qua∣ternarii.</Q>
<PB N="27" REF="22"/>
Praedictio futurorum per ipsum veri∣ficatur, Occultorumque insinuatio, non aliunde quam per ipsum a Natura percipitur.
<Q>Hoc uni∣co Medio secretum Naturae a peritur Alchimi∣stis, sine quo nec Intellectus Artis acquiritur, nec operationis Effectus invenitur. Errant, crede mihi, Errant omnes, qui sine istis Tribus Principiis quicquam operari in occultis Na∣turae Scientiis Se posse confidunt.</Q>
Thus far <HI>Trithemius</HI>; where for thy better understand∣ing of him I must inform thee there is a <HI>twofold Binarius, Lucis, &amp; Confusionis</HI>: but peruse <HI>Agrippa</HI> seriously <HI>de scalis Numerorum,</HI> and thou mayst apprehend all, for our <HI>Abbot</HI> bor∣rowed this <HI>Language</HI> from <HI>Him,</HI> the <HI>perusall</HI> of <HI>whose Books</HI> he had, before he <HI>publish'd</HI> any thing in this <HI>Nature</HI> of his <HI>own.</HI> Now for thy further Instruction go along with me, not to <HI>A∣thens</HI> or <HI>stagyra,</HI> but to that <HI>Secretary</HI> and <HI>Pen-Man</HI> of <HI>God Almighty,</HI> who stood in a <HI>Cleft</HI> of the <HI>Rock</HI> when he made all his <HI>Goodnes</HI> to passe before <HI>him.</HI> I am certain the <HI>world</HI> will won∣der I should make use of <HI>Scripture</HI> to establish <HI>Physiologie,</HI> but I would have them know that all <HI>secrets Physicall</HI> and <HI>Spirituall,</HI> all the <HI>close Connexions,</HI> and that <HI>mysterious Kisse of God</HI> and <HI>Nature</HI> is clearly and punctually discover∣ed there. Consider that <HI>mercifull mystery</HI> of the <HI>Incarnation</HI> wherein the <HI>fullnesse</HI> of the <HI>God∣head</HI>
<PB N="28" REF="23"/>
was <HI>incorporated,</HI> and the <HI>Divine Light</HI> united to the <HI>Matter</HI> in a far <HI>greater measure</HI> then at the <HI>sirst Creation. Consider</HI> it I say, and thou shalt finde, that <HI>no Philosophie</HI> hath per∣fectly united <HI>God</HI> to his <HI>Creature,</HI> but the <HI>Chri∣stian,</HI> wherefore also it is the onely <HI>true Philo∣sophie,</HI> and the onely <HI>true Religion:</HI> for with∣out this <HI>union</HI> there can be neither a <HI>naturall Temporall,</HI> nor a <HI>Spiritual aeternall Life. Mo∣ses</HI> tells us that in the beginning <HI>God</HI> created the <HI>Heaven</HI> and the <HI>Earth,</HI> that is the <HI>Virgin Mer∣curie,</HI> and the <HI>virgin Sulphur.</HI> Now let me ad∣vice you not to trouble your selves with this <HI>Mercurie,</HI> unlesse you have a <HI>true friend</HI> to in∣struct you, or an Expresse Illumination from the <HI>first Author</HI> of it, for it is a Thing attain'd <HI>Arte mirabili.</HI> Observe then what I shall now tell you. There is in every star, and in this <HI>Ele∣mentall world</HI> a certain <HI>principle</HI> which is <HI>Uxor solis.</HI> These <HI>two</HI> in their <HI>Coition</HI> do <HI>emittere se∣men,</HI> which <HI>seed</HI> is carried in the <HI>womb</HI> of <HI>Na∣ture</HI>: But the <HI>ejection</HI> of it, is perform'd <HI>invisi∣bly,</HI> and in a <HI>Sacred silence</HI>: for this is the <HI>con∣jugall mystery</HI> of Heaven and Earth, their <HI>Act</HI> of <HI>Generation,</HI> a thing done in <HI>private</HI> between particular <HI>Males</HI> and <HI>Females,</HI> but how much more think you, between the <HI>Two universall Natures?</HI> Know therefore that it is impossible for you to <HI>extract,</HI> or <HI>receive</HI> any <HI>seed</HI> from the
<PB N="29" REF="23"/>
<HI>Sun,</HI> without this <HI>Faminine Principle,</HI> which is the <HI>Wife</HI> of the <HI>Sun.</HI> Now then my <HI>small Sophi∣sters</HI> of the <HI>stone,</HI> you that <HI>consume</HI> your <HI>time</HI> and <HI>substance</HI> in making <HI>waters</HI> and <HI>Oyles</HI> with a durty <HI>Caput Mortuum</HI>: You that deal in <HI>Gold</HI> and <HI>Quick-silver</HI> being infatuated with the <HI>Legends</HI> of some <HI>late</HI> and <HI>former Mounte∣banks:</HI> Consider the <HI>last end</HI> of such men. Did they obtain any thing by it but <HI>diseases</HI> &amp; <HI>Po∣verty?</HI> Did they not in their old age <HI>Inveterat<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dierum malorum,</HI> fall to <HI>Clipping</HI> and <HI>Counter∣feiting</HI> of <HI>Coyne</HI>? and for a <HI>Period</HI> to their <HI>Me∣mory</HI> did they not die in <HI>Despair,</HI> which is the <HI>Childe</HI> of <HI>Ignorance</HI>? Know then for certain That the <HI>Magicians Sun</HI> and <HI>Moon</HI> are <HI>two universall Peeres: Male</HI> and <HI>Female,</HI> a <HI>King</HI> and <HI>Queen Regents,</HI> alwayes <HI>young,</HI> and never <HI>old.</HI> These <HI>two</HI> are <HI>Adaequate</HI> to the <HI>whole world,</HI> and <HI>coextended</HI> thorough the <HI>universe.</HI> The <HI>one</HI> is not without the <HI>other,</HI> God having <HI>united</HI> them in his work of <HI>Creation</HI> in a <HI>solemn Sacramentall union.</HI> It will then be a hard and difficult Enterprise to <HI>rob</HI> the <HI>Husband</HI> of his <HI>wife,</HI> to <HI>put those asunder,</HI> whom <HI>God himself</HI> hath <HI>put together</HI>: for they <HI>sleep both</HI> in the <HI>same Bed,</HI> and he that <HI>discovers</HI> the <HI>one</HI> must needes <HI>see</HI> the <HI>other.</HI> The <HI>Love</HI> betwixt these two is so <HI>great,</HI> That if you use this <HI>Virgin kindly,</HI> shee will <HI>fetch back</HI> her <HI>Cupid,</HI> after he hath <HI>ascend∣ed</HI>
<PB N="30" REF="24"/>
from her in <HI>wings of Fire.</HI> Observe moreo∣ver that <HI>Materiall Principles</HI> can be multiply∣ed but <HI>materially,</HI> that is by <HI>addition of parts,</HI> as you see in the <HI>Augmentation</HI> of <HI>Bodies,</HI> which is perform'd by a <HI>Continuall Assumption of Nutriment</HI> into the <HI>stomack,</HI> but it is not the <HI>Body</HI> that <HI>transmutes</HI> the <HI>Nutriment</HI> into <HI>flesh</HI> and <HI>bloud,</HI> but that <HI>spirit</HI> which is the <HI>life</HI> and <HI>light</HI> of the <HI>Body.</HI> Materiall Principles are <HI>pas∣sive,</HI> and can neither <HI>alter</HI> nor <HI>purifie,</HI> but well may they <HI>be altered,</HI> and <HI>purified:</HI> neither can they <HI>communicate themselves</HI> to another sub∣stance beyond their own <HI>extension</HI> which is <HI>fi∣nite</HI> and <HI>determinate.</HI> Trust not <HI>those Impostors</HI> then who tell you of a <HI>Sulphur Tingens,</HI> and I know not what <HI>Fables</HI>; who <HI>pin</HI> also that <HI>new</HI> and <HI>narrow name</HI> of <HI>Chemia,</HI> on a <HI>science</HI> both <HI>Ancient</HI> and <HI>Infinite.</HI> It is the <HI>light onely</HI> that can be <HI>truely multiplied,</HI> for this <HI>ascends to,</HI> and <HI>descends from</HI> the first Fountain of <HI>Multiplica∣tion,</HI> and <HI>Generation.</HI> This <HI>Light</HI> applied to any Body whatsoever <HI>exalts</HI> &amp; <HI>perfects it in suo ge∣nere.</HI> If to <HI>Animals,</HI> it exalts <HI>Animals,</HI> if to <HI>Vegetables, Vegetables,</HI> if to <HI>Minerals,</HI> it re∣fines <HI>Minerals, and</HI> translates them from the <HI>worst</HI> to the <HI>best Condition.</HI> Where <HI>note</HI> by the way, that <HI>every Body</HI> hath <HI>passive principles</HI> in <HI>it self,</HI> for this <HI>light</HI> to <HI>work upon,</HI> and therefore needs not <HI>borrow</HI> any from <HI>Gold,</HI> or <HI>silver.</HI> Con∣sider
<PB N="31" REF="24"/>
then <HI>what it is</HI> you search for, you that hunt after the <HI>Philosophers stone,</HI> for <HI>Eiusdem est Transmutare, cujus est Creare</HI>: you seek for that which is most high, but you look on that which is <HI>most Low.</HI> Two things there are which every <HI>good Christian</HI> may, and ought to look after, <HI>Verum, &amp; Necessarium. Trueth</HI> is the <HI>Arcanum,</HI> the <HI>Mystery &amp; Essence</HI> of all Things: for every <HI>secret</HI> is <HI>trueth,</HI> and every <HI>substantiall trueth</HI> is a <HI>secret.</HI> I speak not here of <HI>outward Historicall trueths,</HI> which are but <HI>Re∣latives</HI> to <HI>Actions,</HI> but I speak of an <HI>inward Es∣sentiall Trueth</HI> which is <HI>Light,</HI> for <HI>Light</HI> is <HI>the Trueth,</HI> and it discovers <HI>Falshood</HI> which is <HI>Darknesse.</HI> By this <HI>trueth</HI> all that which is ne∣cessary may be <HI>compass'd,</HI> but <HI>never</HI> without it.
<Q>I preferred wisdom (said the wise King) be∣fore Sceptors and Thrones, and esteemed Ri∣ches nothing in comparison of her. Neither compared I unto her any precious stone, be∣cause all Gold in respect of her is as a little sand, and silver shall be counted as Clay be∣fore her. I loved her above health and beau∣ty, and chose to have her instead of <HI>light,</HI> for the <HI>light</HI> that commeth from her <HI>never goeth out.</HI> All <HI>good things</HI> came to me <HI>together with her,</HI> and <HI>Innumerable Riches in her Hands.</HI> And I rejoyced in them all, because <HI>wisedom goeth before them,</HI> and I knew not that <HI>she</HI> was
<PB N="32" REF="25"/>
the <HI>Mother</HI> of them. If <HI>Riches</HI> be a <HI>Posses∣sion</HI> to be <HI>desired</HI> in this <HI>Life,</HI> what is <HI>Richer</HI> then Wisedom that <HI>worketh all things?</HI> For she is privy to the <HI>mysteries</HI> of the <HI>knowledge</HI> of <HI>God,</HI> and a <HI>lover</HI> of his <HI>works.</HI> God hath granted me to speak as I would, and to <HI>con∣cerve</HI> as is meet for the things that are given me: because it is <HI>he</HI> that <HI>leadeth unto Wisdom,</HI> and <HI>directeth</HI> the <HI>wise,</HI> For in <HI>his hand</HI> are both <HI>we</HI> and our <HI>words,</HI> all <HI>wisdom</HI> also, and <HI>knowledge of workmanship.</HI> For he hath given me <HI>certain knowledge</HI> of the things <HI>that are,</HI> namely to <HI>know</HI> how the <HI>world was made,</HI> and the <HI>Operation</HI> of the <HI>Elements.</HI> The <HI>begin∣ning, ending,</HI> and <HI>middest</HI> of the <HI>Times,</HI> the <HI>alterations</HI> of the <HI>turning</HI> of the <HI>Sun,</HI> and the <HI>Change</HI> of <HI>seasons.</HI> The <HI>Circuit</HI> of <HI>yeeres,</HI> and the <HI>position</HI> of <HI>stars.</HI> The <HI>Natures</HI> of <HI>living Creatures,</HI> and the <HI>furies</HI> of <HI>wild Beasts,</HI> the <HI>violence</HI> of <HI>windes,</HI> and the <HI>reasoning</HI> of <HI>Men:</HI> the <HI>Diversities</HI> of <HI>Plants,</HI> and the <HI>vertues</HI> of <HI>rootes.</HI> And all such <HI>things</HI> as are either <HI>secret</HI> or <HI>manifest,</HI> them <HI>I know. For</HI> wisdom which is the <HI>worker</HI> of <HI>all things taught me.</HI> For in her is an <HI>understanding spirit,</HI> holy, onely be∣gotten, manifold, subtil, lively, clear, undefi∣led, plain, not subject to hurt, <HI>loving the thing</HI> that is <HI>good,</HI> quick, which cannot be letted, ready to do <HI>good, Kind to Man,</HI> stedfast, free
<PB N="33" REF="25"/>
from Care, <HI>having all power,</HI> overseeing <HI>all things,</HI> and <HI>going thorough</HI> all understand∣ing, pure, and most subtill <HI>Spirits.</HI> For <HI>wisdom</HI> is <HI>more moving</HI> then any <HI>motion,</HI> she <HI>passeth,</HI> and <HI>goeth thorow all Things</HI> by reason of <HI>her purenesse.</HI> For <HI>she</HI> is the <HI>Breath</HI> of the <HI>power of God,</HI> and a <HI>pure Influence</HI> flowing from the <HI>Glory</HI> of the <HI>Almighty,</HI> therefore can no <HI>defiled thing</HI> fall into her. For she is the <HI>brightnesse</HI> of the <HI>everlasting light,</HI> the <HI>unspot∣ted mirror</HI> of the <HI>power</HI> of <HI>God,</HI> and the <HI>image</HI> of his <HI>goodnesse.</HI> And being but <HI>One</HI> she <HI>can do all things,</HI> and <HI>remayning in her self</HI> she maketh <HI>all things new:</HI> and in <HI>all</HI> Ages entring into <HI>Holy Souls,</HI> she maketh them <HI>friends</HI> of <HI>God, and Prophets.</HI> For <HI>God</HI> loveth <HI>none</HI> but <HI>Him</HI> that <HI>dwelleth with wisdom.</HI> For she is more beautifull then the <HI>Sun,</HI> and above all the <HI>Order of stars,</HI> being compared with the <HI>Light,</HI> she is found <HI>before it.</HI> For after this commeth <HI>Night,</HI> but <HI>Vice</HI> shall not <HI>prevail</HI> against <HI>Wisdom.</HI></Q>
Thus <HI>Solomon,</HI> and again a <HI>greater</HI> then <HI>Solomon; First seek you the King∣dom of God, and all these Things shall be given you.</HI> For of a trueth <HI>Temporall blessings</HI> are but <HI>ushers</HI> to the <HI>Spirituall,</HI> or to speak more plain∣ly, when once we <HI>begin</HI> to <HI>love</HI> the <HI>Spirit,</HI> then he <HI>sends us</HI> these things as <HI>Tokens</HI> and <HI>pledges</HI> of his <HI>Love.</HI>
<Q>For <HI>Promotion comes neither from the
<PB N="34" REF="26"/>
East nor from the West, but from God that gi∣veth it.</HI> Verum (saith One) est esse, a quo ni∣hil abesse cuiq<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> nil adesse multo{que} minus obesse potest. Necessariū id omne, quo carere nō possu∣mus. Veritas ita{que} sūma virtus est, ac inexpugna∣bile Castrum paucissimis inhaerentibus Amicis, at innumeris obsessum inimicis, paulo minus quam toti mundo nunc invisum, sed insupera∣bile Pignus iis qui possident illud. Hac in Arce verus &amp; indubitatus Philosophorum Lapis, &amp; Thesaurus continetur, qui non erosus a tineis, nec perfossus a furibus, manet in aeternum cae∣teris dissolutis omnibus, multis in Ruinam po∣situs, aliis ad salutem. Haec est res vulgo vilis∣sima, spreta plurimum, &amp; exosa, non tamen o∣dibilis, at amabilis, &amp; preciosa supra Philoso∣phis, supra Gemmas, &amp; aurum obrizon: Om∣nium amatrix, omnibus ferme inimica, ubique reperibilis, &amp; a paucissimis, quasi nullis, inven∣ta per vicos acclamans omnibus, Venite ad me omnes qui quaeritis, &amp; Ego vos ducam in veram semitam. Haec est res illa tautum a veris prae∣dicata Philosophis, quae vincit omnia, nec ab ulla re vincitur, Corpus, &amp; Cor omne durum &amp; solidum penetrans, ac omne molle consolidans, &amp; ab omni duro resistendum confirmans. No∣bis omnibus se facit obviam, &amp; non videmus eam, vociferans, &amp; alta voce dicens, Ego sum via veritatis, transite per me: quia non est alius
<PB N="35" REF="26"/>
ad vitant transitus, &amp; nolumus eam audire.</Q>
O∣dorem sua vitatis emittit, sed non percipimus eum.
<Q>Dapibus sese nobis liberaliter in sua vita∣tem offert indies &amp; non degustamus eam<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Blande nos ad salutem trahit, &amp; ejus tractui resistentes, sentire nolumus. Quoniam facti sumus sicut lapides, oculos habentes &amp; non vi∣dentes, aures habentes &amp; non audientes, nares non olfacientes habentes, ore linguaque muni∣ti non degustantes, neque loquentes manibus &amp; pedibus nil operantes, nec ambulantes. O miserum tale genus Hominum, quod lapidibus non est praestantius, imò longe inferius eo, quod hoc, non Illi rationem daturi sunt operationum suarum! Transmutemini (inquit) transmute∣mini de lapidibus mortuis in Lapides vivos philosophicos. Ego sum vera Medicina, corri∣gens &amp; transmutans id quod non est amplius, in id quod fuit ante Corruptionem, ac in Melius, ac id quod non est, in id quod esse de∣bet. Ecce prae foribus conscientiae vestrae sum Noctes ac Dies pulsans, &amp; non aperitis mihi, t<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>men expecto mitis, nec a vobis irata recedo, sed patiens injurias sustineo vestras, cupiens per patientiam ad eam exhortando vos ducere. Venite iterum, atque saepius iterum venite, Qui sapientiam quaeritis &amp; emite gratis, non auro nec Argento, minus laboribas propriis, quod vobis offertur ultro. Sonora vox, suavis &amp; gra∣ta
<PB N="36" REF="27"/>
Philosophantium auribus. O Fons divitia∣rum Inexhaustibilis veritatem &amp; Justitiam si∣tientibus! O Desolatorum Imperfectioni sola∣tium! Quid ultra quaeritis Mortales anxii? Cur infinitis animos vestros curis exagiratis Miseri? Quae vestra vos excaecat Dementia, quaeso? Cum in vobis, non ex Vobis sit omne quod extra vos, non apud vos quaeritis. Pro∣prium hoc solet esse vulgi vitium, ut Propria contemnens, aliena quae sunt, semper appetat. Proprium hic pro nobis appropriati sumimus, nam ex nobis ipsis nihil habemus Boni, sed si quid habere Boni possumus, ab eo qui solus est Bonus, ferimus acceptum: è Contra quod ha∣bemus Mali, nobis ipsi nos appropria vimus, ex alieno malo per inobedientiam. Proprium er∣go nihil Homini est ex suo praeterquam Malū quod possidet: Quod ex Bono Bonum habet, non ex seipso, sed contribute proprium habet, ex Bono cum recipit tamen. Lucet in nobis (licet obscure) Vita Lux hominum tanquam in Tenebris, quae non ex nobis est, sed ab eo cujus est. Hic Illam planta vit in Nobis, ut in ejus Lumine, qui lucem inhabitat inaccessibi∣lem, videremus Lumen, &amp; hoc Caeteras ejus praecelleremus Creaturas: Illi similes hac ra∣tione facti, quod semtillam sui luminis dederit nobis. Est igitur veritas non in nobis quaeren∣da, sed in imagine Dei, quae in Nobis est.</Q>
<PB N="37" REF="27"/>
<HI>This is He to whom the Brothers of</HI> R. C. <HI>gave the Title of Sapiens, and from whose writings they borrowed most of their Instructi∣ons</HI> ad Candidatum quendam Germaniae. <HI>But that you may the better understand how to come by this stone, hear what he speaks in ano∣ther place.</HI>
<Q>Non prius incipit vera Cognitio, quam perennium &amp; Labilium, cum vitae, tum Intetitus oblatâ comparatione, selegat anima cum animo jungi, deleetatione majori tracto hujus, quam Corporis. Ex eâ <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ognitione Mons oritur, &amp; Corporis voluntaria separatio sumit exordium, cum anima respiciens ex unâ Cor∣poris faeditatem &amp; interitum, ex alterâ parte praesta<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itiam &amp; foelicitatem animi perpetuam, cum isto (divino sic disponente statu) connecti cupit, altero penitus neglecto, ut hoc solum appetat, quod a Deo conclusum esse videt in salutem &amp; Gloriam: Corpus in amborum jam unitotum unionem condescendere cogitur. Haec est admirabilis illa Philosophorum transmu∣tatio Corporis in Spiritum &amp; hujus in corpus, de quâ Dictum nobis relinquitur a Sapienti∣bus: Fac Fixū Volatile &amp; volatile fac Fixū, ut habeas magisterium nostrum: (intellige) fac de pertinaci copore Tractabile, quod animi prae∣stantià cum anima conveniente constantissi∣mum fiat corpus ad omnia sustinendum exa∣mina. Probatur enim aurum igne, quo repro∣batur
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/><PB N="36" REF="28"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/><PB N="37" REF="28"/>
<PB N="38" REF="29" MS="y"/>
omne quod aurum non est. O prae∣stantissimum Philosophorum aurum, quo ditantur sapientiae filii, non Illo quod cu∣ditur: Adeste qui Thesaurum Philosopho∣rum tam vario Conatu quaeritis, reproba∣tum a vobis Lapidem cognoscite, prius quis ille sit antequam quaeratur. Mirum est super omne miraculum, quod quispiam appetat i∣gnotum sibi: fatuum certè videtur id ab ho∣minibus quaeri, cujus Veritatem non norunt investigantes, quia nihil in eo spei relinquitur. Suadeo quibusvis ergo perquirentibus, ut co∣gnoscant prius ejus quod quaerunt, veram exi∣stentiam, antequam quaerant: sic eos laboribus frustrari non continget. Sapiens quaerit quod amat, nec amare potest quod non cognoscit, a∣lioquin Insipiens esset; Ex cognitione igitur natus est amor omnium Veritas, quae sola vi∣get in omnibus veris Philosophis. <HI>Thus He, and again</HI>: Frustra laboratis omnes abdito∣rum Naturae secretorum Indagatores, cum a∣liam ingressi viam, Terrenorum virtutes per Terrena detegere conamini. Discite igitur Coelum per Coelum, non per Terram, sed hu∣jus per illius virtutes cognoscere. Nemo enim ascendit in Coelum quod quaeritis, nisi qui de Coelo (quod non quaeritis descendit, prius il∣luminet eum. Incorruptibilem quaeritis medi∣cinam, quae Corpora nedum a Corruptione
<PB N="39" REF="29"/>
transmutet in verum Temperamentum, sed etiam temperata diutissime conservet: talem alibi quam in Caelo reperire non poteritis un∣quam. Coelum virtute suâ per invisibiles ra∣dios in Terrae Centrum undique concurrentes, omnia penetrat Elementa, &amp; Elementata ge∣nerat, fovetque Nemo in seipso, sed in sui simi∣li, quod etiam ex ipso sit, generare potest. Foe∣tus etiam promiscuus utriusque parentis in se Naturam ita retinet, ut in eo parens uterque potentia &amp; actu sit reperibilis. Quis haerebit amplius nisi lapis in Generatione Philosophi∣câ? Disce ex Teipso, quicquid est in Coelo, &amp; in Terrà cognoscere, ut sapiens fias in omni∣bus Ignoras Coelum &amp; Elementa prius Unum suisse, Divino quoque ab invicem artificio sepa∣rata, ut &amp; Te, &amp; omnia generare possent? si hoc nosti, reliquum &amp; Te fugere non potest, aut Ingenio cares omni. Rursus in omni gene∣ratione talis separatio est necessaria, qualem de te supra dixi fiendam, antequam ad verae Phi∣losophiae studia velum applices. Ex aliis nun∣quam unum facies, quod quaeris, nisi prius ex Teipso fiat unum quod audisti. Nam talis est voluntas Dei, ut pii pium consequantur Opus quod quaerunt, &amp; perfecti perficiant aliud cui fuerint intenti. Malae voluntatis Hominibus nihil praeter quod seminaverint, datur metere: imo quod magis est, persaepe bonum eorum
<PB N="40" REF="30"/>
semen in Lolium, propter eorum Malitiam convertitur. Fac igitur ut Talis evadas, quale tuum esse vis. quod quaesieris opus.</Q>
This is now the true <HI>Essential mystery</HI> of <HI>Regenera∣tion,</HI> or the <HI>Spiritual Death.</HI> This is, and ever was the onely <HI>scope,</HI> and <HI>upshot</HI> of <HI>Magick.</HI> But for your further Instruction ruminate this his other mysticall speech.</P>
<P><Q>Agitedum igitur anima mea, corpusque meum: surgite nunc, animum sequamini ve∣strum. Ascondamus in montem hunc excelsum nobis oppositum, de cujus cacumine vohis o∣stendam iter hoc bivium de quo per Nubem, &amp; sine iumine locutus est Pythagoras. Nobis aperti sunt oculi, tum praelucet sol pietatis &amp; Justitiae, quo duce non possumus à via veritatis deflectere. Volvite primum oculos ad detram, ne videant vanitatem, antequam sapientiam perceperint. Videtisnè relucens illud, &amp; Inex∣pugnabile Castrum? In eo se continet Philo∣sophicus amor, de cujus Fonte fluunt Aquae vi∣vae quas qui degustarit semel, non sitiet vani∣tatem amplius. Ab eo loco tam amaeno, sua∣vique recta progrediendum est ad amaeniorem, in quo Sophia moram trahit: de cujus etiam fonte scaturiunt Aquae primis longe faeliciores, quas qui gustarint inimici, pacem eos mire ne∣cesse est: Eorum qui deveniunt eo plerique solent altius tendere, sed non omnes ontatum
<PB N="41" REF="30"/>
assequuntur. Est locus ultra dictos, quem adire vix licet mortalibus, nisi per Divinum numen ad immortalitatis gradum assumpti sunt: at antequam introducantur, mundum coguntur exuere; caducae vitae spolio retento. Non est eo cum pervenerint, quod amplius mortem time∣ant, imo potius eam indies amplectantur sua∣vius, quam in mundo quid unquam suave ju∣dicatum est eis amplexu dignum. Ultra haec tria loca quicunque progrediuntur, ab homi∣num oculis evanescunt. Quod si secundum &amp; tertium Locos videre lubet, ascendamus altius. En supra Chrystallinam primam arcem, aliam Argenteam videtis, ultra quam &amp; Tertiam a∣damantinam, Quar<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> vero non cadit sub sen∣sum, donec ultra Tertiam deventum sit. Hic est aureus perpetuae foelicitatis locus, sollie itu∣dinis expers, &amp; omni repletus gaudio perenni.</Q>
This is the <HI>pitch</HI> and <HI>place,</HI> to which if any man <HI>ascends,</HI> he enters into <HI>Chariots</HI> of <HI>Fire</HI> with <HI>Horses</HI> of <HI>fire,</HI> and is <HI>translated</HI> from the <HI>earth, soul</HI> and <HI>Body.</HI> Such was <HI>Enoch,</HI> such was <HI>Eli∣jah,</HI> such was <HI>Esdras,</HI> to whom this <HI>Medicine</HI> was ministred by <HI>Vriel</HI> the <HI>Angel.</HI> Such was Saint <HI>Paul,</HI> who was <HI>carried up</HI> to the <HI>third Heaven</HI>; such was <HI>Zoroaster,</HI> who was <HI>trans∣figured,</HI> and such was that <HI>Anonymus</HI> mention'd by <HI>Agrippa: I dipsum</HI> (sayth he) <HI>&amp; de se pro∣didit sapiens quidam, ita ut scintillantes Fla∣minae
<PB N="42" REF="31"/>
hinc inde, etiam cum sono prosilirent.</HI> This I suppose; was <HI>R. C.</HI> the <HI>founder</HI> of almost <HI>Christian,</HI> and <HI>famous society,</HI> whose <HI>Body</HI> also by <HI>vertue</HI> of that <HI>Medicine</HI> he took in his <HI>life time,</HI> is preserv'd <HI>intire</HI> to this <HI>Day,</HI> with the <HI>Epitomes</HI> of <HI>two worlds</HI> about it. Such <HI>Elijahs</HI> also are the <HI>Members</HI> of this <HI>Fraternitie,</HI> who as their own <HI>writings</HI> testifie; walk in the super∣natural light. <HI>Vt nobiscum autem Covenias</HI> (say they) <HI>necesse est hanc Lucem cernas, sine enim huc Luce impossible est nos videre, nisi quando volumus.</HI> I know some illiterate <HI>School-Di∣vines</HI> will no sooner read this, but they will cry out with the <HI>Iewes: away with such a follow from the earth.</HI> Truly they are the men,
<Q>Quibus &amp; ego nunc consulo, ne nostra scripta legant, nec intelligant, nec me<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>inerint: nam noxia sunt, venenosa sunt; acherontis ostium est in in hoc libello, Lapides loquitur, caveant ne cerebrum illis excutiat.</Q>
Let them not mind it, buy it not, touch it not.</P>
<Q><L>—,Procul hinc, procul ite Prophani.</L></Q>
<P>Go on still, and proceed in your own corrupt Fancies, <HI>ut servetur Iustitiae locus.</HI> Follow your <HI>old beggarly Elements,</HI> the <HI>Rudiments</HI> of this <HI>World,</HI> which hitherto have <HI>done despight to the spirit of grace</HI>: which have <HI>grieved that holy and loving spirit of God, whereby you are seal'd to the Day of Redemption.</HI> But consider
<PB N="43" REF="31"/>
whiles you are yet in the <HI>flesh,</HI> whiles it is <HI>to Day</HI> with you, and <HI>timely</HI> to consider, that <HI>God</HI> will <HI>use</HI> those <HI>men</HI> whom you <HI>revile</HI> for his <HI>Trueth,</HI> as <HI>witnesses</HI> against <HI>you</HI> in a <HI>Day</HI> when you shall have <HI>nothing</HI> to speak for your <HI>Ignorance,</HI> unless you <HI>plead</HI> your <HI>obstinacie.</HI> Of a trueth <HI>God himself</HI> discovered this <HI>Thing</HI> to the <HI>First man,</HI> to confirm his <HI>Hopes</HI> of those <HI>three supernatu∣rall mysteries,</HI> the <HI>Incarnation, Regeneration,</HI> and <HI>Resurrection</HI>: For <HI>I amblichus</HI> citing the <HI>AEgyptian Records</HI> with a <HI>Credendum est Arcanis sermonibus,</HI> hath these very words, <HI>Traditam fuisse Materiam quandam a Deis per beata Spectacula, haec ergo illis ipsis traden∣tibus cograta est.</HI> And our <HI>former Christian Author</HI> in a certain place speakes thus. <HI>Du∣bium non est quin Deus Antiquis Patribus medicinam aliquam revelaverit, per spiritum sanctum suum qua tuerentur Carnis Corruptio∣nem &amp; potissimum iis, cum quibus locutus est, &amp; faedus inivit.</HI> Let me tell you then that the <HI>Period</HI> and <HI>perfection</HI> of <HI>Magick</HI> is no way <HI>Physicall,</HI> for this <HI>Art</HI>
<Q><L>Attingit solium Iovis, &amp; Coelestia tentat.</L></Q></P>
<P>In a word it ascends <HI>per lumen Naturae in lumen Gratiae,</HI> and the <HI>last end</HI> of it is <HI>truely Theologicall.</HI> Remember therefore that
<PB N="44" REF="32"/>
Elijah <HI>depos'd his mantle,</HI> and past thorow the <HI>waters</HI> of <HI>Iordan</HI> before he met with the <HI>Cha∣riots of Israel.</HI> But as <HI>Agrippa</HI> sayth, <HI>Clausum est veritatis Armarium:</HI> The Scripture is <HI>obscure,</HI> and <HI>mysticall</HI> even in <HI>Historicall passa∣ges.</HI> Who would believe that in the <HI>History</HI> of <HI>Agar</HI> and <HI>Sarah,</HI> the <HI>mystery</HI> of <HI>both Testa∣ments</HI> was <HI>couch'd,</HI> but that Saint <HI>Paul</HI> himself hath <HI>told us</HI> so?<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Gal.</HI> 4.22.</NOTE> <HI>For it is</HI> written (sayth he)
<Q>that Abraham had two Sons, the one by a Bond∣maid, the other by a Free-woman. But he who was of the Bond-woman, was born af∣ter the flesh, but he of the Free-woman by pro∣mise. Which Things are an Allegorie; for these are the Two Covenants, the one from Mount Sinai, which gendereth to bondage, which is Agar: For this Agar is Mount Sinai in Arabia, and answereth to Jerusalem that now is, and is in Bondage with her Children;</Q>
But Jerusalem from above is free, which is the `Mother <HI>of us All.</HI> I could instance in many more such places, as that of the <HI>Royal Prophet, That the Dew of Hermon descends to Mount Sion,</HI> which is altogether <HI>impossible</HI> in the <HI>lite∣rall Sense,</HI> for every <HI>Geographer</HI> knows there is a <HI>vast distance</HI> between These <HI>two.</HI> But to re∣turn to my former discourse: some <HI>Philosophers</HI> who by the speciall mercy of God attain'd to
<PB N="45" REF="32"/>
the <HI>Ternarius,</HI> could never notwithstanding obtaine the <HI>perfect Medicine,</HI> neither did they <HI>understand</HI> it. I never met in all my Reading but with <HI>Six Authors,</HI> who fully apprehend∣ed this <HI>Mystery.</HI> The first an <HI>Arabian,</HI> a most profound, but exceedingly obscure writer, and from him I conceive, <HI>Artesius</HI> borrowed all his Knowledge. The second a most ancient <HI>Christian Anonymus,</HI> the <HI>greatest</HI> that ever was in point of <HI>Practice,</HI> for he ascended to that glorious <HI>Metaphysicall Height</HI> where the <HI>Archtype</HI> shadows the <HI>Intellectual Spheares.</HI> The other <HI>Four</HI> are <HI>famously</HI> known in <HI>Chri∣stendom.</HI> To instruct Thee then, This <HI>My∣stery</HI> is perfected when the <HI>Light</HI> in a sud∣dain, miraculous <HI>Coruscation</HI> strikes from the <HI>Center</HI> to the <HI>Circumference,</HI> and the <HI>Divine Spirit</HI> hath so swallowed up the <HI>Body,</HI> that it is <HI>Corpus glorificatum tanquam sol &amp; Luna splendidum.</HI> In this <HI>Rotation</HI> it doth <HI>passe</HI> (and no sooner) from the <HI>Na∣tural</HI> to a <HI>supernaturall state,</HI> for it is no more fed with <HI>Visibles,</HI> but with <HI>invisibles,</HI> and the Eye of the <HI>Creator</HI> is perpetually <HI>upon it.</HI> After this the <HI>Material parts</HI> are never more to be seen,
<Q>At{que} haec est illa toties decan∣tata, &amp; sine scelere Magorum Invisibilitas.</Q>
Verily this is the way that the <HI>Prophets</HI> and the <HI>Apostles</HI> went, this is the true <HI>primitive
<PB N="46" REF="33"/>
Divinity,</HI> not that <HI>clamorous sophistrie</HI> of the <HI>Schooles.</HI> I know the world will be ready to <HI>Boy</HI> me out of <HI>Countenance</HI> for this, because my <HI>yeares</HI> are <HI>few,</HI> and <HI>green.</HI> I want their <HI>two Crutches,</HI> the praetended modern <HI>sanctitie,</HI> and that <HI>Solemnity</HI> of the <HI>Beard,</HI> which makes up a <HI>Doctor.</HI> But Reader let me advise thee, if by what is here written thou attain'st to any knowledge in this point (which I hold impos∣sible without a Divine Assistance) let me ad∣vice thee I say, <HI>not to attempt</HI> any thing <HI>rashly</HI>: For <HI>Agrippa</HI> tells me,
<Q>Quicun∣que impurificatus accesserit, superinducit sibi Judicium, &amp; traditur ad devorandum spiritus nequam.</Q>
There is in the <HI>Magicall Records</HI> a memorable story of a <HI>Iew,</HI> who ha∣ving by permission rifl'd some <HI>Spiritual Trea∣sures,</HI> was translated <HI>in Solitudines,</HI> and is kept there for an <HI>Example</HI> to others. I will give thee the <HI>best Counsel</HI> that can be given, and that out of a Poet:
<Q><L>Orandum est, ut sit Mens sana in Corpore sano.</L></Q></P>
<P>Thou must prepare <HI>thy self,</HI> till thou art <HI>conformable to Him,</HI> whom thou wouldest <HI>entertain,</HI> and that <HI>omnimoda Similitudine.</HI> Thou hast <HI>Three</HI> that are to receive, and there are three accordingly that <HI>give.</HI> Fitt thy <HI>Roofe</HI> to thy <HI>God</HI> in what <HI>Thou canst,</HI> and
<PB N="47" REF="33"/>
in what <HI>thou canst not,</HI> he will <HI>help Thee.</HI> When thou hast thus <HI>set</HI> thy <HI>House</HI> in <HI>Order,</HI> do not think thy <HI>Guest</HI> will come without <HI>Invitation:</HI> Thou must <HI>tyre</HI> him out with <HI>pious importunities,</HI>
<Q><L>Perpetuall Knockings at his Doore,</L>
<L>Teares sullying his transparent Roomes.</L>
<L>Sighes upon sighes: weep mors and more,</L>
<L>He Comes.</L></Q></P>
<P><HI>This is the way thou must walk in, which if thou doest, thou shalt perceive a sudden Il∣lustration,</HI> eritque in Te cum
<Q>Lumine Ignis, cum Igne Ventus, cum Vento Potestas, cum Potestate scientia, cum scientià sanae Mentis Integritas. This is the <HI>Chain</HI> that <HI>qualifies</HI> a <HI>Magician</HI>: For sayth <HI>Agrippa,</HI> Explorare de Futuris, &amp; Imminentibus, allisve Occultis, &amp; quae hominibus divinitus portenduntur, veri∣dicas sententias, atque operari opera Virtutum communem Naturae Consuetudinem exceden∣tia, non nisi profundae &amp; perfectae Doctrinae, Integerrimaeque vitae, ac fidei est, non homi∣num <HI>levissimorum, ac indoctorum; and in an∣other place.</HI> Non poterit illa Dare, qui non habet. Habet autem Nemo, nisi qui jam co∣hibitis Elementis, victâ Natura, Superatis Coe∣lis, progre<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sus Angelos, ad ipsum Archetypum
<PB N="48" REF="34"/>
usque transcendit, cujus tunc Cooperator Ef∣fectus potest Omnia. This is the <HI>place,</HI> where if thou canst but once <HI>ascend,</HI> and then <HI>de∣scend,</HI></Q>
<Q><L>Tunc ire ad Mundum Archetypum saepe, at{que} redire,</L>
<L>Cunctarum{que} Patrem rerum spectare licebit.</L></Q></P>
<P><Q>Then I say, Thou hast got that <HI>Spirit, Qui quicquid portentosi Mathematici,</HI> quicquid pro∣digiosi Magi, quicquid invidentes Naturae per∣recutores Alchymistae, quicquid Daemonibus deteriores Malefici Necromantes promittere audent, Ipse novit discernere, &amp; efficere, idque sine omni Crimine, sine Dei offensâ, sine Reli∣gionis injuriâ.</Q>
Such is the <HI>power he</HI> shall <HI>re∣ceive,</HI> who from the <HI>Clamorous Tumults</HI> of this <HI>World</HI> ascends to the <HI>Supernaturall, still Voice</HI>; from this base <HI>Earth</HI> and <HI>Mud</HI> whereto his <HI>Body</HI> is <HI>allyed,</HI> to the <HI>Spiritual invisible Ele∣ments</HI> of his <HI>Soul Ille Deum vitam accipiet, do∣visque videbit Permotot Horoas, &amp; Ipse vide∣bitur Illes.</HI> This, Reader, is the <HI>Christian Phi∣losophers stone:</HI> a <HI>stone</HI> so often inculcated in <HI>Scripture.</HI> This is the <HI>Rock</HI> in the <HI>wildernesse</HI>; in the <HI>wildernesse,</HI> because in great <HI>obscurity,</HI> and <HI>few there are</HI> that know the <HI>right was</HI> unto it. This is the <HI>stone</HI> of <HI>fire</HI> in <HI>Ezekiel</HI>; this is the <HI>stone</HI> with <HI>seven eyes,</HI> upon it in <HI>Zacharie,</HI>
<PB N="49" REF="34"/>
and this is the <HI>white stone</HI> with the <HI>new Name</HI> in the <HI>Revelation.</HI> But in the <HI>Gospel</HI> where <HI>Christ</HI> himself <HI>speakes,</HI> who was born to <HI>disco∣ver Mysteries,</HI> and communicate <HI>Heaven</HI> to <HI>Earth,</HI> it is more clearely describ'd. This is the <HI>Salt</HI> which you ought to have <HI>in your selves,</HI> this is the Water and <HI>spirit</HI> whereof you must be <HI>born again,</HI> and this is that <HI>seed</HI> which falls to the <HI>ground,</HI> &amp; <HI>multiplies</HI> to an <HI>hundred fold.</HI> But reader, be not deceiv'd in me. I am not a Man of any such <HI>faculties,</HI> neither do I expect this <HI>Blessing</HI> in such a great <HI>measure</HI> in this <HI>Life</HI>: God is no <HI>debtor of mine.</HI> I can affirm no more of my self, but what my <HI>Author</HI> did formerly: <HI>Accipe me volo velut Indicem, qui semper prae foribus, manens, Aliis quod Iter ingrediendum sit, ostendat.</HI> Behold<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I will deal fairely with Thee; shew me but one <HI>good Christian,</HI> who is <HI>capable of,</HI> and <HI>fit</HI> to receive such <HI>a secret,</HI> and I will shew <HI>him</HI> the <HI>right, Infallible way</HI> to come by it. Yet this I must tell Thee, It would sink thee to the Ground to hear this <HI>mystery related:</HI> for it cannot ascend to the heart of the <HI>Naturall Man,</HI> how <HI>neer God is to him,</HI> and <HI>how to be found.</HI> But of this Enough. I will now speak of a <HI>Naturall Coelestial Medicine,</HI> and this <HI>latter</HI> is Common a∣mongst some <HI>wise Men,</HI> but <HI>Few are they,</HI> who
<PB N="50" REF="35"/>
attain to the <HI>Former.</HI> The <HI>common Chymist</HI> works with the <HI>common fire,</HI> and without any <HI>Medium,</HI> wherefore he <HI>generates nothing</HI>; for he works not as <HI>God doth,</HI> to preservation, but to Destruction: hence it is, that he ends alwayes in the <HI>Ashes.</HI> Do thou use it <HI>cum Phlegmate Medii</HI>: so shall thy materials rest in a <HI>Third Element,</HI> where the violence of this Tyrant cannot reach, but his <HI>Anima.</HI> There is also a better way: for if thou canst temper him with the <HI>Spirit of Heaven,</HI> thou hast alter'd him from a corrupting to a <HI>gene∣rating fire.</HI> Sublime the middle Nature fire <HI>per Trigonum &amp; Circulum,</HI> till thou com'st to a Breach of Inferiors and Superiors. Lastly, se∣parate from the <HI>Magicall compounded Earth</HI> that Principle which is call'd <HI>Terra Media,</HI> because it is middlemost between the <HI>Vnarius,</HI> and the <HI>Binarius</HI>: for as it attaines not to the simplicity of the First, so it is free from the <HI>Impurities of the Second.</HI> This is the true <HI>Pe∣tra Chrystallina,</HI> a <HI>bright virgin Earth</HI> without spot or Darknesse. This is <HI>Terra Maga in aethere clarificata,</HI> for it carries in its Belly <HI>Winde</HI> and <HI>Fire.</HI> Having got this <HI>fun∣damentall</HI> of a <HI>little new world,</HI> unite the <HI>hea∣ven</HI> in a <HI>triple proportion</HI> to the <HI>Earth,</HI> then apply a <HI>Generative heat</HI> to <HI>Both,</HI> and they will attract from above the <HI>Star-fire</HI> of <HI>Nature.
<PB N="51" REF="35"/>
Sic habebis Gloriam totius Mundi, Ergo fugiet a Te omnis Obscuritas.</HI> Now because the Law of Nature is infallible, and confirm'd to the Creature by Gods Royall Assent, think not therefore there is any Necessity upon God, but what he hath inacted in General, he can <HI>repeal</HI> in <HI>any particular.</HI> Remember who translated the <HI>Dew</HI> from the Earth to the Fleece, and from the Fleece to the Earth. God bestowes not his <HI>Blessings</HI> where they are to turn to Curses. He cursed the Earth once for <HI>Adam's</HI> sake: take heed he doth not curse it again in thy work for thy sake. It is in Vaine to look a <HI>Blessing</HI> from <HI>Nature,</HI> without the <HI>God</HI> of <HI>Nature</HI>: for, as the Scripture sayth, <HI>without Controversie the lesser is blessed of the Greater.</HI> He must be a <HI>good steward,</HI> that shall overlook the <HI>Treasuries</HI> of <HI>God.</HI> Have therefore a Charitable <HI>Seraphick soul</HI>: Charitable at Home, in being not Destru∣ctive to thy self<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> as most men are: Charitable abroad, in a Diffusive goodnesse to the poor, as many are not. There is in every <HI>true Christian</HI> a spice, I can not say a grain of Faith, for then we could work Miracles: But know thou that as God is the Father, so Charity is the Nurse of Faith. For there springs from Charitable works a Hope of Heaven, and who is he that will not gladly believe what he hopes to re∣ceive? On the contrary there springs no Hope
<PB N="52" REF="36"/>
at all from the <HI>Works of Darknesse,</HI> and by Consequence <HI>no faith,</HI> but that Faith of Di∣vels, <HI>To believe and tremble.</HI> Settle not then in the Lees, and Puddle of the World, have thy Heart in Heaven, and thy Hands on Earth: Ascend in Pietie, and descend in Charity, for this is the Nature of Light, and the Way of the Children of it. Above all Things, avoyd the <HI>Guilt of innocent Blood,</HI> for it utterly sepa∣rates from God in this Life, and requires a timely, and serious Repentance, if thou would'st find Him in the Next Now for thy studie, in the Winter Time thy Chamber is the best Resi∣dence; here thou mayest use <HI>Fumigations,</HI> and <HI>spicie Lamps,</HI> not for superstition, but because such recreate the <HI>Animal Spirits,</HI> and the <HI>Braine.</HI> In the <HI>Summer</HI> translate thy self to the Fields, where all are green with the Breath of God, and fresh with the Powers of Heaven. Learn to refer all Natu∣rals to their Spirituals, <HI>per viàm Secretioris Analogiae:</HI> for this is the way the <HI>Magicians</HI> went, and found out Miracles. Many there are who bestow not their Thoughts on <HI>God,</HI> till the World failes them; He may say to such Guests, <HI>Quum Nemini obtrudi potest, itur ad Me.</HI> Do thou think on Him first, and He will speak to thy Thoughts at Last. Sometimes Thou may'st walk in <HI>Groves,</HI> which being
<PB N="53" REF="36"/>
full of <HI>Majestie</HI> will much <HI>advance</HI> the <HI>Soul.</HI> Sometimes by <HI>clear, Active Rivers,</HI> for by such (say the <HI>Mystick Poets</HI>) <HI>Apollo</HI> contemplated.</P>
<Q>Omnia, quae <HI>Phaebo</HI> quondā meditante, beatus Audiit <HI>Eurotas: &amp;c.</HI></Q>
<P>So Have I spent on the Banks of <HI>Ysca</HI> many a serious Hour.</P>
<Q><L>'Tis <HI>Day,</HI> my Chrystal <HI>Usk</HI>: now the sad <HI>Night</HI></L>
<L>Resignes her place, as <HI>Tenant</HI> to the <HI>Light.</HI></L>
<L>See, the <HI>amazed mists</HI> begin to <HI>flye,</HI></L>
<L>And the Victorious <HI>Sun</HI> hath got the <HI>skie.</HI></L>
<L>How shall I recompence thy <HI>streams</HI> that keep</L>
<L>Me and my Soul <HI>awak'd,</HI> when others sleep?</L>
<L>I <HI>watch</HI> my <HI>stars,</HI> I <HI>move</HI> on with the <HI>skies,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>weary</HI> all the <HI>Planets</HI> with mine <HI>Eyes.</HI></L>
<L>Shall I seek thy forgotten <HI>Birth,</HI> and see</L>
<L>What <HI>Dayes</HI> are <HI>spent</HI> since thy <HI>Nativity?</HI></L>
<L>Didst run with <HI>ancient Kishon?</HI> canst thou tell</L>
<L>So many yeers as <HI>holy Hiddekel?</HI></L>
<L>Thou art not <HI>paid</HI> in <HI>this.</HI> I'le <HI>leavie</HI> more</L>
<L>Such harmles <HI>Contributions</HI> from thy <HI>store,</HI></L>
<L>And dresse my <HI>Soul</HI> by <HI>Thee</HI> as thou do'st <HI>passe,</HI></L>
<L>As I would do my <HI>Body</HI> by my <HI>Glasse.</HI></L>
<L>What a <HI>clear, running Chrystall</HI> here I find?</L>
<L>Sure I will strive to <HI>gain</HI> as <HI>clear a Mind.</HI></L>
<L><PB N="54" REF="37"/>And have my <HI>spirits</HI> freed frō <HI>dross,</HI> made <HI>light,</HI></L>
<L>That no <HI>base Puddle</HI> may <HI>allay</HI> their <HI>Flight.</HI></L>
<L>How I admire thy <HI>humble banks</HI>! Nought's here,</L>
<L>But the same <HI>simple vesture</HI> all the <HI>yeer.</HI></L>
<L>I'le learn <HI>simplicity</HI> of <HI>Thee,</HI> and when</L>
<L>I walk the <HI>streets,</HI> I will not <HI>storme</HI> at <HI>Men,</HI></L>
<L>Nor <HI>look</HI> as if I had a <HI>mind</HI> to crie,</L>
<L>It is my valiant Cloth of Gold, and I.</L>
<L>Let me not live, but I'm amaz'd to see</L>
<L>What a <HI>Clear Type</HI> thou art of <HI>Pietie.</HI></L>
<L>Why should thy <HI>Flouds inrich</HI> those <HI>shores,</HI> that sin</L>
<L>Against thy <HI>Liberty,</HI> and <HI>keep</HI> thee in?</L>
<L>Thy <HI>waters nurse</HI> that <HI>rude Land</HI> w<SUP>ch</SUP> <HI>inslaves</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Captivates</HI> thy <HI>free,</HI> and <HI>spacious waves.</HI></L>
<L>Most <HI>blessed Tutors</HI>! I will <HI>learn</HI> of <HI>Those</HI></L>
<L>To <HI>shew</HI> my <HI>charity</HI> unto my <HI>Foes,</HI></L>
<L>And strive to do <HI>some Good</HI> unto the <HI>Poor,</HI></L>
<L>As thy <HI>streams</HI> do unto the <HI>Barren shore.</HI></L>
<L><HI>'All This</HI> from <HI>Thee</HI> my <HI>Ysca?</HI> yes, and <HI>more:</HI></L>
<L>I am for many <HI>Vertues</HI> on thy <HI>score.</HI></L>
<L>Trust me thy <HI>waters</HI> yet: why, wilt not so?</L>
<L>Let me but <HI>drink again,</HI> and I will go.</L>
<L>I see thy <HI>course</HI> anticipates my <HI>Plea,</HI></L>
<L>I'le haste to <HI>God,</HI> as Thou dost to the <HI>Sea.</HI></L>
<L>And when my <HI>eyes</HI> in <HI>waters</HI> drown their <HI>beams,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Pious imitation</HI> of thy <HI>streames,</HI></L>
<L>May every <HI>Holy, happy, hearty Teare</HI></L>
<L>Help <HI>me</HI> to run to <HI>Heav'n,</HI> as <HI>Thou</HI> do'st <HI>there.</HI></L></Q>
<P><PB N="55" REF="37"/>This is the <HI>way</HI> I would have thee walk in, if thou doest intend to be a solid, <HI>Christian Philo∣sopher.</HI> Thou must as <HI>Agrippa</HI> sayth, <HI>Vivere Deum, &amp; Angelos</HI>: reject all Things <HI>Quae Coelo dissimilia sunt,</HI> otherwise thou canst have no Communion with Superiors. Lastly, <HI>Unus esto<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> non Solus</HI>: Avoid the Multitude, aswell of Passions, as Persons. Now for <HI>Authors,</HI> I wish thee to trust no <HI>moderns,</HI> but <HI>Michael Sendi∣vow,</HI> and that other of <HI>Physia Restituta,</HI> especi∣ally his <HI>first Aphonisticall part.</HI> The Rest whom I have seen suggest Inventions of their own, such as may passe with the <HI>Whymzies</HI> of <HI>des Chartes</HI> or <HI>Bovillus</HI> his <HI>Mathematicall Roses.</HI> To con∣clude, I would have thee know, That every <HI>day</HI> is <HI>Annus Contractus</HI>: That every <HI>yeer</HI> is <HI>Dies extensus.</HI> Anticipate the <HI>yeer</HI> in the <HI>day,</HI> and lose not a <HI>day</HI> in the <HI>yeer.</HI> Make use of <HI>Inde∣terminate Agents</HI> till thou canst fi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="under-inked" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de a Deter∣minate One: The Many may wish well, but One onely Loves. Circumferences spread, but Cen∣ters <HI>contract</HI>: so <HI>superiors dissolve,</HI> and <HI>Inferiors coagulate</HI>; stand not <HI>long</HI> in the <HI>sun,</HI> nor <HI>long</HI> in the <HI>shade</HI>: where <HI>Extremes meet,</HI> there look for <HI>Complexions.</HI> Learn from thy <HI>Errors</HI> to be <HI>In∣fallible,</HI> from thy Misfortunes to be constant: There is nothing stronger then Perseverance, for it <HI>ends</HI> in Miracles. I could tell thee <HI>more,</HI> but that were to <HI>puzzle Thee</HI>: learn this
<PB N="56" REF="38"/>
<HI>First,</HI> and Thou mayst teach me the <HI>Last.</HI></P>
<P>Thus Reader, have I published that <HI>knowledge</HI> which <HI>God</HI> gave me, <HI>ad fructum Bonae Conscien∣tiae.</HI> I have not <HI>Busheld</HI> my <HI>Light,</HI> nor <HI>buried</HI> my Talent in the Ground. I will now with∣draw and leave the <HI>stage</HI> to the <HI>Next Actor</HI>: Some <HI>Peripatetick</HI> perhaps, whose <HI>sic probo</HI> shall serve me for a <HI>Comaedie.</HI> I have seen <HI>scolds laugh'd at,</HI> but <HI>never admir'd:</HI> so he that <HI>mul∣tiplies Discourse,</HI> makes a <HI>serious</HI> cause, <HI>Ridi∣culous.</HI> The onely <HI>Antidote to</HI> a <HI>shrew,</HI> is <HI>silence</HI>: And the <HI>best way</HI> to <HI>convince Fools,</HI> is to <HI>Neg∣lect Them.</HI>
<Q><L>Faelices Animae! Quibus Haec cognoscere primū,</L>
<L>Inque Domos Superas Scandere, Cura fuit.</L>
<L>Credibile est Illos pariter Vitiisque Jocisque</L>
<L>Altius Humanis exeruisse Caput.</L></Q>
Si Tu <HI>Iehova,</HI> Deus meus, <HI>Illuminaveris Me, Lux</HI> fient <HI>Tenebrae meae.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="38"/>
<HEAD>To his ever honour'd friend, the Learned Author.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<L>YOur book now finish't. Let a shallower <HI>Pen</HI></L>
<L>Ad these few drops, to your vast Ocean.</L>
<L>Not by my shaddowing praise, <HI>t'eclipse</HI> the glory</L>
<L>Of your high <HI>worth</HI>: this book must tell that story,</L>
<L>To truth-beleiving Soules; whose <HI>Eagle-eyes</HI></L>
<L>Can penetrate these hidden <HI>Mysteries.</HI></L>
<L>But you (thrice honor'd sir) my groveling minde</L>
<L>Have rais'd to higher Pitch, to tell how kinde,</L>
<L>How rare a freind, how deare, how choise a <HI>Treasure</HI></L>
<L>My <HI>Fates</HI> have <HI>blest</HI> me with, above the measure</L>
<L>Of vulgar thought: how this <HI>diviner</HI> ray</L>
<L>Of your <HI>bright</HI> soul, would fill with clearest day</L>
<L>The darkened world: did not earth-shadowing <HI>mist.</HI></L>
<L>With thickest clouds, heavens <HI>influence</HI> resist</L>
<L>But who from envies sordid <HI>mire</HI></L>
<L>Is washt, is clad in pure attire</L>
<L>Of <HI>innocence</HI>; a light shall see,</L>
<L>(unthral'd from errors Sophistry)</L>
<L>Will kindle that <HI>magnetick fire,</HI></L>
<L>Which shall <HI>concenter,</HI> wild desire;</L>
<L>And <HI>fix</HI> the roving thoughts in one</L>
<L>Inseperate TRIVNION</L>
<L>Heel then disdaine the <HI>slymie Earth</HI>;</L>
<L>A house too mean for nobler birth,</L>
<L>His heaven-rais'd soul, will then <HI>aspire</HI></L>
<L>To bear a part in th'Angels quire.</L>
<L><HI>Dear so,</HI> fare well. Let seekers thirsty flames,</L>
<L>Refresht by these your soul-reviving streames,</L>
<L><HI>Eccho</HI> you Praise: with thankfull <HI>elogies</HI></L>
<L>Your ever-living name immortalize.</L>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED>Your own beyond Expresses <HI>H. B.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

