<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A brief discovery of the dangerous principles of John Horne (a priest in Lin) and Thomas Moore junior both teachers of the people called Mooreians or Manifestarians, (and called by some free-willers or independants.) In answer to their book called A brief discovery of the people called Quakers, and a warning to all people to beware of them and of their dangerous principles, &amp;c. Which book is a false narrative of two disputes, the one which they had with John Whitehead at Gedney in Lincoln-shire, and the other with Geo. Whitehead and Geo. Fox the younger, at Lin in Norfolke, both in the seventh moneth, 1659. Also priest Horns testimony against his brethren the priests. This is to go amonst the professors in England in discovery of the truth; ... By the truth which is in George Whitehead. John Whitehead. George Fox the younger.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A65842</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing W1896</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R220960</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99832343</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99832343</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">36816</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A65842)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36816)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2103:14)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A brief discovery of the dangerous principles of John Horne (a priest in Lin) and Thomas Moore junior both teachers of the people called Mooreians or Manifestarians, (and called by some free-willers or independants.) In answer to their book called A brief discovery of the people called Quakers, and a warning to all people to beware of them and of their dangerous principles, &amp;c. Which book is a false narrative of two disputes, the one which they had with John Whitehead at Gedney in Lincoln-shire, and the other with Geo. Whitehead and Geo. Fox the younger, at Lin in Norfolke, both in the seventh moneth, 1659. Also priest Horns testimony against his brethren the priests. This is to go amonst the professors in England in discovery of the truth; ... By the truth which is in George Whitehead. John Whitehead. George Fox the younger.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696. aut</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Fox, George, d. 1661. aut</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 35, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London]</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Thomas Simmons at the Bull and Mouth near Aldersgate,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1659.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>The words "George ... younger." on the title page are joined by a left brace.</NOTE><NOTE>Copy has considerable print show-through.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Horn, John, 1614-1676. --  Breife discovery of the people called Quakers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Moore, Thomas, d. 1672. --  Breife discovery of the people called Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A65842">
<STC T="W">W1896</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99832343</BIBNO>
<VID>36816</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A BRIEF DISCOVERY OF THE Dangerous Principles OF <HI>John Horne</HI> (a Priest in <HI>Lin)</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore junior,</HI> both Teachers of the people called <HI>Moore∣ians</HI> or <HI>Manifestarians,</HI> (and called by some <HI>Free∣willers</HI> or <HI>Independants.)</HI> In Answer to their Book Called <HI>A brief Discovery of the People cal∣led Quakers, and a Warning to all people to beware of them and of their dangerous principles, &amp;c.</HI> Which Book is a false Narrative of two Disputes, the one which they had with <HI>John Whitehead</HI> at <HI>Gedney</HI> in <HI>Lincoln-shire,</HI> and the other with <HI>Geo. White∣head</HI> and <HI>Geo. Fox</HI> the younger, at <HI>Lin</HI> in <HI>Norfolke,</HI> both in the seventh Moneth, 1659. Also Priest <HI>Horns</HI> Testimony against his brethren the Priests. This is to go amongst the Professors in <HI>England</HI> in Discovery of the Truth; For in this Answer the Truth is cleared, and <HI>John Horne</HI> and <HI>Tho. Moores</HI> Ignorance discovered concerning Per∣fection, and the Resurrection, and the Body and Blood of Christ, and his Light, and other things of concernment, and their abusing the Truth (which is set over them and their deceits) made manifest.</P>
<P>By the Truth▪ which is in<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>George Whitehead.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>John Whitehead.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>George Fox</HI> the younger.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<BIBL>Jer 10. 21.</BIBL>
<Q> For the Pastors are become bruitish and have not sought the Lord, therefore they shall not prosper, and all their flocks shall be scattered.</Q>
<P>Printed for <HI>Thomas Simmons</HI> at the <HI>Bull</HI> and <HI>Mouth</HI> near <HI>Aldersgate,</HI> 1659.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE READER.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hat all People who reads this Treatise may see the confusion and Ignorance of <HI>John Horne</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore,</HI> who long have been owned as eminent Teachers by many that are deceived by them, it is seen sit that they seriously here take a view of some of the Principles affirmed by the said <HI>John Horne</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore</HI> at the dispute that we had with them (as ordered of the Lord,) at <HI>Lin in Norfolke,</HI> the fifteenth day of the seventh Moneth, 1659. for their booke which is hereafter confuted, hath some re∣lation to their Principles, which are laid down as follow∣eth.</P>
<P>Thomas Moore <HI>affirmed, That sin is a natural Heritage in the believers while they are here.</HI></P>
<P><HI>That their nature is restored in Christ, (speaking of their own nature) and that their nature is a filthy na∣ture, and Christ took upon him their nature.</HI></P>
<P>John Horne, <HI>That they that had no guile in them had sin in them; That every sin is not guile.</HI></P>
<P>T. M. <HI>That the blood of Christ shed is not in his Person in heaven, but the virtue of it.</HI></P>
<P>T. M. <HI>That the blood of Christ shed is the foun∣dation of their faith, (but where it is they answered not, nor could they tell.)</HI></P>
<P><PB REF="3"/>
T M. <HI>That the Life of Christ is not in the bloud of Christ,</HI> (so from this then the foundation of their faith hath not the Life of Christ in it.)</P>
<P>T. M. <HI>That the Light with which Christ lighteth every man is both natural and spiritual.</HI></P>
<P>T. M. <HI>That the Person of Christ</HI> (viz. <HI>of flesh and bone) is a quickening spirit and dwells in the be∣lievers by faith;</HI> and to prove it, he said <HI>That the</HI> Corin∣thians <HI>dwelt in the heart of</HI> Paul.</P>
<P>J. H. To that of 1 Cor. 15. 45. The last <HI>Adam</HI> was made a quickening spirit, <HI>John Horne</HI> said <HI>That he was distinct from the Eternal Spirit.</HI></P>
<P>T, M. To prove <HI>sin a natural heritage in believers so long as they are here,</HI> he brought that of <HI>Rom. 7. 17.</HI></P>
<P>These Doctrines (with many such like) were taken notice of by many as they were asserted by the said <HI>John Horne</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore,</HI> and contradicted by the Truth at the Dis∣pute aforesaid, wherein it is so easie to see their darknesse and confusion, that we need say little about them at present, but proceed to Answer their Booke which in effect hath the very same Doctrines in it, with many such like; so that we desire that our following Answer may be seriously read with∣out prejudice or envy against us, and let the Light of Christ judge between us and our Accusers; whereby the Readers hereof may see the errours and confusions of these men a∣foresaid confuted by the Truth, and us who love it cleared from their slanders and revilings.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<P>ANd now <HI>John Horne</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore,</HI> you have charg∣ed us called Quakers, with being guilty of <HI>great errors. 1. In that you say we plead for, and maintain a perfection of sinlessnesse in our selves in this life; and to prove this a great Error, you say that the Apostles never said of themselves, or any other man or woman besides Christ. Jesus, that they had no sin in in them.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here you are found in the great Error your selves, who deny the perfection of sinlesnesse in the believers in this life; the Apostle said, he that believeth hath the witnesse in him∣self, 1 <HI>John</HI> 5. 10. which witnesse is perfect and sinlesse, so not without the perfection of sinlesnesse, and he that believeth, hath obtained witnesse that he is righteous, and having this perfect witnesse in himself, he is not without the perfection and purity of it in himself, for the witnesse of God cannot be divided from the nature of it, and <HI>John</HI> said (speaking of Christ) as he is, so are we in this world, 1 <HI>John</HI> 4. 17. so you have manifestly wrong∣ed both us and the Apostles, and we do not say that there is any perfection in ourselves without Christ who is our righte∣ousnesse, and we the righteousnesse of God in him.</P>
<P>Again to prove our maintaining perfection in this life an Er∣rour, you say <HI>Christ was manifested to take away sin, and in him is no sin.</HI> 1 John 3. <HI>but never is it said so of any other, and that it is no where said by any one of the Saints of themselves, or of any of their Brethren, that they had no sin in them, or were not sinners.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here you would accuse the Saints or Brethren with having sin in them, and with being sinners while in this life; But mark how fairly you have contradicted your own doctrine, you tell us, <HI>It is said indeed, that he that abideth in him sinneth not, and he that is born of God, doth not commit or worksin, because the seed of God abides in him; neither can he sin, that is, commit, work, or yield up to sin, because he is born of God,</HI> you say: So you may here see what <HI>J. Horn,</HI> and <HI>T. Moore</HI> have confessed, that he that abideth in Christ sinneth not, and that he that is born of God cannot sin, nor yield up to sin, because his seed remains in him; whereas before they have counted our maintaining a perfection of sin∣lesness
<PB N="2" REF="4"/>
in this life a great errour, and would accuse the Saints and Brethren with being sinners; so any that are not wholly blind may see their confusion, and how they have broken themselves upon the stone which they have been making warre against; for if Christ be made manifest to take away sin, then they in whom he is made manifest are not to have sin remain∣ing in them so long as they are in this life; and if he that is born of God cannot sin, nor yield up to sin; then he is not a sinner, but clear and perfect from sin, And whosoever sinneth hath neither seen Christ nor known him. Now they that affirm that the Saints or they that be born of God are sinners, they might as well say that the Saints have neither seen Christ nor known him; And where it is said, he that is born of God cannot sin, <HI>John Horn</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore</HI> have given their meaning to it, which is, <HI>it's no more then a man acted and led of God cannot therein sin</HI> they say; which is no more then to say, that a man that is acted of God cannot sin in being acted of God, or he that doth righteousness doth not sin in so doing; so that still they reserve an accusation against him that is born of God for being a sin∣ner; whereas <HI>John</HI> saith, be not deceived, he that doth righte∣ousness is righteous even as Christ is righteous in whom is no sin, 1 <HI>John</HI> 3. 7, 8. And now further see how they have accused the Apostle <HI>Paul.</HI></P>
<P><HI>J. Horn</HI> and <HI>T. Moores</HI> words are these; <HI>Yea in</HI> 1 Tim. 1. 16. <HI>he saith he was then, when an Apostle, the chief of sinners.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> So here they have accused <HI>Paul</HI> to be the chief of sin∣ners when an Apostle, when as the same Apostle saith in that 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 1. 12. That Christ counted him faithful, putting him in∣to the Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>istry; but these accusing <HI>Paul</HI> then to be the chief of sinners, when an Apostle, they might as well say, that he that is faithful to Christ is the chief of sinners, when as it is said that Christ came to save sinners, of whom I am chief, and saith, he had obtained mercy; now it doth not follow that <HI>Paul</HI> was then one of the chief or greatest sinners when faithful, but he was one of the chief of sinners that were saved by Christ, who saveth his people from their sins, and doth not suffer them to remain the greatest sinners when they are saved from sin, as they here have accused <HI>Paul.</HI> And as for these Scriptures you bring, 1 <HI>John</HI> 1. 8, 9, 10. and <HI>James</HI> 3. 1, 2. these prove not what you
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
would have them, that the Saints were not perfectly freed from sin in this life; they did not preach up sin, and imperfecti∣on to remain in them while in this life as you do, for both <HI>James</HI> and <HI>John</HI> exhorteth them otherwise for said <HI>James,</HI> let patience have her perfect work, that you may be perfect and entire, wanting nothing, <HI>James</HI> 1. 4▪ and <HI>John</HI> said, If we walk in the light as he is in the light, we have fellowship one with another, and the Blood of Christ cleanseth us from all sin, 1 <HI>John</HI> 1. 7. and chap. 2. 1. <HI>My little children, these things write I unto you that ye sin not, and if any man sin we have an Advacate with the Father.</HI> So he did not include them all as to remain sinners, for they were all sinners while they were not cleansed by the blood of Christ. Now we ask these men aforesaid, seeing <HI>Paul</HI> was counted faith∣full, and <HI>James</HI> a servant of Jesus Christ, and <HI>John</HI> the beloved of Christ, what one sin or sins can they lay to their charge, or to any of them which they were not freed from before their de∣cease? let them prove some sin which was not destroyed in any of these before their decease, (and who can lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect?) let them speak out and answer direct∣ly, or for ever be silent from pleading for sin and accusing the righteous as they have done; <HI>John</HI> did not say, if we say we are not all sinners, we deceive our selves, but if we say we have no sin, and if we say we have not sinned, which if the lit∣tle children whom <HI>John</HI> wrote unto that they might not sin, had sin, then <HI>John</HI> might say we have sin, for he numbred him∣self with them as friends, or those whose sins were forgiven, and yet the young men and Fathers he wrote to had overcome the wicked one, and had the word of God abiding in them, 1 <HI>John</HI> 2. and as for that of <HI>Prov.</HI> 20. 9. who can say I have made my heart clean? this is not against us, for we do not say that we our selves have made our hearts clean, it being Christs work to cleanse, and for ever to have perfected them that are sancti∣fied, <HI>Heb.</HI> 10. 14. and <HI>Solomon</HI> saith, the just man walketh in his Integrity, and the righteousnesse of the perfect shall direct his way, <HI>Prov.</HI> 11. 5. and 20. 7. And as for that of <HI>Eccle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI> 7. he saith, all things have I seen in the dayes of my vanity; there is a just man that perisheth in his righteousnesse, and a wicked man that prolongeth his life in wickednesse, but he that feareth the Lord shall come out of them all, forthere is not a just man up∣on
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
earth: Mark for there among them that were in the change∣able state, not among them that are borne of God, for they can∣not sin, because the Seed of God abides in them, and they in it, neither can the wicked one touch them, 1 <HI>John</HI> 5. 18.</P>
<P>J. Horn and T. Moore say, <HI>There is no man that sinneth not; It is true indeed that Christ said of</HI> Nathaniel, <HI>that he was an Israelite in whom was no guile,</HI> John 1. 47.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here you may see how they are confounded, in what they themselves bring, there was some in whom was no guile, contrary to what they affirmed before against perfection; and as for that 1 <HI>King.</HI> 8. 6. it is said, if they sin against thee, for there is no man that sinneth not; Mark the words (for there) again, among them that sinned against God, and this was in the time of the old Covenant <HI>Solomon</HI> spoke these words, which Cove∣nant they brake; but now the Lord makes a new Covenant with his people, when he takes away their sins, not according to the old Covenant which the Israelites brake, <HI>Heb.</HI> 8. and <HI>Solomon</HI> also said, let your heart be perfect with the Lord your God, and walk in his Statutes, and to keep his Commandements, as at this day, 1 <HI>King</HI> 8. 61.</P>
<P>J. Horn saith, <HI>It is not said that there was no sin in</HI> Nathaniel, <HI>and though</HI> I pleaded that all sin is guile, yet the contrary was testified from 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2. 1, 2. <HI>where hypocrisie, and envie, and malice, and evill speakings are distinguished from Guile, Guile being a deceitful</HI> hiding a mans sin or deceit.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here <HI>John Horne</HI> would accuse <HI>Nathaniel</HI> to have sin in him, when as Christ said there was no Guile in him, <HI>John</HI> 1. 47. and so here he hath affirmed as much as that all sin is not Guile, and so would distinguish hypocrisy and envie from being guile, and yet confesseth Guile to be a deceitful hiding a mans sin or deceit; now let any that have understanding see these mens ignorance; what is not hypocrisy a deceitful hiding a mans sin? and is not every sin deceit, and deceit Guile? see their confusion; and this being <HI>John Hornes</HI> reason to prove all sinne not Guile, because it is said in 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2. 1, 2. laying aside all malice, and all guile (mark all guile) and hypocrisy, the word (and being his distinction, he might as well say that envie is not malice, because there is (and) between them, but in that thing many saw his folly at the dispute, in his affirming that all
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
sin is not guile, when as all guile doth only include one sin as he would have it; but all sin, and any one sin makes a man guil∣ty, and so he hath guile in him, so that he that had no guile in him, had no sin in him, and also <HI>John Horne</HI> hath turned <HI>George Whiteheads</HI> words about this thing, in saying that be said Guile is a transgression of the Law, therefore guile is all sin, which is falsely framed, for the words were to this effect, every trangres∣sion of the Law is guile or sin, and all guile includes all trans∣gression of the Law, therefore every sin is guile, and what sin can they prove had <HI>Nathaniel</HI> in him when he had no guile in him? they must either prove some sin that was then in him, or else see themselves confuted.</P>
<P><HI>J. Horne</HI> and <HI>T. Moore</HI> in the 3. and 4. pages of their Book, say: <HI>That in the Declaration by</HI> Edward Burrough page 4. <HI>that we believe the Saints upon earth may be perfectly freed from the body of sin and death,</HI> herein we are concluded to be Preachers of Lyes and Errors (this they charge the Quakers with) and yet they say, <HI>We are compleat in Christ, and by the Grace of Christ received, shall be and may be here made perfect hearted with Christ, but that some are sin∣lesse here, neither Christ, nor any Apostle or Prophet ever preached of any, therefore the Quakers are deceivers.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Here they might as well have accused the true Pro∣phets and Apostles with being Preachers of Lyes, and decei∣vers, for they witnessed to the same the Quakers witnesse to, as said the Prophet, blessed are the undefiled in the way (mark undefiled in the way) they also do no iniquity, <HI>Psal.</HI> 119. 1, 2, 3. and saith the Lord, ye shall be clean from all your filthinesse, <HI>Ezek.</HI> 36. 25. and Christ exhorted his to be perfect, as their heavenly Father is perfect, <HI>Matt.</HI> 5. 48. and every one that is perfect shall be as his Lord, and the same Apostle who said, ye are compleat in Christ, said in whom also ye are circumcised with the circumcision made without hands, in putting off the body of the sins of the flesh, <HI>Col.</HI> 2. 10, 1.</P>
<P>Now the same spirit in <HI>J. Horne</HI> and <HI>T. Moore,</HI> that hath ac∣cused the Quakers with being deceivers, for bearing witnesse to these Truths, would have accused the true Prophets, Christ and his Apostles for being deceivers; but their confusion and railing against the Innocent is here made manifest, who notwithstand∣ing have confessed a compleatnesse and perfect heartednesse
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
with Christ here, and so in pleading for sin in this life, are sighting against their own words, for they who are compleat in Christ, are perfectly freed from sin, being compleat in Christ in whom there is no sin; and know this, that sinners are out of the compleatnesse which the Saints have in Christ, and the heare that hath sin dwelling in it is not perfect; much more might be said to this.</P>
<P>John Horne and Thomas Moore p. 3. to prove, <HI>that they who have believed in Christ, comes not to prove the first</HI> Adams <HI>state before the fall; say, that</HI> Adam <HI>before his fall had neither sin in him, nor death upon, but surely the Quakers must die as well as other mens</HI> Adam <HI>also before his fall was under a Covenant of works, doe this and live, and might possibly sin and dye, but not so the believers.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Mark their heap of confusion here, they own that the Believers in Christ are come to a further state or Covenant then <HI>Adam</HI> was in before the fall, who then had no sin in him, and yet have accused the Believers with having the body of sin, or not being perfect while they are here; and <HI>Adam</HI> might possibly sin and dye, but not so the Believers they say; And as for the Quakers dying, because of which they would accuse them with being sinners, here their darknesse appears, for Believers dying the natural death, doth not prove them sinners while they are here, for through death they gain more of the Peace and Glory of God which they partake of in their life time, and what doth <HI>John Horne</HI> believe that <HI>Adam</HI> might not have dyed the natural death if he had not sinned? for Christ dyed who had no sin, that he might destroy the death which came by sin, and him that hath the power of it, and they who dye in the Lord are blessed, and to dye is gain unto them, <HI>Phil.</HI> 1. 2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. so that righteous mens dying was not charged upon them as a reward for their sin, but witnessed to be gain unto them, before whose decease their sins are done away, and he that believeth hath everlasting life, yet the wages of sin is death to them who are not freed from it by the gift of God which is life; and God said to <HI>Adam</HI> in the day thou eatest thereof thou shalt surely dye; but <HI>Adam</HI> lost not his natural life in the day he eat of the tree of knowledge, for after that he lived in the body; and as for the Covenant that <HI>Adam</HI> was under before the full, it was a Covenant of life; for he was in the image of God, and a living soule, having the breath
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
of life in him, and had dominion in it while he stood in his ha∣bitation, and this state have the true Believers proved and wit∣nessed that life, and nature, &amp; image that was in man before the fall, though they be come further in the second <HI>Adam,</HI> who is greater then the first <HI>Adam;</HI> and as for <HI>Adam</HI> before the fall, be∣ing under a Covenant of works <HI>do this and live</HI> (as if he had not lived when he was in innocency, till he did something to merit life) you have here spoken ignorantly, for that Covenant of works was established by the Law after the fall, and the Law en∣tered because of transgression till the Seed came, which Seed de∣stroyes sin and redeems the Creature out of the fall, and out of the death which came by sin.</P>
<P>P. 4. And in their second charge against us called Quakers, J. Horne and T. Moor have accused us <HI>to be reprobates concerning faith, as touching he person of Christ;</HI> for they say, <HI>we did not, nor could be brought to acknowledge that Christ is glorified in the heavens, without all men, the heavens above the clouds, and distinct from the visible earth in the same body which suffered, was crucified, dead and buried,</HI> &amp;c. And this have they questioned several times altering their own words, and then in page 5. asking <HI>whether Christ hath any body of flesh and bones, distinct from all other bodies and spirits of m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n,</HI> to which they say, we would by no means be drawn to give a di∣rect answer. But then mark how they have again contradicted themselves; they say, <HI>that we said the same body that suffered was glorified at Gods right hand in heaven;</HI> yet still (they say) we meant but his Church either by his body or by the heavens, and then they charge it upon us as a fundamental error.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Now they that discerne the body of Christ, may see how these wise men of <HI>Babylon</HI> have confounded and stifled themselves in their own confusion, one while saying that we would not be drawn to answer their question, another while confessing that we said the same body that suffered, was glorifi∣ed at Gods right hand in heaven, and now when they can get nought against our words, they charge us ignorantly with what we meant, and here it appears they hold that Christ hath two bodies, in telling of a mystical body, and not receiving that as an answer that his body is the Church, the fulness of him that filleth all in all, so that from their words they would have Christ to have a body besides (or distinct from) the fulness of God, when as the Scripture doth not say that
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
Christ hath two bodies, nor that his body is a body of flesh and bones without the blood in it in the Heavens, as <HI>John Horne</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore</HI> have told us, for its not proper to say that a body of flesh and bones is in the Heavens, as if it were in many places at once, for Heavens are more then one, and the body is one and hath many members, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 12. 12. and this body is not carnal but spiritual, which they who were carnal as these men are, could not discern, though the outward bodies of believers they might discern, and yet this body of Christ is discerned by the believers who are led by the Spirit of God, and its in the heavens above the clouds, which they who are gazing abroad and looking carnally to see Christ they discern not the Lords body, for they see not thorow the Clouds into the Heavens, so Christ is taken out of their sight; But <HI>Stephen</HI> who was full of the Holy Ghost saw the heavens opened, and the Son of man on the right hand of his Father, and <HI>John</HI> in the spirit saw into heaven, and a door opened in heaven; and Christs body is not distinct from the spirits of all men, as it is distinct from carnal bodies, as you imagine by your Question; for the just men who are come unto mount <HI>Zion</HI> where the Lamb Reigneth in his glory, I say their spirits rejoyce in him, and the true Church in Christ which discerneth his body in his fulness, is but one compleat body in the fulness of God which filleth all in all (both in Heaven and Earth) though you imagine two bodies of Christ. And this know, that what the Scriptures do declare of Christ and his body we own; and the same that de∣scended into the lower parts of the Earth is he that Ascended far above all Heavens that he might fill all things; the same Christ that suffered in the body at Jerusalem who ap∣peared in divers forms after his Resurrection, and in the transfiguration before, the same rose again, and was taken in his Ascending out of the sight of them that gazed after him, and is glorified in the same glory which he had with the Father before the world was, <HI>John</HI> 17 and as he who is the Word be∣came flesh, so when the dayes of his flesh were finished he was translated into his own glory which he had with his Father from Eternity, and so the second <HI>Adam</HI> is a quickening spirit and his body is spiritual, not discerned by you whose minds are out from his spirit, neither can his glory by which he was transfigured and is glorified, be seen, but by them who
<PB N="9" REF="7"/>
pass thorow death, and follow him into the mount. And now you who so much contend about the body of Christ, we ask you this Question; whether do you believe that the body of Christ which the Saints upon earth do discern, and which the world cannot discern, is a body of flesh and bones in the Heavens yea or nay? seeing you own the believers or the Church to be a body of Christ, and plead for another body of Christ distinct from them.</P>
<P><HI>John Horn</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore,</HI> p. 5. Say <HI>that believers are members of his body (namely his mystical body) of his flesh and of his bones, not flesh of his flesh and bone of his bone.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> This is grosse confusion to say that believers are mem∣bers of Christs flesh and bones, and then to say they are not flesh of his flesh, and bone of his bone, as if Christ had two bodies of flesh and bones, one of which the Saints are not mem∣bers, when the Apostle saith as much as they were flesh of his flesh, and bone of his bone, in his saying no man ever hated his own flesh but nourisheth it, and cherisheth it even as the Lord the Church, for we are members of his body, of his flesh &amp; of his bones, <HI>Eph.</HI> 5. 30. <HI>J. Horn,</HI> &amp; <HI>Tho. Moore</HI> bring 1 <HI>Thes.</HI> 4. 15. 16. and <HI>Phil.</HI> 3. 20. 21. where it is said Christ shall descend from Heaven; <HI>not from but to his Church</HI> (say they) <HI>yea this of the</HI> Quakers <HI>denying that body glorified doth at once turn up by the roots all the faith of Christs appearing in the presence of God to mediate for us.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ans</HI> Was there ever the like confusion and falshood uttere'd, as these men do appear in? a little before they say of the <HI>Qua∣kers, that they said the same body that suffered was glorified at Gods right hand in Heaven;</HI> and now charge us with denying that body glorified, it were well they would be ashamed of their lies and confusion; and as for that, 1 <HI>Thes.</HI> 4. 15. Concerning the coming of the Lord from Heaven, which these men aforesaid would blindly put afar of, as to a coming of Christ with flesh and bones, the Apostle saith we which are alive &amp; remain unto the coming of the Lord, shall not prevent them which are a sleep; so that coming of Christ, the Saints who then were alive remained unto it: and in that of <HI>Phil.</HI> 3. 20. 21. there it is said our conversation is in Heaven from whence also we look for the Saviour the Lord Jesus Christ; so their conversation was in Heaven, and there they looked for the Saviour, they did not say their conversation was at a distance off above the Clouds,
<PB N="10" REF="8"/>
from whence you look for a Christ like your selves (but that he hath no blood in his body as you imagine) whom we desire not the knowledge of, and that your Faith which is not grounded in Christs appearing in you, is to be turned up by the roots.</P>
<P>Again, <HI>J. Horn</HI> and <HI>T. Moor</HI> do accuse us <HI>to be Reprobate con∣cerning the Faith touching the Resurrection of the dead,</HI> as chiefly they accuse us for affirming that the same body that dyes shall not be raised again, and that <HI>George Fox</HI> would not be brought to say, whether the spiritual body was ever dead, but answe∣red in general equivocal terms.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> They have changed <HI>G. Foxes</HI> words; for he said, That which is raised is a spiritual body, and that which is raised was dead; and we answered them plainly to these things according to the Scriptures, but like fools whom the Apostle reproved, they would not be satisfied when we told them it is sown a na∣tural body it is raised a spiritual body, and receives life and spirit by the Power of God; there is a natural body and there is a spiritual body, howbeit that was not first which is spiritual but that which is natural, and afterward that which is spiri∣tual; so the Apostle distinguisheth between the natural body and the spiritual body, between the earthly bodies and the hea∣venly bodies, and the glories of each, and doth not say, that which dyes or is sown which is earthly shall rise, as we told these said accusers according to the Apostles comparison, thou fool, that which thou sowest is not quickned except it dye, and that which thou sowest thou sowest not that body that shall be, (mark, thou sowest not that body that shall be) but bear grain it may chance of wheat or of some other grain, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 15. 36, 37. contrary to which they have affirmed, that the same body that dyes or is sown in the earth shall raise again, when the Apostle saith, thou sowest not that body that shall be, and his compari∣son is of the grain of wheat and the like, to which <HI>Thomas Moor</HI> answered, <HI>That the same kirnel of wheat rose up again in the blade,</HI> when it is known that the same kirnel doth not rise, but another body or ear of Corn grows forth in the nature of that wch is sown, &amp; yet we say that God giveth a body as it pleaseth him, &amp; to every seed his own body, which seeds being known, &amp; &amp; the nature and kind of each seed discerned, the body of each may be discerned in the Resurrection by the light wch crosseth
<PB N="11" REF="8"/>
mens carnal imaginations, by which they must never know the Mystery of the Resurrection of the bodies nor the seeds, wch the Lord knoweth how to reserve every one in its own center and habitation till the sounding of the last Trumpet at the last day, and there shall be a Resurrection both of the just and the unjust, and many that sleep in the dust of the earth shall rise, some shall come forth to the Resurrection of life, and others to the Resurrection of Condemnation, every one to be rewarded ac∣cording to their works; and <HI>John</HI> said, <HI>The Sea gave up the dead which were in it, and death and Hell delivered up the dead which were in them, &amp; they were Judged every man according to their works, &amp; death and Hell were cast into the lake of fire, &amp; whosoever was not found written in the Book of Life,</HI> Rev. 2. And now this being an an∣swer to their Question about the Resurrection, note, that when <HI>Thomas Moor</HI> was asked what was the seed of which the Apostle said God giveth it a body as it pleaseth him? <HI>Tho. Moor</HI> answe∣red, that the seed was the body that dyes or is laid in the ground, which he pleaded for the rising of, to which it was Re∣plyed then, that every man must rise with two bodies, if that body that is terrestrial must rise and have another body given it, but herein his ignorance was seen; and again, he and <HI>John Horn</HI> have confuted themselves, for in their Post-script they say, <HI>That the Apostle implying plainly, that the raised body in the Re∣surrection shall not be flesh and blood;</HI> Then how is it that they have pleaded so much for the same earthly body that dies to rise again, which is a body of flesh and blood, when the raised body in the Resurrection is not a body of flesh and blood they say? these men are much shut up in <HI>Babylon,</HI> as their con∣fusion manifests.</P>
<P>An accusation of <HI>John Horn</HI> and <HI>Tho. Moor against John White∣head to prove him a Reprobate,</HI> p. 6. <HI>Is that John argued against the Redemption of the body to be waited for or expected after death,</HI> and said, <HI>The Apostle had it before the death of the body;</HI> and in p. 10. <HI>They tell of the nature or being of man, that in the Resurrection it is discharged of sin, and Law, and death.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> So here they expect not the Redemption of the body nor their discharge from sin till after death, wherein they have discovered themselves to be Reprobates and not <HI>John Whitehead,</HI> and their expecting the Redemption of the body to be waited
<PB N="12" REF="9"/>
for after death, is contrary to the Saints expectations, for they waited and groaned for the Redemption of the body from un∣der corruption when they were upon earth, and the Creature it self was to be brought into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God, which state was witnessed by as many as were led by the Spirit of God who were sanctified throughout, in Body, in Soul and Spirit, and put not Redemption afar off till after death, as these men aforementioned have done.</P>
<P>Again, They have accused us for <HI>Antichristians,</HI> from a pas∣sage in <HI>Edward Burroughs</HI> Book, where it is said, That Christ is to be known after the Spirit as he was before the world was, and that is the knowledge of him which is to eternal Salvation. On the contrary they have affirmed in page 7. <HI>That the knowledge of Christ after the Spirit as he was before the world was, is not the know∣ledge of him to eternal Salvation, but on the contrary (they say.)</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> In this they have shewed themselves to be both abu∣sers of the Truth and Antichristians; for to know Christ as he is the power of God, is to know him after the Spirit as he was before the world was, and this is the knowledge of him to E∣ternal Salvation, it is the Power of God that saveth, and we trust in the living God who is the Saviour of all men, specially of them that believe, 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 4. 10. Now as Christ is the li∣ving God, he was before the world was, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jesus Christ, this is the true God and eternal life, 1 <HI>John</HI> 5. 20. And now I say, they that re∣ceive this knowledge of Christ, do not deny his knowledge in his flesh, but witness to the same eternal Power that was ma∣nifest in his flesh, and thorow his sufferings, which Power was before the world was, and hath the same glory that it had then, and is the same for ever.</P>
<P>And in page 7. it is said against the Quakers, <HI>That they can and may in their canting language say, he is manifest in</HI> England, <HI>and is persecuted, and dyes, and rises as well as in</HI> Judea <HI>and</HI> Jerusalem, <HI>however they make nothing of his being born, suffering and dying in the flesh.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Now when <HI>J. Horn</HI> and <HI>T. Moor</HI> can truly prove no∣thing against us called <HI>Quakers,</HI> they have invented these wic∣ked lyes against us, which we utterly deny, and here charge them for forgers of lyes; <HI>Job</HI> 13. 4. for we never used any
<PB N="13" REF="9"/>
such canting language, as they call it, against Christ, but own his sufferings in <HI>Judea</HI> and <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> as he was a true offering and propitiation for the sins of the whole world, whose suffe∣rings were effectual both for the pacifying of his Fathers wrath and for the reconciling of the whole world, as is witnessed by them who receive the Power of his life, which was manifest thorow death to them that truely believed thorow Christs suf∣ferings; and in page 9. the said <HI>J. Horn</HI> and <HI>T. Moor</HI> have belyed <HI>George Whitehead,</HI> in saying that <HI>he alleadging</HI> 2 Cor. 5. 16. <HI>to prove that the Apostles did not know Christ as one that suffered in the flesh, or to be in the flesh;</HI> which is exceeding false, for that Scri∣pture henceforth we know no man after the flesh, and though we had known Christ after the flesh, yet henceforth know we him so no more, it was brought against your knowledge which is but carnal, and stands in imaginations, who neither truly know Christ as he was in the flesh, nor after the Spirit, but contend against the knowing of him as he was before the world was, (and as you say you neglect Christ) and so against the know∣ledge of the glory of God, as a knowledge to Salvation; when as they neither knew Christ, nor any man after the flesh, but after the Spirit, they knew Christ and one another in that Spirit and Power in them which was before the world was, but this knowledge you are out of, who know but natu∣rally.</P>
<P>In page 9, 10. J. Horn and T. Moor again <HI>affirm, that the na∣ture of man as in Christ, is perfectly freed from sin and curse, and with∣out spot of sin, and the same nature of man, even in believers, having sin in it as a naturall Heritage from the first</HI> Adam <HI>fallen.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> See their gross error and confusion, which is as much as to affirm that as the nature of man is in the believers, it's sepa∣rate from Christ, and so believers in Christ having sin in them originally from <HI>Adam</HI> as a natural heritage, so they would make believers have two heritages, a naturall, and a spirituall; an old delusion of the Priests; for the true believers are in Christ, and by his power do witness their nature purified, by that which brings out of <HI>Adams</HI> fallen state, to witness a better heritage then sin in their nature; for they that are in Christ, have escaped the corruptions of the world, and witness an incorruptible he∣ritage in the divine nature, and this is known as there is an
<PB N="14" REF="10"/>
biding in Christ, the power of God.</P>
<P>And in page 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. they charge us with denying the humanity of Christ, and say we judge him only a spirit.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> We never denyed the man Christ, for his flesh is our food; &amp; for our owning Christ to be a spirit, the Apostles owned him to be the same, the Lord is that spirit, and the last <HI>Adam</HI> was made a quickening spirit, 2 <HI>Cor. 3. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 1 Cor.</HI> 15. 45.</P>
<P>Again <HI>they have affirmed that Christ is personally in heaven, and yet by faith in the believing heart;</HI> and that he is not really and per∣sonally in believers, as in heaven, but by faith; <HI>and yet</HI> Moor <HI>be∣fore said, that Christs person of flesh and bone is a quickening spirit.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> If Christ is not really in the believers, and if his being in them by faith is not reall, then it is but imaginary, herein J. Horn and T. Moore, have manifested their faith to be no better then the Papists faith, as I told them, wherein I did not belye them as they accuse me, for the faith of the Elect doth re∣ally evidence to them Christ in them the mystery, and the power of God, and this faith is not divided from Christ the object or foundation of it.</P>
<P>And now concerning the blood of Christ shed, which <HI>T. Moore</HI> at the dispute owned to be the foundation of your faith, and yet affirmed that the body of Christ is in heaven, with flesh and bones, but not the blood in it, and so knew not where the blood is; <HI>Now they tell us in page 11. that his blood was shed or powred out for the Remission of our sins, and in the vertues of it is with the Father, and so in and with Christ.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Herein they have plainly confuted themselves; for they also confess that they could not assert where the material blood (as they call it) or blood of Christ shed is, and yet now say, that in the vertues of it is with the Father, and in and with Christ; so <HI>J. Horn</HI> and <HI>T. Moons</HI> hearers may now see how they have confuted their former Doctrine, who before would not own that the blood of Christ shed is in the body of Christ, yet now say it is with the Father, and in Christ in the vertues of it; and now to clear themselves from our telling them that they preached a foundation of Faith which they knew not where it is, and which according to their own con∣fession before, they knew not whether it is in being or not.</P>
<P>They tell us, <HI>That the dying of Christ or his death is the founda∣tion
<PB N="15" REF="10"/>
of their faith, and yet this dying as to the act of it is not alwayes in being, nor is the blood simply the foundation of their faith.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here again they have preached that to be the foun∣dation of their Faith which is not in being, when as the foundation of the true Faith is Christ, who is in being, and another foundation can no man lay, then that which is laid, which is Christ; and as for what he acted in sufferings, that was done that thorow his sufferings and works men might believe in him who worketh Faith in them, and know him to be the foundation of Faith who is in being, and not that which is not in being, as they imagine and have declared, and they now owning the blood of Christ shed not simply to be the foundation of their faith, then if they own it as part of the foundation of their Faith, then are they still at a loss, for they know not where it is; and so according to their own words they want part of the foundation of their faith, we blame them not, neither did we blame them for not asserting that the blood shed is in the body of Christ, but for calling it the foundation of their faith (whether they own it so simply or compoundedly see∣ing they know not where the blood is, nor whether it is in being; and so we blamed them for their confusion, and e∣stablishing a blind and dead faith.</P>
<P>T. M. his instance for Christs being in Heaven with a body of flesh and bones without blood in it, was, that we do not read that there was any blood in <HI>Adams</HI> body in Paradice; for which he might as well have said, that then <HI>Adams</HI> body in Paradice had no life in it (and such a body they imagine Christs to be) when as the blood is the life, and all Nations are made of one blood, <HI>Acts</HI> 17. 26. Now we ask them if they believe that there was no blood left in Christs body when he was crucified? And when T M. had pleaded for a body of flesh and bones in the Heavens, he did not own that Christs body there is a carnal body; see how flatly therein he contradicted his own words and the Priests doctrine, for Priest <HI>Higginson</HI> and others affirmed, that Christ is in Heaven with a carnal body; but his bo∣dy i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a Mistery which these men of <HI>Babylon</HI> can never know, who are thus in confusion; for Christs body is onely known with that by which God is seen and known, who is not the Authour of their confusion, but of peace.</P>
<P>And in page 12. T M. and J. H. speak as that <HI>Job</HI> said, Behold, God is great, we know him not, and to prove it, bring <HI>Job</HI> 36 26. which is a sad mistake against <HI>Job.</HI> for it was <HI>Elihu</HI> that spoke these words who was one of them that spoke against <HI>Joh, Joh</HI> 35. 2 and 26. 1. for <HI>Job</HI> knew God when they that came against him did not; but this their Accusation against <HI>Job</HI> is even like <HI>John Horns</HI> pleading for sin in a Letter to <HI>Eliz. Underwood,</HI> for
<PB N="16" REF="11"/>
which he brought <HI>Eliphaz</HI> his words, (who was one of them that came a∣gainst <HI>Job,</HI> and sooke not the thing of God that was right) where he said in <HI>Job</HI> 4. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and 15. 14, 15. Behold, he put no trust in his servants, and his Angels he charged with folly, which were none of <HI>Jobs</HI> words, but his against whom the wrath of God was kindled, <HI>Job</HI> 42. 7. and in like man∣ner hath <HI>John Horn</HI> often belyed the servants of the Lord, both in his Book and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se Letters which he sent abroad in the Countrey to several that were brought to see his deceit, and therefore are turned from him, and many more of his lyes in several of his Letters against us I could produce i. oc∣casioned to it.</P>
<P>In page 12. <HI>J. Horn</HI> and <HI>T. Moor</HI> say, <HI>That it is rather a vertue to which we are advised not to be wise, or think or guess above what is written;</HI> but presently they begin to guess that which is not written, and so confound themselves in their saying, <HI>That there are indeed very probable arguments used to prove that that precious blood was reunited again with the body of Christ in the Re∣surrection.</HI></P>
<P>But how shall any that are ignorant believe them, or be in∣structed with their confusion? For again they have (to mend this their matter) confuted these they call very probable arguments, to prove that Christs blood was reunited again with the body of Christ, for in contradiction to this, in their Post-script they say, <HI>But these being but probabilities at most, and on the other side the Scriptures speaking of Christs Resurre∣ction, mentioning only that which was buried, without any mention of his blood reunited;</HI> So from hence we clearly see that <HI>J. Horn</HI> and some of his Company have had much reasoning about the blood of Christ, and are in themselves confounded a∣bout it, one while saying that there are very probable ar∣guments to prove that it was reunited again with the body of Christ, another while not owning that it was reunited again, and with that they conclude; See what blind guides these men are, we might have received as good an answer from School-boyes about the blood of Christ, as they might have guessed at it, as <HI>J. Horn</HI> and <HI>T. Moor</HI> hath done, and have told us, that it is either in the body of Christ, or not in it; But mark how again they have guessed about it, They say in page 12. <HI>Again that which was blood before may be in the changed state turned into pure life and spirit, the thing or sub∣stance remaining.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="11"/>
<HI>Answ.</HI> Here again they have guessed, and thought above that which is written, and how can blood be turned into spirits and the substance of it remaining? this is a meer dream and one of <HI>John Hornes</HI> divinations, and it contradicts <HI>Moores</HI> words, for he said that the life of Christ is not in his blood; Again if the blood that Christ shed be turned into pure spirits and life, what is his body of flesh and bones turned into? or what reason is there that his blood should be altered more then his flesh and bones? but all this con∣fusion and dirty stuff of <HI>John Hornes</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moores</HI> is seen thorow and made manifest with the true light, in which they that walk shall feel the blood of Christ, which cleanseth from all sin, and know that the spirit the water and blood, which bear record in the earth agree in one, and the blood is the life, which is in Christ, whose body is not a body without the blood in it, as these dreamars aforesaid imagines; and as the Prophet said, we witness, that by the blood of the Covenant the prisoners are sent out of the pit which can hold no water.</P>
<P>Again in <HI>pag.</HI> 14. We are falsly accused with denying what the Scripture asserts about the body of Christ, and the Re∣surrection of mens bodies, and about the knowledge of Christ.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here we see plainly that this <HI>John Horne,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore,</HI> do love lying rather then to speak righteousness, for we own what the Scripture asserts about the body of Christ, and the Resurrection, but deny their imaginations; and here again I shall bring their own words to confute them, in <HI>pag.</HI> 5. they have confessed that we said (of Christs body) <HI>that the same body that suffered was glorified at Gods right hand in Heaven,</HI> which might have stopt their mouths from accusing us as they did; and as for our not asserting that the same earthly bodies of men shall rise again, they have in their post-script confessed, <HI>that the raised body in the resurrection shall not be flesh and blood;</HI> to which I say, then not that body which is sown or buried, for that is a body of flesh and blood; Again touching Christs appearance after his resurrection, when he shewed his Disciples his hands and his feet, we do not be∣lieve
<PB N="18" REF="12"/>
that his body then had no blood in it, for he then did eat before them of the broiled fish and honny comb which they gave him, which is nourishment to both flesh and blood, <HI>Luke</HI> 24. 41. 42. and the blood is the life of that which hath need of such outward nourishment, yea the life of all flesh is the blood, <HI>Gen. 9. 4. 5. Levit.</HI> 17. 14. but as Christ is Ascended into his Fathers glory in Heaven, he is in a further state, for he hath not need now of such outward nourishment as broil∣ed fish, or a hony comb, for he is in the same glory which he had with the Father before the world began; and as for the Saints also, their bodies in the resurrection shall as far exceed these our earthen bodies in glory, as the glory of the Sun, Moon and Stars do exceed the glory of Birds, Beasts, and Fishes, but the mystery of these things is for ever sealed as in Parables from such blind guides as these aforesaid, who have long abused the truth of Christ.</P>
<P>In <HI>p. 14. John Horne</HI> and <HI>Moore</HI> have affirmed, <HI>The Scriptures to be the Medium of Faith,</HI> from <HI>John</HI> 17. 20. where its said, nei∣ther pray I for these alone, but for them also which shall be∣lieve on me through their word, and <HI>Acts</HI> 17. 11. 12. of the <HI>Bereans</HI> searching the Scriptures, &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> There is no such Scripture as saith, that the Scri∣ptures are the <HI>Medium</HI> of Faith, for they through whose word many believed were not Ministers of the Letter, but of the spirit, and their Word was before the Letter or writ∣ing was, and it came in Spirit and in Power, and this Word which they Preached was nigh people, even in their hearts, <HI>Rom.</HI> 10. And as for the <HI>Bereans</HI> they first received the Word with all readiness of minde, and then searched the Scriptures, whether these things were so; so it was the Word which brought them to believe and to search the Scriptures, and so we say the Scriptures are truely to be believed and fulfilled, but that which brings any truely to believe and fulfill them, is Christ the Word, the Author and finisher of faith, unto whom they would not come for life, who thought they had Eternal life in the Scriptures, <HI>Joh.</HI> 5. 39 40.</P>
<P>In <HI>pag. 15 John Horne,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore</HI> have accused <HI>John
<PB N="19" REF="12"/>
Whitehead with saying that the Apostles did not bring light to men, but onely pointed to what they had before.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ. John Whitehead</HI> doth witness against them for per∣verting his words, as it hath been examined; the words are not so affirmed by him, but this we say, that the Apostles did not bring another light to people then that which had enlightned them before they Preacht to them, and though the light was more in the Apostles then in them they Preacht to, yet it was the same in nature in both, though known in several measures, and they who will not own the light in the least measure of it in them, they must not know the greater, nor the glory, which the light of Christ shining in the heart gives the knowledge of in them that receive it.</P>
<P>Again, <HI>Horne</HI> and <HI>Moore</HI> say, <HI>Indeed this is a main piece of corrupt Doctrine</HI> (that we Preach) <HI>that all have the light of Christ in them, and that that is, whatsoever reproves any sin in men.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Here they might as well have accused Christ and the Apostles for using corrupt Doctrine; for Christ saith, I am the light of the world, and <HI>John</HI> said of him, that was the true light which enlightneth every man that comes into the world, and that which may be known of God is manifest in them who are in unrighteousness, and like not to retain God in their knowledge, <HI>Rom.</HI> 1. and the grace of God which bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men, and this is the free gift of God, which if it were not given to all men, then wherefore shall the wicked be condemned? and what is it in them that must leave them without excuse, and who can you shew us that have not a light of Christ in them to re∣prove them when they have done evil? And you have again here wickedly wronged us, for we do not affirm that what∣soever reproves any sin is the light of Christ; but whatsoever makes manifest things that are reproved is light, and the light reproves every sin; But such as you that are in deceit and out of the light, do sometimes reprove sin when you live in it your selves, but the light of Christ in you will reprove you for it.</P>
<P>Again in <HI>p.</HI> 16. You <HI>John Horn</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore</HI> say, <HI>That
<PB N="20" REF="13"/>
this way of ours exposes men to follow their own spirits, which we re∣present as a candle in every man.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> This is false, for our way exposes men not to fol∣low their own spirits, nor sparkes of their own kindling as you say, but to follow the light of Christ, which lighteth the spirit of a man, and makes it become the candle of the Lord, that it enlightens the inward parts. Another of your lies against us, is, where in <HI>pag.</HI> 17. you accuse <HI>George White∣head</HI> with deriding at mens faith in the death and blood∣shed of Christ beyond the Sea, for they who truely have faith and hope through Christs sufferings which reacheth within the vail, that is to say Christs flesh, that faith we own, as knowing the Word of it to be in the heart, that we have it not to fetch beyond the Sea, nor from above, nor from beneath, but its nigh in the heart and in the mouth. And to our question which was, whether the light that lighteth every man, be a natural light, or a spiritual light?</P>
<P>You <HI>John Horne</HI> and <HI>T. Moore</HI> answers <HI>(pag.</HI> 17. 18.) <HI>That that light is Christ, and the light with which he lighteth men is both natural and spiritual.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Reply,</HI> Here again you are taken in your own snare, for in your saying the light is both natural and spiritual (mark, it is not the lights are both natural and spiritual, but the light is so) here you could not prove one light that is both natural and spiritual, and contrary to the Scriptures have you spoken, for in Christ was life, and the life was the light of men, which is not natural but spiritual, therefore this your errour may lie upon you.</P>
<P>In <HI>pag.</HI> 18. You say, <HI>That for so much as all men receive not Christ and his light, therefore all have not his light in them.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> This is a poor Argument; the Spirit of the Lord, and the grace of God hath appeared in many who have re∣sisted it and not received it, and a measure of it is in such to condemn them, as the Kingdom of God was in the Scribes and Pharisces, and yet they received it not nor Christ, when they hated him; And to that of <HI>Isai.</HI> 8. 20. where it is said there is no light in them, <HI>John Horne</HI> saith the word in
<PB N="21" REF="13"/>
the Hebrew is sometimes used to signifie <HI>the morning</HI> (and we have read it, no morning in stead of no light) but then saith he, <HI>Christ is called the morning Star, so that if there be no morning light in man, there is none of his light who is the morn∣ing light.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here his ignorance appears again, for the light of Christ shines in darkness in some before the morning, and that led some to the arising of the Day-star in their Hearts, and so the light of Christ, who is the morning light to some, appears as a Candle in the darkness to others, and is not the morning light to them, until they by it see the morning in them, and the light which hath shined in darkness arising out of darkness, so that the light of Christ is both the evening light and the morning light.</P>
<P><HI>Page</HI> 19. Again <HI>John Horn,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore</HI> have accused <HI>us, with telling Mr. Townsend,</HI> (as they call him) <HI>That the light was wholly departed from him.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Herein have you impudently belyed us; for the words against <HI>Townsend</HI> are not so spoken, but that from the light of God in his Conscience he is departed; so blush, and be ashamed of your lyes; for in like manner did a false Priest in <HI>Cambridge</HI> belye us, (in a lying Pamphlet) with the very same thing.</P>
<P>In <HI>Page</HI> 20. you <HI>John Horn,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore,</HI> have <HI>accused</HI> James Nayler <HI>with his discovering more fully the mysterie of Deceit,</HI> (in his Book called, <HI>Love to the Lost)</HI> in saying, <HI>That the Seed to which the Promise was made, and which few know, is a certain Seed or Principle in man, desiring to follow after God, and to be free from sin.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Reply.</HI> Here you are seen to be ignorant of the Seed of God, and enemies to it in his People, which Seed is Christ, and where-ever he is known in such a low measure, as a Seed that suffers, and is burthened in man by corruption, there he desires to be free from the burthen of sin, and alwayes to do his Fathers will, and this Seed the power reaches to, where it is begotten, and in the power it arises in them that believe in the light for their Redemption; and the Apostle travelled again for the <HI>Galatians</HI> until Christ was formed in
<PB N="22" REF="14"/>
them, who first is known as one without form or comliness; and so the seed of God suffers in some, and in others it reigns, and is known to be Prince of Peace; and this is no Mystery of Deceit (as you say) but a mystery that hath discovered your Deceit, who know not the Seed of the Kingdom, nor the power wherein it rises; and have you never known what Christ is without the Camp? But before you (who are neglecters of Christ, and abusers of his truth) can know the Seed of God, and what it is in you, you must come to the light which will condemn you for your Deceits and Lyes with which you have abused the Truth, and then learn to know what and where the grave is which Christ hath made with the Wicked.</P>
<P><HI>J. Horn,</HI> and <HI>T. Moore,</HI> in <HI>Page</HI> 20. saith, <HI>But I shall adde no more, but only desire People to beware of them as a heavy judgement of God, that he hath ordered to us, to punish us for our neglect of Christ, the Salvation of God, and the Truth of him so long abused by us.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here you have made manifest your selves indeed, ye Hypocrites; what have ye been crying out of the <HI>Quakers</HI> calling them deceivers, and warning the people to beware of them, and Writing against them, and judging them to be in delusion and error, when ye your selves neglect Christ the Salvation of God, and have long abused his Truth? (as ye are made to confess) consider your own Conditions, ye are in great delusion and error your selves who neglect Christ the Salvation of God, and have long abused his Truth, and ye are not like, neither can ye bring people to Christ the Sal∣vation of God and his Truth, who are neglectors of Christ Gods Salvation and his Truth your selves; Therefore peo∣ple had need take heed and beware of following you, lest ye lead them to neglect Christ the Salvation of God, and to a∣buse his Truth more and more; you are the Hypocrites that are not to judge, whose beam is yet in your own eyes, for wherein ye judge others for error and delusion, ye condemn your selves, ye being such (as ye confess) that neglect Christ the Salvation of God, and abuse his Truth, and if we be (as ye say) a Judgment ordered of God to punish you for your neglect of Christ the Salvation of God, and the
<PB N="23" REF="14"/>
Truth of him so long abused by you, Why do you not then bear the Judgment of God more patiently, seeing ye have sinned so against him in abusing his Truth, and in neglecting Christ the Salvation of God? Why do you rage so against Gods Judgment? Here all People may see, That ye are not satisfied nor content with what God hath ordered unto you for your neglect of Christ the Salvation of God, and the Truth of him so long abused by you; but we shall yet be a heavier Judgment upon you, for we are a burthensome-Stone to all the ungodly, and the more ye strive against us, the greater will be your Torment; therefore give over your Teaching of others, and be ashamed of your blindness and wickedness and repent, and cease striving and raging against the Truth of God, and us his People; for the more ye strive against us (and the Truth which we live in, and are Wit∣nesses of, which Truth is Christ, who also is in us, which is the Riches of the Mysterie which hath been hid from Ages and Generations, but is now revealed in the Saints by the light) Mark, the greater will be your Judgment and bur∣then; and this ye shall witness to be true: so abuse Gods Truth no longer, neither neglect Christ the Salvation of God as ye have done, but submit to Gods Judgment, and learn to prize Christ the Salvation of God and his Truth, and believe therein, and fight no longer against the Lord and his Truth and Servants, lest he shorten your dayes and cut you off: So remember you are warned, whether you will hear or forbear.</P>
<P>John Horn <HI>and</HI> Thomas Moore, <HI>And indeed the cause of then prevalency is, partly in the Teachers, and partly in the people.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> The cause of our prevailing is not in man, but in God, even the mighty powerful prefence of the Lord which doth accompany us, whereby we reach the faithful Witness of God in people, which answereth to the Truth of God de∣clared by us, and thereby many are turned from darknesse to light, and from Satans power unto God, and we must pre∣vail more and more, for the Lord is opening peoples eyes, and he will teach them himself, and many people begins to see the deceipt and wickedness of such Teachers as ye are
<PB N="24" REF="15"/>
who abuse Gods Truth, and neglect Christ the Salvation of God; and although you have a form of godliness (and have stoln many true words) yet many people sees you to be out of the power, (and fighters against it, and them that be in it) and so they will turn away from you; and all that sets themselves against us shall fall before us, for the Lord is with us and takes our part.</P>
<P>See <HI>J. Horn</HI>'s Testimony against his Brethren the Priests.</P>
<P><HI>John Horn, Thomas Moore,</HI> pag. 20, 21. <HI>Too many of the Teachers are such as</HI> Isaiah <HI>speakes of,</HI> Isa. 56. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, 11, 12. <HI>his Watchmen (which should watch for the good of men) are too generally blind, the Vision of all the Preaching of the Cross of Christ is a sealed Book to them, they are ignorant, they are dumb Dogs that cannot bark, (to give warning of these Beasts, or to set themselves to discover and detect them) sleeping in their security, and lying down loving to slum∣ber, to take their ease and peace, and to content themselves with Dreams instead of searching out Truth, and giving it forth to the People; yea, they are Dogs strong to appetite, greedy Dogs, hunting after Livings and Maintenances, more Means, and so never have e∣nough, too many of them Shepherds that cannot understand, they all look to their own way, every one for his gain from his Quarters; that is, are more mindful of the Fleece then the Flock, and many of them given to voluptuousness; Come, and I will fetch Wine, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Many true words have you here uttered against (your Brethren) the Teachers, but if ye be thus divided a∣gainst your selves, surely ye are not like to stand; the hand of the Lord is turned against you who would stir up your Bre∣thren, the Dogs, to bark against us, and to bite and devour the Lambs of Christ, and now ye lay open one anothers na∣kedness; but as for your railing and calling of us <HI>Beasts,</HI> that will come upon your own heads, and your words shall become your burthen. And as for thee <HI>John Horn</HI> especially, thou canst not clear thy self from being one of those Dogs, (which ye say look for their gain from their Quarter) for thou lookest for thy gain from thy Quarter, and art an Hire∣ling, who pleads for (and takes) Tythes; And it is true, That ye (who pretend your selves to be watchmen) are too generally blind and ignorant, and ye have no true vision, for
<PB N="25" REF="15"/>
Night is come upon all the Hireling Teachers, yea the Sun is set upon you all, and so the blind leads the blind, and both falls into the ditch; So poor people may see, how they have given their money (for that which is not bread, and their la∣bour for that which could not satisfie) even to uphold a company of ignorant blind watchmen that could not under∣stand; for the Preaching of the Cross of Christ (which is the power of God) hath been a sealed Book to them, even to uphold such as have contented themselves with Dreams, and have been given to voluptuousness, and have long abused Gods Truth, and neglected Christ the Salvation of God, as ye confess of your selves and others; so ye are witnesses a∣gainst your selves: Ye Idol Shepherds (who have not profit∣ed the people) the Lord is stretching out his hand, to gather and deliver his Sheep out of your mouths, that ye may no longer make a prey upon them, who through your Cove∣tousness and fained words have long made Merchandize of people.</P>
<P>J. Horn, T. Moore, <HI>The Lord help us to search and try our wayes, and to see how much (any of us) have contributed to the overflowing flood of this ungodliness.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> The Lord hath searched and tryed your hearts and wayes, and he hath found you guilty of much ungodliness, and his light hath often made you sensible of it, and judged you for it; and the Lord hath oft called unto you to forsake your ungodliness, though ye have long slighted the Call of the Lord, and hardened your hearts against his reproof; Therefore repent and dread the Lord, and take heed lest that come upon you, that when ye call upon the Lord he will not answer you.</P>
<P>John Horn, Thomas Moore, <HI>Surely some mens Principles that would be counted Orthodox, give, and have given them great ad∣vantage.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Many corrupt Principles do you and your fellow-Teachers hold, which we are made to witness against, (that so the People may see your Deceits, and not be led into your Imaginations any longer) several of yours are made manifest in this <HI>Book,</HI> as about <HI>Christs Body, and Blood, and
<PB N="26" REF="16"/>
Resurrection of the Body, &amp;c.</HI> And after ye have reckoned up many things which ye say those that would be counted Orthodox hold, whereby ye say we get great advantage, ye then proceed as followeth.</P>
<P>John Horn, Thomas Moore; <HI>But besides this, too general Ignorance, Sloth, Covetousness, Pride found in too many Mi∣nisters, gives advantage to them; even like Foxes and Wolves, to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>laim against the vigilent Shepherds too, as if all were but Hire∣lings, and so that the Flock ought rather to betrust themselves with them.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Great is the Ignorance, Sloth, Covetousness, and Pride which is generally found indeed in you who are cal∣led Ministers, which in the power of the Lord we are oft moved to declare against; but we do not take Advantage thereby, (as ye Lyingly and Railingly accuse us) to declaim against the vigilent Shepherds, as if all were but Hirelings; for we put a great difference betwixt the Proud, Covetous, Slothful Hirelings, and the vigilent Shepherds; for we own the vigilent Shepherds, whom the Holy Spirit hath made O∣verseers over the Flock of God, and have true Unity with them, and we know that they are not Hirelings, for they have freely Received, and they freely Give; and covet no mans Silver, Gold nor Apparrel, but seeks the People, and not theirs; for having Food and Raiment, they are there∣withal content, and receives it of them also that do receive them and imbrace the Truth; and we labour to bring Peo∣ple unto Christ the power of God, that People may be∣trust themselves with him, who is the good Shepherd, and Bishop of the Soul.</P>
<P>John Horn, Thomas Moore; <HI>But it is good for People to mind first, That all are not Hirelings that take Hire, witness</HI> Zach. 11. 12. 2 Cor. 11. 8. <HI>Secondly, That it is safer for the Sheep to a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ide with their Hirelings, if their Shepherds be such, then to l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ave them, and go to Foxes and Wolves; Christ faults the Hir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lings for leaving the Sheep to the Wolves, but never wills his Sheep to leave Hirelings if they will feed them in the Pa∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ures of</HI> Israel.</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here the people may see your exceeding ignorance
<PB N="27" REF="16"/>
and blindnesse in your pleading for taking hire, who say that all are not Hirelings that take hire, and for your wit∣nesse and proof, you have brought that Scripture in <HI>Zach.</HI> which although the Prophet spoke those words, yet it is evi∣dent that he spoke them by way of prophecy concerning <HI>Judas</HI> (who afterwards should ask a price for Christ and fell him, which prophesie came to passe; for <HI>Judas</HI> said to the Jews who sought to take Christ, <HI>what will you give me, and I will deliver him unto you?</HI> and they covenanted with him for thirty pieces of silver; so it appears by your words that you would perswade the people that <HI>Judas</HI> was no Hireling; for it is evident that that which ye bring for your witness, was spoken concerning <HI>Judas,</HI> who asked for the price or hire, and received it; so <HI>Judas</HI> is your witnesse and example for asking and taking of hire (and not Christ) <HI>Mat.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>6. 15. so the people may mind this, (mark) that it was <HI>Judas</HI> the betray∣er of Christ, that asked for the hire and covenanted for it, and those that rejected Christ and were chief actors in the murthering of him, they gave the hire; and then was fulfil∣led that which was spoken by the Prophet, read <HI>Mat.</HI> 27. and what the Apostle took of the Churches (for his relief) which received the truth, amongst whom he sometimes la∣boured, that will not prove that it is lawful for the Priests to take Tithes and Hire of all sorts of people that have Land in Parishes whither the people own them or not, as it is evident that the Priests do; And the Hirelings and all devouring Beasts are in one Nature, and it is not safer for the Sheep (as ye have falsely said) to abide with the one then the other, for neither of them cares for the Sheep no further then to make a prey upon them, and all such we bear a Testimony against, being redeemed out of their Nature; and it is the will of Christ that his sheep should leave the hirelings (for they care not for the Sheep) and that they should follow him and hear his voice, and Christs sheep do so, they hear Christs voice who have called them from the Hirelings and Stran∣gers, and their voices they will not regard; And such as Christ sends to feed his Sheep in the Pastors of Israel, they are no Hirelings (as ye foolishly imagine) but they have free∣ly
<PB N="28" REF="17"/>
received, and they freely give, and such are not greedy of filthy lucre, neither do they rèceive Tithes by a corrupt unjust Law made by Apostates (as thou <HI>John Horn</HI> dost) but they do what they do of a willing and a ready mind, and are not hired to it for a certain sum, but such if they have not of their own, may and do receive Food and Rayment of such as receive them and their Testimony; and this is according to the Apostles Doctrine, and is owned and pra∣ctised amongst us the Servants of the Lord (called <HI>Quakers)</HI> whom ye in your rayling, lying accusations liken unto Foxes and Wolves, but your words shall become your own burthen, and with the Spirit of the Lord we see you in the de∣vouring beastly Nature which the Lord is against, and will rent.</P>
<P>J. Horn T. Moor, <HI>the people are too generally guilty too, and lay themselves open to these delusions and deluders, because too ge∣nerally they neglect Christ and his Truth, take no pleasure therein, but rather in slothfulnesse, formality, covetousnesse pride and va∣nity in apparel, and in many other things, by which means they are in danger to perish, whether they keep out of these mens snares or falls into them; howbeit they are exposed to their snares thereby, be∣cause they afford the deceivers matter to work upon, can find many faults in them, many things to accuse them of, though some things that God never charged them with before these men came &amp; set them∣selves Masters; but in many things really evil, they have too great ad∣vantage, and mens consciences by the effect of the law in them (which is not Christ) bearing witnesse that they say true in those things that they fault them in.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Here it is manifest by your own words, that ye are the false Prophets that have not profited the people, that notwithstanding all your Preachings, the people still neglect Christ and his Truth, and take no pleasure therein, but ra∣ther in slothfulness, formality, covetousnesse, pride and vanity in apparel, and in many other things, and are in dan∣ger to perish whether they come after us or not as ye confess; so it is clear to all that have any understanding, that ye have not stood in the Counsel of God, for if you had, then you should have turned the people (that had received your
<PB N="29" REF="17"/>
Doctrine) from the evil of their way, and from the evil of their doings, <HI>Ier.</HI> 23. but People have long received you and your Doctrine, and yet live in their evil wayes: There∣fore be ashamed and stop your mouths ye Hypocrites, who also speaks against covetousnesse, pride and vanitie in appa∣rel in the People, and of their neglect of Christ and his Truth, when many of you their Teachers are found in covetousnesse, Pride and vanity in apparel, wearing your Cuffs and Ribbands, (and White Boot-hose-tops) and Teaching for Tithes, and Gifts, and Rewards, and most of these in particular thou <HI>Iohn Horn</HI> art guilty of, and in the twentieth page of your Book, ye confesse your selves to be guilty of the neglect of Christ the salvation of God, and the abuse of his truth; so here it is plain, that wherein ye have judged others, ye have condemned your selves, <HI>Rom.</HI> 2. 1. and made it appear that you are like Priests like People, <HI>Hos.</HI> 4. 9. and we whom the Lord have redeemed out of the vani∣ty and wickednesse of this world, do judge you for your wickednesse, and bear our Testimony against it in that which hath redeemed us from it; and although we are counted by you to be deceivers when we judge you for your wickednesse, yet the Lord owns our judging of you, because it is in that which answereth the effect of his Righteous Law in mens consciences, which beareth witnesse that we speak true, as you our enemies are made to confesse; And it was the Ministers of Christ that were manifested to Peoples con∣sciences in the sight of God, and not the deceivers, for the effect of the Law in people where it was witnessed or was, did not nor do not cause their consciences to bear witness to the deceivers Doctrine but against it; so it is manifest that you judge contrary to the effect of the Law who have judged them to be deceivers, whom mens consciences by the effect of the Law in them beareth witnesse unto; And the Law in men (which witnesseth unto the truth and against sin) is light, and it is the Law of the Spirit of Life which is in Christ Jesus, which freeth (those that believe and walk in it) from the power of sin and death, but those that believe not in it, but hate it, it beareth witness against them and their
<PB N="30" REF="18"/>
evil deeds, and remains their condemnation; and it is you that have set your selves masters (and not we) who exercise Lordship one over another, and have mens persons in admi∣ration, and respect mens persons, and calls (and are called of) men Masters, contrary to Christs Doctrine; but we, although we be the Lords free men, yet we are become servants unto many in the truth, Ministring, and labouring for the ga∣thering of the scattered Seed.</P>
<P><HI>John Horn, Thomas Moore, They to get a partie (as the Jesuits do) exposing themselves to some abuses and sufferings from the rude people, make themselves more like Chri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is Ministers to the simple people.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> We indeed suffer much for righteousness sake, and for bearing our testimony against unrighteousness, and you who are Teachers oft causeth our sufferings to be the greater, by your lying and railing against us, thereby stirring up the rude people to abuse us, even as your forefathers the Priests and Pharisees did, who stirred up the rude people against our Master Christ and his servants in former dayes, for which the Lord will assuredly reward you in righteousness; But we will in all things approve our selves as the Ministers of God, in much patience, in affliction, in necessitie, in distresses, in stripes, in imprisonments, in tumults, &amp;c. 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 6 and our lives are not dear unto us, but are freely given up to serve the living God, in spreading his living truth, and it is for no other end, God is our witness, though ye wickedly judge otherwise. And then <HI>John Horn,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moore</HI> goes about to shew the cause why, and how the people are overcome, and led captive by the <HI>Quakers,</HI> and say,</P>
<P>John Horn, Thomas Moore, <HI>Its through their own careles∣ness and formality, or also through their Teachers, they are not so instructed, as to be able to examine and discern them; Through their carelesness, and weakness therethrough in their understand∣ing of the things of God, and conceiting themselves to know and be able to judge and discern of spirits, they neglect the helpfulness, and gifts of brethren, as also the advice of their Teachers and in∣structors
<PB N="31" REF="18"/>
that have the oversight of them, and spoken to them the Word of the Lord.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Oh be ashamed to see what a bad crop is brought forth; what have you been Teachers so long, and taking peoples mony for this, that notwithstanding they have owned you and your Doctrine, and followed you so long that yet they should bring forth no better fruits then these, as carelesness, and formality, and conceitedness, and neglect, and weakness in understanding the things of God? ye have sown but to the fleshly part, and thats the cause you have such a corrupt crop; And now we see your Kingdom is near falling, who are accusing your fellow Teachers for not instructing the people, so as to be able to examine and dis∣cern us, and the people are led captive already who brings forth such bad fruits as these, and had you spoken the Word of the Lord to them, and they had believed it, surely they would have brought forth better fruits; but because you have but stoln from your neighbours much of what you have spoke, and added your own imaginations thereto, and hath run but the Lord hath not sent you, that is the cause you have not profited the people, though you have believed what you have spoke, and have contended much for your Doctrine, yet ye receiving it not from the Lord, it was without life and power, and so was not effectual to the people.</P>
<P>John Horn, Thomas Moore, <HI>Oh that all both Ministers and people would yet be awakened to search and try our wayes, and to make straight steps to our goings.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Yes, ye had need to be awakned indeed; for it is manifest that ye both Teachers and people have been asleep in the night of thick darkness, and you have brought forth night works, neglecting Christ the salvation of God, and abusing his tru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h, taking no pleasure therein, but rather in slothfulness, formality, covetousness, pride and vanity in ap∣parrel, and many other things, and Teachers not instruct∣ing people, so as they might be able to examine and discern such as come unto them; Ye sluggish Shepherds, who are yet to be awakened, what have you taken peoples mony and
<PB N="32" REF="19"/>
goods for all this time, was it for your sleeping and dream∣ing? awake, awake ye sluggards, and own the light of Christ which he hath enlightned you withal, and that will shew you your dreaming, and the deeds of the night, and that will teach you to make straight steps to your goings, and to search and try your wayes.</P>
<P>John Horn, Thomas Moore, <HI>Look to your selves, whosoever transgresseth and abideth not in the Doctrine of Christ hath not God, he that abideth in the Doctrine of Christ, hath both the Fa∣ther and the Son.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> Then it is manifest that you <HI>Thomas Moore,</HI> and <HI>John Horn,</HI> have not God, and out of your own mouths ye shall be Judged; for in the 20. <HI>pag.</HI> of your Book, you speak of the heavy Judgement of God that he hath ordered to you, to punish you for your neglect of Christ the Salvation of God, and the truth of him so long abused by you, now it is plain to any that have any true understanding, that such as neglect Christ the Salvation of God, and abuse his truth, that they transgresse and abide not in the Doctrine of Christ; and this you have confessed your selves to be guilty of, and now your blindness and folly, and confusion, and wicked∣ness is discovered by the spirit and wisdom of God, which abideth in us who abide in the Doctrine of Christ, and have both the Father and the Son.</P>
<P>Many more of your lies and slanders and confusion we could shew you in your Book, but that they are not worth the mentioning; And think not with your selves, that because we reckon not up the rest of your accusations and railing against us, that therefore we consent to them as truth, for we know that the Lord God will judge and punish you for your perverting the truth, and your railing against us, and slandering and belying us called <HI>Quakers</HI> as you have done, both in your Book and in many Papers of <HI>John Hornes</HI> that were posted up against us in <HI>Lin;</HI> and this know that the Lord God of power hath by his mighty power and wisdom armed us to make War against you and to mani∣fest your deceits, who are found to be forgers of lyes and deceivers, and in enmity against the living truth of God;
<PB N="33" REF="19"/>
and the longer you proceed therein against us and the truth witnessed by us, the more will you be confounded, and your folly made manifest, that so the honest hearted will begin to loath you, and you had better have put your mouths in the dust and been silent then to have blasphemed against the truth of God and against his people, as you have done; leave your hypocrisie and deceit wherewith you blind the people, and feed them no longer with your dreams, lyes, and (stoln) dead words, least the Lord cut you off in your iniquity, for a time of withering is already come upon you.</P>
<P>And as for you who are the Hearers of the said <HI>John Horn</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moor,</HI> our Souls pitty you, knowing you are under a vail of thick darkness and bondage, as we can no otherwise conclude, seeing your leaders are tryed, and found so much in ignorance and confusion, and we wish ra∣ther then you would remain under their darkness and de∣ceits, that you would come back to the witness of God, which hath in many of you been often moving, but often hath been quenched through yielding to the sleights and deceits of men, and striving to get more into knowledge then into the life and power; and now you are but feeding death, and seeking the living among the dead, while ye go to them for help, who are out of the power of God, in their own imagi∣nations, wherein they are confounded, and if ever you come to the Fathers House, and there to find the spiritual nourish∣ment, you must first return to the light of the Lord in you, which you have transgressed and grieved, when often it hath appeared against your ungodliness.</P>
<P>And we would not have you think much against us, be∣cause we have here dealt plainly by your Teachers, in disco∣vering them, for we were first occasioned to give forth this, because of their false railing book against us, or else we had not thus appeared in publick against them; and compare this and their book together, and you may soon see (if you read them sincerely) how deservedly we have dealt by them, more then they have by us, for we sent Queries to <HI>John Horn</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moor</HI> in manuscript for them to answer, not ex∣pecting
<PB N="34" REF="20"/>
they would have wronged us, as they have done in Print; And therefore if they in like manner do again pro∣ceed against us in Print, we purpose in the Lord further to have their deceits discovered publickly, that the truth which is professed and dearly owned by us, may be cleared, and its enemies have the fruits of their own doings.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="postscript">
<HEAD>Post-script.</HEAD>
<P>AND seeing that ye (called Moorians) hold forth, <HI>That flesh and blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God,</HI> yet <HI>flesh and bones may;</HI> we ask you these Questions;</P>
<P>If <HI>Elijahs</HI> flesh and bones could enter into Gods Kingdom (when he was taken up) and if his blood could not, then when, and where, and how, and by whom was his blood taken and separated from his flesh and bones? And what is become of his blood?</P>
<P>And what is it that hinders the blood, that it may not enter into Gods Kingdom as well as the flesh and bones, which ye say may? Is the transgression of the blood greater then the transgression of the flesh and bones? And shall the flesh and bones be redee∣med and delivered from corruption, and shall not the blood? What is the Cause? For although the Lord doth what he please, yet, doth he do any thing without a Cause?</P>
<P><PB N="35" REF="20"/>
And whether do you own that Doctrine, that when Christ appeared amongst the Disciples after his Resurrection (when the doors were shut, <HI>John</HI> 20. 19.) that then his body being spiritualized, it glided in at the key-hole of the door? Which doctrine <HI>Thomas Moor</HI> sen. hath formerly preached, as some hath affirmed who heard him.</P>
<P>And where do the Scriptures say, That flesh and bones may in herit the Kingdom of God?</P>
<P>And where you <HI>John Horn</HI> and <HI>Thomas Moor</HI> in page 16. say, That Sathan doubtless may reprove of some sins, and press to some duties; Now have you not here shewn your selves to be Ministers of Sathan, and not of Christ? And we ask you what duties (or a∣ny things that are duties) doth Sathan press men to? Answer directly, or let shame cover you, which at length will come upon you for your deceits.</P>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="21" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="21" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="22"/>
<PB REF="22" MS="y"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

