<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Poor Robin's true character of a scold, or, The shrews looking-glass dedicated to all domineering dames, wives rampant, cuckolds couohant, and hen-peckt sneaks, in city or country.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Poor Robin.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A66710</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing W3077</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R11577</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12930252</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12930252</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">95637</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A66710)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95637)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 993:6)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Poor Robin's true character of a scold, or, The shrews looking-glass dedicated to all domineering dames, wives rampant, cuckolds couohant, and hen-peckt sneaks, in city or country.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Poor Robin.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Winstanley, William, 1628?-1698.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>8 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for L.C.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1678.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>William Winstanley is usually credited with authorship of the "Poor Robin" pamphlets, although imitators undoubtedly wrote some of them.  Cf. NUC pre-1956.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Women --  Anecdotes</TERM><TERM>Scolds --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A66710">
<STC T="W">W3077</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12930252</BIBNO>
<VID>95637</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Poor Robin's
TRUE
CHARACTER
OF A
SCOLD:
OR, THE
SHREWS Looking-glass. DEDICATED
To all
<LIST>
<ITEM>DOMINEERING DAMES,</ITEM>
<ITEM>WIVES RAMPANT,</ITEM>
<ITEM>CUCKOLDS COUCHANT, and</ITEM>
<ITEM>HEN-PECKT SNEAKS,</ITEM>
</LIST> In City or Country. With Allowance.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI> Printed for <HI>L. C.</HI> 1678.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Poor Robin's
True Character of a SCOLD.</HEAD>
<P>A Rank SCOLD is a Devil of the
Feminine gender; a <HI>Serpent,</HI> per∣petually
hissing, and spitting of Ve∣nom;
a Composition of <HI>Ill-nature</HI>
and <HI>Clamour.</HI> You may call her a∣nimated
<HI>Gun-powder,</HI> a walking Mount <HI>Aetna</HI> that
is always belching forth flames of Sulphur, or a
Real <HI>Purgatory,</HI> more to be dreaded in this world,
than the Popes Imaginary <HI>Hot-house</HI> in the next.
A <HI>Burr</HI> about the Moon, is not half so certain a
Presage of a <HI>Tempest</HI> at Sea, as her <HI>Brow</HI> is of a
Storm on Land. And though <HI>Laurel, Haw-thorn,</HI>
and <HI>Seal-skin</HI> are held Preservatives against <HI>Thun∣der,</HI>
Magick has not yet been able to finde any
<HI>Amulet</HI> so Sovereign as to still her Ravings: for,
like Oyl pour'd on Flames, Good words do but
make her Rage the faster; and when once her
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
Flag of Defiance, the Tippet, is unfurl'd, she
cares not a straw for Constable nor Cucking-stool.</P>
<P>Her Tongue is the <HI>Clapper</HI> of the Devil's
<HI>Saints-bell,</HI> that rings <HI>all-in</HI> to Confusion: It runs
round-like a Wheel, one spoak after another, and
makes more <HI>Noise and Jangling,</HI> than Country-Steeples
on the Fifth of <HI>November.</HI> She is never
less at <HI>ease,</HI> than when she is <HI>quiet;</HI> never <HI>quiet,</HI> but
when she is <HI>sleeping;</HI> nor then neither: for either
she <HI>talks</HI> in her Dream, or awakes the whole house
with a terrible fit of <HI>Snoring.</HI> She makes such a
Pattering with her Lips when she walks the streets,
as if she were <HI>possest;</HI> so indeed she is, with
the <HI>spirit of Contention.</HI> The <HI>Dog-days,</HI> with
her, continue all the year round; nor can she
possibly take <HI>Cold</HI>: for she is ever <HI>in an Heat,</HI>
and holds neither <HI>Pox</HI> nor <HI>Plague</HI> so grievous a
Disease, as being <HI>Tongue-ty'd.</HI></P>
<P>She makes an Ass of <HI>Aristotle,</HI> and demonstrates,
That though every <HI>man</HI> be, yet many a <HI>woman</HI>
is not, <HI>A sociable Creature:</HI> for there is no Good
humour can charm her to be Civil or Agreeable;
no Company, how affable or compaisant soever,
that can long content her. She seeks occasions
for Railing, as eagerly as a Common Barretor does
to go to Law. If you will not anger her, she
will be angry with you for thus neglecting her:
and you cannot vex her worse, than to be silent,
unless you sing or whistle at her Folly. She in∣terprets
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
all she hears in the worst sense, and sup∣plies
the defect of real Affronts with jealous <HI>sus∣pitions.</HI>
She is more <HI>captious,</HI> than <HI>capable</HI> of
Offence; and all her Neighbours bless themselves
from her, wishing this <HI>Quotidian Feaver</HI> of her
Tongue cur'd with a Razor. Yet is not that her
onely weapon; for she has Hands to Clap with,
and Nails to Scratch with, and Teeth to Bite
with, and much more Furniture for War; so that
being lookt upon as Invincible, her bad humour
gets her a <HI>Priviledge:</HI> for where-ever she comes,
she may be sure to have the <HI>Room</HI> to her self; nor
needs long Contest for priority of <HI>Walk,</HI> or pre∣cedency
at <HI>Table,</HI> or opinion in Argument: for
the <HI>proudest Gossip</HI> will quit Pretensions, rather
than stand the <HI>shock</HI> of her well-known <HI>Rhe∣torick.</HI></P>
<P>If she be of the preciser Cast, she abuses <HI>Sa∣cred
Language</HI> in her Railing, as Conjurers do in
their Charms; calls her Neighbours <HI>Heathen E∣domites,</HI>
her Husband, <HI>Reprobate,</HI> or <HI>Son of Belial,</HI>
and will not <HI>cudgel</HI> her Maid without a Text
for't. But now I speak of Husband, methinks I
see the <HI>creeping snail</HI> shivering in an Ague fit
when he comes in her presence. She is worse
than Cow-itch in his Bed, and as good as a Cha∣fing-dish
at Board: but has either quite <HI>forgot</HI>
his <HI>Name,</HI> or else she <HI>likes</HI> it not; which makes
her <HI>Rebaptize</HI> him with more noble Titles, as
<HI>White-liver'd Raskal, Drunken Sot, Sneaking
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
Ninkompoop,</HI> or <HI>pitiful lowsy Tom Farthing,</HI> Thus
she worries him out of his senses at home, and
then ferrets his Haunts abroad worse than a needy
Bawd does a decay'd Bully's. Taverns and Ale-houses
dread her single Alarm, more than the
joynt Attaques of the Constable and Watch; and
his Companions are content to pay his Club and
dismiss him, on news of her approach, rather
than be at the charge of so many Glasses and
Bottles as she will quickly salute his Coxcomb
with. A full Glass seasonably offered, may some∣times
pacifie her for a moment; but immediately
the Ill spirit returns, and she can be quiet onely
just so long as she is drinking. Thus she clamours
at him so long without occasion, that at last he
gives her enough; and rails at him for keeping
Ill Company, till she forces him to it; being a∣sham'd
to go into any Good Society, or they a∣sham'd
of him; which makes him seek blinde
Bubbing-schools to hide himself in from her fury,
and resolve to stay out all Night, rather than en∣dure
a double Rally.</P>
<P>In a word, (for I perceive our Character begins
to be infected with the contagious Talkativeness
of its subject) a <HI>virulent Scold</HI> is her Neighbours
perpetual Disquiet, her Families Evil Genius, her
Husbands Ruine, and her own dayly Tormentor:
And that you may the better know her Pedigree,
I'll give you a serious Account of the Receipt or
Method made use of for her Production into the
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
world, lately found in a long-concealed Manuscript
of <HI>Theophrastus Bombastus Paracelsus,</HI> as follows:
<HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P>That Nature long since finding many of her
Sons oft-times bewitcht to their own Ruine by
the Charms of Women, for their punishment con∣triv'd
this Monster call'd <HI>A Scold:</HI> To form which,</P>
<P>She first took of the Tongues and Galls of Bulls,
Bears, Wolves, Magpies, Parrets, Cuckows, and
Nightingales, of each a like number: The Tongues
and Tails of Vipers, Adders, Snakes and Lizards,
Seven apiece: Aurum Fulminans, Aqua Fortis
and Gun-powder, of each one pound: The Clap∣pers
of Nineteen Bells, and the Pestles of a dozen
Apothecaries Mortars. Which being all mixt, she
calcin'd in Mount <HI>Strombelo,</HI> and dissolv'd the
Ashes in a water distill'd just under <HI>London</HI>-bridge
at three quarters Flood, and filtrated it through
the leaves of <HI>Calepines</HI> Dictionary, to render the
Operation more verbal. After which, she distill'd
it again through a Speaking-Trumpet, and closed
up the remaining Spirits in the mouth of a Cannon.
Then she open'd the Graves of all new-deceased
Pettifoggers, Mountebanks, Barbers, Coffee-news-mongers,
and Fish-wives; and with the skin of
their Tongues, made a Bladder cover'd o're with
Drum-heads, and fill'd with Storms, Tempests,
Whirlwinds, Thunders, Lightnings, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> These,
for better Incorporation, she set seven years in a
rough Sea to ferment, and then mixing them with
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
the rest, rectified the whole three times a day for
a Twelve month in a Balneo of Quick-silver.
Lastly, to irrabiate the whole Elixir, and make it
more Churlish, she cut a vein under the Tongue
of the Dog-star, drawing thence a pound of the
most Cholerick blood; from which sublimating
the Spirits, she mixt them with the Foam of a
mad Dog: and then putting all together in the
forementioned Bladder, stitcht it up with the
Nerves of <HI>Socrates</HI>'s Wife.</P>
<P>Out of this noble Preparation, and a <HI>Crooked
Rib</HI> (Emblem of future Crosness) Dame Nature
first composed a SHREW, whose Posterity
(as is frequent with noxious Animals) has since
so over-spread the world, that scarce an <HI>Alley</HI> or
<HI>Village</HI> is free from some of her Lineage.</P>
<P>But that you may see her End as well as Be∣ginning,
be pleased to peruse this</P>
<LG>
<HEAD>EPITAPH.</HEAD>
<L>After some Threescore years of Catterwauling,</L>
<L>Here lies <HI>A SCOLD,</HI> stopt from above-ground
Bawling.</L>
<L>Though Ill she liv'd, I dare not read her Doom;</L>
<L>But fure, go where she will, she's Troublesome.</L>
<L>I wish her, in Revenge, amongst he Blest:</L>
<L>For she'd as lief be Damn'd, as be at Rest.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

