<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Poor Robins perambulation from Saffron-Walden to London performed this month of July, 1678.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Poor Robin.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A66709</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing W3076</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R26388</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">09448162</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 09448162</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">43135</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A66709)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43135)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1321:4)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Poor Robins perambulation from Saffron-Walden to London performed this month of July, 1678.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Poor Robin.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Winstanley, William, 1628?-1698.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>22 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by T.E. and are to be sold by the General Assemby of Hawkers,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1678.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>In verse.</NOTE><NOTE>"With allowance, July 11, 1678, Ro. L'Estrange."</NOTE><NOTE>William Winstanley is usually credited with authorship of the Poor Robin pamphlets--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Hotels --  England --  Poetry.</TERM><TERM>Bars (Drinking establishments) --  England --  Poetry.</TERM><TERM>Taverns (Inns) --  England --  Poetry.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Taryn Hakala</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A66709">
<STC T="W">w3076</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">09448162</BIBNO>
<VID>43135</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>Poor Robins PERAMBULATION FROM Saffron-Walden TO LONDON: Performed this Month of <HI>JƲLY,</HI> 1678.</P>
<P>With Allowance, July <HI>11. 1678.</HI> Ro. L'Estrange.</P>
<P>LONDON: Printed for <HI>T.E.</HI> and are to be Sold by the General Assembly of Hawkers, 1678.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="perambulation">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>Poor ROBIN'S <HI>Perambulation from</HI> Saffron-Walden <HI>to</HI> London, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="poetic part">
<LG>
<L>NOw have amongst you Gallants, here's a story</L>
<L>Will make you laugh, or else I should be sorry:</L>
<L>'Tis of a Journey lately made from <HI>Walden</HI></L>
<L>To <HI>London,</HI> and of several places call'd in</L>
<L>As by the way I travel'd, with their Rarities</L>
<L>Of Vice and Virtue, and their great disparities.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>'Twas in the year of Grace call'd Sixteen hundred</L>
<L>Seventy and seven, as our account is numbred,</L>
<L>The Eve o'th' <HI>Scottish</HI> Champion St. <HI>Andrew,</HI></L>
<L>Who wore as good a sword as e're man drew,</L>
<L>Being the twenty-ninth day of <HI>November,</HI></L>
<L>Called St. <HI>Saturnine</HI> as I remember,</L>
<L>The very next day when the <HI>Term</HI> was ended,</L>
<L>Wherein much (ah too much) Coin is expended,</L>
<L>The sign was in <HI>Aquarius,</HI> or the Legs,</L>
<L>Being <HI>Wednesday,</HI> a day for <HI>Fish</HI> and <HI>Eggs.</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Moon</HI> full four days old, the wind was <HI>North,</HI></L>
<L>When I on this mad Journey did set forth.</L>
<L>As for the <HI>Tide</HI> I will not mention here,</L>
<L>For we have neither <HI>Sea</HI> nor <HI>Thames</HI> us near,</L>
<L>And therefore of their <HI>Ebbs,</HI> or of their <HI>flowing,</HI></L>
<L>Very few persons thereabouts are knowing.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus having shown you when, in the next place</L>
<L>I'le show you whence my Journey I did trace:</L>
<L>'Twas from the <HI>Rose and Crown,</HI> where Mr. <HI>Eve</HI></L>
<L>Doth keep a House like to an Under-sheriff;</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="3"/>There is good Sack, good <HI>French</HI>-Wine, and good Beer.</L>
<L>And if you'l dine or sup, there is good cheer:</L>
<L>Or does your stomack to a Breakfast stand,</L>
<L>There's cold roast Beef, or Pork at your command.</L>
<L>For those men who the truth of this deny it,</L>
<L>Let them go there, and do as I did, try it;</L>
<L>There for your money you shall have kind usage,</L>
<L>Good words, and reckonings right, without abusage.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There at my parting, some kind friends of mine</L>
<L>Would needs bestow on me a quart of Wine,</L>
<L>Where with stout drinking e're my parting hour,</L>
<L>That Quart was made at least a three or four;</L>
<L>But <HI>Sol</HI> his speedy journey would not stay,</L>
<L>And posting-time did call me thence away:</L>
<L>Yet would my Jovial friends on me attend</L>
<L>Part of my Journey unto <HI>Audley-end,</HI></L>
<L>By them call'd <HI>Nineveh,</HI> but no great City,</L>
<L>Though too much sin may be there, more's the pity</L>
<L>There at the sign (of such a thing I think</L>
<L>As never swam on pond or rivers brink)</L>
<L>Of a <HI>Black Swan,</HI> which is as rare 'tis said</L>
<L>As of a wench with child to be a maid.</L>
<L>Yet although of this Sign there's no such thing,</L>
<L>It was a sign there was good drink within,</L>
<L>And that we found fresh, sprightly, and well tasted;</L>
<L>With drinking which, we a long hour wasted.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But friends at last must part, though loth they be.</L>
<L>And so with much leave-taking then did we,</L>
<L>When, 'cause bad company should be withstood,</L>
<L>I walkt alone, and so had none but good.</L>
<L>The first Town I came to, was <HI>Wenden</HI> nam'd,</L>
<L>Who hate <HI>Eighth Henry,</HI> though a King much sam'd;</L>
<L>The reason of the same, they understand</L>
<L>He was the first man ever wore a <HI>Band,</HI></L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="3" MS="y"/>And that's a fashion to which they'l not come,</L>
<L>As being chargeable and troublesome,</L>
<L>Therefore without Bands commonly they go,</L>
<L>By which sign you a <HI>Wenden</HI>-man may know.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>From <HI>Wenden</HI> I my course did next way bend</L>
<L>Unto the place is called <HI>Sparrows-end,</HI></L>
<L>Where Mr. <HI>Harris</HI> my old friend the Tanner</L>
<L>Did entertain me in most courteous manner,</L>
<L>And having drunk such strong drink as we found,</L>
<L>With which his House doth commonly abound,</L>
<L>To <HI>Newport-pond</HI> my course I next way bent,</L>
<L>And in at the sign of the <HI>Black-Bull</HI> went,</L>
<L>Where scarcely in a room I had set down</L>
<L>When in came my old friends kind Mr. <HI>Br</HI>—</L>
<L>And Mr. <HI>Woo</HI>—two who love their friend</L>
<L>With true and hearty love unto the end;</L>
<L>For though they in another Town do live,</L>
<L>They to their Neighbour some kind Visits give.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>'Twas twelve a Clock, Dinner-time did approach,</L>
<L>When men whet Knives on Wheels of Cart or Coach;</L>
<L>The Cloth was laid, and by the scent o'th' meat</L>
<L>One might perceive there something was to eat,</L>
<L>And so it prov'd indeed, for from the pot</L>
<L>Came forth a Rump of Beef was piping hot;</L>
<L>And from the Spit was brought a loyn of Mutton</L>
<L>Would satisfie the stomack of a Glutton;</L>
<L>For like a Loyn of Beef it might been knighted;</L>
<L>To which our Hostess kindly us invited,</L>
<L>Which we accepted of; and to delight her,</L>
<L>Told her none could deny such an inviter:</L>
<L>For she's a Widow of such excellent carriage,</L>
<L>Would make a man most happy in her Marriage,</L>
<L>Being young, fresh, fair, of a most pregnant wit,</L>
<L>And for a kind good Husband sure most fit.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="4" REF="4"/>We having din'd, and join'd a pint or two,</L>
<L>Then forwards on my Journey I did go.</L>
<L>And first I came unto a Town called <HI>Rickling,</HI></L>
<L>Where for to stay a while I made no stickling,</L>
<L>But presently in at the <HI>Kings-head</HI> fell,</L>
<L>Where of <HI>Compounding Dick</HI> I there heard tell,</L>
<L>To whom if that it please you to resort ye,</L>
<L>He for a hundred pound will mortgage forty</L>
<L>Shillings a year, nor do you think I jest,</L>
<L>It's very true indeed, <HI>probatum est.</HI></L>
<L>Or lend him lesser sums, which if you do,</L>
<L>For twenty Shillings he will pay you two;</L>
<L>Not two and twenty Shillings, no such plenty,</L>
<L>I mean he'l pay you two Shillings for twenty;</L>
<L>Pray lend him then, and this shall be your portion,</L>
<L>You shall not need fear being su'd for extortion.</L>
<L>From the <HI>Kings-head</HI> I out of doors scarce went,</L>
<L>But was in <HI>Quenden</HI>-street incontinent;</L>
<L>Of many a handsome Country-House the station,</L>
<L>It seems to be a little Corporation,</L>
<L>Yet are the Houses not so neat as strong,</L>
<L>And doth most to one Gentleman belong.</L>
<L>For nothing on it can you look asquint,</L>
<L>Unless cause there is ne're an Ale-house in't.</L>
<L>Good air, brave Woods, and fine rich Meadow-ground,</L>
<L>And doth with every sort of Grain abound.</L>
<L>The young men there do bear the Bell away</L>
<L>From all the Towns about at Foot-ball play.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Unto a Farmers House I went out-right,</L>
<L>Who entertained me like to a Knight:</L>
<L>And though at <HI>Newport</HI> I had din'd before,</L>
<L>Yet here with him I must eat one bit more,</L>
<L>Some Ribs of Pork new kill'd, broil'd on a Gridiron</L>
<L>Of seven ribs, three on each side, and one mid-iron.</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4" MS="y"/>But ere they laid them on, they did them Salt,</L>
<L>A Shooing-horn to draw down juice of Malt;</L>
<L>Yet thus much of his Beer's strength I do know,</L>
<L>'Twould well go down without helps thereunto;</L>
<L>And who thereof to drink too much on't ventures,</L>
<L>'Twill turn him Scrivener for to make Indentures;</L>
<L>Which made me have a care of that same drink,</L>
<L>Because some Scriveners are K—s I think,</L>
<L>But whether so or no I'le leave to Pen,</L>
<L>They may be Knaves or may be honest men:</L>
<L>But to the matter, ere that we did part</L>
<L>I of his liquor took down many a quart;</L>
<L>Then fear lest I should of a Fox-skin smell,</L>
<L>I bid to him (as he made me) farewell.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>From <HI>Quenden</HI> I my ready course did frame</L>
<L>Thorow a Town that hath an <HI>Ʋgly</HI> name,</L>
<L>Indeed to call it so they did not well,</L>
<L>Because that handsom Women in it dwell;</L>
<L>Nor are the Men for ought that I can find</L>
<L>But good condition'd, debonair, and kind:</L>
<L>And therefore he who ere the name it gave,</L>
<L>To call it so was but an ugly K—.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>From <HI>Ʋgly</HI> I next way to <HI>Stansted</HI> travel'd,</L>
<L>Upon a plain High-way well ston'd and gravel'd;</L>
<L>This Town of <HI>Stansted</HI> for distinctions sake</L>
<L>Doth unto it the name <HI>Montfitchet</HI> take,</L>
<L>From the <HI>Montfitchets</HI> once Lords of great fame,</L>
<L>And who ere while were owners of the same.</L>
<L>There at the <HI>Bell,</HI> at my old friend's <HI>George Perrin,</HI></L>
<L>We drunk and tipled like unto a Herring;</L>
<L>For there is Ale and Stale-beer strong and mighty,</L>
<L>Will burn ith' fire like unto <HI>Aqua-vitae</HI>;</L>
<L>And that the reason is, as you may know,</L>
<L>That this <HI>Bells</HI> Liquor makes Mens <HI>Clappers</HI> go:</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="5"/>Then when mens brains begin for to grow addle,</L>
<L>Some talk of riding ne'r sat on a Saddle,</L>
<L>And every one doth think himself a Prince,</L>
<L>Though he in's Pocket scarce hath Thirteen-pence.</L>
<L>This Town from <HI>Walden</HI> is eight miles they say,</L>
<L>All which long space I travel'd in one day,</L>
<L>But wearied sore, and having drunken deep,</L>
<L>The leaden god then summon'd me to sleep;</L>
<L>So that for to repose my drowzy head,</L>
<L>It was not long before I went to bed;</L>
<L>And though I did not go out of my way,</L>
<L>Yet I that very night in <HI>Holland</HI> lay.</L>
<L>Next morn, ere <HI>Titan</HI> shew'd his glorious head,</L>
<L>My Host did rouze me from my drowzy bed;</L>
<L>And for so doing this was his pretence,</L>
<L>To pay a Groat for my last nights offence,</L>
<L>Which I soon gave unto the jovial Croney,</L>
<L>For being so ore-reached by <HI>Vulpone</HI>;</L>
<L>And being up, we briskly did it spend,</L>
<L>And so of the <HI>round</HI> Groat made a <HI>square</HI> end.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus arm'd with Toast and Ale, my Muse and I,</L>
<L>Having no other in our company,</L>
<L>Footed it on the Road, and straightway came</L>
<L>Unto a Town <HI>Birchanger</HI> call'd by name,</L>
<L>Of which there is a Proverb very old,</L>
<L>From one Age still unto another told</L>
<L>That there they christen Calves, which by mens bounty</L>
<L>It may extend to each Town in the County;</L>
<L>Because the plenty of the Veal from thence,</L>
<L>To call them <HI>Essex Calves</HI> is a pretence.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thorow <HI>Birchanger</HI> I pass'd without drinking,</L>
<L>The reason thereof you perhaps are thinking;</L>
<L>Yet don't believe herein that I do scoff-ye,</L>
<L>They there sell neither Ale, Wine, Beer, nor Coffee;</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="5" MS="y"/>Therefore unless without Town they be sped,</L>
<L>They very soberly may go to Bed:</L>
<L>But though such liquors are not sold among them,</L>
<L>Because that I would willingly not wrong them,</L>
<L>Strong drink in private Houses there may be,</L>
<L>Of which the owners may be frank and free;</L>
<L>But whether that the same be so or no,</L>
<L>To tell to you the truth, I do not know,</L>
<L>Therefore it to avouch I were to blame,</L>
<L>Unless that I had tasted of the same.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus something dry within, yet ne'retheless</L>
<L>In a good plight, my way I next address</L>
<L>Unto a place call'd <HI>Hockrell,</HI> and there took</L>
<L>In at the <HI>Crown,</HI> with honest Mr. <HI>Cook</HI>;</L>
<L>Now here I did no entertainment lack,</L>
<L>With <HI>French</HI>-Wine, <HI>Rhenish,</HI> and good <HI>Spanish</HI> Sack;</L>
<L>And being Dinner-time I fill'd my gullet,</L>
<L>Begun with powder'd Beef, ended with Pullet;</L>
<L>And after Dinner we to drinking fixt,</L>
<L>With taking of Tobacco intermixt.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Minding that Town my Journeys end should be</L>
<L>For that same night, I was resolv'd to see</L>
<L>The rarities of the same, which to disclose</L>
<L>A little while I'le turn my Verse to Prose.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="prose part">
<P>This place called <HI>Hockrell</HI> belongeth to <HI>Bishop Storford,</HI> so named from the Bishops of <HI>London,</HI> who once had a Pa∣lace here, being an ancient Castle given by <HI>William</HI> the <HI>Conquerour</HI> unto the Bishop <HI>Mauritius,</HI> with all the appur∣tenances belonging thereunto for ever; the Ruins of which Castle remain to this day. On the upper side of the Town stands a fair Church, in which lie Interred many of the <HI>Flemings,</HI> a Family whose numerous branches have spread themselves thorough <HI>England, Scotland</HI> and <HI>Wales,</HI> ever
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>
since the time of Sir <HI>John le Fleming,</HI> Knight, who flourish∣ed in the Reign of King <HI>William Rufus.</HI> Their Market (which is kept on on Thursdays) is very well served with all sorts of Provisions for the sustentation of life, especially <HI>Barley</HI> and <HI>Malt,</HI> which makes our English <HI>Bachanialian</HI> juice; the operations of which liquor take from the Poet:
<Q><L>Whilst Pearls and Rubies doth strong drink disclose▪</L>
<L>They make their purse poor to enrich their nose.</L></Q>
They have three Fairs in the year, one nine days before <HI>Whitsontide,</HI> another nine days after it, and the third on <HI>Michaelmas</HI>-day. This Town is also accommodated with three Taverns, <HI>viz.</HI> the <HI>Crown,</HI> the <HI>Rein-deer,</HI> and the <HI>George,</HI> at either of which, bringing the merry Chink, you may have the merry drink. How many Ale-houses is there, I had not time to number, only I saw the signs of some Horned Beasts, as the <HI>Bull,</HI> the <HI>Ram, &amp;c.</HI> but what the people are that dwell therein, I know not, but guess you may have good liquor there for your money. As for the <HI>Cage</HI> and <HI>Stocks</HI> there, let those who have been in them give you a description of them. And now after this serious view of the Town, I returned to my Quarters, where I had dined, and took up my lodging there that night.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="poetic part">
<LG>
<L>From <HI>Bishop-Storford</HI> I next day set forth</L>
<L>Unto a Town is called <HI>Sabridgworth,</HI></L>
<L>Contracted <HI>Sapssord</HI>; but call't what you will,</L>
<L>In the same place it did, the Town stands still.</L>
<L>Good Corn they say within the same doth grow,</L>
<L>And good Beer may be in't for ought I know;</L>
<L>But at that time I had no list to drink,</L>
<L>So past I thorough it, and sav'd my Chink.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Unto <HI>Pye-corner</HI> went I, to the <HI>Rose,</HI></L>
<L>Where for a time I staid and tope't my nose;</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="6" MS="y"/>There was a jolly <HI>Hostess,</HI> and good tipple,</L>
<L>Would make the tongue run, and the legs a cripple.</L>
<L>But of large drinking, Reader, this know of it,</L>
<L>There is small pleasure in it, and less profit;</L>
<L>'Twill quickly empty all the purse of crosses,</L>
<L>Which will breed discontentment for such losses.</L>
<L>My Hostess without coyn you can't accost her,</L>
<L>Her rule is, <HI>No peny, no Pater-noster</HI>;</L>
<L>She cares not for your company a bean-straw,</L>
<L>You can't come at her back-side with a hand-saw.</L>
<L>But if you have the white and yellow mettle,</L>
<L>She simpers like to a Furmety-kettle.</L>
<L>The servants nimble are, and you may brag on</L>
<L>The credit, not to call twice for a flaggon:</L>
<L>The female servants, lest they should be shent,</L>
<L>Do answer (as they are) <HI>incontinent.</HI></L>
<L>For Claret, Sack, strong Beer you shall not stand Sir,</L>
<L>Both Hostess, men and maids, are at command Sir.</L>
<L>But if the Purse chance to be in the wane,</L>
<L>Then you may call, and call, and call again,</L>
<L>You have free liberty for to be gone Sir,</L>
<L>For <HI>quickly come,</HI> is turn'd <HI>anon, anon Sir.</HI></L>
<L>Therefore kind Reader spend not all away,</L>
<L>But keep a peny 'gainst a rainy day;</L>
<L>Then shall you welcome be where e're you come,</L>
<L>Where otherwise more welcome is your room.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But I've digrest, but hope have not transgrest</L>
<L>In these invective lines I've here exprest;</L>
<L>Yet Reader know, although Inns and Ale-houses</L>
<L>Were not ordain'd for men to drink Carrouses,</L>
<L>Yet are they for the Trav'ller necessary,</L>
<L>Who else his meat and drink must with him carry;</L>
<L>And very oftentimes it would be found</L>
<L>He must his lodging take on the cold ground;</L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="7"/>This also must of them be understood,</L>
<L>That many Hosts and Hostesses are good,</L>
<L>Use people kindly for their drink and diet,</L>
<L>And lodg them softly, where they rest in quiet.</L>
<L>Where we will leave them sleeping in their bed,</L>
<L>To show how after in my way I sped.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Crossing the Fields, I in short space came down</L>
<L>To <HI>Eastwick,</HI> to the sign o'th' <HI>Rose and Crown,</HI></L>
<L>Where for to stay I did not once intend,</L>
<L>But at the Inn-door there I met a friend,</L>
<L>An old acquaintance newly come from <HI>London,</HI></L>
<L>Where women some are done, some men are undone;</L>
<L>To see how resolutions soon may alter,</L>
<L>At sight of him my legs began to falter,</L>
<L>And though before I had no list to drink,</L>
<L>Now other thoughts into my mind did sink;</L>
<L>Methoughts I was as dry as was a bottle</L>
<L>Turn'd upside downward, and without a stopple;</L>
<L>My eyes 'gan view the door, which open stood</L>
<L>To invite all Company in that wou'd;</L>
<L>Seeing an opportunity so fit,</L>
<L>How every thing invited us to it,</L>
<L>My friend and I resolv'd e're we did go,</L>
<L>To enter in and drink a quart or two;</L>
<L>Yet did we think the House not so resplendent,</L>
<L>Because no Bush was to the sign dependent;</L>
<L>But this gave comfort, <HI>What could not be cur'd,</HI></L>
<L><HI>It must be with a patient mind endur'd</HI>;</L>
<L>Because therefore no Wine we could come by,</L>
<L>We were resolv'd Beer should us satisfie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Being in, the first thing that our eyes beheld,</L>
<L>(like to two Soldiers marching in the field)</L>
<L>Came in a Bag-pudding and piece of Beef,</L>
<L>Which unto hungry stomacks gives relief.</L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="7" MS="y"/>By what is writ, Reader, thou maist suppose</L>
<L>(without the smelling, snuffing sence, the Nose)</L>
<L>'Twas Dinner time, when men do meat devour,</L>
<L>Or (as the Quaker saith) 'bout the Twelfth hour,</L>
<L>Our Stomacks were provided for the meat,</L>
<L>Nor did our Host fail for to bid us eat,</L>
<L>Few complements need to be us'd to do it,</L>
<L>For (hungry) we did stoutly fall unto it.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And being thus refresht with wholsom diet,</L>
<L>You'd think our Stomacks should have been at quiet:</L>
<L>But other thoughts did in our mind take place,</L>
<L>And liquor there was wanting in the case;</L>
<L>Our Hostess she was very blithe and handy,</L>
<L>And brought us in a quartern of <HI>Nantz-Brandy,</HI></L>
<L>A Liquor which the <HI>Dutch-men</HI> prize, I think,</L>
<L>More than <HI>Ambrosia</HI> which the gods do drink;</L>
<L>Therefore its fame unto the Heav'ns they raise,</L>
<L>Indeed that Liquor well deserveth praise</L>
<L>Beyond <HI>Metheglin, Ʋsquebah,</HI> or <HI>Perry,</HI></L>
<L>Or nappy <HI>Ale</HI> that makes mens hearts full merry.</L>
<L><HI>Worstershire-Sider,</HI> nor yet <HI>Brunswick-Mum,</HI></L>
<L>In goodness nothing near unto it come.</L>
<L>Your liquorish <HI>Steponey,</HI> or your <HI>Bracket,</HI></L>
<L>For goodness like to <HI>Brandy</HI> they much lack it.</L>
<L><HI>Cardimum, Rosa-solis, Aqua-vitae,</HI></L>
<L>Although that they be very strong and mighty,</L>
<L>They are no more comparable to <HI>Brandy,</HI></L>
<L>Than is a <HI>Gyant</HI> to a <HI>Jack-a-dandy:</HI></L>
<L>Nor yet that Liquor <HI>Fancy</HI> on us thrusts,</L>
<L>Which scalds our mouths, and tasts like to burnt Crusts,</L>
<L>As Black as <HI>Soot,</HI> or as the River <HI>Stix,</HI></L>
<L>Which they with Kennel water (surely) mix,</L>
<L>It comes far short of <HI>Brandy</HI> all will say,</L>
<L>Not to be mention'd with it the same day.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><PB N="12" REF="8"/><HI>Brandy</HI> (according to the drinking Law)</L>
<L>It is both good and wholesom burnt or raw;</L>
<L>Or raw mixed with Sugar, if you do it,</L>
<L>There is no drink comparable unto it;</L>
<L>It clears the Stomach, and it helps digestion,</L>
<L>And is a wholesom Liquor without question.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Now we at this good Liquor there did stay</L>
<L>Till two full hours were wasted of the day;</L>
<L>When time, which every one of truth convinces,</L>
<L>And will not stay one jot, no not for Princes,</L>
<L>Told us that we must part, that too much drinking</L>
<L>Cripled the Legs, and made the wits be shrinking,</L>
<L>Then 'cause we would not be contradictory</L>
<L>To Time, although to part we were right sorry,</L>
<L>We paid the shot, a thing must not be undone,</L>
<L>And parted, he towards <HI>York,</HI> and I towards <HI>London.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>From thence I on my journey forwards fell</L>
<L>Unto a Town nam'd <HI>Stansted-Deal,</HI> or <HI>Dell,</HI></L>
<L>So call'd 'cause it is in a bottom founded,</L>
<L>With <HI>Dells</HI> or watry places most surrounded:</L>
<L>Here runs a River which doth save them charges,</L>
<L>Being capable of bearing Boats and Barges,</L>
<L>By which to <HI>London</HI> they send store of Grain,</L>
<L>And bring thence Coles and other things again.</L>
<L>There is good liquor in that Town they say,</L>
<L>But 'twas near half a mile out of my way:</L>
<L>Wherefore because I would not go about,</L>
<L>I of that nappy liquor went without;</L>
<L>For why, the nearest way to <HI>London</HI> lies</L>
<L>Over a Common-meddow call'd the <HI>Ryes,</HI></L>
<L>Which way I took, and crossed the <HI>New-River,</HI></L>
<L>That unto <HI>London</HI> doth her Streams deliver.</L>
<L>But now some other matters to explain,</L>
<L>A while I'le turn my Verse to Prose again.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="prose part">
<P><PB N="13" REF="8" MS="y"/>As I was thus going over the <HI>Ryes,</HI> there over-took me a Journey-man Shoo-maker, going so fast, as if his business required wonderful hast; however I had that inquisitive∣ness to ask him why he went so fast, and that if he went softlier I should be glad of his company, as being alone: He replied, that he was one of the <HI>Gentle-Craft,</HI> and ha∣ving by the perswasions of <HI>Monsieur Malt-worm</HI> spent all his chink, he must hast to <HI>London</HI> that night, having no Money to accommodate him with a lodging by the way. I laughed heartily at his discourse, and told him he was not to be blamed for being money-less, seeing the same was or∣dained by <HI>Jupiter</HI> before. Those words struck <HI>Crispin</HI> into a great amazement, who would needs know how it came to pass that <HI>Jupiter</HI> should be such an enemy to good fel∣lowship? Marry (said I) I think him to be no enemy unto good fellowship, though it hath happened that he hath predestin'd most of you to be unthrifts, the manner where∣of I will relate unto you.</P>
<P>It happened some Ages before my Grandmother was born, that <HI>Jupiter</HI> and <HI>Mercury</HI> travelled together upon the earth; <HI>Mercury</HI> was wonderfully hungry, and had no Money in his Purse to buy him any food; and at last to his great comfort he spied where a company of Taylors were at dinner with butter'd Pease, eating their Pease with their Needles points one by one: <HI>Mercury</HI> came to them, and asked them his alms; they proudly bid him sit down and do as he saw them did, and with that delivered him a Needle. The poor God being passing hungry, could not content his Maw with eating one by one, but turned the eye of his Needle, and eat two or three together; which the Taylors seeing, they start up, and said, What fellow, a Shovel and Spade to butter'd Pease! hast thou no more manners? Get out of our company: and so they sent him packing with many strokes. <HI>Mercury</HI> coming back, <HI>Ju∣piter</HI>
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
demanded of him what news? And he told him how churlishly he was used by the Taylors. Well, wandering on further, <HI>Mercury</HI> espied where a company of Shoo-makers were at Dinner with powdred Beef and Brewess; going to them, before he could ask them any alms, they said, Welcom good fellow, what is thy Stomack up? Wilt thou do as we do, and taste of our Beef? <HI>Mercury</HI> thanked them, and sat down and eat his Belly-full, and drank well of Double-Beer; and when he had done, went home to his Master; as soon as he came, <HI>Jupiter</HI> asked him what news? And he said, I have lighted amongst a crew of Shoo-makers, the boonest Fellows that ever I met withal, they have frankly fed me without grudging, and therefore grant me a Boon for them. Ask what thou wilt, <HI>Mercury</HI> (quoth he) and it shall be granted. Why then quoth he, grant that for this good turn they have done me, they may ever spend a Groat afore they can earn Twopence; It shall be granted quoth he: <HI>Mercury,</HI> as soon as <HI>Jupiter</HI> had said the word, he bethought himself, and said, Not so, but that they may earn a Groat before they spend Twopence, for my Tongue slipt at first; but <HI>Jupiter</HI> replied, my grant cannot be recalled, your first wish must stand firm. And hence it comes to pass that by <HI>Mercuries</HI> mistake, and <HI>Ju∣piters</HI> grant, that the Journey-men of the Gentle-craft have been ever since such boon blades, and toping good Fellows.</P>
<P><HI>Crispin</HI> heard my Story with much attention, and I per∣ceived that had his Purse been answerable to his heart, we had tasted what liquor had been at the next Ale-house: But as the old song says, <HI>Poverty parts good company</HI>; my Lady <HI>Pecunia</HI> having parted from him, he soon parted from me, and made all the hast he could towards <HI>London.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="poetic part">
<LG>
<L><PB N="15" REF="9" MS="y"/>Passing thus as I told you o're, the <HI>Rye,</HI></L>
<L>Incontinent to <HI>Hodsden</HI> I did hie,</L>
<L>A great th'row-fare, consisting of one street,</L>
<L>But seated in an Air wholesom and sweet;</L>
<L>There is therein of Inns the duce and all,</L>
<L>But Beer in them methought was very small,</L>
<L>I try'd not only one, but two or three,</L>
<L>But Beer in none did with my taste agree;</L>
<L>Indeed there is good Ale at the Thatcht-house,</L>
<L>Which followed will give a man a douce,</L>
<L>And likewise in the Town you there may see</L>
<L>Of Taverns there's no less than two or three,</L>
<L>Wherein with Wine you there may fill your gorges,</L>
<L>But not so good (methinks) as my friend <HI>Georges.</HI></L>
<L>There is a Statue of a Nimph-like charm,</L>
<L>Which always holds a Pitcher in her arm,</L>
<L>Through which she water constant doth deliver,</L>
<L>Which saves the fetching of it from the River;</L>
<L>What other Rarities in this Town be,</L>
<L>Let them who list go thither for to see.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>From thence I went and had a little pull</L>
<L>At <HI>Broksborn,</HI> at the Sign of the <HI>Black-Bull,</HI></L>
<L>Where though there was not high and mighty Liquor,</L>
<L>'Twas stronger than at <HI>Hodsden,</HI> and more quicker;</L>
<L>Quicker in two respects, Pots came more thick,</L>
<L>And then the Beer in drinking was more quick;</L>
<L>But having by such quickness much coyn spent,</L>
<L>I parted thence, and unto <HI>Wormly</HI> went;</L>
<L>There did I stay all night at the <HI>White-Hind,</HI></L>
<L>And found an Host was debonair and kind.</L>
<L>He told me many tricks done in his youth,</L>
<L>Which if so be they all of them were truth,</L>
<L>I must conclude (for so it plain appears)</L>
<L>He was an arch wag in his younger years.</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="10"/>My Hostess she was bonny, tite, and neat,</L>
<L>And full of mirth, as is an Egg of meat.</L>
<L>She bid me kindly welcome, so she may</L>
<L>I think to any one that freely pay;</L>
<L>Yet this I'le say, her Meat was of the best,</L>
<L>Fresh, sweet, and good, and very cleanly drest;</L>
<L>All her discourse was pleasant, sweet as honey,</L>
<L>And I was kindly welcome for my money.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Next morn no sooner <HI>Phoebus</HI> did appear,</L>
<L>And with his beams did gild our Hemisphear,</L>
<L>But I soon shook off <HI>Morpheus</HI> drowzy clog,</L>
<L>First drank, and paid, then forwards on did jog</L>
<L>Unto a Town call'd <HI>Cheshunt,</HI> wheretofore</L>
<L>Was a Religious House of <HI>Nuns</HI> great store;</L>
<L>These <HI>Nuns</HI> were Maids or Virgins, chuse you which,</L>
<L>Or at the leastwise they should have been such,</L>
<L>But same hath told (if same hath not beli'd them)</L>
<L>They no such Cattel were by those that try'd them;</L>
<L>For under ground they had a private Cell</L>
<L>To <HI>Waltham-Abby</HI> where the <HI>Monks</HI> did dwell,</L>
<L>By which conveyance they each other met,</L>
<L>And many Bastards by this means did get;</L>
<L>But whether that the same were true or no,</L>
<L>'Tis only God Almighty that doth know.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This <HI>Cheshunt</HI> Town is three miles long or near,</L>
<L>And scattered with Houses here and there;</L>
<L>Some Alehouses upon the Road I saw,</L>
<L>And some with bushes, shew'ng they Wine did draw,</L>
<L>But whether Beer or Wine were good or bad,</L>
<L>To tast thereof no time as then I had:</L>
<L>For should a man at every Ale-house call,</L>
<L>'Twould empty his Purse, and spoil his brains withal;</L>
<L>And truly unto me it is a wonder</L>
<L>To see how Ale-houses the Road do <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>er,</L>
<L><PB N="17" REF="10" MS="y"/>It does to me much admiration give</L>
<L>To think which ways they make a shift to live!</L>
<L>And yet I think a man may wonder more</L>
<L>That many men about them live so poor!</L>
<L>The Reason is, that what these poor men gain,</L>
<L>The Ale-houses for drink from them do drain;</L>
<L>And so these poor men, to be term'd good fellows,</L>
<L>Do toil and moil for to maintain the Ale-house.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As to this purpose did a Neighbour mine,</L>
<L>Who to maintain the Ale-wives to go fine,</L>
<L>And idly live, whatever that he got</L>
<L>He spent upon them, on the Pipe and Pot;</L>
<L>He following this Trade continually,</L>
<L>Fell grievous sick, as if he straight would die;</L>
<L>Desiring his Wives pity, he to move her,</L>
<L>Told her if that please God he did recover,</L>
<L>And that his help he to him would be giving,</L>
<L>Hee'd make the Ale-wives to spin for their living.</L>
<L>Soon after he recover'd his distemper,</L>
<L>But quickly grew he to be <HI>idem-semper,</HI></L>
<L>The Ale-houses he no ways would refrain,</L>
<L>Which made his wife thus carefully complain,</L>
<L>Husband, you said, if that God sent you health,</L>
<L>You would unto your self return your wealth,</L>
<L>And make the Ale-wives for their living spin,</L>
<L>But now another mind I see you're in.</L>
<L>True Wife (reply'd the man) I were to blame</L>
<L>Should I deny't, and still my mind's the same:</L>
<L>But first they must have Money wherewithall</L>
<L>For to buy Flax, ere they to spinning fall.</L>
<L>"Thus still what vice a man is to addicted,</L>
<L>"He by excuses seeks to be protected.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But to return where I did leave before,</L>
<L>This Town of <HI>Cheshunt</HI> having passed o're,</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="11"/>I came to <HI>Waltham-Cross,</HI> from <HI>London</HI> Town</L>
<L>A Dozen miles just, either up or down:</L>
<L>Of which same Cross, because that I will write,</L>
<L>I will again in Prose a while indite.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="prose part">
<P>This Cross was erected by King <HI>Edward</HI> the first, in memory of his Wife Queen <HI>Eleanor,</HI> a renowned and vertuous Lady, Sister to <HI>Alphonsus</HI> King of <HI>Castile,</HI> Daughter to King <HI>Ferdinand</HI> the third, and only Child of <HI>Joan</HI> his second Wife, Daughter and Heir of <HI>John</HI> Earl of <HI>Ponthien.</HI> She accompanied her Husband to the Holy Land, in which Voyage, he being stabbed by a <HI>Saracen</HI> with a poysoned Dagger, when no Medicine could extract the poyson, she did it with her Tongue, licking daily, while her Husband slept, his rankling wounds, whereby they perfectly closed, and yet her self received no harm! <HI>So soveraign a medicine</HI> (said <HI>Speed</HI>) <HI>is a womans tongue, a∣nointed with the vertue of lovely affection. Pity it is,</HI> saith Mr. <HI>Fuller, such a pretty story should not be true, because then we might hear of one womans tongue that hath done good, whereas otherwise we have heard of a hundred womens tongues that have done hurt.</HI> However, no question she was a woman of excellent parts, to our Nation a loving Mother, <HI>and</HI> (saith <HI>Walsingham</HI>) <HI>the Column and Pillar, as it were, of the whole Realm.</HI> She dyed at <HI>Herdby</HI> in <HI>Lincolnshire, November</HI> 29, 1290, ha∣ving been King <HI>Edwards</HI> Wife 36 years, who erected to her honour these Crosses, as Statues, at <HI>Lincoln, Grantham, Stanford, Geddington, Northampton, Stony-Stratford, Dunstable,</HI> St. <HI>Albans,</HI> this at <HI>Waltham,</HI> and one at <HI>Westminster</HI> called Charing-cross; which last was by the Rump, that Maggot-end of a Parliament, pulled down; to such un∣certain periods come oftentimes the fairest Structures, as this which was built of Marble, and therefore the more subject to the covetous∣ness of avaritious hands. Thus, as <HI>John Taylor</HI> hath it,
<Q><L>Old <HI>Charing-Cross</HI> that lasted many lives,</L>
<L>Is turn'd to Saltsellers and H<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of Knives.</L></Q>
But this Cross at <HI>Waltham</HI> being not so rich, escaped ruine, though time hath made it something ruinous in respect of its former beauty and splendor. But enough of this Cross, lest I cross my Reader with the tediousness of the relation thereof.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="poetic part">
<LG>
<L><PB N="19" REF="11" MS="y"/>From <HI>Waltham-Cross</HI> I went to <HI>Enfield</HI> Town,</L>
<L>Unto the Sign there of the <HI>Rose and Crown,</HI></L>
<L>A noted place; which House much money takes</L>
<L>For sale of Butter'd bread, Eel-pies and Cakes;</L>
<L>There also is good Beer, and Ale so great,</L>
<L>'Tis said that it will make a Cat to speak.</L>
<L>But there is one thing makes amends for all,</L>
<L>Although their Ale be great, their pots are small.</L>
<L>This House is call'd <HI>old Joans,</HI> but wherefore so,</L>
<L>To tell to you the truth, I do not know;</L>
<L>Nor can we ought of its antiquity read</L>
<L>In learned <HI>Cambden,</HI> or laborious <HI>Speed,</HI></L>
<L>For had they at the same but tope't their nose,</L>
<L>They would have writ of it I do suppose;</L>
<L>Nor did <HI>John Taylor</HI> the brave <HI>Water▪Poet</HI></L>
<L>In all his rambling Travels surely know it,</L>
<L>For honest <HI>John</HI> did ne're commit that crime,</L>
<L>To drink good Ale, and mention not the Sign;</L>
<L>But since that time I have informed been,</L>
<L>That those same persons who now live therein,</L>
<L>Were in another House living e're while,</L>
<L>Nearer to <HI>London</HI> much about a mile,</L>
<L>And coming for to live where now they do,</L>
<L>They brought the name of <HI>old Joans</HI> thither too.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Here after I had staid a little space,</L>
<L>Towards <HI>London</HI> then I forwarder did trace,</L>
<L>And weary as I was at last did come</L>
<L>To the <HI>Blew Bell</HI> in merry <HI>Edmonton</HI>;</L>
<L>I call it merry, for it doth appear</L>
<L>That once a merry Devil lived there.</L>
<L>Or else the story lies, and the <HI>Devil</HI>'s in't,</L>
<L>If men would dare for to put lies in print;</L>
<L>But ancient Records they be-like do tell</L>
<L>One <HI>Peter Faber</HI> he therein did dwell,</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="12"/>And he deceiv'd the Devil as 'tis sed,</L>
<L>The Devil sure was fairly brought to bed;</L>
<L>That he should be deceiv'd 'tis to be wonder'd,</L>
<L>Where one deceives him, he deceives a hunder'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But Holla Muse, where runs my busie pen!</L>
<L>Return unto thy subject once agen,</L>
<L>Here at the <HI>Bell</HI> I found good Beer, good Sack,</L>
<L>Nor did they Customers at that time lack,</L>
<L>Whose postures to express as they sat quaffing,</L>
<L>Would make a Horse his Bridle break with laughing:</L>
<L>Here one sate in a fume of <HI>Tunidado,</HI></L>
<L>Whose vapours unto Heaven did make scalado;</L>
<L>Another he did spit and spall so sore</L>
<L>As if he'd see what he had drunk before;</L>
<L>Another he did sing so out of frame,</L>
<L>'Twould scare the schreich-owles for to hear the same;</L>
<L>One had his tongue continually a walking,</L>
<L>Yet none could gain one wise word by his talking;</L>
<L>Another did better decorum keep,</L>
<L>Nodding his head a while he fell asleep;</L>
<L>Some could not to one seat their breeches fix,</L>
<L>But walking still were full of antick tricks:</L>
<L>So each a several posture did express,</L>
<L>Acted with very much rediculousness,</L>
<L>That it would make one think, a man to see</L>
<L>What kind of Beasts and Anticks, Drunkards be,</L>
<L>That he from over-drinking should refrain,</L>
<L>Or having been drunk, ne're be drunk again.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Here at the <HI>Bell</HI> I little time did stay,</L>
<L>Drank only one bare pint, and went my way.</L>
<L>But in the Road another Tavern spi'd,</L>
<L>Where what juice was within I went and tri'd;</L>
<L>To give you commendations of the Wine</L>
<L>It much doth need, 'twas neither brisk nor fine,</L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="12" MS="y"/>Racy, nor pure; therefore I do not scoff,</L>
<L>It needs much praises for to put it off;</L>
<L>But yet the Drawer like an honest Lad</L>
<L>Told me, although the first pint proved bad,</L>
<L>Bid me I should not be too much perplext,</L>
<L>For why it should be mended in the next;</L>
<L>But I well knowing his wire-drawing tricks,</L>
<L>By which on many a person they do fix;</L>
<L>Did leave him for some other one to taper on,</L>
<L>And bid adieu to him and his blue apron.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Next I to <HI>Totnam-High-cross</HI> took my way,</L>
<L>And at the Sign o'th' <HI>Swan</HI> a while did stay,</L>
<L>Being by a friend call'd in, who with a glance</L>
<L>From out the window spied me by chance;</L>
<L>No Complements betwixt us were neglected,</L>
<L>Being glad to meet together unexpected,</L>
<L>And then as when friends meet, the common use</L>
<L>Is to enquire straight, <HI>Pray what good news?</HI></L>
<L>So was it then with us, our tongues 'gan prate</L>
<L>Of such transactions as were done of late,</L>
<L>And afterwards to other matters fell;</L>
<L>And first of all our tongues began to tell</L>
<L>How Honesty we thought from earth was fled,</L>
<L>Money was scarce, and that made trading dead.</L>
<L>That men of parts were flighted and neglected,</L>
<L>Whilst mimick anticks were too much respected;</L>
<L>How that Hypocrisie bare so much rule,</L>
<L>Plain dealing now accounted was a fool;</L>
<L>How <HI>yea and nay,</HI> if you do rightly scan him,</L>
<L>Would cozen, but more slylier far than <HI>dam-<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>im</HI>;</L>
<L>That some men, though in Knavery were mounted;</L>
<L>Yet would be angry to be Knaves accounted▪</L>
<L>These last were my friends words which he me told,</L>
<L>But I straightway desir'd him to hold,</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="13"/>And bid him speak with better circumspection,</L>
<L>(There is no gen'ral Rule without exception)</L>
<L>For in our Country I my self did know</L>
<L>As great a Knave as thereabouts did grow,</L>
<L>Who cause he would be known to be a Knave,</L>
<L>To have it under-hand five shillings gave,</L>
<L>And that this was a▪ real truth, no jest,</L>
<L>Hundreds might sign it with <HI>Probatum est.</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus we of Knav'ry did our judgments scan,</L>
<L>Yet Knav'ry will be us'd do what we can;</L>
<L>Which made that Knave to think he did not leese,</L>
<L>When as he paid ten pounds by one poor Cheese;</L>
<L>Well may we say with <HI>Rombus</HI> the School master,</L>
<L>'Twill cause a broken head to have such plaister;</L>
<L>And thus a man might eas'ly make it plain,</L>
<L>That some are but bare Knaves, some Knaves in grain.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But to return where we did leave before▪</L>
<L>And of these cheating Knaves to write no more:</L>
<L>Commanding Time which will not stay for no man,</L>
<L>Me to my Journey once again did summon;</L>
<L>My friend and I that was so honest hearted,</L>
<L>Drunk to each other▪ then shook hands and parted.</L>
<L>Going still nearer <HI>London,</HI> I did come</L>
<L>In little space of time to <HI>Newington.</HI></L>
<L>Now as I past along I cast my eye on,</L>
<L>The Signs of <HI>Cock and Pie,</HI> and <HI>Bull</HI> and <HI>Lion,</HI></L>
<L>And Handsome Hostesses, with smiling looks,</L>
<L>And thought that <HI>Jack-daws</HI> might be caught by <HI>Rooks.</HI></L>
<L>So I ne're staid, but unto <HI>Kingsland</HI> came,</L>
<L>Where at that place I found the very same</L>
<L>Signs to invite the people in to drink,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Where (if you will) you may spend store of Chink.</L>
<L>From thence my course to <HI>London</HI> I did bend,</L>
<L>And at the City made my Journeys▪</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>END.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<PB REF="13"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

