<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Hero and Leander in Durlesque</TITLE><AUTHOR>Wycherley, William, 1640-1716.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A67200</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing W3746</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R34099</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">13764507</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 13764507</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">101711</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A67200)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101711)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1055:10)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Hero and Leander in Durlesque</TITLE><AUTHOR>Wycherley, William, 1640-1716.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 76 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>[s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>MDCLXIX [1669]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>In verse.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A67200">
<STC T="W">W3746</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">13764507</BIBNO>
<VID>101711</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>HERO AND LEANDER, IN Burlesque.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed in the Year, MDCLXIX.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>HERO AND LEANDER. IN <HI>BURLESQUE.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THe Towns of <HI>Sestus</HI> and <HI>Abidus</HI> stood</L>
<L>As near to one another as they cou'd;</L>
<L>For spightfull <HI>Hellespont</HI> still 'tween them ran,</L>
<L>Of whose outragiousness you'l hear anon:</L>
<L>Yet that they still communicated, note,</L>
<L>By floating Bridge now call'd a Ferry-boat,</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="3"/>
Which if this year lay on <HI>Abidus's</HI> side,</L>
<L>The next to <HI>Sestian</HI> Dock was to be ty'd:</L>
<L>For Senates sage of both Towns cou'd agree</L>
<L>By turns to be the Masters of the Sea:</L>
<L>But always when <HI>Abidus</HI> had the Boat,</L>
<L>The State, and it had but the same Pylot;</L>
<L>A shrewd old Swabber with a neck a tight,</L>
<L>And evermore inclined to the right;</L>
<L>His fellow Burgers sage remark, and cause</L>
<L>Why he was chosen fisher of the Laws:</L>
<L>Besides the scituation of his ears</L>
<L>They saw was such, no trayt'rous whisperers</L>
<L>Could easily approach them, one was still</L>
<L>Prickt up to heaven to receive her will,</L>
<L>T'other did earthward lop, good man, with pain</L>
<L>To hear the needy, and oppress'd complain.</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="3"/>
But when you know his Education, you'l</L>
<L>Allow the man in all points fit to rule.</L>
<L>He was brought up to danger, and to rapin,</L>
<L>Dabled ith'sea, and with a line, and a pin,</L>
<L>Which the young Urchin cunningly wou'd crook,</L>
<L>With fly, or worm disguise it then, and rook</L>
<L>The Ocean of her fish; for e're a Swabber</L>
<L>He was a Sprat-catcher, or good Eele-bobber.</L>
<L><HI>Alcides</HI> when a whuleing piss-abed</L>
<L>By Poets (if you'l trust 'em) hath been sed</L>
<L>Over a thumping Adder to prevail;</L>
<L>This little Rogue cou'd hold an Eele by th'tail:</L>
<L>And with his strength his art increas'd, was able</L>
<L>Soon well to steer a Skiff, and grasp a Cable,</L>
<L>Cou'd tack about, shift sails, wheadle the wind,</L>
<L>And make it come before him, or behind:</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="4"/>
Knew where the rocks did ly, &amp; sneaking shelves,</L>
<L>And places where bold men might drown them∣selves;</L>
<L>Kenn'd Storms far off, knew whether they had more</L>
<L>A mind to come to Sea, or stay a shore:</L>
<L>But to be short, and plain, he knew as well</L>
<L>The Sea, as Beggar doth his Dish, cou'd tell</L>
<L>What the least Cockle did in's shell, and guess</L>
<L>How many arms length where 'twas bottomless;</L>
<L>Such was the man for sway, you'l think him now</L>
<L>Worthy as Roman newly ta'ne from Plow:</L>
<L>Yet know his praises I have not begun,</L>
<L>Fine Gentleman <HI>Leander</HI> was his Son,</L>
<L>With whose most gen'rous inclination he</L>
<L>To's cost (few Fathers doe so) did agree,</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4"/>
And bound him Prentice to a worthy Barber,</L>
<L>The best, not such another in the harbour,</L>
<L>Unless our poor <HI>Leander</HI> had liv'd to't</L>
<L>Most probable opinion to confute.</L>
<L>He was so handy, nimble, tight, so neat</L>
<L>In's person, and his implements compleat:</L>
<L>His Towels, like his skin, were white, and fine,</L>
<L>Nought but his face his bason could out-shine;</L>
<L>So pickt, so wash't his Combes of Ivory,</L>
<L>Unless his teeth their whiteness nought came nigh,</L>
<L>With others that were made of horn, or box,</L>
<L>He often wou'd compare his golden locks;</L>
<L>With whom (if none had too much beard) he'd play,</L>
<L>And innocently sport out half the day;</L>
<L>But when you did sit down, with such a grace</L>
<L>Handled your throat, your ears, your nose, your face,</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
Tickled where others pain; Maids who did eye him</L>
<L>Wish'd themselves Satyrs to be trimmed by him:</L>
<L>Cou'd dive into the channels of your brain,</L>
<L>And with a feat dexterity make plain</L>
<L>The passage, though before 'twas nere so rough,</L>
<L>Yet with less pain to you, then taking snuff;</L>
<L>For he wore nails as long as bill of Bittern,</L>
<L>For that to scrape teeth, and to play on Cittern;</L>
<L>Nay he had all good qualities, cou'd tye</L>
<L>A Cuff-String, or Crevat so jantyly:</L>
<L>With all had conscience, and for copper spanker</L>
<L>Wou'd make Sea-faring beard look like an anchor.</L>
<L>For's mettle, and agility, with which</L>
<L>Writers are bound their Heroes to inrich;</L>
<L>I must confess I can't say much, but know</L>
<L>For certain he could crindge, and bow full low.</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="5"/>
For throwing of the Bar he never car'd,</L>
<L>Cudgels, nor wrestling, that I ever heard,</L>
<L>Or any brutish sports, which make men wrangle;</L>
<L>On Holy-days he went alone to angle;</L>
<L>Lov'd swimming well, and swam like any Duck;</L>
<L>But where most skill there ever is least luck:</L>
<L>And Arts, like women after a long wooing,</L>
<L>Oft shame our industry, and prove undoing.</L>
<L>Now towe me Muse o're to the other side,</L>
<L>Where most egregious <HI>Hero</HI> did abide;</L>
<L>You sacred Dame I mean who once did steer</L>
<L>The prosp'rous praise of great <HI>Magnanos</HI> dear;</L>
<L>If you have any time, help me ashore</L>
<L>With <HI>Heros</HI> commendation, and though poor</L>
<L>I am, in socket trimm'd with bayes I swear,</L>
<L>I'll tall rush candle to thy glory rear;</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="6"/>
Which likewise may as <HI>Pharo</HI> serve to light</L>
<L>Your groaping Orators, when it is night,</L>
<L>Throughout <HI>Parnassus;</HI> come 'tis as folks say,</L>
<L>Who'd have his business done, must bribe, not pray.</L>
<L>What do you pause at now? I know as Muse</L>
<L>To scorn good wages was your simple use;</L>
<L>With me hang not an arse: <HI>Hero</HI> then was</L>
<L>A bonny buxom bounsing <HI>Sestian</HI> Lass,</L>
<L>Of all the Grecian Girls the very Flower,</L>
<L>Liv'd at the Towns end at the sign of Tower,</L>
<L>With her own Mother a large hearted woman,</L>
<L>Whose house to merry Greeks was alway common;</L>
<L>A comely Widow, and had long been so,</L>
<L>For th'oldest in the town did never know</L>
<L>The Father of fine <HI>Hero,</HI> whence disputes</L>
<L>That some Sea-god disguis'd in fishing boots</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="6"/>
Did catch her on the shore, &amp; there did strand her,</L>
<L>And so contriv'd a Mistress for <HI>Leander.</HI></L>
<L>But whether so, or no, or how it was,</L>
<L>She grew too great for Mortal to embrace,</L>
<L>And haughtily did stave off many proffers,</L>
<L>Resolv'd to keep the Keys of her own Coffers,</L>
<L>And scorn'd to be with any a yoke-fellow,</L>
<L>Or to admit competitor of pillow:</L>
<L>But kept the Empire of her bed to cough,</L>
<L>Snore, belch, break wind, and no one shou'd cry soh:</L>
<L>And hows'ere Love, and Lover did contrive it,</L>
<L>The cunning willful Widow did not wive it,</L>
<L>Unless she practis'd secret Matrimony,</L>
<L>For licence but for wine she had not any.</L>
<L>But what of that? I warrant she was wise</L>
<L>Enough to keep her self from Church Excise.</L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="7"/>
Was <HI>Hero</HI> not in spight of all the Clerg'in</L>
<L><HI>Sestus,</HI> and what they all cou'd do, a Virgin?</L>
<L>And to her Mother was but young, yet cou'd</L>
<L>Some say as much as she, nay much more did</L>
<L>Within-doors, and long of her complaisance</L>
<L>It was, her mothers liquor had good utterance.</L>
<L>For she was still in motion, now i'th'Garret,</L>
<L>And strait down in the Cellar drawing Clarret;</L>
<L>Hasty as lightning she wou'd shoot the stairs,</L>
<L>If no one did oppose her unawares;</L>
<L>Wou'd bolt into the room like startled Cunny,</L>
<L>But still dropt at the door due Ceremony;</L>
<L>Then mumpt out, Gentlemen what d'you lack—</L>
<L>When strait she's answer'd with a bob, or smack:</L>
<L>But some one rising, in her ear doth tell her,</L>
<L>She answers him aloud, the best i'th'Cellar:</L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="7"/>
He follows down, and broaches where he will,</L>
<L>But with a gentle caution not to spill.</L>
<L>She made, and unmade beds most nimblely,</L>
<L>Not like her Dammes, hers was a slim-belly:</L>
<L>And now and then, with her sweet company</L>
<L>Cou'd satisfy gay guest for lodging high;</L>
<L>His rageing bowels supper should not miss,</L>
<L>For she cou'd stay a stomack with a kiss:</L>
<L>At coming in and out cou'd complement</L>
<L>The guests, and give 'um marvelous content.</L>
<L>For truly she well-spoken damsel was,</L>
<L>Like fav'rite Advocate brought all to pass,</L>
<L>And not as foolish Maids with nature nice,</L>
<L>But boldly us'd her own good qualities</L>
<L>Not only for her self, but other foke,</L>
<L>Cou'd break mad ranting Girls to th'marriage yoke.</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="8"/>
To bashful, or dumb Lovers she was common,</L>
<L>And publick mouth, or as we say, Spokes-woman:</L>
<L>In other terms a Maidenhead-ensurer,</L>
<L>A Wife, or as it were a Wife-procurer:</L>
<L>For in old Grecian Writ it manifest is,</L>
<L><HI>Hero</HI> had Orders, and was <HI>Venus</HI> Priestess.</L>
<L>At once she drew, and answer'd Lovers pleas,</L>
<L>'Tween them she made, and carry'd messages,</L>
<L>Hagler of <HI>chere entier,</HI> and did supply,</L>
<L>For modest gain, humane necessity;</L>
<L>But needy folks for nothing wou'd relieve▪</L>
<L>And still of her own store was free to give.</L>
<L>She was, I vow and swear, as good a creature</L>
<L>As ever wore bright Symptome of good nature,</L>
<L>Loves Cobweb, or his net, or golden fleece,</L>
<L>As Poets say, who can choose Mistresses,</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="8"/>
And they their meanest Heroe will not bed,</L>
<L>With any thing whose Hair is not Fox-red.</L>
<L>Her Brows soft Fur was of a paler Dye,</L>
<L>Conformable to that which prettily</L>
<L>Peep'd on her upper Lip, and cowardly</L>
<L>Made shew of Heroine Virility.</L>
<L>Day in her large Cow-Eyes was broad awake,</L>
<L>No heavy sleepy Morn there seem'd to break.</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Phoebus</HI> given, as you know, to flatter,</L>
<L>With his own Lustre did her Face bespatter:</L>
<L>For then Freckles of night on Cheeks not strew'd</L>
<L>To make the White remaining be allow'd:</L>
<L>Her Lips—but stay, was not <HI>Pigmalion</HI> won</L>
<L>With a senseless Description of his own?</L>
<L>Let it suffice then all who are concern'd,</L>
<L>That in her Face 'twas openly discern'd</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="9"/>
How near she was to <HI>Venus</HI> in her place;</L>
<L>And by her Stature seen her Heavenly Race:</L>
<L>For she not only streight, but tall as Mast:</L>
<L>Beauty's whole World in all perfection vast.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yearly at <HI>Sestus</HI> Town for <HI>Venus</HI> sake,</L>
<L>Mother of Wakes, was kept a jolly Wake:</L>
<L>But <HI>Greeks</HI> say 'twas a customary Howling</L>
<L>For her <HI>Adonis,</HI> or Annual Condoling</L>
<L>Their Goddesses and Countries active Drudge,</L>
<L>Who keenly carry'd on their mortal Grudge</L>
<L>Against a certain Outlaw, who i'th' Woods</L>
<L>Reign'd Lord, and King, and liv'd on true mens Goods:</L>
<L>That reap'd and mow'd where he did never plow,</L>
<L>But where he plow'd, none e're cou'd reap or mow:</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="9"/>
Who Plow-mans Joy did trample under foot,</L>
<L>And Tyrant-like, let nothing near him sprout.</L>
<L>But those small faults, such as the <HI>Greeks</HI> cou'd pardon,</L>
<L>And composition Carrots out of Garden</L>
<L>Had giv'n him yearly, wou'd the Churl have spar'd</L>
<L>But their meat, drink, and cloth in the Vineyard:</L>
<L>Yet he wou'd not be wean'd; but at their charges</L>
<L>Basely alone went on carowsing Verjuice,</L>
<L>And was before the pressing of the Liquor,</L>
<L>Of jolly Grecian Bowls the shrewdest Nicker:</L>
<L>Whence all the thirsty <HI>Greeks</HI> grew mad, &amp; swore</L>
<L>Deeply, they'd drink the rest out in his Gore;</L>
<L>And straight the bold Associates pitch'd upon</L>
<L>A Chief to lead them, or to bid 'em on;</L>
<L>Who though he had no hair on Chin, or Brest▪</L>
<L>Had Valour nevertheless most manifest:</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="10"/>
And <HI>Mars</HI> himself 'tis thought hath oft out-done;</L>
<L>For it is certain <HI>Venus</HI> loved none</L>
<L>Like him of all her Lusty Boys, and Cronies</L>
<L>Good Bit of flesh, call'd as I said, <HI>Adonis;</HI></L>
<L>Had gift of Vigilance to boot, no Snorter:</L>
<L>Must rise betimes that cou'd beat up his Quarter;</L>
<L>For when Night 'gan to peel, and Day was dawn∣ing,</L>
<L>Up he wou'd get, and leave his Goddess yawn∣ing,</L>
<L>Who waking, turn'd to th' Wall, and thought t'ave had 'im,</L>
<L>As other Utensils, where she had laid him;</L>
<L>But found the eager Huntsman still would leap</L>
<L>The Fence, not taking notice of the Gap:</L>
<L>Whence straight in rage she call'd him curtail'd Fellow,</L>
<L>And then to ease her heart, she cuff'd her Pillow.</L>
<L><PB N="17" REF="10"/>
So when the Hare is mist where she was squatting,</L>
<L>Next Bush the mump'd Pursuers fall a beating.</L>
<L>But when sh'ad paus'd (quoth she) 'tis <HI>Phoebe</HI> is chief</L>
<L>Cause, and Contriver alway of my Mischief:</L>
<L>That long-legg'd Ramp, that daggle-tail'd she-Ranger,</L>
<L>To well disposed Folkes still Dog in Manger:</L>
<L>She leads the able Youth astray, bewitches</L>
<L>Them with that early Itch of leaping Ditches;</L>
<L>And in their warm Bed will not let them tarry,</L>
<L>Where if they love toil they might be aweary,</L>
<L>And to the prickly Thickets need not roam;</L>
<L>Till out of breath might beat the Bush at home.</L>
<L>But let 'um go like Fops, for know stale Maid,</L>
<L>(With that she snear'd) that we have men more staid,</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="11"/>
And you but spoil our sport to make it better,</L>
<L>And when my Foe, in truth art but my Setter.</L>
<L>So fumbling Bards do oft depose a Rhime,</L>
<L>But to admit one that will better chime.</L>
<L>Mean while the Goddess held all these discourses,</L>
<L><HI>Adonis</HI> was a tooting for his forces:</L>
<L>For note though Hunting's said to be in fashion,</L>
<L>Much like to grinning Honours Recreation;</L>
<L>In this they disagree, for in the War</L>
<L>O'th Woods, the Captain is the Trumpeter,</L>
<L>And makes the first proof of his scorning Death,</L>
<L>By being free, and lavish of his Breath.</L>
<L>So did our Leader, who when he had drawn</L>
<L>His Band of Green-coats out upon the Lawn,</L>
<L>By Proverbs sage advise to scape a trip,</L>
<L>Resolv'd with them to look ere he did leap;</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="11"/>
Which to wise Warriors custom is according,</L>
<L>Who ere they fall to Blows, do fall a Wording;</L>
<L>By which means those that are in Reason stout,</L>
<L>The Enemy before they see him, rout.</L>
<L>And first as they in Story oft did find,</L>
<L>Sly Ancients did, they made the most o'th' wind:</L>
<L>Then sent abroad their Scouts, which man still rec∣kons</L>
<L>In time of War or Peace, his faithful Seconds.</L>
<L>For when the Shepherd hath a mind to sleep,</L>
<L>They are the Guard, and <HI>Hectors</HI> of the Sheep;</L>
<L>And when it is his pleasure to go murther,</L>
<L>In that Heroick Vertue none go further;</L>
<L>So that if I may judge, they have much wrong,</L>
<L>To be left out of Registering Song.</L>
<L>But he which makes, not he who ends the quarrel,</L>
<L>Is known to run away still with the Lawrel.</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="12"/>
But to leave off the wont Poetick Pother,</L>
<L>Small sense with heaps of words t'orelay and smo∣ther.</L>
<L>The Chase, know then in few words, was begun,</L>
<L>And nimble Rogues had got the start o'th' Sun,</L>
<L>And to the Forest merrily did trudge</L>
<L>With Pole on shoulder to leap Ditch, or Hedge,</L>
<L>Which Pole (some say) had iron Peg at end on't,</L>
<L>In case that Boar should chance to prove Defen∣dant.</L>
<L>By Thorn, or Holly Turn-pikes of the Wood</L>
<L>The doubty Yongsters scorn'd to be withstood;</L>
<L>For through the surly Thickets each did rush,</L>
<L>And manfully then fall upon his Bush:</L>
<L>So that, alas, throughout the spacious Forest,</L>
<L>The smallest of her Tenants cou'd have no rest.</L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="12"/>
The Hare <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> lurking Cunny, and the Squirril,</L>
<L>Must all have then sate still at their own peril.</L>
<L>For lazy <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> himself began to reckon</L>
<L>That he <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> move if he wou'd save his Bacon;</L>
<L>And as all Heroes who are truly bred,</L>
<L>Scorn'd to be caught by sneaking Death abed;</L>
<L>So took his heels; yet as bold <HI>Parthian,</HI></L>
<L>His teasing Foes still wounding as he ran:</L>
<L>But finding odds against him, not afraid,</L>
<L>Yet danger prudently with honour weigh'd;</L>
<L>And since not able to resist their force,</L>
<L>Bravely resolv'd to beat 'um in a course:</L>
<L>Or rather (as some guess) he had the cunning</L>
<L>Of the sly <HI>Roman</HI> who made a shew of running,</L>
<L>His Foes not to avoid, but separate;</L>
<L>That singly with 'em he might try his fate.</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="13"/>
For when the Sentinel <HI>Adonis</HI> popt</L>
<L>Out of his Hawthorn ambush, strait he stopt;</L>
<L>And Youth no sooner shew'd his meaning cruel,</L>
<L>But Boar tossing his Snout, receiv'd the Duel.</L>
<L>But Fate not half so meek as now adays,</L>
<L>Contented to take up with bloodless frays,</L>
<L>Sends folkes afield to measure Swords, and Valour,</L>
<L>And after trial neither found the taller;</L>
<L>But both lest Fame should lie, do live to tell</L>
<L>The world that they were both invincible:</L>
<L>Nor then was Honour bound by Law of Quarter,</L>
<L>To chouse her self of many a brave Martyr.</L>
<L>The Boar, as wise folkes say, harm watch, harm catch,</L>
<L>In's own defence, his Huntsman did dispatch:</L>
<L>Now tender Virgins who are always ready</L>
<L>To shew y'ave bowels, hold yet till I bed ye:</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="13"/>
Hold, hold, I say, a while, if ye are able,</L>
<L>For Subject to ensue more lamentable.</L>
<L>The savage Conqueror not satisfy'd,</L>
<L>Till's stomack as his vengeance he had cly'd,</L>
<L>And <HI>Tartar-</HI>like not only to o'rethrow</L>
<L>Contented, but must dine upon his Foe,</L>
<L>Alas! first of that chary Morsel carv'd</L>
<L>Sacred to <HI>Venus,</HI> while she for it starv'd,</L>
<L>And many others since, by the Confession</L>
<L>Of <HI>Sestian</HI> Virgins yearly Lamentation,</L>
<L>In which poor <HI>Hero</HI> bore the greatest part,</L>
<L>And wronging none did take it most to heart;</L>
<L>And yet her Beauty truckled not to grief,</L>
<L>For both she was the Representative</L>
<L>Of Widow <HI>Venus,</HI> and at once did make</L>
<L>Stout hearts with Love and Pity both to ake;</L>
<L><PB N="24" REF="14"/>
But most the Youngsters of <HI>Abidus,</HI> who</L>
<L>Came o're the water but to see the show;</L>
<L>The show! fie, let's employ words more in fashion;</L>
<L>The holy March, or Trapesing, or Procession:</L>
<L>Much such as now adays when to keep Noses</L>
<L>From sense of Death, are worn Rosemary Posies.</L>
<L>But how now fisking Muse, again a straying?</L>
<L>Let's back to <HI>Hero,</HI> who as I was saying</L>
<L>Did lead the dumpish Rout, which 'twas suspitious</L>
<L>Whether to her, or to the day officious;</L>
<L>For some 'tis sure scorning the Gods to flatter,</L>
<L>But cause she went before to Church, went a'ter.</L>
<L>So if the Gods good Houses have resort,</L>
<L>Our mortal Goddesses they may thank for't.</L>
<L>But she minding her grief, or pride to chear</L>
<L>Their drooping hearts, refus'd but with a Lear,</L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="14"/>
And but when each the other 'gan to justle,</L>
<L>And only to come near her made a bustle,</L>
<L>Turn'd to 'um, yet with hanging Lip, and Frown,</L>
<L>T' assure 'um she wou'd not be blown upon.</L>
<L>So have I—but comparisons are odious,</L>
<L>Yet tell not me with Rhimes So is commodious;</L>
<L>So then as <HI>Hero</HI> I have seen the teasty</L>
<L>Proud paramour of the Heroick Masty,</L>
<L>Trot on in hast; and would not deign to mind</L>
<L>Humble Addresses made to her behind;</L>
<L>Unless, as with her Betters 'tis the fashion,</L>
<L>To snub, to snarl at, or snap up a passion.</L>
<L>So all Loves mystery is jogging on,</L>
<L>And savage Mistresses must be run down.</L>
<L><HI>Leander</HI> knew't, and therefore did not falter</L>
<L>In's course, but chas'd fair Murdress to the Altar,</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="15"/>
Where <HI>a la</HI> Negligence Dame <HI>Venus</HI> loll'd,</L>
<L>And Supplicants with smerking looks cajol'd.</L>
<L>But if some medling Gossip should ask why,</L>
<L>As ev'ry other watchful Deity,</L>
<L>She in her Temple did not stand upright:</L>
<L>In t'other posture sure she did delight,</L>
<L>Above them all; nor was her comely mold</L>
<L>Of Marblefram'd, obdurate still, and cold,</L>
<L>But willing Wax, whose nature did express</L>
<L>The complaisant, and gentle Goddesses.</L>
<L>Nor did she, as all other heav'nly fo'ke,</L>
<L>Put Mortals to the charge of Veil, or Frock,</L>
<L>Mortals whose blind Zeal so the Gods blaspheme,</L>
<L>Imputing to their spotless Worships shame:</L>
<L><PB N="27" REF="15"/>
She graciously shew'd all, so did provoke</L>
<L>To Adoration the most frozen stock.</L>
<L>The little Ape her Son with Bow unbent</L>
<L>(As shock guarding the Toes of Monument)</L>
<L>Lay at her feet, but not to hold'um, for</L>
<L>She like her self Compulsion did abhor;</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As on the Chappel walls it oft appear'd,</L>
<L>Which Daw ber without Pencil had besmear'd</L>
<L>With artful scratches, and in smutty scores</L>
<L>Of Charcole smutty doings, or Amours</L>
<L>Of Gods laid open, but in manner ampler,</L>
<L>Then in Madam <HI>Arachnes</HI> bawdy Sampler.</L>
<L>Nay sure they were the Types, Hints, or Instructi∣ons</L>
<L>To <HI>Aretines</HI> pathetical Productions,</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="16"/>
The modest <HI>Aretine;</HI> for none of those</L>
<L>Was he, whose Art on Nature <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> impose:</L>
<L>Pragmatick saucy slaves who take upon <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>To teach their Dame, they might as well their Grannum;</L>
<L>And with Mechanick Drapery do hide</L>
<L>But their own botches, and frank Natures pride,</L>
<L>At least unreas'nably from neck do stretch</L>
<L>White Hankerchief to cover whiter Breech,</L>
<L>And for the naked Nymphs of their own Locks</L>
<L>Contrive 'um Aprons, Petticoats, and Smocks:</L>
<L>But Apron sure not one of them must lack,</L>
<L>Though the poor Slut hath ne're a Rag to'r back,</L>
<L>For they to any thing will run o'th' score,</L>
<L>Rather than Nymph shou'd Facing want before.</L>
<L>They'll pluck Loves Wings, and tear his Clout from's eyes,</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="16"/>
Take Satyrs Beard, Fawns Scut, so mak't ap∣pear</L>
<L>Like <HI>Russians</HI> Cap, or <HI>Frizlanders</HI> Montier;</L>
<L>Take Monkeys tickling Paw, or Ear of Dazy,</L>
<L>While four-leg'd Favourite in Lap is lazy;</L>
<L>Take shading Branches from the Trees high top:</L>
<L>But <HI>Aretine</HI> not so</L>
<L>He complaisant to Nature, and to Female,</L>
<L>Alloweth her no Covering, but the Male:</L>
<L>And precious things of man doth only hide</L>
<L>In Cabinet which Nature did provide.</L>
<L>But Virgin who perhaps may long to know</L>
<L>What Gods o'th' Temple-walls did seem to do,</L>
<L>Faith I do beg thy pardon, for 'tis certain</L>
<L>I've been too long in drawing of the Curtain:</L>
<L>Yet I might hope that patience Feminine</L>
<L>Wou'd stay the praising of great <HI>Aretine.</HI></L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="17"/>
First <HI>Jove</HI> the surly Master of the Fam'ly</L>
<L>Had left off's Thunder, and there look'd so tame∣ly,</L>
<L>And turn'd away his feather'd Steed, for hark ye,</L>
<L>His Eagle was not hatch'd of <HI>Tuscan</HI> Turkey:</L>
<L>Therefore he in her stead did then bestride</L>
<L>A plump young Goldy-lock call'd <HI>Ganimed;</HI></L>
<L>Which though performed flyly under cloak,</L>
<L>Made of the thickest of Aetherial smoak,</L>
<L>He there was found out by his restless <HI>Juno,</HI></L>
<L>(The Jealous have but little sleep, as you know)</L>
<L>For rage o'th' sight her blew-thin-lip she bit;</L>
<L>And tore her Smock from Navel down to'r feet;</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>So shew'd her own, and Husbands discontent,</L>
<L>Which made him leave her, and his high-built Pa∣lace,</L>
<L>To seek him to his heav'nly Gusto a Lass.</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="17"/>
And if he had not, he had been to blame,</L>
<L>To lie still with his Sister was a shame.</L>
<L>To th' whoring Earth <HI>incognito</HI> he goes,</L>
<L>But not as Gallants now with Cloak o're Nose;</L>
<L>The habit of a Town-bull there he took,</L>
<L>Not to bear yoke, but ramping Nymph o're brook;</L>
<L>And the all-knowing four-legg'd Thunderer</L>
<L>To get upon her, first got under her.</L>
<L>So Bow must bend (as <HI>Cupid</HI> makes it out)</L>
<L>Ere the aim'd Arrow does come near the Clout:</L>
<L>And all but Whore, and Widow <HI>Amazon</HI></L>
<L>By sneaking, and submission still are won.</L>
<L>In the next place th' immortal Bullock did</L>
<L>Gore his dear Heifer <HI>Io</HI> till she bled.</L>
<L>Then was he seen in shining Coat of Mail</L>
<L>Of Ginneys, <HI>Danaes</HI> Fortress to assail;</L>
<L><PB N="32" REF="18"/>
Meer Whore who till she was greas'd in the Fist,</L>
<L>Was always devilish streight about the Twist.</L>
<L>Then <HI>Laeda</HI> he appeared to trapan;</L>
<L>Who taking him but for a Goose or Swan,</L>
<L>Lay still like Stock;</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Next with <HI>Asteria</HI> he did seem to struggle,</L>
<L>And you may swear he made not the spread Eagle.</L>
<L>But yet in all this sport his Royal Dame</L>
<L>Was but an envious looker on o'th' Game.</L>
<L>With her he did not deal a single Bout;</L>
<L>For Wrangler, or for Wife she was shut out.</L>
<L>The heav'nly Ruffian next as stout's he is,</L>
<L>By naked <HI>Venus</HI> was brought on his knees:</L>
<L>Hers, and her Husbands Pris'ner, for a Grate</L>
<L>He made for warlike Bum to look out at.</L>
<L><PB N="33" REF="18"/>
O subtilty of thinking Cuckolds Brains,</L>
<L>Who still blow up themselves with their own trains!</L>
<L><HI>Vulcan,</HI> thou only didst a fault proclaim,</L>
<L>Of which thou only wer't to bear the shame:</L>
<L>In the next place the Queen of Sluts alone is</L>
<L>With dainty fine Hober-de-hoy <HI>Adonis,</HI></L>
<L>Who for his part much rather wou'd have bin</L>
<L>A setting Springes, laying Snare, or Gin,</L>
<L>Than lie a Pris'ner in a Female Trap,</L>
<L>Or irksom Pitfal of a Womans Lap.</L>
<L>Yet from her for his heart he cou'd not flirt,</L>
<L>Sh'ad better hold than by the tail of Shirt.</L>
<L><HI>Apollo</HI> then in Shepherds Calves-skin sute</L>
<L>(As <HI>Francion)</HI> taught a Wench to play o'th' Lute.</L>
<L><HI>Neptune</HI> like Sea-Calf next upon a Bed</L>
<L>Of Sedges got <HI>Aeolian</HI> Maidenhead.</L>
<L><PB N="34" REF="19"/>
Then nimming <HI>Mercury</HI> with his sly Art,</L>
<L>Went the next way to steal a Maidens heart,</L>
<L>With Picklock opening Virgin Chest,</L>
<L>Where still the more is robb'd, the less is mist.</L>
<L>His Wench did seem to sleep, but though Dog∣sleep,</L>
<L>Such was his Art, she nought from him cou'd keep.</L>
<L>Then <HI>Saturn</HI> whom time almost made a Guelding,</L>
<L>To get a manly Fole leap'd kicking Heiding.</L>
<L>The Wood-Gods next appear'd in Dells and Dit∣ches,</L>
<L>A clapping of some Ramping Wenches Breeches.</L>
<L>And here and there a two legg'd Goat a rutting,</L>
<L>With little Sluts that thither came a nutting.</L>
<L>And while in private shades the Nymphs lay snug,</L>
<L>Kind Satyrs cover'd them with living Rug.</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="19"/>
And lest they for their scratching Dame should whoop,</L>
<L>They with their Tongues and Beard their mouths did stop.</L>
<L>For honour then of white-breech'd Patroness,</L>
<L>The Dawber thought that he cou'd do no less</L>
<L>Than judgment draw, judgment not to afright</L>
<L>(Like <HI>Angelo</HI>'s) Spectators, but delight.</L>
<L>It was that of the upright <HI>Phrygian</HI> judge,</L>
<L>To whom three squabling Goddesses did trudge,</L>
<L>And by the fair Looks of her Face and Breech,</L>
<L>Each from his hand the Golden Ball beseech.</L>
<L>But if in Dawber there be any trust,</L>
<L>To <HI>Venus</HI> giving it, he was most just.</L>
<L>Yet some say she brib'd him, as he did her,</L>
<L>And gave the Ball for, Wench that made great stir;</L>
<L><PB N="36" REF="20"/>
For Pimp as well as Lawyer doth deserve his</L>
<L>Reward before that he hath done his Service;</L>
<L>Since he's a Pleader too, and doth discover</L>
<L>The miserable case of Plaintiffe Lover,</L>
<L>And seldom 'tis but does obtain Relief.</L>
<L>But what before was I a saying? if</L>
<L>That <HI>Venus</HI>'s Competitors were such</L>
<L>As Painter made 'um, no true man would grutch</L>
<L>Her sure the sentence; and to bring't to trial</L>
<L>Before plain-dealing Swain, yet youthful Spy-all</L>
<L>Offore-sight <HI>Juno</HI> sage had not a whit,</L>
<L>And <HI>Pallas,</HI> though a snotty Nose, no Wit.</L>
<L>What though Dame <HI>Juno</HI> there appear'd so pro∣per,</L>
<L>That not a Car-man in the World could top her:</L>
<L>And Dawber gorgeously her head had drest;</L>
<L>For her dear Peacocks Rump paid for her Crest;</L>
<L><PB N="37" REF="20"/>
And had bestow'd on her the killing meen</L>
<L>Of Drunkards Eye, Purse-mouth, and bridled Chin</L>
<L>Made up; but kindness more than that came to</L>
<L>She had, he made her stand cross-legg'd, that so</L>
<L>What 'twas a shame to see might lurk behind;</L>
<L>That which is out of sight is out of mind.</L>
<L>And sure the heav'nly What-d'y'-calt's dimension</L>
<L>Cou'd not be spann'd by mortal comprehension.</L>
<L>For there was left apparent competency</L>
<L>For the most hungry Youngsters, who do fancy</L>
<L>Of that good thing they ne'r can have enough,</L>
<L>Until they are condemn'd unto the proof.</L>
<L>But married men, ye greedy dogs can tell ye,</L>
<L>Your Eyes are always bigger than your Belly.</L>
<L>What though Dame <HI>Pallas</HI> too was trick'd up in</L>
<L>A French Hood not of Velvet, but of Tin;</L>
<L><PB N="38" REF="21"/>
So <HI>Trulla</HI> have I seen in Coif of Mettle,</L>
<L>To ease her dear Lords shoulder of a Kettle;</L>
<L>But such as our bright <HI>Amazons</HI> now wear,</L>
<L>When to <HI>Hide-Park</HI> they ride to make fokes stare,</L>
<L>O Wits, was your Aunt <HI>Pallas</HI>'s Montier!</L>
<L>By whose reflection as a face divine</L>
<L>In flaunting Coyf of Glory hers did shine.</L>
<L>With meen was furnish'd too by Dawber partial,</L>
<L>Keen as her Thought, and as her Head-piece Martial.</L>
<L>Her Mouth the Mansion of her Charms, or Shop</L>
<L>Of Eloquence he kindly had set ope,</L>
<L>To shew she was a Wit; but sure moreover</L>
<L>The vastness of its Treasure to discover.</L>
<L>For not like common Baggage, or mean Girl,</L>
<L>Were her Gums set with beggarly seed Pearl:</L>
<L><PB N="39" REF="21"/>
But such each was as you might see, when State</L>
<L>Bids the great <HI>Spanish</HI> Monarch cock his Hat;</L>
<L>Or else in Chamber of Escurial most rich,</L>
<L>Is hung as in spruce Parlour Egg of Estrich.</L>
<L>And (as for <HI>Juno</HI>'s) to keep Judge from loathing,</L>
<L>For her Obscenity he found a cloathing,</L>
<L>Causing a Flap, or Apron natural</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Half way down to her knees to fall.</L>
<L>But do the Artist what he cou'd, a Blouze</L>
<L>She was, and <HI>Juno</HI> too to <HI>Vulcan</HI>'s Spouse,</L>
<L>Who though with <HI>Mars</HI> had newly had a Ruffle,</L>
<L>And black and blew eyes had got in the Scuffle,</L>
<L>Was tumbled, jumbled, tous'd, and mous'd, and wurry'd,</L>
<L>And so disturb'd the Pigs-tails on her Forehead;</L>
<L>The native Corral of her Lip too missing,</L>
<L>By boyst'rous sharp-set <HI>Hectors</HI> cruel kissing:</L>
<L><PB N="40" REF="22"/>
But not as some may doubt were the fair Cherries</L>
<L>By smutty Cuckolds Chaps turn'd to Mulberries:</L>
<L>Yet howso'ere her Graces were impair'd,</L>
<L>The Judge for's heart cou'd not defer's award,</L>
<L>But strait his Conscience in his Face up-star'd.</L>
<L>And while the wonder of her Form he kenn'd,</L>
<L>All that he had about him stood an end,</L>
<L>The sole unfeigned way Lass to commend.</L>
<L>Of <HI>Hero</HI>'s such <HI>Leander</HI>'s commendation,</L>
<L>Who made (while she to th'Gods) to her Oration.</L>
<L>But hold a stroak, you nimble Slut; for sure</L>
<L>We skip the Chappels choicest Furniture,</L>
<L>Which for the sake of Sex inquisitive,</L>
<L>For tail of our Description I'll retrive;</L>
<L>Though you wou'd let it, to save pains, escape us.</L>
<L>The <HI>Romans</HI> had a God well-known <HI>Priapus:</HI></L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="22"/>
The <HI>Greeks</HI> too had the like, for Heathen none</L>
<L>So blind, but his Almightiship wou'd own.</L>
<L>And <HI>Romans</HI> now who their old Gods reject,</L>
<L>Have seriously for him a great respect.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The mighty, and yet humble God did dwell</L>
<L>There to his mind in dark, and narrow Cell:</L>
<L>But cou'd not hide himself; for pale-fac'd Rout</L>
<L>Of Virgin Penitents soon found him out:</L>
<L>And Mother, and the Son lay both unheeded,</L>
<L>While they invoked him whose aid they needed,</L>
<L>And not the common way did they adore him;</L>
<L>But as they should, lay prostrated before him.</L>
<L>The little piss-tail Girls made long Oration</L>
<L>To's Worship, to be freed from Chalkes tempta∣tion</L>
<L><PB N="42" REF="23"/>
The ugly stale despairing Maids petition</L>
<L>But in a Dream for's heav'nly apparition.</L>
<L>New marri'd Dames did only laud his Name,</L>
<L>And seem'd his Bounty to receive with shame.</L>
<L>But the starv'd Widows were importunate,</L>
<L>As <HI>Spanish</HI> Beggars who do scorn to wait;</L>
<L>And ask as if they would not be deni'd,</L>
<L>And yet so as they cannot be suppli'd.</L>
<L>Amongst those Cravers <HI>Hero</HI> was not hindmost,</L>
<L>As Swabbers Son observ'd, who her did mind most▪</L>
<L>And while all shew the Gods their Whites of eyes,</L>
<L>In <HI>Hero</HI>'s bright ones he his Heaven spies.</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Hero</HI>'s so on Heaven were not bent,</L>
<L>But they on leering Lover eke did squint,</L>
<L>And through the corner of their Lids did wander</L>
<L>Some of their keenest Rays upon <HI>Leander;</HI></L>
<L><PB N="43" REF="23"/>
So Gods and him at once brought to her beck,</L>
<L>And rais'd his hope, yet did his Courage check.</L>
<L>For like a bashful Spaniel strait he stole</L>
<L>With modest joy his Nose into his Pole,</L>
<L>His tail between his Legs, yet slided to her,</L>
<L>And had the Heart, though not the Face, to woe her</L>
<L>In words like these; I must fu-forsooth own</L>
<L>I am a harmless poor Youth of our Town,</L>
<L>Who but to see fine sights this morning came here,</L>
<L>And not to learn of little Love to stammer;</L>
<L>Who tongue, as well as Heart, from me hath ta'ne,</L>
<L>So that I can't, if that I wou'd, complain;</L>
<L>Yet something I wou'd say if that I durst,</L>
<L>But I wou'd have these jeering Fokes gon first.</L>
<L>Scarce had he whisper'd that, but Congregation</L>
<L>Quite weary of their deaf Gods Conversation,</L>
<L><PB N="44" REF="24"/>
Rose up, and ending their unanswer'd Speeches,</L>
<L>To their Discourteous Worships turn'd their Breeches.</L>
<L>But when he saw that they indeed were gone,</L>
<L>And had left him with <HI>Hero</HI> all alone,</L>
<L>(As if it had been for the nonce) he fain</L>
<L>Would have invited them all back again;</L>
<L>And with a new wish did recant his former;</L>
<L>For though his Rival's gone, he durst not storm her.</L>
<L>And she (thinking no harm, as one wou'd say)</L>
<L>Did even for it then behind them stay.</L>
<L>For Women when they dare to keep the Field,</L>
<L>Wou'd have you know they do not fear to yield.</L>
<L>While dumb <HI>Leander</HI> look'd down on his Toes,</L>
<L>And numbered the Pinks upon his Shoes,</L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="24"/>
She did survey his Leg, the shape and fashion</L>
<L>Of the whole Youth with silent commendation.</L>
<L>For modest Maid I hope may leer and peer</L>
<L>On all man hath, if he, or none else see her.</L>
<L>And if by fear a Lovers voice be frose,</L>
<L>May break the Ice, and pris'ner Tongue let loose.</L>
<L><HI>Hero</HI> therefore (that knew the world) took on her</L>
<L>For slouching Lad the wooing in brisk manner;</L>
<L>And roundly said, Feat Youth, for want of speak∣ing,</L>
<L>D'y' think that I will suffer a heart-breaking?</L>
<L>When Men are become Women, Women then</L>
<L>May without shame (I take it) become Men.</L>
<L>But Custom's crueller than Love, to gag us:</L>
<L>For Silence more than Love before doth plague us.</L>
<L>Why must nice Slut be dumb, though rack'd, nay prest,</L>
<L><PB N="46" REF="25"/>
When it is impudence not to confess't?</L>
<L>Alas when I'm on fire, I must cry out</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Can Female-hold keep Loves Wild-Fire within∣dore?</L>
<L>If we do shut the Door, 'twill out at Windore.</L>
<L>We are but Paper Lanthorns to his Torch,</L>
<L>Whose Wafer-sides he instantly will scorch,</L>
<L>And never leave till through a way he find,</L>
<L>To blaze out lavishly before the Wind.</L>
<L>So to hold Love, for Maids as hard a matter,</L>
<L>As when they'r tickled, 'tis to hold their water.</L>
<L>But why pray shou'd it trouble Lovers Brains</L>
<L>If his kind well-bred Mistriss save him pains?</L>
<L>Though proffer'd Service stinks, you'll say; my mind is</L>
<L>To give before one's ask'd, endears a Kindness,</L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="25"/>
But for it wilful men I know do slight one,</L>
<L>And all but shy, and sullen Sluts set light on.</L>
<L>But Men in Love more savage, rude, and stupid</L>
<L>Than Brutes, and more do shame their Tutor <HI>Cü∣pid:</HI></L>
<L>And four-legg'd Dame may without Vanity</L>
<L>Vye with our Lords, their Lords humanity.</L>
<L>And we must own the Bear, Boar, Ass appear</L>
<L>Indeed to have more of the Cavalier.</L>
<L>When th'Asses solitary Miss doth bray</L>
<L>For want of him, he does not farther stray,</L>
<L>Nor stop his ears, her voice he thinks melodious,</L>
<L>Nor is she for her Summons to him odious:</L>
<L>Nay when Whip cann't, by her is wrought upon</L>
<L>To leave his <HI>Spanish</HI> Gravity, and run.</L>
<L><PB N="48" REF="26"/>
And for their Wench will fight brave Bear and Boar,</L>
<L>After enjoyment, as well as before.</L>
<L>Nor will their noble Spirits let a Mistress,</L>
<L>While they do live, be brought to want, or di∣stress.</L>
<L>But may be they so good are and observing,</L>
<L>Because their Dames are more than us deserving.</L>
<L>And to speak truth, I do believe those Ladies</L>
<L>Are something constanter than we now adays;</L>
<L>More generous by far, and bravely scorn</L>
<L>To take half Crown, or Guinney for good turn.</L>
<L>Their wit too, and discretion ours out-does;</L>
<L>Lovers they run not from, but lead by th' Nose,</L>
<L>But such as ne'er put finger in the eye,</L>
<L>Like ours, who snivel, sob, and sigh, and cry,</L>
<L>For what but they themselves themselves deny.</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="26"/>
When Love by shoulder look their Dames do crave,</L>
<L>They stare not on 'um, and ask what they'd have.</L>
<L>And happy Dames, they never were put to't yet</L>
<L>To speak as I am now, or go without it.</L>
<L>Then to <HI>Leander</HI> she made but one stride,</L>
<L>To peer in's Face, which his coy Hands deny'd,</L>
<L>But to withdraw 'em, when in vain she askt him,</L>
<L>She like a <HI>Bully</HI> swore, and then unmask'd him</L>
<L>By force of Arms, since she cou'd not intreat him,</L>
<L>And vow'd she cou'd find of her heart to beat him.</L>
<L>Then poor <HI>Leander</HI> gave himself for gone,</L>
<L>And thought his Breeches were already down:</L>
<L>And of remorse in her he quite despairing,</L>
<L>Took heart, and spoke out thus, in her own hear∣ing;</L>
<L><PB N="50" REF="27"/>
Are you the same that look'd but now forsooth</L>
<L>As if Butter wou'd not melt in your mouth?</L>
<L>She that just now refus'd to bait the passion</L>
<L>Of gaping Lovers with the least temptation?</L>
<L>She that did make green Apron fall so low</L>
<L>One might have seen that same assoon as Toe?</L>
<L>And rather than she wou'd take up her Coat,</L>
<L>She with a shameless daggle-tail did trot,</L>
<L>To keep her Followers from sight-provoking</L>
<L>Of Blew, of Russet, or of yellow-Stocking?</L>
<L>And while she follow'd was with humble praying,</L>
<L>She ne'er look'd back, but gave them all their say∣ing.</L>
<L>She cou'd not speak, at least that one cou'd hear her,</L>
<L>And is she grown o'th' sudden such a Tearer?</L>
<L><PB N="51" REF="27"/>
<HI>Hero</HI> mean while was not abash'd a whit;</L>
<L>But rather glad he Venom had to spit:</L>
<L>I mean, that of his Tongue he was so able,</L>
<L>To which she suddenly was responsible:</L>
<L>And with a shrug, a mouth, and cogging smile,</L>
<L>Such as of wrath a Cuckold wou'd beguil,</L>
<L>She said, What will you be a new way jealous,</L>
<L>And 'cause I am not kind to other Fellows,</L>
<L>Naughty <HI>Leander,</HI> think that I can be</L>
<L>But from Teeth outward other ways to thee?</L>
<L>And 'cause for you their Suits I do reject,</L>
<L>Will you inconscionable mine neglect?</L>
<L>The Turtle might as well repudiate</L>
<L>His Female, 'cause with him she'll only mate,</L>
<L>And scorns the common Flocks communication;</L>
<L>But groans out to him (all day) her chast passion,</L>
<L><PB N="52" REF="28"/>
And 'cause with neck thrust out shews she is wil∣ling,</L>
<L>As well might he (I say) refrain from Billing;</L>
<L>As you, because you see that I am coming,</L>
<L>Refrain the most delicious sport of Bumming;</L>
<L>And (as 'tis falsely said of us) to spight</L>
<L>Others, will not your self, lov'd self delight?</L>
<L>Be't so, I with your hardship am content,</L>
<L>But you for me shall not your self torment:</L>
<L>For in spight of your teeth you shall consent,</L>
<L>To take on me your full divertisement.</L>
<L>So took him 'bout the neck, and was so quick,</L>
<L><HI>Leander</HI> had not time to turn his Cheek.</L>
<L>But scarce cou'd Five be told, when with his Fist,</L>
<L>Plac'd in the Pit-hole of her Love-sick Brest,</L>
<L>Her tender Breech he had laid on the ground,</L>
<L>Had not kind Hassock in its way been found,</L>
<L><PB N="53" REF="28"/>
Which rais'd up lower end so fav'rably,</L>
<L>That something there <HI>Leander</HI> did espy,</L>
<L>That call'd back to his heart Humanity:</L>
<L>And then taking her up by painful halling,</L>
<L>Did expiate his laying her a sprawling.</L>
<L>And mannerly with Leg drawn back did own</L>
<L>His hainous fault in throwing of her down;</L>
<L>But she good-natur'd Maid, said it was none:</L>
<L>And ask'd him pardon if sh'ad done him wrong.</L>
<L>Alas, said he, good <HI>Hero,</HI> if your Tongue</L>
<L>You had kept to your self but when you kist,</L>
<L>I likewise to my self had kept my Fist.</L>
<L><HI>Catso,</HI> quoth <HI>Hero,</HI> was that all the Matter?</L>
<L>Indeed you shan't find fault with that herea'ter,</L>
<L>But try me once again: he cry'd Come 'an.</L>
<L>But from her Sluts Trick she cou'd not refrain:</L>
<L><PB N="54" REF="29"/>
Whereat <HI>Leander</HI> once more did look big,</L>
<L>And sputt'ring call'd her Impudent <HI>Tom-Rigg:</HI></L>
<L>While she with Court'sie said, no one exact is</L>
<L>In any thing at first; but let me practise</L>
<L>On you a while, and whip me, if I'm missing</L>
<L>A Tittle in your Method nice of kissing;</L>
<L>But sweet <HI>Leander,</HI> do not turn away</L>
<L>A faithful willing Servant the first day.</L>
<L>As Courts do say, Assurance innocent</L>
<L>I have, but not as you said, Impudent:</L>
<L>I have no harm in me, although I'm frolick,</L>
<L>Which most men (as my Mother tells me) do like.</L>
<L>Therefore but for your satisfaction,</L>
<L>And but to you have now good humour shown.</L>
<L>For as you did observe your self, I'm rugged</L>
<L>To other solkes, ill-natur'd, cross, and dogged:</L>
<L><PB N="55" REF="29"/>
But wou'd endeavour to please you alone,</L>
<L>'Cause besides you I pleased am with none.</L>
<L>With that she pump'd some tears into her eyes,</L>
<L>Which into his did pump up some likewise.</L>
<L>For tears do tears beget, and 'tis a true thing,</L>
<L>The Lovers falling out is Loves renewing.</L>
<L>But while he sob'd, <HI>Hero</HI> had prudent thought</L>
<L>Of striking of the Iron while 'twas hot.</L>
<L>Therefore took out crack'd Groat from Purse of Leather,</L>
<L>To witness they wou'd thenceforth lie together,</L>
<L>And ask'd him if he'd deign to break it with her.</L>
<L>He chearfully did lend her all his force;</L>
<L>So they to joyn themselves crack'd Groat divorce.</L>
<L>Now Lover mark you well from Custom antique</L>
<L>I mean thou silly Rogue that art so frantick</L>
<L><PB N="56" REF="30"/>
To bustle for a Mistress, sigh, and sob,</L>
<L>When thou hast not a Penny in thy Fob:</L>
<L>For all your pains is lost when you have woo'd her,</L>
<L>If Money you have not your hearts to so'der.</L>
<L>For now not one like <HI>Hero</HI> will disburse</L>
<L>On Love a grey Groat out of her own Purse.</L>
<L>Nay they'll not trust on tick a pair of Kisses,</L>
<L>Nor can you trade with Rhimes, or fine promisses.</L>
<L>But <HI>Hero</HI> was a Lady of a thousand,</L>
<L>Who by her self of her own heart was cousen'd:</L>
<L>For sure <HI>Leander</HI> knew no Politicks,</L>
<L>No Lime-twig words, or subtle sly Dog-tricks</L>
<L>To chase, to circumvent her, or to catch'er;</L>
<L>Or where she itch'd did know, or where to scratch her;</L>
<L><PB N="57" REF="30"/>
For she was forc'd, although 'twas not the fashion,</L>
<L>To put him first in mind of consummation;</L>
<L>And told him that about Twelve of the Clock</L>
<L>She wou'd expect him with clean Sheets &amp; Smock,</L>
<L>At her own Mothers House, at sign of Tow'r:</L>
<L>But warn'd him he shou'd knock at the Back-door;</L>
<L>And that her old Nurse should sit up, and spin,</L>
<L>To drown the noise he'd make, and let him in.</L>
<L>In the mean time to th' May-pole, and the Green</L>
<L>She bid him go to see, and to be seen,</L>
<L>Or where he wou'd might saunter up and down,</L>
<L>And count the Signs, and fine things of the Town:</L>
<L>Or to the Shore might go, if nothing else</L>
<L>He had to do, and pick up pretty Shells.</L>
<L>But howsoe're himself he chose to recreate,</L>
<L>He should be sure to keep her Honours Secret.</L>
<L><PB N="58" REF="31"/>
There are, quoth she, who kill a womans honour,</L>
<L>Rather than lose their Glory to have won her.</L>
<L>But were there Justice, sure they shou'd have rea∣son</L>
<L>By Halter done, to their pernicious treason.</L>
<L>For plaguy, and unspeakable's the wrong</L>
<L>To the whole world by those Blabs of their tongue</L>
<L>Many an Innocent on both sides mourn,</L>
<L>Look pale, and pine away, in Feavers burn,</L>
<L>And can't trust, nor be trusted for good turn,</L>
<L>But he who is of Female good name chary,</L>
<L>With the whole Sex sure as it were may marry.</L>
<L>Be warn'd <HI>Leander</HI> then; for I defie</L>
<L>'Till now the world to say that black's my Eye,</L>
<L>And none cou'd touch my Reputation</L>
<L>'Till now with man I've been two hours alone;</L>
<L><PB N="59" REF="31"/>
Which lest that it shou'd come to be Town-talk,</L>
<L>Prithee my sweet <HI>Leander,</HI> let us walk.</L>
<L>Why don't you wag, my Heart, why do you stay?</L>
<L>Quoth he, d'y' think that I'll lead you the way?</L>
<L>Sure, sure, Fair <HI>Hero,</HI> I'll not go before ye:</L>
<L>Pish, pish, quoth she, again that's such a Story,</L>
<L>I am the Priestess, and must shut the door;</L>
<L>Leave Fooling prithee, and go on before.</L>
<L>Only remember that you keep your hour;</L>
<L>And when 'tis dark, find out your way to th' tow'r.</L>
<L>Then rather than be troublesom, he chose</L>
<L>To do as he was bid, and follow's Nose:</L>
<L>And to the Woods (as Lovers use) did ramble.</L>
<L>Mean while his Mistress to the Town did amble.</L>
<L>But 'twixt true Lovers (you'l say 'tis a wonder)</L>
<L>There's no absence though ne're so much asunder.</L>
<L><PB N="60" REF="32"/>
For busie mind can find out no evasion,</L>
<L>Sweet Miss will hang upon imagination.</L>
<L>Though <HI>Hero</HI> and her Dear went quite contrary,</L>
<L>Yet in his heart and mind she still did tarry;</L>
<L>Or else ('tis thought) ere Twelve he had been weary;</L>
<L>Though he had all the pretty Recreations,</L>
<L>With which Lovers do hush their whuling passi∣ons.</L>
<L>As he stalk'd on sometimes he fell a Quaiting</L>
<L>Round Tiles to be unmindful of his Waiting.</L>
<L>And as he reel'd along the green Hedge-Rows,</L>
<L>He rummag'd them for Black-berries and Sloes.</L>
<L>Or then on Mole-hill squatted, with a Key,</L>
<L>Did whistle out a chearing Roundeley,</L>
<L>'Till Emmet put him out to make him scratch</L>
<L>Impatient Buttock, where she made it itch:</L>
<L><PB N="61" REF="32"/>
Or by cool Spring lay down on Bed of Dazies,</L>
<L>And on her Cristal Surface made Love-faces,</L>
<L>Or in her murmuring soft conversation</L>
<L>Did weep, and murmur too to cool his Passion:</L>
<L>With <HI>Philomel,</HI> or Pye, or Daw did prate,</L>
<L>And sometime too with Gossip Eccho chat:</L>
<L>Or with the Tag of Codpiece Point on Bark</L>
<L>Of Trees did scratch and scribble <HI>Hero</HI>'s Mark▪</L>
<L>Or did unravel all her Sacred Name,</L>
<L>To knit it up again in Anagram.</L>
<L>And sometime in tight Rhime as much bely'd her,</L>
<L>As if the Rogue ne'er in his Life had spy'd her;</L>
<L>For sure <HI>Leander</HI> was a <HI>Burlesque</HI> Poet,</L>
<L>Though 'till in Love (like me) he did not know it.</L>
<L>In such like exercise he whil'd away</L>
<L>The fant'ring minutes of the tedious day:</L>
<L><PB N="62" REF="33"/>
But when night came, to keep off Spright or Else,</L>
<L>He talk'd, and sung, and whistled to himself.</L>
<L>But in the Woods no longer then wou'd tarry,</L>
<L>Lest that his Breech shou'd feel the Nails of Fairy.</L>
<L>He therefore back to <HI>Sestus</HI> Town did creep,</L>
<L>And while Folkes were abed, and all asleep,</L>
<L>(As oft his Betters) on a Bulk, or Bench,</L>
<L>Three or four hours had patience for his Wench.</L>
<L>But ere the drawling Clock knockt out thrice four</L>
<L>He was a knocking at back-door of Tow'r,</L>
<L>But first (some say) he had a special care</L>
<L>To make the most of his long yellow hair,</L>
<L>And with his Comb, and Fingers made it stare</L>
<L>Methodically, and look killing big,</L>
<L>For he grand <HI>Virtuoso</HI> was in Wig.</L>
<L>Besides he put his willing Hat in mind</L>
<L>Of cocking up before, and eke behind:</L>
<L><PB N="63" REF="33"/>
And then with single Knuckle; and no more,</L>
<L>Inform'd the watchful Nurse he was at dore,</L>
<L>By whom ('tis said) he was not long unheard;</L>
<L>As <HI>Hero</HI> knew she was a trusty Card.</L>
<L>For on Love-Errands oft she made her trudge,</L>
<L>Indeed, she was an honest careful Drudge,</L>
<L>Loves painful Char-woman, and ever did</L>
<L>Help on all Bawdy work in time of need.</L>
<L>When she had let <HI>Leander</HI> in, she made him</L>
<L>Pull off his Shoes ere she to <HI>Hero</HI> led him:</L>
<L>For by the door of <HI>Hero</HI>'s Mothers Chamber</L>
<L>To <HI>Hero</HI>'s Garret he was bound to clamber.</L>
<L>Besides she knew Love is inhans'd by fear;</L>
<L>So stollen Bread and Cheese is mighty Chear.</L>
<L>But though <HI>Leander</HI> went as if on Eggs,</L>
<L>Yet he so loftily did bear his Legs,</L>
<L><PB N="64" REF="34"/>
That of four or five steps, he made but one,</L>
<L>And lingring <HI>Hero</HI> was no more alone,</L>
<L>Nor unprepar'd for his Reception.</L>
<L>Her Garret was new swept, and she well drest</L>
<L>For exercise in <HI>Just-au-Corps</HI> or Vest,</L>
<L>As those who can't endure to be strait-lac'd;</L>
<L>Or may be in a Petticoat, and Wastcoat,</L>
<L>In Bawdy <HI>Indian</HI> Gown, or Bawds long last-coat,</L>
<L>In Cloak of Ermin, or a <HI>Tyrian</HI> Mantle;</L>
<L>But for my part, what she had on, I can't tell;</L>
<L>For some are not asham'd to say a Blanquet;</L>
<L>But two joyn'd-stools were cover'd with a Ban∣quet,</L>
<L>Which made her Dear <HI>Leander</HI> not much matter</L>
<L>How she was drest, 'twas that made his mouth water:</L>
<L><PB N="65" REF="34"/>
She saw't, and therefore let her Passion wait,</L>
<L>Till hungry Lover had ta'ne out his Bait.</L>
<L>So strait, to lose no time, did pull him down</L>
<L>Into a Chair with Arms, and cry'd, Fall on,</L>
<L>If you can like of any thing that's here.</L>
<L>He vow'd it was most excellent good Chear,</L>
<L>But he did praise it better by his Swallow,</L>
<L>And there was nought that was not a <HI>Regallo.</HI></L>
<L>Botargo first, and a Red Herring, for</L>
<L>She still had her <HI>pet it morceau aboire.</HI></L>
<L>But for <HI>Leanders</HI> curious maiden Chaps</L>
<L>There were provided dainty fine Flip-flaps,</L>
<L>Apple-pie, Custard, Florentine, and Cheese-cake,</L>
<L>And only as I said before, for his sake,</L>
<L>Gingerbread, and stew'd Prunes of her own stew∣ing,</L>
<L>And for his Drink, Stypone of her Brewing;</L>
<L><PB N="66" REF="35"/>
To which, <HI>Hero,</HI> and he were both beholden,</L>
<L>For modest Lover it did soon embolden,</L>
<L>To take her by the sweaty hand, and sip</L>
<L>Far stronger Nectar from her Blabber-Lip.</L>
<L>And when she had made him drink off his rest,</L>
<L>He cou'd begin a Brimmer to the Best.</L>
<L>But subtle <HI>Hero</HI> in her over-tunning</L>
<L>Of empty Lover, was but over-cunning.</L>
<L>For quite contrary to her wise intent,</L>
<L>All she tunn'd up in him had a false Vent.</L>
<L>Indeed she made him ready for the Bed,</L>
<L>And had the Drunkards sport to hold his head,</L>
<L>But she unfortunate, meant something else,</L>
<L>And ere she was aware, o're-turn'd the Bells;</L>
<L>So oflewd expectation quite did miss,</L>
<L>As now chaste Reader doth I'm sure, of his.</L>
<L><PB N="67" REF="35"/>
But be not angry, ere Cock-crowing season,</L>
<L>To you, and <HI>Hero</HI> too I'll see done reason.</L>
<L>But let her put <HI>Leander</HI> first to Bed,</L>
<L>And on Flock-Pillow rest Lop-heavy Head;</L>
<L>Then fit it with a Coifin stead of Cap,</L>
<L>Tuck up the Cloaths in order to his Nap,</L>
<L>And then let her a while but pick her Toes,</L>
<L>And Lamp goes out, and into Bed she goes.</L>
<L>Then (as I told you) ere the Cock crow'd thrice</L>
<L>And <HI>Hero</HI> had piss'd once, <HI>Leander</HI> twice,</L>
<L>(But forward Sir, pray do not now mistake)</L>
<L>Did yawn, and stretch, and civilly awake</L>
<L>At the first Summons of her Elbow, which</L>
<L>On purpose lent his side a plaguie stitch.</L>
<L>Then did he puff, and belch, and sigh, and groan,</L>
<L>And to the Gods make lamentable moan:</L>
<L><PB N="68" REF="36"/>
But <HI>Hero</HI> for her sake took pity on him,</L>
<L>Did stroak him, feel his Pulses, and bemoan him,</L>
<L>And charitably too his Stomack settle,</L>
<L>By help of Life-restoring Pewter Bottle:</L>
<L>So by her Aid, Directions, and Dalliance,</L>
<L>As well's he cou'd he made out's new Alliance.</L>
<L>But spiteful Jade <HI>Aurora</HI> strait intruding,</L>
<L>There was an end then of the Secret Wedding:</L>
<L>And glad <HI>Leander</HI> in such hast arose,</L>
<L>That out of Bed he tumbled on his Nose;</L>
<L>And for his own Stockings put on <HI>Hero</HI>'s:</L>
<L>Fate's still contriving Lovers to disclose.</L>
<L>Nor staid to wash his stinking hands, or put on</L>
<L>His Azure Band, or Shamey Doublet button:</L>
<L>But with a Kiss took leave of his dear Bride,</L>
<L>Resolving for her not to lose his Tide;</L>
<L><PB N="69" REF="36"/>
For from the Shore was heard thrice, <HI>Eastward hol</HI></L>
<L>And with his Towns-folkes he was mad to go:</L>
<L>So lost no time; but while he was let out,</L>
<L>To the old Nurse made this true Lovers doubt,</L>
<L>That <HI>Hero</HI> wou'd procure her self some <HI>Monsieur,</HI></L>
<L>Who many a good time and oft wou'd bounce her</L>
<L>Ere he shou'd get o'th' t'other side 'oth' water.</L>
<L>To which she said Fie, Fie man, no such matter.</L>
<L>Though heavy Judgments fall upon ye, you men</L>
<L>Will never leave your base thoughts of poor Wo∣men.</L>
<L>But time will come (and she or none cou'd tell,</L>
<L>For she in Magick Art had devilish skill,</L>
<L>And on a Col-staff oft had gall'd her Breech,</L>
<L>Was tri'd, and got off'cause she was a Witch)</L>
<L>When all men shall for something be afraid,</L>
<L>And for your Jealoufie be soundly paid.</L>
<L><PB N="70" REF="37"/>
When Love incens'd, won't tyrannize alone</L>
<L>In Lovers heart (as now he doth) but bone:</L>
<L>When Lover for his Miss obtain'd shall groan,</L>
<L>And through a single Nostril tune his moan:</L>
<L>And jealous man shall envy happy Brute,</L>
<L>Who without fear, or shame does go to Rut.</L>
<L>To this <HI>Leander</HI> nothing cou'd reply,</L>
<L>For Prophesies must give themselves the Lie.</L>
<L>But Pox upon her soul for her Record,</L>
<L>All the World knows she was as good's her word.</L>
<L>She wou'd have farther spun the Pockey Riddle,</L>
<L>But Youth in hast did break't off in the middle,</L>
<L>And left her, and Town <HI>Sestus</HI> 'till dark night,</L>
<L>When he was to return by Candle-light;</L>
<L>The same that was as Sea-light in that Entry</L>
<L>Where marking <HI>Hero</HI> in the Bar sate Centry;</L>
<L><PB N="71" REF="37"/>
As he, and <HI>Hero</HI> had contriv'd, was his</L>
<L>To keep him in his way where no path is.</L>
<L>And by her means he did not run aground,</L>
<L>But in the right Port whither he was bound</L>
<L>Unladed safe, and sound his precious Stowage,</L>
<L>And made (as Folkes do say) a happy Voyage,</L>
<L>Nay some (at least) say half a dozen, but</L>
<L>Dame Fortune first, or last, doth prove a Slut.</L>
<L>She did contest with the more faithless wind,</L>
<L>Which should be more false to him, or unkind,</L>
<L>For in the Window of vex'd <HI>Hero</HI>'s Garret</L>
<L>Five or six long Watch-lights in vain did blare out,</L>
<L>Ere he cou'd put to Sea; and when he did,</L>
<L>It had been better he at home had staid.</L>
<L>But though the huffing surly Winds did nose him,</L>
<L>And strutting Billows crowded to oppose him,</L>
<L><PB N="72" REF="38"/>
From's Mistress he no longer wou'd be kept,</L>
<L>But like a drunken Heroe headlong leapt</L>
<L>Amidst his Foes, resolving to come at her,</L>
<L>Though Seas on Seas were set, and hills of Water</L>
<L>On watry hills to intercept his course;</L>
<L>But Death old-fashion'd Lovers can't divorce.</L>
<L>As Reader (if you've any patience) you</L>
<L>Too soon, too soon, alas, alas! shall know:</L>
<L>But Gossip first I know you wou'd be prying</L>
<L>Into the manner of our Lovers dying:</L>
<L><HI>Leander</HI> wou'd not give his head for th' washing</L>
<L>You may be sure, nor was afraid of Dashing:</L>
<L>He cuff'd the Waves aside, and through did break</L>
<L>His way, in spight of Northern Blubber-Cheek;</L>
<L>Mean while ('tis said) they made e'ne nothing of him,</L>
<L>And while he puff'd, and sputtred, did but scoffe him.</L>
<L><PB N="73" REF="38"/>
And as in Blanket you wou'd toss a Whelp,</L>
<L>Tost him, while he no more himself cou'd help.</L>
<L>And though he sprawl'd, and kept on going still,</L>
<L>It was, as one may say, e'ne but up hill.</L>
<L>So to his Oars of Flesh such chearing words,</L>
<L>Was fain to use, as Errants to their Swords;</L>
<L>And told them, if they wou'd row stoutly on,</L>
<L>They shou'd embrace his naked Miss anon.</L>
<L>But finding soon that Harangue prov'd but idle,</L>
<L>He turn'd his Stile, the wind and waves to whedle:</L>
<L>And vow'd if they wou'd please but to reprieve him</L>
<L>From drowning 'till he came back, he'd forgive 'um.</L>
<L>But Fate whose slaves they were, cou'd not be chous'd,</L>
<L>For all his Vows he still was soundly dous'd:</L>
<L><PB N="74" REF="39"/>
Yet sneering Fate but to augment her sport,</L>
<L>Permitted him almost to touch his Port.</L>
<L>So Tyrant Puss of Mouse does make a Fool,</L>
<L>And let's him get again half into's hole.</L>
<L>But then <HI>Leanders</HI> time was come, when Lamp</L>
<L>Went out, or when his left Leg had the Cramp.</L>
<L>For he so much in Love was you may see,</L>
<L>He quite forgot a String about his Knee,</L>
<L><HI>Hero</HI> mean while who in her Bed had tost</L>
<L>As much as he at Sea had, or almost.</L>
<L>For she had dream'd of Flowers all the night,</L>
<L>Shrewd sign that some body is to turn Spright.</L>
<L>So weary of her Dreams, awak'd and rose;</L>
<L>But some say she awak'd ta'ne by the Nose</L>
<L>With the rude Haut-Goust of deceased Lamp,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Omen</HI> seiz'd her heart with pannick Damp</L>
<L><PB N="75" REF="39"/>
For her Sweet-heart, but ah! when she did hear</L>
<L>The Winds and Sea so loud, she was past fear,</L>
<L>And by her croaking bowels then cou'd tell</L>
<L>(Were he at Sea) all with him was not well,</L>
<L>So grown impatient, to the Window flew,</L>
<L>And from her Eye-lids proking off the Glew,</L>
<L>Into the boiling water fell a staring,</L>
<L>Where she perceiv'd her dear Duck dead as her∣ring.</L>
<L>But Day but just had shewn her Scarlet Snout,</L>
<L>So she had time for comfortable doubt,</L>
<L>And took her poor <HI>Leander</HI> for a Whale;</L>
<L>But prying to find out the proof of's Tail,</L>
<L>She out of Window thrust her self so far,</L>
<L>That Tiptoes slipt, and ere she was awar</L>
<L>(Some do dispute it though) she tipt clean over</L>
<L>Into the Brine upon her pickled Lover.</L>
<L><PB N="76" REF="40"/>
Now hasty Lover do not damn the River,</L>
<L>Which though a while true Lovers it did sever,</L>
<L>Yet did unite 'um afterward for ever.</L>
<L>And let none take my tristful Song to heart,</L>
<L>Or for drown'd Lovers be concern'd a Fart;</L>
<L>For they but div'd directly to <HI>Elizium,</HI></L>
<L>Where such Folkes pass their time as you cou'd wish 'um.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="40"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

