<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The hearts-index, or, Self-knowledg [sic] together with I. the wonderful change that the word and spirit do work upon the heart when a sinner is converted II. the excellency of grace above nature III. the safety and calm of such as have sued out their pardon in Christ / by R. Younge ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Younge, Richard.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A67756</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing Y160</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R16696</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12546042</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12546042</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">63054</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A67756)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63054)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 952:33)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The hearts-index, or, Self-knowledg [sic] together with I. the wonderful change that the word and spirit do work upon the heart when a sinner is converted II. the excellency of grace above nature III. the safety and calm of such as have sued out their pardon in Christ / by R. Younge ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Younge, Richard.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>32 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by J. Hayes, and are to be sold by Mrs. Crips ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1667.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</NOTE><NOTE>Caption title.</NOTE><NOTE>Imprint taken from colophon.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Calvinism --  Great Britain.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A67756">
<STC T="W">Y160</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12546042</BIBNO>
<VID>63054</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE Hearts-Index. OR Self-Knowledg: Together with
<LIST>
<ITEM>I. The wonderful Change that the <HI>Word</HI> and <HI>Spirit,</HI> do work upon the <HI>Heart,</HI> when a Sinner is converted.</ITEM>
<ITEM>II. The excellency of <HI>Grace</HI> above <HI>Nature.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>III. The <HI>Safety</HI> and <HI>Calm</HI> of such as have sued out their pardon in <HI>Christ.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>By R. YOUNGE of <HI>Roxwell</HI> in <HI>Essex.</HI></P>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="imprimatur">
<P>Imprimatur</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Ex Aed. Sab.</HI> <DATE>Aug. 8, 1663</DATE>.</DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Geo. Stradling, <HI>S. T. P. Rev. in Christo Patr. Gilb. Epist. Lond. à Sac. Domest.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<P>Section <HI>I.</HI></P>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">P</SEG>Robable it is, that that <HI>medicine</HI> which hath cured one desperate <HI>Patient,</HI> if it be communicated, may work the same effect upon others; the con∣cealment whereof, would argue in a <HI>Physitian,</HI> either too <HI>much lucre,</HI> or too <HI>little love.</HI> However, the conscience of good intentions in themselves (let their suc∣cess be what it will) is both a discharge and comfort to a free and willing mind.</P>
<P><PB N="2" REF="2"/>
A <HI>fine wit,</HI> and a <HI>Christian will,</HI> is like the little <HI>Bee,</HI> that will not off the meanest <HI>flower,</HI> until she hath made somewhat of it: whereas an <HI>unsanctified heart,</HI> will (<HI>spider</HI>-like) <HI>suck poy∣son</HI> from the choisest of <HI>flowers.</HI></P>
<P>Every line of <HI>God's word</HI> shall adde finew to the virtuous mind; and withal heal that vice, which would be springing in it. But with the carnally minded, it is far otherwise. The same re∣port, wherewith the spirit of <HI>Rahab melteth, hardens</HI> the <HI>King of Jericho,</HI> Josh. 2. <HI>Sergius Paulus</HI> was <HI>converted, Elimas obdu∣rated,</HI> at the same Sermon, <HI>Acts</HI> 13. that one hard saying of our <HI>Saviour,</HI> John 6. like a <HI>file sharpened</HI> eleven of his <HI>Apostles</HI>; while it so <HI>blunted</HI> the rest of his <HI>Disciples,</HI> that many of them <HI>murmured, and from that time went back, and walked no more with him,</HI> verse 66, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> Whence observe, that as <HI>all bodies,</HI> are not equally apt to be wrought upon, by the same <HI>medicine</HI>; so are not <HI>all souls</HI> by the <HI>same means</HI> of Grace. One remains <HI>obstinate</HI> and <HI>refractory,</HI> whiles others are <HI>pliable.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sin</HI> and <HI>Satan,</HI> have no <HI>Servants</HI> but the <HI>simple.</HI> As for in∣stance: A <HI>wise man</HI> hearing in what a dangerous condition he is in, by reason of <HI>original</HI> and <HI>actual sins,</HI> and how God is so incensed with wrath and indignation against him, that he means utterly to destroy him, if he go on in his impenitency; <HI>foreseeth the evil of Hell,</HI> and <HI>preventeth it,</HI> by departing from his evil wayes: but <HI>fools go on and are careless,</HI> Prov. 22.3. and 14.16. Stark fools indeed: For if their eyes were opened, to see in what a condition, they are content at present to continue in; they should need no intreaty, to turn their course another way. <HI>Luther</HI> says, that if a man could perfectly see his own evils, and the misery that attends them, the fight thereof would be a per∣fect <HI>Hell</HI> unto him: and this indeed might prove to be his way to <HI>Heaven</HI>; For then, and not till then, a man sees what need he hath of a <HI>Saviour</HI>; and then he begins tightly to prize the <HI>joys of Heaven,</HI> when he sees he hath escaped the <HI>Flames of Hell,</HI> which those fools before spoken of, never mean to do, because they think themselves <HI>wise, good, happy,</HI> and what not? The case of all men by Nature. And until that <HI>vail</HI> or <HI>curtain</HI> which is <HI>drawn over their hearts,</HI> be removed, and taken away by unseigned <HI>repentance,</HI> and turning to the <HI>Lord,</HI> they remain
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
stark blind to all saving truths, as the <HI>Apostle</HI> plainly sets down, 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 3.14, 15, 16, 17, 18. See <HI>Rev.</HI> 3.17. 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 6.4. And the truth is, were it not for <HI>pride</HI> and <HI>Ignorance</HI> (springing hence) every man would make it his main business, <HI>to work out his salvation with fear and trembling.</HI> But to proceed, for this is but an excursion, let in, by way of a <HI>parenthesis, and in zeal</HI> for their good; that desire not their own. The <HI>Ninivites</HI> by hearkning to <HI>Jonah,</HI> and those <HI>murtherers of the Lord of Life,</HI> by listning to <HI>Peter,</HI> were <HI>converted</HI> and <HI>saved,</HI> Jonah 3.4, 5. Acts 2.37. <HI>Wax</HI> (we know) yeeldeth sooner to the <HI>seal,</HI> than <HI>steel</HI> to the <HI>stamp.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 2. Of <HI>Hearers,</HI> there are usually <HI>four sorts,</HI> as our <HI>Sa∣viour</HI> shews, in the <HI>Parable of the seed,</HI> Mat. 13.3, to 24. As first, <HI>An honest and good heart,</HI> will not return from hearing the Word unbettered: yea, he will so note what is spoken to his own sin, that it shall <HI>increase his knowledg,</HI> and <HI>lessen his vices.</HI> As who (by looking in a <HI>glass</HI>) shall spy <HI>spots</HI> in his <HI>face,</HI> and will not forthwith wipe them out? A <HI>wise man</HI> will not have one sin twice repeated unto him; Yea, he more rejoyceth, <HI>in being overcome</HI> with a wise and gracious advice, then he would have rejoyced <HI>in a revengeful victory.</HI> Of which we have a rare example, 1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 25.32, 33. A true argument of an ingenuous nature. Whereas those that will not hearken to, nor obey the voice of <HI>Christ,</HI> but rage and storm; are more stubborn than the <HI>wind</HI> and <HI>sea,</HI> Luke 8.24, 25. enough to make them blush blood, when told of it. But</P>
<P>Secondly, Another sort of <HI>Hearers,</HI> are like <HI>Tully's strange soil; much rain</HI> leaves them <HI>still</HI> as <HI>dry as dust.</HI> Or the <HI>Wolf</HI> in the <HI>Emblem,</HI> which though it <HI>suckt the Goat,</HI> kept notwith∣standing his <HI>Woolfish nature</HI> still. And indeed, untill the <HI>spirit of God</HI> meekens the <HI>soul,</HI> say what you will, it minds <HI>nothing,</HI> or <HI>nothing</HI> to <HI>purpose.</HI> Whatever an impenitent sinner hears, it presently passes away, like the <HI>sound</HI> of a <HI>Bell</HI> that is rung. Let <HI>testimonies</HI> and <HI>examples</HI> never so much concern them, it makes an impression but <HI>skin,</HI> or <HI>ear deep</HI>: For as in an <HI>hour-glass</HI> or <HI>conduit,</HI> that which in one hour <HI>runneth in</HI> the same in another hour <HI>runneth out</HI> again. Who may be resembled to the <HI>Smiths Iron,</HI> put it into the <HI>fire</HI> it is much <HI>softned,</HI> but put it into the <HI>water</HI> it is <HI>harder</HI> than before.</P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="3"/>
Thirdly, Another sort will very orderly <HI>hear</HI> the Word, and <HI>delight</HI> in it, until it comes home to their <HI>consciences,</HI> touches their Copy hold (as <HI>John</HI> served <HI>Herod</HI>) but then they will turn their backs upon it, as the <HI>Jews</HI> served our <HI>Saviour,</HI> John 6.66. the <HI>Athenians, Paul,</HI> Acts 17.16, to 34. and <HI>Ahab, Micaiah,</HI> 1 Kings 228. Now these that will not hear an <HI>untoothsome truth,</HI> but turn their backs upon and fly from instruction. <HI>Joh.</HI> 3.19, 20, 21. not onely declare themselves to be <HI>guilty persons</HI> (for <HI>he confesseth the fact, who to judgment turneth his back:</HI> And 'tis onely the <HI>weak sighted,</HI> that cannot abide the <HI>light</HI>) but it proves them to be <HI>out of all hope to become better.</HI> For that sin is <HI>past cure,</HI> which turns <HI>from,</HI> and <HI>refuseth the cure,</HI> Deut. 17.12. Prov 29.1. 1 Sam. 2.25. 2 Chron. 25.16. turn to the pla∣ces. And take this for a <HI>Rule,</HI> if ever you see a <HI>drowning man refuse help,</HI> conclude him a <HI>wilful murderer.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 3. Fourthly and lastly, (for I pass by those blocks; that can hear the Word powerfully delivered for twenty or thirty years together, and mind no more the <HI>spirituality of the matter,</HI> than the <HI>seats</HI> they <HI>fit on,</HI> or the <HI>stones</HI> they <HI>tread on.</HI>) There are a generation of hearers, who being told the naked truth, plainly reproved for their sins, shewn the judgments of <HI>God,</HI> and the due of what they deserve, and are like to undergo, if they go on, to the end they may <HI>repent</HI> and <HI>believe,</HI> that so they may be <HI>saved,</HI> will (<HI>Ahab</HI> like) <HI>carp,</HI> and <HI>fret,</HI> &amp; <HI>chafe,</HI> and <HI>fume,</HI> and <HI>swell</HI>; and <HI>spurn,</HI> against the very <HI>Word of God,</HI> and be ready to <HI>burst</HI> again for being so <HI>sharp</HI> and <HI>searching</HI>; and thereupon persecute the Messenger, as <HI>Herodias</HI> did <HI>John,</HI> and the <HI>Phari∣sees, Christ.</HI> They love application as dearly, as a Dog does a cudgel. So that like <HI>Adders,</HI> they are not only <HI>deaf</HI> to the <HI>Charmer,</HI> but like <HI>Slow-worms,</HI> they <HI>hiss,</HI> and then turn their <HI>tails</HI> to <HI>sting</HI> him.</P>
<P><HI>Gods</HI> holy <HI>precepts</HI> and <HI>prohibitions harden</HI> them; as the <HI>Sun</HI> hardens <HI>clay,</HI> and <HI>water hot iron.</HI> Or else they inrage them, as a <HI>furious mastiff Dog,</HI> is the <HI>madder for his chain.</HI> But when it comes to this, that men spurn at the means, and are <HI>hardned with the word,</HI> as <HI>steel is hardned with strokes</HI>; or as <HI>Bulls</HI> grow <HI>mad</HI> with <HI>baiting:</HI> the best way is to leave them to their <HI>Judg,</HI> who hath <HI>messengers of wrath,</HI> for them that despise the <HI>messen∣gers
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
of his love,</HI> Psal. 81.11, 12. See <HI>Luke</HI> 10.10, 11. Prov. 29 &amp; 1.24, 25, 26, to 33. 2 Chron. 25.16 20. 1 Sam. 2.25. And in reason, <HI>herbs</HI> that are worse for <HI>watering, trees</HI> that are less <HI>fruit∣ful</HI> for <HI>digging, dunging, pruning,</HI> are to be <HI>rooted out,</HI> or <HI>hewed down</HI> And to admonish them is to no more purpose, than if one should speak to <HI>lifeless stones,</HI> or <HI>senseless plants,</HI> or <HI>witless beasts:</HI> for they will <HI>never fear</HI> any thing, till they be in <HI>Hell-fire.</HI> Wherefore <HI>God</HI> leaves them to be confuted with <HI>fire and brim∣stone,</HI> since nothing else will do it.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 4. Thus you see what a wonderful difference there is in Hearers! Onely herein they agree, all men (good and bad) <HI>love the light as it shines</HI>; but the most of men <HI>hate it, as it dis∣covers and directs.</HI> But the difference is so great, that it is ad∣mirable to think, how some men would not be prevailed with∣all, though an <HI>Angel should be sent unto them from the dead.</HI> And yet with what small means some others have been converted, as were <HI>Justin</HI> the <HI>Philosopher, Ciprian</HI> the <HI>Nicromancer,</HI> Saint <HI>Austin, Fulgentius, Francisco Junius, Malancton, Adrianus, La∣timer,</HI> and many others.</P>
<P>One treating upon the <HI>Prodigal son,</HI> and the <HI>Thief upon the Cross,</HI> mentions <HI>two famous strumpets,</HI> that were <HI>suddenly con∣verted</HI> by this onely argument, that <HI>God seeth</HI> all things, even in the <HI>dark,</HI> when the <HI>doors are shut,</HI> and the <HI>Curtains drawn</HI>; and <HI>Mountaigne</HI> tells of a <HI>Gallant,</HI> that (sporting with a <HI>Cur∣tezan</HI> in a house of sin) happened to ask her name, which she said was <HI>Mary</HI>; whereat he was so stricken with reverence and remorse, that he instantly both cast off the Harlot, and amended his whole future life. And indeed no <HI>means</HI> can be too weak where <HI>God</HI> intends <HI>success</HI>: yea, a thought onely hath some∣times served the turn. Nor needs there any more to a clarified understanding, than the bare thought of <HI>Gods Omnipresence, Omnisciency,</HI> or <HI>Omnipotency</HI>; as being present every where, knowing every thought and intent of the heart, and being al∣mighty to <HI>punish or reward evil and good</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 5 And so much of the kinds of hearers Onely a <HI>Que∣stion</HI> or <HI>Scruple</HI> may hereupon arise. The <HI>Minister</HI> or <HI>Author</HI> out of compassion to their precious souls, would shew them from <HI>Gods Word,</HI> the very <HI>faces of their hearts,</HI> and like <HI>Peter</HI>
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
to <HI>Cornelius,</HI> Acts 11. tell them that, whereby (with blessing from above) they might be saved, <HI>vers.</HI> 14. the which some do kindly entertain, as <HI>Lot</HI> did those <HI>Angels</HI> that came to fetch him out of <HI>Sodom,</HI> Gen. 19. Others as churlishly reject, and as villainously entreat and handle them, as the <HI>Ammonites</HI> did <HI>Davids messengers,</HI> 2 Sam. 10.4. Wherein (may some say) lies the difference?</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> I could give you sundry <HI>Reasons</HI> of it, I'le onely name a few, being injoyned to contract all my matter into two sheets.</P>
<P>First, <HI>Will</HI> makes the difference, and who makes the <HI>difference of wills,</HI> but he that made them? He that creates the new heart, leaves a <HI>stone</HI> in one bosom, puts flesh into another; and yet if <HI>God</HI> denies his grace, it is onely when he sees it contemned: As <HI>God</HI> oftentimes is so provoked, by their obstinate hardness and impenitency, that he gives them over to <HI>Satan,</HI> and up to the hardness of their own hearts, to be led by their lusts, and to walk in their own counsels; as it is, <HI>Psal.</HI> 81.12. <HI>Rom.</HI> 1.24, 26. So that not <HI>God,</HI> but our selves, are the authors of <HI>sin,</HI> and of our own <HI>damnation,</HI> as it is, <HI>Hos.</HI> 13.9. Of which, more in its due place.</P>
<P>Secondly, The holy <HI>Word of God,</HI> which is <HI>Spirit</HI> and <HI>Life,</HI> is so <HI>quick, powerful</HI> and <HI>operative,</HI> that it will have its effect: where it does not <HI>quicken,</HI> it <HI>kils.</HI> None ever heard it, but they were either <HI>better</HI> or <HI>worse</HI> by it. It is a <HI>holy fire</HI>; those whom it doth not <HI>purifie</HI> and <HI>cleanse,</HI> by <HI>melting</HI> into <HI>repentance,</HI> it doth <HI>consume</HI> and <HI>destroy</HI> by <HI>burning,</HI> into the <HI>ashes</HI> of <HI>prophane∣ness</HI> here, of <HI>confusion hereafter.</HI> It is the <HI>power of God unto sal∣vation, to every one that believeth,</HI> Rom. 1.16. And <HI>a sweet savour of life unto life, to them that are saved,</HI> 2 Cor. 2.16. But it be∣comes <HI>the savour of death unto death,</HI> unto such as <HI>wrest</HI> and <HI>pervert the same to their own destruction,</HI> 2 Pet. 3.16. And no marvel, for the <HI>same cause</HI> may have <HI>divers</HI> and <HI>contrary effects,</HI> in respect of <HI>sundry objects,</HI> as might be exemplified in the Sun, the <HI>wind,</HI> the same <HI>breath</HI> out of one <HI>mouth,</HI> the <HI>earth</HI>; the <HI>stomack,</HI> the <HI>rain,</HI> &amp;c. as might be largely shewn. In <HI>one garden,</HI> growes an <HI>hundred kinds of herbs</HI> of several operations and qualities; some <HI>nutritive,</HI> others <HI>infective</HI>; yet they all draw their <HI>juyce</HI> from one and the <HI>same Earth.</HI> Every <HI>Member</HI> receiveth
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
nourishment from the <HI>stomack</HI>; yea, the <HI>same meat</HI> in the <HI>sto∣mack</HI>? but that which the <HI>Liver</HI> receives becomes <HI>blood,</HI> that which the <HI>Gaul</HI> receiveth becomes <HI>cholar,</HI> that which the <HI>Lungs</HI> receive becomes <HI>fleam,</HI> and that which passeth into the <HI>paps</HI> be∣comes <HI>milk</HI>: So all receive the same good Word of <HI>God,</HI> but every one does not make the same use of it. For as one hath his <HI>faith strengthened by it,</HI> his <HI>patience increased,</HI> his <HI>judgment rectified,</HI> his <HI>will reformed,</HI> his <HI>life</HI> and <HI>practice amended,</HI> his <HI>love</HI> and <HI>zeal inflamed</HI>: so fares it with wicked men, in respect of the contrary <HI>vices, &amp;c.</HI> Again, the <HI>Word of God,</HI> is like a fructifying <HI>dew</HI> or <HI>rain,</HI> which falls not upon any ground in vain. If these <HI>Celestial showers,</HI> fall into the <HI>Garden</HI> of a good heart, they raise up <HI>herbs</HI> and <HI>flowers</HI>; if in a <HI>field, corn</HI> or <HI>grass</HI>; whereas if they fall on <HI>clay,</HI> they make but <HI>dirt</HI>; yea, the <HI>more rain,</HI> the <HI>more dirt</HI>: If upon <HI>kennells,</HI> or <HI>dunghils,</HI> a <HI>stink.</HI> Or if they produce any <HI>fruit,</HI> it is <HI>Weeds</HI> instead of <HI>herbs</HI>; or perhaps <HI>briars</HI> and <HI>thorns,</HI> to <HI>scratch</HI> and <HI>wound</HI> the <HI>Husbandman</HI> that <HI>dresses</HI> it. Thus I might go on, and shew you how the <HI>Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</HI> is recieved by one to <HI>salvation,</HI> by another to his greater <HI>damna∣tion,</HI> 1 Cor. 11.29. The <HI>cloudy pillar,</HI> which gave <HI>light,</HI> and was a <HI>defence</HI> to <HI>Israel,</HI> became <HI>darkness</HI> and <HI>offence</HI> to the <HI>Egyptians,</HI> Exod. 14 20. And the like of <HI>Manna,</HI> Exod. 16 20. The <HI>Ark</HI> the <HI>Red Sea,</HI> and sundry the like which I might weary you with. Yea, <HI>Christ</HI> himself, who is a <HI>Rock to save</HI> all that <HI>believe</HI> in him, shivers his <HI>enemies</HI> in pieces, <HI>Mat.</HI> 21.44. And <HI>immortality,</HI> the greatest <HI>blessedness</HI> of the <HI>Saints,</HI> is the greatest <HI>misery</HI> to the <HI>damned.</HI> No wonder then, if these <HI>Spiders,</HI> those <HI>Bees</HI>; the wicked and the godly, <HI>suck,</HI> the one <HI>honey,</HI> the other <HI>poyson</HI> from the self fame <HI>flower</HI> of holy Writ.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 6 Thirdly, Another reason why they so swell against their reprehender, is their <HI>guiltiness.</HI> And it is a sure sign the <HI>horse is gauled,</HI> that stirs too much when he is touched. In the <HI>Law of jealousies,</HI> if the <HI>suspected wife</HI> were <HI>guilty,</HI> that drank of the bitter <HI>waters of tryal,</HI> she would presently <HI>swell</HI>: if other∣wise, she was well enough, <HI>Numb.</HI> 5.27. Nor did you ever hear of any that were offended with wholsome truth for being untoothsom, that disliked the Minister for being too sharp and searching, but evil minds. But as <HI>good meats</HI> are unwelcome
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
to <HI>sick persons:</HI> so is good counsel to obstinate and resolved sinners. <HI>Vnfound flesh</HI> loves to be <HI>stroaked,</HI> the least <HI>roughness</HI> puts it into a <HI>rage. Bad wares</HI> would have <HI>dark shops, Thieves</HI> will put out all the <HI>lights,</HI> that in the <HI>dark</HI> they may more se∣curely <HI>rifle</HI> the house, <HI>John</HI> 3.19.20, 21. So the <HI>conscience</HI> that is <HI>guilty</HI> of flagitious crimes, could wish the <HI>Heavens</HI> blind.</P>
<P>Fourthly, No wicked man can indure to hear the down∣right truth: For then they must also hear the <HI>sentence</HI> of their own <HI>condemnation.</HI> What the Minister delivers is the very <HI>Word by which they are judged and condemned,</HI> therefore they loath as much to hear it, as the <HI>Prisoner at the Bar</HI> does abhor to hear <HI>his sentence</HI> from the <HI>just judg.</HI> And indeed, if many (as we well know by experience) love not to hear the worst of their tempo∣ral <HI>causes</HI> and <HI>cases,</HI> nor yet of their <HI>bodily distempers,</HI> with which their <HI>lives</HI> or <HI>estates</HI> be endangered; how much more will wicked men decline from seeing their <HI>hainous abominations,</HI> and themselves <HI>guilty of Hell and eternal damnation</HI>? though there∣of, there be an absolute necessity, if ever they be saved.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 7. And so much of the <HI>Reasons.</HI> From all which we may learn not to impute the <HI>cause of wicked mens raging,</HI> to any mis∣carriage in the <HI>messenger</HI>: for he may vindicate himself as <HI>Paul</HI> did, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 7.10. <HI>I have not spoken, but the Lord.</HI> And there∣fore as the <HI>Lord</HI> said unto <HI>Saul,</HI> Acts 9.4. that he persecuted him: So they which <HI>reject any truth</HI> delivered out of the <HI>word,</HI> do <HI>resist God himself,</HI> and not his <HI>messenger.</HI> And this for certain were <HI>Christ himself</HI> their <HI>Minister,</HI> they would much more op∣pose and persecute him, as the <HI>Priests</HI> and <HI>Pharisees</HI> did, when they heard him.</P>
<P>Yea, consider it rightly, and you will grant, that there cannot be a <HI>greater honour</HI> done to a poor <HI>minister,</HI> than this. For, what sayes one of the <HI>Fathers</HI>? It may well be doubted that <HI>ministers open</HI> not the <HI>Word aright,</HI> when <HI>wicked men kick</HI> not against it. Yea, sayes <HI>Luther,</HI> To <HI>preach the Gospel as we ought,</HI> is to stir up all the <HI>furies of Hell against us.</HI> And what saith our <HI>Saviour</HI> himself to his <HI>Apostles,</HI> in their <HI>pupil-age? The World can∣not hate you, but me it hateth; because I testifie of it, that the works thereof are evil,</HI> John 7.7. And so touching <HI>Paul,</HI> who had never <HI>become their enemy,</HI> but for <HI>telling</HI> them the <HI>truth,</HI>
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>
and dealing so plainly, and so roundly with them. Nor can there be such an argument, that a <HI>Minister studies</HI> more to <HI>pro∣fit,</HI> than to <HI>please</HI> men with his wholsome <HI>counsel</HI>; as when he will not let them <HI>sleep</HI> and <HI>snort</HI> in their <HI>sins,</HI> but <HI>cry aloud</HI> a∣gainst their <HI>abominations.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, We may learn from the premises, that if any re∣ceive the Word with readiness, and become <HI>new creatures</HI> by hearing the same: not to attribute, or ascribe the praise there∣of to the <HI>parties converted,</HI> or to the <HI>means</HI> or to the <HI>instrument</HI>; but to <HI>God,</HI> who is the <HI>Author,</HI> and gives the <HI>blessing.</HI> For <HI>Paul may plant, and Apollo may water, but it is God onely that gives the increase.</HI> It is <HI>God</HI> alone that <HI>giveth words unto the wise, and virtue unto their words,</HI> 1 Cor. 3.5, 6, 7. And he will give <HI>suc∣cess to whom, when, and as he pleaseth.</HI> Even <HI>twelve</HI> mean <HI>Fisher∣men,</HI> when he pleaseth, shall <HI>without force,</HI> or <HI>weapon, armour, bands of men,</HI> or <HI>stroke stricken, subdue the whole world</HI> to their <HI>King! Hillary</HI> found not seventeen <HI>believers,</HI> and left not so many <HI>unbelievers</HI> in the <HI>whole City.</HI></P>
<P>Indeed in these dayes, <HI>Ministers</HI> may <HI>tear their throats, spend their lungs,</HI> and <HI>force their sides,</HI> in suing to' a <HI>deaf world,</HI> and say, when they have done all they can, <HI>Who hath believed our report? And to whom is the arm of the Lord revealed</HI>? Yea, how many painful <HI>Peters</HI> have complained to <HI>fish all night,</HI> and <HI>catch nothing? Many professors,</HI> and <HI>few converts,</HI> hath been the lot of the <HI>Gospel</HI> in these last times, and since our <HI>means</HI> hath exceeded. <HI>Gods house</HI> (as the <HI>streets of Jericho</HI>) may be <HI>throng∣ed,</HI> and yet but one <HI>Zacheus</HI> gained to the faith. And why so? but for this cause; if some few like the <HI>Bee,</HI> do <HI>gather</HI> from the <HI>Word,</HI> whatsoever addeth to their <HI>knowledg</HI> and <HI>vertue</HI>: the greatest number, use the same as some do <HI>artificial teeth,</HI> more for <HI>shew,</HI> than <HI>service</HI>; more for <HI>ability of discourse</HI> than <HI>activity of practise</HI>; to <HI>talk of it,</HI> than to <HI>walk by it.</HI> Whence it is, that <HI>God utters</HI> his <HI>saving truths,</HI> as it were in <HI>Parables</HI>; so hiding them from the <HI>wise and prudent</HI> (namely the <HI>proud,</HI> that are wise in their own Eyes) and <HI>reveales them to babes and sucklings,</HI> (that is, the <HI>humble</HI> and <HI>lowly</HI>) as <HI>Austin</HI> speaks.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 8. Which being so, let not him that hath <HI>five Talents,</HI>
<PB N="10" REF="6"/>
despise him that hath but <HI>two</HI>: Even those <HI>great lights of Hea∣ven,</HI> the <HI>Sun</HI> and <HI>Moon,</HI> take not away the necessity of <HI>lamp light.</HI> To the making of the <HI>Tabernacle, fine linnen,</HI> and <HI>Goats hair,</HI> had their use; as well as <HI>gold, silver,</HI> and <HI>precious stones.</HI> And the same <HI>God</HI> that gave proportion to the <HI>Cedar,</HI> gave also be∣ing to the <HI>Mushroom.</HI></P>
<P>Nor is the <HI>strength</HI> or <HI>weakness of means,</HI> either <HI>spur</HI> or <HI>bridle</HI> to the <HI>determinate choises of God</HI>; who not seldom does <HI>greatest acts,</HI> by <HI>weakest agents.</HI> He chose <HI>Davids sling,</HI> rather than <HI>Sauls sword,</HI> to <HI>conquer Goliah Frogs Grashoppers,</HI> &amp; <HI>Lice,</HI> rather than <HI>Bears</HI> and <HI>Lions,</HI> to fight against <HI>Pharaoh.</HI> Yea, he that with <HI>Rams horns overthrew the Walls of Jericho,</HI> hath some∣times chosen vile and <HI>weak means,</HI> to serve himself by, in <HI>great matters. Peter</HI> hath a <HI>Cock</HI> to tell him of his <HI>cowardise.</HI> And <HI>Balaam</HI> an <HI>Ass,</HI> to reprove his <HI>avarice.</HI> Yea, that <HI>God,</HI> who will bless where he pleaseth; now and then gives the <HI>greater success to the weaker means. The men of Nineveh repented at the preaching of Jonas</HI>: yet not the <HI>Jews,</HI> at the preaching of <HI>Christ, who was greater then Jonas.</HI> The <HI>Apostles</HI> did greater signs in <HI>Christs Name,</HI> than <HI>Christ himself,</HI> Joh. 14.12. It was a greater <HI>miracle,</HI> that the <HI>shadow</HI> of St. <HI>Peter</HI> (<HI>as he walked in the street</HI>) should <HI>heal many sick persons,</HI> Acts 5.15, 16. than that the <HI>hem of Christs vesture</HI> should <HI>heale one single woman of her bloudy Issue,</HI> Mat. 9.21, 22. Who then can cavil, or indeed wonder, at the ensuing story the which I am now to relate?</P>
<P>Yea, who that hath either <HI>heart</HI> or <HI>brain,</HI> shall well consider this preceding matter, and the <HI>difference of Hearers,</HI> and not be forced to acknowledg that which follows, to be the <HI>case of every one</HI> that shall hear it, be they what they will? I mean <HI>before their hearts are renewed with the power of Gods word,</HI> which is <HI>the strong arm of the Lord, and the mighty power of God to sal∣vation.</HI> Rom. 1.16. <HI>And the sword of the spirit,</HI> Eph. 6.17. <HI>And like as a fire, or an hammer that breaketh even the Rock in pieces,</HI> Jer 23.29, 30. And that irresistable <HI>Cannon-shot,</HI> that is <HI>mighty to beat down all the strong holds of sin and Satan,</HI> 2 Cor. 10.4. <HI>Quick and powerful, and sharper than any two edged sword, and pierceth even to the dividing asunder of the soul and spirit, and of the joynts and marrow; and to the discerning of the very,
<PB N="11" REF="6"/>
thoughts, and most secret intents of the heart,</HI> Heb. 4 12.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 9. And look to it, for if thou dost not see and ac∣knowledg the <HI>very secrets of thy heart</HI> to be clearly laid open to thy <HI>conscience,</HI> in the one or other, first or last of these ensu∣ing <HI>Characters</HI>: I dare peremptorily conclude, <HI>That Satan the God of this world, hath blinded thy mind, that the light of the glo∣rious Gospel of Christ, who is the image of God, should not shine un∣to thee,</HI> 2 Cor. 4.3, 4. Eph. 2.2. 2 Thes. 2.9.10, 11. 1 Tim. 4.2.</P>
<P>But this is the misery! and a just plague upon our <HI>so much ignorance, formality,</HI> and <HI>prophaness,</HI> under our <HI>so much means of Grace</HI>: there be very few men, that make not the <HI>whole Bible,</HI> and all the <HI>Sermons</HI> they hear: yea the <HI>checks of their own Con∣sciences,</HI> and the <HI>motions of Gods spirit</HI> utterly <HI>ineffectual</HI>; for want of wit and grace, to <HI>apply the same to themselves,</HI> as they can unto others; being better able to discern <HI>others meats,</HI> than their <HI>own beams.</HI></P>
<P>If you question what <HI>Satan</HI> can do in this case? Look upon what he hath done to others, as <HI>wise,</HI> and as <HI>good,</HI> as the best of us. Ile give you <HI>instances,</HI> both of the <HI>godly</HI> and <HI>wicked,</HI> and like∣wise <HI>Testimonies</HI>: I pray mind them seriously, and turn to the places, for they are exceeding considerable. In the first place take notice, how he <HI>blinded</HI> and <HI>deluded Ahabs four hundred Prophets,</HI> 1 Kings 22.22. And <HI>Judas,</HI> John 13.2. And all <HI>Ma∣gistrates,</HI> when they <HI>persecute</HI> the people of <HI>God,</HI> Rev. 2.10. And indeed all men in their natural estate; whereof not a few, <HI>think they do God good service, in persecuting and killing the Prophets</HI>; as our <HI>Saviour</HI> expresly tells us, <HI>John</HI> 16 2. But see other particu∣lar instances, as that of <HI>Ananias</HI> and <HI>Saphira,</HI> Acts 5.3. Then for the <HI>godly,</HI> how he hath blinded and beguiled them, as our first <HI>Parents, Adam</HI> and <HI>Eve; Eve by himself,</HI> and <HI>Adam</HI> by making <HI>her</HI> his instrument; and that <HI>in the state of innocency,</HI> when they had <HI>wit at will,</HI> Gen. 3. And <HI>holy David, a man after Gods own heart,</HI> 1 Chron. 21.1. Then <HI>Peter,</HI> who so dearly loved <HI>Christ,</HI> Mat. 16.22, 23.</P>
<P>And having this done, argue thus with thy self; If <HI>Satan</HI> so blinded and besotted these; if he made such use of all these, whereof some were the best and wisest of <HI>Gods</HI> children and servants, who <HI>hate the very appearance of evil,</HI> 1 Thes. 5 22.
<PB N="12" REF="7"/>
Jude 23. Ephes. 5.27. 2 Pet 3.14. James 1.27. <HI>Have the eye of faith, and the spirits direction, and know the mind of Christ a∣bove others,</HI> 1 Cor. 2.12, to 17. John 10.14. How much more can he work the same upon his own children and servants? that delight onely in wickedness, and are <HI>ignorant of Satans wiles,</HI> as not having the least knowledge or ability to <HI>discern spiritual things,</HI> 1 Cor. 2.14. 2 Cor. 4 4.</P>
<P>But if you still question the truth of this, turn to <HI>Joh.</HI> 14.30. and 12.31. <HI>Gen.</HI> 3.15. <HI>John.</HI> 8.44. 2 <HI>Tim</HI> 2.20. <HI>Eph.</HI> 2.2, 3. which are such clear testimonies, that none (who <HI>shut</HI> not their <HI>eyes</HI> a∣gainst the <HI>light</HI>) can gainsay, <HI>Mat.</HI> 13.15.</P>
<P>Which being so, in reading this ensuing <HI>Dialogue</HI> or <HI>Index of the heart, Make</HI> the <HI>application</HI> to <HI>your selves</HI> and <HI>not to others</HI>; as <HI>David</HI> did <HI>Nathans parable,</HI> 2 Sam. 12.1, to 8. And <HI>Ahab</HI> the <HI>Prophets,</HI> 1 Kings 20.39, to 43. which yet concerned no less then their own lives And so much the rather, for that in all probability, what this will not effect touching your amendment no ordinary means are like to doe. As what can be further ex∣pected? No <HI>glass</HI> can more lively represent <HI>your faces,</HI> than this Book does your <HI>hearts,</HI> if you be yet in your <HI>natural con∣dition, unregenerate.</HI> Neither can you look that <HI>Christ Jesus</HI> him∣self should call to you severally by name, as he did to <HI>Saul</HI>; for now we have the <HI>Gospel</HI> written at large: <HI>Visions</HI> and <HI>Miracles</HI> cease. Or put case <HI>Christ himself</HI> should do so, I question whether you would be any more warned, or reclaimed by it, than <HI>Hazael</HI> was, when the <HI>Prophet</HI> told him, what abomina∣ble wickedness he should shortly commit, 2 <HI>Kings</HI> 8.12, 13, &amp;c. Yea, <HI>Abraham</HI> tells <HI>Dives</HI> the contrary, <HI>Luke</HI> 13 31. And so I come to the <HI>Conference</HI> it self.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 10. A <HI>loose Libertine</HI> meeting with his friend that had lately been a <HI>formal Christian,</HI> he greets him as followeth:</P>
<P>Sir! Me thinks I have observed in you a strange alteration, since our last meeting at <HI>Middleborough</HI>: not onely in your behaviour, company, and converse? but even in your counte∣nance: What is the matter if I may be so bold?</P>
<P><HI>Convert.</HI> Truly Sir, you are not at all mistaken, nor am I unwilling to acquaint you with the cause, if you can afford to hear it.</P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="7"/>
Soon after my return into <HI>England,</HI> I was carried by a friend to hear a <HI>Sermon,</HI> where the <HI>Minister</HI> so represented the very <HI>thoughts, secrets,</HI> and <HI>deceitfulness</HI> of my <HI>heart</HI> unto my <HI>consci∣ence,</HI> that I could not but say of him, as the <HI>Woman</HI> of <HI>Samaria</HI> once spake of <HI>our Saviour; He hath told me all things that ever I did.</HI> Which made me conclude with that <HI>unbeliever,</HI> 1 Cor. 14. 24, 25. <HI>That God was in him of a truth</HI>: nor could he ever have so done, <HI>if he were not of God,</HI> as the <HI>Young man</HI> in the <HI>Gospel</HI> reaso∣ned with the <HI>Pharisees,</HI> touching <HI>Jesus,</HI> when he had <HI>opened his eyes that had been blind from his birth,</HI> John 9.32, 33. Whereup∣on I could have no peace nor rest, until I had further commu∣ned with him about my estate; for I found my self in a lost condition touching <HI>Eternity:</HI> It faring with me, as it did with those <HI>Jews,</HI> Acts 2. when <HI>Peter</HI> by his searching Sermon had convinced them, that <HI>Christ, whom they had by wicked hands crucified and slain, was the onely Son of God, and Lord of glory,</HI> verse 36, 37. And having had the happiness to injoy the be∣nefit of his sage advice, as I stood in need thereof, (<HI>God</HI> having given him <HI>the tongue of the learned to administer a word in season to them that are weary,</HI> Isa. 50.4.) I bless <HI>God</HI> his <HI>word</HI> and <HI>spirit</HI> hath wrought in me such a change and strange alteration, that it hath <HI>opened mine eyes</HI> that were <HI>blind</HI> before, <HI>inclined</HI> my <HI>will</HI> to <HI>obedience,</HI> which before was <HI>rebellious, softned</HI> my <HI>heart, san∣ctified,</HI> and <HI>quite changed</HI> my <HI>affections:</HI> so that I now <HI>love</HI> that <HI>good</HI> which before I <HI>hated,</HI> and <HI>hate</HI> that <HI>evil</HI> which before I <HI>lo∣ved</HI>; and am <HI>delighted</HI> with those <HI>holy exercises,</HI> which hereto∣fore did most <HI>displease me</HI>; and am <HI>displeased</HI> with those <HI>vain pleasures</HI> and <HI>filthy sins</HI> which in times past did most <HI>delight</HI> me. Which is such a mercy, that no tongue is able to express! for till that hour, I went on in the <HI>broad way,</HI> and <HI>worlds road to de∣struction,</HI> without any <HI>mistrust,</HI> whereas now <HI>God</HI> hath been plea∣sed to take me into his <HI>kingdom of grace here,</HI> &amp; will never leave me, until he hath brought me to his <HI>kingdom of glory hereafter.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Loose Libertine.</HI> What you speak makes me wonder: for I ever held you the compleatest man of my acquaintance; <HI>just</HI> in all your <HI>dealings, temperate</HI> and <HI>civil</HI> in your <HI>deportment</HI>; yea, I have never seen you exceed in the least, nor heard you <HI>swear</HI> an <HI>oath,</HI> except <HI>faith</HI> and <HI>truth,</HI> and that very rarely. Besides you
<PB N="14" REF="8"/>
have been a good <HI>Protestant,</HI> and gon to <HI>Church</HI> all your days.</P>
<P><HI>Convert.</HI> What you speak, none that know me can contradict; nor could they ever accuse me of any scandalous crime, or un∣just act. Yea, I had the same thoughts of my self; and should a∣ny one have told me formerly, that I was such a <HI>great sinner,</HI> such a <HI>devil incarnate</HI> as I was! I should have replied as <HI>Haza∣el</HI> did to the <HI>Prophet</HI> (telling him of the abominable wickedness he would ere long commit) <HI>What am I a dog, &amp;c.</HI> 2 Kings 8.12, 13. And no wonder, for as every <HI>man</HI> in his <HI>natural conditi∣on</HI> is <HI>stark blind to spirituall objects,</HI> 1 Cor. 2.14. so <HI>the heart of man is deceitful above all things</HI>: even so deceitful, that <HI>none</HI> but <HI>God</HI> alone can <HI>know</HI> it, as the <HI>Prophet</HI> shews, <HI>Jer.</HI> 17.10. But be∣cause this is a truth that transcends your belief, and because it may be of singular use to you also, to know the same: I will give you a short <HI>character</HI> of my former condition; the which done, I doubt not but you will assent unto what I have hitherto said, or shall further relate.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 11. First, Touching my knowledge, (I mean <HI>saving knowledg,</HI> without which the <HI>soul cannot be good,</HI> as wise <HI>Solo∣mon</HI> witnesseth, <HI>Prov.</HI> 19.2.) it was such, though I thought my self wiser than to make scruple of, or perplex my self about mat∣ters of <HI>Religion,</HI> as do the <HI>religious</HI>: even as the King of <HI>Tyrus</HI> thought himself <HI>wiser than Daniel,</HI> Ezek. 28.3. that <HI>spiritual things</HI> were mostly represented to my understanding false, and clean contrary to what they are indeed. Like <HI>corporal things</HI> in a <HI>looking glass,</HI> wherein those that are on the <HI>right hand</HI> seem to be on the <HI>left,</HI> and those that are on the <HI>left hand</HI> seem to be on the <HI>right.</HI> As it fared with St. <HI>Paul</HI>; while he was in his na∣tural condition, <HI>Acts</HI> 26.9. which made me think and call <HI>e∣vil, good</HI>; and <HI>good, evil; bitter, sweet</HI>; and <HI>sweet, bitter</HI>; to <HI>ju∣stifie the wicked,</HI> and <HI>condemn the just,</HI> as the Prophet complains, <HI>Isa.</HI> 5.20, 23.</P>
<P>As for instance, I most sottishly thought, that I both <HI>loved</HI> and <HI>served God</HI> as I ought; yea, I should have taken it in foul scorn, if any one had questioned the same; when indeed I was a <HI>traytor to God, and took up arms against all that did worship him in spirit and in truth.</HI> I was so far from <HI>loving</HI> and <HI>serving him,</HI> that I <HI>hated</HI> those that <HI>did it</HI>; and that for their so <HI>doing.</HI> I could
<PB N="15" REF="8"/>
also hear him <HI>blasphemed, reproached,</HI> and <HI>dishonoured,</HI> without being once stirred or moved at it. I loved him dearly, but I could never afford to speak a word for him: And likewise his Children entirely; but instead of justifying them, or speaking in their defence when I heard them <HI>scoft, scorned</HI> and <HI>abused</HI> by wicked and ungodly men; all my <HI>delight</HI> was to <HI>jear</HI> at, <HI>slight</HI> and <HI>slander</HI> them wherever I came. I more <HI>feared the Magi∣strate,</HI> than I <HI>feared God,</HI> and more regarded the <HI>blasts of mens breath,</HI> then the <HI>fire, of Gods wrath.</HI> I chose rather to <HI>disobey God,</HI> than to <HI>displease great ones</HI>; and feared more the <HI>worlds scorns,</HI> than <HI>his anger.</HI></P>
<P>And the like of <HI>Christ</HI> that died for me; a strong argument that I <HI>loved Christ,</HI> when I <HI>hated</HI> all that resembled him in <HI>holi∣ness.</HI> Yea, I so <HI>hated holiness,</HI> that I most bitterly <HI>hated men for being holy:</HI> insomuch that my <HI>blood</HI> would <HI>rise</HI> at the sight of a <HI>good man,</HI> as some stomacks will rise at the sight of <HI>sweet∣meats.</HI> I was a <HI>Christian in name,</HI> but I could scoff at a <HI>Christian indeed.</HI> I could honour the <HI>dead Saints</HI> in a formal profession, while I worried the <HI>living Saints</HI> in a cruel <HI>persecution.</HI> I con∣demned all for <HI>Roundheads,</HI> that had more religion than a <HI>Hea∣then,</HI> or knowledg of <HI>Heavenly things,</HI> than a <HI>child in the womb</HI> hath of <HI>the things of this life,</HI> or <HI>Conscience</HI> than an <HI>Atheist,</HI> or care of his <HI>soul,</HI> than a <HI>Beast.</HI> I had alwaies the <HI>basest thoughts</HI> of the <HI>best men:</HI> making <HI>ill constructions</HI> of whatsoever they <HI>did</HI> or <HI>spake</HI>; as the <HI>Scribes</HI> and <HI>Pharisees</HI> dealt by our <HI>Saviour.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 12. As, O what a <HI>poor slave</HI> did I hold the man of a <HI>ten∣der conscience</HI> to be! Yea, how did I applaud my self for being <HI>zealless</HI> and <HI>fearless</HI>; together with my great <HI>discretion</HI> and <HI>mo∣deration</HI>: when I saw this man vexed for his <HI>zeal,</HI> that other <HI>hated</HI> for his <HI>knowledg,</HI> a third <HI>persecuted</HI> for the <HI>profession</HI> of his <HI>Faith,</HI> &amp;c. For, (being like <HI>Cain, Ishmael, Eliah, Michel, Pharaoh</HI> and <HI>Festus</HI>) I thought their <HI>Religion Puritanism,</HI> their <HI>conscience of sin, hypocrisie</HI>; their <HI>profession, dissimulation</HI>; their <HI>prudence, policy:</HI> their <HI>faith</HI> and <HI>confidence, presumption</HI>; their <HI>zeal of Gods glory,</HI> to be <HI>pride</HI> and <HI>malice,</HI> their <HI>obedience to Gods laws, rebellion to Princes</HI>; their execution of <HI>justice, cruelty</HI> &amp;c. If they were any thing devout, or forward to admonish others, that so they <HI>might pluck them out of the fire</HI>; I conceived them
<PB N="16" REF="9"/>
to be <HI>beside themselves,</HI> as <HI>our Saviour</HI> was thought to be by his <HI>Kinsfolk,</HI> and St. <HI>Paul</HI> by <HI>Festus,</HI> Mark 3.21. John 10.20. Acts 26.24. 1 Cor. 1.18. My <HI>religion</HI> was to oppose the <HI>power of religion,</HI> and my <HI>knowledge of the truth,</HI> to know how to <HI>argue against the truth.</HI> I never affected <HI>Christs Ambassadours,</HI> that preached the <HI>glad tidings of salvation,</HI> but had a spleen against them; yea, I hated a <HI>Minister</HI> for being a <HI>Minister,</HI> especially if a <HI>godly</HI> and <HI>zealous</HI> one, that spake home to my <HI>conscience,</HI> and told me of my <HI>sins</HI>; much more if he would not admit me to the <HI>Lords Table</HI> without <HI>trial</HI> and <HI>examination</HI>; yea, then like <HI>Ahab</HI> to <HI>Eliah,</HI> I became his <HI>enemy,</HI> and <HI>hated him</HI> ever after; would <HI>impeach his credit,</HI> and <HI>detain from him his dues.</HI> And are not all these strong evidences, that I <HI>loved</HI> and <HI>served God,</HI> and <HI>my Redeemer</HI> as I ought? But to make it more manifest what a rare <HI>Christian</HI> I was,</P>
<P>I thought my self a <HI>Believer</HI>; yea, I could boast of a <HI>strong Faith,</HI> when yet I fell short of the very <HI>Devils</HI> in <HI>believing</HI>: for they <HI>believe</HI> the <HI>threats</HI> and <HI>judgments</HI> contained in the <HI>Word,</HI> and <HI>tremble</HI> thereat <HI>James</HI> 2.19. Whereas I thought them but <HI>Scare-crows</HI> to fright the simple withal: yea, I held <HI>Hell</HI> it self but a <HI>fancy,</HI> not worth the <HI>fearing.</HI></P>
<P>Because I was not <HI>notoriously wicked,</HI> but had a <HI>form of godli∣ness,</HI> was <HI>civil,</HI> &amp;c I was able to delude my own soul, and put off all <HI>reproofs</HI> and <HI>threatnings,</HI> by comparing my self with those, that I presumed were worse than my self; as <HI>Drunkards, Adul∣terers, Blasphemers, Oppressors, shedders of blood,</HI> and the like; counting none wicked but such. Yea, looking upon these, I admired my <HI>own holiness,</HI> and thought my <HI>moral honesty</HI> would be sufficient to save me. Nor did I know wherein I had of∣fended.</P>
<P>And whereas the <HI>Law</HI> is <HI>spiritual,</HI> and binds the <HI>heart</HI> from <HI>affecting,</HI> no less than the <HI>hand</HI> from <HI>acting:</HI> I was so <HI>blind</HI> and <HI>ignorant,</HI> that I thought the <HI>Commandment</HI> was not broken, if the outward gross sin be forborn. Whence these were my thoughts, I never brake the <HI>first Commandment</HI> of having <HI>many gods</HI>; for I was no <HI>Papist,</HI> nor <HI>Idolater:</HI> nor the <HI>second,</HI> for I worshipped <HI>God</HI> aright. Nor the <HI>third,</HI> for I had been no common swearer, only a few petty oaths. Nor the <HI>fourth,</HI> for I had every <HI>Sabbath</HI>
<PB N="17" REF="9"/>
gone duly to <HI>Church.</HI> Nor the <HI>fifth,</HI> for I ever honoured my <HI>pa∣rents,</HI> &amp; have been <HI>a loyal subject.</HI> Nor the <HI>sixth, seventh, eighth, ninth,</HI> or <HI>tenth</HI>; for I never committed <HI>murder</HI> or <HI>adultery,</HI> ne∣ver <HI>stole</HI> ought, never <HI>bare false witness</HI>; nor could I call to mind that I had at any time <HI>coveted</HI> my <HI>neighbours wife, servant, estate,</HI> &amp;c. And nothing more common with me, than to brag of a <HI>good</HI> heart and <HI>meaning,</HI> of the strength of my <HI>faith</HI> and <HI>hope,</HI> of my <HI>just</HI> and <HI>upright dealing,</HI> &amp;c. And because I abstained from noto∣rious sins, I thought my self an excellent Christian, if <HI>God</HI> was not beholding to me for not wounding his Name with Oaths; for not drinking &amp; playing out his <HI>sabbaths,</HI> for not railing on his <HI>ministers,</HI> for not <HI>oppressing</HI> &amp; <HI>persecuting</HI> his poor <HI>members,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 13. And yet had it been so, as I imagined: Admit I had never offended in the least all my life, either in thought, word, or deed; yet this were but one half of what I owe to <HI>God,</HI> this were but to observe the <HI>negative part</HI> of his <HI>law,</HI> still the <HI>affirma∣tive part</HI> thereof I had been so far from performing, that I had not so much as thought of it. And to be just in the sight of <HI>God,</HI> and graciously accepted of him; these two things are required: the <HI>satisfactory part to escape hell,</HI> and the <HI>meritorious part to get heaven.</HI> And the true method of grace is, <HI>Cease to do evil, learn to do well,</HI> Isa. 1.16, 17. The <HI>Fig tree</HI> was <HI>cursed,</HI> not for bearing <HI>e∣vil fruit,</HI> but because it bare <HI>no good.</HI> The <HI>evil servant</HI> was <HI>not bound hand and foot, and cast into prison,</HI> for <HI>wasting his masters goods</HI>; but for <HI>not gaining</HI> with them. And those <HI>reprobates</HI> at the last day shall be bid <HI>depart into everlasting fire</HI>; not for <HI>wronging</HI> or <HI>robbing</HI> of any, but for <HI>not giving,</HI> for <HI>not comforting Christs poor members,</HI> Mat. 25. So that my case was most desperate! For though with that <HI>Pharisee,</HI> Luk. 18.11. I was apt to thank <HI>God</HI> and <HI>brag,</HI> that I was <HI>just, and paid every man his due,</HI> yet I never thought of being <HI>holy,</HI> and of <HI>paying God his dues</HI>; as his due of <HI>believing,</HI> or <HI>repenting,</HI> of <HI>new obedience</HI>; his due of <HI>praying, hear∣ing, conferring, meditating</HI> on his <HI>word</HI> and <HI>works, sanctifying his sabbaths,</HI> and <HI>instructing</HI> my <HI>children</HI> &amp; <HI>servants,</HI> teaching them to fear the <HI>Lord.</HI> His due of <HI>love, fear, thankfulness, zeal</HI> for his <HI>glory, charity</HI> and <HI>mercy</HI> to <HI>Christs poor Members,</HI> and the like I should have serv'd <HI>God</HI> in <HI>spirit,</HI> &amp; according to <HI>Christs Gospel</HI>: as all that are <HI>wise hearted</HI> indeavour go <HI>live,</HI> &amp; <HI>believe,</HI> &amp; <HI>hear,</HI>
<PB N="18" REF="10"/>
and <HI>invocate,</HI> and <HI>hope,</HI> and <HI>fear,</HI> and <HI>love,</HI> and <HI>worship God</HI> in such manner as his <HI>word</HI> prescribes. I should have been <HI>effectually called,</HI> and become a <HI>new creature</HI> by <HI>regeneration,</HI> being <HI>begotten</HI> and <HI>born anew</HI> by the <HI>immortal seed of the word.</HI> I should have found an apparent <HI>change</HI> wrought in my <HI>judgment, affections,</HI> and <HI>actions,</HI> to what they were formerly. The <HI>Old man</HI> should have changed with the <HI>New-man, Worldly wisdom</HI> with <HI>Hea∣venly wisdom, carnal love</HI> with <HI>spiritual love, servile fear</HI> for <HI>Christian</HI> and <HI>Filial fear, idle thoughts</HI> for <HI>holy thoughts, vain words</HI> for <HI>holy</HI> and <HI>wholsom words, fleshly works</HI> for <HI>works of righteousness:</HI> even <HI>hating</HI> what I formerly <HI>loved,</HI> and <HI>loving</HI> what I formerly <HI>hated.</HI></P>
<P>But alas! I have heard the <HI>Gospel</HI> day after day, and year after year: which is <HI>the strong arm of the Lord,</HI> and the <HI>mighty power of God to salvation.</HI> That is <HI>quick, and powerful, and sharper than any two Edged sword,</HI> and yet stood it out and re∣sisted, instead of submitting to <HI>Christs call</HI>; even <HI>refusing the free offer of Grace and Salvation.</HI> I have <HI>heard</HI> the Word faith∣fully and powerfully preached for <HI>forty years,</HI> yet remained in my natural condition unregenerate, without which new birth there is no being saved, as our <HI>Saviour</HI> affirms, <HI>John</HI> 3.5 I had not trodden one step in the way to conversion; for the <HI>first part of conversion is to love them that love God,</HI> 1 John 3.10, 11, 14. I should daily have <HI>grown in grace, and in the knowledg of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ:</HI> but I was so far from growing in <HI>grace,</HI> that I had not one spark of <HI>grace</HI> or <HI>holiness, without which no man shall see the Lord,</HI> Heb. 12.14. I was all for ob∣serving the <HI>second Table,</HI> without respect to the <HI>first</HI>; or all for <HI>outward conformity,</HI> not at all for <HI>spiritual</HI> and <HI>inward holiness of the heart.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 14. Either what I did was not morally <HI>good for the mat∣ter,</HI> or not <HI>well done for the manner</HI>; nor to any <HI>right ends</HI>: as out of <HI>duty</HI> and <HI>thankfulness to God and my Redeemer,</HI> and out of <HI>love</HI> to my <HI>fellow members.</HI> Without which, the most glori∣ous performances, and the rarest vertues, are but <HI>shining sins,</HI> or <HI>beautiful abominations. Gods glory</HI> was not my principal <HI>end,</HI> nor to be <HI>saved my greatest care.</HI></P>
<P>I was a <HI>good civil, moral honest hypocrite,</HI> or <HI>infidel</HI>; but <HI>none</HI>
<PB N="19" REF="10"/>
of these <HI>graces grew in the garden of my heart.</HI> I did not <HI>shine out as a light,</HI> by a <HI>holy conversation to glorifie God,</HI> and <HI>win o∣thers.</HI> Now onely to <HI>refrain evil,</HI> except a man <HI>hates it also,</HI> and <HI>does</HI> the contrary <HI>good,</HI> is to be <HI>evil</HI> still: because <HI>honesty</HI> without <HI>piety,</HI> is but a <HI>body</HI> without a <HI>soul.</HI></P>
<P>All my <HI>Religion</HI> was either <HI>superstition</HI> or <HI>formality,</HI> or <HI>hypo∣crisie,</HI> I had a <HI>form of Godliness, but denied the power thereof: I often drew near unto God with my mouth, and honoured him with my lips, but my heart was far from him,</HI> Isa. 25.13. Mark 7.2, to 14. Mat. 15.7, to 10. All which considered, <HI>viz</HI> the <HI>means</HI> which <HI>God</HI> had afforded me, and the little use I had made there∣of, left me in a far worse condition, then the very <HI>Heathen</HI> that never heard of <HI>Christ.</HI> So that it was <HI>Gods</HI> unspeakable mercy, that I am not at this present <HI>frying in Hell flames, ne∣ver to be freed.</HI></P>
<P><HI>God</HI> hath sent unto us all <HI>his servants the Prophets, rising up early, and they have been instant in preaching the Gospel, both in season, and out of season:</HI> but my carnal <HI>heart</HI> hath ever been <HI>flint unto God, wax unto Satan: You shall die</HI> if you continue in the practise of sin, I <HI>heard</HI>: but <HI>you shall not die,</HI> (as saith the <HI>Devil</HI>) <HI>I believed.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 15. Besides all this, Suppose I had none of these to an∣swer for; neither <HI>sins of Commission,</HI> nor <HI>sins of Omission:</HI> yet <HI>Original sin</HI> were enough to damn me, no need of any more; and yet my <HI>actual transgressions</HI> have been such, and <HI>so many,</HI> and my <HI>ingratitude</HI> therein so <HI>great,</HI> that it might have sunk me down with shame, and left me hopeless of ever obtaining pardon for them. As see but some small <HI>part of my monstrous</HI> and <HI>devilish ingratitude to so good a God, so loving and merciful a Saviour and Redeemer,</HI> that hath <HI>done,</HI> and <HI>suffered</HI> so much for me, even more than can either be <HI>expressed</HI> or <HI>conceived,</HI> by any <HI>heart,</HI> were it as deep as the <HI>Sea</HI>!</P>
<P>Touching what <HI>God</HI> and <HI>Christ</HI> hath done for me; in the first place he gave me my <HI>self,</HI> and all the <HI>creatures</HI> to serve for my use; yea he <HI>created me after his own image in righteousness and holiness,</HI> and in perfect <HI>knowledg of the truth,</HI> with a power to stand, and for ever to continue in a most blessed and happy condition. But this was nothing in comparison; for when I
<PB N="20" REF="11"/>
was in a sad-condition; when I had <HI>forfeited</HI> all this, and <HI>my self</HI>; when by sin I had turned that <HI>image of God</HI> into the <HI>image</HI> of <HI>Satan,</HI> and wilfully plunged my <HI>soul</HI> and <HI>body</HI> into Eternal torments: when I was become his <HI>enemy,</HI> mortally <HI>hating</HI> him, and to my utmost <HI>fighting against him,</HI> and taking part with his onely enemies <HI>Sin</HI> and <HI>Satan,</HI> not having the least thought or desire of reconcilement, but a perverse and obstinate will to resist all means tending thereunto: he did redeem me, not onely without asking, but even against my will; so making of me his cursed <HI>enemy,</HI> a <HI>servant</HI>; of a <HI>servant,</HI> a <HI>son</HI>; of a <HI>son,</HI> an <HI>heir,</HI> and <HI>coheir with Christ,</HI> Gal. 4.7. But how have I <HI>required</HI> this so great, so superlative a <HI>mercy</HI>? All my recompence of <HI>Gods love</HI> unto me, hath been to do that which he <HI>hates,</HI> and to <HI>hate</HI> those whom he <HI>loves.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Christ</HI> the fountain of all good, is my <HI>Lord</HI> by a <HI>manifold right,</HI> and I his <HI>servant by all manner of obligations.</HI> First, he is my Lord by the right of <HI>creation,</HI> as being his <HI>workmanship</HI> made by him. Secondly, by the right of <HI>Redemption,</HI> being his purchase <HI>bought</HI> by him. Thirdly of <HI>preservation</HI> being kept, upheld, and maintained by him. Fourthly, his by <HI>Vocation,</HI> even of his <HI>Fami∣ly,</HI> having admitted me a <HI>member of his visible Church.</HI> Fifthly, his also (had it not been my own fault) by <HI>sanctification,</HI> where∣by to possess me. Lastly, he would have me of his <HI>Court</HI> by <HI>glorification,</HI> that he might <HI>crown</HI> me, so that I was every way his <HI>God</HI> had raised me from a <HI>beggar to a great estate:</HI> But how did I requite him? I would not, if possible, suffer a godly and <HI>con∣scientious minister</HI> to be <HI>chosen,</HI> or to abide where I had to do, but to bring in one that would <HI>flatter sin,</HI> and <HI>flout holiness, dis∣courage the godly,</HI> and <HI>incourage the wicked.</HI> I used both <HI>my own</HI> and all <HI>my friends</HI> utmost ability. Much more might be menti∣oned, but I fear to be tedious.</P>
<P>Now argue with <HI>all the world,</HI> and they will <HI>conclude,</HI> that there is <HI>no vice like ingratitude!</HI> But I have been more ungrate∣ful to <HI>God,</HI> than can be exprest by the <HI>best Oratour alive.</HI> It was horrid ingratitude in the <HI>Jews,</HI> to scourge and crucifie <HI>Christ,</HI> who did them good every way; for he <HI>healed their diseases fed their bodies, enlightned their minds, of God became man,</HI> and lived miserably amongst them many years, that he might <HI>save</HI> their
<PB N="21" REF="11"/>
<HI>souls</HI>: but they fell short of my ingratitude to <HI>God,</HI> in that most of them were not in the least convinced, that he was the <HI>Mes∣sias sent</HI> from <HI>God,</HI> and promised from the beginning. But I have not onely denied this <HI>Lord</HI> that bought me, but I hated him; yea, most spitefully and maliciously fought on <HI>Satans</HI> and <HI>Sins</HI> side against him, and persecuted his children, and the truth with all my might: and all this against <HI>knowledg</HI> and <HI>conscience,</HI> after some measure of <HI>illumination,</HI> which cannot be affirmed of the <HI>Jews.</HI> Yet miserable wretch that I was, if I could have given him my body and soul, they should have been saved by it, but he were never the better for them.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 16. Lastly, to tell you that which is more strange! Not∣withstanding all this that hath been mention'd, and much more: Yet I thought my self a <HI>good Christian forsooth</HI>; yea, with that <HI>young man</HI> in the <HI>Gospel.</HI> I thought <HI>I had kept all the command∣ments.</HI> Nor was I a whit troubled for sin, either <HI>original</HI> or <HI>actual,</HI> but my <HI>conscience</HI> was at <HI>quiet,</HI> and I was at <HI>peace</HI>; nei∣ther did any sin trouble me. Yea, I would applaud my self with that <HI>Pharisee,</HI> Luke 18.9, to 15. and say, <HI>I was not like other men</HI>: not once doubting of my salvation. I ever refused <HI>to do what my Maker commanded,</HI> and yet <HI>confidently hoped to e∣scape what he threatned.</HI> Nor did I doubt of having <HI>Christ my Redeemer</HI> and <HI>Advocate in the next life,</HI> when I had been a <HI>bitter enemy to him and his members in this life.</HI> Here was blindness with a witness; as it is not to be believed how blind &amp; blockish men are, that have onely the <HI>flesh</HI> for their <HI>guide</HI>; especially if they have <HI>hardned their hearts,</HI> and <HI>feared</HI> their <HI>consciences</HI> with a <HI>customary sinning.</HI> As I could give you for instance, a large <HI>catalogue</HI> of rare <HI>Examples</HI> how <HI>sin</HI> hath <HI>besotted men,</HI> and what <HI>stark fools carnal men are in spiritual things,</HI> be they never so wise for mundane knowledg. But least it should be taken for a digression or excursion, you shall have a list of them by them∣selves, the which I will add as an <HI>Appendix</HI> to this <HI>Discourse,</HI> or <HI>Dialogue.</HI> In the mean time I have given you a brief of my ma∣nifold provocations, and great ingratitude, to my <HI>Maker</HI> and <HI>Redeemer</HI> (for otherwise I might be endless in the prosecution thereof.) It remains that I should in like manner lay open my <HI>Original Defilement</HI>; which is the <HI>Fountain</HI> whence all the
<PB N="22" REF="12"/>
former (whether sins of <HI>commission,</HI> or sins of <HI>omission</HI>) do <HI>flow.</HI> But touching it, be pleased to peruse that small Tract, intituled, <HI>A short and sure way to Grace and Salvation</HI>: Or, <HI>Three Funda∣mental Principles of Christian Religion,</HI> by <HI>R.Y</HI> from <HI>p.</HI> 4 to <HI>p.</HI> 10.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 17. <HI>Loose Libertine.</HI> if this hath been your case, no won∣der it hath startled you; for to deal plainly with you, as you have done with me; what I have heard from you, makes me tremble. For if such <HI>honest moral men,</HI> that live so <HI>unreproveably</HI> as you have done, go not to <HI>Heaven,</HI> what will become of me, that have been so <HI>openly prophane,</HI> and <HI>notoriously wicked</HI> all my time? Yea, it contented me not to doe wickedly my self, and to damn my own soul, but I have been the occasion of drawing hundreds to hell with me, by seducing some, and giving ill ex∣ample to others, (the <HI>infection of sin,</HI> being much <HI>worse than the act.</HI>) As how many have I drawn to be <HI>drunkards,</HI> and <HI>swearers,</HI> and <HI>whoremongers,</HI> and <HI>prophane persons</HI>; Insomuch, that the blood of so many souls, as I have drawn away, will be required at my hands. Yea, my life hath been so debauch'd and licentious, that I have brought a <HI>scandal upon the Gospel</HI> and made it odious to the very <HI>Turks</HI> and <HI>Infidels,</HI> Rom. 2.24.</P>
<P><HI>Convert.</HI> Alas I what I <HI>did</HI> that was morally <HI>good,</HI> or what <HI>e∣vil I refrained,</HI> was more for <HI>self-ends,</HI> or for <HI>fear of mens Laws,</HI> than for <HI>love of Christs Gospel.</HI> True, I went under the notion of an <HI>honest man,</HI> and a <HI>good Christian</HI>: I was <HI>baptized</HI> into the Faith, and made a <HI>member of Christs visible Church</HI>; but I was so far from endeavouring to <HI>perform</HI> what I then <HI>promised,</HI> that in effect I even <HI>renounced</HI> both <HI>Christ,</HI> and my <HI>Baptism,</HI> in per∣secuting him, &amp; all that sincerely professed his Name, thinking I did <HI>God good service</HI> therein, <HI>John</HI> 16.2. <HI>Gal.</HI> 1.13, 14. <HI>Phil.</HI> 3.6. Nor was it for want of ignorance, that you thought so of me: for by <HI>nature</HI> (be we never so mild and gentle) we are all the <HI>seed of the serpent,</HI> Gen. 3.15. and <HI>children of the Devil,</HI> John 8.44. Yea, the very best <HI>moral man,</HI> is but a <HI>tame Devil,</HI> as <HI>A∣thanasius</HI> well notes. But it is a true Proverb, <HI>The blind eat ma∣ny a Fly,</HI> and <HI>all Colours are alike to him that is in the dark.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Loose Libertine.</HI> So much the worse is my condition; for my conscience tells me, there is not a word you have spoken of your self, but I can justly apply the same unto my own soul, &amp; a
<PB N="23" REF="12"/>
great deal more: for whereas you have been a <HI>moral honest man,</HI> so that none except your self, could tax you for breaking ei∣ther <HI>Gods Law,</HI> or mans: I have been so <HI>wicked</HI> and <HI>prophane,</HI> that I could most presumptuously, and of set purpose, take a <HI>pride in my wickedness, commit it with greediness, speak of it, de∣fend it, joy in it, boast of it, tempt, and inforce to it</HI>; yea, <HI>mock them that disliked it.</HI> As if I would send challenges into Heaven, and make love to destruction, and yet did applaud my self, and prefer my own condition before other mens: saying, I was no dissembler; yea, I hated the hypocrisie of <HI>Professors</HI>: I do not justifie my self, and despise others, like the <HI>Puritans</HI>: I am not factious, schismatical, singular, censorious, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> I am not re∣bellious, nor contentious, like the <HI>Brownists</HI> and <HI>Anabaptists.</HI> I am a <HI>good fellow,</HI> and <HI>love an honest man with my heart,</HI> &amp;c. and as touching a <HI>good conscience,</HI> I was never <HI>troubled in mind,</HI> as many scrupulous fools are. I have a <HI>good heart,</HI> and <HI>mean as well</HI> as the precisest. But now I see the <HI>Devil</HI> and my own <HI>deceit∣ful heart</HI> deluded me so, that my <HI>whole life</HI> hitherto, hath been but a <HI>dream,</HI> and that like a <HI>blind man, I was running headlong to Hell,</HI> when yet I thought my self <HI>in the way to Heaven.</HI> Just as if a <HI>Beggar</HI> should dream that he were a <HI>King</HI>; or as if a <HI>Tray∣tor</HI> should dream of his being <HI>Crowned,</HI> when indeed he was to be <HI>beheaded</HI>; the case of <HI>Laodicea,</HI> Rev. 3.17. the <HI>young man</HI> in the <HI>Gospel,</HI> Luke 18.20, 21. and that <HI>Pharisee,</HI> spoken of, <HI>Luke</HI> 18.11, 12.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 18. <HI>Convert.</HI> It was not your case alone, but so it fares with the worst of sinners: Onely it much rejoyces me, that it hath pleased <HI>God</HI> to open your eyes, to see all this in your self. For <HI>flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto you.</HI> Yea, we are <HI>na∣turally so blind, and deaf, and dead in sin, and in soul,</HI> that we can no more discern our <HI>spiritual filthiness,</HI> nor <HI>feel sin</HI> to be a <HI>bur∣den,</HI> than a blind <HI>Ethiopian</HI> can <HI>see his own blackness,</HI> or then a <HI>dead man can feel the weight of a burden,</HI> when it is laid upon him, <HI>Acts</HI> 28.27. <HI>Isa.</HI> 6 9, 10.</P>
<P>And this common <HI>experience</HI> shews; for if you observe it, who more <HI>jocund, confident,</HI> and <HI>secure,</HI> than the worst of <HI>sinners?</HI> They can strut it under an unsupportable mass of <HI>Oaths, Blas∣phemies, Thefts, Murders, Adulteries, Drunkenness,</HI> and other
<PB N="24" REF="13"/>
the like sins; yea, can easily <HI>swallow</HI> these <HI>spiders</HI> with <HI>Mithri∣dates,</HI> and <HI>digest</HI> them too: when one that is regenerate <HI>shrinks</HI> under the <HI>burden</HI> of <HI>wandring thoughts,</HI> and <HI>want of proficiency.</HI> But why is it? They are <HI>dead in sin,</HI> Ephes. 2.1. Revel. 3.1. Now lay a <HI>mountain</HI> upon a <HI>dead man,</HI> he feels not once the <HI>weight.</HI></P>
<P>To a <HI>Christian</HI> that hath the <HI>life of grace,</HI> the <HI>least sin</HI> lies <HI>hea∣vy</HI> upon the conscience! but to him that is dead, let his sins be as <HI>heavy</HI> as a <HI>mountain of lead,</HI> he feels in them no weight at all.</P>
<P>Again they are insensible of their sin and danger, because ig∣norant; for, for <HI>what the eye seeth not, the heart rueth not.</HI> Security makes worldlings merry, and therefore are they secure, because they are ignorant. A dunce, we know, <HI>seldom</HI> makes <HI>doubts:</HI> Yea, a <HI>fool,</HI> says <HI>Solomon, boasteth and is confident,</HI> Prov. 14.16. neither do <HI>blind men ever blush.</HI> And the truth is, were it not for <HI>pride</HI> and <HI>ignorance,</HI> a world of men would be ashamed to have their faces seen abroad. For take away from mens minds <HI>vain opini∣ons, flattering hopes, false valuations, imaginations,</HI> and the like; you will leave the minds of most men and women, but poor <HI>shrunken things, full of melancholy, indisposition,</HI> and <HI>unpleasing</HI> to themselves. <HI>Ignorance</HI> is a <HI>vail or curtain to hide away</HI> their sins, wherupon they are never troubled in <HI>conscience,</HI> nor mace∣rated with <HI>cares</HI> about <HI>eternity</HI>; but think that all will be well.</P>
<P>The <HI>Devil</HI> and the <HI>Flesh</HI> prophesie prosperity to sin; yea, <HI>life</HI> and <HI>salvation,</HI> as the <HI>Pope</HI> promised the <HI>Powder Traytors</HI>: but <HI>Death</HI> and <HI>Damnation</HI> (which <HI>Gods Spirit</HI> threatens) will prove the <HI>crop</HI> they will <HI>reap.</HI> For <HI>God is true,</HI> the <HI>Devil</HI> and all <HI>Flesh</HI> are <HI>liars.</HI></P>
<P>When we become <HI>regenerate,</HI> and forsake sin; then the <HI>devil</HI> strongly and strangely assaults us▪ as he did <HI>Christ,</HI> when he was newly <HI>baptized</HI>; and <HI>Pharaoh</HI> the children of <HI>Israel,</HI> when they would forsake <HI>Egypt</HI>; and <HI>Herod</HI> the <HI>children,</HI> when <HI>Christ</HI> was come to deliver his people. Whence commonly it comes to pass, that those <HI>think best of themselves, that have least cause</HI>; yea, the true <HI>Christian,</HI> is as fearful <HI>to entertain</HI> a good opinion of himself, as the <HI>false</HI> is <HI>unwilling</HI> to be <HI>driven</HI> from it. They that have <HI>store of grace</HI> mourn for the want of it, and they that indeed <HI>want it, chant their abundance.</HI> None so apt to <HI>doubt</HI>
<PB N="25" REF="13"/>
their <HI>Adoption,</HI> as they that may be <HI>assured</HI> of it: nor none more usually <HI>fear</HI> then they that have the greatest <HI>cause to hope.</HI> We feel <HI>corruption,</HI> not by corruption, but by <HI>Grace,</HI> and therefore the more we <HI>feel</HI> our inward <HI>corruption,</HI> the <HI>more Grace</HI> we have.</P>
<P>Contraries, the nearer they are one to another, the sharper is the conflict betwixt them. Now of all enemies, the <HI>Spirit</HI> and the <HI>Flesh</HI> are nearest one to another, being both in the <HI>Soul</HI> of a regenerate man, and in all <HI>faculties</HI> of the <HI>soul,</HI> and in every <HI>action</HI> that springeth from those <HI>faculties.</HI> The more Grace, the more Spiritual life; and the more Spiritual life, the more antipathy to the contrary; whence none are so <HI>sensible</HI> of corruption, as those that have the most <HI>Living Souls.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 19. Now for <HI>Remedy</HI> of the contrary, there cannot be a better <HI>lesson</HI> for carnal men to learn, than this, All the <HI>promises of God</HI> are <HI>conditional,</HI> to take place, if we <HI>repent</HI>; as all the <HI>threatnings of God</HI> are <HI>conditional,</HI> to take place, if we <HI>repent not.</HI> But wicked men, as they <HI>believe without repenting</HI>; their <HI>Faith</HI> being meer <HI>presumption</HI>: so they <HI>repent without believing,</HI> their repentance being indeed <HI>Desperation</HI>: and this observe, we are <HI>cast down</HI> in the disappointment of our hopes, in the same <HI>mea∣sure,</HI> as we were too much lifted up in expectation of <HI>good</HI> from them. Whence these peremptory presumers, if ever they re∣pent, it is commonly as <HI>Francis Spira,</HI> an <HI>Advocate</HI> of <HI>Padua,</HI> did: and never did any man plead so well for <HI>himself,</HI> as he did <HI>against himself.</HI></P>
<P>One Star is much <HI>bigger</HI> than the Earth, yet it seems many degrees <HI>less.</HI> It is the nature of <HI>fear</HI> to make <HI>dangers greater, helps less</HI> than they are <HI>Christ</HI> hath promised peace and rest un∣to their souls that <HI>labour,</HI> and <HI>are heavy laden,</HI> and to those that <HI>walk according to rule,</HI> Mat. 11.29. Gal. 6.16. even <HI>peace celesti∣al</HI> in the <HI>state of grace,</HI> and <HI>peace eternal in the state of glory.</HI> Such therefore as never were distressed in conscience, or live loosly, never had true <HI>peace. Peace</HI> is the <HI>Daughter of Righteousness,</HI> Rom. 5.1. <HI>Being justified by faith, we have peace with God.</HI> But he who makes a <HI>Bridge</HI> of his own <HI>shadow,</HI> will be sure to <HI>fall</HI> into the <HI>Water.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="26" REF="14"/>
Those <HI>blocks,</HI> that never in their life were moved with <HI>Gods threatnings,</HI> never in any streight of conscience, never groaned under the burden of <HI>Gods anger</HI>: they have not so much as en∣tred into the <HI>porch of this house,</HI> or lift a foot over the <HI>threshold</HI> of this <HI>school of repentance,</HI> Oh! that we could but so much fear the eternal pains, as we do the temporary: and be but so careful to save our <HI>souls</HI> from torment, as our <HI>bodies.</HI> In the mean time, the case of these men is so much the worse, by how much their <HI>fear</HI> is the less. It faring with the <HI>soul,</HI> as with the <HI>body,</HI> Those <HI>diseases,</HI> which do take away all sense of pain, are of all others <HI>most desperate.</HI> As the <HI>dead palsie,</HI> the <HI>falling sickness,</HI> the <HI>sleepy lethargy,</HI> &amp;c. And the <HI>patient</HI> is most <HI>dangerously sick</HI> when he hath <HI>no feeling</HI> thereof. In like manner, whilest they suppose themselves to be free from <HI>judgment,</HI> they are already smitten with the <HI>heaviest of Gods judgments,</HI> a heart that cannot repent, <HI>Rom.</HI> 2.5.</P>
<P>In a <HI>Lethargy,</HI> it is needful the <HI>Patient</HI> should be cast into a <HI>burning Feaver,</HI> because the <HI>senses</HI> are <HI>benummed,</HI> and this will <HI>waken them,</HI> and <HI>dry up</HI> the <HI>besotting humours.</HI> So in our dead security, before our conversion, <HI>God</HI> is fain to let the Law, Sin, Conscience, and Satan <HI>loose</HI> upon us, and to kindle the very <HI>fire</HI> of <HI>Hell</HI> in our souls, that so we might be roused out of our se∣curity: but thousands of these blocks both live and depart with as great hopes, as men go to a Lottery, even <HI>dreaming</HI> of <HI>Hea∣ven,</HI> until they <HI>awake</HI> in <HI>Hell.</HI> For they too often die without a∣ny remorse of conscience, like <HI>blocks</HI>; or as an <HI>Ox dies in a ditch.</HI> Yea, thousands that <HI>live</HI> like <HI>Laban, die</HI> like Nabal, (which is but the same word inverted) whilest others, the dear children of <HI>God,</HI> die in distress of Conscience. For it is not every good mans hap to die like <HI>Antonius Pius,</HI> whose <HI>death</HI> was after the fashion and semblance of a kindly and <HI>pleasant sleep.</HI> However St. <HI>Austins</HI> rule will be sure to hold, He cannot <HI>die ill,</HI> that hath <HI>lived well</HI>; and for the most part, He that <HI>lives conscionably, dies comfortably,</HI> and departeth rich. And so you see how it fares with the wickedest and worst of men. Wherefore if you are truly sensible of your wretchedness, it is a good sign, that you are in some forwardness to be recovered: and really to be∣come so good, as formerly you but dreamed, or imagined your
<PB N="27" REF="14"/>
self to be. And indeed the very <HI>first step to grace,</HI> is to <HI>feel the want of grace,</HI> and the next way to <HI>receive mercy,</HI> is to see your <HI>self miserable.</HI> Therefore our constant and most diligent search should be to find out the naughtiness of our own hearts; and to get strength from <HI>God</HI> against our prevailing corruptions.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 20. <HI>Loose Libertine.</HI> But is there any hope for one so wicked as I? who have <HI>turned the grace of God into wantonness,</HI> applying <HI>Christs passion</HI> as a <HI>warrant</HI> for my licentiousness, not as a <HI>remedy,</HI> and taking <HI>his death</HI> as a <HI>license</HI> to <HI>sin,</HI> his <HI>Cross</HI> as a <HI>Letters patent</HI> to do <HI>mischief.</HI> As if a man should <HI>head his drum of rebellion with his pardon.</HI> For I have most spightfully, and ma∣litiously taken up <HI>Arms</HI> against my <HI>Maker,</HI> and <HI>fought</HI> against my <HI>Redeemer</HI> all my dayes.</P>
<P><HI>Convert.</HI> Do but unfeignedly <HI>repent you of your sins,</HI> and <HI>for∣sake your former evill wayes, and lay hold upon Christ by a true and lively faith</HI>; my soul for yours, <HI>God</HI> is very ready to for∣give them, be they never <HI>so many,</HI> and innumerable for <HI>multi∣tude</HI>; never so <HI>hainous</HI> for <HI>quality</HI> and <HI>magnitude.</HI> Yea, I can shew you your Pardon from the great King of <HI>Heaven,</HI> for all that is past, the which you may read at large, <HI>Isa,</HI> 55.7. <HI>Ezek.</HI> 18.21, to 29. and 33.11. <HI>Joel</HI> 2.12, 13, 14. Yea, read 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 6.10, 11. together with the story of <HI>Manasses, Mary Magdalen,</HI> the <HI>Thief,</HI> and the <HI>Prodigal Son</HI>; and you shall see <HI>presidents</HI> there∣of. Yea, the very <HI>murderers</HI> of the <HI>Son of God,</HI> upon their serious and unfeigned repentance, and stedfast believing in him, recei∣ved <HI>pardon</HI> and <HI>salvation.</HI> And indeed <HI>despair</HI> is a sin which never knew <HI>Jesus.</HI> True every <HI>sin</HI> deserves <HI>damnation</HI>; but no sin shall <HI>condemn,</HI> but the <HI>lying</HI> and <HI>continuing</HI> in it. True re∣pentance is ever blest with forgiveness. And know this that <HI>Gods mercy</HI> is greater than <HI>thy sin,</HI> whatever it be: you cannot be so <HI>infinite in sinning,</HI> as he is <HI>infinite in pardoning,</HI> if you repent; yea, sins upon repentance are so <HI>remitted,</HI> as if they had never been <HI>committed. I will put away thy trans∣gressions as a cloud, and thy sins as a mist, Isa.</HI> 44.22. And what by <HI>corruption</HI> hath been done, by <HI>repentance</HI> is undone. As the former examples witness. <HI>Come and let us Reason toge∣ther, saith the Lord, though your sins be as scarlet they shall be as white as snow,</HI> Isa. 1.18. Yea, <HI>whiter</HI> than <HI>snow.</HI> For the
<PB N="28" REF="15"/>
Prophet <HI>David,</HI> laying open his <HI>blood guiltiness,</HI> and his <HI>original impurity,</HI> useth these words, <HI>Purge me with Hysop, and I shall be clean; wash me, and I shall be whiter than snow,</HI> Psal. 51.7. And in reason, did <HI>Christ</HI> come to call <HI>sinners</HI> to repentance? and shall he not shew mercy to the <HI>penitent?</HI> Or, who would not cast his <HI>burden</HI> upon him, that desires to give <HI>ease? As I live, saith the Lord, I would not the death of a sinner,</HI> Ezek. 18.32. and 33.11.</P>
<P>Onely, <HI>apply</HI> not this <HI>salve,</HI> before the <HI>ulcer</HI> be searched to the bottome: Lay not hold upon <HI>mercy,</HI> until thou be'st throughly <HI>humbled.</HI> The onely way to become <HI>good,</HI> is, first to believe that you are <HI>evil,</HI> and by <HI>accusing</HI> our selves, we prevent <HI>Satan</HI>; by <HI>judging</HI> our selves, we prevent <HI>God.</HI></P>
<P>Are we as sick of <HI>sorrow,</HI> as we are of <HI>sin?</HI> Then may we hopefully go to the <HI>Physitian of our Souls,</HI> who came into the World onely to <HI>cure the sick,</HI> and to give <HI>light</HI> to them onely, <HI>who sit in darkness, and in the shadow of Death. God</HI> does not pour the <HI>Oyl of Grace,</HI> but into a <HI>broken and con∣trite Heart.</HI></P>
<P>Wouldest thou get out of the miserable estate of Nature, into the blessed estate of Grace? and of <HI>Satans bond-slave,</HI> become the <HI>Child of God,</HI> and a <HI>Member of Christ?</HI> Wouldest thou truly know thine own Heart? and be very sensible how evil and wicked it is? that so thou mayest have a more humble conceit of thy self? Lay to heart these three particulars: 1. The <HI>corruption of our nature,</HI> by reason of <HI>original sin.</HI> 2. Our manifold <HI>breach of Gods Righteous Law, by actual sin.</HI> 3. The <HI>guilt</HI> and <HI>punishment</HI> due to us for them <HI>both.</HI> This being done, thou wilt see and finde thy <HI>necessity</HI> of a <HI>Redeemer.</HI> And it is <HI>Thirst</HI> onely that makes us relish our <HI>Drink, Hun∣ger</HI> our <HI>meat:</HI> The <HI>full Stomack of a Pharisee,</HI> surcharged with the super∣fluitics of his own Merits, <HI>will loath the Honey-comb of</HI> Christs <HI>Righte∣ousness.</HI> This was it which made the <HI>Young Prodigal</HI> to relish even ser∣vants fare, though before wanton, when full fed at home. No more relish feels the <HI>Pharisaical heart</HI> in <HI>Christs blood,</HI> than in a chip: But O how acceptable is the <HI>Fountain of living Waters,</HI> to the <HI>chased Heart panting and braying?</HI> The <HI>blood of Christ,</HI> to the weary and tired soul; to the thirsty Conscience scorched with the sense of <HI>Gods</HI> wrath: He that presents him with it, how welcome is he? even as a special choice man, one of a thou∣sand. And the deeper the sense of Misery is, the sweeter the sense of Mercy is.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 21. Then if you would be satisfied for time to come, whether your Repentance and Conversion be true and sound, these particulars will infallibly inform you. If you shall persevere (when this trouble for sin is over) in doing that which now you purpose, it is an infallible signe your Repentance is found, otherwise not. If thou doest call to minde the <HI>Vow</HI> which thou madest in <HI>Baptism,</HI> and doest thy endeavour to perform that which then thou didst promise. If thou doest square thy life according to the <HI>Rule of Gods</HI> Word, and not after the <HI>Rudiments</HI> of the World. If thou art willing to forsake <HI>all sin,</HI> without reserving one, (for otherwise that <HI>one sin,</HI> may prove the <HI>bane</HI> of all thy <HI>Graces,</HI> even as <HI>Gideon</HI> had <HI>seventy
<PB N="29" REF="15"/>
sons,</HI> and but one <HI>Bastard,</HI> and yet that <HI>Bastard</HI> destroyed <HI>all</HI> the rest that were legitimate, <HI>Judg.</HI> 9.5.) Sin is like the <HI>Ivy</HI> in the <HI>Wall,</HI> cut off <HI>bough, branch, body, stump,</HI> yet some Sprigs or other will sprout out again: Till the <HI>Root</HI> be pluckt up, or the <HI>Wall</HI> be pulled down and ruined, it will never utterly die.</P>
<P><HI>Regeneration</HI> or <HI>New-birth,</HI> is a <HI>creation of new qualities</HI> in the soul; as being by nature onely evil disposed. <HI>Gods</HI> children are known by this mark, <HI>They walk not after the Flesh, but after the Spirit,</HI> Rom. 8.1. If <HI>Christ</HI> have called you to his service, your life will appear more spiritual and ex∣cellent than others.</P>
<P>As for your <HI>fails,</HI> it is a sign that <HI>sin</HI> hath not gained your <HI>consent,</HI> but committed a <HI>Rape</HI> upon your <HI>Soul,</HI> when you cry out to <HI>God.</HI> If the <HI>ravished Virgin</HI> under the Law <HI>cryed out,</HI> she was pronounced <HI>guiltless.</HI> A <HI>sheep</HI> may <HI>fall</HI> into the <HI>mire,</HI> but a <HI>swine delights</HI> to <HI>wallow</HI> in the <HI>mire.</HI> Great diffe∣rence between a <HI>woman</HI> that is <HI>forced,</HI> though she cries out and strives, and an alluring <HI>Adultress.</HI></P>
<P>Again, the thoughts of the <HI>godly,</HI> are <HI>godly,</HI> of the <HI>wicked, worldly</HI>; and by these, good and evil men are best, and truliest differenced one from ano∣ther. Would we know our own hearts, and whether they be changed by a new birth: Examine we our <HI>thoughts, words, actions, passions,</HI> especially our <HI>thoughts</HI> will inform us, for these cannot be subject to hypocrisie, as words and deeds are.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 22. Then by way of <HI>Caution,</HI> know, That a <HI>Childe</HI> may as soon <HI>create it self,</HI> as a <HI>man</HI> in the <HI>state of nature, regenerate himself.</HI> We cannot act in the least, unless <HI>God</HI> bestows upon us daily <HI>privative grace</HI> to <HI>defend</HI> us from <HI>evil,</HI> and daily <HI>positive grace, enabling us</HI> to do <HI>good.</HI> And those that are of <HI>Christs</HI> teaching, know both from the <HI>Word,</HI> and by <HI>Experience,</HI> that of themselves they are not onely <HI>weak,</HI> but even <HI>dead</HI> to what is <HI>good, moving</HI> no more than they are <HI>moved</HI>; that their <HI>best works are faulty,</HI> all their <HI>sins deadly,</HI> all their <HI>Natures corrupted originally. You hath he quickned, that were dead in trespasses and sins,</HI> Eph. 2.1. Yea, we are altogether so <HI>dead in sin,</HI> that we cannot stir the least <HI>joynt,</HI> no not so much as feel our <HI>own deadness,</HI> nor <HI>desire life,</HI> except <HI>God</HI> be pleased to raise and restore our <HI>souls,</HI> from the <HI>death of sin,</HI> and <HI>grave of long custom,</HI> to the <HI>life of grace.</HI> Apt we are to all <HI>evil,</HI> but reprobate and indisposed to all <HI>Grace</HI> and <HI>Goodness</HI>; yea, to all the means thereof.
<Q><L>My Powers are all corrupt, corrupt my will:</L>
<L>Marble to good, but Wax to what is ill.</L></Q> Insomuch, that we are <HI>not sufficient</HI> of our selves <HI>to think,</HI> much less <HI>to speak,</HI> least of all <HI>to do</HI> that which is <HI>good,</HI> 2 Cor. 3.5. John 15.4, 5. If we have <HI>power</HI> to <HI>chuse</HI> or <HI>refuse</HI> the object, to do these well we have no power. We have <HI>ability,</HI> we have <HI>will</HI> enough, <HI>to undo our selves, scope</HI> enough <HI>Hell-ward</HI>; but neither <HI>motion,</HI> nor <HI>will to do good,</HI> that must be put into us by him that gives both <HI>power and will,</HI> and <HI>power to will.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="30" REF="16"/>
Finally, Each sanctified heart feels this, but no words are able suffi∣ciently to express, what impotent wretches we are, when we are not sustain∣ed. So that we have <HI>no merit,</HI> but the <HI>mercy of God</HI> to save us: nothing but <HI>the blood of Christ,</HI> and his mediation <HI>to cleanse and Redeem us:</HI> nothing but <HI>his obedience to inrich us.</HI> As for our <HI>good works,</HI> we are altogether behold∣ing to <HI>God</HI> for them, not <HI>God</HI> to us, nor we to our selves, because they are only <HI>his works in us.</HI></P>
<P>Whatsoever thou <HI>art,</HI> thou <HI>owest</HI> to him that <HI>made thee:</HI> whatever thou hast, thou <HI>owest</HI> to him that <HI>Redeemed thee.</HI> Therefore if we do any thing amiss, let us <HI>accuse our selves:</HI> if any thing well, let us give all <HI>the praise to God.</HI> And indeed, this is the <HI>test</HI> of a <HI>true</HI> or <HI>false Religion:</HI> that which teacheth us to <HI>exalt God</HI> most, and most to <HI>depress our selves</HI> is the true: that which doth most <HI>prank up</HI> our selves, and detract from <HI>God,</HI> is the <HI>false,</HI> as <HI>Bonaventure</HI> well notes.</P>
<P><HI>Sect.</HI> 23. Now to wind up with a Word of <HI>Exhortation</HI>; If thou beest convinced, and resolvest upon a new course; let thy resolution be peremp∣tory and constant, and take heed you harden not again, as <HI>Pharaoh,</HI> the <HI>Philistines,</HI> the <HI>Young man</HI> in the <HI>Gospel, Pilate</HI> and <HI>Judas</HI> did: resem∣ble not the <HI>Iron,</HI> which is no longer <HI>soft,</HI> than it is in the <HI>Fire</HI>; for <HI>that good</HI> (saith <HI>Gregory</HI>) will do us <HI>no good,</HI> which is not <HI>made good by per∣severance.</HI> If with these premonitions, the <HI>Spirit</HI> hath vouchsafed to stir up in thine heart any good motions, and holy purposes to obey <HI>God,</HI> in let∣ting thy sins go; <HI>Quench not,</HI> grieve not the <HI>spirit,</HI> 1 Thes. 5.19. <HI>Return</HI> not with the <HI>Dog</HI> to thy <HI>vomit,</HI> least thy <HI>latter end</HI> prove <HI>seven-fold worse than thy beginning,</HI> Mat. 12.43, 45. Oh it is a fearful thing to receive tho grace of God in vain! and a <HI>desperate thing,</HI> being warned of a <HI>Rock,</HI> wilfully to cast our selves upon it. Neither let <HI>Satan</HI> perswade you to de∣fer your repentance; no not an hour, lest your <HI>Resolution</HI> proves as a <HI>false conception,</HI> which never comes to <HI>bearing.</HI> Besides, death may be sudden: even the least of a thousand things can kill you, and give you no leisure to be sick.</P>
<P>Thirdly, If thou wilt be safe from <HI>evil works,</HI> avoid the <HI>occasions</HI>; have no fellowship with the workers of iniquity: neither fear their scoffes; for this be sure of, If your person and wayes <HI>please God,</HI> the <HI>world</HI> will be <HI>dis∣pleased</HI> with both: If <HI>God</HI> be your <HI>friend, men</HI> will be your <HI>enemies:</HI> if they exercise their <HI>malice,</HI> it is where he shews <HI>mercy.</HI> But take heed of losing <HI>Gods</HI> favour to keep theirs.</P>
<P><HI>Beda</HI> tells of a <HI>Great man,</HI> that was admonished by his friends in his sick∣ness to repent: who answered, He would not yet; for that if he should re∣cover, his friends and companions would laugh at him: but growing sick∣er and sicker, they again prest him; but then his answer was, That it was now too late; for I am judged and condemned already.</P>
<P>A man cannot be a <HI>Nathanael, in whose heart there is no guile,</HI> but the World counts him a <HI>fool.</HI> But <HI>Christ</HI> sayes, <HI>Verily except ye be converted, and become as little Children, ye shall not enter into the Kingdome of Hea∣ven,</HI> Matth. 18.3.</P>
<P><PB N="31" REF="16"/>
Again, <HI>Satan</HI> and your deceitful heart will suggest unto you, that a <HI>Religious life,</HI> is a <HI>dampish</HI> and <HI>melancholy life:</HI> but holy <HI>David</HI> will tell you, <HI>That light is sown to the Righteous, and joy to the upright,</HI> Psal. 97.11. Isa. 65.14. And experience tells us, that <HI>Earthly</HI> and <HI>Bodily joyes,</HI> are but the <HI>body,</HI> or rather the <HI>dregs</HI> of that <HI>joy,</HI> which <HI>Gods</HI> people feel and are ravi∣shed with. As Oh the calm, and quietness of a good Conscience! the assu∣rance of the pardon of sin, and joy in the Holy Ghost, the honesty of a virtuous and holy life, how sweet they are! Yea, even <HI>Plato,</HI> an <HI>Heathen</HI> could say, That if Wisdome and Virtue could but represent it self to the Eyes, it would set the heart on fire with the love of it. And the like of a sinners sadness, as hear what <HI>Seneca</HI> sayes; If there were no <HI>God to punish him, no Devil to torment him, no Hell to burn him, no man to see him</HI>; yet would he not sin, for the ugliness and filthiness of sin, and the guilt and sadness of his Conscience. But Experience is the best informer: where∣fore take the counsel of holy <HI>David,</HI> Psalm 34.8. <HI>O taste and see! that the Lord is good, blessed is the man that trusteth in him.</HI> To which accor∣deth that of holy <HI>Bernard, Good</HI> art thou, <HI>O Lord,</HI> to the soul that <HI>seeks thee</HI>; what art thou then, to the soul that <HI>findes thee?</HI> As I may appeal to any mans Conscience, that hath been softned with the Unction of Grace, and truly tasted of the powers of the World to come, to him that hath the <HI>love of God shed abroad in his heart by the Holy Ghost</HI>; whether his whole life be not a perpetual <HI>Hallelujah</HI> in comparison of his natural condition: Whence they are able to slight all such objections, as he did. You tell me that scrupling of small matters, is but stumbling at straws, that they be but trifles: when I know your tongue can tell nothing but truth, I will believe you.</P>
<P>Fifthly, Beg of God that he will give you a <HI>new heart,</HI> and when the <HI>heart</HI> is changed, all the <HI>members</HI> will follow after it, as the rest of the <HI>creatures</HI> after the <HI>Sun</HI> when it <HI>ariseth.</HI> But without a work upon the heart, wrought by the spirit of God, it will follow its own inclination to that which it affecteth, whatsoever the judgment shall say to the contrary. That must be first <HI>reformed,</HI> which was first <HI>deformed.</HI> It is idle, and to no purpose to purge the <HI>chaanel,</HI> when the <HI>fountain</HI> is corrupt. Whence the <HI>Apostle</HI> orderly bids us, first, <HI>Be renewed in the Spirit of our mindes</HI>; and then, <HI>Let him that stole, steal no more,</HI> Ephes. 4.23, 24. Yea, it is Gods own counsel to the men of <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> Jer. 4. <HI>Wash thy heart from wicked∣ness: that thou mayest be saved,</HI> verse 14. It is most ridiculous to apply <HI>Remedies</HI> to the outward parts, when the <HI>distemper</HI> lies in the stomack. To what purpose is it to <HI>crop off</HI> the top of <HI>weeds,</HI> or <HI>top off the boughes</HI> of the <HI>Tree,</HI> when the <HI>Root</HI> and <HI>Stalk</HI> remain in the Earth? As cut off the <HI>sprig</HI> of a Tree, it growes still; a Bough, an Arm, still it growes; lop off the top; yea, saw it in the midst, yet it will grow again; stock it up by the roots, then (and not till then) it will grow no more: Whence it is that God saith, <HI>Give me thine heart,</HI> Prov. 23.26. <HI>Great Cities</HI> once expunged, the <HI>dorps</HI> and <HI>villages</HI> will soon come in of them∣selves: the <HI>heart</HI> is the <HI>treasury</HI> and <HI>storehouse</HI> of wickedness, <HI>Mat.</HI> 12.34.
<PB N="32" REF="17"/>
such as the heart is, such are the actions of the body which proceed from it, <HI>Mat.</HI> 12.35. Therefore as <HI>Christ</HI> saith, <HI>Make clean within, and all will be clean,</HI> otherwise not, <HI>Mat.</HI> 23.26. therefore <HI>Davids</HI> prayer is, <HI>Create in me a new heart, O Lord and renew a right spirit within me,</HI> Ps. 51.10. Do thou the like, im∣portune him for grace, that you may firmly <HI>resolve,</HI> speedily <HI>be∣gin,</HI> and continually <HI>persevere,</HI> in doing and suffering his holy will: desire him to <HI>inform</HI> and <HI>reform</HI> you so, that you may nei∣ther <HI>mis-believe,</HI> nor <HI>mis-live,</HI> to change and purifie your <HI>na∣ture, subdue</HI> your <HI>reason, rectifie</HI> your <HI>judgment, reform</HI> and strengthen your <HI>will, renew</HI> your <HI>affections,</HI> and beat down in you whatsoever stands in opposition to the <HI>Scepter of Jesus Christ.</HI></P>
<P>Sixthly and lastly, If you receive any power against your former corruptions, forget not to be <HI>thankeful,</HI> yea, study all possible thankfulness; for that you and I are not at this present <HI>frying in Hell flames,</HI> never to be freed; that we have the offer of <HI>Grace here,</HI> and <HI>Glory hereafter,</HI> it is his unspeakable good∣ness. And there is nothing more <HI>pleasing</HI> to God, nor <HI>profita∣table to us,</HI> both for the <HI>procuring of the good we want,</HI> or <HI>continu∣ing the good we have,</HI> than thankfulness. He will sow there (and there onely) <HI>plenty of his blessings,</HI> where he is sure to reap <HI>plen∣ty of thanks</HI> and <HI>service.</HI> But who will <HI>sow</HI> those barren <HI>sands,</HI> where they are sure not onely to be without all hope of a good <HI>harvest,</HI> but are sure to lose both their <HI>seed</HI> and <HI>labour? Consider what hath been said, and the Lord give you understanding in all things.</HI></P>
<P>And so much for the <HI>Second Part. An Appendix</HI> follows wherein you may have instances of all sorts, how <HI>sin besots Men.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed by <HI>J. Hayes,</HI> and are to be sold by Mrs. <HI>Crips</HI> in Popes-head-Alley, with nine and Thirty other Pieces composed by the same <HI>Authour.</HI> 1663.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

