<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Bacchus bountie describing the debonaire dietie of his bountifull godhead, in the royall obseruance of his great feast of Pentecost. Necessarie to be read and marked of all, for the eschuing of like enormities. By Philip Foulface of Ale-foord, student in good felloship.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Foulface, Philip.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A68064</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 11208</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S105623</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99841350</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99841350</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">5926</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A68064)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5926)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 230:06, 384:11)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Bacchus bountie describing the debonaire dietie of his bountifull godhead, in the royall obseruance of his great feast of Pentecost. Necessarie to be read and marked of all, for the eschuing of like enormities. By Philip Foulface of Ale-foord, student in good felloship.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Foulface, Philip.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[24] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>At London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed [by T. Orwin] for Henry Kyrkham, and are to be solde at his shop, at the little north dore of Paules Church, at the signe of the black Boy,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1593.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Philip Foulface is a pseudonym.</NOTE><NOTE>Partly in verse.</NOTE><NOTE>Printer's name from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A-C⁴.</NOTE><NOTE>Identified as STC 11208a on UMI microfilm reel 230.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE><NOTE>Appears at reel 230 (Bodleian Library copy) and at reel 384 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy).</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Alcoholism --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ali Jakobson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ali Jakobson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A68064">
<STC T="S">11208</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99841350</BIBNO>
<VID>5926</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>BACCHVS BOVNTIE,</P>
<P>Describing the debonaire dietie of his
<HI>bountifull godhead, in the royall obseruance</HI>
of his great feast of Pentecost.</P>
<P><HI>Necessarie to be read and marked of all, for</HI>
the eschuing of like enormities.</P>
<P>Faecundi calices quem non fecere disertum?</P>
<P>By Philip Foulface of Ale-foord, student
in good felloship.</P>
<P>AT LONDON
Printed for <HI>Henry Kyrkham,</HI> and are to be solde at his shop, at
the little north dore of Paules Church, at the signe
of the black Boy. 1593.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the right worthie, and renowmed
Roister, Sir Richard Swash, Lorde and Master
on mount Maluorn, cheefe controller on Salisburie
plaine, keeper of Accounts-in the Cart-way, chiefe Foster in
the forest of Dalamere, high Generall of the Downes, Baron
of Birlip hill, Sergeant of the Shoares and Sea side, and
Vicar of the Vallies: your dayly Orator Philip Foul∣face,
wisheth all health, wealth, might, long
life, and prosperous successe, in all
your affaires and enterpri∣ses
where so euer.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Hen <HI>Iupiters</HI> head was great with
childe, and the time of trauaile nere
at hand: he skorning to complaine,
yet put to his shiftes, was faine to
send for <HI>Vulcan</HI> the Smith, to crase
his crowne with a downedriuing
blow; not only to cause the swel∣ling
to cease, but also to prouide
passage for the birth of his babe. Which thing when
<HI>Vulcan</HI> had performed in giuing him a sound pat on the
pate, out start <HI>Pallas</HI> at the opening of his head, and dan∣ced
before him so maiden-like, that the present sight so
pleasant, expelled all former paines in the birth. Euen so
(most worthie sir) when the confused Chaos of this mat∣ter
following, was first inhabitant in my witlesse head:
then feared I no such swellings, as since I did feele, nor re∣garded
those throwes, which now are ouerpast. Neuer∣thelesse,
<PB REF="3"/>
when my braines fell to their busines, and began
to beate as tho my head had been ready to burst, disdai∣ning
withall the help of mother <HI>Crackfart</HI> the Midwife;
<HI>Iuno Lucina</HI> was as deafe as a dishclout, so that <HI>Volens
nolens</HI> I betooke my selfe to the hearbe <HI>Hellebore,</HI> whose
pleasant operation produced so present a purgation, that
forthwith there followed a most speedie deliuerance, ex∣cluding
cares, renuing ioy. This young impe thus borne,
being brought to the font, was named <HI>Bacchus Bounty.</HI>
Which <HI>Bounty</HI> I willingly offer vnto your worthines;
doubting not at all, but that you will highly accept of
him; not only because he is a bonny boy, and the gift of
a welwiller: but also because hee was begot by <HI>Bacchus</HI>
your welbeloued friend; conceaued by me, &amp; nourished
euer since with the iuice of the grape. From <HI>Ale-foorde</HI>
this 9. of December. Anno Dom. 1592.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Bounden to your bignes,
Philip Foulface.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Philip Foulface to the
courteous Reader.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>O many men (some say) so many mindes,</L>
<L>The brauest Gnatho cannot but offend:</L>
<L>Mens mindes doe wauer like vnconstant windes,</L>
<L>Hard then sometimes to please our dearest friend.</L>
<L>Some hungrie curre may bark aboue the rest,</L>
<L>But please, or displease, I haue done my best.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>He that delights to heare of mortall warres</L>
<L>Is too austere to reade this little booke:</L>
<L>But he that ioyes to heare of good ale iarres,</L>
<L>I licence him with leaue herein to looke.</L>
<L>Here (gentle reader) maiest thou finde great sport</L>
<L>To ease thy cares, if hither thou resort.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And welcome all, which reade and meane none ill,</L>
<L>No further ill than I, and welcome all:</L>
<L>A mery minde to mirth enclineth still</L>
<L>If waightie causes doe not backward call.</L>
<L>Be mery then: reade here, and doe not spare,</L>
<L>And welcome still: here is no better fare.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Philip Foulface.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="4"/>
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>BACCHVS BOVNTIE,</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Describing the debonaire dietie of his
bountifull godhead, in the royall obseruance
of his great feast of Pentecost.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><L>Quint. Allicit externas praesuaui nectare gentes.</L>
<L>Polit. —non mollia pleno</L>
<L>Desunt vina cado.</L></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>He groutheaded <HI>Graecians,</HI> especiallie the
annointed <HI>Achiues,</HI> I meane the Bezila∣distes,
those deuout doctors of <HI>Lob libers</HI>
canne, these (I say) with their knightlike
crue, thought it an high assumption to be
as fathers in a frolicke feaste, or as base
borne brothers, in bickering with the
broth of bountifull <HI>Bacchus.</HI> Which
coppernosed crue, the Knuckledebunions of <HI>Rome▪</HI> so assaul∣ted
with a fresh Canuazado the citie of <HI>Vinosa,</HI> that the ala∣rum
of the <HI>Romans</HI> brake <HI>Nectars</HI> necke, head, and shoulders;
in so much that <HI>Vesta</HI> in great outrage rushed out of a rocke,
and dedicated to swéet father <HI>Bacchus</HI> as Crimson a colour as
was then séene in her péereles peticote, most fragrantlie fu∣ming
vp vnto <HI>Bacchus;</HI> and likewise into the nostrills of all
his nosled nouises wheresoeuer.</P>
<P>This newfound Sacrifice in this sort offered to this bur∣sten-bellied
God; lent such a swéet sent to the rest of the gods
and goddesses, especially to platter-faced <HI>Iupiter,</HI> that present∣ly
he appeased their furie, mitigated the afore offered iniurie,
<PB REF="5"/>
renued <HI>Nectar</HI> to former iollitie, &amp; sent out <HI>Mercurie</HI> as Am∣bassadour,
to parle with <HI>Neptune</HI> rector of the Seas; that
<HI>Triton</HI> his trustie trumpeter should sound along from shoare
to shoare throughout the whole worlde the blessed bountie of
<HI>Bacchus.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Mercury</HI> discharging himselfe, and <HI>Triton</HI> by commaunde∣ment
of his king, tied to the aforesaid chardge, with clatte∣ring
clang he thundred out such ioyfull newes, that not only
mount <HI>AEtna</HI> yeelded forth fierie flames in signification of
sodaine ioyes: but also <HI>Olympus</HI> merily mounted, in hope that
<HI>Permessus</HI> that pleasant spring, should bée somewhat tainted
with the swéet taste of so louely a liquor.</P>
<P>The decréed tidings of <HI>Iupiter</HI> are worde by worde in ef∣fect
as followe.</P>
<LG>
<L>PAsse <HI>Mercury</HI> to <HI>Neptunes</HI> brinish bowers,</L>
<L>My wish, my will, in hast to him vnfolde;</L>
<L>Let <HI>Tryton</HI> scale those hiest fleeting towers,</L>
<L>In <HI>Bacchus</HI> praise let all his tale be tolde.</L>
<L>Let him commaund, the Curists change their liues,</L>
<L>In vaine striues he, with <HI>Bacchus</HI> brood which striues.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The <HI>Bacchanals</HI> hence forth shall beare the sway</L>
<L>With help of Hypocrites they shall doe well,</L>
<L>This gift I giue, it shall be as I say,</L>
<L>Their forwardnes in fraies shall beare the bell.</L>
<L>I giue them right to sweare it out with wordes,</L>
<L>I giue them might to swash it out with swordes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I will that these the auncient order holde,</L>
<L>Th'order of knighthood neuer to decay:</L>
<L>The greatest soakers shalbe least controulde,</L>
<L>Each <HI>Tyro</HI> shall of <HI>Nectar</HI> make his pray:</L>
<L>And whose conceipts God <HI>Bacchus</HI> deemes the best,</L>
<L>Shall haue a rich reward aboue the rest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="5"/>
<L>Come <HI>Ganimedes,</HI> come with christall cups,</L>
<L>Some nappie <HI>Nectar</HI> bring me here in place,</L>
<L>Accurst be he which <HI>Nectar</HI> only sups,</L>
<L>And turns not ouer pot by pot apace.</L>
<L>Accurst be he which after <HI>Ceres</HI> gapes,</L>
<L>And shunnes to sucke the sugred sappe of grapes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>In griefe liue they with carkes of cares opprest,</L>
<L>Which leaue their liquor and away depart,</L>
<L>Till <HI>Bacchus</HI> haue them crowned with his crest,</L>
<L>Whose force expelles all sorrowes from the hart.</L>
<L>With <HI>Viuat Bacchus,</HI> let the <HI>Ocean</HI> ring</L>
<L>The same let <HI>Africk, Asia,</HI> and <HI>Europe</HI> sing.</L>
</LG>
<P>Now <HI>Eccho,</HI> the babbling nymph at the sound of <HI>Tritō,</HI> ha∣uing
intelligence hereof; resounded this decrée so mightilie
towards the maine, that it easily entred into the hearing of
all the inhabitants in euery hauen. And euen as at the belle∣wing
of the bonnie white Bul, the ardent heates of <HI>Pasiphaë</HI>
were more &amp; more increased; in so much that one horne of his
head, was more precious in her precise imagination, then all
her former sacrifices dedicated as dainties to delectable <HI>Dia∣na:</HI>
euen so as soone as the bruite of most bountifull <HI>Bacchus</HI>
was blazed abroad, <HI>Tom Typsay,</HI> an english tapster, wel-nere
choaked with a marueilous drie heat, which he of late had got
by lifting ouerlong at old mother <HI>Redcaps;</HI> this <HI>Tom Typsay,</HI>
I say, with a wel tried tankard trailing at his taile: the more
he thought of <HI>Bacchus</HI> bountie, the more he desired to trie the
experience: and the further hée laboured after his liking; the
longer he lusted after his liquor: wishing at euery foote, the
worthie presence of so gracious a God.</P>
<P>Thus <HI>Tom Typsay,</HI> not only in hope to tipple with the best,
but trusting to merite a further rewarde: fell flat downe on
both his maribones, holding vp his hands on hie towardes
the heauens, and made his Orison to the renoumed god <HI>Bac∣chus,</HI>
as hereafter followeth.</P>
<Q><PB REF="6"/>
<L>BOnny <HI>Bacchus</HI> God of wines,</L>
<L>Cheefe maintainer of our vines,</L>
<L>Sucker the soule, in greefe which pines,</L>
<L>Water to drinke, I hold not good,</L>
<L>Thy iuice oh <HI>Bacchus</HI> breeds best blood.</L>
<L>Nectar (<HI>good</HI> Bacchus) Nectar <HI>send,</HI></L>
<L>Braue <HI>Bacchus</HI> doe thy bounty lend:</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Tom Typsay</HI> stand a frend,</L>
<L>And so thy fame shall neuer ende.</L>
<L><HI>Nectar,</HI> sweet <HI>Nectar,</HI> is my wish,</L>
<L>Behold my tankard, and my dish,</L>
<L>As for my plate I haue it solde,</L>
<L>And for pure broath my money tolde;</L>
<L>Yet once againe let me beholde,</L>
<L>Euery morning warme or colde,</L>
<L>Nappie liquor stout and bolde</L>
<L>Commended and boasted</L>
<L>In a pot trimly toasted,</L>
<L>The pots feet finely roasted</L>
<L>In a worthie fire.</L>
<L>And first of all for my part,</L>
<L>To besiege and sacke the quarte</L>
<L>Till it warme me well at hart,</L>
<L>And then doe it feele</L>
<L>Sincke downe into my heele:</L>
<L>And so next to take the paines</L>
<L>To passe vpward through the vaines,</L>
<L>And soake withall into these braines,</L>
<L>Which witles now alas remaines</L>
<L>For want of good liquor.</L></Q>
<P>Scarse had he ended this his petitory prattle, but <HI>Bacchus</HI>
as willing to lend him a long eare to heare, as hée to open a
wide mouth to aske: and as desirous to fetch him in for a foot
man, as to turne him off his trusse, &amp; as ready to féed him as
fat as a foole, as to teach him the tricke to shue the go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se: pre∣sently
<PB REF="6"/>
he roused vp his moysty head, and from a muddie mufe
so cléered vp his cherilike countenance, that the maiestie of
his nose séemed as the beames of the sunne shining along
throughout the coastes of <HI>Archadie.</HI> But missing the sight
of him whom he lately heard, forthwith he tumbled vpon his
tunne, and standing bolt vpright, through the merueilous in∣fluence
which to him was imparted by <HI>Euriopazeus;</HI> he saw
<HI>Tom Tipsay</HI> in an excéeding quandary, in so much that <HI>Bac∣chus</HI>
for very pittie, through the might of his deitie, so curi∣ously
soared through the airie region, that in a moment he de∣scried
this perplexed Tapster, and drawing nere him, he hail∣std
him after this maner.</P>
<P>Whereas (my friend) thy groanes are so great and grie∣uous,
that they haue ascended the hiest cloudes, which cry out
in thy behalfe for my accustomed clemency, and pierced with∣all
into my bountifull tunne, which now troubled with the
sharpnes of thy spéech, threates out a danger to her former
swauitie: behold <HI>Bacchus, Bacchus</HI> I say, thy best beloued god,
ready prest to performe what thou art willing to demaunde.</P>
<P>Say on therefore boldly and feare not: and withall know
this, that <HI>Bacchus</HI> hath not only a care to kéepe his clients in
safety, but great cause (no doubt) to preserue them in felicity:
for who is he that hath euer heard, much lesse séene, that any
of the gods, at any time so tendred the welfare of their suppli∣ants,
as from age to age, both dayly and hourely béen séene in
me. The tyrannie of <HI>Iupiter</HI> is testified by his threatning
thunderbolte: the malice of <HI>Mars</HI> is expressed by his bloody
blade. The outrage of <HI>Pallas</HI> is dissembled by the booke; but
euidently perceiued by the piercing launce. The broyles of
<HI>Pan</HI> are performed by the crooke. The furie of <HI>Syluanus</HI> is
knowne by the Clubbe: the dismall decrées of <HI>Diana</HI> are no∣ted
by her dartes, and to be briefe, all the other gods and god∣desses,
<HI>Hercules</HI> like are cloyed with such cholericke clubbs;
that their mouthes taste nothing sauing wordes of wrath,
and their déeds séeme vndecent, vnlesse they smel of reuenge.</P>
<P>But <HI>Bacchus</HI> that braue god, whom thou séest here present,
<PB REF="7"/>
abhorreth that his wightes should bee wearied with the
waight of such vnweildie weapons. No, no, I beare (as thou
maiest sée) a beautifull braunch of goodly grapes in token of
ioy &amp; gladnes: whereas the terrour of other gods, to the griefe
of many, doth prognosticate sorrow and sadnes.</P>
<P>Now therefore Tapster, if thou wilt be as readie to make
trial of my bountie, as I willing to inuite thée to my banquet;
beholde, Whilson-wéeke is néere at hand, then are my feasts
called <HI>Bacchanalia;</HI> then resort together the whole band of
<HI>Bacchus</HI> in their chiefest brauerie, amongst whome (if it so
please thée) thou shalt be entertained as a guest most welcom
to <HI>Bacchus.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Tom Typsay</HI> hearing so courteous a discourse, as a man
marueilously amazed for ioy, stood a long time staring in <HI>Bac∣chus</HI>
face, not able poore soule (as then) to make a reply. But
<HI>Bacchus,</HI> a perfect phisitian willing to preserue his patient in
so pitifull a plight, reuiued his spirites with the swéet moy∣sture
of his tunne, and refreshed his braines with the iuice of
his grapes. Hereat <HI>Tom Typsay</HI> awaking as it were from a
drousie slumber, yéelded to his god <HI>Bacchus</HI> a tub full of
thankes, and promised at the time appointed to bée there
with the first. Yet because hée knew not the place, hée deman∣ded
of him thus.</P>
<P>Sith your worships godhead hath vouchsafed to com∣maund
my companie to so famous a feast; let it not dis∣please
your maiestie to put mee in memorie of the place:
else by the masse, I promise you, I feare mée, I shall ne∣uer
finde out your honours house; I pray you sir how do you
call it?</P>
<P>To resolue this doubt (quoth <HI>Bacchus</HI>) vnderstand there∣fore,
that my mansion house is called <HI>Alepotto,</HI> scituate on
the south side of <HI>Quaffington,</HI> enquire for mée at the signe
of the scarlet nose, and from thence shalt thou bée set aright
into <HI>Beerebury</HI> lane, so that being there, thou canst not
misse to finde out my palace, for thou shalt plainely sée it
before thine eyes.</P>
<P><PB REF="7"/>
Hereat <HI>Tom Typsay</HI> made a long legge, vowing to bée
there without faile, and <HI>Bacchus</HI> willing to dismisse him,
blessed the Tapsters tankard with part of his bountie, and
thereupon departed.</P>
<P>Thus the Tapster in great haste hies him home as mery
as any hare in the moneth of March. For whereas before
this so comfortable a conference, hée was so lazie, that e∣uery
foote séemed to haue a leaden héele: euerie legge in
such a quandarie, as though they had tooke some new ac∣quaintance
with the goute; yea his very head so heauie,
as if it had béene harnessed in an horse-nightcap: and his
whole bodie so distempered, as though he had beene prickt
to the very heart with a belclapper: beholde, nowe the
case is altred, and hée is altogether become another man:
for now is hée as nimble as a dogs taile, as couragious
as a butterflie, and as merrie at the heart, as the best
paire of bagpipes in all the countrey.</P>
<P>But as times are altred, so diuers accidents are infer∣red.
Happie was <HI>Midas</HI> when it was graunted vnto
him, that all which hée touched should bée golde: but soone
haples againe, when his meate was metamorphosed into
metall, and hée with his wish ready to starue. Glad was
<HI>Acteon</HI> at the sight of <HI>Diana,</HI> when shee bathed her selfe
amongst her nimphes: but luckles was his lot, when
shortly after hée became himselfe a present pray to bée de∣uoured
of his owne dogs. And ioyfull was <HI>Tom Typsay</HI> in
remembraunce of the bountie of his god <HI>Bacchus,</HI> but sor∣rowfull
alas at his returne when first hée came within
the viewe of his wife: for shée (as is the manner of all
headie huswiues, whose tongues are more readie to raue,
than their hands to worke) not sticking one iot to teache
him a new lesson, tooke him roundly by the topping, and
welcomed him home after this manner.</P>
<P>Ah ah sirra, I sée by Astronomie that the Moone is
euen now at full, and the signe setled iust in the nose: in so
<PB REF="8"/>
much that (as by all mathematicall probabilities I doe con∣iecture)
backe and bellie may this yeare both goe bare, so
that there be no want of harnes for the head. Well, well I
néed not to tel thée what thou art, the gilding of thy nose suf∣ficiently
bewraies thy good behauiour. In so much that either
<HI>Luna</HI> hath come downe alone, and in taking thée for her olde
<HI>Endimion,</HI> hath made thée her newe Moone face: or (as thy
tottering too and fro doth plainely testifie) thou hast had some
long tariance at <HI>Simon Soakers</HI> house, the coppernose smith,
your euer assured friend. But one thing assure thée, for so am
I certainely perswaded, that as the diuell hath already dub∣bed
thée for a drunkard: so hereafter, one time or other, but
neuer too late, <HI>Don Tyburne</HI> will inuite thée to a liueles feast,
and teach thée the crosse caper in an halfepennie halter. And
thus in a fustian fume flung away.</P>
<P>If true it be, as many report, that a curst queanes tongue
is as sharpe as a razor: experience then proueth, that this
poore shaueling néeded no better a barber. How euer it be, I
will referre it to their rehearsall, which haue had their
crownes smoothed as well with a crabtrée combe, as those
which haue tried the sharpnes of the sisers.</P>
<P>But euen as the clap of the thunder the greater it is, the
sooner it ceaseth: and the blastes of <HI>Boreas</HI> the more furious
they are, the lesse while is their continuance: so likewise, a
womans mouth the more full it is of wordes, the lesse it is of
force, and sooner it wasteth into winde. The falling out of
louers is the renuing of loue, and the bitternes of the tongue
is easely seasoned with the swéetnes of the lippes: for what
with pleasing spéeches, swéete conceipts, the clinking of the
pot, and the drinking of new <HI>Nectar,</HI> these two swéete soules
became both as one, and the heate of their former furies were
frozen vp as it were into a lake of euerlasting loue.</P>
<P>Thus whiles this couple continued in solacing themselues
to their hearts content, behold Whitsontide drew on: and to
be briefe, away they both doe walke to the banquet, but be∣cause
these guestes were wrapped vp in their chiefest roabes;
<PB REF="8"/>
it wil not be a misse to describe them in their chéefest brauery,
as they passed along on their iorney.</P>
<Q><L>THe Tapsters hat was all in blew:</L>
<L>Beseeming well his nut-browne hiew:</L>
<L>His nose was ruddy as I weene</L>
<L>And bending as the Faucons beene.</L>
<L>His thin-set heire along did sit</L>
<L>Which represents a woodcocks wit,</L>
<L>Yet bald withall was <HI>Tipsay</HI> found</L>
<L>With eares side hanging like a hound.</L>
<L>His eyes were fiery on each side</L>
<L>His mouth was open gaping wide,</L>
<L>His lippes great as cable rope,</L>
<L>His teeth white as washt in sope.</L>
<L>A bristled beard did flower his cheekes,</L>
<L>His breath was sweete as vnset leekes.</L>
<L>Vpon his chinne a wart did grow</L>
<L><HI>Bacchus</HI> thereby might well him know.</L>
<L>About his neck he wore a ruffe</L>
<L>A quarter long, which was enuffe.</L>
<L>His iacket gray, well fac'd with furre,</L>
<L>His voyce was like a barking curre.</L>
<L>His shoulders did like horseloues stand,</L>
<L>As pillers to vphold his band.</L>
<L>His back was ridged like a boare,</L>
<L>His belly like a tunne before.</L>
<L>There hangs a tap betweene his legs</L>
<L>From whence he turneth foorth his dregs.</L>
<L>On either hand was placde a cuffe,</L>
<L>And brauely was he breecht in buffe.</L>
<L>His leggs they were so crooked seene</L>
<L>A yoked hog might run betweene.</L>
<L>One foot was of the largest sice</L>
<L>The other clubbed crabtree wise.</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
And here described is the guest</L>
<L>Which <HI>Bacchus</HI> bad vnto his feast.</L></Q>
<P>Now as concerning the costly attire of the Tapsters wise,
because I am in hast at this time, I am rather willing to slip
ouer so cumbersome a matter with filence, than to trouble i∣dle
heads with matters of so great importaunce.</P>
<P>As they thus traueled togeather, at length they obteined
their long desired hauen, and entered into the Pallace of
god <HI>Bacchus,</HI> where they were, so worthilie entertayned,
that the sunne in his midday spheare shining out most bright∣lie,
doth scarce halfe represent such glorie, as was by report
séene in this feast. For whereas commonly now a daies, wée
either inuite them of our acquaintance, or such whose new-found
friendship may be as meanes to cure olde soares: this
mightie god <HI>Bacchus,</HI> to the wonder of the worlde, inuiteth
not onely such as bée his familiars, but men altogether vn∣knowne,
as well the poore as the rich.</P>
<P>Sée then the goodnes of this so gracious a god, al yée, which
in the driest drought of summer had rather shroude your
throates with a handfull of hemp, then with the expence of
an odde Crinclepouch wash your selues within and without,
and make your selues as mery as dawes: yea learne yée nig∣gards
at god <HI>Bacchus</HI> to bée liuely; whose especiall fauour
spreads out it selfe so far, that euery nation doth magnifie his
name, euery countrey speakes in his commendation and all
people paint him out with pen and pensill, in so much that <HI>Iu∣piter</HI>
himselfe doth wonder at his worthines.</P>
<P>But to returne from whence I came, their entertainment
I say was such, that they rather thought themselues trans∣ported
into <HI>Paradice</HI> that place of pleasure, then remayning
in any earthly habitation: for there they saw a royal resort as
well of all lands and languages, as of all degrées and callings
whatsoeuer.</P>
<P>There was <HI>Ganimedes</HI> sent from <HI>Iupiter,</HI> to imploy his ser∣uice
at <HI>Bacchus</HI> table, there was halting <HI>Hebe</HI> sent by <HI>Iuno</HI> to
<PB REF="9"/>
furnish this feast with all solemnitie. There was <HI>Sylenus,</HI> a
stately seruitour, waiting at euery winke, &amp; preuenting euery
want. Yea such was the bounty of <HI>Bacchus,</HI> that he sent downe
to <HI>Plutus</HI> prince of hell, and craued the company of diuers his
acquaintance, which <HI>Plutus</HI> performed accordingly.</P>
<P>Thither rode great <HI>Alexander</HI> vpō the back of prauncing <HI>Bu∣cephalus,</HI>
brauely accōpanied with <HI>Sardanapalus</HI> king of <HI>Assiria,</HI>
quéene <HI>Semiramis</HI> and <HI>Ninus</HI> her sonne, first founders of <HI>Babilō.</HI></P>
<P>After these came <HI>Claudius Tiberius,</HI> the Romaine Emperour,
who for the zeale hée had to the vintrée, was merely termed
<HI>Caldius Biberius mero:</HI> with him came <HI>Caligula, Nero,</HI> and <HI>Helio∣gabalus,
Anthonie, Cleopatra,</HI> and such like.</P>
<P>After these againe came stumbling in blind <HI>Homer</HI> the greci∣an
poet, and with him came <HI>Aristophanes, Menander,</HI> &amp; others:
and along with these came <HI>Virgill, Horace, Ouid,</HI> olde father <HI>En∣nius,
Geffery Chaucer, Lydgate, Anthony Skelton, Will. Elderton▪</HI>
with infinite mo, whose seuerall names to rehearse, were no les
labour then to make a mouse to pisse ouer Poules, or a louse to
leap ouer the high tops of Maluerne hills.</P>
<P>Moreouer after these came young <HI>Cicero,</HI> who for the large
loose that he had in turning downe his liquor, was called <HI>Bicon∣gius;</HI>
with him came the blockheaded <HI>Balatronus,</HI> and <HI>Vibidius,
Mecenas</HI> trencher-mates: &amp; that old huddle and twang <HI>Aristo∣demus,</HI>
the shadow of Saint <HI>Socrates.</HI></P>
<P>And <HI>Proserpina</HI> the infernall quéene, willing to honour <HI>Bac∣chus</HI>
in what she might, releaseth <HI>Tantalus</HI> from out of the riuer,
causeth <HI>Sysiphus</HI> to cease from his tumbling taske, sets <HI>Ixion</HI> frée
from his torture: cals downe <HI>Prometheus,</HI> and compels the vul∣tures,
deuouring his heart, to cease from their pray, and for the
tune only that <HI>Bacchus</HI> feast continueth, she doth licence them al
to depart.</P>
<P>Glad were they to be released tho but for a time, and glad was
<HI>Bacchus</HI> that it was his lot to welcome such willing guestes.</P>
<P>As <HI>Bacchus</HI> was thus most busie amongst his friends, behold
a reuerend route resorted towardst his court with a trumpet
before them sounding most melodiously in token of great ioy,
for that they were so nere the pleasant paradice of god <HI>Bacchus.</HI>
<PB REF="10"/>
Who they were, from whence they came, and in what manner
they appeared in presence, followeth as thus.</P>
<P>First of all came <HI>Dauid Drie-throte,</HI> from <HI>Lesbona</HI> in <HI>Portu∣gale;</HI>
in his hand hee held a peece well fild with wine of <HI>Canary,</HI>
which with cap and knee hee presented to god <HI>Bacchus,</HI> and gaue
place to the rest.</P>
<P>Secondly, came <HI>Alexander Addlehead,</HI> from <HI>Dun Baur,</HI> a <HI>Scot,</HI>
who offered to his god a dozen of red herrings to season his mouth
before he sat downe to taste his liquor.</P>
<P>Thirdly, there skipt in a Spaniard, of the city of <HI>Logronio,</HI> na∣med
<HI>Blayner Bloblip,</HI> who gratifying his god with two limons, &amp;
an orenge pill, with a most lowly legge he lept aside.</P>
<P>Fourthly, came wallowing in a Germane, borne in <HI>Mentz,</HI> his
name was <HI>Gotfrey Grouthead;</HI> with him he brought a wallet full
of woodcocks heads, the braines thereof tempered with other
sauce, is a passing preseruatiue against the ale-passion or paine in
the pate.</P>
<P>Fiftly, came posting in one <HI>Peers Spendall</HI> from <HI>Brundusium,</HI> an
Italian frier, with a pot full of holy water, sprinkling to and fro,
and round about him, to driue away the diuell, least hee should
chance to come inuisible and deceaue them of their drinke.</P>
<P>The 6. was one <HI>Frauncis Franckfellow,</HI> a <HI>Corinthian</HI> in the
the coasts of <HI>Achaia,</HI> with him he brought a box of oyle, that <HI>Bac∣chus</HI>
therewith might baste his belly, when it was ready to crack,
with licking vp ouer lauishly the small crums that tumbled out of
his tunne.</P>
<P>The seuenth was one <HI>Simon Swil-kan,</HI> he came from <HI>Colops</HI> a
citie in <HI>Africa,</HI> and presented to <HI>Bacchus</HI> a buttock of Bacon:
which broyled on the coales, and so eaten, will set a man on
longing for his liquor before sunne shine, bee the morning neuer
so moysty.</P>
<P>The eight was of <HI>Capsa,</HI> a towne well knowne in <HI>Numidia:</HI>
his name was <HI>Geffery Gooscap,</HI> and with him hee brought a
night cap for god <HI>Bacchus</HI> great godhead, least through his hot
compotations in the day, his head should crow with cold consump∣tions
in the night.</P>
<P>The 9. was a iolly gentlewoman, named mistris <HI>Merigodown;</HI>
<PB REF="10"/>
she came from <HI>Archelais,</HI> a citie in <HI>Cappadocia,</HI> with a fanne of fe∣thers
in one hand, and a looking glasse in the other: which both she
gaue to <HI>Bacchus:</HI> the one to gather winde, least his breath shoulde
faile him when he blew a long blast in a wine pot: the other to see
to his nose, least continuing ouerlong in a fierie colour, it shoulde
chance to be changed into a Carbuncle.</P>
<P>The 10. was one <HI>Phillip Filpot,</HI> brought vp in <HI>Varica</HI> a citie of
<HI>Iberia,</HI> and one of the sect of Saint <HI>Sinckator.</HI> This <HI>Philip</HI> was
a phisition, and brought to his god <HI>Bacchus</HI> a certaine potion,
merueilous in operation, of which who euer he were that did
drinke after hee had beene well whitled, by vertue thereof, if
hee once were a sleepe, shoulde neuer awake till hee were
wiser.</P>
<P>The 11. was a Iewe borne in <HI>Ioppa,</HI> hee had to name <HI>Chri∣stopher
Crabface,</HI> a man famous in Astrologie: hee brought in
his hand a Prognostication newly composed, which hee besto∣wed
on god <HI>Bacchus.</HI> In which booke hee had largly set down
diuers detriments accidentall this yeare: Especially this I no∣ted,
that many drunkards whiles they looked vpwards on high
towards the man in the Moone, shall breake their necks down∣wards
below in the bottome of a ditch.</P>
<P>The 12. was <HI>Gilbert Goodfellow,</HI> from <HI>Arbila,</HI> an <HI>Assyri∣an:</HI>
this <HI>Gilbert</HI> was a butcher, and brought with him an
hoggs head, a sheepes tongue, and a calues chauldron; the
hogs head for harnesse against entreatie: the sheepes tongue to
temper his owne the better in telling of a true tale, and a
calues chauldron to wrap vp his noddle, least in the ende of a
banquet his inward heate should fume out with a farewell to all
good felowship.</P>
<P>The 13. came from <HI>Choka</HI> a citie in <HI>Arabia,</HI> named <HI>Nicho∣las
Neuerthriue;</HI> hee brought with him a pudding pie, pretilie
powdred with such hot spices as his countrie plentifully dooth
afforde: which beeing once tasted, dooth maruellously en∣crease
a moystie appetite, which <HI>Bacchus</HI> receaued very thank∣fully.</P>
<P>The 14. was called <HI>Hodge Heauie-breech,</HI> hee came frome
<HI>Miserga</HI> a cittie in the confines of <HI>Persia: Hodge</HI> by his
<PB REF="11"/>
occupation was a Cardmaker, who for the zeale he had to god <HI>Bac∣chus</HI>
and al good fellows, offered vp to him that renowmed ruffler
the knaue of <HI>Clubs,</HI> with a box of trim trillilles, commonly called
the dice: the one to aide him in a needeles combat, the other after
his losse, to serue him in stead of recreation.</P>
<P>The 15. was one <HI>Maudlen Moonface,</HI> a mery gentlewoman
of <HI>Dublin,</HI> a citie in <HI>Ireland:</HI> with her she brought a glasse ful, nose
high of <HI>Aquauitae,</HI> the operation where of is no lesse monstrous
than m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rueilous, for being drunke in a morning it so warmeth the
heart, as if the body were in a bath, whose inward heats whē they
begin to budforth, transforme themselues into gosbery grapes to
be seene most plainely as vnder a vizard of glistering glasse.</P>
<P>The 16. was a pleasant <HI>Parthian</HI> of the stately cittie <HI>Catompy∣lon,</HI>
called <HI>Loblurchall;</HI> this youth was a feate fellow, and a fine
faulkner, with him he carried a water <HI>Wagtaile,</HI> readie to flie at the
fairest goofe in <HI>Winchester:</HI> which present god <HI>Bacchus</HI> accepted
very gratefully.</P>
<P>The 17. was borne in <HI>India,</HI> at a faire citie called <HI>Tyndis,</HI> this
forsooth was a coy dame, called <HI>Cate Crashpot,</HI> she came clincking
a quart pot for sweete musicke, in stead of the ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ret, to which ma∣ner
of melodie god <HI>Bacchus</HI> listned exceedingly.</P>
<P>The 18. was one <HI>Baudwin Barrelbely</HI> from <HI>Ormusa,</HI> a place
sufficiently knowne in the ile of <HI>Cyprusse,</HI> with him he brought a
firkin full of wine of <HI>Basterdes:</HI> assuring god <HI>Bacchus</HI> on his fideli∣tie,
that so many as he made thereof partakers with him, as long
as they applied themselues to the harty carouse, should neuer be
daunted by death, and faile footing.</P>
<P>The 19. came from <HI>Garma</HI> in <HI>Aethiopia,</HI> called <HI>Goody Good∣ale:</HI>
shee (in token of pure deuotion) deliuered to <HI>Bacchus</HI> a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ack
full of groute, and a sack-full of hops, standing stoutly in this opi∣nion,
that the barly broath aboue all other did beare away<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th bell,
and that neither grape nor very might in any respect be compared
to the maiestie of the mault.</P>
<P>The 20. was a worthie yeoman, one <HI>Tom Tospot,</HI> he came from
<HI>Friburgum</HI> an <HI>Heluetian,</HI> he as willing to pleasure himselfe, as to
honour his god, presented to <HI>Bacchus,</HI> a dainty deuised compound,
of sundry simples pastiewise, as the trimming of tripes, the fat of
<PB REF="11"/>
chitterlings, and the marrow of swéet souse, lapt vp altogether
within the crusty walls of paste royall, in so much that a world of
be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly cheere was contained therein, which god <HI>Bacchus</HI> receaued
with so great thankes, that he promised to honour the eating there∣of,
with the best increments of his ouer-flawing tunne.</P>
<P>When these had ended their deuotion, they were placed all in
order, and vsed as most welcome guests: busie was <HI>Bacchus</HI> in vtte∣ring
his bounty, and the rest of the seruitors no l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse diligent, so
that no man wanted his wish, nor depriued of his will.</P>
<P>Scarse had they tipled gyrum wise, as commonly the sect of
the <HI>Surratims</HI> vse to doe, as only of triall to wet their whistles: but
in comes <HI>Bat Barlycap,</HI> a mery musitian, ready with cap and knee
to giue them a song: which proffer god <HI>Bacchus</HI> accepted gladly;
wherupon M. <HI>Barlicap</HI> tempered vp his fidle, &amp; begā as followeth.</P>
<LG>
<L>THe Gods of loue</L>
<L>Which raigne aboue</L>
<L>Maintaine this feast:</L>
<L>Let Bacchus find</L>
<L>Their hearts most kind</L>
<L>To euery guest.</L>
<L>And long may Bacchus braue it here</L>
<L>in pleasures to abound,</L>
<L>That wine &amp; beere, &amp; belly gut cheere,</L>
<L>with plenty here be found.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I pray likewise,</L>
<L>That ere you rise</L>
<L>You drink your fill,</L>
<L>That no man want</L>
<L>Nor finde it skant</L>
<L>Whereof to swill.</L>
<L>Then may you all carouse in blisse,</L>
<L>and bid farewell to woe,</L>
<L>Who liues in this, he cannot misse</L>
<L>but straight to heauen goe.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Be mery all</L>
<L>Both great and small</L>
<L>Be mery here,</L>
<L>And with your liquor</L>
<L>Sweetly bicker,</L>
<L>Doe not feare.</L>
<L>Wash wel your throates which now are dry,</L>
<L>and spare not you for cost,</L>
<L>I tell you true, no shot is due</L>
<L>where Bacchus rules the rost.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sadnes and griefe</L>
<L>Bring no reliefe,</L>
<L>Bid them adiew:</L>
<L>In paine none pine</L>
<L>Which loue strong wine</L>
<L>I tell you true.</L>
<L>Then learne to laffe, carouse &amp; quaffe,</L>
<L>and spare not while you may.</L>
<L>Hey dery dery, my masters be mery,</L>
<L>and looke for a ioyfull day.</L>
</LG>
<P>This song thus ended, the whole hall for ioy did ring out a loud
laffing peale, and thanked the fidler for his mirth. <HI>Bacchus</HI> made
him drinke, <HI>Silenus</HI> bad him not spare, so <HI>Barlicap</HI> did drink till his
eyes did stare.</P>
<P>Thus euery man falls to his taske, and hee happie that is able
<PB REF="12"/>
to stand stoutly in the forefront, to giue the brauest onset.</P>
<P>Whiles thus they tipled, the fidler he fidled, and the pots dan∣ced
for ioy the old hop about, commonly called Sellengars round:
euery man set to his foot, there was not whip snatch and away, but
plaine rack and manger, where euery one dranke himselfe out of
danger: cups and cans went clip clap, the guests were al welcome,
their tongues ran at randome, sir <HI>Prattle</HI> kept a wrangling, and
dame <HI>Tattle</HI> a great iangling, each one was mery, &amp; no man wan∣ted
words to solace his next neighbour: to be briefe, heauen was
here, and hell where they were not, yea who but the guests of god
<HI>Bacchus.</HI></P>
<P>Amids these only pleasures, and ioyes incomparable, <HI>Iupiter</HI>
sends downe <HI>Mercury</HI> to make them pleasant: &amp; <HI>Venus</HI> the queene
of loue, sent also her son <HI>Cupid</HI> to creep in amongst thē for kindnes,
and to lead them along blindfold vnto lust &amp; loathsome self-liking.</P>
<P>Then <HI>Pluto</HI> the master diuell of hell seeing fit opportunity and
place conuenient, sent amongst the ioyfull guests of this feast, the
furies of hell, who with all speed posted to god <HI>Bacchus</HI> pallace, to
exercise their hellish outrage.</P>
<P>Now <HI>Cupid</HI> lingred not out his time, but did driue his dartes
amongst thē with such force, that some for pure loue wedded them
selues to wine: some became sworne brethren to the beere pot, o∣ther
some matched themselues only to Metheglin, one liked this,
another that, all was wonderfull to behold.</P>
<P><HI>Bawdwin Barrelbelly</HI> was greatly grieued with loue gripes,
especially through the desire hee had to goody <HI>Goodale</HI> the
<HI>AEthiopian.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Kit Crabface</HI> so ardently burned in the loue of <HI>Maudlin Moone∣face,</HI>
that well nere he burned himselfe to ashes.</P>
<P><HI>Mercury</HI> he cast his eloquence amongst them by horse loades at
once, so that large promises with no performance, were as easie to
be heard, as small bells in a morrice daunce.</P>
<P><HI>Medusa, Megera</HI> and the rest of those furious hags, flie al at once
in amongst them, and sets their teeth on edge to practise villanie,
one against another: one puls his felow by the beard without cause;
another crackes his next felowes crowne with a quart pot, one
flings a glasse in another mans face, another makes a buckler of
<PB REF="12"/>
his hat to saue himselfe before, whiles another with a black iack
breakes his head behinde: one cries downe with him, downe with
him, not able of himselfe to kill a louse, another lies lurking vn∣der
the table altogether speechles.</P>
<P>Here <HI>Dauid Drithroat</HI> gathered vp his teeth, which <HI>Pierse
Spendall</HI> the Frier had lately strooke out, because <HI>Dauid</HI> like an
vnmannerly knaue, presumed to pisse in the holy water pot.</P>
<P>There <HI>Gotfrey Grouthead</HI> begins to fume, and fometh at the
mouth like a sauage bore, hee falls at variance with mistris <HI>Meri∣godowne,</HI>
and hales her along by the haire of the haead: in so much
that (thou knaue) was as common amongst them as cartway, or
<HI>probo</HI> in the schooles: and (thou whore) as vsuall a terme, as hait
hary in the mouth of a carter.</P>
<P>Whiles thus they lay on heapes, one on the neck of another,
some spurning others w<SUP>t</SUP> their heeles, some scratching their heads
where they itched not, some sprauling vnderneath most glad to
rise vp againe, some wiping the blood away from their faces: some
rubbing their shinnes which they burst on the frames: some gaping
for winde, almost choked with flies, while these, I say, did lie in
this so great disorder, the gods aboue were constrained to winke
at their follies, and the diuels below reioyced at the viewe of this
our mortall wretchednes.</P>
<P>Thus <HI>Bacchus</HI> arose, with the rest of his Barons, and dismis∣sed
euery man very bountifully: who after long stumbling, at the
last returned from whence they came. And <HI>Bacchus</HI> himselfe reti∣red
to <HI>Archadie,</HI> whereat this day, for his singular liberali∣tie,
&amp; bounteous behauiour towardes all inhabitants
trauellers &amp; passengers, he is of power to make
a greater companie of able men then
any man of his degree.</P>
<Q>Et largas epulas &amp; bona vina dedit.</Q>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

