<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A warning agaynst the dangerous practises of papistes and specially the parteners of the late rebellion. Gathered out of the common feare and speche of good subiectes. Sene and allowed.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Norton, Thomas, 1532-1584.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A68512</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 18685.7</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S113364</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99848600</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99848600</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">13707</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A68512)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13707)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1322:3, 327:4)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A warning agaynst the dangerous practises of papistes and specially the parteners of the late rebellion. Gathered out of the common feare and speche of good subiectes. Sene and allowed.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Norton, Thomas, 1532-1584.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[112] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[Imprinted at London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>By Iohn Daye, dwelling ouer Aldersgate. These bookes are to be solde [by L. Harrison] in Paules churchyarde at the signe of the Crane,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>[1569]]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>By Thomas Norton.</NOTE><NOTE>Printer's name and bookseller's address from colophon; bookseller's name and publication date from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A-O⁴.</NOTE><NOTE>Another state of STC 18686, with "Sene and allowed" added at foot of title.</NOTE><NOTE>Identified as STC 18686 at  reel 327:4 and as STC 18687 on reel 1322:3.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (reel 327:4) and Cambridge University Library (reel 1322:3).</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Catholics --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  Northern Rebellion, 1569 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A68512">
<STC T="S">18685.7</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99848600</BIBNO>
<VID>13707</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>¶A warning agaynst the
dangerous practises of Papistes,
and specially the parteners of the
late Rebellion.</P>
<P>¶Gathered out of the common feare
and speche of good subiectes.</P>
<P>Vox populi Dei, vox Dei est.</P>
<P>Sene and allowed.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>He state of this Realme
considered, and specially
such accidentes touching
the same, as late troubles
haue ministred, do make
it dayly more and more e∣uident
how precious and how deare a
iewell is the safetie of the Quéenes most
excellent Maiestie our most louing and
beloued soueraigne Lady.<NOTE PLACE="marg">The Q. preci∣ous.</NOTE> Compare the
time of her most noble and gracious go∣uernement,
with ages long agoe passed,
and specially with the miserable and dan∣gerous
dayes immediatly preceding her
most happie &amp; comfortable reigne: call to
memorie the weaknesse &amp; perils wherin
the common weale stoode, before her high∣nesses
comming to the crowne: wey the
infinite benefites, both bodily and ghost∣ly,
that the whole realme and all her sub∣iectes
haue and do daily receaue by her
meanes: thinke vpon the greuous and
vnspeakable miseries that we all shalbe
like to susteine by losse of her vnualuable
presence: it shall be plaine that he is wil∣fully
blinde that can not sée, he is wicked∣ly
malicious that will not acknowledge,
he is obstinately stone harted that shall
not with sorrow and trembling déepely
<PB REF="3"/>
imprint in carefull hart, those motions
and thoughtes that such consideration
shall lay before him.<NOTE PLACE="marg">The Queenes good go∣uernement.</NOTE> Remember the quiet
of conscience, the comfort of true seruing
of God, the fréedome of the Realme, the
deliuerance from foreine thraldome of
soules, the escape of the heauie yoke of
strange dominion, the recouerie of welth,
the benefite of peace, the common and
egall distribution of iustice, the familiar
cherishing of Nobilitie, the good preser∣uing
and loue of the Commonaltie, the
mutual and tender kindnesse at home, the
amitie and awe abroad, the swéete enioy∣ing
of all these commodities: match here∣with
the danger and feare of losing them:
how can it then be, but that the minde
shall be marueilously distracted? Great
and full of diuersities are the sittes of a
passioned louer, but yet greatest where
reason ruleth least. Farre greater to a
good minde must be the panges of con∣sideration
in thys case, but yet greatest
where reason ruleth most. The silly lo∣uer
is transported (as they complaine
poore soules in their dities) somtyme with
ioyes of hys enioying, sometyme with
feare of his forgoing, there is no meane
or order of his excessiue affection, and all
<PB REF="3"/>
is because the abused creature hath set his
felicitie in a wrong conceite: But if such
vaine, short, repentable, and feble delite of
fansie haue such force vpon the minde of
man, how much more ought the déepe,
wise, naturall, and true impression of the
eternall comfort of soule, the good and safe
estate both of the common weale and of
the priuate hauiour of him selfe, and of
those thinges and persons that he holdeth
dearest, yea and of hys posteritie for euer,
worke more mighty, violent, and continu∣ing
effectes in the minde of an honest good
man, that setteth hys thought vpon iuste
and assured groundes? All these contem∣placions
can not but fill a good Christians
and a good subiectes eye with sight and
knowledge, how vnestimable a treasure
our Quéene, our I say Quéene Elizabeth,
is to the Realme of England,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Resest sol∣liciti plena timoris amor.</NOTE> and the same
can not but pearce hys hart with strong
feare and care for her preseruation, so
farre as surely it were able (as in the
dumme borne sonne of Cresus) to breake
the stringes of a tyed toung, to drawe
speach out of the most barbarous and ru∣dest
subiect, to crie out at her highnesses
perill, and with such noyse as he is able
to make, though it were but as a goose of
<PB REF="4"/>
the Capitole, to geue warnyng to the
watchmen of the toure of all our safeties.
This hath moued me to forget how vn∣skilfull
and how vnapt I am to treate of
matters so farre aboue me, and onely to
remember how méete it is for all men to
thinke of those thinges that touch them so
nerely. Neyther do I altogether allow of
the manerlinesse of that good fellowes cur∣tesie,
that would not vnlocke a gate to the
kyng, but made the kyng to staye there,
while he ranne two miles to fetch a more
worshipfull man to open it. And farre
more discommendable had such good ma∣ner
ben, if the kyng had then ben nerely
and egrely pursued by an enemye. When
traiterous affection so boileth in subiectes
hartes, as it can not be conteined in sto∣make,
but must breake out into open re∣bellion,
when the very humor that féedeth
such treason is so strong and so angry,
that neyther lenitiues of clemencie and
bountie can allay it, nor purgatiues of ho∣nestie
and loyaltie can expell it, it is hye
tyme to looke to the health of the body.
When the furie of treason outrageth so
farre,<NOTE PLACE="marg">A figure of the Nor∣thren rebel∣lion.</NOTE> that it ouerfloweth all the banke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
of discretion, and all the boundes of re∣membring
theyr owne perill: when they
<PB REF="4"/>
drawe euery ambitious popular witte in∣to
their fellowship, lyke an eatyng canker
or infecting sore: when they can not tary
the auantage of theyr owne tymes, the
ripenesse of their deuises, the redinesse of
their aydes, the fitnesse of seasons, nor o∣ther
circumspections of policie: when the
stay or seuering of their heades can not
holde them, but that, like an Adder when
her head is cut of, they will still be wrig∣ling
with theyr tailes and threaten a sting∣ing,
when being vanquished, they yet
finde some newe resorters vpon olde ho∣pes:
surely it must néedes appeare to be a
wonderfully malicious poyson of treason
that possesseth them, and so a great necessi∣tie
to know who be enuenimed with it,
the causes of the disease,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Sero me∣dicina pa∣ratur, cum mala per longas in∣ualüere moras.</NOTE> and the signes of
the infection, that conuenient cure may be
applied, or for the vncurable some good or∣der
may be prouided, that the head and
hart may be preserued. It is now hie time
therefore, when traitors them selues haue
geuen warning of their owne treasons,
to search the confederacie, yea and as mi∣ners
follow the signes euery way as they
spred in the ground till they be guided to
the trunke or body of the metall, so to fol∣lowe
the apparances of suspicions and
likelihodes, till it appeare plainely what
<PB REF="5"/>
light made the shadowe, or what fire raised
the smoke. It is not good tarying till the
flame mountyng in the ayre aboue the
house teppe, the principalls and pillers
consumed, and eche part so embraced with
fire that no ayde dare approch, do plainly
declare the whole building past hope of re∣couery.
Fyres oftentimes negligently ra∣ked
vp, stickes endes not throughly quen∣ched,
embers not regarded, a candeles end
not looked vnto, haue brought many an ho∣nest
man to pitifull calamitie. I like there∣fore
better the honest wisedome of those
that study how the Queene may stand
and not fall, then the reaching policie of
those that deuise how them selues may
stand when the Quéene is fallen. God pre∣serue
her highnesse long, for her fallyng
would make a Samsons poste with vs all,
yea and rightly a Samsons poste, for no
dout it woulde broose them too, that be bu∣siest
to pull it downe. I haue thought good
therfore, as a faythfull subiect, staying my
whole trust of well doing vpon the well
continuing of thys blessed estate, without
other respect, or rather prospect beyond
it, to disclose in briefe collection of the com∣mon
brute of good and honest men, that
loue thys estate and be carefull for it, so
much as I haue noted, or rather common
<PB REF="5"/>
experience &amp; euident truth hath opened,
concerning the dispositions of sundry dan∣gerous
thinges, doinges, and persons, a∣gaynst
God, the Quéenes, highnesse, the
Realme and her most noble gouernment,
to the entent that vpon laying abrode of
their faultes, them selues may be refor∣med,
or her highnesse by warning so ar∣med,
as they may be lesse dangerous, that
is to say, more restrayned and dishabled,
and her maiesties true subiectes more
strengthened and emboldened.</P>
<P>Surely all true Christians and all true
Englishe subiectes ought to beleue,<NOTE PLACE="marg">True cou∣clusions.</NOTE> and
may wel know, that these are true conclu∣sions.</P>
<P>First that euery papist, that is to say, e∣uery
one that beleueth all the Popes doc∣trine
to be true, is an enimie &amp; traytor, a∣gaynst
the maiestie and honor of God, a∣gaynst
the crownes and dignities of all
kinges and temporall princes, and against
the wealth and safetie of all ciuile king∣domes,
policies, and common weales.</P>
<P>Item that euery such English Papist
is a traytor to the Quéene of England,
and hateth her life, wisheth the alteration
of her gouernement, and liueth in hope of
an other world, which euen by an ordinary
<PB REF="6"/>
byword, it is sayd that them selues doo call
theyr Golden day.</P>
<P>Item that euery such Englishe Papist
is a speciall traytor to the realme of Eng∣land,
and hath no regarde into what slaue∣rie,
conquest, subiection to foren tyrannie,
dishonor or other miserie it be throwen, so
that theyr false idolatrous and superstici∣ous
religion be restored, with libertie
to spoyle and murder, without respect of
dignitie, age, sexe, learning, reuerence, ho∣nestie,
or nature.</P>
<P>Item that no clemencie, gentlenesse, be∣nefites,
or louing dealing, can winne a
Papist while he continueth a Papist, to
loue her maiestie, how much so euer he dis∣semble,
nor bring them to ascribe theyr
safetie to any her benefites, nor to any
prayse of her owne goodnesse, but either to
theyr own dissimulation, practise, and fals∣hed,
which some call cunning, or to the ho∣linesse
of theyr cause, for whom God for∣soothe
so prouideth as his anoynted ones
may not possibly by any law, or at least exe∣cution
of law, be touched: where in
deede, if they continue still vnpunished, it
must be thought that God so purueyeth▪
because the punishmentes of this world
are not sufficient for them. But yet in the
<PB REF="6"/>
meane time it serueth to make them vnex∣cusable,
by whose default so dangerous
wolues remayne in the flocke.</P>
<P>Item that Papistrie hath this propertie
of heresies, contrarie to the nature of
Gods truth: that is, to be throwen down
with aduersitie, and to florishe with indul∣gence
and lenitie.</P>
<P>Item that as it is reason that the owner
of a shepebiter mastife, knowing his dogs
qualitie, should either hang vp his dog,
or paye for the shéepe that his dog wori∣eth,
so those that haue notorious Shepebi∣ters,
murderers of Gods flocke, in theyr
custodie and power, must make theyr ac∣compt,
either to hang vp or otherwise dis∣patch
their curres, or ells to answere to
God for the bloud of his shéepe, both such
as they haue destroyed, and such as they
may destroy by any possibilitie hereafter.</P>
<P>Item that all aduises to great persona∣ges,
to persuade neutralitie or an enter∣teyning
of contrary sides in religion with
vncertaintie of countenance and fauor,
is the way to supplant assured safetie, to
make sure enimies and vnsure frendes, to
yle open to parasites &amp; traytors, to be vn∣knowen
to other, and to be vnhable to dis∣cerne
what other be to them.</P>
<P><PB REF="7"/>
Item that timorous policie is the worst
policie that may be, what soeuer the cause
be, good or bad, and worst of all it is in best
causes: wherein as her maiestie hath nei∣ther
want of constant magnanimitie, nor
cause of feare, so is it méete that her eni∣mies
haue no stomake to contemne her,
nor by excesse of clemencie to misconstrue
her goodnesse as lacke of daring.</P>
<P>Item that by the great nouelties and
alterations of times that haue happened
within our memorie, there is risen a com∣mon
policie among people, to ioyne to
strong and safe sides, whereby they are a∣liened
from the fearefull, and therefore it
is to be prouided, that there be a boldnesse
of safetie to serue the Quéene truely and
zelously, and an assurednesse of danger to
her enemies.</P>
<P>Item by boldnesse and sharpe executi∣on
vpon enemies, the frendes are encora∣ged,
and contrariwise if the dangerous
traytor be not remoued, the true subiect
may be left in perill, and thereby the rest
of good subiectes disabled, or at lest discou∣raged
to venture so farr agayne, and the
fréedome of consultation in the meane
time for preseruing the prince empeched.</P>
<P>Item that it is truely sayd <HI>Improbum
<PB REF="7"/>
hominem praestat non accusasse quam
absoluere.</HI> It is better not to meddle
with a dangerous noughty man, than to
let him goe: for what were it els than to set
a house a fier and runne away by the
light?</P>
<P>Item that occasions and fitte opportu∣nities
ouerslipped are not recouerable.</P>
<P>Item that many times it is as small an
offense to geue a warrant to kill a true
man, as to pardon a murderer or traytor,
as a wise shepeherd will rather geue leaue
to a hunter to kill the best lambe in hys
flocke, than to let goe a foxe or a wolfe.</P>
<P>Item that the liues of kinges and prin∣ces
are the liues and soules of theyr king∣domes
and common weales, whereby
they are to consider that in being prodigall
of theyr owne safeties in excesse of clemen∣cie
to traitors, or in securitie of exposing
theyr persons to perils, <HI>Largiuntur ex a∣lieno,</HI>
they be liberall of that which is not
theyr owne to geue.</P>
<P>Item that no traytor is more perilous,
than he that wresteth the law to rayse an
vnderminer of the princes crowne to her
danger.</P>
<P>Item that he is iustly to be suspected
that shall practise with any vayne deuise of
<PB REF="8"/>
pacification, or colored clemencie, to rebat∣or
blunt the edge of the princes sworde, or
so to tye it in the scaberde that it may not
be drawen for her defense, as if such qua∣lifiers,
hiders, and clokers, should séeke to
abuse that most reuerend and holy signe
of maiestie to no good ende or other end
than God ordeined it.</P>
<P>Item that God can not well take it, if
he be lesse zelously serued than the diuell,
that there be lesse feruencie shewed by tru∣ly
learned princes for auauncing of Gods
honor against his enemies, than hath ben
by abused and deceiued princes for setting
vp of the kingdome of the diuell and Anti∣christ.</P>
<P>Item that Gods commandementes of
placabilitie and forgeuenesse extend to our
owne enemies, but not to his enemies, a∣gainst
reuenge of priuate displeasures, and
not against seueritie &amp; sharpe execution in
cases of Gods honor and common weales:
wherein is alway to be noted, that the
Prince is so not a priuate but a publike
person, as no attempt against her safetie
can or ought to be accompted a priuate
cause.</P>
<P>The full proofe and larger explication
of these conclusions, though it be easy, as a
<PB REF="8"/>
thing which not onely all conuenientie of
reason affirmeth, but also dayly experience
laieth before all mens eyes that haue a frée
consideration not accombred with corrupt
zeale and affection, so yet surely were it a
méete thing to be handled by some such
man, as could adde thereto such ornaments
of speche, such strength of eloquence, and
pith of persuasion, as myght not onely be
vnderstoode &amp; beleued, but be felt &amp; mouel
Here any most excellent orators special-vertues
might be well employed. A fit ar¦gument
sure it were to shewe witte and
knowledge, but specially truth and good
meaning. But till some fitte person shall
take in hand to bestow his more profitable
trauayle that way, let vs yet for vnlading
of some of the abundance of our entier de∣uotion
for Gods truth, for her maiestie,
and our countrey, haue some remem∣brance
of the particularities thereof.</P>
<P>For the first article that defineth pa∣pistes,
that accuseth thē of treason to God,
to kings, and to realmes, if it be well wey∣ed
it can not but quickly be séene for vn∣douted
truth. Though it be true, that eue∣ry
one that holdeth any one error or arti∣cle
of doctrine that the Pope teacheth, va∣rying
<PB REF="9"/>
from the worde of God, is in that ar¦ticle
a papist, as for example the heresie of
transubstantiation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Not all Papistes traitors.</NOTE> the blasphemie of po∣pish
masse, or any such other, yet compt I
not euery such a one wholy a papist with∣in
compasse of this article, that is, vnder ti∣tle
of a traitorous Papist, but such a one as
holdeth all the Popes doctrine to be true,
that the Romane church erreth not, that
it hath rightfully such superioritie and pri∣macie
in others kingdomes and diocesces
as it hath proudly claimed &amp; vsurped, and
that Christians are bound to referre their
fayth vnto it, and to hang vpon the Popes
determinations. Many men otherwise
good &amp; honest subiectes are not yet purged
of all errors wherwith Rome hath infec¦ted
them, &amp; must haue their tyme to be bet∣ter
instructed. But those that are perfect
Papistes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Which Papistes, be traitors</NOTE> that publish the Pope to be head
of the church (which yet in dede is no
member of the true church) and would
haue vs with an implicite &amp; bond faith, to
depend vpon that sea, &amp; for that reason will
refuse by all lawful meanes to confesse the
right of Princes in their kingdomes ouer
all their subiectes, they be perfect traitors
in deede, yea and the learned sort of them
<PB REF="9"/>
be wilfull heretikes &amp; traitors.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Learned Papistes wilfull traytors.</NOTE> For though
in the darke tymes, when controuersies of
religion were not brought into searching,
the streame of error caried men awaye
without douting, yet since that by deba∣ting
the light hath bene euidently opened,
and men haue sought and throughly exa∣mined
the matter, there is no learned pa∣pist
but he knoweth he mainteineth error,
and in defending and spreading the same
he defendeth and spreadeth, and so directly,
aduisedly, wilfully, and maliciously, put∣teth
in execution to his vttermost power,
hye treasons against God, against kinges,
and kingdomes.</P>
<P>Against God I cal them treasons,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Treason offence a∣gainst ma∣iestie.</NOTE> though
our law, the iudge of ciuil treasons in Eng¦land,
haue no such name, because the na∣ture
of the offence so properly receaueth
that title, and also the vsuall name of hye
treason <HI>in iure gentium,</HI> in the common
law of nations, and in other languages,
doth so playnely expresse it. Hye treasons
are in their true nature, offences against
hye maiestie, that is, either to the destructi∣on
of the persons, or denyall and deface∣ment
of the iust dignities and authorities
of those that beare the name of maiestie,
<PB REF="10"/>
and to whom the hyest dutie of obedience
faith and alleageance extendeth. And there∣fore
is treason called <HI>Crimen lesae maie∣statis,</HI>
the crime of violating or abating of
maiestie. Greater maiestie than the maie∣stie
of God can not be, therefore hyer and
verier treasons then against God can not
be.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Treason against God.</NOTE> His person can not be destroyed, or tou∣ched:
his dignitie, honor, glorie, and autho∣ritie,
may be sclaundered and blasphemed,
and his subiectes, that is, mortall men,
may be withdrawen from their due obedi∣ence,
and drawen into rebellion against
him. And this I say is hye treason to God,
to violate or abate the maiestie of God:
and this do papistes. For though God be
king of the whole world, and so is rightly
called the Lord by vniuersall name, yea e∣uen
of deuilles: yet is hys chirch hys more
proper and certaine kingdome, whereby
he is more restrainedly and aptly called
our king and our father, and so more fitly
called our head in respect of the body, which
is his chirch and not the rest of the worlde.
In this kingdome hys hyest dignitie is to
be the onely head thereof, which the Pa∣pistes
take from him, and deriue it to their
Pope. And though with gloses they excuse
<PB REF="10"/>
it, that theyr Popes take it not from God,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> vnder God, as his vicars, yet
must they be admonished, that wythout
sufficient deputation and warrant from
the kyng himselfe, (which the Pope hath
not) the subiect to thrust himselfe into go∣uernance
of the kingdome is hye treason,
where he that being a stranger would seke
to conquere it, were but an enemy. And so
is it rightly to be sayd that the Turke is
to God an enemy, and the Pope is to God
a traytor, and all his adherentes principall
traytors, for treason admitteth no accessa∣ries.</P>
<P>Also one great part of Gods maiestie
standeth in making of lawes, to gouerne
his kingdome, that hys shéepe shall heare
hys voyce and no strangers. Against which
poynt of maiestie, as it is hye treason to
publish lawes and proclamations in ciuile
kynges names against their wyll, so are
papistes hye traytors in publishing and re∣ceauing
lawes, proclamations, and decrées
from a climing and vsurping tyrant to
bynde Gods subiectes the chirch, wythout
the wyll and warrant of God.</P>
<P>Also rebelliously to burne, destroy,
tread downe, or deface in great contempt,
<PB REF="11"/>
the commissions and lawes of temporall
kynges, is an hye offence against maiestie,
and therefore papistes, that dishonor and
discredit the word of God, and destroy the
bookes thereof, are hye offenders agaynst
hys maiestie.</P>
<P>Also hie treason it is for the subiect to
leuie warre agayst hys soueraigne, and to
destroy hys lande, hys faythfull subiectes,
and true liege people. And therefore Pa∣pistes
in their persecuting and murderyng
of Christians with open hostilitie, haue
shewed themselues hye traytors to the vni∣uersall
King of Christians.</P>
<P>Also where the counterfaityng of prin∣ces
handes and coynes, and the clipping
and abating the value of their true coynes,
and the vttering of such forged and abated
coine, is hie treason: what lesse name than
hye treason agaynst God, can we geue to
papistes, that haue counterfait the writing
and coynes of God, and geuen out false
commissions, false patentes and false char∣ters
in stede of his worde, that clippe from
the dignitie and sufficiencie of hys word,
that haue coyned false heresies, abated true
doctrines, &amp; so do publish and vtter them.</P>
<P>Also if corrupting and counterfaityng
<PB REF="11"/>
of Princes seales, and geuing out or an∣nexing
his seales to false charters of theyr
owne in the Princes name, be hye trea∣son:
are they not hye traitors to God, that
corrupt his seales his Sacramentes, and
set forth new priuate institutions of
their owne, as Masses, and such bagages,
in stede of them, I meane not onely the in∣uenters
and forgers, but also the recei∣uers,
publishers, vtterers, and cariers a∣brode
of such abhominable vntruthes?</P>
<P>Also what greater offense agaynst Ma∣iestie
can be, than to commaunde the
Princes subiectes not to beleue the Prin∣ces
word or writyng, nor any thyng that
shall passe by his authoritie, without such
offenders confirmation and allowance:
And that the Princes word and writyng
suffiseth not to direct the subiectes dutie,
without such offenders explication and
addicions: And that such offenders
may adde at their pleasure: And that
such addicions are to be holden equal with
the Princes word: And that the Princes
word must euer be so taken as such offen∣ders
expound it, &amp; none otherwise? Then
must the Papistes, in theyr discredityng
the word of God, in their dishablyng it as
not sufficyng to the instruction of our
<PB REF="12"/>
fayth, for the saluation of our soules▪ in
theyr clayming false and vndue authoritie
to theyr traditions, and in their restray∣ning
the word of God to their expositions
though directly against the word &amp; against
the spirite of God, nedes be accompted
hye traitors agaynst Gods maiestie.</P>
<P>Also the greatest honor and dignitie
that God hath and chalengeth ielously to
hym selfe among men, is the redemption
and iustification of man. The Papistes,
which draw that from God to man, from
grace to workes, as they are most hay∣nous
and blasphemous traitors to God
in denying his frée graciousnesse therin, so
are they most arrant theues to Christian
men in robbyng them of the benefite
therof.</P>
<P>Also if to deny that the Prince ought to
enioye the stile, kyngly name, and dignitie
of the realme, with al preeminences to they
same belongyng, be hye treason: are the
not hye traitors to God, that take from
God the name of our onely Iustifier, and
from Christ the title of our onely redemer
and Aduocate, and from the holy ghost the
office and stile of our onely true and suffi∣cient
Instructer?</P>
<P>Also seing that to defile the kynges wife
<PB REF="12"/>
is hye treason, wherby the succession of
hys crowne may growe to dishonor and
oncertaintie: are not Papistes then hye
traitors that haue made the church the
spouse of God, to commit so many fowle
spirituall whoredomes, with idolatries,
heresies and yeldyng her selfe to be abused
of strangers?</P>
<P>So appeareth it euidently that, if vio∣latyng
of maiestie: if denyng the kyng to
be the onely kyng and hed of hys owne
realme: if vsurpyng supreme gouernance
without the kynges assignement: if ma∣kyng
and receiuyng lawes and proclama∣tions,
in the kynges name, without hys
warrant: if destroyeng and defacyng
in contempt, the kynges charters: if le∣uyeng
warre agaynst the kyng, within
the realme, and murderyng hys subiectes:
if counterfaityng the kynges coyne or
seales: if annexyng hys seales to false wri∣tynges:
if abatyng hys coyne, by clippyng
or otherwise: if vtterance of such forged,
or abated ware: if discredityng the Prin∣ces
word and authoritie, and auauncyng
their owne aboue it: if denyeng the kinges
right to hys kyngly office: if takyng from
him hys royal stile name &amp; dignitie: if cor∣ruptyng
hys wife with adulterie: if any of
<PB REF="13"/>
these, if all these together, be hye treason:
Papistes are hye traitors to the maiestie
of almightie God.</P>
<P>But these parhappes may be thought
to be but allegoricall or figuratiue trea∣sons,
(so litle the matters of God do moue
vs) and in the eye and consideration of the
law of the realme they are none other, yet
are they in very dede truely treasons &amp; of∣fenses
agaynst the hyest maiestie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Kinges should haue care of Gods honour.</NOTE> euen the
same maiestie by whom kynges do reigne
and are vpholden, and the same maiestie
for which kynges ought to be carefull, if
they will haue hym to prouide for theyr
maiesties. Yea they are the very sedes of
ciuil &amp; temporall treasons. For vndouted∣ly,
as no man breaketh out into actuall
sinne agaynst men, that hath not first yel∣ded
to an assent to offend God: so no man
procedeth so farre as to commit treason a∣gaynst
the Prince,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistrie sede of ci∣uile trea∣son.</NOTE> that hath not first con∣ceiued
a traiterous minde to rebel against
God. And as of ordinarie course and na∣turall
necessitie it foloweth, that full and
strong sedes, throwen in ground fit for
them, cherished with conuenient moi∣sture,
and comfortable heate of norishyng
sonne, must rankly growe and bring forth
herbes or wedes of theyr propre kynd: so
<PB REF="13"/>
these traitorous sedes layed vp in fat soile
of Papistes bosomes, if they be watered
with welth and indulgence, and shyned
vpon with the cherefull glimses of oppor∣tunities,
will surely bryng forth the frutes
of theyr owne qualitie, treasons agaynst
princes.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Heresies punished by tempo∣rall law.</NOTE> And for this respect, other offenses
that haue in tymes past ben wrongfully
supposed to be of this nature, haue ben al∣so
punished by the lawes of the realme. In
ancient order of Letes, and other courtes,
they haue ben enquired vpon before trea∣sons
done to the prince. They haue had
theyr seuerall formes of punishmentes,
yea in some cases they haue ben, and in
some places and causes they yet be, ex∣empted
from the Princes power to par∣don.
They haue bene termed by speciall
names of heresies and blasphemies: and
theyr punishementes, byside temporall
peynes, haue ben extended in opinion to
the further reuenge of the eternall Ma∣iestie,
whoes crowne and dignitie they
haue ben thought to violate. And surely,
if in discernyng which were heresies and
blasphemies, they had not erred: if they
had not mistaken, and executed the true
man for the traitor: the generall care
which was pretended to mainteyne truth
<PB REF="14"/>
and the church, stode well with the dutie
of Christian Princes, as viceroyes and de∣puties
iustly zelous for theyr superior or
rather supreme Lord king of kynges and
Lord of lordes, the true monarch of whole
vniuersalitie. And though the same late
&amp; new deceiued antiquitie swarued from
true iudgement of the persons and causes,
I can not well sée howe that should be a
warrant to disburden Princes of imita∣tion
of that zele, when it is ones ioyned
with right vnderstandyng, no more than
the wrongfull hangyng of a true man by
mistakyng hym for a thefe or a murderer,
ought to be a discharge for the very thefe
or murderer, when he is afterward taken
in dede. And without doubt more hole∣some
and profitable it were for these here∣ticall
traitors agaynst God,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mercie to punish Papistes.</NOTE> I meane the
Papistes them selues, to be in this lyfe, by
some sharper law and execution driuen to
repentance, than to be repried or reser∣ued
to arrainement before the last iudge,
whoes knowledge can not be deciued,
whoes iusties can not then be entreated,
whoes execution hath neither end nor
measure: and so a litle more hardnesse
with them a while, would be a very bene∣ficiall
and mercyfull sharpnesse.</P>
<P><PB REF="14"/>
But now let vs come to that part that
toucheth men more nerely than any loue of
God.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistes traitors to kinges and king∣domes.</NOTE> Let vs sée how they be traitors to
kinges and kingdomes. If we haue minde
to sée that Papistes, which holde all the
Popes doctrine, to be true, are traitors in
déede to kinges and kingdomes, it beho∣ueth
to call to minde what be the Popes
doctrines, doinges &amp; practises concerning
the crownes of kinges and states of king∣domes.
Popes haue chalenged, and Pa∣pistes
that affirme the Popes to be frée
from errour,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Traito∣rous doc∣trines of Popes for kinges and kingdoms.</NOTE> their doctrine to be true, and
their authoritie to be lawfull, do also holde
that it is their due which they chalenge,
that is, to haue the authoritie of both
swordes, spirituall and temporall, the one
in exercise, the other in power: to haue
the disposition of all the crownes of Chri∣stian
Princes: to haue the iudgement of
deciding to whom the right of any king∣dome
belongeth: to haue power for dis∣obedience
to him, or by hys discretion, to
transferre the crownes of kings to whom
he will: to haue lawfull power, to geue
kingdomes to prey, spoyle, and conquest,
to such as can inuade and possesse them: to
haue power to assoile and discharge Chri∣stian
subiectes, from fayth and allegeance
<PB REF="15"/>
to their lawfull and naturall soueraigne
Lordes, Kinges, and Princes: to haue
power to geue leaue, yea commaunde∣ment,
blessing, reward, forgeuenesse of
sinnes, and heauen it selfe, to subiectes to
rebell against the Prince, to depose the
Prince, disherite and destroy him: that
there is of common right, and by the mere
lawe of God, reserued to the Pope a spe∣ciall
subiection, resort, appellation, and o∣bedience
of one great part of all Princes
subiectes, yea and of all subiectes of all
Princes in one great part of their causes.
Be not these hainous treasons? And these
can not be denied to be the naturall and
very treasons of all Papistes, that is to
say, of all that depend vpon credit of the
Pope, that holde hym for Gods vicar, for
Peters successor, for whom Christ prayed
that hys fayth should not faile, that applie
to him this title <HI>ad quem persidia non po∣test
accedere,</HI> to whom falshode can not
reach, that holde hym for a constant rocke,
an assured preacher of truth, an apostoli∣call
man, if he be not some other thing
than a man, to whom our belefe is boun∣den,
with such other false titles, where∣with
Popes them selues haue garnished
them selues and their parasites haue ouer∣loden
them.</P>
<P><PB REF="15"/>
Consider the ordinarie practise of
Popes and Papistes accordyng to these
doctrines,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Traite∣rous do∣inges of Papistes against kinges and king∣domes.</NOTE> and than shall you sée, that
from the most hye treason which the Pope
committed against hys soueraigne Lorde
the Emperour, the renting and destructi∣on
of the Empire, all the victories and suc∣cesses
of the Saracens &amp; Turkes against
Christendome, all the tearyng away of
most noble and large kingdomes and pro∣uinces
from the body of Christianitie, all
the subduing and thrallyng of infinite
Christian soules to Mahomete and the de∣uill,
all the deposinges, murderinges, tur∣moyllinges,
ciuile warres, debates be∣twene
Christian Princes, shedinges of
Christian bloud, indignities and oppressi∣ons
of Christian kinges and Emperours,
conquestes, rebellions, and mischiefes, for
these v. C. yeares and aboue, are wholly
or chiefly to be imputed to the treasons of
Popes and Papistes. All sometime most
learned and noble Grecia yet lamentably
rueth it. All Africa the mother of most con∣stant
Martyrs féeleth it. The Germane
Emperours, with most hainous repro∣ches
and foule treading in their neckes,
may not forget it. The kinges of Fraunce
and Spaine, bothe at home in their natiue
<PB REF="16"/>
kingdomes, and abrode, as well in Na∣ples,
Sicile, Lombardie, as in other terri∣tories
of Italie and of the Empire, haue
sharply felt it. The Lordes and states of
Italie haue bene daily and long shaken
with it. The kinges of England haue bene
poisoned, whipped, beaten with roddes,
murdered, deposed, the land geuen in con∣quest,
enterdited, made tributarie, robbed,
pilled &amp; scraped of their treasure, brought
into slauishe subiection, depriued of honour
and estimation, euery way most villa∣nously
abused. To let passe the elder times
and further realmes, let vs speake nothing
of deposing of olde Emperours, erecting of
new, setting the sonne against the father,
the subiect against his Lord, making them
come barefooted them selues with theyr
wiues and children long wayting with
submission in colde frostes, treading in
their neckes, spurning of their crownes,
and a thousand such abhominable prides of
Popes and slaueries of Princes. Let vs
deale, but with our selues, and with our
owne féeling, knowledge, and memorie.
The accursing of king Iohn, the receauing
him vassall, the making his Realme sub∣iecte
and feudatarie to the Pope, the ar∣ming
<PB REF="16"/>
his subiectes against him, the poyso∣ning
of him at length, the geuing the land
to the French Kinges sonne, the inuading
thereof by the Dolphine of Fraunce, his
so long possessing a great part of it, the re∣bellion
of the Barons to take the French∣mens
part, all the mischiefes that fell in
all this while, were they not the good
workes of Popes and Papistes? The great
diuision of the two noble houses of Yorke
and Lancaster, which cost so much English
bloud, that there remaineth no house of hie
or meane nobilitie, that hath not smarted
for it, so many foughten fieldes within the
Realme, so long and so great vncertaintie
which side were true men and which
were traitors, and for how many daies
or houres they should be so estéemed, such
desolation and miseries, to whom are they
to be imputed, but to the Popish Clergie
and Papistes, and among other to Tho∣mas
Arundell Archebishop of Canterbu∣rie
that traitorously practised the depo∣sing
of his lawfull soueraigne Lord king
Richard the second? But come yet to la∣ter
times. How was the Quéenes ma∣iesties
most noble father assalted by the
Pope and Papistes? His Realme was
<PB REF="17"/>
interdited and geuen away to him that
could catch it. Legates, and one notable
Englishe traitor, were sent about to per∣suade
Christian Princes, to inuade Eng∣land,
to destroy and depose King Henrie,
and to take the Realme in reward for
their labour. When Charles the late
Emperour was setting forward against
the Turke, Cardinall Pole being sent
by the Pope, made a solemne Oration
to him, which is yet extant in Print, to
persuade the Emperour to turne his pre∣pared
power from inuading the Turke,
and to bend it against King Henrie the
viij. as one worse then any Turke. What
turmoile was raised then by the Northren
rebells against him, whereof some by his
elemencie (a good example) haue liued to
this day to raise a new rebellion? How
troubled they her maiesties most excel∣lent
brother with vnhappie seditions?
How vexed they and how endangered they
the Realme and the Quéenes owne per∣son
in her sisters time? What might
Charles the Emperour haue done for re∣couerie
and enlarging of Christendome,
if his force that way entended had not by
Popish practise bene peruerted sundry
<PB REF="17"/>
waies and times, to the sheding of Chri∣stian
bloud and wasting of Christen∣dome,
and to the ouerthrow of his victo∣rious
course? What tempestes hath the
late conspiracie of Trent blowen vp in
Christendome, that can not yet be quie∣ted,
and all because the Pope hath in∣stilled
an opinion into his Papistes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Pope tea∣cheth to keepe no fayth.</NOTE> that
Princes, if he dispense with them, are
not bound to kéepe fayth and promise, no
not the word of a king, wherby no peace
can yet be assured? Whereof yet riseth
one good admonition, to trust them no
more, and to be well ware of them, and
specially to thinke of this one particular,
that wicked persons which haue geuen
occasion of dangerous rebellions against
the Quéenes maiestie their chiefe and
onely succour and refuge, will neuer be
witholden by any respecte from attemp∣ting
or procuring to be attempted any
most hie and hainous treason and mis∣chiefes,
against our soueraigne Ladies
safetie, if auantageable opportunitie may
serue them, so long as such persons are
infected with Papistrie, and can thinke
the Pope hable to pardon or rather wil∣ling
to reward them, yea so farre as they
shall suppose them selues not onely to
<PB REF="18"/>
winne the kingdome of England therby,
but also the kingdome of heauen. It is
perilous to thinke what traitorous rage
may do, being armed with dronken su∣perstition.
It is a sore thing to consider
the impotentie of ambition, specially
when it is ioyned with the furie of rea∣sonlesse
loue. The common experience
is, how dangerous those knottes of
théeues be where there is a woman in
the companie. Thus is it plaine, that
for as much as the Pope claimeth such
wrongfull vsurpation and tyrannie ouer
kinges and realmes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ladie of North.</NOTE> and sith Papistes
holde that he saith true, and claimeth but
his right, and can not erre in discerning
it, all such Papistes are traitors to all
kinges and kingdomes.</P>
<P>As for the second conclusion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">English Papistes traitors to the Q.</NOTE> which
accuseth English Papistes of treason to
the Quéenes maiestie, it is sufficiently
proued, for that it is as a particular with∣in
a generall, included in the former. Yet
for the speciall confirmation of it, it hath
certaine priuate and seuerall reasons.
It is well knowen how they sought her
graces death in her sisters time: what
practises, what fetches were vsed for it:
what examinations, what searchinges,
<PB REF="18"/>
were to finde color of her destruction,
yea (if it be true, which is credibly sayd)
how farre without color they proceded,
if God had not miraculously kept her,
to the preseruation of this Realme and
the comfort of whole Christendome. But
to make some demonstration of their ha∣tred
to her maiestie by reason, and after
to descend to the examples and practi∣ses,
let vs examine the causes.</P>
<P>Whereas the Papistes holde, that
the Pope is head of Gods vniuersall
Church, and that such authoritie as the
Quéene claimeth in England ouer ec∣clesiasticall
persons and in ecclesiasticall
causes, as due to her highnesse in right
of her crowne, is not due to her, but be∣longing
to the Pope, in so saying they
must say that her maiestie claimeth an vn∣iust
tyrannicall power. And whosoeuer
shall so say, though not in the same silla∣bles,
is an vniust and an errant traitor,
and can not loue her that hath pulled
downe him whom they call head of their
Church.</P>
<P>Also where Papistes affirme the
Chirch of Rome to be the true Catho∣licke
Chirch of God, and that, as out of
Noes Arke there was no safetie from
<PB REF="19"/>
drowning, so out of the Romane Church
there is no escape of damnation: is there
any hope, that they so thinking can or
do loue her highnesse, that hath dismem∣bred
them from the body of that Chirch,
and plucked them out of that Cocklorelles
boate?</P>
<P>Where Papistes holde the heresie of
transubstantiation, and the bread to be
Christes naturall bodie, the blasphemie
of Popishe Masse to be an auailing sacri∣fice
for quicke and dead, the Popes par∣dons
to be hable to deliuer them from
hell and damnation:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Traian.</NOTE> is it likely that they
loue her whom they thinke to depriue
them of so great treasures?</P>
<P>Where the Papistes holde our whole
forme of seruing of God,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistes take not the Q. for Queene.</NOTE> which forme
the Quéenes maiestie hath prescribed and
deliuered to her subiectes, to be schisma∣ticall,
our lawes in spirituall thynges no
lawes, our sacramentes no sacramentes,
our Bishops no Bishops, our Clergie
no Clergie, surely they thinke our Coro∣nations
no Coronations, our Quéene no
Quéene, or at least they are sory she is so.</P>
<P>Where Papistes beleue a Purgatorie,
and that Masses, Diriges, and such other
gainfull marchandise of the Popish Cler¦gie,
<PB REF="19"/>
be beneficiall for their frendes soules
and their owne, and do in the meane time
imagine that theyr fathers, grandsires,
grandames, wiues, and other frendes
soules lie frying in vnexplicable tor∣mentes,
and the Quéenes maiestie hol∣deth
from them the onely meane to release
them: thinke you such persons grudge
not at her excéedingly?</P>
<P>Where the Pope hath accursed the
Quenes maiestie as an heretike and schis∣matike,
all those Papistes which suppose
that the Pope hauing the disposition of
Gods sentence and the thunderbolt of ex∣communication
in his hand, can not erre,
do also suppose that the Quenes highnesse
(our Quene Elizabeth I meane) is not
lawfull Quene of England, for so must all
Papistes hold, that hold the Pope to say
true, for the Pope doth not so accept her.</P>
<P>And true it is that the refusall of the
othe for the acknowledging her Maiesties
supremacie ouer ecclesiasticall persones
and in ecclesiasticall causes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistes refuse the othe, be∣cause they beleue not the Q. ti∣tle to the crowne.</NOTE> is for very
good reasons to be suspected, that for the
most part it is but coloured with pretense
of conscience for ecclesiasticall causes, and
to be thought that in very deede it depen∣deth
chefely vpon this poynt, that sith her
<PB REF="20"/>
Maiestie hath bene suspended, excommu∣nicated
and declared out of the church by
the Pope, they thinke her Maiestie not
lawfull Quene of England. For the like
example or preiudice haue the like Pa∣pistes
geuen heretofore at many times,
and namely when Elizabeth Barton, that
hipocriticall harlot, sometime called the
holy mayde of Kent, with whose false
traitorous practises were fowly spotted
and entangled More and Fisher the new
Romishe Saintes, published as a reuela∣tion
from God, a traytorous article sug∣gested
vnto her by popishe Priestes and
Monkes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">In the sta∣tute of her atte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nder.</NOTE> with whom she carnally and fil∣thily
liued, that the Queenes Maiesties
most noble father after a time by them li∣mited,
was not King of England one
houre in the sight of God. The like in∣terpretation
did Papistes make of king
Iohn. And Papistes haue published that
Gospellers, whom they call heretikes,
ought not to haue any office among Gods
people, much lesse a kingdome.</P>
<P>And this poynt is well to be considered
that they which take from the Quéenes
maiestie the supremacie ouer ecclesiastical
persones and causes, do transferre the
same iurisdiction to the Pope, for they ne∣uer
<PB REF="20"/>
yet bouch saued to geue it to any other▪
and I am sure that after so many parables
and examples of bées and beastes and o∣ther
thynges, they will not now haue any
particular church hedlesse and destitute of
a supreme gouernor, either vniuersall like
a monarch as they wold haue it, or speciall
vnder God of eche kingdome or dominion
as Gods good disposition hath sorted it. If
then the Pope haue in theyr opinion any
ecclesiasticall iurisdiction in England, he
must haue <HI>Ius excommunicandi</HI> lawfull
power and authoritie to excommunicate
in England, without which the ecclesia∣sticall
power can not stand. Which power
if he iustly haue, and hath excommunicate
and accursed the Quéene, either by speciall
name or generally vnder title of heretikes
of which sort he estemeth her, then hath
he therin done <HI>pro suo iure</HI> as he lawful∣ly
myght do. And this beyng so supposed
true,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistes draw obe∣dience from the Q.</NOTE> then is it good to consider what is ta∣ken
for Gods law and the law ecclesiasti∣call
<HI>De vitandis excommunicatis,</HI> for
shonnyng of excommunicate and accursed
persones which yeld not to any repen∣tance
submission or reconciliation to
that church, forsothe that euery Christian
in peyne of excommunication <HI>de iure</HI>
<PB REF="21"/>
(wherein to dye is thought to dye in state
of damnation) is bound to withdrawe
from such accursed persons not repen∣tyng,
all frendly or louyng company and
countenance, all ayde and relefe, all ser∣uice
and obedience. Which doyng, for
these good subiectes of England to put in
execution toward the Quéene,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistes meritori∣ous trea∣son.</NOTE> were a ve∣ry
meritorious act: But what doth it me∣rite?
the iust peynes of treason for brea∣kyng
theyr due allegeance, and eternall
damnation (if they repent not) for resi∣styng
Gods lawfull ordinance. This
géere goeth sore, it is very euident and
playne, that by necessary consequence, to
this confession of traitorousnesse they
must be driuen, if they will continue Pa∣pistes,
that is will affirme the Popes sen∣tences
not to erre, or will geue the Pope
any spirituall iurisdiction in England.</P>
<P>Wherfore these refusalles to acknow∣ledge
her maiesties lawfull power by
othe,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Refusers of the othe, mete to be well exa∣mined.</NOTE> would be well looked vnto, and the
pretenses, colors, and causes of such refu∣salles
would be well examined, namely in
such as shall haue to do with iustice and
gouernyng the contrye, but specially with
those that shall haue accesse into her hygh∣nesse
houshold and presence. And well it
<PB REF="21"/>
would be sought what defense of dispen∣sation,
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Popish dispensati∣ons to dis∣semble.</NOTE> or toleration they haue for theyr dis∣semblyng
theyr purposes in not yet execu∣tyng
the Popes sentence agaynst her, and
what deuises they haue for warrantyng
of theyr consciences in suspendyng such
treasons till stronger opportunities, what
absolutions or instructions Popishe A∣postles
haue brought at theyr secret step∣pyng
into England agayne. For such
salues are not vnlikely to come out of hys
shoppe that dispenseth with breach of
fayth, yea that openly proclaymeth that
there is no fayth to be kept with Christes
frendes &amp; hys aduersaries, hys shop I say
that can geue grace to haue consecrated
altarstones or superaltares for hys traito∣rous
frendes in enterdited landes to haue
masse without peril, his shop that can send
out badges with leaue to sweare and vn∣sweare
with so liberal permissiō, as to say,
<HI>Geue me thy hart and it suffiseth.</HI> And
well may it suffice, for the hart will cary
the hand too, when opportunitie serueth,
&amp; when theyr Golden day approcheth, of
which they make so great accompt. Such
good fellowes would be well looked vpon?</P>
<P>And for as much as Papistes accompt
theyr Popes decrées the voyce of Gods
<PB REF="22"/>
spirite frée from error, it is to be weyed,
how farre we must nedes thinke they
suppose the Popes curse to haue extended
agaynst our most noble Quéene &amp; realme,
with whoes publike seruice and prayer,
yea where nothyng is vsed but the vndou∣ted
word of God and agreable with it,
they can not finde in theyr hartes to com∣municate,
but abhorre it as schismaticall.
They would be opposed with a few inter∣rogatories.
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Interro∣gatories for Papistes.</NOTE> It would be enquired, whe∣ther
they thynke our Quéene lawfully
Quéene of thys realme before God, not∣withstandyng
the Popes sentence? And
whether they thinke the Popes sentence
to reache any nerer vnto her hyghnesse,
then if it had béen the sentence of the By∣shop
of Toledo, or the Byshop of Paris,
and not geuen by the Byshop of Rome or
vnder hys authoritie? And if it reach nea∣rer,
then how farre it reacheth? And if it
extend to cases touchyng her hyghnesses
crowne and dignitie, or the seruice and o∣bedience
of her subiectes, or so farre as it
were treason for any English subiect to
put it in execution in England: then whe∣ther
the Pope in so presumyng, and publi∣shyng
that he doth but as he lawfully
may do, haue iudicially erred, &amp; in matter
<PB REF="22"/>
both of fact &amp; doctrine passed hys boundes
or no?</P>
<P>But to come somewhat nerer to Pa∣pistes,
alway supposing such Papistes as
I haue before specially described, I shall
in one thyng moue myne owne conceite
for a question in law, referring it yet to the
correction &amp; iudgement of such as be lear∣ned
in law, of which sort I trust there be
none that haue not already by theyr othes
acknowledged the Quéenes maiesties full
authoritie and so haue declared that them
selues be not giltie.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistes traitors by statute.</NOTE> The statute made in
the first yeare of the Quéenes maiesties
reigne, the vj. Chap. sayth thus: <HI>And be it
&amp;c. that if any person or persones at
anie tyme after the sayd first day of May
next to come, by any writing, printyng,
ouert dede or act, maliciously, aduised∣ly
and directly do affirme that the
Quenes maiestie that now is ought not
to haue and enioy <HI>the stile, honor, and
kingly name of this realme &amp;c.</HI> shalbe de∣med
and adiudged hye traitors.</HI> I take
it by the same Statute that such an affir∣mation
that the Quéenes maiestie ought
not to haue and enioy the crowne of Ire∣land,
is hye treason, for that the kingdome
of Ireland is of ryght perteinyng to the
<PB REF="23"/>
crowne of England, and the title therof
is belongyng to and parcell of the <HI>stile, ho∣nor
and kingly name of this realme,</HI> and is in
the Quenes maiesties vsuall stile so plain∣ly
expressed. And so thynke I so much as
is conteyned in the Quéenes maiesties
royall stile, or as the law doth in anie wise
say to be parcell of the <HI>stile, honor or kingly
name of this realme.</HI> But the Quéenes iu∣risdiction
ouer ecclesiasticall persones &amp; in
ecclesiasticall causes within this realme, is
parcell of the ancient right of the crowne,
and so part of the <HI>stile, kingly name or honor
of this realme,</HI> and so it is acknowledged in
the first statute of the same Parliament,
where it is sayd, <HI>May it &amp;c. for the resto∣ryng
of the rightes, iurisdictions and
preeminences apperteinyng to the im∣periall
crowne of this your realme &amp;c.</HI>
Item, <HI>for the restoryng and vnityng to
the imperial crowne of this realme the
auncient iurisdictions, authoritie, supe∣riorities
and preeminences to the same
of right belongyng and apperteinyng,</HI>
Also the authoritie of Rome is in sundry
places of the same first statute recogni∣sed
to be <HI>vsurped,</HI> which can not be if the
Quenes supremacie do not of right per∣teine
to her croune. Which act is also in∣titled
<PB REF="23"/>
<HI>An act for restoryng to the croune the
auncient iurisdiction ouer the state ecc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esia∣sticall
&amp;c.</HI> Moreouer the same her maie∣sties
right is playnty expressed to be par∣cell
of the <HI>stile, honor and kingly name of
this realme</HI> in the vsuall stile as it is set out
at large in her maiesties Iniunctions, and
also conteyned in the commonly written
stile vnder thys clause <HI>et cetera,</HI> which
wordes <HI>et cetera</HI> can not be referred to no∣thyng.
And therfore I playnly gather that
to play the good plaine Papist, to affirme
the Popes hedshyp of the Church of Eng∣land,
or to denie the Quéenes supremacie
in her owne realme, so farre as her maie∣stie
by the law hath it, and as it is incident
to her croune, is to play or rather in good
earnest to be a hye traitor.</P>
<P>As for the maner of affirmation <HI>(ma∣liciously,
aduisedly and directly)</HI> menci∣oned
in the statut: if it be affirmed by a
man sober, it wil easelie enough be iudged
to be <HI>aduisedly and maliciously.</HI> And I
nothing doubt that the terme <HI>directly</HI>
doth not restrayne to the same forme of
syllables, but at least to any plaine, cer∣taine,
or indicatiue proposition concluding
or expressing the same effect.</P>
<P>But now how haue these good fellowes
<PB REF="24"/>
shewed their good affection in practise?<NOTE PLACE="marg">Practises of Papists against the Q.</NOTE>
For sothe some, the great ghostlie fathers,
whereof some yet liue <HI>et insidiantur sa∣luti
bonorum &amp; reipub.</HI> and lie in waite
for destruction of the state and of good sub∣iectes,
refuse to acknowledge her Maie∣sties
authoritie, and that so doubtfully, as
it is not expressedly certaine, how soeuer
it be consequently euident, whether they
sticke at the matter of the supremacie, or
the very title of the crowne.</P>
<P>Other some are such,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Storie.</NOTE> as one of them,
euen openly in her Maiesties hiest court
of Parliament made such mone that his
counsell was not followed in Quene Ma∣ries
time to hew vp the roote, as all men
plainly saw and vnderstood his greefe that
the Quenes Maiestie was not in her si∣sters
time dispatched. And it is sayd that
some other made graue motions for her
disheritance.</P>
<P>Other,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lonanists.</NOTE> because they can not get her
highnesse to cesse to be their lawful quene,
them selues haue deuised to cesse to be her
actuall subiectes. Because they can not
shift her Maiestie from her crowne, they
haue shifted them selues out of her high∣nesses
dominions, and are fled beyond the o¦seas.
<PB REF="24"/>
Some being there send hether their
heretical,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Seditious writers.</NOTE> seditious and traitorous bookes,
yet licenced there against good president of
Princes, and against the example of her
Maiesties honorable demeanour toward
the same Princes, which by them selues or
their Officers, rather ought to haue re∣strained
such doinges, then to leaue so
shrewd occasion of taking harme them sel∣ues
by the like. In these bookes her right
is impugned: her faith is defamed: her go∣uernement
is discredited: her honour is
touched: her Maiestie is many wayes vi∣olated
and abated: the Religion that her
highnesse holdeth and publisheth, is called
schismaticall, heretical, deuellish, and with
as many ill fauored names as they can re∣herse,
being yet in such eloquence perfecte
oratours: the Preachers and professers
of the religion that her highnesse setteth
forth and professeth, are termed worsse
then Infidels: her title of supremacie ouer
all her subiectes is defaced for an vsurped
and vndue name. And yet forsothe they
thinke this geare gayly colored, and there∣by
conducted to haue safe passage among
her subiectes, if they can say, not that the
Queene is an heretike, a schismatike,
<PB REF="25"/>
worse then an Infidel, not to be heard, not
to be obeyed, not to be esteemed to haue in
dede the holy places and offices whose title
she beareth, but pardie that al they be such
that holde the same religion which the
Quene doth not only hold, but also aduise,
commaund &amp; procure to be holden. They
thinke it trimly handled, if they do not
say that the Quene chalengeth and vsur∣peth
a proude, wrongfull and false title,
but onely that her Clergie haue fastened
vpon her such a title, which it is well kno∣wen
that with free conscience she vseth.
They thinke them selues cunning fel∣lowes,
and their bookes well warranted
in England, if they do not call the Quene
in plaine speache Tirant, Infidel, Arrian,
and such like, when vndirectly they implie
it, and do applie to her cause the examples
of pagane, Arrian, tirānous and wicked
Kinges and Emperours. Who seeth
not this so grosse a mockerie offered to so
wyse a Prince? as if for good maners sake
they would forbeare to say that Iohn is a
foole, and onely say that he that is in Ihons
skinne is a foole. God rid their skinnes of
vntrue subiectes. This is done like fine
men, all together as suttle and as false, as
<PB REF="25"/>
our late Rebelles, that rising in armour
with actuall rebellion against her Maie∣stie
and her gouernance, would yet nedes
proclaime that they were true and faith∣full
subiectes, well disposed persons, and
had very good meanings. Yet were those
false traytours somewhat more curious of
their honestie and truth than these good
writers, for those Rebelles yet reserued
one sure starting hole, to defend their fast∣nesse
to the Quene, because they haue not
told vs what Quene they meant.</P>
<P>An other companie of good sure men
at home,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Spreders of seditious bookes.</NOTE> receiue these goodly bookes, sprede
them abroade, rede them in audiences and
corners, commend them, defend them,
geue them great praises for learning and
substantialnesse, as matters vnanswera∣ble,
they amplifie them, they set them out,
much like to false seditious talebearers
that during this late rebellion spred ru∣mors
in the quiet partes of the Realme,
what numbers of thousandes these re∣belles
were, how armed, how horsed,
what rank riders, what mighty strong, ac∣tiue
and couragious fellowes, what Gi∣antes,
as if all the rest of England were
but shepe: what wonderous confederates,
what aydes, by land, by sea, from Hierusa∣lem,
<PB REF="26"/>
and no man knoweth whence, I
thinke euen out of Purgatorie, as the po∣pish
Festiual telleth, of the dead felowes in
the churchyard that rose with their spades,
shouelles, &amp; other tooles that they vsed in
their life, to defend him that was impea∣ched
by theeues to say <HI>De profundis</HI> for
their soules. And all this was no more
but to discourage the Queenes true sub∣iectes
and soldiers, and to rayse vp in dout∣full
men inclined to papistrie, a daring to
ioyne themselues to such a supposed strong
side and faction. And yet these be not ta∣ken
for seditious, as they are: the reason
is because they are not yet hanged as they
ought.</P>
<P>An other knot of such good companie
be common rumorspreders,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Spreders of rumors.</NOTE> of whom the
publike fame is that there be or haue bene
certaine notable and noted walkers in
Paules and such places of resort,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Good chirch will it neuer be.</NOTE> so com∣mon
that the very vsuall places of their
being there, are ordinarily knowen by the
names of Papists corner, and liers bench,
sauing that I heare say now of late many
of them flocke more into the middle isle,
which is supposed to be done partly for bet∣ter
harkening, and partly for more com∣modious
publishing. The suspition,
<PB REF="26"/>
grudge &amp; talke goeth among the Quenes
good subiectes, how such fellowes be the
coyners of newes: In the beginning of the
rebellion, how lustie they were, how their
countenances, their fléering, their flinging
paces, their whisperinges shewed their
hartes: how they had newes of euerie en∣crease,
of euery going forward, and of eue∣rie
auantageable doing of the Rebelles:
how they haue newes out of Fraunce and
Flaunders with the soonest, God knoweth
what they send thether, and with what re∣ciprocation
they requite suche newes a∣gaine:
how they had newes of the late hor¦rible
murder ere it were done, as if they
had ben accessaries before the fact:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Clubbe. Basto.</NOTE> how
they write letters at home directed to them
selues: how with these prety letters, while
they be fresh bléeding, that is, so scarcely
drie that the ink blotteth, with their great
countenaunces, with their taking vpon
them wonderous intelligence and great
insightes in secretes of Princes, as if they
were Kinges cousines, and with their of∣fringes
of wagers, and such other bragge∣ries,
they deface (as men say) all that can
be brought or reported neuer so truly of
<PB REF="27"/>
any good successe to the Queene or her
frendes.</P>
<P>And other sort there is,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ouer∣thwart Papistes.</NOTE> like kestrelles or
troutes, they euer flye agaynst the wynde,
or swimme agaynst the streame, in quéene
Maryes time great Gospellers, now great
Papistes,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>op. &amp;c.</NOTE> men that would euer séeme wy∣ser
than the present world, and wold faine
be noted to sée some singular thing, when
for the most part themselues are the most
vayne and singular fooles that liue. No
gouernement pleaseth them, &amp; as they be
content with no world, so are they mete
to liue in none. But let them beware the
sinne against the holy ghost, it is a perilous
thing. God graunt them to see the horror
of it, so farre as it may auayle to their
tymely repentance, before that mere apo∣stasie
bring them into it.</P>
<P>There is feared to be an other suttle
sort,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistes counterfai∣ting Gos∣pellers.</NOTE> that are in déede of no religion, and
yet at sundry tymes and places, to some se∣cretly,
to some openly, to some one where
to some an other, much like the deuided
counselles in Edwarde the fifthes tyme,
would séeme of all religions. These be
most enclined to papistry, eyther because
God will not vouchsafe that such dissem∣blers
<PB REF="27"/>
féele true religion, or that they be
rancke papistes in déede, howsoeuer they a∣buse
men wyth other shew for purposes, or
(which I rathest thinke) for that they are
persuaded that the Popish faction eyther
for multitude, for welth, for foreine alli∣ances,
or for hatred to the Quéene and her
gouernement (which they perhaps would
wishe to be ouerthrowen as all perfect pa∣pistes
would) or for other respectes, is
more commodious for their desire and am∣bition
or for the toyes in their heades, to
rise to vātage in an other world. Such be∣like
haue a good mynde to the aduise that
<HI>Lentulus</HI> wrote to <HI>Catiline, Auxilium
petas ab omnibus, etiam ab infimis,</HI>
séeke helpe of all sortes, yea euen of the
meanest, they make much of al sides. Such
can I compare to notable pyrates, that
wil euer haue within boorde men of all na∣tions
and flagges of all Princes and coun∣tryes.
If he méete with Englishmen stron∣ger
than himselfe, out goeth a flagge of
England and Englishmen aboue hatches,
that he may passe in peace, likewise he doth
with the Frenchman, Scot, Flemming,
Spanyarde, or other, and many tymes he
doth this not to much to passe peaceably
<PB REF="28"/>
himselfe, as that he may the more vnpro∣uidedly
set vpon hym whom he desireth to
spoyle. So happeneth it sometymes that
such a counterfait papist, as my Lorde of
Westmerland and other, finding the plain
shew of papistry not so commodious pro∣fitable
or safe for hym by reason of many
occurrentes that may happe to haue ouer∣taken
hym, till he were ready for his pur∣pose,
hangeth out a flagge of Christianitie,
dealeth with the Bible &amp; other good bookes
as the decayed knight did to whom Bishop
Cranmer vpō a good hope gaue fifty pound
yearely pension to cherishe his toward∣nesse,
he setteth hys men of that nation a∣boue
hatches, he deceaueth good men that
be not <HI>filij huius seculi,</HI> no children of
this world, those he abuseth with protesta∣tions:
and God wote with the same fayth
that teacheth to kéepe no faith, while in the
meane tyme for all this, of their certayne
purpose of pyracie, of their prouision pre∣paration
and furniture, of their former de∣uises,
nothing is chaunged, their other
company though vnder hatches yet still be
ready till the opportunitie of mischiefe
biddes them start vp sodenly like the chil∣dren
of the earth that rose by miracle of the
<PB REF="28"/>
serpentes téeth that Cadmus had sowen.
These be watchers and reach euer to an o∣ther
world, they prouide for succeding of
tymes to come, imagining what day shall
follow the dreadfull night. They woulde
be looked vnto by the present day light, be∣fore
the night come. These to speake plain∣ly
be they (if any such be, as of such mind al
perfect papistes be) that are weary of her
maiesties gouernment, &amp; fal to deuising by
planting a hope of strange titels to vnder∣myne
her maiesties estate, such as hang
vpon the hope of Rome after her decesse,
which hope they know can not haue ef∣fect,
while her highnesse lyueth and reig∣neth,
to whome almighty God graunt to
lyue &amp; reigne while the world lasteth, in
person or in succession of her owne most
royall body. Of this sort was Gardiner
that abused K. Henry with a false flagge of
religion, when he made hys booke of true
obedience. Of this sort was Boner when
he fauned vpon the L. Cromwell, &amp; made
a notable preface to Gardiners booke. Of
this sort was Tonstall, and the rest that
wrote against the Pope, Pole, and all pa∣pistry.
Of this sort are all those Catilines
companions Papistes that beare a glosing
<PB REF="29"/>
shew of obedience and waite for a tyme to
vtter their malice, till they droppe away
into <HI>Manlius</HI> campe, or tary with <HI>Lentu∣lus,
Cethegus, Ceparius,</HI> and the rest to
murder the Consul <HI>Cicero,</HI> or set the Ci∣tie,
I meane the Realme on fire.</P>
<P>An other leud sort eyther depraue what∣soeuer
the Quéenes Maiestie and her most
honorable Counsell doth for the safegarde
and commoditie of the realme,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the Q. good do∣inges.</NOTE> or of things
which they can not deface, they transferre
the praise to other, being desirous as it
were by false flattery to créepe into ambi∣tions
bosome, to raise vp a faction against
her highnesse: as if her Maiestie do any
popular or beneficiall act to the com∣monaltie,
by and by they imagine some
one or other whom they would make an
Absolon whether he will or no, to embe∣sell
the peoples loue, seyng full well but
not caring at all how they burden with
great suspicious those whom they lode
with false praises &amp; perhaps draw into vn∣iust
harmes those whom they claw with
vntrue flatterie. Howbeit I trust all men
of credit and greatnesse, haue taken héede
and will beware that wrongfull praises
and imputations raise not their mynde,
<PB REF="29"/>
to a wrong way of climing, for surely
such popularities and hanginges by the
vayne ayre, are not auancementes but
precipitations. But such is the corne pou∣der
of treason wherewith these popish ru∣mor
spreaders hartes be double charged,
that it must nedes breake forth, and com∣monly
to his destruction or great danger
of singeing that ministreth the fire.</P>
<P>An other sort exercise their rayling
tonges,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Railers vp on the cler∣gie.</NOTE> which by great vse at tables and o∣ther
places, they haue made very slippery,
voluble, &amp; flowing, in vntrue defacing the
clergie of the realme, their liues, examples
mariages, &amp; doctrines: some tell of the li∣beralities
of times past, some of the old me¦ry
world. And all this is but to this end, to
driue into subiects a lothing of present go∣uernment,
&amp; a misliking of the state wher∣in
our good prelates &amp; preachers are main∣teined.
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papists in places of credit.</NOTE> An other spitefull dangerous sort
being placed or rather left in places of good
countenance and credit, either in Colle∣ges,
houses of studie, offices in the grea∣test
houshold, in Courtes, in Cathedrall
churches, worshipfull roomes in the coun∣trey,
and such like, with the very shew of
their countenance, with their liking or
<PB REF="30"/>
disliking, pulling forwarde or pressing
down, open preferring or secret pinching,
so handle the matter that many times it
is more safe, or at least more commodious
and auantageable to be taken for a Pa∣pist,
than for a Christian. For well you
wot how men will smell men of their
owne faction. And sometyme by these
meanes, vnconstant Gospellers for ne∣cessitie
or profites sake, become yelders,
and dissemblers, till at length by Gods
grace forsaking them, and by his iust
plage ordinarilye lighting vpon yelders
and halters, they slide by degrées from
hypocrites to playne apostataes, which
are in déede the most desperate kinde of
Papistes. And if this be not redressed,
in vaine the Preacher preacheth, in vaine
the Prince and Counsell setteth forth true
doctrine.<NOTE PLACE="marg">A gentle prouerbe. Let <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> haue their wordes.</NOTE> For this they can say: when the
Preacher hath sayd, he hath done, but con∣tinuall
execution carieth away the power,
credite, and people. Trow ye these be good
meaning men to her Maiestie, that so per∣secute
&amp; vndermine the religion, whereof
her Maiestie is vnder God, and by Gods
prouision, the great base and meane of
stay in this Realme?</P>
<P><PB REF="30"/>
But aboue all other dothe it not plain∣ly
appeare what hartes papistes beare to
her maiestie, when papistes them selues
and notorious open traitors and rebelles
made their plaine accompt, that to rebel a∣gainst
the Quene, to practise the alterati∣on
of her gouernement, the ouerthrow of
her estate, the displacing of her counsell,
the foysting in of a farre worse in her stead
whosoeuer it be, and the destruction of her
persone, is the very naturall humor, affec∣tion
and desire of papistes? Consider the
rebellious Earles, loke vpon their compa∣nie
and assistantes, viewe them wel, note
their ensignes of woundes and crosses, the
inscriptions about them, <HI>In hoc signo
vinces,</HI> in this signe thou shalt ouer come,
abusing the wordes of Constantine to en∣coragement
of their false hipocrisie. Note
their procedinges, their tearing and bur∣ning
the booke of God, their breaking the
Communion table, their prophaning of
Churches with vile Idolatrie, their erec∣ting
of abhominable Masse, their chaplens
leud and seditious sermons, and chefely
rede their first proclamation. Find you not
there, in their proclamation, where their
trust was reposed? forsothe in men of that
<PB REF="31"/>
sort which they call the old and Catholike
religion, to whome their proclamation
was directed. Finde you not there in their
proclamation, the summe of their com∣plaint▪
the cause and color of their rebelli∣on?
forsothe that euell disposed persones a∣bout
the Quéene haue ouercome the old
and catholike religion within the realme.
Finde you not there, in their proclamati∣on,
the declaration of their intent &amp; pur∣pose?
forsothe to restore old customes and
liberties to the Churche of England. If
these be true pretenses, then is papistrye
being the ground thereof, plainely, flatly,
and truely treason. If they be not true, but
false and vaine colors, abused by these re∣bels
to deceiue and drawe moe subiectes
to take their partes, then sée what folow∣eth,
then must it nedes consequently be e∣uident
that they them selues yet supposed
&amp; knew papistrie to be the very likely and
apt color and meane to allure men to re∣bellion
and treason against the Quéene,
as the very kindely baite,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Treason the natural humor of Papistrie.</NOTE> and as their na∣turall
affection daily gaping for such op∣portunitie,
howsoeuer at this time incon∣uenience
of season, vnripenesse of matter,
vntowardnesse of aide, vnredinesse of pro∣uision,
unfitnesse of guides, preuenting of
<PB REF="31"/>
counsels, stay of their heds &amp; colors, with
other good meanes of gods merciful proui∣dence,
repressed their vnhappy courages,
which yet daily l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke for new time &amp; cir∣cumstances
of lesse encombrance. But in
the meane time as God gathereth his glo∣ry
out of al things, yea euen out of sinnes,
so let vs out of this great euell yet gather
some good, a good example and a good lesson
to learne to know that papistrie is treason
and he that is infected with treason is a
traitor, and so to prouide agaynst them
thereafter.</P>
<P>Whense come I pray you the prophe∣sies
commonly talked of in the beginning
of her most gratious and blessed reigne,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Traito∣rous pro∣phecies.</NOTE>
how many yeares and how many months
her maiesty should continue? Whense
came the leude coniurers conference with
the deuill, how long the Quéenes high∣nesses
gouernement and this religion
should endure? Commeth not this geare
from traytorous affections of those well
disposed persons? Commeth it not from
the same fountayne of treason, from
whense did flow the supplications which
the late monster Gardiner penned and
preferred in Quéene Maries time, for
restitution to the heyres of the northen re∣belles
<PB REF="32"/>
that rose in her most noble fathers
daies, yea and adding the consideration of
theyr restitution to be, because they were
in armour agaynst the king her father for
defense of religion (meaning Papistrie)
and for reuenge of iniuries and dishoners
(as they sayd) done to her mother? Com∣meth
it not from the same affections that
haue raysed the great and lamentable tu∣multes
in the realme? And trow you the
same affection still lodgeth not with the
same opinion? I am halfe afrayd, that out
of this fountaine should also spring a few
blinde demie prophecies enterlaced in
prognostications,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prognosti∣cations.</NOTE> as Nestradamus and o∣thers
pretie bywordes and this that lately
hath written: <HI>Alas the Moone shall be
called in the house of enemies and pri∣son,
wherby is like to happen to vs spe∣cially
to the common people much ad∣uersitie.
&amp;c.</HI> and some other such toyes
to fill the peoples heads with buzzes. But
let the best of such be construed. Yet I
would for frendshippe and learninges
sake tell those authors, if I were ac∣quainted
with them, that such vanities
might be spared, and onely so much out of
that art would be set out to the people as
is commodious and fitte for them to sée,
<PB REF="32"/>
and lawful &amp; standing with good discretion
for the writers to publish. Such a writer
might happe to be a man so holden suspec∣ted
of Papistrie as he mought so encrease
the misdemyng agaynst his owne person
shrewdly. I speake nothing of the prog∣nosticating
toy of a mariage sent vp to be
printed. But let vs sée moe examples.</P>
<P>Remember I pray you Gardiners ser∣mon
at Paules crosse in Quéene Maries
time vpon this text <HI>Hora est iam nos è
somno surgere,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gardiners traitorous sermon.</NOTE> It is now time for vs
to rise out of sléepe. There he shewed
how God dispenseth eche thing and eche
successe in conuenience of times, he decla∣red
what wayes had bene attempted for
restitution of the Popes primacie in Eng∣land,
wherein he diuers wayes falsely
defamed King Henrie with intentes of
submission, such was the byshops impu∣dence.
He named the rebellions in the
North in King Henries tyme, and in the
West in King Edwardes time, which he
clothed with cleanly names, as enterpri∣ses
and assemblies, as our late rebells doo
in both their first and second proclamati∣ons.
But sayth he, the houre was not yet
come. He by way of obiection wondered
how the people could without rebelling
<PB REF="33"/>
beare such iniuries oppressions and rob∣beries
which they susteined as he sayd in
the fall of money and otherwise in King
Edwardes reigne.<NOTE PLACE="marg">He did not foresee the fall of Rose pens to no∣thing.</NOTE> He answered him
selfe, that the houre was not yet come.
But now (sayth he) the houre is come,
now is the time for vs to wake from slepe,
as who should say.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Accipe nunc <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, et cri∣mine ab v∣no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ce omnes.</NOTE> Long haue we slept,
or long haue we winked, long haue we
bene holden in awe, glad to dissemble our
treasons and to semble good subiects, long
haue we borne our soueraigne Lord a
faire face, as if we acknowledged his due
authoritie and detested the enimie to him
and to all Kinges the Pope, long haue we
cloked and hidden our zeale, wayting for
a good houre. Now the dreadfull King
Henrie is dead, the hopefull King Ed∣ward
is taken away, the Christian nobili∣tie
entangled in snares of law specially
if it may be partially and violently vsed,
the prince and tyme fauoreth our side, a
mightie foren match is made for the van∣tage
of our part, now the sonne of our vic∣torie,
and the day of our triumph shineth
vpon vs, now is it tyme for vs to wake
from sléepe. Though the time once were,
specially in the L. Cromwelles dayes,
when we in shew abhord the name of
<PB REF="33"/>
Papistes, and would commonly say we
had as leue be called traitor as Papist, and
bring actions of the case for our purgati∣on,
yet now is the time that we glorie
in these titles, either of Papist in respect
of these tymes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Filii huius mundi.</NOTE> or of traytor in respect of
those tymes. Let vs not now lese our oc∣casion,
for we shall neuer haue the like a∣gayne,
specially for that so much of the no∣bilitie
snared with treason are yelded to
our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Note this geare well, for
Papistes did neuer beare her maiestie
greater countenaunce of loyaltie, neuer
serued her with greater shew of faythful∣nesse,
neuer protested more truth and good
meaning, than those did to King Henrie
the eight and to King Edward, which af∣terward
yet openly shewed what secret
disloyaltie vnfaythfulnesse and vntruth
had so long lurked in their bosomes.
Geue once the like opportunities, and be
bold that you shall haue the like speches,
for they haue still the like hartes and like
expectations. They comfort them selues
with this, that the remembrance of these
thinges will one day be pleasant vnto
them, and in the meane tyme (as Cicero
sayth) <HI>oculis designant ad caedem vnum∣quem{que}
nostrum,</HI> they note euery one of
<PB REF="34"/>
vs with theyr eyes and register vs to be
destroyed. Let vs therefore take the con∣trarie
course to them. Where they looke
for an other tyme, let vs doo our endeuour
to mainteine this tyme, where they reach
with expectation to altering of gouerne∣ment,
let vs bend all our force, policie and
meanes of seruice to the defense of thys e∣state.
Where they pray for change, special∣ly
of Quéenes, let vs pray for continuance
of her highnesses reigne. Where they
hyde rebellious stomakes, let vs shew true
and faythfull hartes. Where they desire
that her maiestie and her Counsel may be
deceiued with flattering and erronious
pretense of policie, pacification, and colour
of clemencie, that vnder that shadow they
may lurke and be norished as serpent in
bosome, let vs praie to God to geue iudge∣ment
to discerne them, to search the bot∣tome
of the late treasons, that they may
be shaken out and vsed as dangerous vi∣pers.
Where their trust is in their Pope
and Popishe treasons and conspiracies,
let our confidence be in God and his pro∣uidence,
not shrinking from the same
with our best courage and prudence.
Where they will not sticke to vse all sut∣tle
vndermyninges, and will not lose the
<PB REF="34"/>
vantage of times, that they may one day
triumph in cruel violence, let vs pray that
on this part be vsed all good policies, that
Gods offred meanes &amp; good opportunites
be not refused or ouerslipped, that God
rent not the kingdome from his anoynted
for sparing his enemies, but that it may
long flourishe in the handes of his most
noble and vertuous handmayde our most
excellent &amp; gratious Soueraigne Ladie.
Thus is it euident by reasons and exam∣ples,
what hartes Papistes beare to her
maiestie.</P>
<P>The third conclusion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">English Papistes traitors to England.</NOTE> that such Eng∣lish
Papistes are traytors to the realme
of England &amp;c. hath receaued two proues
already, the one in the generall treasons
of all Papistes to all realmes, wherein
England and English Papistes are in∣cluded,
the other in their traitorous
mindes to the Quéenes maiesties person
and dignitie, which is the hyest treason
that can be to the realme of England. Yet
are there some other particular doinges
more specially to enforce it, namely the
experience that hath bene of theyr casting
away the care of their countrie, no all o∣ther
naturall affections, to the end with all
immanitie &amp; outragious vnnaturall cruel∣tie
<PB REF="35"/>
to torment Englishe Christians and to
subiect the realme to foren power for their
false religions sake. I am sure there are
enow and to many that can remember
both that they haue red in credible histo∣ries,
and séene in lamentable experience,
how the Papistes haue shewed them
selues so addicted to their supersticion, and
so captiued to an vndue reuerence of their
tyrānous Pope, that they haue for it re∣iected
the care of country and of those to
whome naturall dutie bound them.</P>
<P>It is certayne that that Englishe man
which can be contented for Papistrie to
rayse or fauor rebellion in our countrey:
to ioyne in conspiracie with strangers, to
helpe to inuade and spoyle our countrey:
to conuey the crowne of our countrey to
a forener: to agrée with them in faction
that offer our countrey to prey spoyle and
conquest: to colour foren subiections of
our countrey with false titles of wrested
law, to submit his fayth to that potentate
that hath accursed and geuen our coun∣trey,
theyr soules to the diuell their bodyes
landes and possessions to them that can
catch them: to beleue or fauor them that
spred all vile dishoners agaynst our coun∣trey:
to take his part as the most holy one,
<PB REF="35"/>
that claymeth to him selfe from our natu∣rall
prince the obeysance of one great part
of her subiectes, yea &amp; of all her subiectes
in a great part of theyr affaires: to assent
that a foren vsurper shall by deceaueable
shewes of false religion haue ordinarie
meanes by colors of sutes, resortes, an∣nates,
frutes, pensions, inuestitures, and
other infinite craftes to robbe our coun∣trey
of treasure: to like wel of his doinges
and to hold that he doth no more than he
lawfully may doo, which beyng an alien
a foren byshop shall take vpon him to ex∣tend
hys curse to the prince of our coun∣trey
and all the people thereof, and that he
hath power to discharge the subiectes of
the realme from their fayth and alle∣geance,
and hath authoritie to binde theyr
obedience to whome he will, and is able
to geue heauen to rebelles that shall
venture theyr liues in wasting and de∣stroying
our countrey: he I say that can
yelde hys consent to these doinges &amp; thin∣kinges,
must néedes be a traitor to hys
countrey. And such a one is euery such
English Papist as I haue described, and
can be none other if he hold the Pope for
a true teacher and haue good opinion of
of the Popes doctrine and examples. And
<PB REF="36"/>
to defend that we ought to yelde our
saythes or submission to the Pope, is in
generalitie to affirme all these mischiefes
and treasons. And such as be of that
minde, as all such Papistes bée, can not
in true iudgement be seuered from trai∣torous
watchers to put the same in execu∣tion
when so euer they may haue times
and meanes to beare them harmelesse.</P>
<P>Let be called to minde the treasons of
the clergie agaynst Henrie the second,
and specially the vile practises of the two
traitorous byshops of Lincolne and Here∣sord
agaynst Edward the second. But
principally how as I haue aforesayd the
Dolphin of Fraunce by color of title ge∣uen
him from the Pope for King Iohns
disobedience to that apostaticall seate, in∣uaded
and long possessed a great part of
England: how the deceaued barons of
England, both at that time specially, &amp; at
some other times seuerally, at the Popes
will and vpon pronouncing of his curse
against the king, forsooke their allegeance,
looke part with the frenchmen, spoyled
their owne countrey, and like most vnna∣turall
children, at an adulterous stop fa∣thers
bidding did thrust theyr swordes in∣to
their mothers bellie. Remember Cardi∣nall
<PB REF="36"/>
Poles message to the Emperor: the
rebellions raysed in that time, and since:
the late practises in Queene Maries
dayes, to bring the realme in thraldome
to the most insolent and intolerable na∣tion,
and to transfer the inheritance of
the crowne, with not onely disheriting
but also destroying the true and naturall
heire: their great sorrow, that it was not
performed: the great trust that our Pa∣pistes
in all their countenances and spe∣ches
shewed them selues to haue of the
good successe of Henrie the french king,
whome God tooke away before his accom∣plishment
of thretened enterprises against
this realme. Let not be forgotten their
glorienges in their champion of Guise.
It is yet fresh and raw in remembrance,
how openly they vttered their as it were
applaudinges, gratulations, and cherefull
significations of fauor to that side, euen
then when, as it is well knowen, the
same familie of Guise sought, vnder co∣lor
of his kinswomans title, and by that
foren title which was made the title and
fundation of this last rebellion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Romish religion.</NOTE> to inuade
this land, to ouerthrow the Quéenes ma∣iesties
estate, and to transport the crowne
of our countrey to strangers.</P>
<P><PB REF="37"/>
Let it be considered what good practi∣ses
these late Rebels haue had with stran∣gers
to the hazard of their countrie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rebelles confedered with stran∣gers.</NOTE> euen
so far forth as they feared not in their pro∣clamations,
with a litle colorable forme of
pennyng, to brag and put their confede∣rates
in hope of strangers coming to in∣uade
and destroy the realme, which by a
prety, gentle, false terme they call refor∣ming
the realme. Let it be well weyed
what they meane to the realme, that vn∣der
colour of succeding do so far vnder∣mine
the head of our country, that by ray∣sing
some to a hope of the next succeding,
they conuey the countenance, fauour and
supportation of a great corrupt nomber
of suche as may frame them selues any
hope of gaine that way, to other persones
that by such kindled ambition may be the
more hastely enboldned. Such mad hopes
made lewd bokes to be published in print
to entitle strangers to our crowne, and to
geue aduise to cherishe the amitie of
Fraunce to this ende that the rebellious
nation of England (as they terme vs)
may by that meanes be tamed,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prouing of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</NOTE> if we wyll
not contentedly yeld to such subiection. It
is not nothing that the same bookes were
ambiciously published in Paris, and set vp
<PB REF="37"/>
vpon euery post and piller, and by men of
great place and charge most earnestly de∣fended,
when on our Quéenes Maiesties
behalfe they were required to be suppres∣sed.
I speake not yet of the worst bookes,
well knowen to the best persons.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Plures ad∣orant so∣lem orien∣tem quam occiden∣tem.</NOTE> This
to doo is to shew vs a Sunne rysing to
whose worship they would faine draw vs
from our Sunne declinyng, as they sup∣pose.
No, no, our Quéene is our true
Sunne: and what soeuer shinyng thyng
they wold set vp in her tyme, it is no right
Sunne,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mutantem regna Co∣meten.</NOTE> but an vnlucky Comete. And it is
not yet noone, I trust, with our Sunne:
or if it be, I hope yet God will lengthen
the day to our Sunne for his honors sake,
as he dyd to Iosua, and the rather shall all
good subiectes haue cause so to hope it, if
the residue of the day may be so spent as
Iosua spent it, and for which purpose God
dyd prolong it, to rid the world of Gods
enemies. Let it be suspected what hopes
of preuention, anticipation &amp; most dread∣full
mischief, which I feare and abhorre
to name, the encouragement of such suc∣cedyng,
which is the worke of Papistes,
may minister where the onely person of
our most deare and precious soueraigne
Ladie standeth without any moe meane
<PB REF="38"/>
stayes of her most honorable and ioyfull
issue betwene them and their desired ef∣fect
the vtter vndoing of vs all, and special∣ly
where the power of reuenge may by
possibilitie fall into their handes for whose
sake it should be attempted. It is no small
mischiefe, danger, and apallyng of fayth
and courage, when our prince must be de∣fended
agaynst those that by possibilitie
may aspire to hope to haue colour to be
our Princes them selues and to wreke it
vpon good subiectes that serue our Quéene
truely. What kindnesse or naturalnesse
will doo, hath béen abundantly shewed al∣ready
diuerse wayes. And in the late
murderous mischief, a most foule presi∣dent,
but a most perfect lesson, this one
thyng is much to be noted, that it was
here by rumor reported as done, before it
were done there, which argueth that the
conspiracie extended hither, and how farre
further (or rather nerer) is good to be quick∣ly
and earnestly searched, and by the same
example to be remembred, what harme
the losse of vsyng occasion hath bredde,
when it might haue so béen preuented,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Nouissi∣mus error peior pri∣ore.</NOTE>
that neither he had bene murdered, nor the
Quéene encombred. I dispute no titles. I
<PB REF="38"/>
haue no reache beyond our Quéene. I can
sée nothyng beyond our Quéene but a
<HI>Chaos</HI> of miserie, therfore I am lothe to
looke so farr. My onely care is, as my pray∣er
is, &amp; all good subiectes ought to be, for our
Q. Maiesties preseruation. What other
title so euer be pretended, be it good or bad,
if it shall once threaten danger to the Q.
Maiestie whose title and gouernance we
know to be true and haue felt to be good, I
wish it destroyed and put out of hope, least
it hope to sone, to fast, to much, to hye, and
ioyne with to many.</P>
<P>Record I pray you the anathemaes of
the conspiracie of Trent, theyr cruell and
dangerous practises agaynst this realme,
and agaynst all other of Christian profes∣sion,
the Popes sentences agaynst our
Quéene and Countrey, and all this well
liked of, and holden for holy by our owne
vnhappy Papistes. Remember the deui∣ses
to put the same sentences and conspi∣racies
in execution, in Fraunce and Flan∣ders
all at one tyme.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Haud rec∣te tempo∣ribus diui∣sa sunt tibi ista, Daue.</NOTE> Consider the con∣currence
and euennesse of tyme of this re∣bellious
enterprise in England, and that
late murderous and haynous attempt in
Scotlande. But to pyke a litle more
<PB REF="39"/>
good out of the late ill déede of horrible
murder. What say the Quéenes good
subiectes to be the cause, why after our
rebelles vanquished, the Regent was
slayne, that should haue bene done before
to serue our rebelles and their conspira∣ters
turne. For sooth their traitors there
and some conspiraters here Englishe or
Scottish saw full well the sincere frend∣ship
of the Regent to the Quéene, that not∣withstandyng
all the practises from hense
to the contrarie, he mynded to deliuer our
rebelles, whereby the counselles and com∣plices
both here and there must haue bene
disclosed, they politikely prouided, by assent
to murder that noble gentleman betimes,
whose bloud added to other bloudes so crye
to God, as it is perilous to draw to much
into societie and partnershyp of those a∣gaynst
whom such bloud so crieth. This
is the common feare of good subiectes: and
to feare to much rather then to little, may
be more folly, but it is lesse fault. It may
haue lesse cause, but it hath more truth ho∣nestie
and fayth. Wey well if these be
the meanes that my lordes of Northum∣berland
and Westmerland, and their com∣pany
haue sought to bryng the vnityng of
<PB REF="39"/>
realmes and crownes, and to worke the
effect of theyr proclamations both for state
and religion, which doyng such men brag
to be so beneficiall, &amp; sith the same and the
titles thereof reach not so farre as by any
these meanes to make such vnityng in the
person of our most noble Quene, nor such
attemptes for religion and other effectes
can be atcheued with her likyng: then
what successe is to be looked for of theyr de∣uises
and what marke is it to be feared
they shoote at? They and such other Pa∣pistes
and ambitious practisers may per∣haps
iustly and truly say, protest &amp; sweare
that they entended not the effect of such
purposes while her Maiestie liueth, for it
may be that they meane peraduenture
that her hyghnesse should not lyue so long.
God preserue her to outlyue all them that
haue lyued to long. This example is terri∣ble,
and would be profitably vsed.</P>
<P>You can not forget how the Pope
claimeth,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Popish clergie no good sub∣iectes.</NOTE> and our Papistes do graunt him
the superioritie ouer Ecclesiasticall per∣sons.
Theyr obedience is thereby with∣drawen
from theyr Prince, and from the
seruice of theyr Countrey, &amp; they exemp∣ted
from theyr duties to the Prince and
<PB REF="40"/>
realme. Like is the referryng of all ecclesi∣asticall
causes to the Pope as to the su∣preme
iudge and ruler. Great wrong ther∣by
is done to the Realme, great with∣drawyng
of the bodyes of subiectes from
presence to serue and defende the Realme,
and great transportation of the treasure:
the foule examples whereof in pilfring and
scrapyng within the Realme, to serue the
vnsatiable couetise of Rome, appeareth by
the many lamentable complaints in theyr
owne histories, with which enormities
and oppressions as most burdenous and
perilous to the Realme, our Parlamentes
and specially Conuocations, haue before
tyme found them selues meruelously agre∣ued.
And yet this heuie &amp; ouerchargeable
yoke must be reduced agayne by our Pa∣pistes,
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Harding.</NOTE> yea and our new angeles of Lo∣uaine,
with whom the euil sprites at home
do accord, can terme these intollerable ex∣actions,
but a small pitance or trifle to
acknowledge our good will to our mother
church, and can call the reasonable misly∣king
or iust gronyng thereat as a niggard∣ly
grudgyng. Liberall men, I assure you,
and no maruell, for they be of hys faction,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Wolsey.</NOTE>
that sometyme bragged that the aduaun∣cyng
<PB REF="40"/>
of hym selfe to the throne of Rome,
should cost hym all England. So small
a thyng these Papistes accompt it to ven∣ture
all England at a cast. And good rea∣son
haue they, for they venture it at the
perill of other mens losses, for whosoeuer
reigne here by their treason, they are lyke
to kéepe or increase theyr wealthes and
dignities.</P>
<P>Let it be thought vpon how much these
fellowes esteme the common knot of fide∣litie
to the Prince, whereby the peace of
the land is holden together, and eche mans
due propertie is preserued, which beleue
that the same faith is dissoluble at the will
of a foreine priest.</P>
<P>Let also this descendyng gradation be
considered concernyng Papistes and their
hope,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Traitours not true to theyr owne fellowes.</NOTE> how true they will be to their Coun∣trey,
that are not true to God: how true
they will be to their good Prince, that are
not true to their Countrey: how true they
will be to any subiect, that are not true to
their Prince: and thereby let theyr confe∣drates
beware that they be not made bot∣tels,
first filled &amp; then emptied, &amp; afterward
hanged vp by the walles. Let the Duke
of Buckingham in king Richardes tyme,
<PB REF="41"/>
and infinite other beate this wisdome in∣to
theyr head, to know how ill a tyrant or
one that atteyneth a crowne by mischiefe
and wrong, can beare to liue detbounden
to those that aduaunced hym, or subiect to
their reproche, &amp; being once fleshed in mis∣chiefes
by theyr helpe how litle conscience
he maketh to procede further and specially
vpon them whom he knoweth in hys con∣science
in ioynyng with hym to haue well
deserued it. Let them well digest the
vicont of Melunes admonition on hys
death bed to the English barons in the be∣ginning
of the reigne of king Iohns heire.
And let them neuer say that they the late
rebels and theyr complices had no such in∣tētion
to ouerthrow her Maiesties estate,
sith the thinges expressed in their first pro∣clamation
can not be done while her Ma∣iesties
estate continueth, who hath so ho∣norably
oft protested to preferre Gods
truth aboue her crowne and lyfe, which
God long preserue.</P>
<P>Let all Englishmen, thinke of this and
beleue it as experience hath taught it, that
where Monkes and religious persons
changed their surnames and had many o∣ther
solemne ceremonies at their professi∣ons,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Monckes forswore theyr coun∣trey and na∣turall dutie.</NOTE>
which they sayd dyd signifie their ver∣tuous
<PB REF="41"/>
renouncing of worldly and carnall
fansies,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Therefore many Bi∣shops wold not be con∣secrate till they were made Monkes.</NOTE> the same pretense of signifiyng
was vtterly false, like the pretense of re∣fusing
the othe to the Quéene: and the very
true meaning such as is proued by the con∣sequence
of their déedes, was no other but
that euery perfect Papist doth take vpon
him a zeale, for defense of their God the
Pope and his heresie to throwe away all
due and naturall beneuolence and fayth to
Prince, Countrey, parentes, frendes, and
all those iust and due respectes, whereunto
God by the law of nature hath bounde
them in this world: and this must so be,
for the other true vowe of renouncing, was
made before in Baptisme, and remayned
still in force.</P>
<P>To all these inconueniences and trai∣torous
absurdities they must nedes be sub∣iect
which hold that the Church of Rome
is the true Catholike Church of Christ,
and that the Catholike Church of Christ
can not erre.</P>
<P>The horror of their cruelties to the peo∣ple
of their country,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Cruelties of Pa∣pistes.</NOTE> of whom their country
consisteth, whose liues they haue regar∣ded
no more then shéepe, yea no more then
fleaes, and that with such delite of torment
<PB REF="42"/>
as if they still cryed out as the heathen ty∣rant
did <HI>fac vt sentiat se mori,</HI> let him
fele that he is dying, &amp; as the Pope himself
did that caused some of his Cardinales to
be tormented in such maner by speciall cō∣mandement,
that he being in a garden vn∣derneth
saying hys deuotions, might heare
them cry: all this I referre to the large,
faithfull and learned explication of that
good diligent and vertuous man Master
Foxe in his Booke of Actes and Monu∣mentes
of the Church, where as in a glasse
doth euidently appeare what nature or
any kinde, respect to kinne, reuerence, pi∣tie,
loue, or countrey, reigned or rather re∣mayned
in the furious hartes of Papistes,
how smothly soeuer the hypocrites wyth
Crocodiles teares or wild Irish laughter,
do faine, flatter and abuse those in whose
power they be, till they haue their time of
auantage. Though the remembrance of
these thinges be bitter, yet is it holsome.
And therefore let it not out of their hartes
that haue harty care, and specially charge
of their countrey.</P>
<P>That clemencie and gentlenesse can
not reclaime them from traitorous minds
while they continue in Papistrie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Clemencie can not winne a Papist▪</NOTE> is as
<PB REF="42"/>
plaine and as true a forme of speach, as if
a man sholde say they must nedes be tray∣tors,
so long as they be full of treason, for
treason and Papistrie are vnseparable
while they be kept vnder, euen as crueltie
and Papistrie are vnseperable when they
are gotten aboue. Yet for some more ample
opening of the truth of this conclusion, let
vs somewhat more wey their qualities
with reasonable consideration and confe∣rence
of their doinges.</P>
<P>If clemencie and benefites should be
hable to reclaime them, it must be for some
regard that they must haue of the dutie of
thankefulnesse, for benefites receaued of
those persons from whose sincerely louing
minde toward them, and not from any
foreine enforcing cause, they accompt the
benefites to procede. Wherein is to be
searched, how much they are likely to e∣steme
such dutie, by their weying other &amp;
nere duties, and agayne how well they ac∣knowledge
from whence this clemencie
and benefites haue proceded. For if the
hiest and greatest duties of kindnesse moue
them not, then is small accompt to be
made of their thankfulnesse for temporall
commodities, or at the least for bare suffe∣ring
<PB REF="43"/>
them to liue vnpunished. And againe
if the same impunitie and other beneficiall
doinges, be thought to come enforced from
other, or craftily wonne by their owne po∣licie,
or so to come from your selfe as you
could not chose, then is your thanke fo far
lost as there is no hope that euer any such
meane can reclaime a Papist.</P>
<P>Surely he that regardeth not the hyest
dutie, will neuer regarde the meanest.
The dutie of the loue or feare of God can
not hold a Papist from blasphemie against
God. The dutie of faith &amp; allegeance to his
Prince can not kéepe a Papist from trea∣son
to his Prince. The dutie of deare loue
to his natural countrey can not withdraw
a Papist from assenting to, yea and procu∣ring
the spoyle, destruction, bondage, and
alienation of his countrey, as I haue al∣redy
proued. The dutie of kinde and na∣turall
pitie can not stay a Papist from
murdering the feble sexe, nor the silly ten∣der
infancie, nor reuerend eldest age. The
dutie of familiaritie in youth, of frendship
in grauer yeares, of continuall societie du∣ring
all the life passed, with heapes of
mutuall commodities, can not pull backe
a Papist from immanitie of sacrificing his
derest frendes. The dutie of honor of Chil∣dren
<PB REF="43"/>
to parentes, or loue of parentes to
children, remoueth not a Papist from vn∣naturall
crueltie. The dutie of entier loue
and felowship betwene man and wife, hol∣deth
no place in the hart of a Papist. No
dutie of kinred, no estimation of learning
&amp; vertue, no good respect that moueth good
men to loue &amp; compassion, once toucheth a
stubburne Papist. Al these duties we haue
sene broken, yea neglected and throwen
away by Papistes. And is there hope that
clemencie can so farre winne them, as to
hold them in truth to the Prince, from
whom they receiue it, if opportunitie
serue to bring them out of her danger, or
her highnesse into their danger, which
God forbid?</P>
<P>Whensoeuer (which God graunt
neuer be) her Maiestie person should
stand in theyr curtesie, it is euident that
then the gate were open to their de∣sires,
to theyr florishing, to theyr con∣quest,
to theyr abilities of reuengyng,
and to their perfect triumphyng. And
will they, trow you, omit all these that
they so earnestly gape for? will they let
passe any occasion that may bryng these?
and all in respect of her gracious clemen∣cie,
and benefites? no no, that will not be.
<PB REF="44"/>
It greueth me to thinke and I abhorre to
write what opportunities they are lyke∣ly
to séeke and vse, hauyng now pressed so
farre as they haue alreadie done with
theyr enterprises, shadowed with such
hopes as theyr proclamation hath vttered.</P>
<P>But admit kyndenesse were in them for
benefites where they impute them. It is
as well knowen as a common prouerb
that, where her Maiestie of her singular
goodnesse of nature (which yet were farre
greater goodnesse, if it be directed to the
onely preseruation of good men, and not
further stretched and abused to the cheri∣shyng
of euill and dangerous men) hath
forborne and restrayned execution of law
agaynst them, which yet are the lawes
made expressely for her Maiesties safetie,
theyr ordinarie saying is, you can haue no
law agaynst vs, God so prouideth for vs
hys chosen anointed, that you can haue no
law, or if you haue, you can not execute it,
god so preserueth theyr side forsoth &amp; so bri∣dleth
her Maiesties power, by hyw own in∣stinct
or by theyr owne meanes of policie.</P>
<P>Sée the examples of theyr thankeful∣nesse.
Did euer those Papists, whose liues
were saued by good Byshop Cranmers
meanes, who were brought vp, who were
defended, who were aduanced, who were
<PB REF="44"/>
shelded from harme &amp; perill by hym, ones
requite hym with one drop of kyndnesse?
And yet they spake hym faire in hys pro∣speritie.
Auayled the great liberalitie of
kyng Henry the viij. to rayse vp any kinde
remembrance in Papistes, that were
great in Quéene Maryes dayes, to stay
them from assentyng to the captiuitie and
danger and sekyng the bloud of hys most
noble daughter our most gracious soue∣raygne
Ladie? And yet duryng kyng Hen∣ryes
reigne, they shewed a seruiceable
face, as if they would haue spent theyr
bloudes, to kepe wrong from hym and
hys, and dyd serue agaynst Papistrie it
selfe, till theyr treason and Papistrie was
rype to be aduaunced. Are not the great
doers of thys last rebellion and conspira∣cie,
those of whom her Maiestie hath most
well and bountifully deserued? And yet
while they were in her presence, they were
as desirous as any that be now about her
to haue her Maiestie thinke of them as of
good and faithful subiectes. Yea when they
were nere the execution of theyr treasons,
beyng suspected and examined therof,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Periuri {que} arte Sino∣nis.</NOTE> de∣nyed
it, and made vehement hye protesta∣tions
with great othes of theyr purpose
to the contrarie, and theyr readynesse to
<PB REF="45"/>
subdue them that should breake the peace,
as in her Maiesties proclamation appea∣reth.
The successe of whoes doynges, so
shortly folowyng, amounteth to as much
as if they had playnly sayd,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Vnum nôris, omnes nôris.</NOTE> what soeuer
viser of faith, whatsoeuer promysse of true
allegeance, what soeuer assurance of
wordes, what soeuer employeng them sel∣ues
agaynst theyr owne partes till perfect
readinesse, what soeuer iudgyng and con∣demnyng
of theyr owne faction beyng not
yet strong enough, Papistes do pretend, it
is to no other end but to insinuate them
selues into fredome from mistrust, and to
draw her Maiesties eyes to looke an other
way, to bryng her into a securitie till the
danger be vnauoidable, as I trust it neuer
shalbe, if good subiectes sticke well toge∣ther
to her hyghnesse, which shalbe so long
as her Maiestie shall as she doeth sticke
well to God &amp; her good subiectes, &amp; not to
suffer them to be dishabled to defend her.</P>
<P>Surely when Papistes are come so far,
that the wyfe can procure the murder of
her husband, the father of hys sonne, the
mother of her child, the frend of hys dea∣rest
frend, and so in all degrées of coniun∣ction,
shall her Maiestie looke to haue cle∣mencie
and liberalitie requited with loy∣altie
<PB REF="45"/>
at theyr hands, that already bost that
they receyue no clemencie or goodnesse of
her, but by theyr owne cunnyng meanes,
or by a superior enforcement?</P>
<P>And truly of this theyr great vnkynd∣nesse,
there is one great reason while Pa∣pistrie
remayneth in them, Earthly
thynges must geue place to heauenlie, and
transitorie to eternall. They esteme the
voyce of the Pope as the voyce of the eter∣nall
God. Whyle her Maiestie actually
reigneth ouer them, they suppose not them
selues to lyue vnder her hyghnesse as sub∣iectes,
but to be holden as captiues, and so
with all theyr fained shewe they beare to
her a seruile reuerence,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistes obedience vntrue.</NOTE> euen altogether
such as the bond Mores haue done to the
Spanyardes, and as Gardiner and hys fel∣lowes
dyd beare to kyng Henry the viij.
and to kyng Edward, and my Lordes of
Northumberland and Westmerland and
theyr companie with these that haue drop∣ped
to them since or shall hereafter shrinke
lykewise from her, do beare to her selfe.
They are ready further at theyr God the
Popes voyce, whensoeuer they may be ha∣ble
to shake of her yoke and gouernement,
with opinion of meritoriousnesse, as the
<PB REF="46"/>
vyle Monke that tempered a tode for hys
naturall kyng, and as doctor Mackerell in
tymes past, and some other both then and
since haue openly vttered. Agayne where
they suppose theyr auncesters and frendes
soules, for lacke of the helpe which the
Quéene kepeth from them, to lye in vn∣speakeable
peynes: where also they sup∣pose
their owne soules to lacke their ghost∣ly
comfortes, them selues to be cut from
Gods church beyng seuered from the pope
the hed thereof: chiefly where they thinke
not onely them selues, but also theyr chil∣dren
and posteritie for euer, to be by the
settyng forth of this Religion which the
Quenes hyghnesse auaunceth, drawen in∣to
a continuall dangerous streame and
vnrecouerable state of damnation. And
where all this whyle they are further per∣suaded
(as they must nedes be, if they think
the Romane church catholike &amp; the Pope
the hed therof, and the catholike church
and the hed thereof to be preserued from
possibilitie of error) that by force of the
Popes sentence and for schismaticall and
vnrepentant swaruyng from hys church,
her Maiestie is not in Gods sight iust
Quene of this realme, with remembring
<PB REF="46"/>
how farre they thinke they may or ought,
when they dare, to shonne her as a person
excommunicate, and to withdraw from
her all ayde, relief, seruice and obe∣dience:
is it, trow you, to be thought that
such benefites as they receiue in clemen∣cie
and otherwise, which yet they impute
to Gods preseruing them for the holynesse
of theyr cause, or to theyr owne policies in
deceiuyng her, are hable to weye downe
those depe and eternall considerations of
miseries which they beleue them selues to
sustayne by her meanes? It is not possible,
beyng so persuaded of her right to the
croune, and of the Popes power ouer her
croune and person, as they be. Whyle they
thinke them selues true Israelites, the
chosen people of God, and the Pope theyr
Moses or rather Christ, what accompt
make they of the prince, whom they serue,
other than as of Pharao? or make they any
more conscience of withdrawyng all du∣ties
from the Prince and theyr whole con∣trey,
than the Israelites dyd of robbyng
the Egyptians, how fayre soeuer they
spake, promysed, or bound them selues
when they borrowed theyr iewelles? Ma∣ny
such examples haue ben seen in her
<PB REF="47"/>
Maiesties most noble progenitors dayes,
but most chiefely and most euidently in
her owne.</P>
<P>Of lyke truth it is that Papistrie being
an heresie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistrie encreaseth by lenitie.</NOTE> or rather a bondle made vp of
an infinite nomber of heresies, must nedes
haue the propertie of heresie, to florish
with indulgence and lenitie. We sée the
lyke example in the sect of Arrians, which
vnder hereticall Emperours excedingly
encreasced, and beyng ones condemned
&amp; restrayned by punishment, hath worne
away to a few. So farre as kyng Henry
the viij. went in reforming religion, which
was to abolish the primacie of Rome out
of this realme (a noble conquest) with cer∣taine
grosse idolatries: dyd not the seueri∣tie
of hys lawes, the awe of hys person,
&amp; the dred of due execution, so hold downe
those partes of Papistrie which he sup∣pressed,
that they durst not ones shew
them selues in hys dayes? and yet in the
same tyme the greuous law of sixe Ar∣ticles
made agaynst Gods truth, and sini∣sterly
procured by Popish clergie, nor yet
the earnest inquirie, nor cruell executyng
of it by Byshops &amp; other, could hold downe
the truth of the Gospell, but that it brake
<PB REF="47"/>
out more and more vpon them. The rea∣son
is, that Papistrie and Christian truth
haue two seuerall endes: truth respecteth
heauen, and Papistrie the world. Wherby
theyr aduentures &amp; enterprises are com∣monly
diuerse: the Papist dare boldly set
vpon any mischief, where he hath hope to
auaunce hys falsehode: The Christian
dare constantly abyde any torment to
geue witnesse of Gods truth. And such
qualitie of Gods truth haue the auncient
fathers described, when one of them cal∣leth
the bloud of Martyrs the water to
water Gods garden, an other sayth that
they encreace with cuttyng downe, and o∣ther
in other maner haue expressed the
same meanyng.</P>
<P>But now being vnder a Christian Prince
in dayes of rest (blessed be almighty God,
and long preserued be her maiestie the in∣strument
of it) as it is not mete that Gods
Church, after Iulian the Apostataes
maner, be persecuted to make it encreace,
but holden downe with good discipline for
maners that it grow not wilde and runne
out into wantonnesse, so is not the Church
of the Deuill to be mainteined and multi∣plied
with indulgence, winking and slack∣nesse
<PB REF="48"/>
of correction, but with good seueritie
to be restreyned, that it grow not to such
ranknesse to choke the true church in dede.
The licentiousnesse of Papistes speach is
great,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Papistes dangerous∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> cheri∣shed.</NOTE> they dare do and say they care not
what, they haue their assemblies and or∣dinary
conferences together, their leude
and seditious bookes, and such courage as
the truer sort of her Maiesties part are o∣uercrowed,
as the good preachers dayly
complayne, and so long I pray God they
complaine not that God heare them, and
be angry that other heard them not. Po∣pish
priestes, who sometime triumphed
that they were so estemed Popish, and by
that meane got those thinges together,
enioy the great ecclesiasticall liuinges
without recantation or penance, yea and
in simoniacall heapes: Cathedrall Chur∣ches
are stuffed with them, as dennes of
theues: they are in offices: the meaner
sort depend vpon them, and partly by ex∣ample,
partly by common desire to crepe
into fauour of their superiors, and partly
also for that the great ones are loth to
haue other about them, are perilously in∣fected:
the very spyes and promoters of
Quéene Maries time, without change of
<PB REF="48"/>
their opinion are cherished &amp; marke men
against an other day. Mercie may haue
her excesse, and clemencie may be great
crueltie, when it ouerfloweth to the good
mans danger.</P>
<P>Yet is not my minde that for mens
bare opinions or mistakinges in contro∣uersies
of religion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">No cruel∣tie for sim∣ple opini∣ons.</NOTE> being otherwise honest
and ciuile men, &amp; where the same extend
not to participation of treason, or to those
Articles that implie a dangerous mea∣ning
to the state, they should be byandby
destroyed, but restrayned from insolence
and licentious spreding of their errors,
and with doctrine &amp; examples be reduced,
but specially that confidence be reposed
in men that be better assured. Such ma∣ner
of crueltie were to imitate Papistes,
rather than to correct Papistes. Meaner
punishmentes than the paines of treason
ar meter. Conuenient discipline, comming
after good teaching, were profitable. But
those of them that in tyme past haue bene
shepebiters,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Old shepe∣biters pe∣rilous to be kept.</NOTE> and hetherto shew no true
repentance, it is likely that they haue the
common qualitie of olde shepebiters, they
will neuer leaue it, and they cannot be
kept without danger of the flocke and
<PB REF="49"/>
state. Of this may Gardiner and Boner
(whom God hath sent from hence, I dare
not say taken from hence) be notable ex∣amples.
Many moe there haue bene and
be: and some of those that be, remaine not
onely in her Maiesties power, but also in
her charge.</P>
<P>The other Conclusions following haue
great difference from these wherof I haue
made some explication. Of these yet no∣thing
so large an explication haue I made
as truth is well and easily able to furnish,
nether can I so well make it as the expe∣dience
of the cause asketh to geue the van∣tage
of eloquence to the goodnesse of the
matter, to helpe to draw it into credit and
effect of well mouing. But being as it is,
rude and true, great conning and finenesse
is the least nedefull, where those for whom
it is most intended are so wise as it is farre
more easie for naked troth to enforme
them, than for any gay speach to leade
them. This is the diuersitie of the articles
declared,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Matters of facte not knowen but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> and of the articles remayning:
those that be past conteyne matters of fact,
doinges, maners, and dispositions of men
abrode, the certainties and circumstan∣ces
whereof cannot be vnderstoode of any
<PB REF="49"/>
the wisest men in the worlde by way of
contemplation, but must be brought vnto
them by relation of true and faithfull sub∣iectes,
by common rumor and speach of
the honest sort, or some such other meane of
intelligence and experience: by reason
wherof I haue ben bolder of things con∣sisting
in doing, and tossed in talke abrode,
to gather luch a certaintie of report of
things, for the better considering of danger
to her Maiestie and the estate, as is in dede
the very common and ordinary burden of
euery honest mans hart to sée them, and
necessarie thynges to be layed before those
that may amend them.</P>
<P>The other conclusions that follow,
wherin I neither haue nor will wade so
farre, are matters of consultation and me∣ditation.
The effect therof, which is the
safe preseruation of the Quéenes royall
Maiestie and the realme, the auoydyng of
dangers that threaten the same, the esta∣blishyng
of assurednesse, boldnesse, courage
and fréedome of her hyghnesses most good
counsellers and subiectes, the taking auan∣tages
of opportunities and occasions, the
wedyng out of deceiuers and vndermy∣ners,
the defense of her Maiesties honor
<PB REF="50"/>
&amp; dignitie, the meanes to answere charge
toward God, &amp; namely in dealyng with
men as they be affectioned to or agaynst
God, this effect I say of those other conclu∣sions
I know doth continually occupie her
Maiestie and her most honorable counsel∣lers
in thinkyng on them and prouidyng
for them: therfore it shall no further occu∣pie
me and other meane subiectes than in
prayer and readynesse to serue as her Ma∣iestie
and her counsell shall sée fit to em∣ploy
vs. I will not therfore in discoursing
of them encomber my selfe and other. It
shall suffice me, and so ought it to content
all other, to know as we do know, what a
wise Prince we haue, what good Counsell
she hath chosen, how well they haue go∣uerned,
what frute we haue had of it, so as
nothyng is left to vs, but to geue thankes,
to beware that our owne sinnes geue not
the occasion of losse and change, to serue
dutifully and to pray deuoutely.</P>
<P>Howsoeuer the nature of Papistes
hath shewed it selfe, that they are most glo∣sing
traitors till they haue theyr aduan∣tage,
and most cruell tormenters when
they haue obteyned it: howsoeuer it be
true that though her Maiestie heape them
<PB REF="50"/>
with infinitie benefites and cherish them
with vnmeasurable and dangerous cle∣mencie,
though they crepe and crouch, and
with theyr promise of fayth which they
thinke bound to kepe no fayth, speake ne∣uer
so faire, and for the tyme dissemble
theyr zele, holdyng them contented with
glorious and false shewes of policie to per∣suade
a certaine traitorous temper and pe∣rilous
neutralitie (if they repent not their
error and change not their Religion) they
hate her, they watch theyr tymes, they
transferre the prayses of her good gouerne∣ment
to those that neuer deserued it, they
be redy to vndermine her estate while she
lyueth, as they did with her brother, and to
defame and deface her beyng dead as they
dyd with her father: howsoeuer they now
hide, or hereafter vtter theyr stomackes: it
is on the other side true that though her
Maiestie should shew to Christians in bo∣dylie
and temporall thynges great hard∣nesse,
yet is it so recompensed and ouer∣weyed
to vs in the fréedome and ioy of our
consciences, that we must and will still
loue her how much more then beyng our
so good, louyng and benefici<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll seueraine?</P>
<P>It is we that depend vpon her, it is
<PB REF="51"/>
we that thinke it shalbe more easy and
better for vs (euen in respect of our world∣ly
life, and benefites, though there were
not a greater prospect beyond) to die at her
fote in her defence than to ouerliue her
Maiestie, the same being expressed by her
enimies. Gospellers be they, whom though
her maiestie can by no meanes make to
cease to loue her, yet by ouermuch cheri∣shing
of Papistes, she may make lesse
strong to defend her. Our case is such as
her Maiestie may be assured of vs,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Onely Christians true to the Queene.</NOTE> that we
stand for her, not only as for our Prince,
our louing soueraigne, our mother, our
countrey, our hauiours &amp; possessions, but
also for the liues, and (that most is) for the
seules of our selues, our wiues, our chil∣dren
&amp; posterity for euer. If any of this part
haue bene seduced by Papistes, as perhaps
there be, error I hope it is and not malice,
And as it is error, so is it mete to be forsa∣ken
as error, I meane not onely forsaken
in pursuing, but also in defending, succo∣ring,
pacifiyng and helping. For let such
make their accompt to finde no truth, de∣fence,
mercy, nor kindnesse in Papistes,
when they get aboue, howsoeuer their
<PB REF="51"/>
present turne be serued. To late shall they
wish for the good Prince, whom their own
follies shall haue lost. Let them remem∣ber
the policies of Charles vsed with
Maurice and other for assurance of religi∣on
against the confederates of Smalcald.
Let them remember the Fremingham
promises for not altering religion. Let
them remember that the very pro∣misers
eyther in dede shall not be ha∣ble,
or will be glad to say they are not
able to kepe promise with them, or if
they would faine kepe promise they may
hap to be sent after their predecessors.
Let them remember the keping of e∣dictes
and word of a king in other places,
by meane of persons somewhat allied.
Let them remember that them selues
shall not dare to chalenge such promises,
no more then the Crane his reward for
pulling the bone out of the wolues throte.
Let them remember they shall haue to do
with such as thinke not themselues bound
to kepe faith with them nor any of our side,
&amp; can haue a dispensation at their pleasure.
It is we therefore that pray God to geue
her Maiestie iudgement and all timely
<PB REF="52"/>
meanes of intelligence, to discerne her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nemies,
and courage to vse such opportu∣nities
of times as God throweth vpon her.</P>
<P>It is we that with thankes to God do
acknowledge that God hath so guided the
successe of this late rebellion, as if he should
haue sayd to her maiestie, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe daughter, al
though necessitie of mine ordinance, and
the disposition of thinges for my glorie
(which shalbe in the end also your benefit)
be such as there must be a traitorous re∣bellion
in your realme, yet this will I do
for you: you shall vnderstand it in tyme:
you shall haue the meanes, whereby they
should accomplish their entent, in your
owne power: you shall make your owne
match: you shall haue the choyse to name
the parties your selfe, that shalbe the leders
and doers of it, euen the weakest of credit,
wit, and power that you can chose to with∣stand
you: you shall chuse the tyme, when
they shall attempt it, the most vnsea∣sonable
for them, either to procede in
their owne doinges together, or for hauing
aide to resort to them, either of foraine ene∣mies
or domesticall traytors: you shal chose
the place where you would haue it begon,
<PB REF="52"/>
such as lyeth best for danger of contagion
of other, easiest for your selfe to enclose,
hardest for your enemyes to come to, and
nearest borderyng vpon your best foreine
frendes: they shall want furniture, your
selfe shall haue abundance: your good and
true counsellers shall nobly and truely
stand by you: your nobilitie shalbe prouo∣ked
to reuenge dishonor &amp; slanderous suspi∣tions
throwen vpon them by the rebelles
and therby shall haue cause to striue who
may best serue you: your good subiectes
shall euery way shew theyr zeale in your
seruice: your poore clergie shall poure out
theyr deuout prayer for you and I will
heare them: I will guide the successe to
your victorie: your enemies shalbe so sna∣red,
as the victorie well folowed, the trea∣son
well examined, the faultie well remo∣ued,
the roote well &amp; cleane hewed vp, you
may sit frée from traitors whyle you lyue,
and your good &amp; true counsellers and sub∣iectes
may be set in safe abilitie and en∣couraged
to serue you truly and stand
faythfully and boldly by you. Sée now
that you fayle not me nor your selfe, and
neither by missuser, nor nonvser, forsake
<PB REF="53"/>
me, nor lose the benefites that I haue so
prouided for you.</P>
<P>We therefore acknowledge all these
things to haue so come to passe, and dout
not that her Maiestie will euer with in∣uincible
constantie so prouide that those
most noble Counsellers be mainteyned to
serue God and her without feare, and be
so cherished as they may with delite and
frée carelesnesse and assurednesse of their
owne estates from perill of reuenge or any
other assault, bend them selues wholly to
studie for her highnesses preseruation.
We pray God to geue her Maiestie euer
the hart to suspect his truth whatsoeuer he
be, (if any euer be as I trust there shall
not) that shall practise to abate any credite
of these most true counsellers, or shall in∣sinuate
or geue any aduise to stay the true
and perfect serching of the bottome of these
treasens to forbeare the full destruction of
the roote thereof, or to extenuate her Maie∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ies
perill, and to say to euery such a one
if any smoke or glimse of signification may
thereunto leade, <HI>et tu ex illis es.</HI> Thou
art also one of them. We confesse it is
time, and we pray, that all her Maiesties
subiects by othe and al other good meanes
<PB REF="53"/>
may be assured vnto her, and that al titles,
all bondes, knottes▪ alliances, colours and
pretences to her Maiesties danger may be
cut of, what shew soeuer they make, kno∣wing
and hartely desiring it may be re∣membred,
that no common law of nati∣ons,
no title of anoynted, or what soeuer
face they set vpon it, may be warrant for
for any perilous creature, Papist, Bishop,
Priest, runaway, gentleman, marchant,
or other, man or woman, to be dangerous
to her Maiestie in her own realme. We
know well that a gallon of Rats bane in
an Apothecaries shop will not hurt a man
halfe so much as an ounce in his bellye.
We are not so madde to haue such a fonde
longyng for the flesh pottes of Egypt, for
marie &amp; marie bones that we wold with
the rebellious Iewes desire to returne a∣gaine
to the land of Egipt the house of bon∣dage
&amp; forein slauerie both of body &amp; soule,
to suck them, and that not for lacke but for
lothing of fine natural and holesome foode.
We pray that we may once see euery ti∣tle
destroyed, whatsoeuer it be, either in
ciuill respect or ecclesiasticall, that hath or
shall any way threaten her Maiesties
danger, that hath or shall any way clayme
<PB REF="54"/>
the crounerom frm her hed, or her power
out of her hand, that hath or shall seke any
dispossession of her estate and the inuasion
of her land,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Romane tyrannies and cruel∣ties.</NOTE> &amp; specially the titles and lewd
hopes of Romish Popes that haue by no∣torius
wickednesse excedyng the olde
Romane Emperours shewed them selues
vnmete to lyue among Christian people,
much lesse to gouerne them, that haue by
murrible and vnnaturall murders and
hoactise of poysoning and other mis∣chieues
shewed that them selues and their
Papistes are not to be wonne with kinde∣nesse
to be true to the Queene, that could
not be holden by nature from slaughter of
t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eir own, as by many euident histories
appeareth, yea where their treason may
be rewarded with a kingdome, yea with
the kingdome of heauen: those fained and
wicked titles (we say) of Romish vsur∣pation,
that haue interrupted the blessed
yea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e which we haue so long enioyed, that
haue drawen into conspiracie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Treasons of Papists.</NOTE> alliance &amp;
knottes of fauour those of whom her Ma∣iestie
hath well deserued, that hath armed
the rebell against lour most good swete so∣ueraigne
Ladies life, croune, and dignitie,
and put weapon in traytors handes to cut
<PB REF="54"/>
true subiectes throtes, and vtterly to de∣stroy
the wealth, safetie and honor of Eng¦land.</P>
<P>We pray that we may see when those
that shall wrest or procure to change law,
to erect the courage of any dangerous Vi∣per
to such endes, or to any aspiring hope
of preuenting and vndermining, vnder
whatsoeuer colour, name, pretēce or shew
in proclamation or otherwise, or to the
safegard of their persones that haue so at∣tempted,
may be declared and executed as
enemies to this estate, and to the Quenes
safety. We pray that we may se such laws
prouided for her highnesses preseruation,
&amp; the same so executed without restraint
or slacknesse for any respect as the hope of
Papistes, such as be enemies to God, the
Quéene, and the realme, may if they re∣pent
not, be cut of for euer. We pray to
liue to sée that none may haue place, office
nor accesse into her Maiesties court nor
houshold, no nor once to her presence, that
shall not be well knowen to fauour both
God and her, so far as any circumspection
and policie may prouide it. We pray God
that we may once sée the administration,
yea and studie of law and iustice wholly
<PB REF="55"/>
taken from those that shall not be knowen
to fauour the law of God, and to acknow∣ledge
her Maiesties right, that is head of
law and iustice in the realme. We pray
God that her Maiestie and her Counsell
may haue such particular knowledge of
men that her enemies may be weakened,
and her frendes strengthned, al auantages
vsed for her safetie, all neutrall aduises sus∣pected
for surtle vnderminings. We trust
it wil be so, for God hath not drawen these
late mischiefes into light for nothing. But
afore all thinges we pray God to send vs
true repentance, more ioyfull receiuing of
his Gospel, and more vertuous ensuing it,
least as we lost our best king with liuing
ill, so we may lose our best Quene with li∣uing
worse. And that therewith it may
please him to direct all the doinges of her
Maiestie and Counsell to procéede in their
good aduauncing his glorie and preserua∣tion
of the state, which without ielous cir∣cumspection
for preseruing the Queenes
most royall person can not be done, and
that such good meanes and prouisions as
God offereth to that end, be not refused or
neglected, which were to tempt God, to
forsake his cause, to betray our noble
<PB REF="55"/>
Prince, and to geue away or rather cast
away the realme.</P>
<P>These be the dayly and nightly prayers
of good subiectes. And while we busie our
selues with these praiers, we do after
our principall confidence in Godes good∣nesse,
rest our selues vpon the trust of her
Maiestie and her most honorable Coun∣sell,
for whom we prayse God, and to them
we referre the guiding of vs and ours,
ready to follow them, when we are com∣maunded
with the vttermost of our pow∣er
and perill, knowing how they spare not
their vttermost endeuour and perill, with
susteyning the most vnpleasant life, God
wot, that may be, for our sakes, for our
quiet, profite and defense.</P>
<P>Consider these thinges ye that haue
bene and haue not yet ceased to be such
Papistes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Good coū∣sell to Pa∣pistes.</NOTE> remember how in that state ye
be neither true Christian men nor true
English men, wherby if ye repent not you
are not worthy to liue in the kingdome
of England, and you are sure not to come
in the kingdome of Heauen. Let euery good
thing moue you to truth and to your pre∣fitte.
Let euery euill thing fray you from
treason &amp; from eternall vndoing. Learne
<PB REF="56"/>
religion of God alone, render your alle∣geance
to your prince alone, liue in bond
of countrey with English men alone. Ac∣knowledge
how God hath sent his truth
to shine vpon you, her maiestie hath pou∣red
all benefites of her good gouernaunce
among you, her true subiectes desire euery
way both in soule and body to be comfor∣table
to you. Put of onely the cankerd
affection or rather passion of inhumanitie.
Doo but once come home from those arti∣cles
that can not stand with out treason
to the prince and state, bynde not your
selues, your soules and fayth to the autho∣ritie
of any mortall and sinfull man, geue
euer infinitly to God, resort faythfully to
him, pray deuoutely to him, to shew you
his truth by his owne worde. And so I
dout not but hauing once forsaken foreine
subiections, and being once so farre vnpa∣pisted
that ye may come into the number
of true subiectes, for the rest God shall ac∣cord
vs, and shall reueale vnto you sinceri∣tie
of all truth in time, and in such time as
shall be the greatest comfort that euer you
felt in your liues. And so yet till other er∣rors
be purged by Gods grace working by
the hearing of his word, we shall al goe vn∣der
<PB REF="56"/>
the gentle yoke of our naturall soue∣raigne,
there let vs draw louingly toge∣ther,
and then saye and sing merily God
spede the ploughe of England. <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<CLOSER>¶God saue our Queene
Elizabeth, and con∣found
her ene∣mies.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<P>¶Imprinted at London by Iohn
Daye, dwelling ouer
Aldersgate.</P>
<P>These Bookes are to be solde in
Paules churchyarde at the
signe of the Crane.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

