<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Orders, thought meete by her Maiestie, and her priuie Councell, to be executed throughout the counties of this realme, in such townes, villages, and other places, as are, or may be hereafter infected with the plague, for the stay of further increase of the same Also, an aduise set downe vpon her Maiesties expresse commaundement, by the best learned in physicke within this realme, contayning sundry good rules and easie medicines, without charge to the meaner sort of people, aswell for the preseruation of her good subiects from the plague before infection, as for the curing and ordering of them after they shalbe infected.</TITLE><AUTHOR>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A69358</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 9187.9</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S115132</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99850351</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99850351</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">15543</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A69358)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15543)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1483:4 or 1752:34)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Orders, thought meete by her Maiestie, and her priuie Councell, to be executed throughout the counties of this realme, in such townes, villages, and other places, as are, or may be hereafter infected with the plague, for the stay of further increase of the same Also, an aduise set downe vpon her Maiesties expresse commaundement, by the best learned in physicke within this realme, contayning sundry good rules and easie medicines, without charge to the meaner sort of people, aswell for the preseruation of her good subiects from the plague before infection, as for the curing and ordering of them after they shalbe infected.</TITLE><AUTHOR>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>England and Wales. Privy Council.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[28] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>Imprinted at London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>By Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>[1578?]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>The orders are undated; publication date suggested by STC.</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² (-A1).</NOTE><NOTE>This state does not have a cut of the royal arms on D2v.</NOTE><NOTE>Identified as STC 9199 at reel 1483:4.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and Cambridge University Library.</NOTE><NOTE>Formerly STC 9195.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Plague --  England --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Plague --  Prevention --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Plague --  Treatment --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2006-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2006-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ali Jakobson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Ali Jakobson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A69358">
<STC T="S">9187.9</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99850351</BIBNO>
<VID>15543</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>ORDERS,
thought meete by her
Maiestie, and her priuie Councell, to be
executed throughout the Counties of this Realme,
in such Townes, Villages, and other places, as are, or
may be hereafter infected with the plague, for
the stay of further increase of the same.</P>
<P>❧Also, an aduise set downe vpon her
Maiesties expresse commaundement, by the best lear∣ned
in Physicke within this Realme, contayning sundry good
rules and easie medicines, without charge to the meaner
sort of people, aswell for the preseruation of her good
Subiects from the plague before infection,
as for the curing and ordring of them
after they shalbe infected.</P>
<P>❧Imprinted at London by Christo∣pher
Barker, Printer to the Queenes
most excellent Maiestie.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>❧Orders thought
meete by her Maiestie and her priuie
Councel, to be executed throughout the Counties
of this Realme, in such Townes, Villages, and other
places, as are, or may be hereafter infected
with the plague, for the stay of fur∣ther
increase of the same.</HEAD>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>Nprimis,</HI> all the Iustices in euery <MILESTONE N="1"/>
Countie, aswell within the liberties
as without, immediatly▪ vpon know∣ledge
to them giuen, shall assemble
themselues together at some one ge∣nerall
place accustomed, being cleare from infecti∣on
of the plague, to consult howe these orders follo∣wing
may be duely put in execution, not meaning
that any Iustices dwelling in or nere places infec∣ted,
shall come thither whiles their comming may
be doubtful. And after their first generall assembly▪
they shal make a distribution of themselues to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣dry
limits and diuisions, as in other <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> serui∣ces
for the Countie they are accustomed to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for
the prosecution thereof.</P>
<P>2 First, they shall inquire, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> informe <MILESTONE N="2"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
habitants of the same Townes and Parishes are,
to be hable to relieue the poore that are or shalbe in∣fected,
and to be restrained in their houses.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="3"/> 3 Item, thereupon after conference vsed▪ accor∣ding
to the necessitie of the cause, they shall deuise
and make a generall taxation, eyther by charging
the Towne infected with one summe in grosse, or
by charging the speciall persons of wealth within
the same, to be forth with collected for the rate of one
moneth at the first, and so if the sicknesse shall conti∣nue,
the collection of the like summe, or of more or of
lesse, as time and cause shall require, and the same
to be euery first, seconde, third, or fourth weeke em∣ploied
to and for the execution of the saide orders.
And in case some of the said Townes infected shall
manifestly appeare not to be of sufficient habilitie
to contribute sufficient for the charges requisite,
then the taxation or collection shalbe made or fur∣ther
extended to other partes, or in any other fur∣ther
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, as by the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shalbe thought requisite
where there shalbe any such Townes or Villages
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and vnable to relieue themselues. And
if the said Townes be scituated in the borders and
confines of any other shire, then as the Iustices
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> neede for the greatnesse of the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>arge <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, that the pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ioy∣ning
to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
the next Iustices of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
Shire <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o confir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>g, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o procure by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> some
reliefe, as in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to relieue them, in
respect of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of the place, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
that the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> infection <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
from the said adioyning places, though they be se∣parated
<PB REF="3"/>
by name of the Countie.</P>
<P>4 Item, they shal cause to be appointed in eue∣ry <MILESTONE N="4"/>
Parish aswell infected as not infected, certaine
persons to viewe the bodies of all such as shall die,
before they be suffered to be buried, and to certifie
the Minister of the Church and Churchwarden, or
other principal officers, or their substitutes, of what
probable disease the said persons died: and the saide
viewers to haue weekely some allowance, and the
more large allowance where the Townes or Pa∣rishes
be infected, during the infection, towards
their maintenance, to the end they which shal be in
places infected, may forbeare to resort into the com∣panie
of others that are sounde: and those persons
to be sworne to make true report according to their
knowledge, and the choise of them to be made by
direction of the Curat of the Church, with three or
foure substantiall men of the Parish. And in case
the said viewers either through fauour or corrupti∣on,
shal giue wrong certificat, or shal refuse to serue
being thereto appointed, then to cause them to be
punished by imprisonmēt, in such sort as may serue
for a terror to others.</P>
<P>5▪ Item, the houses of such persons out of the <MILESTONE N="5"/>
which there shall dye any of the plague, being so
certified by the viewers, or otherwise knowen, or
where it shalbe vnderstood, that any person remai∣neth
sicke of the plague, to be closed vp on all parts
during the time of restraint, vz. sixe weekes, after
the sicknesse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e ceased in the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e house, in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the
said houses <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> infected sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lbe within any Towne
ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing houses nere adio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ning to the same. And if
<PB REF="4"/>
the infection happen in houses dispersed in Villa∣ges,
and separated from other houses, and that of
necessitie, for the seruing of their cattel, and manu∣ring
of their ground, the said persons cannot conti∣nue
in their houses, then they to be neuerthelesse re∣strained
from resorting into companie of others, ei∣ther
publiquely or priuately during the said time of
restraint, and to weare some marke in their vpper∣most
garments, or beare white rods in their hands
at such time as they shall goe abroade, and if there
be any doubt that the masters and owners of the
houses infected, will not duely obserue the directi∣ons
of shutting vp their doores, specially in the
night, then shall there be appointed two or three
watchmen by turnes, which shalbe sworne to at∣tend
and watch the house, and to apprehend any
person that shall come out of the house contrary to
order, and the same persons by order of the Iusti∣ces,
shal be a competent time imprisoned in y<SUP>e</SUP> stocks
in the highway next to the house infected: and fur∣thermore,
some speciall marke shalbe made and fix∣ed
to the doores of euery of the infected houses, and
where any such houses shall be Innes or Alehou∣ses,
the signes shalbe taken down for the time of the
restraint, and some crosse or other marke set vp in
the place thereof, to be a token of the sicknesse.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="6"/> 6 Item, they shall haue good regarde to chuse
honest persons that either shall collect the summes
assessed, or shall haue the custodie thereof, &amp; out of
the said collection to allot a weekely proportion for
the finding of victuall, or fire, or medicines for the
poorer sort, during the tyme of their restraynt. And
whereas some persons being well disposed to yeeld
<PB REF="4"/>
almes and reliefe, wil be more willing to giue some
portions of victuall, as corne, bread or other meate,
the same shall be committed to the charge of some
speciall persons, that will honestly and truely pre∣serue
the same, to be distributed as they shall be ap∣poynted
for the poore that are infected.</P>
<P>7 Item, to appoynt certaine persons dwelling <MILESTONE N="7"/>
within the townes infected, to prouide and deliuer
all necessaries of victuals, or any matter of wat∣ching
or other attendance, to keepe such as are of
good wealth being restrained, at their owne proper
charges, and the poore at the common charges: and
the said persons so appoynted to be ordered, not to
resort to any publique assemblie during the tyme of
such their attendance, as also to weare some marke
on their vpper garment, or to beare a white rod in
their hande, to the ende others may auoyde their
companie.</P>
<P>8 Item, that in the shire towne in euery Coun∣tie,<MILESTONE N="8"/>
and in other great townes meete for that pur∣pose,
there may be prouision bespoken and made, of
such preseruatiues &amp; other remedies, which other∣wise
in meaner townes can not be readily had, as
by the Physicians shall be prescribed, and is at this
present reduced into an Aduise made by the Physi∣cians,
and nowe printed and sent with the sayd or∣ders,
which may be fixed in market places, vpon
places vsual for such publique matters, and in other
townes in the bodies of the parishe churches, and
chappells, in which aduise only such things are pre∣scribed,
as vsually are to be had and founde in all
countries without great charge or cost.</P>
<P><PB REF="5"/>
<MILESTONE N="9"/> 9 Item, the Ministers and Curates, and the
Church wardens in euery Parish, shall in writing
certifie weekely to some of the Iustices, residing
within y<SUP>e</SUP> Hundred or other limit where they serue,
the number of such persons as are infected and doe
not die, and also of all such as shall die within their
Parishes, and their diseases probable wherof they
dyed, and the same to be certified to the rest of the
Iustices at their assemblies, which during some
conuenient time would be euery xxi. dayes, and
thereof a particular booke kept by the Clerke of the
peace, or some such like.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="10"/> 10 Item, to appoynt some place apart in each
parish for the burial of such persons as shal die of the
plague, as also to giue order that they be buryed af∣ter
sunne setting, and yet neuerthelesse by daylight,
so as the Curate be present for the obseruation of the
rites and ceremonies prescribed by the lawe, fore∣seeing
as much as conueniently he may, to be distāt
from the danger of infection of the person dead, or
of the companie that shall bryng the corse to the
graue.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="11"/> 11 Item, the Iustices of the whole Countie to
assemble once in xxi. dayes, to examine whether
those orders be duely executed, and to certifie to the
lordes of the priuie Councell their proceedings in
that behalf, what townes and villages be infected,
as also the nombers of the dead, and the diseases
wherof they dyed; and what summes of money are
taxed and collected to this purpose, and howe the
same are distributed.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="12"/> 12 Item, the Iustices in the hundred, where a∣ny
<PB REF="5"/>
such infection is, or the Iustices next adioyning
therunto, to assemble once a week, to take accompt
of the execution of the said orders, and as they finde
any lack or disorder, either to reforme it themselues,
or to report it at the generall assemblie there, to be
by a more common consent reformed.</P>
<P>13 Item, for that the contagion of the plague <MILESTONE N="13"/>
groweth and increaseth no way more, then by the
vse and handling of such clothes, bedding and other
stuffe as hath bene worne and occupyed by the in∣fected
of this disease, during the time of their
disease: the sayde Iustices shall in the places in∣fected
take such order, that all the saide clothes
and other stuffe, so occupied by the diseased, so
soone as the parties diseased of the plague are all of
them either well recouered or dead, be either burnt
and cleane consumed with fire: or els ayred in such
sort as is prescribed in an especiall article conteyned
in the Aduise set downe by the Physicians. And for
that peraduenture the losse of such apparell, bed∣ding
and other stuffe to be burnt, may be greater
then the poore estate of the owners of the same may
well beare: it is thought very good and expedient,
if it be thought meete it should be burnt, that then
the said Iustices, out of such collections as are to be
made within their Counties for the reliefe of the
poorer sort that be infected, allowe also to them such
summe or summes as to them shall be thought rea∣sonable,
in recompēce of the losse of their said stuffe.</P>
<P>14 Item, the said Iustices may put in executi∣on <MILESTONE N="14"/>
any other orders that by them at their generall
assemblie shall be deuised and thought meete, ten∣ding
<PB REF="6"/>
to the preseruation of her Maiesties subiectes
from the infection, and to the end their care and di∣ligence
may the better appeare, they shall certifie in
writing the sayde orders newly deuised, and if any
shall wilfully breake and contemne the same or any
the orders herein specified, they shal either presently
punishe them by imprisonment, or if the persons so
contemning them, shall be of such countenance as
the Iustices shall thinke meete to haue their faults
knowen to her Maiestie, or to the Councell, they
shall charge and binde them to appeare before vs, &amp;
the contempt duely certified, that there may bee a
more notorious sharpe example made by punish∣ment
of the same by order of her Maiestie.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="15"/> 15 Item, if there be lacke of Iustices in some
partes of the shire, or if they which are Iustices
there shall be for the tyme absent, in that case the
more nomber of the Iustices at their assemblie shal
make choyse of some conuenient persons to supply
those places for the better execution hereof.</P>
<P><MILESTONE N="16"/> 16 Item, if there be any person Ecclesiastical or
laye, that shall holde and publishe any opinions (as
in some places report is made) that it is a vayne
thing to forbeare to resort to the infected, or that it
is not charitable to forbid the same, pretending that
no person shall dye but at their tyme prefixed, such
persons shalbe not onely reprehended, but by order
of the Bishop, if they be ecclesiasticall, shalbe forbid∣den
to preache, and being laye, shalbe also enioyned
to forbeare to vtter such dangerous opinions vpon
payne of imprisonment, which shall be executed, if
they shall perseuer in that error. And yet it shall ap∣peare
<PB REF="6"/>
manifestly by these orders, that according to
Christian charitie, no persons of the meanest degree
shalbe left without succour and reliefe.</P>
<P>17 And of these things aboue mencioned, the <MILESTONE N="17"/>
Iustices shall take great care, as of a matter speci∣ally
directed &amp; commanded by her Maiestie vpon
the princely and naturall care shee hath conceyued
towards the preseruation of her subiectes, who by
very disorder, and for lacke of direction do in many
partes wilfully procure the increase of this general
contagion.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="7"/>
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>An aduise set dovvne
vpon her Maiesties expresse comman∣dement,
by the best learned in Physicke within this
Realme, contayning sundry good rules and easie medi∣cines,
vvithout charge to the meaner sort of people,
as well for the preseruation of her good Sub∣iectes
from the plague before infection,
as for the curing and ordring of
them after they shal be
infected.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Preseruatiue by correcting the aire
in Houses.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Ake <HI>Rosemarie</HI> dried,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Preserua∣tiues.</NOTE> or <HI>Iuni∣per,
Bayleaues,</HI> or <HI>Frankincense,</HI>
cast the same on a Chafindish,
and receiue the fume or smoke
therof▪ Some aduise to be ad∣ded
<HI>Lauender,</HI> or <HI>Sage.</HI></P>
<P>Also to make fires rather in
Pannes, to remoue about the
Chamber, then in Chimneis, shall better correct
the aire of the Houses.</P>
<P>Take a quantitie of <HI>Vineger</HI> very strong, and
put to it some small quantitie of <HI>Rosewater,</HI> tenne
branches of <HI>Rosemarie,</HI> put them all into a basen,
then take fiue or sixe <HI>Flintstones,</HI> heated in the fire
till they be burning hotte, cast them into the same
<HI>Vineger,</HI> &amp; so let the fumes be receiued from place
to place of your house.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB REF="8"/>
<HEAD>Perfuming of Apparel.</HEAD>
<P>SVch apparel as you shal commonly weare, let
it be very cleane, and perfume it often eyther
with some red <HI>Saūders</HI> burned, or with <HI>Iuniper.</HI>
And if any shal happen to be with them that are
visited, let such persons as soone as they shal come
home, shift themselues, &amp; aire their other clothes,
in open aire for a time.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Preseruation by way of defence in open
aire, and common assemblies to
be vsed outwardly.</HEAD>
<P>IT is good in going abroade into the open aire
in the streetes, to hold some things of sweete sa∣uour
in their hands, or in the corner of a hand∣kerchiefe,
as a sponge dipped in <HI>Vineger</HI> &amp; <HI>Rosewa∣ter</HI>
mixed, or in <HI>Vineger,</HI> wherein <HI>Wormewood,</HI> or
<HI>Rue</HI> called also <HI>Herbegrace,</HI> hath bene boyled.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Preseruatiue by way of inward
medicine.</HEAD>
<P>TAke a quantitie of <HI>Rue,</HI> or <HI>Wormewood,</HI> or of
both, and put it into a potte of vsuall drinke,
close stopped, let it lie so in steepe a whole
night, and drinke thereof in the morning fasting.</P>
<P>In all Sommer plagues, it shalbe good to vse
<HI>Sorrel sauce</HI> to be eaten in y<SUP>e</SUP> morning with bread,
And in the fall of the leafe to vse the iuice of <HI>Bar∣beries</HI>
with bread also.</P>
<P><PB REF="8"/>
Mens bodies
are apt to take
infectiō, either
<LIST>
<ITEM>By the constitution of the heart,
the vitall spirites being weake,
and the naturall heate feeble, in
which case thinges Cordiall are
to be vsed.</ITEM>
<ITEM>By repletion,
the body being
filled with hu∣mors,
either
<LIST>
<ITEM>Good, and then
is the party to
be let blood.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Euill, and then
is hee to be cu∣red
with medi∣cine
purgatiue.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Preseruatiues Cordialls.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Mithridates Medicine.</HEAD>
<P>TAke of good <HI>Figges</HI> not wormeaten, cleane
wasshed, of <HI>Walnuts</HI> y<SUP>e</SUP> kernels cleane picked,
of either of them an hundred, of the leaues of
greene <HI>Rue,</HI> otherwise called <HI>Herbgrace,</HI> y<SUP>e</SUP> weight
of ii. s. of common Salt the weight of iiii. d. cut
the <HI>Figges</HI> in pieces, and stampe them and the
<HI>Walnut</HI> kernels together in a morter of Marble
or wood a good space, vntil they be very smal, and
then put your <HI>Rue</HI> leaues vnto them, stampe and
stirre them well together with the rest, last put in
the Salt and stampe and stirre these things toge∣ther,
vntill they be encorporated and made of one
substance. Of the which take the quantitie of ii. or
iii. <HI>Figges</HI> euery morning fasting, to children the
halfe wil serue, and he that listeth to increase or di∣minish
<PB REF="9"/>
the substance of this Medicine, shall easely
do it, by taking of a greater or lesse quantitie of the
simples according to a due proportion.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>A well approued Medicine to
preserue.</HEAD>
<P>TAke of the finest cleare <HI>Aloes</HI> you can buy, in
colour like to a Liuer, and therefore called
<HI>Hepatica,</HI> of <HI>Cinamō,</HI> of <HI>Myrrhe,</HI> of ech of these
the weight of iii. French crownes, or of xxii. d. of
our money, of <HI>Cloues, Maces, Lignum Aloes,</HI> of <HI>Ma∣sticke,</HI>
of <HI>Bole Oriental,</HI> of ech of these half an ounce:
mingle them together and beate them into a very
fine powder. Of the which take euery morning
fasting the weight of a grote of this in white wine
delayed with water, and by the grace of God you
shall be safe from the plague. No man which is
learned, if he examine the simples of this medicine
whereof it consisteth, and the nature and power of
them, can denie but that it is a medicine of great
efficacie against the plague, and the simples wher∣of
it is made, are easily to be had in any good Apo∣thecaries
shoppe, except <HI>Bole Orientall,</HI> which is
vsed in the stead of true <HI>Bolus Armenus,</HI> wherof we
haue seene great store in the shopps of master <HI>Rich</HI>
the Queenes Maiesties Apothecarie, and master
<HI>Morgans</HI> in <HI>Cheapsyde.</HI></P>
<P>Take a drie <HI>Figge</HI> and open it, and put the ker∣nel
of a <HI>Walnut</HI> into the same being cut very smal,
iii. or iiii. leaues of <HI>Rue</HI> cōmonly called <HI>Herbgrace,</HI> a
corne of Salt, then rost the <HI>Figge</HI> &amp; eate it warme,
fast iii. or iiii. houres after it, and vse this twyse in
the weeke.</P>
<P><PB REF="9"/>
Take the powder of <HI>Turmentill,</HI> the weight of
vi. d. with <HI>Sorrell</HI> or <HI>Scabious</HI> water in Sommer,
and in Winter with the water of <HI>Valerian</HI> or com∣mon
drinke.</P>
<P>Or els in one day they may take a litle <HI>Worme∣wood,</HI>
and <HI>Valerian</HI> with a graine of Salt. In an∣other
day they may take vii. or viii. berries of <HI>Iuni∣per,</HI>
dried and put in powder, and taking the same
with common drinke, or with drinke in which
<HI>Wormwood</HI> and <HI>Rue</HI> hath bene steeped al y<SUP>e</SUP> night.</P>
<P>Also y<SUP>e</SUP> triakle called <HI>Diaresseroū,</HI> which is made
but of iiii. things of light price easie to be had.</P>
<P>Also the roote of <HI>Enula Campana,</HI> either taken in
powder with drinke, or hanged about the br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t.</P>
<P>Likewise a piece of <HI>Arras</HI> roote kept in y<SUP>e</SUP> mouth
as men passe in the streetes, is very good <HI>Cordiall.</HI></P>
<P>Take vi. leaues of <HI>Sorrell,</HI> wash them with wa∣ter
and vineger, let them lye to steepe in the said
water and vineger a while, then eat them fasting,
and keepe in your mouth and chewe nowe or then
either <HI>Setwall,</HI> or the roote of <HI>Angelica,</HI> or a litle
<HI>Cinamon.</HI></P>
<P>Take the roote of <HI>Enula Campana</HI> being layde
and steeped in vineger, &amp; grosse beaten, put a litle
of it in a handkercheife, and smel to it if you resort
to any that is infected.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>For women with childe, or such as be delicate
and tender, and cannot away with
taking of medicines.</HEAD>
<P>MAke a tost of white or of the second bread, as
you thinke good, and sprinkle on it being
hotte a litle good wine vineger, made with
<PB REF="10"/>
Rose leaues, and for want of it any good common
or vsed vineger, &amp; spreade on the tost a litle butter,
and cast thereon a litle powder of <HI>Cinamon,</HI> and
eate it in the morning fasting. The poore which
can not get vineger nor buy <HI>Cinamon,</HI> maye eate
bread and Butter alone, for Butter is not onely a
preseruatiue against the plague, but against all
maner of poysons.</P>
<P>When one must come into the place where in∣fectious
persons are, it is good to smel to the roote
of <HI>Angelica, Gentian</HI> or <HI>Valerian,</HI> and to chewe any
of these in his mouth.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>An other preseruatiue for
the poore.</HEAD>
<P>IT shalbe good to take an handfull of <HI>Rue,</HI> and
as much common <HI>Wormwood,</HI> and bruse them
a litle: and put them into a potte of Earth or
Tinne, with so much Vineger as shall couer the
herbes: keepe this pot close couered or stopt, and
when you feare any infection, dippe into this Vi∣neger
a piece of asyonge, and carie it in your hand
and smell to it, or els put it into a round ball of
<HI>Yuorie</HI> or <HI>Iuniper</HI> made ful of holes of the one side,
carying it in your hand vse to smell thereunto, re∣newing
it once in a day.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>To be vsed after infection taken.</HEAD>
<P>FOr as much as the cause of the plague stan∣deth
rather in poyson▪<NOTE PLACE="marg">Curati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</NOTE> then in any <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
of humours as other agues doe, the chie∣fest
<PB REF="10"/>
way is to moue sweatings, and to defend the
heart by some cordiall thing.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Suppositary.</HEAD>
<P>IF the Pacient be costiue and bound in his bo∣die,
let him take a <HI>Suppositarie</HI> made with a litle
boyled <HI>Honney,</HI> and a litle fine powder of <HI>Salt,</HI>
and so taken in at the Fundament and kept till it
mooue a stoole.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>An excellent Medicine made with∣out
charges.</HEAD>
<P>TAke of the powder of good <HI>Bayberries,</HI> the
huske taken awaye from them, before
they be dried, a spooneful: Let the Patient
drincke this, well mingled in a draught of good
stale Ale or Beere, which is neither sowre nor
dead, or with a draught of white Wine, and go to
bedde and cast himselfe into a sweat, and forbeare
sleepe as is aforesaid.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>An other soueraigne remedie, that is
a stilled water.</HEAD>
<P>TAke the inwarde barke of the <HI>Ashe</HI> tree, a
pound, of <HI>Walnuts</HI> with the greene outward
shelles, to the number of 50. cut these small,
of <HI>Scabious,</HI> of <HI>Veruen,</HI> of <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>timorel,</HI> of <HI>Howsleeke,</HI> of
euery one a handfull, of <HI>Saffron</HI> halfe an ounce,
powre vpon these y<SUP>e</SUP> strongest Vineger you can get
foure pynts let them a litle boyle together vpon a
very soft fire▪ and then stand in a very close potte
<PB REF="11"/>
well slepe all a night vpon the embers, afterward
distill them with a soft fire, and receyue the water
close kept. Giue vnto the Patient layd in bedde &amp;
wel couered with clothes, two ounces of this wa∣ter
to drink, &amp; let him be prouoked to sweat, &amp; eue∣ry
sixe houres, during the space of xxiiii. houres,
giue him the same quantitie to drinke. This Me∣dicine
for the worthines therof, and because it wil
stand the maker thereof in little charge, it shall be
very well done to distill it in the Sommer when
the <HI>Walnutts</HI> hang greene on the tree, that it maye
bee ready against the time that occasion serueth
to vse it.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>1. Bloud letting.</HEAD>
<P>IF the Pacient be ful of humors which be good,
let him immediatly be let bloud vpon the Ly∣uer
veine in the right arme, or in the Median
veine of the same arme (if no sore appeare) in the
first day.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>2. Medicine purgatiue.</HEAD>
<P>FOr the poore take <HI>Aloes</HI> y<SUP>e</SUP> weight of vi. d. put
in the pappe of an Apple: and for the richer
<HI>Pilles</HI> of <HI>Rufus</HI> to be had in euery good Apothe∣caries
shoppe.</P>
<P>After letting of bloud and purging (as shall be
needfull) some of the forenamed Cordials are to
be vsed.</P>
<P>These preparations thus vsed y<SUP>e</SUP> first day that
the Pacient shall fall sicke, as cause shalbe to vse
the one or the other (no sore appearing) in which
<PB REF="11"/>
case if the sore shal appeare, they are both to be for∣borne▪
the next is to vse all meanes to expell the
poyson, and to defend the heart by Cordials.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>3. Medicament expulsiue.</HEAD>
<P>THe poyson is expelled best by sweatings pro∣uoked
by posset Ale, made with <HI>Fenel</HI> &amp; <HI>Ma∣rigolds</HI>
in Winter, and with <HI>Sorrell, Buglosse</HI>
and <HI>Borage</HI> in Sommer, with the which in both
times they must mixe the triacle of <HI>Diatessaroum,</HI>
the weight of ix. d. &amp; so to lay them selues with all
quietnes to sweat one halfe houre or an houre, if
they be strong. For they that be neither full of hu∣mors
nor corrupt in humors, neede neither pur∣ging
nor letting of bloud, but at the first plunge
maye moue themselues to sweat with Cordiall
things mixt with such things as moue sweat, and
are before declared.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>What is to be done when there is any
rising or swelling in any part.</HEAD>
<P>THen if by these three meanes the poyson be
expelled outward by Botches, carbuncles or
markes, called Gods markes, according as
nature doth expell, so must the further procedings
be, prouiding still, that they continue still in the vse
of the cordiall and moderate sweating now and
then, al the time that the sores be in healing, which
must by the Surgion be handled with great dis∣cretion.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB REF="12"/>
<HEAD>Medicine to be vsed in ordinarie dyet.</HEAD>
<P>IT is thought that the powder of harts horne
hath a speciall prerogatiue, to be vsed al the time
of their sickenesse in their broths, and supping,
which in Sommer must euer haue <HI>Sorrell, Borage,
Buglosse,</HI> and in winter, <HI>Betony,</HI> and <HI>Scabious,</HI> or
<HI>Morsus▪ Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</HI> and if their habilities do not serue,
let them vse it with Aleburies made with a litle
<HI>Nutmegge,</HI> or one <HI>Cloue,</HI> or with <HI>Cawdelles</HI> in like
maner▪ made with <HI>Cloues, Maces, Nutmegges, San∣ders</HI>
or such like.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Both to preserue and cure the
sickenesse.</HEAD>
<P>TAke an egge &amp; make a hole in the toppe of it,
take out the white &amp; y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lke, fil the shel with the
weight of two frēch crownes of <HI>Saffron▪</HI> rost
the said egge thus filled with <HI>Saffron</HI> vnder the
embres, vntill the shell begin to waxe yelow, then
take it from the fire, and beate the shel and <HI>Saffron</HI>
in a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> together, with halfe a spoonefull of
<HI>Mustard</HI> seede▪ take of this powder a french crown
weight, and assoone as you suspect your self infec∣ted,
dissolue it into tenne spoonfulles of posset ale, &amp;
drinke it luke warme, then go to bed and prouoke
your selfe to sweating.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>To be vsed in the first time of
the Sickenesse.</HEAD>
<P>ANother is to take fiue or sixe handefull of
Sorrel, that groweth in the field, or a grea∣ter
quantitie according as you will distill
<PB REF="12"/>
more or lesse of the water thereof, and let it lye
infrised or steeped in good Vineger the space of
xxiiii. houres, then take it of &amp; drie it with a linen
cloth put into a Limbecke, and distill the water
thereof: And assoone as you finde your selfe tou∣ched
with the sickenesse, drinke foure spoonfulles
of the sayde water with a litle sugar, and if you be
hable, walke vpō it vntil you do sweat, if not, keep
your bed, and being well couered, prouoke your
selfe to sweating, and the next day to take asmuch
againe of it a litle before supper.</P>
<P>Item, to prouoke vomit with two ounces of
rancke oyle, or walnutte oyle, a spoonefull of the
iuyce of <HI>Celendyne,</HI> &amp; halfe a spoonfull of the iuyce
of radice roote, so that the party infected do walke
and not sleepe, is better then any letting of blood,
or any purging. For the disease neither can suffer▪
agitatiō of humors, nor when one is infected, hath
no time to bleede or to purge.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Outward medicines for to be ap∣plyed
to the sore.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">The first.</HEAD>
<P>TAke of <HI>Scabiouse</HI> two handefulls, stampe it in
a stone morter with a pestell of stone if you
can get any such, then put vnto it of olde
swynes grease salted, two ounces, and the yelke
of an egge, stampe them well together, &amp; lay parte
of this warme to the sore.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB REF="13"/>
<HEAD>The second.</HEAD>
<P>TAke of the leaues of <HI>Mallowes,</HI> of <HI>Camomill</HI>
flowers, of eyther of them an handfull, of
<HI>Lineseede</HI> beaten into pouder two ounces,
boyle the <HI>Mallowe</HI> leaues first cut, and the flowers
of the <HI>Camomil</HI> in faire water standing aboue a
fingers breadth, boyle all them together vntil all
the water almost be spent: then put thereunto the
<HI>Lineseede,</HI> of <HI>Wheate</HI> flower halfe an handful, of
swines grease the skins taken away iii. ounces,
of oyle of Roses two ounces, stirre thē still with a
sticke, and let them all boyle together on a soft fire
without smoke, vntill the water be vtterly spent,
beate them all together in a morter, vntill they
be wel encorporated together, &amp; in feeling smooth,
&amp; not rough: then make part thereof hot in a dish
set vpon a chaf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndish of coales, &amp; lay it thicke vpō a
linnen cloth applying it to the sore.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Another excellent medicine to ripen and
bring out the Sore.</HEAD>
<P>TAke a white <HI>Onion</HI> cut in pieces, of fresh
butter three ounces, of <HI>Leuen</HI> the weight of
twelue pence, of <HI>Mallowes</HI> one handfull, of
<HI>Scabious</HI> if it may be had one handefull, of <HI>Cloues</HI>
of garlicke the weight of xx. d. boyle them on the
fyre in sufficient water, and make a pultesse of it,
and lay it warme to the sore.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Another.</HEAD>
<P>TO the sore it selfe do thus. Take two hand∣full
of <HI>Valerian,</HI> three rootes of <HI>Danewort,</HI> a
handefull of <HI>Smalledge,</HI> or <HI>Louage,</HI> yf you can
<PB REF="13"/>
get it, seethe them al in butter and water, &amp; a fewe▪
crommes of bread, and make a pultesse thereof, &amp;
lay it warme to the sore vntill it breake.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Another for the same.</HEAD>
<P>IF you can not haue these herbes, it is good to
laye a loafe of bread to it, hot as it commeth out
of the ouen, (which afterward shal be burnt or
buried in the earth) or the leaues of <HI>Scabious</HI> or
<HI>Sorrell</HI> rosted, or two or three <HI>Lillie</HI> rootes rosted
vnder embers, beaten and applied.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>A generall medicine for all sorts of people
taken with the plague, to be had
without cost.</HEAD>
<P>TAke of y<SUP>e</SUP> roote of butter burre, otherwise cal∣led
pestilēt wort, one ounce, of y<SUP>e</SUP> root of great
<HI>Valerian</HI> a quarter of an ounce, of <HI>Sorrel</HI> an
hādful, boyle al these in a quart of water to a pint,
then straine it and put thereto two spoonfulles of
<HI>Vineger,</HI> two ounces of good <HI>Sugar,</HI> boyle all these
together vntill they be wel mingled, let y<SUP>e</SUP> infected
drinke of this so hotte as he may suffer it a good
draught, and if he chaunce to cast it vp againe, let
him take the same quantitie straight way vpon
it, and prouoke himselfe to sweat, and he shal finde
great helpe.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Time of continuance apart from com∣mon
assemblies.</HEAD>
<P>SVch as haue bene infected, should keepe their
house without being conuersant with the
whole, vntill the sores shall haue left running
<PB REF="14"/>
and be perfectly whole and sound, which in san∣guine
&amp; cholericke persons will be healed sooner,
then in melancholike &amp; flegmatike complexions.</P>
<P>SVch persons may not wel be conuersant with
them which are not infected, for the space of
one moneth.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Infected clothes.</HEAD>
<P>THe cōtagion suspected to remaine in clothes,
either wollen or linnen, cannot wel be auoy∣ded
by better meanes, then by fire and wa∣ter,
by often washing &amp; airing the same in frosts,
and sunne shine, with good discretion, and bur∣ning
the clothes of small value.</P>
<P>❧Imprinted at London by Christo∣pher
Barker, Printer to the Queenes
most excellent Maiestie.
(∵)</P>
<PB REF="14"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

