<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A letter to Anonymus in answer to his Three letters to Dr. Sherlock about church-communion</TITLE><AUTHOR>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A71019</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing S3300</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R14302</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12004712</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12004712</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">52277</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A71019)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52277)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 802:13 or 1514:13)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A letter to Anonymus in answer to his Three letters to Dr. Sherlock about church-communion</TITLE><AUTHOR>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 58 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Fincham Gardiner ...,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1683.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Written by William Sherlock.  Cf. DNB.</NOTE><NOTE>Signed at end: W.S.</NOTE><NOTE>Anonymous is identified as William Atwood.  Cf. Clark Memorial Lib. dict. cat.</NOTE><NOTE>This work is also appears on reels 1514:13 and 528:1 (as the third item in v. 1 of: A collection of cases and other discourses (Wing C5114)).</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of originals in the Duke University Library, Harvard University Library and Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Atwood, William, d. 1705? --  Three letters to Dr. Sherlock concerning church-communion.</TERM><TERM>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Lord's Supper --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A71019">
<STC T="W">S3300</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12004712</BIBNO>
<VID>52277</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A
LETTER
TO
ANONYMUS,
In Answer to his
Three Letters
TO
Dr. SHERLOCK
ABOUT
<HI>Church-Communion.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI>
Printed for <HI>Fincham Gardiner,</HI> at the <HI>White-Horse</HI>
in <HI>Ludgate-street.</HI> 1683.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>A
LETTER
TO
ANONYMUS,
In Answer to his Three LETTERS to
Dr. SHERLOCK about
Church-Communion.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I Am very sorry, that my Silence and Patience has
been mistaken by you for an affront and neglect;
which is such a provocation, as I find some sort
of great minds cannot bear.</P>
<P>But yet that you may have a little mercy, I shall give
you a brief account of the reason, why you had not an
Answer before.</P>
<P>I did not answer your first Letter in so publick a
manner as you desired, because I believed your Ob∣jections
were such, as no body was concern'd in but
your self; and I cannot think it decent to trouble so
numerous an Auditory with every particular mans
conceits. I did not answer your Second Letter, be∣cause
by the Temper and Spirit of it, I easily foresaw,
that it would end in a publick Quarrel; and if I must be
in Print, I henceforth resolve to Correct the Press my
self, and not to suffer any man to Print my private
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
Letters for me. But yet I called at Mr. R's Shop, whi∣ther
you directed me, several times, to have Invited
you to a private Conference, but could never see him,
till I accidentally met him in the street, the same day
I received the present of your Printed Letters. The
reason why I Printed those Discourses, which you
heard me Preach, was because they were designed for
the Press, before they were designed for the Pulpit,
and before I dream't of your terrible Queries; and
were Printed and Preach'd exactly by the same Copy,
excepting the Introduction to fit them to a Text, which
you know is very <HI>convenient for a Sermon.</HI> And the
reason why I sent you one of those Tracts, when it
was Printed, was because I did hope you might have
had understanding enough, upon a careful perusal of it,
when it lay before you, to have answered those Ob∣jections
which you made against it, at the first hear∣ing.</P>
<P>And now Sir, I come to consider the Contents of
your First Letter; you have made some Repetition of
what I Discoursed, and a very good Repetition to be done
by memory, which gives you the commendable Cha∣racter
of a diligent and attentive hearer: but when you
had the Discourse before you in Print, you ought not
then to have depended upon your memory, but to
have given me my own again in my own words and
order, and with that dependance and connexion, in
which the whole strength of that Discourse consists;
and to have applied your Queries distinctly to those
parts of the Discourse, which they related to: Had
you done this, you would either have been able to
have resolved your own Queries, or would more effe∣ctually
have convinc'd me of my mistake, or at least
have given your Readers better satisfaction in the pe<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣tinency
of what you say; but now you have onely
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
given us a heap of Queries, which it is no easie matter
to know to what they relate.</P>
<P>As for your Repetitions, the Reader who desires sa∣tisfaction
may compare them with what I have writ,
which is exactly the same with what I Preach'd: and
as for your Queries, you know how easie a thing it is
to ask Questions; however, I will endeavour to find
out to what they belong, and give as plain and short an
Answer to them as I can; for I assure you, I am not at
leasure now to write a long Book upon this Argument,
and therefore it is a great comfort to me, that there is
no need of it.</P>
<P>After your Repetition of what you could remember,
or what you thought fit to take notice of in my Sermon,
you give us a very mistaken Summary of it.</P>
<P>To sum up <HI>(say you)</HI> what I take to be the force of all
this.<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 4.</NOTE></P>
<P>The Apostles and their Successors were by our Saviour
invested with a power of receiving Members into his
Church upon his Terms, and with such Rites as they should
think fit; and they who are not so received into the Church,
have no right to any of the blessings promis'd to the Mem∣bers
of Christ's Body.</P>
<P>This Power is by an uninterrupted Succession, derived
upon the Governours of our National Church, wherefore all
others, that pretend to the exercise of this Power within
this Nation, are Vsurpers; and all the Laity Baptized by
their Pastors, not being duly admitted into any particu∣lar
Church, are so far from being Members of Christ's
Body, that they are Vsurpers and Traitors to that Power,
which is derived from him in a right line. <HI>Durus hic
Sermo.</HI></P>
<P>Had you not told the World in your Title-Page, that
you are a Lay-man, to make your Triumph over a
poor undone Dr. of Divinity the more glorious, I should
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
have taken you to be the Founder of some new Sect of
Conjectural Divines; and truly you are so happy in
your guesses, that I believe few men will ever be able
to out-do you in this Art. For there is not one word
of all this matter in the Discourse, which you pretend
to sum up, as it was delivered by me. That to which
you seem to refer, is contained in one short Paragraph,
which I shall Transcribe, and leave the most fanciful
Reader to try his skill to sum it up as you have done.
Having before asserted, that <HI>God onely can Constitute a
Church,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Resolut. of Cases, p. 5.</NOTE> I added, <HI>And I think it is as plain, that the on∣ly
visible way God has of Forming a Church (for I do not
now speak of the Invisible Operations of the Divine Spirit)
is by granting a Church-Covenant, which is the Divine
Charter whereon the Church is Founded, and investing
some persons with Power and Authority to receive others
into this Covenant, according to the terms and conditions
of the Covenant, and by such Covenant-Rites, and Forms
of Admission, as he is pleased to Institute; which under
the Gospel is Baptism, as under the Law it was Circum∣cision.</HI></P>
<P>I was discoursing of Gods visible way of Forming a
Church, which I asserted to be by granting a Church-Covenant,
which is that Divine Charter on which the
Church is Founded; but then lest any one should
question, how men are admitted into this Covenant,
I added, that God had invested some Persons with
Power and Authority to receive others into this Cove∣nant
by Baptism; and by receiving them into Cove∣nant,
they make them Members of that Church, which
is Founded on this Covenant.</P>
<P>Now what of all this will any sober Dissenter deny?
Here is no dispute, who is invested with this Power,
what form of Church-Government Christ Instituted,
whether Episcopal or Presbyterian; here is no Dispute
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
about the validity of Orders, or Succession, or in what
cases Baptism may be valid, which is not Administred by
a valid Authority; This did not concern my present Ar∣gument,
which proceeds upon a quite different Hypo∣thesis,
<HI>viz.</HI> the necessity of Communion with the <HI>one</HI>
Church and Body of Christ, for all those who are, or
would be owned to be Christians, or Members of
Christs Body. I make no inquiry, by whom they
have been Baptized, or whether they were rightly
Baptized or not; but taking all these things for granted,
I inquire whether Baptism do not make us Church-Members;
whether it makes us Members of a Particu∣lar
or Universal Church; whether a Church-Member
be not bound to Communion with the whole Catho∣lick
Church; whether he that separates from any
sound part of the Catholick Church, be not a Schis∣matick
from the whole Church; whether we be not
bound to maintain constant Communion with that
particular Church, in which we live, and with which
we can, when we please, Communicate occasionally;
whether it be consistent with Catholick Communion,
to communicate with two Churches, which are in
a state of Separation from each other: if you have
any thing to say to these matters, you shall have a
fair hearing; but all your Queries, which proceed up∣on
a mistaken Hypothesis of your own, do not concern
me; and yet to oblige you, if it be possible, I shall
briefly consider them.</P>
<P>1. <HI>Your first Query is,</HI> Whether a Pious Dissenter
supposed to be received into the Church by such as he
believes to be fully invested with sufficient Power, is in as
bad a condition as a Moral Heathen, or in a worse than
a Papist.</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
<HI>Ans.</HI> The Catholick Church has been so indulgent to
Hereticks and Schismaticks, as to determine against the
Necessity of Rebaptization, if they have been once,
though irregularly baptized. This you may find a par∣ticular
account of, in the Vindication of the Defence of
Dr. <HI>Still.</HI> p. 22. &amp;c. But the question is, whether if
they continue Schismaticks, whatever their other pre∣tences
to Piety be, their Condition be not as dange∣rous,
as the Condition of Moral Heathens and Pa∣pists.</P>
<P>2. Whether the Submission to the Power and Censures of
this Church, (which all must own to be a sound Church) be
part of the Divine Covenant, which Vnites the Members of
the Catholick Church to God and to each other.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> This is a captions question, which must be distinct∣ly
answered. A general Submission and Obedience
to the Authority and Censures of the Church, though
it cannot properly be called a part of that Divine Cove∣nant
whereon the Church is founded, which primari∣ly
respects the promise of Salvation by Christ through
Faith in his Bloud; yet it is a necessary Church Duty,
and Essential to Church-Communion, and so may be cal∣led
a part of the Covenant, if by the Covenant we un∣derstand
all those Duties which are required of bapti∣zed
Christians, and Members of the Church, by a Di∣vine
positive Law, as Obedience to Church-Governours
is.</P>
<P>But then Obedience to the Church of <HI>England</HI> is
not an universal Duty incumbent on all Christians, but
onely on those, which are, or ought to live, in Obe∣dience
to this particular Church: for the particular ex∣ercises
of Church-Authoritie and Jurisdiction is consi∣ned
within certain limits, as of necessitie it must be; and
though all <HI>Orthodox</HI> Churches must live in Communion
with each other, yet no particular Church can pretend
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
to any original Authority over another Church, or
the Members of it, as is the constant Doctrine of Pro∣testants,
in opposition to the Usurpations of the Church
of <HI>Rome.</HI> But I perceive Sir you know no difference be∣tween
the Authority and Power, and the Communion
of the Church.</P>
<P><HI>But you add,</HI> If it be, then as he who is not admitted
into this Church, is no Member of the Catholick, and has
no right to the benefits of being a Member of Christs Body:
so is it with every one, who is excluded by Church-Censures,
though excommunicated for a slight contempt or neglect, nay,
for a wrongful cause.</P>
<P>Truly Sir, I know not how any man is admitted
into the Church of <HI>England,</HI> any otherwise than as he
is admitted into the whole Catholick Church, <HI>viz,</HI> by
Baptism, which does not make us Members of any par∣ticular
Church, but of the Universal Church, which
Obliges us to Communicate with that part of the Ca∣tholick
Church wherein we live; and whoever lives
in <HI>England,</HI> and renounces Communion with the
Church of <HI>England,</HI> is a Schismatick from the Catho∣lick
Church.</P>
<P>And whoever is Excommunicated from one sound
part of the Catholick Church, is Excommunicated from
the whole. But then, there is this difference between
Excommunication and Schism; the first is a Judicial
Sentence, the second is a Mans own Choice; the first
is not valid unless it be inflicted for a just cause, the se∣cond
is always valid, and does in its own nature cut
Men off from all Communion with Christs Body. I say
in its own Nature, for I will not pretend to determine
the final States of Men, for I know not what gracious
allowances God will make for some Schismaticks, no
more than I do what favour he may allow to other Sin∣ners.</P>
<P><PB N="8" REF="6"/>
<HI>But you proceed.</HI> If it be no part of the Divine Cove∣nant,
then a Man that lives here may be a true Member of
the Catholick Church, though he is not in Communion with this
Sound Church.</P>
<P>This is another Horn of your formidable Dilemma.
If Obedience to the Authoritie and Censures of the par∣ticular
National Church of <HI>England</HI> is no part of the
Divine Covenant, then those Baptized Christians, who
live in <HI>England,</HI> are not bound to the Communion of
the Church of <HI>England,</HI> and may be Catholick Christians
for all that. As if because the Subjects of <HI>Spain</HI> are not
bound to obey the King of <HI>England,</HI> therefore English
Men are not bound to obey him neither, but may be
very good Subjects for all that.</P>
<P>We are bound by the Divine Law, to live in Commu∣nion
with all true Catholick Churches, and to obey the
Governours of the Church wherein we live; and there∣fore
though Obedience to the Church of <HI>England</HI> be not
a Law to all the World, yet it is a Law to all English Chri∣stians
inhabiting in this Church. But your way of argu∣ing
is, as if a Man should say, It is a Divine Law to obey
Civil Magistrates, but there is no Divine Law that all
the World should obey the King of <HI>England, France</HI> or
<HI>Spain,</HI> therefore French or English Subjects are not bound
to obey their own Prince. Oh what comfortable Do∣ctrine
is this to some Men!</P>
<P><HI>You proceed.</HI> But you will say (which I think is not
much to the question) that he ought to Communicate, if Com∣munion
may be had.</P>
<P>Yes, I do say this; and I believe by this time you see,
or at least others will see, that it is much to the questi∣on.</P>
<P>But then Query, whether the Dissenters may not reply, that
they are ready to Communicate, if the Communion be not clog'd
with some things, which are no part of the Divine Covenant.</P>
<P><PB N="9" REF="6"/>
Yes, they may replie so if they please, or <HI>Anonymus</HI>
for them; but whoever does it, the replie is very weak
and impertinent. It is weak, because Obedience to Au∣thority,
in all lawful things, is in a large notion part of the
Divine Covenant: And it is very impertinent, because
the Supposition of Communicating, <HI>where Communion
may be had,</HI> supersedes that Query. For Communion
cannot be had, where there are any sinful Terms of
Communion: and though I assert, that the Church must
be founded on a Divine Covenant, I never said, that no∣thing
must be enjoyned by the Church, but what is ex∣press'd
in that Covenant. A Corporation, which is foun∣ded
upon a Royal Charter, you know, may have Autho∣ritie
to make By-Laws, which shall oblige all the Mem∣bers
of it, and so are Terms of Communion with it; and
yet it is the Charter, not these By-Laws, whereon the
Corporation is founded. I was not concerned to Ex∣amine
the Terms of Communion, (that is, and will be
done by other hands) but, supposing nothing Sinful
in our Communion, whether all Christians, that live in
this Church, are not bound to live in Communion with
it.</P>
<P><HI>Q.</HI> 3. Your next Query concerns the Derivation of
Church-Power from Christ himself, without any im∣mediate
Derivation from other Church-Governours;
which does not at all concern my Doctrine of Church-Communion;
for whether it be so or so, still we are
bound to maintain Communion with all sound parts of
the Catholick Church; so Church-Authoritie be Deri∣ved
from Christ any way, it is well enough, but then
we must be sure that it is so: and if Christ have appoin∣ted
no ordinarie way for this, but by the hands of
Men, who received their Authoritie immediately from
himself, I know not who can appoint any other
way.</P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="7"/>
But may not a Lay-man preach the Gospel and ga∣ther
a Church in a Heathen Country, where there is
none of the Clergy to do it? I suppose he may; and if
you please to consult the Vindication of the Defence of
Dr. <HI>Stilling fleets</HI> Unreasonableness of Separation, <HI>p.
331, &amp;c.</HI> you will finde this case largely deba∣ted.</P>
<P>But it seems it doth not satisfie you, that this be al∣lowed
onely in case of Necessity, for then up start two o∣ther
Queries.</P>
<P>1. Whether this will not put the being of our Church up∣on
a very hazardous issue, and oblige your self to prove, that
it was a true Church before the Reformation?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> This is no hazard at all, for the Church of <HI>En∣gland</HI>
was certainly a true, though a corrupt, Church be∣fore
the Reformation, as the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> is at this
day. A true Church is that which has every thing Es∣sential
to the being of a Church, though mixt with such
other Corruptions, as make its Communion dangerous
and sinful, as a Diseased Man is a true Man; and remove
these Corruptions, and then it is not onely a true, but a
sound Church, as the Church of <HI>England</HI> is at this day.
And if you will not allow this, I doubt, Sir, all private
Christians will be at as great a loss for their Baptism, as
the Church will be for Orders. But the case of a True
and Sound and Catholick Church,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Vindicat. <HI>p.</HI> 64. &amp;c.</NOTE> if you please, you
may see Stated in the same Book to which I referred you
before.</P>
<P>And thus your second Query is answered, that
though this Church was Antichristian before the Re∣formation,
yet there was not the same Necessity for
private Christians to usurp the Ministerial Office with∣out
a regular Authoritie, as there is for a Lay-man in
a Heathen Nation, because an Antichristian, that is, the
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
most corrupt Church, retains the Power of Orders, as
well as of Sacraments.</P>
<P>As for that Independent Principle, that Christ has in∣stituted
a Power in the Church to ordain her own Offi∣cers,
you may see it Examined in the Defence of Dr. <HI>Still.
Vnr. of Sep.</HI> p. 306, &amp;c.</P>
<P>But what now is all this to me? I don't charge our Dis∣senters
with Schism from the Invalidity of their Orders,
but for their causeless and sinful Separation. Let us sup∣pose,
that they have no need of any Orders, or that such
Orders as they have are good, or that they had Episco∣pal
Orders, and were Governed by Bishops of their own,
as the Donatists were, yet they would be never the less
Schismaticks for that, while they separate from the
Church of <HI>England,</HI> and from each other. If Orders be
necessary, and they have no Orders, then they are no
Churches at all; if they have true Orders, and are true
Churches, but yet divide Christian Communion by Se∣parating
from any Sound part of the Christian Church,
they are Schismaticks.</P>
<P>4. <HI>Q</HI> Whether from the Supposition, that there ought
to be but one Church-Covenant throughout the Catholick
Church, that there cannot be one true Church within another,
and that the Nature of Catholick-Communion is such, that
one ought to be ready to Communicate with any Sound
Church, from which one is not hindred by reason of the Di∣stance
of Place? it do's not follow.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Fair and Softly! let us first consider the Suppo∣sitions,
before we consider what follows from them; for
you have so mis-represented, so eurtailed these Proposi∣tions,
and so mixt and blended things of a different Na∣ture,
that it is necessarie to restore them to their true
Sense and proper Place again, before we can tell what
follows.</P>
<P>I asserted, that the Christian Church is founded upon
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
a Divine Covenant, and since God hath made but one
Covenant with mankind in Christ Jesus, therefore there
can be but one Christian Church throughout the World,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Resol. of Cases, <HI>p.</HI> 8.</NOTE>
founded on this one Covenant.</P>
<P><HI>Having explained the general notion of</HI> Church-Com∣munion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 10.</NOTE>
which signifies no more than Church-Fellowship and
Society, that to be in Communion with the Church is to be
a Member of the Church, <HI>I came to enquire, what made a
Separate Church.</HI> For if there be but one Church and one
Communion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 19.</NOTE> of which all true Christians and Christian Chur∣ches
are or ought to be Members, then those Churches, which
are not Members of each other, are Separate Churches.
<HI>And for a fuller explication of this,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 20.</NOTE> <HI>I observed several
things.</HI></P>
<P><HI>I.</HI> That there must be but one Church in one Place. Be∣cause
there is no other Rule of Catholick-Communion, but to
Communicate in all Religious Offices, and all Acts of Govern∣ment
and Discipline, with those Christians with whom they
live. For to Renounce the Ordinary Communion of Christi∣ans,
or true Christian Church, is to divide the Vnity and
Communion of the Church; and to withdraw our selves from
Ordinary Communion with the Church in which we live,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 21.</NOTE> in∣to
distinct and separate Societies for Worship, is to Renounce
their Communion, and when there is not a necessary cause for
it, is a Schismatical Separation.</P>
<P><HI>And a little after I added,</HI> If all Christians are Members
of the one Body of Christ, nothing can justifie the distin∣ction
of Christians into several Churches, but onely such a di∣stance
of place, as makes it necessary and expedient to put
them under the Conduct and Government of several Bishops,
for the greater Edification of the Church in the more easie and
regular Administration of Discipline. And therefore nothing
can justifie the gathering a Church out of a Church, and di∣viding
Neighbour-Christians into distinct Communions.
<HI>Now then let us consider what follows.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="8"/>
1. <HI>You say,</HI> either that the French Protestants have
no church here, but are Schismaticks in not Communicating
with ours; Or that ours is guilty of Schism, in making the
Terms of Communion so streight, that it is not the Duty of
of every one (though a licensed Stranger) to Communicate
with this Church.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> If any Foreign Church among us, which by
Royal Favour is allowed the Observation of their
own Discipline and Rules of Worship, Renounce Com∣munion
with the Church of <HI>England,</HI> or Communicate
with our Separatists, she is Schismatical her self; as
the Protestant Churches in <HI>France, Geneva,</HI> or <HI>Holland</HI>
would be, should they do the like. But if there be any
reason to allow those Foreigners, which are among us,
to Form and Model their Congregations according to
the Rules of their own Churches to which they original∣ly
belong, this is no more a Schism, than there is be∣tween
the Protestant Churches of <HI>France</HI> and <HI>England,</HI>
which own each others Communion.</P>
<P>A bare Variety of Rites and Ceremonies makes no
Schism between Churches; our Church pretends not
to give Laws to other Churches, in such matters, but
leaves them to their Liberty, as she takes her own:
and why an Ecclesiastical Colony may not for great
reasons be Transplanted into another Church, as well
as a Civil Colony into another Kingdom, while they
live in Communion with each other, I cannot tell. It
is a different thing to gather a Church out of a Church,
and to Transplant some Members of one Church into a∣nother
(maintaining the same Communion, though with
some peculiar an different usages) with the consent of
the Church to which they come.</P>
<P>The case of Strangers and Natives has always been
accounted very different, both upon a Religious and Ci∣vil
account: Every particular National Church has
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
Authority over her own Members, to direct and Go∣vern
her own Communion, and prescribe the Rules of
Worship; but as she does not Impose upon other
Churches at a distance, so she may allow the same li∣berty
to the Members of such Foreign Churches, when
they live within her Jurisdiction, without breach of
Communion: for tho the Communion of the whole
Christian Church is but one, and all true Catholick
Churches are Members of each other, yet the Authori∣ty
and Jurisdiction is different; every Church challeng∣ing
a peculiar Authority, which it exerciseth in its
own Communion; and therefore for the Church of
<HI>England</HI> to suffer Foreign Churches to observe their
own Customs and Usages, is not to allow of distinct
and separate Communions in her own Bowels, (which
were Schismatical,) but onely to exempt such Con∣gregations
of Strangers from her particular Jurisdiction,
and to leave them to the Government and Authority of
the Church to which they belong.</P>
<P>There was no such thing indeed allowed in the
Primitive Church, as distinct Congregations of Foreig∣ners
under a different Rule and Government; and it
were very desirable, that all Christians who have oc∣casion
to live in other Countries, would conform to
all the innocent and laudable customs of the Church
where they sojourn, which seems most agreeable to Ca∣tholick
Communion; but yet distinct Congregations of
Foreigners, who own the Communion of our Church,
tho they observe the customs of their own, are not
Schismatical, as the Separate Conventicles of Dissenters
are.</P>
<P>2. <HI>But</HI> does it not follow from the obligation to com∣municate,
or to be ready to communicate with any true
Church where distance does not hinder, that a Member of
the Church of <HI>England</HI> is not obliged to constant Commu∣nion
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>
with that Church, but may occasionally communicate
with the French Church, nay with Dissenters too, if he be∣lieves
that any of their Congregations is a true Member of
the Catholick Church?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> This is a great Mastery of Wit, to turn my
own Artillery upon me. I prove the Dissenters to be
Schismaticks, because they set up a Church within a
Church, whereas there ought to be but one Church and
one Communion in one place, every Christian being
bound to Communicate with the sound part of the
Catholick Church in the place wherein he lives; for
according to the Laws of Catholick Communion, no∣thing
but distance of place can suspend our obligation
to actual Communion; Hence you conclude, that we
must Communicate with Schismaticks, if there be any
among us, or so near to us, that distance does not hin∣der
our Communion. But you should consider, that
our obligation to Catholick Communion does equally
oblige us to renounce the Communion of Schismaticks
whether at home or abroad; and tho we should allow
them to be true Churches, yet if Schismatical, they are
not Catholick Churches, and therefore not the objects of
Catholick-Communion.</P>
<P>But however, we may lawfully Communicate with
the French Church that is among us, as occasion
serves. Yes, no doubt we may, because they are in
Communion with us. But then follows the Murder∣ing
consequence, <HI>that a Member of the Church of</HI> Eng∣land
<HI>is not bound to a constant Communion with her.</HI> I
pray, why so? every Member, as a Member, is in
constant Communion;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Resol. of Cases, <HI>p.</HI> 10.</NOTE> for to be in Communion with
a Church, is to be a Member of it, as I pro∣ved
at large: but then Church-Communion does
not primarily respect a Particular but the Universal
Church,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 13.</NOTE> and therefore it is no interruption of our
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>
Communion with the Church of <HI>England</HI> to Commu∣nicate
actually with any Church, which is in Commu∣nion
with her: for as all Christians, who are neither
Hereticks nor Schismaticks, are Members of the Ca∣tholick
Church, so they are in Communion with the
Catholick Church, and every sound part of it. The
State of Communion is constant with the whole Ca∣tholick
Church, the acts of Communion are performed
sometimes in one part of it, sometimes in another, as
our presence, abode, or occasions, require; and thus
it is possible actually to Communicate with the French
Church, either in <HI>England</HI> or out of <HI>England,</HI> without
interrupting our Communion with the Church of <HI>Eng∣land;</HI>
for the Communion is one and the same in all
Christian Churches, which are in Communion with each
other, though they may observe different Rites and
Modes of Worship.</P>
<P>And this I suppose is a Sufficient answer to that o∣ther
untoward consequence, that if the Members of the
Church of <HI>England</HI> may occasionally Communicate
with the French Church, <HI>then Constant Commnnion is not
always a Duty, where occasional Communion is lawful;</HI> I
suppose, because we are not bound to a constant a∣ctual
or presential Communion with the French
Church, though we may occasionally Communicate
with it.</P>
<P>But certainly, Sir, Had you ever considered, what I
discourst about constant and occasional Communion, you
would not have made such an Objection as this: For this
is a Modern distinction, which has no sence at the bottom,
as I plainly shewed. But however, by constant Com∣munion,
our Dissenters understand the performing the
Acts of Communion, always or ordinarily in the same
Church; and by occasional Communion, performing the
Acts of Communion sometimes, or as occasion serves, in
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
another Church; now with respect to this Notion of
constant or occasional Communion, as it signifies the
constant and ordinary, or the Occasional Acts of Com∣munion,
must that question be understood, <HI>whether Con∣stant
Communion he a Duty, where Occasional Communion
is Lawful;</HI> the meaning of which question is this, whe∣ther
when other reasons and circumstances determine
my Personal Communion Ordinarily to one Church,
it be not my Duty to Communicate ordinarily with that
Church, if I can lawfully Communicate sometimes with
it: and there being no other reason to justifie non-Com∣munion
with any Church with which I am bound for
other reasons Ordinarily to Communicate, but onely
Sinful Terms of Communion, and there being no Co∣lour
for such a Pretence, where occasional Communion
is acknowledged Lawful, (for Sinful Terms of Com∣munion
make occasional as well as constant Acts of
Communion Sinful) I hence conclude, that it is a neces∣sary
Duty to Communicate constantly or ordinarily
with that Church in which I live, if it be Lawful
to Communicate occasionally, or sometimes, with
it.</P>
<P>But if any Man will be so perverse as to understand
this Question, as you now do, not of the Communion
of a Church which for other reasons we are bound to
Communicate Ordinarily with, but of any Church
with which I may Lawfully Communicate as occasion
serves, it makes it an absurd and senseless Proposition, to
say, that constant Communion (by that meaning pre∣sential
and personal Communion) is always a Duty,
where occasional Communion is lawful. For at this rate,
if occasional Communion with the Protestant Church∣es
of <HI>France, Geneva, Holland, Germany,</HI> be Lawful,
it becomes a necessary Duty for me to Communicate
always personally and presentionally with all these
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>
Churches at the same time, which no man can do, who
can be present but in one place at a time. But yet thus
far the Proposition holds universally true, that whatever
Church I can occasionally Communicate with without
Sin, I am also bound to Communicate constantly with,
whenever such reasons, as are necessarie to determine
my Communion to a particular Church, make it my Du∣tie
to do so. And no man in his Wits ever understood
this Question in any other sense.</P>
<P><HI>But this you think cannot be my meaning; For</HI> accor∣cording
to me, no Man is obliged to be a Member of one Sound
Church more than another, provided the distance is not so
great, but that he may Communicate with both.</P>
<P>It is wonderful to me, Sir, how you should come to fa∣sten
so many absurd Propositions upon me; and I would
desire of you for the future, if you have no regard to
your own Reputation, yet upon Principles of Com∣mon
Honesty, not to write so hastily, but to take some
time to understand a Book, before you undertake to con∣fute
it.</P>
<P>Where do I say, <HI>that no man is Obliged to be a Member
of one Sound Church more than of another?</HI> I assert in∣deed,
that no Baptized Christian is a Member of any par∣ticular
Church, considered meerly as particular, but is a
Member of the universal Church, and of all sound Ortho∣dox
Churches, as parts of the Universal Church. This
puts him into a State of Communion with the whole
Church, without which he cannot be properly said to
perform any Act of Church-Communion, though he
should join in all the Acts and Offices of Christian
worship: But is there no difference between being a
Member of the Universal Church, and of all particular
Churches, which are Parts and Members of the Uni∣versal
Church, and <HI>not to be Obliged to be a Member of
one Sound Church more than of another?</HI> The first sup∣poses,
<PB N="19" REF="11"/>
that every Christian, whatever particular Church
he actually Communicates in, is a Member of the whole
Christian Church, and of all particular Sound Churches;
the second supposes the quite contrary, that Christians
are so Members of one Church, as they are not of ano∣ther;
that constant Communion in a particular Church
confines their Church-Membership to that particular
Church in which they Communicate.</P>
<P>So that the question is not, what Church I must be
a Member of; for every Christian is a Member of the
whole Church, not meerly of this or that particular
Church; but what particular Church I must Commu∣nicate
in: now our Obligation to Communicate in a
certain particular Church, results from the place where∣in
we live; The Church in which we were Born and
Baptized, and have our Ordinary abode and Residence,
the Church which is incorporated into the State of
which we are Natural Subjects, if it be a true and sound
Christian Church, Challenges our Communion and
Obedience.</P>
<P>Now in the same place, there never can be any Com∣petition
between two Churches, because there must be
but one Church in the same place, and therefore there
can be no dispute in what Church we must constantly
Communicate, which must be the Church in which we
live.</P>
<P>But is there not a <HI>French,</HI> and a <HI>Dutch,</HI> as well as an
<HI>English</HI> Church in <HI>London,</HI> and since distance of place does
not hinder, may we not choose, which of these we will or∣dinarily
Communicate with?</P>
<P>I answer no, we have onely the Church of <HI>England</HI>
in <HI>England.</HI> The <HI>French</HI> Church is in <HI>France,</HI> and the
<HI>Dutch</HI> Church is in <HI>Holland,</HI> though there is a <HI>French</HI>
and <HI>Dutch</HI> Congregation allowed in <HI>London.</HI> These Con∣gregations
belong to their own Original Churches,
<PB N="20" REF="12"/>
and are under their Government and Censures; but there
is no Church-Power and Authority in <HI>England,</HI> but on∣ly
of the Church of <HI>England,</HI> and therefore though we
may occasionally Communicate with the <HI>French</HI> Con∣gregation,
our Obligation to constant Communion is
with the Church of <HI>England,</HI> which alone has Authori∣ty
and Jurisdiction in <HI>England</HI> to require our Commu∣nion
and Obedience: one particular Church is distin∣guisht
from another not by a distinct and separate
Communion, which is Schismatical, but by distinct
Power and Jurisdiction; and that Church within whose
Jurisdiction we live, can onely Challenge our Commu∣nion;
and I suppose no Man will say, that in this sence,
we live in the <HI>French</HI> or <HI>Dutch</HI> Church, because there is
a <HI>French</HI> and <HI>Dutch</HI> Church allowed among us.</P>
<P>5. <HI>Your next Query is,</HI> Whether a true Christian,
though not visibly admitted into Church-Communion, where
he wants the Means, has not a virtual Baptism in the
Answer of a good Conscience towards God, according to 1.
<HI>Peter,</HI> 2. 21.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> What this concerns me, I cannot tell. I speak
onely of the Necessity of Visible Communion in Visible
Members, you put a question, whether the want of
Visible Admission by Baptism, when it can't be had,
may not be supplied with the answer of a good Con∣science
towards God. I hope in some cases it may,
though I do not hope this from what St. <HI>Peter</HI> saies,
who onely speaks of that Answer of a good Conscience,
which is made at Baptism, not of that, which is made
without it. But what God will accept of in this case, is
not my business to determine; unbaptized Persons are no
Visible Members of the Church, and therefore not ca∣pable
of Visible Communion, and therefore not concer∣ned
at all in this dispute.</P>
<P>6. Query, Why a profest Atheist, who has been Bapti∣zed,
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>
and out of Secular Interest continues a Communicant
with this Church, is more a Member of the Catholick Church
than such as are above described.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Neither Atheists nor Schismaticks are Mem∣bers
of the Catholick Church. But this is a vile insinu∣ation
against the Governours and Government of our
Church, as if profest Atheists were admitted to Com∣munion.
Though possibly there may be some Atheists,
yet I never met yet with one, who would profess him∣self
an Atheist. If I should, I assure you, I would not
admit him to Communion, and I hope there is no Mi∣nister
of the Church of <HI>England</HI> would; and I am sure,
no Man, who had any kindness for the Church, with
which he pretends to hold Communion, would ask such
a question.</P>
<P>7. Query. Whether as the Catholick Church is compared
to a Body of Men incorporated by one Charter should upon
supposition of a possibility of the forfeiture of the Charter to
the whole Body, by the Miscarriages of any of the Officers,
does it likewise follow that the Miscarriages of any of the
Officers, or the Church Representative, as I remember
Bishop <HI>Sanderson</HI> calls the Clergy, may forfeit the Privi∣ledges
given by Christ to his Church, or at least may su∣spend
them? As suppose a Protestant Clergy taking their
Power to be as large as the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> claim'd,
should deny the Laity the Sacraments, as the Popish did in
<HI>Venice,</HI> and here in King <HI>Johns</HI> time, during the Interdicts,
<HI>quid inde operatur?</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Just as much as this Query does, the reason of
which I cannot easily guess. I asserted indeed, that as
there is but one Covenant on which the Church is foun∣ded,
so there can be but one Church to which this Co∣venant
belongs; and therefore those, who divide and
separate themselves from this one Body of Christ,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Resol. of Cases, <HI>p. 8. &amp;c.</HI></NOTE> for∣feit
their right to this Covenant, which is made onely
<PB N="22" REF="13"/>
with the one Body of Christ; which I illustrated by
the instance of a Charter granted to a particular Corpo∣ration,
which no Man had any interest in, who divi∣ded
himself from that Corporation to which this Char∣ter
was granted: but what is this to forfeiting a Char∣ter
by the Miscarriages of Officers? I doubt Sir, your
Head has been Warmed with Quo Warranto's, which
so affect your Fancy, that you can Dream of nothing
else.</P>
<P>I was almost afraid, when your hand was in, I
should never have seen an end of these Questions; and I
know no more reason, why you so soon left off asking
Questions, than why you askt any at all; for I would
undertake to ask five hundred more, as pertinent to the
business as most of these. You have not indeed done
yet, but have a reserve of particular Queries; but gene∣ral
Queries are the most formidable things, because it is
harder to find what they relate to, than how to Answer
them.</P>
<P>You have three sets of Queries relating to three seve∣ral
Propositions, besides a parting blow of four Queries
relating to my Text.</P>
<P>The first Proposition you are pleased to question me
about is this, <HI>That our Saviour made the Apostles and
their Successors Governours of his Church, with promise
to be with them to the end of the World.</HI> Which I al∣ledged
to prove, that when the Church is called <HI>the
Body of Christ,</HI> it does not signifie a confused multitude
of Christians, but a regular Society under Order and
Government.</P>
<P>Now Sir, is this true or false? if it be false, then
the Church is not a governed Society, is not a Body,
but a confused heap and multitude of Independent In∣dividuals,
which is somewhat worse than Independent
Churches. If it be true, why do you ask all these
<PB N="23" REF="13"/>
Questions, unless you have a mind to confute our Savi∣our,
and burlesque his Institutions: but since I am con∣demned
to answer questions, I will briefly consider them.</P>
<P>1. Whether our Saviours promise of Divine Assistance,
did not extend to all the Members of the Church, consider∣ing
every man in his respective station and capacity, as well
as the Apostles, as Church-Governours? For which you may
compare St. <HI>John</HI> with St. <HI>Matthew.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> No doubt but there are promises, which relate to
the whole Church, and promises which belong to parti∣cular
Christians, as well as promises which relate peculi∣arly
to the Apostles and Governours of the Church, in
the exercise of their Ministerial Office and Authority:
but what then? Christ is with his Church, with his Mi∣nisters,
with particular Christians, to the end of the
World, but in a different manner, and to different pur∣poses;
and yet that promise there is peculiarly made to
the Apostles, including their Successors also; for the A∣postles
themselves were not to continue here to the end
of the World, but an Apostolical Ministry was.</P>
<P>2. <HI>Therefore Query,</HI> Whether it signifies any thing to
say there is no promise to particular Churches, provided
there be to particular Persons, such as are in charity with
all Men, and are ready to communicate with any Church
which requires no more of them, than what they conceive to
be their duty; according to the Divine Covenant?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> It seems to me to be a harder Query, what
this Query means; or how it concerns that Authority,
which our Saviour has given to his Apostles for the
Government of the Church; to which this Query re∣lates.
I asserted indeed, that Christ hath made no
Covenant with any particular, but onely with the U∣niversal
Church, which includes particulars as Mem∣bers
of it; nor has he made any promise to particular
Persons, but as Members of the Church, and in Com∣munion
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>
with it, when it may be had upon lawful terms.
Whoever breaks the Communion of the Church
without necessary reason, tho he may in other things
be a very good natur'd man, yet he has not true Chri∣stian
Charity, which unites all the Members of the
same Body in one Communion; and tho the Church
may prescribe Rules of Worship, which are not ex∣pressed
in the Divine Covenant, this will not justifie
a Separation, if she commands nothing which is for∣bid;
for the very Authority Christ has committed to
his Ministers, requires our obedience to them in things
lawful; and if Men will adhere to their own private
Fancies in opposition to Church-Authority, they are
guilty of Schism, and had best consider, whether such
pride and opinionativeness will be allowed for ex∣cuse.</P>
<P>3. Whether if the promise you mention be confined to
the Apostles, as Church-Governours, it will not exclude the
Civil Power.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> There are peculiar promises made to Church-Governours,
and to Civil Magistrates; their Autho∣rity
and Power is very distinct, but very consi∣stent.</P>
<P>4. What was the extent of the promise, whether it was
to secure the whole Church, that its Governours should
never impose unlawful Terms of Communion, or that there
never be a defection of all the Members of the Catholick
Church, but that there should always be some true Mem∣bers?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> The promise is, that Christ will be with be them
in the discharge of their Ministry, and Exercise of their
Power, and this is all I know of the matter; our Saviour
gave them Authority to Govern the Church, and this
was to last to the end of the World, as long as there is any
<PB N="25" REF="14"/>
Church on Earth, which is all I cited it for, and so much
it certainly proves.</P>
<P><HI>The Second Proposition: you raise Queries on, is this.</HI>
'Tis absurd to gather a Church out of a Church of Baptized
Christians.</P>
<P>This I do indeed assert, that since the Church is
founded on a Divine Covenant, and to be in Covenant
with God, and to be Members of his Church, is the same
thing; therefore Baptism whereby we are received in∣to
Covenant with God, makes us Members of the
Church also; and this makes it very absurd, to gather
a Church out of Churches of Baptized Christians, which
supposes that they were not a Church before: instead
of considering the reason, whereon this is founded, as
every honest Writer should do, you onely put a perverse
Comment on it.</P>
<P><HI>By which</HI> (say you) <HI>I suppose you mean, That Men
ought not to Separate from such, and live in a distinct
Church-Communion from any Church of Baptized Christi∣ans;
which I conceive needs explaining.</HI> But if this were
true, it were plain enough, but the fault is, that it is
not true; for we may Separate from any Church of
Baptized Christians, if their Communion be Sinful;
which justifies a Separation from the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI>
and answers your two first Queries.</P>
<P>But indeed the Proposition, as asserted by me, does
not so much as concern a Separation from a Church,
let the cause be what it will, just or unjust. For the
Independents, who are the Men for gathering Church∣es,
do not own, that they Separate from any Church,
but that they form themselves into a Church-State,
which they had not before, and which no Christians,
according to their Principle, have, who are not
Members of Independent Churches. Baptism, they
acknowledge, makes Men Christians at large, but not
<PB N="26" REF="15"/>
Church-Members, which I shewed must needs be very
absurd, if the Church be a Body and Society of Men
founded on a Divine Covenant; for then Baptism, which
admits us into Covenant with God, makes us Members
of the Church; and they may as well rebaptize Christi∣ans,
as form them into new Church-Societies.</P>
<P>This I suppose may satisfie you, how impertinent all
your Queries are under this head.</P>
<P>Your two first concern the Separation from the
Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> which was not made upon Indepen∣dent
Principles, because they were no Church, but be∣cause
they were a corrupt Church.</P>
<P>3. <HI>Whether every Bishoprick in England be not so ma∣ny
Churches within the National. Ans.</HI> Every Bishop∣rick
is a distinct Episcopal Church, and the Union of
them in one National Communion, makes them not so
many Churches, within a National, but one National
Church; which you may see explained at large in the
Defence of Dr. <HI>Still. Vnr.</HI> of Separation.</P>
<P>4. And therefore Independent and Presbyterian
Churches are indeed within the National (Churches
within a Church, which is Schismatical) but not one
National Church, as Bishopricks are.</P>
<P>5. And therefore tho we should allow them to have
the External Form and all the Essentials of a Church
(which is a very liberal grant) yet they are not in Catho∣lick
Communion, because they are Schismaticks.</P>
<P>6. And this is all I am to account for, that they are
not in Visible Communion with that one Church and
Body of Christ to which the promises are made. But
what allowances Christ will make for the mistakes of
honest well-meaning Men, who divide the Communi∣on
of the Church, I cannot determine. I can hope as
Charitably, as any Man, but I dare not be so Cha∣ritable,
as to make Church-Communion an indiffe∣rent
<PB N="27" REF="15"/>
thing, which is the great Bond of Christian Cha∣rity.</P>
<P>3dly. You take occasion for your next Queries, from
what I say of the Independent Church-Covenant; you
say, I <HI>suppose, that the Independents exclude themselves
from Catholick Communion, by requiring of their Members a
new contract, no part of the Baptismal vow.</HI></P>
<P>I prove indeed from their placing a Church-State in
a particular explicite Covenant between Pastor and
People, that they separate themselves from the whole
Body of Christians; for no other Christians, which are
not in Covenant with them, are Members of their
Church, nor can they be Members of any other
Church.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Resol. of Cases. <HI>p.</HI> 10. 32.</NOTE> And I proved that those are Separate Church∣es,
which are not Members of each other, and do not
own each others Members for their own. For the
Notion of Church-Communion consists in Church-Membership,
and therefore no Man is in Communion
with that Church of which he is no Member; and if
no Man can be a Member of a Church, but by such an
explicite Independent Covenant, then he is a Member
of no Church but that, with which he is in Covenant,
and consequently is in Communion with no Church,
but that particular Independent Congregation of which
he is a Member by a particular Covenant. And if those
be Schismaticks and Schismatical Churches, which are
not in Communion with each other, then all Indepen∣dents
must be Schismaticks, for they are in Communion
with none, but their own Independent Congregations.
Let us now hear your Queries.</P>
<P>Q. 1. Whether any Obstack to Catholick Communion
brought in by Men, may not be a means of depriving Men
of it, as well as Covenant or Contract?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Yes it may, but with this Material difference:
Other things hinder Communion as Sinful Terms of
<PB N="28" REF="16"/>
Communion, this Independent Covenant in its own
Nature Shuts up, Encloses, and breaks Christian
Communion into as many Separate Churches and
Communions, as there are Independent Congregations.
Sinful Terms of Communion are a just cause of Sepa∣ration;
an Independent Church-Covenant is a State
of Separation in its own Nature. The Communion of
the Church may be restored by removing those Sinful
Terms of Communion, but there can be no Catholick
Unity or Communion in the Church under Independen∣cy.</P>
<P>Q. 2. If it may, which I suppose you will not deny, will
you not then upon this account, make the Church you live
in more guilty than the Independents? Baptism you own
is the onely thing, which admits into the Catholick Church,
but they require no new Covenant at Baptism, <HI>Ergo,</HI> they
admit into the Church without any clog or hindrance of hu∣mane
Inventions.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Pray what comparison is there between the
Church of <HI>England</HI> and Independency? Whatever fault
the Church of <HI>England</HI> may be charged with, as to
its Rites and Ceremonies (which I will not now di∣spute
with you) yet all this is capable of a Remedy;
she may give occasion to Schism, if she imposes any
unlawful and Sinful Terms of Communion, but yet
the Frame and Essential constitution of the Church is
not Schismatical; but Independency is Schism in the
very notion of it, and an Independent Conventicle is
never capable of becoming a Member of the Catholick
Church.</P>
<P>But you say, <HI>I own that Baptism is the onely thing
which admits into the Catholick Church,</HI> i. e. which
makes us Members of the Universal Church, and all
sound parts of it, and that nothing else is necessary to
make a Church-Member. Very right! I do own this;
<PB N="29" REF="16"/>
but what is my owning this, to the Independents? For
they do not, and will not own it; they admit into their
Churches, not by Baptism, but by a Human and Vo∣luntary
Covenant, and will own none for Church-Members
but such. Baptism at most gives Men onely
a disposition to be Church-Members, but does not make
them Members of any Church.</P>
<P><HI>But they require no new Covenant at Baptism,</HI> ergo,
<HI>they admit into the Church without any clog or hindrance
of human Invention,</HI> that is, they admit to Baptism with∣out
any new Covenant: because Baptism does not, as they
believe, admit into the Church, <HI>ergo,</HI> they admit into
the Church without any clog of human Invention.
And yet Sir, I perceive you do not understand this
matter neither: for though what their practise is now
I cannot tell, yet according to their Principles, and
former Practise, though they required no new Covenant
of the Child to be Baptized, yet they would Baptize
no Children, but of such Parents, as were in Church-Covenant
with them, which is the same thing; and a
much greater clog to Baptism, than the Sign of the
Cross, which when I know your exceptions against, I
will consider them.</P>
<P>And now Sir, nothing remains of your First Letter,
but some few Queries relating to the meaning of my
Text. Your Three first Queries come onely to this,
whether every particular Church may not be called the
Body of Christ. I answer, no doubt but it may, and
yet Christ has but one Body, and all the sound Church∣es
in the World are but one Body, and must be but one
Communion. As you may see proved at large in the
Defence of Dr. <HI>Still.</HI> and the Vindication of that Defence,
and thither I refer you. But what you mean by Christs
<HI>Metaphorical Body,</HI> I confess, I cannot tell, and therefore
cannot answer that Question.</P>
<P><PB N="30" REF="17"/>
Your Fourth Query, concerns the nature of Schism,
which you would not have consist in dividing Com∣munion
through difference of Opinions, but through
want of Charity, because the Apostle say, that the
Members have the same care one of another. Now
methinks in the natural Body, should the Members
divide from each other, though they should pretend to
love one another dearly, they would not be thought to
have such care of one another, as the Members of the
same Body ought to have. The Application is easy,
and you may find this matter plainly stated in the De∣fence
to which I have so often referred you.</P>
<P>Thus Sir I have honestly answered all your Queries,
which you sent me in your First Letter, and which
you challenge me, and <HI>conjure me</HI> as a Protestant Di∣vine
to answer <HI>Categorically</HI> in your Second; whether
they were so very considerable as to deserve either to
be Printed or Answered, I leave the Reader to con∣sider.</P>
<P>Your Second Letter, though it be somewhat Pee∣vish,
yet creates me but little trouble. It has brought
forth but one Query, and half of that is already An∣swered.</P>
<P>Whether, if the nature of Catholick Communion re∣quires
a readiness to Communicate with any sound Church,
and yet a Church obliges us to Communicate with that
alone, while distance does not hinder the occasional and
frequent Communion with others, is not that Church guilty
of Schism in such an Injunction contrary to the nature of
Catholick-Communion?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> No Church can be so supposed to forbid Com∣munion
with any Church, which is in Communion
with her: and as for Schismatical Conventicles, which
you are pleased to call sound Churches, it is the Duty
of the Church to forbid all Communion with them,
<PB N="31" REF="17"/>
how near soever they be. For Catholick Communion
obliges us only to Communicate in the Catholick
Church, from whence Schismaticks have withdrawn
and separated themselves; and whoever Communicates
with Schismaticks, is in so doing a Schismatick.</P>
<P>Or at least, <HI>(as you proceed)</HI> is it not impossible,
that he who Communicates sometimes with one true
Church, sometimes with another, can be a Schismatick, or
any more than an Offender against a positive human
Law?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> If such true Churches be Schismatical, he that
Communicates with a Schismatical Church, is Guilty
of a Schismatical Act; and how is it possible, it
should be otherwise? Should a Man sometimes joyn
with his Princes Forces, and sometimes with his Ene∣mies,
and Fight sometimes on the one side, and some∣times
on the other, were he a Rebel or not? To be
sure he is a Rebel when he Fights against his Prince,
though sometimes he Fight for him. We may, and
ought as occasion serves to Communicate with any
Church, which is in Catholick Communion; but where
there are two opposite and separate Communions, to
Communicate with both, is like taking part on both
sides; and if one be in the right, and the other in the
wrong, such a man cannot be in the right al∣ways.</P>
<P>Well but however, <HI>he is no Schismatick, but only an
Offender against a positive human Law.</HI> Yes, certainly
he is a Schismatick, and an Offender, not meerly against
human positive Laws, but against the Unity of the
Church, and the Evangelical Laws of Catholick Com∣munion.</P>
<P><HI>But this mention of Law puts me in mind of a pas∣sage
or two at the beginning of your Preface. You
say,</HI> perhaps it's no absurdity to suppose, that Men may
<PB N="32" REF="18"/>
as well continue Members of the National Church, not∣withstanding
their breaking many positive Laws, made for
the outward management and ordering of it, though not
Fundamental and necessary to its being; as he who in∣curs
the penalty of any Statute of the Realm about Civil
affairs, may however be a sound Member of the State,
if he keep from Treason and other Capital Crimes.</P>
<P>Very right Sir! While Men continue in the Com∣munion
of the Church, they are Church-Members,
though they may be irregular, and guilty of some Acts
of Disobedience; but methinks it is a little absurd to
say, that those continue Members of the Church,
who separate from it: Schism and Separation from
the Church, is just what Treason and Rebellion is in
the State, and such persons by your own confession
cease to be sound Members.</P>
<P><HI>You add,</HI> Nay possibly, that there should be several
Religious Assemblies, living by different Customs and
Rules, and yet continuing Members of the National Church,
is not more inconsistent, than, that particular places should
have their particular Customs and By-Laws, differing
from the Common Law of the Land, without making a di∣stinct
Government.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> Whatever variety and difference in the Rules
of Worship in several Congregations, is consistent with
one Communion, may be granted, when the prudence
of Governours sees it fit and expedient. But Mr. <HI>Hum∣phry</HI>'s
project, which I perceive you are nibling at, of
making a National Church by an Act of Parliament,
which should declare Presbyterians, Independants, <HI>&amp;c.</HI>
to be Parts of the National Church, is certainly the
cunningest way of curing Schism, that ever was thought
on: but you may find that expedient for Union at
large considered in the Vindication of the Defence
of Dr. <HI>Still.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="33" REF="18"/>
And thus Sir I proceed to your Third Letter, and
here you run nothing but Dregs and Lees; and I hope
you will not think it any neglect of you, if I do not
answer you Paragraph by Paragraph, as I have done
your first Letter, there being little new in this, but
only a Repetition of your old Queries: and though
you know Repetitions are very <HI>convenient to lengthen a
Sermon,</HI> there is no need of such Arts to lengthen this
Answer, which is too long already.</P>
<P>Your first Charge upon me is, that I only amuse
People with Equivocal Words and Terms:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Letters 3. p. 16.</NOTE> that I play
with the words, <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>Schism;</HI> which had been no
fault, had I played the right way with them, that is, had
I ridiculed them, as you do, who think them words on∣ly
fit to be played with, who have found out a Church
without any Government, which is,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 12.</NOTE> only <HI>an Intreague
between Clergy-men on all sides,</HI> who will not allow
<HI>causeless Separation from a Sound part of the Catholick
Church</HI> to be Schism,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 17.</NOTE> but place Schism <HI>wholly in want of
Charity,</HI> and make it nothing else but some Divisions
and Contentions between the Members of the same
Church, who still live in Communion with one another;
a true Independent Notion to justifie causeless Separa∣tions.
Divisions in the Church are certainly very Sinful,
and a degree of Schism, as unnatural, as if the Mem∣bers
of the same Body should fight with each other,
while they are United to the same Body; but to divide
from the same Body is the perfection of Schism, unless
a quarrel be a Rent and Schism, but Separation be
none.</P>
<P>You desire me to define, what I mean by a Church,
when considered as Catholick and Universal, and when
taken in a more restrained sense. But this, I think I
have done already, if you had eyes to see it; and you
may find it done more largely in the Defence of Dr. <HI>Still.</HI>
<PB N="34" REF="19"/>
But would not any Man, who had ever seen this discourse,
which you undertake to confute, wonder to hear you
ask me;<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 18.</NOTE> <HI>whether a Man has a right to be of a particular
Church as he is a Christian;</HI> when the whole design of
that Tract is to prove, that every Christian by being so,
is a Member of the Catholick Church, and has a right
to Communicate with all sound parts of the Catholick
Church, and bound to Communicate with that part of
it, in which he lives?</P>
<P>In the next place you attempt to prove, that the
Influences and Operations of the Holy Spirit, are not
confined to the Visible,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 19.</NOTE> but Invisible Church: but not
to examine your proof of it, which is nothing to the
purpose, you may consider, that the Visible and Invi∣sible
Church on Earth are not two, but one Church;
not that every Member of the Visible Church is a
Member also of the Invisible, that is, every profest
Christian is not a true Believer; but whoever is not a
Member of the Visible Church, and does not live in
Communion with it, when it may be had, is not,
that we know of, a Member of the Invisible
Church.</P>
<P>We have no way to prove, that any Man is a Mem∣ber
of the Invisible, who is not a Member of the Visi∣ble
Church; and what we do not, and cannot know,
does not concern us; secret things belong to God, and
with him it becomes us to leave them. But this also
you may find more largely discourst in the Vindication
of the Defence.</P>
<P><HI>You urge the case of Pope</HI> Victor, <HI>who, as you say,</HI>
in a Council or full representative of that Church,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 21.</NOTE> ex∣communicated
the poor Asians <HI>upon the Paschal Contro∣versy.</HI>
And that each Church was far enough from own∣ing
each others Members for their own—What should the
poor Lay-Christians do in this divided State? could they
<PB N="35" REF="19"/>
not Communicate with both, or either, without danger of
Schism themselves?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.</HI> It is an easie matter to put hard Cases, almost
about any thing; and if a particular hard Case, which
either may possibly happen, or has sometimes happen∣ed,
is sufficient to overthrow a standing and general
Rule, and to confute the most plain and convincing
Evidence for it, there is nothing in Religion can be
firm and stable. In the very same manner Men Di∣spute
against the Being of a God, and a Providence,
against the necessity of Baptism, and the Lords Sup∣per,
against the Apostolical Power and Ministry, and
all Church-Government, against the necessity of Be∣lieving
many fundamental Articles of our Faith, be∣cause
many, otherwise very good Men, from the
Power and Prejudice of Education, or through weakness
of understanding, may be guilty of some damnable He∣resies.</P>
<P>But must there be no standing Laws or Rules, be∣cause
there may happen some hard and difficult Cases?
Does not humane Power make Provision against such
Cases by Courts of Chancery, or the Prerogative of the
Prince, and yet maintain the Authority and Sacredness
of Laws? And will we not allow God himself a Power
of Dispensing with Laws in hard Cases, without destroy∣ing
the Authority of his Laws? Is not Church-Com∣munion
a necessary Duty, because it may so happen,
that sometimes I cannot Communicate with any
Church? Is not Schism a very grievous and damning sin,
because it may happen, that Men may be unavoidably,
innocently, and without a Schismatical mind, engaged
in a Schism?</P>
<P>I have evidently proved the necessity of Church-Unity
and Communion, and the evil and danger of
Schism; and if you can answer the Scripture-Evidence
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
produced in this Cause, I will carefully consider it;
but it is no confutation of a plain Law, to urge hard
Cases against it, which will overthrow all Laws, that
ever were made. If you imagine, or can produce
any real Case, wherein it is almost impossible for the
Persons concerned to know, that they are guilty of
Schism, or to discover on which side the Schism lies,
or to avoid it without renouncing all Communion
with the Church, which course soever they take, I
leave all such Cases to God, who knows, when it is
fit to dispence with his own Laws; and will take care
of my own Duty according to Scripture-Rules, and
not hope to justifie the ordinary breach of known Laws
by some extraordinary Cases.</P>
<P>And yet the Case, which you propose, is not so un∣answerable
a difficulty, as you imagine. Several Coun∣cils
in <HI>Palestine,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Euseb.</HI> b. 5. cap. 23.</NOTE> in <HI>Rome,</HI> in <HI>Pontus,</HI> and other places,
Determine the Celebration of <HI>Easter</HI> on the day of the
Resurrection, not on the Fourteenth Day of the
Month, which was the Jewish Passover, (which di∣spute
you call <HI>a Mistake in Arithmetick,</HI> but for what
reason I know not) the Bishops of <HI>Asia</HI> at the same
time decree the observation of <HI>Easter</HI> on the Four∣teenth
Day, whatever Day of the week it fell on, ac∣cording
to the Ancient Observation of the <HI>Asian</HI>
Churches. Pope <HI>Victor</HI> upon this, writes to several
Bishops very bitterly against them, and was very de∣sirous
to have them Excommunicated,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>p. 24.</NOTE> and did as much
as in him lay, denounce the Sentence against them.</P>
<P>But this was ill resented by other Bishops in Com∣munion
with him; and particularly <HI>Ireneus</HI> wrote a
Letter to him about it, and earnestly disswades him
from it, and did prevent it from taking effect, if we
will believe <HI>Eusebius.</HI> So far is it from being true, as
you assert, that Pope <HI>Victor</HI> in a Council Excommu∣nicated
<PB N="37" REF="20"/>
the poor <HI>Asians;</HI> what he did was only his
own Act, which was displeasing to other Bishops, and
which he was forc't to undo. So that here was a great
deal of Heat and Warmth, and tendency towards a
Schism, but no Schism followed upon it, among the
Catholick Churches.</P>
<P>But suppose Pope <HI>Victor</HI> had Excommunicated the
<HI>Asian</HI> Churches, and this Excommunication had taken
effect, this could not make the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches Schis∣maticks:
for there is a great deal of difference between
being cast out of the Communion of a Church, and
forsaking the Communion of a Church. The first is
matter of censure, the second is our own choice; the
First is an Ecclesiastical Punishment, the Second when it
is causeless, is Schism.</P>
<P>So that had the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> Excommunicated
the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches, unless the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches upon
this, had made a Separation from the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI>
this Excommunication could not make them Schisma∣ticks,
and therefore any one might safely Communi∣cate
with them without partaking in a Schism.</P>
<P>Nor was it a just reason for the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches to
have renounced the Communion of the Church of
<HI>Rome,</HI> though they had been Excommunicated by
<HI>Victor;</HI> for this had been to do as ill a thing as <HI>Victor</HI>
had done, for no other reason, but because Pope <HI>Victor</HI>
had set them an example. And therefore we find
Saint <HI>Cyprian</HI> of another temper, when he and the
<HI>African</HI> Bishops were threatned in the same manner
by Pope <HI>Stephen,</HI> upon occasion of that warm Dispute
about rebaptizing Hereticks. At that very time, in his
Epistle to <HI>Jubaianus,</HI> he declares his resolution, not to
break Communion with any Church or Bishops upon
that account, and therefore not with Pope <HI>Stephen</HI>
himself, notwithstanding his rash and furious Censures.
<PB N="38" REF="21"/>
And concludes, that Patience and Forbearance was the
best Remedy in such Cases, and therefore upon this
occasion, he says, he wrote his Book <HI>de bono Patien∣tiae.</HI></P>
<P>Well, but if the Asiatick Churches were not Schis∣maticks,
yet Pope <HI>Victor</HI> had been a Schismatick, had
he Excommunicated the Churches of <HI>Asia,</HI> or with∣drawn
Communion from them. And this had made
the case of the <HI>Roman</HI> Christians very hard: for they
must either have suspended Communion with both
these divided Churches, and lived without the comfort
and advantages of Christian Communion; or they must
have rejected the Communion of their own Bishop,
and Churches, or have rejected the Communion of the
Churches of <HI>Asia,</HI> or have maintained Communion
with them both, that is, with two Separate Churches,
which according to my Principles, is to Communicate
in a Schism. If they Communicate with their own
Schismatical Bishop, this is to Communicate in a
Schism, by Communicating with a Schismatick; if
they Renounce his Communion, when he imposes no
new unlawful Terms of Communion upon them, this
is to Separate from a Sound and Orthodox Church, for
the sake of a Schismatical Bishop. If they Communicate
with the Churches of <HI>Asia,</HI> this is to break Communion
with their own Bishop, who has Excommunicated
them▪ if they separate from the Churches of <HI>Asia</HI> for
no other reason, but because they are unjustly Excom∣municated,
this is to Separate for an unjust cause,
which is a Schism; if they communicate with both,
they Communicate with two Separate Churches, and
therefore must be Schismaticks on one side or other. If
you can find any more difficulties in this matter, you
may. And yet after all this, I do believe the Christians
of <HI>Rome</HI> might have Communicated both with the <HI>Ro∣man</HI>
<PB N="39" REF="21"/>
and <HI>Asian</HI> Churches without Schism; and this I be∣lieve
upon these Principles, which I shall briefly explain,
and confirm.</P>
<P>1. That the Personal miscarriage of the Bishop in the
exercise of <HI>Ecclesiastical</HI> Censures, cannot involve his
whole Church in the guilt of Schism, though it may
make him a Schismatick: and certainly since Bishops
are but Men, and Subject to the like passions and in∣firmities,
that other men are, it would be a very hard
case, if his personal Schism should be imputed to the
whole Church.</P>
<P>Though the Bishop have the chief Authority in the
Church, yet it is hard to say, that every abuse of his Au∣thority
is the Act of the whole Church; and therefore
the Church may not be Schismatical, when the Bishop
is; and it is possible to Communicate with a Church,
whose Bishop is a Schismatick, without Communicating
in the Schism. And therefore though <HI>Victor</HI> had Schis∣matically
Excommunicated the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches, the
Christians of <HI>Rome</HI> at that time might have Communi∣cated
with the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> without partaking in
<HI>Victors</HI> Schism.</P>
<P>For, tho a particular Church-Society consists in that
Relation, which is between the Bishop and his Clergy
and People, yet it is possible, that the Bishop in the ex∣ercise
of his Authority may violate the Fundamental
Laws of Communion, on which the Christians of such
a Church unite into one Body and Society: and when
he does so, it being an abuse of his Episcopal Autho∣rity,
it is his personal fault, which cannot affect the
whole Church.</P>
<P>The case is very plain, where there is an Established
constitution in a Church (as it is in the Church of <HI>Eng∣land</HI>)
which obliges the Bishops as well as People.
For should any <HI>English</HI> Bishop require any thing of his
<PB N="40" REF="22"/>
Clergy or People, which is contrary to the Establish't
Laws and Canons of the Church, or should exercise
any Authority in Censures and Excommunications,
which is not allowed him by those Canons, this can
in no sense be called the Act of the Church, nor is any
one bound to obey him in it; and though such a Bi∣shop
should do any Schismatical Act, the Church is
not Schismatical, because he did not pursue the Laws
of the Church, in what he did, but gratified his own
Humour and Passion. If the Church indeed Unites
upon Schismatical Principles, as the <HI>Novatians</HI> and <HI>Do∣natists</HI>
did, whatever the Bishops do in pursuance of
such Principles is the Act of the Church, and if the Bi∣shops
be Schismaticks, the Church is so too; but when
there is nothing Schismatical in the Constitution of the
Church, the personal Schism of Bishops cannot make
their Churches Schismatical.</P>
<P>And though the Primitive Churches before the Em∣pire
turned Christian had not such a Firm and Legal
Constitution, as the Church of <HI>England</HI> now has, yet a
Constitution they had, which consisted either of Apo∣stolical
Rules handed down by Tradition, and confirmed
by long custom and usage, or the Canons of particular
Councils, which in ordinary cases made standing Laws
of Discipline and Government, and in extraordinary
cases provided for new Emergent difficulties; and ante∣cedently
to all these positive Constitutions, they were
all under the obligation of that great Law of Catho∣lick
Communion. So that the Government of the
Church since the Apostles days, was never so intirely
in the Bishops Breast, that what he did, should be
thought the Act of the Church, any farther than as
he complied with those Laws, by which the Church
was to be Governed: and therefore there was reason in
<PB N="41" REF="22"/>
those days to distinguish between the Act of the Bishop
and the Act of the Church.</P>
<P>As to shew you this particularly in the case before us.
The Church of <HI>Rome</HI> from the time of the Apostles had
observed <HI>Easter</HI> on the day of the Resurrection, which is
the first day of the week, or the Lords day, the <HI>Asian</HI>
Churches on the 14th day of the Month; and there∣fore
the Bishop of <HI>Rome,</HI> according to the Laws of that
Church, might require all the Members of his Church,
to observe <HI>Easter</HI> according to the usage of the Church
of <HI>Rome,</HI> and might regularly inflict Church-Censures
upon the obstinate and refractory; and this would be
accounted the Act of the Church, because it was in pur∣suance
of the Laws and Constitutions of it. But there
was no Canon, nor Custom in the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI>
to deny Communion to Foreign Churches, who ob∣served
their own Customs in this matter, and would
not conform to the Custom of the Church of <HI>Rome.</HI>
Nay, there was the Practise and Example of Former
Times against it; for <HI>Anicetus</HI> Bishop of <HI>Rome</HI> received
<HI>Polycarp,</HI> an <HI>Asian</HI> Bishop, to Communion, though they
could not agree about this matter. And therefore when
<HI>Victor</HI> Schismatically Excommunicated the <HI>Asian</HI>
Churches for this different observation of <HI>Easter,</HI> it
was his Personal Act, not the Act of the Church of
<HI>Rome,</HI> which had no such Law, and owned no such
Custom: and therefore though this might make Pope
<HI>Victor</HI> a Schismatick, it could not make the Church of
<HI>Rome</HI> Schismatical; the guilt went no farther than
<HI>Victors</HI> Person, unless other Persons voluntarily made
themselves guilty, by abetting and espousing the
Quarrel.</P>
<P>So that had <HI>Victor</HI> persisted in his Excommunica∣tion
of the <HI>Asiatick</HI> Churches, none had been guilty
of Schism but himself, and such as approved, and con∣sented
<PB N="42" REF="23"/>
to it, but the Body of the Clergy and People,
who had not consented unto it, had been Innocent,
and therefore any Catholick peaceable Christian, who
lived in <HI>Rome</HI> in those Days, might have Communica∣ted
with the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> without Schism.</P>
<P>The like may be said of the Quarrels and Contro∣versies
of particular Bishops, which have sometimes
ended in formal Schisms, and denouncing Excommu∣nication
against each other; which cannot make their
Churches Schismatical, any further than they take
part with their respective Bishops. For this is rather
a Personal Schism and Separation, than a Church
Schism: neither of them Separate from the Commu∣nion
of the Church, under the Notion of such a
Church, though they Separate from each others Com∣munion
upon some personal Quarrels.</P>
<P>This was the Case of St. <HI>Chrysostom</HI> and <HI>Epiphanius,</HI>
and some other Bishops in those days, which were Ca∣tholick
Bishops, and maintained Communion with the
Catholick Church, but yet Separated from each other,
which is a very great fault, as all Contentions and
Divisions in the Church are, but has not the Evil and
Destructive Nature of a Church Schism.</P>
<P>But you will say, can we Communicate with a
Church without Communicating with its Bishop? or
can we Communicate with a Schismatical Bishop, with∣out
Communicating in his Schism?</P>
<P>I Answer, Yes, we may Communicate with a Schis∣matical
Bishop, without Communicating in his Schism.
When Schism is his personal fault, our Communion
with him makes us no more guilty of it, than of any
other Personal fault, our Bishop is guilty of. While we
take care to Communicate with him in no Schismati∣cal
Act, no Man is bound to forsake the Communion
of the Church for the Personal faults of his Bishop.</P>
<P><PB N="43" REF="23"/>
So that the <HI>Roman</HI> Christians might Communicate
with the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> without Schism, notwith∣standing
Pope <HI>Victors</HI> Schismatical Excommunication
of the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches. And now the only difficulty
that remains is, whether the Christians of <HI>Rome</HI> might
have Communicated with the <HI>Asiatick</HI> Churches not∣withstanding
<HI>Victor</HI> had Excommunicated them, for if
they could not, then they must inevitably partake in
<HI>Victors</HI> Schism, if his sentence obliged them to deny
Communion to the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches. And in answer to
this we may consider.</P>
<P>2. That those, who Condemned the Excommuni∣cation
of the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches, did in so doing own their
Communion, which is one way, and the Principal
way of maintaining Communion, between Churches at
a Distance, who cannot actually Communicate with
each other.</P>
<P>3. That <HI>Victor</HI> being the Bishop of <HI>Rome,</HI> who had
the supreme Authority of receiving in, or shutting out
of the Communion of that Church, if any Persons of
the <HI>Asian</HI> Communion had come to <HI>Rome,</HI> private
Christians could not receive them into the Communi∣on
of the Church without the Bishops Authority, and
therefore could not actually Communicate with them
in the publick Offices of Religion, though they owned
their Communion; but this is no more their fault, than
the Excommunication of the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches was; they
Communicate with their own Church, and would be
very glad that the <HI>Asians,</HI> that are among them, might
be received into Communion, but they have no Au∣thority
to do it, and therefore the fault is not theirs,
for this is not to Renounce the Communion of the <HI>A∣sian</HI>
Christians, but is only a forc't Suspension of Com∣munion.</P>
<P>4. If the Christians of <HI>Rome</HI> should Travel into <HI>Asia,</HI>
<PB N="44" REF="24"/>
I doubt not, but that they might very lawfully Com∣municate
with the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches, notwithstanding
they were Excommunicated by the Bishop of <HI>Rome.</HI>
For the Bishop of <HI>Rome</HI> had no just cause to Excom∣municate
the Bishops and Churches of <HI>Asia,</HI> and there∣fore
the Sentence is void of it self; and the <HI>Roman</HI>
Christians when they are in <HI>Asia,</HI> are not under the Au∣thority
and Jurisdiction of the Bishop of <HI>Rome,</HI> and
therefore must not forbear nor suspend Communion
with the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches, unless they will justifie this
Schismatical Excommunication. The Jurisdiction of a
particular Bishop is confined within the Bounds of his
own Church, and every Christian is Subject to the Au∣thority
of the Church where he is; and therefore though
the <HI>Roman</HI> Christians at <HI>Rome</HI> cannot receive the Ex∣communicated
<HI>Asians</HI> to their Communion without the
Authority of their Bishop, yet when they are in <HI>Asia,</HI>
where the Bishop of <HI>Rome</HI> has no Authority over them,
they may and ought to joyn themselves to the Com∣munion
of the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches, during their abode a∣mong
them, if the <HI>Asians</HI> would receive them without
Commendatory Letters from their Bishop, which
they could not have in such a case as this.</P>
<P>Thus Sir, I have considered the Case you put about
Pope <HI>Victors</HI> Excommunicating the <HI>Asian</HI> Churches,
which is not a real, but a feigned Case, for there was no
actual Schism upon it, as I perceive some body had told
you, there was. And yet supposing it had been so, I
have shewn you, how the <HI>Roman</HI> and <HI>Asian</HI> Churches
might have maintained Communion with each other,
and that the case of private Christians was not so despe∣rate,
as you represent it.</P>
<P>Your following exceptions concerning National
Communion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Latters 3. p. 22.</NOTE> and National Churches, and the possibi∣lity
that there should be several Sound and Orthodox
<PB N="45" REF="24"/>
parts of the Church at the same place, have been suffi∣ciently
considered already: and you twit me so often
with my repetitions, that though I find you want ve∣ry
frequent repetitions to make you understand the
plainest sence, yet I will for my Readers sake and my
own, correct that fault.</P>
<P>Your attempt to prove Congregational Churches
from 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 14. 23. has been so often answered by<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 24.</NOTE>
the Presbyterian as well as Episcopal Divines, that to
save my self the labour of transcribing, I shall refer
you to them, and particularly to the Defence of Dr.
<HI>Still. Vnr.</HI> of <HI>Separ. p. 392. &amp;c.</HI> where you may find
this matter largely debated, in answer to Dr. <HI>Owen</HI>'s O∣riginal
of Churches.</P>
<P>You say, <HI>it is evident that one of these</HI> (Separate
Churches) <HI>must needs be cut off from Christs Body.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 26.</NOTE> I
readily grant it; for Christ has but one Body, which
is one Communion; and therefore two Churches,
which are not in Communion with each other, cannot
both belong to the same Body, or the one Catholick
Church; but the Church which is the Schismatick, ac∣cording
to the Language of the Primitive times, is out
of the Catholick Church, <HI>extra Ecclesiam foris,</HI> as is dis∣courst
at large in the Vindication of the Defence.</P>
<P>In the next place you endeavour to make me con∣tradict
my self, <HI>in talking of occasional Communion and
occasional Membership,</HI> and <HI>different Relations,</HI> when
else-where I assert, <HI>That the Communion of the Church does
not make us Members of any particular Church.</HI> But pray
Sir, where do I assert this? I am sure I assert the quite
contrary, that Church-Communion consists in Church-Membership.
I say indeed, <HI>That Church-Communion Pri∣marily
and Principally refers to the Vniversal Church,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Resol. of Cases. <HI>p.</HI> 13,</NOTE> <HI>not
to any particular Church or Society of Christians. That a
Member is a Member of the whole Body, not meerly of
<PB N="46" REF="25"/>
any part of it. That Baptism, which is the Sacrament of
our admission into the Covenant of God, and the Commu∣nion
of the Church, does not make us Members of any par∣ticular
Church, as such, but of the Vniversal Church.</HI>
And I do as plainly assert, <HI>that every true Catholick
Christian is a Member of the Vniversal Church, and as
such is a Member of every particular Church, which is a
sound part of the Vniversal Church.</HI> That no Man can
properly be said to Communicate with any Church,
whatever Acts of Communion he may perform in it,
who does not Communicate with it as a Member, and
that therefore to talk of <HI>Occasional Communion,</HI> in the
sense of our Dissenters, is as absurd as to talk of <HI>an Oc∣casional
Membership;</HI> these are the very Principles on
which I dispute against those absurd Distinctions of
<HI>constant</HI> and <HI>occasional</HI> Communion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 30.</NOTE> which I confess to
be <HI>absurd, and a Contradiction to all the Principles of
Catholick Communion,</HI> and therefore you are concerned
to answer this absurdity, not I. I have charged this ab∣surdity
upon our Occasional Communicants, and let
any man take it off, that can.</P>
<P>But are you not Sir, admirably qualified to Answer
Books, without so much as understanding the general
scope and design of the Book you Answer, without know∣ing
what makes for you or against you?</P>
<P>As for your next Question, <HI>How does it appear?
that it is necessary to Communion with the Catholick
Church, that we must perform the constant Acts of Com∣munion
in that part of the Catholick Church, where we
constantly live.</HI> You ought instead of asking this Questi∣on,
to have shown, that what proofs I have alleadged
for this are not conclusive, or do not sufficiently prove
the thing; but your Question insinuates, that I have
said nothing at all about it, or at least that you do not
know, that I have, though it be the Principal Design
<PB N="47" REF="25"/>
of that discourse, and then I am a very careless writer,
or you a very careless Reader. But the Answer to it in
short is this, That every Christian is Bound to live in
Communion with the Catholick Church, no Man lives
in Communion with the Church, who does not perform
the External visible Acts of Communion, when he
may do it without sin; The whole Catholick Church
being but one Communion, whoever Communicates
with any sound part of it, Communicates with the
whole; no Man can ordinarily Communicate in a
Church, in which he does not ordinarily live, and
therefore if he be bound at all to the External and vi∣sible
Acts of Communion, he must perform them in
the Church wherein he lives, and in so doing, if it be
a true Catholick Church, he lives in Communion with
the whole Catholick Church.</P>
<P><HI>But you attempt to prove,</HI> That you are not bound to
Communicate so much as sometimes with a sound part of
the Catholick Church,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ibid.</NOTE> because you live where there is such
an one.</P>
<P>And this you prove from Mr. <HI>Chillingworth</HI>'s Autho∣rity,
who says, that <HI>if you</HI> (speaking to the Papists)
<HI>require the belief of any Error among the conditions of
your Communion, our Obligation to Communion with you
ceaseth.</HI> Now is not this an admirable proof, that we
are not bound to Communicate with a sound part of
the Church, where we live, because we are not bound
to Communicate with an erroneous Church, which
imposes the belief of her Errours as Terms of Com∣munion?
Is not this a wonderful sound Church? And
are not you a very subtil Arguer?</P>
<P>You produce another passage of Mr. <HI>Chillingworth,</HI>
by which I cannot tell what you intend to prove, un∣less
it be, that there is no need, there should be any
External or Visible Church-Society, so Men do but
<PB N="48" REF="26"/>
Profess the Faith of Christ; which seems to be the
sence of your foregoing Paragraph. But the words are
these; <HI>I believe our Saviour ever since his Ascension,
hath had in some place or other a Visible true Church on
Earth, I mean, a Company of Men, that profest at least
so much as was necessary to Salvation; and I believe there
will be some where or other such a Church to the Worlds
end.</HI> This is his answer to that Popish Question about
<HI>the perpetuity of the Visible Church;</HI> whereby it appears,
that this <HI>Company of Men</HI> he speaks of, are not single
and scattered Individuals, which are no Visible Church,
but he means a Formed and Visible Church-Society:
and his Answer is true, though there were never a
sound Church in the World. For a corrupt Church,
which retains all the Essentials of Faith and Worship,
is a true Visible Church, and this is the meaning of
Mr. <HI>Chillingworth</HI>'s Answer; but how this proves, that
there is no need there should be any Visible Church at
all, or that Christians are not bound to actual Com∣munion
with the sound and Orthodox Church where∣in
they live, is past my understanding.</P>
<P>At the same rate you defend your self against me in
your Preface, by the Authority of those two excellent
Persons, the Dean of <HI>Canterbury,</HI> and the Dean of
Saint <HI>Pauls.</HI> Dr. <HI>Stillingfleet</HI> had asserted, <HI>That all
things necessary to Salvation, are plain in Scripture, to
all that sincerely endeavour to understand them;</HI> hence
S. C. infers, <HI>That the Governours of our Church have no
Authority to teach Truth, or to condemn Errours, and all
the People are become Prophets,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Answer to several Treatises, <HI>p. 272. &amp;c.</HI></NOTE> <HI>and all their Articles,
Constitutions, and Ordinances, have been composed and
enjoyned by an usurped Authority;</HI> and if he had added,
as he might have done with the same reason, And all
Church-Communion is needless, it had been exactly
what you aim at in this Citation. The Dr. vindicates
<PB N="49" REF="26"/>
his Doctrine from such a wild Fanatical inference.
1. By shewing <HI>the intention of those Principles, which
was plainly to lay down the Foundations of a Christian
Faith, living in the Communion of our Church.</HI> And if
this was his design, as he says, it was, certainly he
could neither before nor after say any thing, which
should overthrow the necessity of Church-Commu∣nion;
and then he can say nothing against me, nor for
you. 2. He distinguishes between <HI>the necessaries to
Salvation, and to the Government of the Church:</HI> that
is, what is necessary for every Christian,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 275.</NOTE> considered in
a private Capacity to know and believe, to make him
capable of Salvation; and what care the Church must
take <HI>to instruct the ignorant, to satisfie the doubting, to
direct the unskilful, and to help the weak; and not barely
to provide for necessity but safety, and not barely the
safety of particular persons, but of it self;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 276.</NOTE> <HI>which cannot
be done without prudent Orders, setting the bounds of
Mens Employments,</HI> &amp;c. i. e. though it is possible for
a private Christian, who lives alone, and has the use of
the Bible in a Language which he understands, by dili∣gent
and honest inquiries to find out so much truth, as
is absolutely necessary to Salvation, yet this does not
overthrow the necessity of a setled Ministry, and a re∣gular
Authority in the Church; all this I firmly assent
to, and yet do as firmly believe the necessity of Church-Communion,
when it may be had upon Lawful Terms,
and so does this Reverend Person also: and therefore
I cannot look upon your alleadging his Authority a∣gainst
me, to have any other design than to affront the
Dean for his excellent Pains in vindicating the Com∣munion
of our Church, and shewing people the Evil
and Danger of Separation. He has sufficiently declared
what his Judgment is about Separation, and therefore
<PB N="50" REF="27"/>
I need not concern my self any farther to prove that he
is not my Adversary in this Cause.</P>
<P>At the same rate you deal with that <HI>great Man</HI> (as
you deservedly call him) Dr. <HI>Tillotson,</HI> who says,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Preface.</NOTE> <HI>I
had much rather perswade any one to be a good Man, than
to be of any Party and denomination of Christians whatso∣ever;
for I doubt not but the belief of the Ancient Creed,
provided we entertain nothing that is destructive of it,
together with a good life, will certainly save a Man; and
without this, no man can have reasonable hopes of Salvation,
no not in an Infallible Church, if there were any such to
be found in the World.</HI> How does this oppose me, who
assert the necessity of Church-Communion? Is the <HI>Catho∣lick
Church</HI> then, and the <HI>Communion of Saints,</HI> no part
of our Creed? and is not Schism destructive to these
great Articles of our Faith? or is Schism, which is the
breach of Christian Charity properly so called (which
is the Love and Charity, which the Members of the
same Body, ought to have for each other, and con∣sists
in Unity and Communion) consistent with a
good Life, if by that we understand an Universal good∣ness,
of which Charity is the most vital and essential
part?</P>
<P>But do you indeed think, Sir, that the Dean believes
a Man may be saved without Communion with any
Church, when it may be had without Sin? when in
the very next Paragraph he so earnestly exhorts them
to Communion with the Church of <HI>England?</HI> I can ea∣sily
forgive your usage of me, since I find you cannot
Read the best Books without perverting them, and
that you never spare any Mans Reputation to serve
your Designes: for your Reproaches and your Com∣mendations
are but different ways of abuse, though I
confess, I should rather chuse to be reproached by
you.</P>
<P><PB N="51" REF="27"/>
Your last Consideration is, whether it be a good
way to convert Schismaticks,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Letter 3. <HI>p.</HI> 29.</NOTE> to prove <HI>that Schism is as
Damning a Sin, as Murder or Adultery.</HI> Truly Sir, <HI>St.
Cyprian</HI> and <HI>St. Austin,</HI> and all the Ancient Fathers of
the Church, thought this a very good way, for they
insisted very much upon this Argument; and if Men
will not forsake their Schism, though the Salvation of
their Souls be endangered by it, I am apt to think, that
no other Arguments will perswade them. And if this
be true (as I verily believe it is, and shall believe so,
till I see the Third Chapter of the Vindication of the
Defence of Dr. <HI>Still.</HI> fairly answered) I think it the
greatest Charity in the World, to warn Men of it;
and if it should prove by their perverseness no Charity
to them, it is Charity to my own Soul, and delivers
me from the guilt of their Bloud, whether such Do∣ctrine
Preach Men into, or out of, the Church.</P>
<P>And now for your parting Blow. <HI>Certainly if our
Church required Conformity to its Rites and Ceremonies
as necessary to Salvation, It could not blame Men for di∣viding
from it. Yes certainly</HI> upon such a Supposition,
the Church could and would blame Men for their Se∣paration,
though it may be, they might not deserve to
be blamed: for no doubt, the more necessary the
Church judges her Constitutions, the more she will
blame Dissenters.</P>
<P>But <HI>he, who tells us, or he saies nothing, that the di∣vine
Spirit confines his Influences and Operations to the
Vnity of the Church in such Conformity, not only makes
such Conformity necessary to Salvation, but imputes to the
Church the Damnation of many Thousands of Souls,
who might expect to be saved upon other Terms.</HI>
That the Divine Spirit confines his influences
(ordinarily) to the Unity of the Church I do
assert, but that this is <HI>in Conformity to the Church
<PB N="52" REF="28"/>
of England,</HI> I do not assert. For Conformity to the
Church of <HI>England</HI> is not Essential to the Unity of the
Catholick Church: for every Church has authority to
prescribe its own Rites and Ceremonies of Worship,
in Conformity to the general Rules of the Gospel.
And therefore though the Unity of the Church is
necessary to intitle Men to the ordinary influences of
Gods Grace, and consequently is necessary to Salvation,
yet Conformity to the Church of <HI>England</HI> is not neces∣sary
to the Unity of the Church, because Christians
who live under the Government and Jurisdiction of
other Churches, may and do preserve the Unity of the
Church without conformity to the Church of <HI>England.</HI>
Obedience indeed, and Subjection to Church-Authority
in all Lawful things, is necessary to the Unity of the
Church, and necessary to Salvation, and consequently it
is a necessary Duty to conform to all the Lawful and
Innocent Customs of the Church wherein we live; but
this does not make the particular Laws of Conformity,
which are different in different Churches, to be neces∣sary
to Salvation, unless you will say the Church has
no Authority but only in things absolutely neces∣sary
to Salvation; which destroys all the external Or∣der
and Discipline of the Church, and charges all the
Churches in the World, with destroying Mens Souls,
if any persons be so Humorsom and Peevish as to break
Communion with them for such Reasons. But such
kind of Cavils as these, you may find answered at large
in the Vindication of the Defence; and thither I refer
you, if you desire to see any more of it.</P>
<P>Thus Sir, I have with great patience answered your
Questions, not that they needed or deserved any An∣swer,
but that you might not think your self too much
despised, nor other weak People think your Questions
<PB N="53" REF="28"/>
unanswered. And now I have given you an Answer, I
shall take the Confidence to give you a little Ghostly
Counsel too, which you need a great deal more than an
Answer.</P>
<P>I have not troubled my Head to inquire Scrupulous∣ly,
who you are, nor do I use to trust Common Fame
in such matters: but though I know not you, yet I
perceive you know me; and if as you say,<NOTE PLACE="marg">p. 1.</NOTE> <HI>you have of∣ten
heard me with great Satisfaction, and as you hope not
without edifying thereby,</HI> I think it would have become
you to have treated me with a little more Civility
than you have done, if it be in your Nature to be Civil
to a Clergy-Man. And I wish more for your own sake,
than for mine, you had done so; for I thank God I
have learnt not only by the precepts and example of
my great Master, but by frequent Tryals, to go through
good Report and evil Report, and to bear the most in∣vidious
and Spightful Reflections with an equal mind.
But as contemptible as a Clergy-Man is now, these
things will be accounted for another day.</P>
<P>For it is very evident, that you have a great Spight
at the whole Order, whatever personal kindness you
may have for some Men; they are but <HI>a Herd of Cler∣gy-men,</HI>
and you know no other use of a Bishop, but
<HI>to oversee, admonish,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Preface.</NOTE> <HI>and Censure those, who are apt to
go beyond their due Bounds.</HI> I confess this way of Railery
is grown very fashionable, and I perceive you are re∣solved
to be in the Mode, and to be an accomplisht
Gentleman; but I never knew a man that was seriously
religious, who durst affront the Servants for their Ma∣sters
sake.</P>
<P>But you Sir, are in the very height of the fashion,
and think their Office as contemptible, as their Per∣sons
generally are thought to be: <HI>you hope to be saved
without understanding the Notion of Church-Government as
<PB N="54" REF="29"/>
'tis intreagued by Clergy-men of all sides.</HI> And I hope
you may be saved without understanding a great many
other things besides Church-Government, or else I
doubt your Salvation may be hazardous.</P>
<P>But this is too plain a contempt of all Church-Au∣thority;
for though the Church of <HI>Rome</HI> has usurpt an
unlimited and Tyrannical Power under the Notion of
Church-Government, yet what has the <HI>Sound Church
of England</HI> (as you own it) done? What occasion did
I give for this Censure? who have expresly confined
<HI>the Exercise of Church-Authority to Church-Communion,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Resol. of Cases, <HI>p.</HI> 39.</NOTE>
<HI>to receiving in, and putting out of the Church.</HI> And if
the Church be no Society, I would desire to know what
it is; and if it be a Society, how can any Society sub∣sist
without Authority in some Persons to receive in
and to shut out of the Society? But the truth is, tho
you pretend to be in Communion with the Church of
<HI>England,</HI> you make the Church it self a very needless
and insignificant thing, for you know no necessity of
Communicating with any Church, you will not allow
it to be Schism to Separate from the Church, you
think it a pretty indifferent thing, whether Men be
Baptized or not, or by whom they are Baptized: what
your Opinion is about the Sacrament of the Lords Sup∣per
I do not know, though if you are consistent with
your self, I doubt that is a very indifferent Ceremony too.</P>
<P>Truly to deal plainly with you, I think you have
more need to be taught your Catechism than to set up
for a Writer of Books; and let me in time warn you,
what the consequence of this way you are in, is likely
to be, which is no less than a contempt of all revealed
and instituted Religion, and consequently of Christi∣anity.
Natural Religion may subsist without any posi∣tive
Institutions, but revealed Religion never did, and
never can; for when God Transacts with Mankind in
<PB N="55" REF="29"/>
the way of a Visible Covenant, there must be some Vi∣sible
Ministers, and Visible Sacraments of this Cove∣nant.
And when the Evangelical Ministers and Sacra∣ments
fall into contempt, Men must think meanly of
Christianity, and return to what they call natural
Religion, which is a Religion without a Priest and
without a Sacrifice; which cannot save a Sinner, but
by uncovenanted Grace and Mercy; which no Man
can be sure of, and which no Man shall find, who re∣jects
a Priest and Sacrifice of Gods providing.</P>
<P>And to convince you of this, you may observe, that
the contempt of the Notion of a Church, of the Evan∣gelical
Priesthood and Sacraments, is originally owing
to <HI>Deists</HI> and <HI>Socinians,</HI> to those who profess to believe
in God, and to worship him according to the Laws
of natural Religion, but believe nothing at all of
Christ; or to those, who profess to believe in Christ,
but believe him only to be a meer Man, and a great
Reformer of Natural Religion, but make nothing at all
of his Priesthood and Sacrifice. If Christ be our great
High Priest, and we must hope for Salvation only in
vertue of his Sacrifice, There must be some way ap∣pointed
to apply his Merits and Salvation to us, and
this will convince us of the necessity of Church-Com∣munion,
and a visible Confederation by Sacraments
of divine appointment:<NOTE PLACE="marg">See Vindic. of the Def. <HI>cap.</HI> 3.</NOTE> But if Christ came only as a
great Prophet to instruct us more perfectly in the
Rules of Vertue, and to give us more certain Hopes of
a future State, there can be no more necessity of a
Church now, than there was in a State of Nature.
Christians may associate, if they please, for Acts of
publick worship, and they may break Company, when
they please, without any danger; and the Evangelical
Sacraments can be only significant Ceremonies,
<PB N="56" REF="30"/>
which may be used or let alone, as every one likes
best.</P>
<P>At this Rate you every where discourse; and I be∣lieve
so well of our Dissenters, that though they
would be glad to be excused from the guilt of Schism,
yet they will not thank you, for excusing them upon
such Principles, as tend to undermine Christianity;
and I believe so well of you, that though you affect
to talk in the modish way, yet you do not understand
whither it tends: and I hope this timely Caution may
prevent your embracing those Principles, whereon
your Conclusions are Naturally Built.</P>
<P>Another thing I would warn you of, is, that these loose
Principles of Church-Communion do not tempt you to
Schism, and State-Factions, which usually go together.
You pretend indeed to be in constant Communion
with the Church of <HI>England;</HI> but according to the
Principles of your Letters no Church in the World can
have any hold of you, every Man is a Communicant
at his own pleasure who thinks he may part without
Sin; And it is much to be suspected, that no Man,
who is a hearty lover of the Church of <HI>England,</HI> can
make such a Zealous Defence for Dissenters, who has
not some private reasons for his Zeal: and when Men
are not Endeared to each other by one Communion, it
is to be feared they are linked together by some other
Common Interest. Now should you prove a Schisma∣tick,
to say no worse, it will not excuse you, how many
Fine Questions soever you can ask about it.</P>
<P>And that which will greatly endanger you, is that
great Opinion you have of your self: for some men are
so wanton as to espouse a Schism or Faction only to
shew their Wit in Defending it, and to make themselves
considerable by espousing a Party. I will not so much
wrong you, as to say that you have shewn any great
<PB N="57" REF="30"/>
Wit or Judgment in this Cause; but it is evident to
every impartial Man, who reads your Letters, that
you have betrayed too great a conceit of both, and
that is a great deal the more dangerous of the two;
for true Wit and Judgment will secure Men from those
mischiefs, which a vain conceit of it betrays them
to.</P>
<P>And now Sir, all that I shall add, concerns your way
of Writing, which neither becomes a wise Man, nor a
fair Disputant; you have not offered any Argument to
disprove any one thing I have said, you have no where
shewn the weakness of my Arguments to prove what
I undertook, but have at all Adventures askt a great
many Questions, and generally nothing to the purpose.
Now it had been easie to have askt you as many cross
Questions, which had been as good an Answer to your
Questions, as your Questions are to my Discourse; and
thus People might have gazed on us, and have been ne∣ver
the wiser. For to raise a great many difficulties
onely tends to Scepticism, and will never end a Dispute.
I am loth to mind you of the Proverb, because I do not
think the application belongs to you; but yet it should
make any Man of Wit ashamed of such Methods of
Dispute, wherein he may be out-done by a Man of no
Wit.</P>
<P>I confess I have with some regret stole time from
better Employment to answer your Letters, but do not
think my self bound to do so, as often as you think
fit to give a publick Challenge. This Controversie,
if you had pleased, might have been ended more pri∣vately;
which had been less trouble to me, though it
may be you thought it might have been less glorious
to your self, which I presume was your reason of first
spreading your Letter in Writing, and then of Prin∣ting
it. I shall not envy your Glory; I had rather con∣tinue
<PB N="56" REF="31"/>
mean and obscure in a humble Obedience to
Church and State, than to raise the most Glorious
Triumphs and Trophees to my memory, by giving the
least disturbance to either. And that you and all sober
Christians may be of the same mind, is the hearty
Prayer of,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE>
<SIGNED>Your very Humble Servant.
<HI>W. S.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<PB REF="31"/>
<HEAD>BOOKS Printed for FINCHAM
GARDINER.</HEAD>
<P>A Continuation and Vindication of the Defence of
Dr. <HI>Stilling fleet</HI>'s Unreasonableness of Separati∣on,
in Answer to Mr. <HI>Baxter</HI> and Mr. <HI>Lob, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>Considerations of present use, considering the Dan∣ger
resulting from the change of our Church-Govern∣ment.</P>
<P>1. A Perswasive to Communion with the Church of
<HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>2. A Resolution of some Cases of Conscience which
respect Church-Communion.</P>
<P>3. The Case of Indifferent things used in the Wor∣ship
of God, proposed and Stated, by considering these
Questions, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>4. A Discourse about Edification.</P>
<P>5. <HI>The Resolution of this Case of Conscience,</HI> Whe∣ther
the Church of <HI>Englands</HI> Symbolizing so far as it doth
with the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> makes it unlawful to hold Com∣munion
with the Church of <HI>England?</HI></P>
<P>6. A Letter to <HI>Anonymus,</HI> in answer to his three Let∣ters
to Dr. <HI>Sherlock</HI> about Church-Communion.</P>
<P>7. Certain Cases of Conscience resolved, concerning
the Lawfulness of joyning with Forms of Prayer in
Publick Worship. In two Parts.</P>
<P>8. The Case of mixt Communion: Whether it be
Lawful to Separate from a Church upon the account of
promiscuous Congregations and mixt Communions?</P>
<P>9. An Answer to the Dissenters Objections against the
Common Prayers, and some other parts of Divine Ser∣vice
prescribed in the Liturgy of the Church of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>10. The Case of Kneeling at the Holy Sacrament
stated and resolved, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> The first Part.</P>
<P>11. Certain Cases of Conscience, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> The second
Part.</P>
<P><PB REF="32"/>
12. A Discourse of Profiting by Sermons, and of go∣ing
to hear where men think they can profit most.</P>
<P>13. A serious Exhortation, with some important
Advices, relating to the late Cases about Conformity,
recommended to the present Dissenters from the
Church of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>14. An Argument for Union; taken from the true
interest of those Dissenters in <HI>England</HI> who profess and
call themselves Protestants.</P>
<P>16. Some Considerations about the Case of Scandal,
or giving Offence to Weak Brethren.</P>
<P>17. The Case of Infant-Baptism, in Five Questions,
<HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>1. A Discourse about the charge of Novelty upon
the Reformed Church of <HI>England,</HI> made by the Papists
asking of us the Question, Where was our Religion
before <HI>Luther?</HI></P>
<P>2. A Discourse about Tradition, shewing what is
meant by it, and what Tradition is to be received, and
what Tradition is to be rejected.</P>
<P>3. The difference of the Case between the Separa∣tion
of Protestants from the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> and the
Separation of Dissenters from the Church of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>4. The Protestant Resolution of Faith, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<PB REF="32"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

