<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The opinion of the Roman jvdges touching imprisonment and the liberty of the subject, or, A sermon preached at the Abby at Westminster, at a late publique fast, Jan. 25, 1642 by J.V. Prisoner.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Vicars, John, 1579 or 80-1652.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A71209</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing V320</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R4189</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">12137428</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 12137428</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">54778</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A71209)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54778)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 242:E88, no 16)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The opinion of the Roman jvdges touching imprisonment and the liberty of the subject, or, A sermon preached at the Abby at Westminster, at a late publique fast, Jan. 25, 1642 by J.V. Prisoner.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Vicars, John, 1579 or 80-1652.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 25 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London? :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.]</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1643.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Attributed to John Vicars by Halkett and Laing and Wing.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XXV, 27 --  Sermons.</TERM><TERM>Fast-day sermons.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A71209">
<STC T="W">V320</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12137428</BIBNO>
<VID>54778</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>The Opinion
OF THE
ROMAN <HI>JVDGES</HI>
Touching Imprisonment, and
the Liberty of the SUBJECT,
OR,
A SERMON
Preached at the <HI>Abby</HI> at <HI>Westminster,</HI>
at a late publique FAST,
JAN. 25. 1642▪</P>
<Q><BIBL><HI>ACTS 25. V.</HI> 27.</BIBL>
<P>It seemes unreasonable to me to send a Prisoner, and not to
signifie the crimes against him.</P></Q>
<P>By J. V. Prisoner.</P>
<P>Printed in the yeare of our Lord, 1643.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE READER.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>He occasion of this Ser∣mon
was the importu∣nity
of Prisoners, and by
the same importunity it
is printed without addition or de∣traction
of any thing materiall,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Acts 24. 1.</NOTE> not
with a majestick style, like <HI>Tertullus</HI>
the Oratour, but like <HI>Paul</HI> a Priso∣ner;
<HI>neque altum semper urgendo, neque
dum procellas, cautus horrescis nimium
premendo, Littus iniquum:</HI> It was
Preached on the day of <HI>Pauls</HI> Con∣version,
and the Subject is <HI>Paul</HI> the
Prisoner, and on a Fast day, a day of
Humiliation, and who is so hum∣bled
as a Prisoner: If any receive
profit thereby, Let him pray for
Prisoners.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>J. V. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>A Sermon preached at the Ab∣by
at Westminster, on the last pub∣lick
Fast, January 25.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>ACTS 25. 27.</BIBL>
<Q>It seemes unreasonable to mee to send a prisoner,
and not withall to signifie his crimes against him.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Reade since our Saviour
Christ of a fivefold persecu∣tion;<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE>
the first, the persecuti∣on
of the high Priests, the
Archierarchical persecution,
<HI>Act. 4. 1. And when they spake
these things to the people, there
rose up against them the Priests and Sadduces, and
Rulers of the Temple, being filled with rage against
them, because they taught the people,</HI> they laid
hands on them, and put them in<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> custody, after∣wards
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
into the common Gaole: this is the Ju∣daicall
persecution that lasted 40. yeares after
Christ, as it is in the Syrian Paraphrase. Se∣condly,
when this began to coole, then followed
the persecution of<NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Arethas.</NOTE> old Rome by the <HI>Cesars,</HI>
which continued about 600. yeares, till <HI>Constan∣tine</HI>
the great. By<NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Tres Fon∣tane.</NOTE> <HI>Nero</HI> Saint <HI>Paul</HI> was deca∣pitated
at Rome at the<NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Epiphan. Oecumen. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Euseb. 13. Nero.</NOTE> three Fountaines, and
Saint <HI>John</HI> banished to the Isle of Patmos.</P>
<P>When <HI>Constantine</HI> came, then <HI>omnia nova,</HI> all
things were new, and he saw a signe from Hea∣ven,
<HI>In this signe thou shalt prevaile.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, there followed<NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>persecutio Haeretico∣rum,</HI>
whereof <HI>Epiphanius</HI> and others write. I
begin with the Gnosticks, and I find in <HI>Epipha∣nius,</HI>
first<NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Epi∣phan.</NOTE> they despise dominion, to which A∣nabaptists
succeed. Secondly,<NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Epi. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Epiph.</NOTE> they deny the
Law, as the Antinomians now doe, that say, <HI>God sees no iniquity in Jacob, nor perversenesse in Isra∣el,</HI>
and all the sinnes they commit are workes of
the outward man, not of the mind. Thirdly,
they understand not, nor allow the Hebrew
text: The Hebrew and Greek these unlearned
men regard not, though they be the languages
of the holy Ghost. Secondly, <HI>Euchitae,</HI> such as
abused the saying of Saint <HI>Paul,</HI><NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>Pray continual∣ly,</HI>
to vaine babling, and thinke that God is per∣swaded
by Battalogies and Tautologies, yet in
<HI>Eccles.</HI> 5. 1. it is said, <HI>God is in heaven, and thou
on earth, therefore let thy words be few.</HI> Thirdly,
the Pelagians and Semipelagians, to which the
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
Arminians now succeed for their <HI>Liberum arbi∣trium,</HI>
free will. Fourthly, the Enthusiasts, that
pretended Enthusiasme, and that they spake by
the Spirit, as Brownists now doe. Fifthly, Ar∣rians,
to whom the Socinians answer, that deny
the Divinity of the Son of God. Sixthly,<NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Donatistae, &amp;c. S. Austin.</NOTE> Do∣natists,
that are separated from the Church, and
and so the Separatists. Seventhly, Marcianites,
that held<NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Epiphan.</NOTE> second Baptisme, as Anabaptists now
doe: Thus much of the persecution of the Here∣tickes,
which were limbs and fore-runners of
Antichrist.</P>
<P>Fourthly, the persecution of the Turkes,
which was about the yeare 666. by the compu∣tation
of <HI>Lyranus.</HI> Fifthly, the persecution of
Antichrist, which begun at the same time, <HI>Re∣vel.
13. ver. ult. The number of the Beast is</HI> 666.
that is, the time of his rising, and his fall shall
be 1260. yeares after, that is, neare a thousand
yeares he hath already continued by <HI>Nauclerus,</HI>
and the Magdeburg Centurists: then <HI>Constans</HI>
the Emperour gave to Pope <HI>Vitalian, Imperium
urbis,</HI> the rule of the City; and this is the worst
persecution of all the former, because the Here∣tickes
are incorporated into a body, and the uni∣ted
force is stronger. The reason of my large
Preface is this, because my Text falls under the
second persecution: for <HI>Festus</HI> was Deputy un∣der
bloudy <HI>Nero,</HI> who wished that Rome had
onely one head, that hee might cut it off at one
blow, who clothed Christians in beasts skins, and
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
after devoured them, who ript up <HI>Agrippina</HI>
his mother, to see the place of his generation;
yet I shall speake <HI>tria memorabilia,</HI> three memo∣rable
things in commendation and discommen∣dation
of this Deputy: His<NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Dictamen rectae rationis.</NOTE> right opinion of
the person, and of his cause, <HI>It seemes to mee un∣reasonable;</HI>
therefore he had reason, and the Hea∣thens
had the Law<NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Rom. 2.</NOTE> written in their hearts. And
in <HI>Isa. 24. 5. They have made void the everlasting
covenant,</HI> or covenant made with the<NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> whole
world, this is the law of Nature: First, hee ap∣proves
of his appeale to <HI>Cesar,</HI> as the chiefe of
the Senate, <HI>Act. 25. 25. Because hee desires to be
kept to the hearing of Cesar, I have determined to
send him.</HI> Secondly, he approves of his cause, <HI>he
had done nothing worthy of</HI><NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Syr. </NOTE> <HI>death, or bonds.</HI> Third∣ly,
he calls him to speak for himselfe, after eight
or ten dayes he came to Cesarea, <HI>Act.</HI> 25. 6. and
the next day sate on the Judgement seat, hee did
not stay two or three yeares, or ten yeares; the
Jewes after five dayes came downe, <HI>Act.</HI> 24. 1.
they delayed not, but hastened his doom. Fourth∣ly,
not before meane, ignoble men of no reason,
birth or education, but by a<NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Oecumen.</NOTE> Roman Deputy, a
King, Queen, Chiliarch, and chiefe of the City,
he saith, <HI>I have brought him before you, and speci∣ally
before thee, O King Agrippa.</HI> A King is of
Royall bloud, and will not trample upon a
worme; <HI>but a poore man oppressing the poore, is a
sweeping raine, that will leave no food.</HI> The Lion is
the King of Beasts, and is satisfied with homage,
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
<HI>Corpora magnanimo satis est prostrasse Leoni. Au∣gustus
Caesar</HI> was called<NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Pater atque Princeps, <HI>Hor.</HI></NOTE> Father and Prince.
Fifthly, he thinkes it unreasonable to send a pri∣soner,
and not signifie the crimes. Sixthly, to
signifie them in<NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Syr.</NOTE> writing, for perpetuall me∣moriall.</P>
<P>But here is a grand objection: Were not
grievous crimes objected against the Apostle?
as first, that hee was a pestilent fellow, that is, a
man dangerous, as one infected with the pesti∣lence,
or a<NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Chrys. Gr. Ba∣sil.</NOTE> pernicious fellow, as it is in the Sy∣rian.
Secondly, a sower of sedition among the
<HI>Iewes</HI> in the whole world, <HI>Acts</HI> 24. 6. That he
<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Syr. a <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Syr. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE>raised sedition, and spread it, and<NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Gr. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Epiphan. Be∣da, Jerom.</NOTE> obstinately
maintained it. Thirdly, a Ring-leader of the
sect of the Nazarens, this crimination over∣throwes
the former; Nazarens were Christians,
and Christ was Prince of Peace; and his Mini∣sters,
Ministers of peace, how then should he
sow division? Fourthly, a prophaner of the Tem∣ple,
that is called by <HI>Iosephus</HI> the<NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Antiq. 15. cap. 14.</NOTE> holy place:
So Christ saith, <HI>When ye see the abomination of de∣solation
stand in the holy place.</HI> These are the
crimes objected against Saint <HI>Paul, and the Iews
affirmed,</HI> or as the Father saith with impreca∣tion,
<HI>that these things were so.</HI></P>
<P>To the first hee makes no answer;<NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Oecumen.</NOTE> for it was
in generall, that he was a dangerous fellow: and
a generall proves nothing, neither is worthy of
an answer by the divine Apostolicall wisdome.</P>
<P>To the second he answers by way of negation,
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>
that hee was no sower of sedition, but that they
themselves first caused the tumult,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Syr. &amp; Vatab.</NOTE> <HI>Acts 24. 19.
The Iewes that came from Asia caused the tumult,
for they saw him in the Temple, and stirred up the
people against him, and laid hands on him</HI> in that
sacred place and Sanctuary, <HI>Men of Israel, help,
this is the man that teacheth against this people in
every place, Acts</HI> 21. 27. he was accused by them
that were the onely actors in the tumult. Hence
we learne to stand for peace, and avoid sedition.
In the 120. <HI>Psalme, ver. 5. Woe is mee that I se∣journe
with Mesech, and have my dwelling in the
tents of Kedar.</HI> Mesech and Kedar are Tuscany
and Turky, by <HI>Kimchi</HI> out of <HI>Ioseph ben Gorion.</HI>
Here are the two great enemies of the Church,
in whose person <HI>David</HI> here speakes. His so∣journing
with the Tuscans was tedious, and his
dwelling with the Turkes called Kedar, so the
tongue of Kedar is the Arab. in <HI>Abben Ezra,</HI> and
in Arab. the Alcoran is written. <HI>My soule hath
long dwelt,</HI> hee saith not his body; but hee was
grieved at the heart that he dwelt with such ill
neighbours,<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> <HI>with him that hated peace,</HI> hee saith
not with them, but <HI>with him,</HI> because there was
one a ring-leader of the rest; neither doth hee
say unquiet, but <HI>that hateth peace,</HI> and will never
admit<NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> reconciliation. And hee addes, <HI>I am
peace,</HI> God is love, Christ is out peace, and the
Church is peace, yet not without truth, though
it be not expressed, it is understood; for peace
and truth doe meet together, and sweetly kisse
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
each other. Christ is our peace, and yet hee is
truth: <HI>But when we speake for peace, they are for
warre.</HI> If wee pray, or petition, or preach for
peace, they are for warre; what shall I say of
them? they are Mesech and Kedar.</P>
<P>To the third he confesseth, that <HI>according to
the way that they call Heresie, so he worshipped the
God of his Fathers:</HI> Here we learne three things,
Faith, Hope, and Charity.</P>
<P>1. Faith, to beleeve the Law and Prophets
as he did, <HI>to worship the God of our Fathers,</HI> not
new Gods, and in a new way; enquire for the
old way and walke therin, that is, the way of the
Law, not in the way of our Fathers, against the
Law, Prophets and Apostles before the Refor∣mation;
<HI>To the Law and the Testimony, if they
walke not by this rule there is no light in them, with
the heart man beleeveth, and with the tongue con∣fession
is made to salvation.</HI></P>
<P>2. Wee learne Hope, for if we beleeve wee
shall have hope towards God, <HI>Acts</HI> 24. 15. no
hope in our selves, but in him.</P>
<P>3. Wee learne Charity, the third Theologi∣call
vertue, v. 16. <HI>for this cause I labour,</HI> this is
the labour of love, love to all, as in <HI>Rom. 13. 8.
Owe nothing to any man but love,</HI> pay to every
man his due, <HI>Custome to whom custome, tribute to
whom tribute, feare to whom feare, honour to whom
honour;</HI> custome is ordinary, tribute extraordi∣nary,
both due to the Roman Caesars, persecu∣tors
of the Christians, <HI>Iustin Martyr,</HI> and <HI>Ter∣tullian</HI>
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
in their Apologetikes prove this duty
from thence, and that Tribute they payed, was
imployed for the eradication of the Christians,
but they suffered, and the blood of Martyrs was
the seed of the Church, the armes whereof were
prayers and teares, so then <HI>feare God, and honour
the King, and meddle not with them that are given
to change;</HI> Againe, love worketh no ill, shall I
say that he who kills and robbs his brother loves
him? seeing love fulfills the law, and if a man
<HI>have this worlds good, and see his brother in want,
and shut up his bowels of compassion, how dwells the
love of God in that man?</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Micah. 6.</NOTE> Three things are requi∣red
of a man, 1. <HI>to doe justly, 2. to love mercy,
3. and to walke humbly with God,</HI> Love is above all,
above Tongues, faith of Miracles, Prophecy,
Knowledge, Almes, Burning, 1 <HI>Cor. 13. 1, 2.
It beareth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all
things;</HI> embrace this charity with peace, and
the peace of God be with you.</P>
<P>To the fourth he answereth and denyeth, that
he was a prophaner of the Temple, but they pro∣phaned
it by raising a tumult in it, as is shewed
before, a thing abhorred of Heathens, I read in
<HI>Herodotus,</HI> that certaine profane Atheists robbed
the Temple of <HI>Venus,</HI> and the Goddesse, by way
of punishment, sent the<NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Herod.</NOTE> faemineall disease a∣mong
them, thought to be new, but Elder then
<HI>Herodotus.</HI></P>
<P>Thus I have done with the right opinion of
this Heathen deputy.</P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="7"/>
Now I proceed to shew how Antichrist is op∣posite
in every particular, and his persecution
worse then the Pagans, out of three prophecyes
of <HI>Dan. 7. 25. he shall speake words on the side
of the most high,</HI> this I take for granted, by the
best expositors, that it is meant literally of <HI>An∣tiochus,</HI>
mystically of Antichrist, that is, <HI>pro &amp;
contra,</HI> for and against Christ, a little home in
his beginning, but hath eyes and pollicy, and
a mouth, speaking great things, <HI>he shall weare out
the Saints of the most high,</HI> those that have gray
haires here and there upon them, he weares out
by long imprisonments without cause, as in the
Spanish and Italian Inquisitions he is kept 2. 4.
yeares, all the dayes of his life, and no accuser
known, but they ask him what he hath done, what
enemies he hath, &amp;c. The Romane deputy al∣lowed
appeale to Caesar,<NOTE PLACE="marg">In utroque jure sunt tituli de appellatio∣nibus.</NOTE> but the Conclave and
their adherents deny all appeales, and trample
upon Princes, and depose Kings upon suspition
of another Religion: The Romans after a small
time called the Apostle to his answer, and not
before ignoble, but honourable persons; but An∣tichrists
limbes to the greater disgrace, judge
them by meane persons, of no birth, education,
or religion: The Romans thought it reasonable
to signifie the crimes, but these imprison with∣out
any crime, except bare affirmation without
oath prove a crime: <HI>The Iewes affirme these
crimes forenamed</HI> against Saint <HI>Paul;</HI> but he saith,
<HI>They cannot prove the things whereof they doe ac∣cuse
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
mee, Acts</HI> 24. 13. In the mouth of two or
three witnesses every word shall stand. Thus by
tedious delayes of judgment and imprisonment,
Antichristians weare out the Saints, <HI>And he shall
thinke to change times and lawes, Dan.</HI> 7. 25. he
shall thinke to make a new Heaven and Earth, a
new Church and State, a new Sun, Moone and
Starres, which God made for times and seasons,
he shall make new Lawes, abrogate the old, <HI>and
all shall be delivered into his hand, for a time, and
times and halfe a time,</HI> that is, three years and a
halfe, In Queene <HI>Maryes</HI> time the presecution
was about three yeares and a halfe, and in the last
times of Antichrist shall be the like, <HI>Rev. 11. 7.
The bodies of the witnesses lye unburied three yeares
and a halfe:</HI> In <HI>Dan.</HI> 8. 10. it is said, the horne
<HI>shall grow great to the host of Heaven,</HI> and <HI>shall cast
to the earth some of the host, and of the starves, and
trample on them,</HI> not only shall Antichrist throw
out of their places, but by contumelies trample
the Ministers of Christ in the mire, <HI>And he shall
take away the dayly sacrifice,</HI> this signified the
publike formes of Gods<NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Chrysost.</NOTE> worship, as in <HI>Ps. 141.
1. My prayers as incense▪ and lifting up of my hands
as a dayly sacrifice,</HI> in <HI>Dan. 11. 36.</HI> it is said, that
Antichrist shall presume to be a King, and do,
or make Warre according to his will, by an ar∣bitrary
government, not by any law, <HI>and shall ex∣alt
himselfe</HI><NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Heb.</NOTE> <HI>above every God,</HI> that is, every King
who is called a God in Scripture, so 2 <HI>Thess.</HI> 2.
every<NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>Augustus</HI> or <HI>Caesar, And be shall not regard
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
the God of his Fathers,</HI> but a new God, and a new
Religion; <HI>Nor the desire of women,</HI> that is spiri∣tuall
fornication with Idols he shall detest, but
shall commit sacriledge, <HI>And he shall honour the
God of forces,</HI> he shall ever be for warre, and not
for peace; so <HI>Mahomet</HI> propagated his Religi∣on
by warre, <HI>Christ Jesus</HI> by peace, <HI>A bruised reed
shall he not breake, and smoaking flax shall he not
quench,</HI> because <HI>David</HI> had shed much blood, he
must not build the Temple, and in the building
no Toole of Iron was heard, for it was a House
of peace; but Antichrist is all for the God<NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Dan. 11.</NOTE> of
forces.</P>
<P>Thus I have done with the first thing imita∣ble
in this Roman Deputy, his Right Opinion.</P>
<P>Secondly, his humanity, <HI>In sending a Prisoner,</HI>
so saith the Text, and it is expressed in what
manner he was sent elsewhere,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Syr.</NOTE> <HI>Acts 27. 3. The
Centurion shewed pity to S.</HI> Paul, <HI>and suffered him
to goe to his friends to refresh himselfe,</HI> he suffered
him to goe to his friends, a great favour, much
more then to suffer his friends to come to him,
he gave him<NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Potestatem egredieuti, Cartluisian.</NOTE> power to goe forth, there was an
opening of the Ports, that he might be refreshed
with food and rayment necessary: Likewise the
other Roman Deputy <HI>Petix, Acts 24. 23. Hee
commanded a Centurion,</HI> no meaner man, <HI>to keepe
him,</HI> not to hurt him;<NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Syr. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> with gentlenesse, not ri∣gour
and fircenesse, (as the Gaoler in <HI>Acts</HI> 16.
that put them in the hole, in the stockes) and
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
that he should forbid, or restrayne, or<NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Syr. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> discou∣rage
none of his acquaintance to minister to
him; And when he was in <HI>Rome</HI> two yeares, <HI>he
dwelt in his owne hired house, and received all that
came unto him, preaching the kingdome of God, and
teaching with all liberty, no man forbidding him;</HI>
but Antichristian sectaries forbid all to publish
any doctrine against their way, as appeares in
<HI>Waldus,</HI> the Albingers, <HI>Husse, Jerom, Luther,</HI> &amp;c.
neither will they afford bread to eate, rayment
to put on, or house wherein to hide their heads,
or bed to rest upon, more cruell then bloudy
<HI>Nero</HI> to the Christians and Doctor of the Gen∣tiles.</P>
<P>Some read<NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">De suis sa∣cultatibus, Gloffa ordi∣naria.</NOTE> none of his goods were restrai∣ned
from him in his Imprisonment, but such
men take away both liberty and goods at
once.</P>
<P>Thirdly, observe the justice of the Romans,
<HI>Acts 25. 16. It was not the manner of the Romans to
give up a man, till his accuser came face to face,</HI> to
justifie the crimes objected, <HI>and that he have</HI>
<NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Syr. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE><HI>space and place to answer for himselfe;</HI> but among
Antichristians, no accuser shall appeare, but
the same man shall be accuser, Judge, and wit∣nesse;
or if he doe appeare, it shall be as a back∣biter,
not face to face; or if he confront the de∣fendant,
he shall have convenient place of Apo∣logy,
but among his enemies, to be derided as
<HI>Sampson</HI> was; or he shall have no space for his
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>
defence, but he must answer <HI>Oretenus &amp; ex tem∣pore,</HI>
according to their <HI>ex temporary</HI> prayers and
sermons: Is this justice? Likewise the Romans
stood much for the Liberty of the Subject, <HI>Acts
22. 25. Is it lawfull for you to scourge a Roman, and
uncondemned?</HI> The Orator said, that Citizens
of <HI>Rome</HI> may not be scourged, whether they were
borne Romans, or<NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Cives Roma∣ni verberibus caedi non pos∣sunt, <HI>Cicero.</HI> Nati, &amp; Civi∣tate do nati <HI>Ci∣ceo.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> made free, there were two
kinds; now Saint <HI>Paul</HI> was borne free, for his
Father was a<NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Oecumen,</NOTE> Roman, and<NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Chrysost. Oe∣cumen. Theo∣phylact.</NOTE> <HI>Cilicia</HI> was under
<HI>Rome,</HI> or <HI>Tarsus</HI> was called<NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Dio. Cassius.</NOTE> <HI>Juliopolis,</HI> howsoever
it were, he had the Liberty of a Subject and Ci∣tizen
of <HI>Rome;</HI> but if a mans goods be taken a∣way
by violence, and himselfe imprisoned,
where is the Roman Liberty? Pagans shall rise
up in judgment against Antichristians: Yet
more, the Romans rescued from violence such
as were Freemen, <HI>Acts 23. 10. The chiefe Cap∣taine
fearing lest</HI> Paul <HI>should be torne in peeces
in a Tumult, sent Romans to deliver him;</HI> farre it
was from him to send Troupes to destroy his
owne Citizens, as Antichristians have done: and
he further saith, <HI>Acts 23. 26. The Jewes tooke
this man, and I came with the</HI><NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Syr. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> <HI>Roman Souldiers
and rescued him, understanding that he was a Ro∣man.</HI></P>
<P>Lastly, they opposed all private ordinances,
and inventions of men, therefore <HI>Festus</HI> saith of
<HI>Paul, his accusers stood up against him,</HI><NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Syr.</NOTE> <HI>and could
prove no evill accusation against him as I supposed,
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>
but had certain questions of their own superstition,</HI>
private ordinances and inventions <HI>Act. 25. 18.
19.</HI> he stood for the Roman laws, which were so
good that the<NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Plutarc, in vita Cam.</NOTE> <HI>Falisci</HI> did chuse rather to serve
the Romans then to be free. The use hereof is in
<HI>Mal.</HI> 6. He hath told thee, O man, what the Lord
requireth of thee, <HI>to doe justly,</HI> as this Romane,
<HI>to love mercy,</HI> and to walk humbly with God,
which are the three and all to be imitated in this
Romane spirit.</P>
<P>Now briefly I come to the other three which
are to be avoyded. First, Popularity. Secondly,
Bribery. Thirdly, Obloquy.</P>
<P>1. Popularity, <HI>Acts 25. 2. Festus would
doe the Iews a pleasure,</HI> and <HI>Felix Acts 24. 27. be∣cause
he would doe the Iewes a pleasure he left</HI> Paul
<HI>bound,</HI> but this popular Aire is but a staffe of
reed bruised, and shaken with the winde, <HI>Gaius
Marius,</HI> who was seven times Consul, and the
third<NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Nobilium turba, Quiri∣lium Odi pro∣fanum vulgus &amp; atceo. Malignum spernere vul∣gus. Horat. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plutarch. in Mario.</NOTE> Founder of Rome, yet by envy expelled;
so <HI>Coriolanus</HI> and <HI>Scipio Africanus</HI> that wonne
his name<NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Ejus qui domita nomen ab Africa, Lucratus re∣diit. Incendia Car∣thaginis im∣piae. Rejectaeque retrorsum Hannibalis minae.</NOTE> from the subduing of <HI>Afrike,</HI> the bur∣ning
of <HI>Carthage,</HI> the victory over <HI>Hannibal,</HI> and
had marble inscriptions to his honour, yet loo∣sing
the popular respect, was banished for ever,
<HI>de repetundis.</HI></P>
<P>The people almost in one breath cryed <HI>Ho∣sanna,</HI>
and crucify him:<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Syr. Inscriproque notis marmo∣ra publicis.</NOTE> <HI>Herod Agrippa, Acts
12. 2. Killed Iames, and because it pleased the peo∣people
imprisoned Peter,</HI> under the custody of
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
<NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Syr. Non Vox hominem so∣nat.</NOTE>sixteen souldiers, but observe his end, the peo∣ple
cryed, The voice of a God not of a man, and
he became wormes meat. How can you please
God that seek honour one of another?</P>
<P>The second blemish in the Roman is bribery,
not expressed in the text, but implyed, <HI>he desired
to doe the Iewes a pleasure,</HI> it was hot for nothing.
And of <HI>Felix</HI> his predecessour it is said, <HI>he hoped
that money should have been given to him,</HI> by S<SUP>t</SUP>.
<HI>Paul, Act.</HI> 24. 26. The Romans were covetous, &amp;
therefore bitter was the <HI>Sarcasme</HI> of <HI>Methridate</HI>
upon them, that the Founders of Rome, <HI>Romulus</HI>
and <HI>Remus,</HI> were nursed by<NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Some say <HI>Lupa</HI> was a Woman.</NOTE> a hungry wolfe,
and therefore the posterity were so greedy of
wealth, that <HI>Tertullian</HI> saith, he not<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Non solum spcrabat, sed clam tracta∣bat.</NOTE> onely ho∣ped,
but privately dealt for bribes.</P>
<P>The third fault in this Romane was obloquy,
<HI>Acts</HI> 26. 24.<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Oecumen.</NOTE> out of wrath and fury, when S<SUP>t</SUP>.
<HI>Paul</HI> made his Apology, <HI>Festus</HI> exclaimed, <HI>Thou
art mad, much learning hath made thee mad;</HI> so the
limbes of Antichrist, <HI>Ieroboams,</HI> and <HI>Micah's</HI>
Priests, cry out, of learned men that they are
mad, because themselves cannot understand
them: If they be mad, it is for Christ; and oppres∣sion
oft times makes a wise man mad: but indeed
<HI>they are not mad, but speak forth the words of truth
and sobernesse,</HI><NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, 2 Tim. 1.</NOTE> They have not the spirit of bon∣dage
or feare, but of a sound mind.</P>
<P>Let us eschew bribery, popularity, and ob∣liquv,
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>
loquy, for who shall dwell in Gods Tabernacle?
First, <HI>He that backbitoth not with his tongue,</HI> that
makes not his tongue,<NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> his foot to trample the
reputation of his neighbour in the mire. Se∣condly,
<HI>In whose eyes a vile person is contemned,</HI>
therefore he is no man-pleaser. Thirdly, <HI>That
takes no reward against the Innocent,</HI> yea saith
<HI>Solomo Jarchi,</HI> that takes no reward to do ju∣stice;
therefore he is no briber, <HI>He that doth these
things shall never fall, Psal. 15. 1, 2, 3, 4. &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>Thus I have described a Roman spirit, and
compared the Romans and Antichristians to∣gether,
who are the greater persecutors; which
may be, first a premonition to us in these last
dayes, to expect perilous times for three yeares
and a halfe, <HI>Revel</HI> 11. 7. worse then those of
Jewes, Turkes, and Infidels; even the times of
Hypocriticall Antichristian Heretickes, 2. <HI>Tim.</HI>
3. 1. Secondly, an exhortation to patience, for
he that kills with the sword, shall be killed with
the sword; he that now leads into captivity,
shall be led; he that robbs, shall be robbed;
here is the patience<NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Revel. 13.</NOTE> of the Saints,<NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Zach. 9. 10.</NOTE> <HI>Returne
to the strong hold, yee prisoners of Hope, this day I
declare unto you, that I will restore double to
you.</HI></P>
<P>And as I have preached for Love and Peace,
so let us conclude with a Prayer, for the peace
of God that passeth all understanding, to guide
<PB N="19" REF="11"/>
our hearts and mindes in the knowledge and
love of our Lord Jesus Christ, to whom
with the Father and Holy spirit,
be honour and glory
throughout all
ages. Amen.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prayer">
<PB N="20" REF="12"/>
<HEAD>The prayer before SERMON.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">O</SEG> Eternall, the high and only<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">1. Tim. 6.</NOTE> Potentate, the
King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, before
whom thousands of<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Dan. 7.</NOTE> Angels doe minister,
and ten thousand times ten Thousand doe
stand before thee, who makest thy Angels
Spirits, and thy Ministers a flame of fire, who ridest on the
wings of the wind, and makest the cloud thy<NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Psal. 104. 2. 3. v.</NOTE> Pavillion,
and art clothed with glory and Majesty. At the foot-stoole
of thy Throne are we prostrate, sinfull dust and ashes, be∣seeching
the<NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Ezra 1.</NOTE> God of heaven to have mercy upon us mi∣serable
sinners. Have mercy on us, O Lord, and accor∣ding
to the<NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Psal. 51.</NOTE> multitude of thy mercies blot out our offen∣ces,
in thought, word, and deed, and thou that hast proclai∣med
the name of the Lord, the Lord God<NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Exod. 34.</NOTE> mercifull and
gracious, long-suffering, abundant in kindnesse and truth,
for giving iniquity, transgression and sinne, and shewing
mercy to thousands: shew mercy to us the chiefe of sinners,
forgive our<NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Psal. 51.</NOTE> originall sinne wherein we were borne, our
actuall sinnes, the sinnes of our youth; Remember not how
<NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Psal. 25.</NOTE>ignorant we have been of thy truth:<NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Psal. 19.</NOTE> Lord, who can
understand his errours, who knowes how often he hath of∣fended.
Then clense us from our secret sinnes, forgive our
presumptuous sinnes, perpetrated with a<NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Numb. 15.</NOTE> high hand, and
our rebellions wherin we have warred with the Almigh∣ty,
and keepe backe thy servants from the like iniquity, so
shall we be innocent, and avoid the great transgression, and
though we sin of weaknesse, or ignorance<NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 7.</NOTE> (for no man
lives on earth that sinneth not) yet restrainus by thy grace
from sins of stubbornnesse, which is as Idolatry, and from
the<NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Matth. 12.</NOTE> irremissible sin against the spirit of grace.<NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Iohn 17.</NOTE> Holy
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>
Father, we desire not only remission of sins, but the sancti∣fication
of the Holy Ghost, though sin tyrannize and dwell
in us,<NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Rom. 5. Galath. 5.</NOTE> so that we cannot do the things we would, yet let not
sin<NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Rom. 6.</NOTE> reigne in our mortall bodies, that we should obey it in
the lusts thereof, that we who are dead to sin, may live no
longer therein, but<NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Rom. 6.</NOTE> as Christ is risen from the dead, so we
may rise to newnesse of life, and as wee have yeelded our
members servants to iniquity, so to yeeld them weapons of
righteousnesse unto holinesse, the end whereof may be ever∣lasting
happinesse, and as we rise, so help us to ascend with
Christ to heaven, minding heavenly things,<NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Col. 3.</NOTE> where Christ
sits at Gods right hand, teach and enable us to doe justly, to
love mercy,<NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Micah 6.</NOTE> and walke humbly with our God, denying
ungodlinesse and worldly lusts, and walking holily, righ∣teously,
and soberly in this present evill world, waiting for
the<NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Titus 2.</NOTE> appearing of the glorious Judge to Judgement. Wee
believe O Lord, the way of man is not in himselfe, neither
is it in man to guide his steps, it is not in him that willeth,
nor that runneth, but in God that sheweth mercy, who hath
mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he
hardeneth. Give therefore grace, O heavenly Father, for
Christs sake: In whose name wee pray not onely for our
selves, but for the whole estate of Christs Church on
earth, distressed and dispersed. The Spouse of<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Lament. 1.</NOTE> Christ
sits as a widow that is desolate, her haire hanging downe,
rivers of teares falling from her eyes without intermissi∣on,
and it is nothing to all them that passe by the way,<NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Lament. 1.</NOTE> no
sorrow is like to her sorrow, yet none of her sons doth com∣fort
her, none doth turne out of the way to aske how shee
doth,<NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Lament. 2.</NOTE> the breach is like the wide sea, who can heale it?
there is no balme in Gilead, there is no Physitian there.
<NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Ier. 4.</NOTE>O thou sword of the Lord, when wilt thou bee quiet,
when wilt thou returne into the sheath, and bee at rest?
When, O Father of mercies, and Lord of hoasts, wilt thou
turne the edge thereof against the Heathen that know thee
<PB N="22" REF="13"/>
not, and call not on thy Name? Shall thy wrath burne
like fire against <HI>Germany,</HI> which before the Civill war
was as the garden of <HI>Eden,</HI> but now is a desolate wilder∣nesse,
and many yeares bath groaned under that unnatu∣rall
intestine war?<NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Psal. 90.</NOTE> Thou hast turned man to destru∣ction,
say likewise returne to life yee sons of men. Just art
thou, O Lord, to punish their Idolatry, sacriledge, and
high contempt of the Ministry;<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Habak. 3.</NOTE> but in the middest of
thy Justice remember Mercy: And forget not our bre∣thren
in <HI>Ireland,</HI> who have suffered cruell mockings,
scourgings, bonds, imprisonments, rapines, deaths under
the mercilesse Rebels, that curse<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Isay 8.</NOTE> their God and their
King, and looke upwards; They have bewed in pieces thy
Prophets, throwne downe thy worship, and killed thy ser∣vants
with a rage that<NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">2 Chron. 28.</NOTE> reacheth to heaven. Thy truth
falleth in the streets, and righteousnesse cannot enter. O
God of truth, justice, and vengeance, shew thy selfe, let not
the sons of wickednesse ever prevaile. More especially we
entreat for <HI>England,</HI> wherein we are a<NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Zephan. 2.</NOTE> Nation that is
not worthy to be beloved, for there is no truth, or mercy,
or<NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Hos. 4. 1. 2. 3. 4.</NOTE> knowledge of God in the Land, but by swearing, ly∣ing,
killing and stealing, we breake out, and bloud touch∣eth
bloud, wee have oppressed one another, and therefore
are justly<NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Gal. 5.</NOTE> devoured one of another, every one by the hand
of his neighbour, friend, and brother, <HI>Manasses, Ephraim,</HI>
and <HI>Ephraim Manasses,</HI> and every one eats the<NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Isay 9.</NOTE> flesh of
his owne arme, the son riseth up against the father, and
the father against the son, to put him to death, and they
<NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Iohn 16.</NOTE>thinke in so doing, they doe God good service. Who could
have thought that this flourishing Countrey should have
become a sea of bloud, and this <HI>Eden</HI> a dead sea? Oh the
severity of Gods justice against our sins<NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Ezek, 16.</NOTE> of Sodom, such
fulnesse of bread, abundance of idlenesse, and oppression
of the poore and needy; our crying sins have called for
plagues of leading into captivity, and complaining in our
<PB N="23" REF="13"/>
streets. Oh ever happy <HI>England,</HI> the glory of Nations is
now become the seat of Sects and Heresies, the daughter of
Babel, the mother of all confusion, Gods Temple pro∣phaned,
his Ministers misused, <HI>Jeroboams</HI> and <HI>Micaes</HI>
Priests of the lowest of the people substituted. To thee, O
Lord, we make our complaint:<NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Ezech. 20. last.</NOTE> This is, and shall be a
lamentation, <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"> Ierem. 13.</NOTE> O thou hope of Israel, the Saviour there∣of
in time of trouble, why shouldest thou be as a wayfaring
man, as a traveller that abides for a night? Awake, O
Lord, have mercy on Sion, that sits as a woman,<NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Ierem 30.</NOTE> or cast
away, that none looketh after; build up the wals of Jeru∣salem,
restore her Teachers, as at the beginning. Have
mercy on our dread Soveraign Lord, <HI>CHARLES,</HI> by the
grace of God, King of Great Britaine France and Ire∣land,
Defender of the true ancient Catholike, and Apo∣stolike
Faith, and in all causes, and over all persons Ec∣clesiasticall
and Tempor all supreme moderator and Go∣vernour,
bind up his Soule in the<NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 25.</NOTE> bundle of life with the
Lord his God, as for his enemies sling them as a stone out
of the middle of a sling, cloth them with shame, but upon
himselfe let his Crowne flourish. According to his pre∣sent
afflictions let thy Comforts refresh his soule. Give
not thy Honour to another, but for thy Names sake (who
hast said of Princes, yee are Gods Vicegerents) save the
face of thy Annointed from the tongues of men, and in the
middest of weapons of war, that no weapon framed against
him may prosper, that every tongue which shall rise up
against him, may be condemned, and he in due time re∣stored
to his former and greater royall splendor and digni∣ty,
and after this triall may come forth as gold: And as a
Father of the Country may pity his children, and lament
the shedding of the bloud of his sons and daughters. Blesse
the Queens most excellent Majesty, ourillustrious Prince
<HI>CHARLES,</HI> and the rest of the Royall Progeny, that
they may bee like Olive plants round about their Table,
suffer not the sonnes of wickednesse to afflict them. Wee
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>
pray likewise for the Lords of his Majesties most Hono∣rable
Privy Counsell, the True hearted Peeres and Com∣mons
assembled in Parliament: Give<NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Ephes. 4.</NOTE> them the spirit of
Vnity in the bond of Peace, the spirit of<NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Phil. 4.</NOTE> Moderation
betweene the two extreames, that by the wise accomoda∣tion,
this civill war may cease, the head and body may be
united, Religion restored, Sectaries and Heresies restrai∣ned,
and so Prince and people, Church and State their
due repayed, that wee may owe nothing,<NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Prov. 24. Rom. 13.</NOTE> but to feare
God, honour the King, and love one another. Vphold
the Ministers of thy holy Word, by what names or
titles soever dignified or distinguished, though they be
<NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Dan. 8.</NOTE>trampled under foot by Antichristians, yet raise them
up againe, to shine like Stars in the firmament, all clouds
of obscuration and opposition scattered and consumed, and
for a continuall supply of them, Blesse the two Vniversi∣ties,
<HI>Cambridge</HI> and <HI>Oxford,</HI> that from thence religious
and learned men may come forth, whose<NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Mal. 2.</NOTE> lips may pre∣serve
Knowledge, and disporse it thorow the whole Land,
that the<NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Psal. 107.</NOTE> mouth of ignorance and iniquity may be stop∣ped.
Remember all that are afflicted, especially thy ser∣vant
that desireth the prayers of this congregation: Oh
Father of mercies, and God of all consolations, comfort
those that be any Way cast downe. The living, the living,
shall<NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Isay 38.</NOTE> praise thee, the dead cannot praise thee, nor such as
go downe into silence; O great Physition of the bodies and
soules of thy servants, heale those whom thou hast woun∣ded;
<NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Ier. 10.</NOTE>Correct them, but in thy judgement, not in thy fu∣ry,
lest they be confounded. Neither ought we in this day
of humiliation, to forget our thankesgivings unto thee, O
Father of mercies, who hast chosen us in Christ before the
<NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Ephes. 1.</NOTE>foundation of the world was laid, to the glory of thy
grace, wherein we are accepted in thy beloved, who hast
called us with an holy calling, and sealed us with the ear∣nest
of the Spirit, who hast perswaded us of thy love here,
<NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Rom 8.</NOTE>and given us some hopes of glory hereafter, who hast fed
<PB N="25" REF="14"/>
us all our life long, even from our mothers brests, and will
beare us even in old age when our strength faileth us, who
hast led us by the Word and Spirit, and drawn us by cords
of love by the<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Hos. 11.</NOTE> bands of a man, who hast delivered us in
seven troubles and in eight, that they have not hurt us.
To thee<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Ioh. 5.</NOTE> bee glory and praise for ever and ever. Oh
let the thoughts of our hearts, the words of our mouths,
and the workes of our hands, be<NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Psal. 19.</NOTE> now and ever accepta∣ble
in thy sight. O Lord our strength and our Redeemer,
<NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Chro. 29.</NOTE>keepe these good imaginations in the hearts of thy people
for ever, and prepare our hearts unto thee, put thy feare
into us, and cause us to walke in the way of thy Comman∣dements,
that wee may never depart from thee; at this
time teach us the way, and lead us O God of our salva∣tion,
for we are children and cannot go. Help us by power
from on high, that wee may begin, continue, and end in
thee, by the helpe of Iesus: In whose Name and words we
conclude our prayers in the most<NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Matth. 6.</NOTE> absolute forme of
Prayer which he hath taught us in his holy Gospell.
<Q>Our Father, &amp;c.</Q></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

