<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Vox cœli, or, Nevves from heaven Of a consultation there held by the high and mighty princes, King Hen.8. King Edw.6. Prince Henry. Queene Mary, Queene Elizabeth, and Queene Anne; wherein Spaines ambition and treacheries to most kingdomes and free estates in Europe, are vnmasked and truly represented, but more particularly towards England, and now more especially vnder the pretended match of Prince Charles, with the Infanta Dona Maria. Whereunto is annexed two letters written by Queene Mary from heauen, the one to Count Gondomar, the ambassadour of Spaine, the other to all the Romane Catholiques of England. Written by S.R.N.I.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Reynolds, John, fl. 1621-1650.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A71313</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 20946.8</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 22096A</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S114764</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99849987</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99849987</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">17522</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A71313)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17522)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1584:16)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Vox cœli, or, Nevves from heaven Of a consultation there held by the high and mighty princes, King Hen.8. King Edw.6. Prince Henry. Queene Mary, Queene Elizabeth, and Queene Anne; wherein Spaines ambition and treacheries to most kingdomes and free estates in Europe, are vnmasked and truly represented, but more particularly towards England, and now more especially vnder the pretended match of Prince Charles, with the Infanta Dona Maria. Whereunto is annexed two letters written by Queene Mary from heauen, the one to Count Gondomar, the ambassadour of Spaine, the other to all the Romane Catholiques of England. Written by S.R.N.I.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Reynolds, John, fl. 1621-1650.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Scott, Thomas, 1580?-1626, attributed name.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[10], 60 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>Printed in Elesium [sic] [i.e. London] :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>s.n.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1624.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>S.R.N.I. = John Reynolds. Sometimes wrongly attributed to Thomas Scott.</NOTE><NOTE>The imprint is fictitious; correct place of publication from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>B1r, last line: 'his Palatinate'.</NOTE><NOTE>Formerly STC 22096a, identifed as such on UMI microfilm reel 1584.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Spain --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="fulc" R="UM" ID="A71313">
<STC T="S">20946.8</STC>
<STC T="S">22096A</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99849987</BIBNO>
<VID>17522</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>VOX COELI, OR, NEWES FROM HEAVEN.</P>
<P>OF A CONSVLTATION THERE HELD BY THE HIGH and mighty Princes, King HEN. 8. King EDW. 6. Prince HENRY. Queene MARY, Queene ELIZABETH, and Queene ANNE; wherein SPAINES ambition and treacheries to most Kingdomes and free Estates in EVROPE, are vnmaskd and truly represented, but more particularly towards ENGLAND, and now more especially vnder the pretended match of Prince CHARLES, with the Infanta DONA MARIA.</P>
<P>Whereunto is annexed two Letters written by Queene <HI>Mary</HI> from Heauen, the one to Count <HI>Gondomar,</HI> the Ambassadour of SPAINE, the other to all the Romane Catholiques of ENGLAND.</P>
<P><HI>Written by</HI> S. R. N. I.</P>
<P>Printed in Elesium. 1624.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE ILLVSTRIOVS AND GRAVE ASSEMBLY OF THE HIGH COVRT OF PARLIAMENT
The fruition of all Temporall Blessings. The felicitie of all Spirituall Blessings.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>LORDS. KNIGHTS. BVRGESSES.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>TO you who are the re-presentiue body of <HI>England,</HI> and the Ep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣tomie and Compendium of this great Volume of our Estate; To you who are assummoned by our King, and sent vp by our Country, to obay the first with your best Fidelities, to serue the second with your chiefest Zeale and endeuours, and to affect and honour both, with your most religious Prayers and wishes. To you from whom God for his glory, our Soueraigne for his honour and safety, and our Church and Common-weale for their flourishing well-fare and prosperity, doe expect much by your transcendent and honourable imployments: To you I say, and to no other, doe I present this Consultation (termed <HI>VOX Coeli</HI>) to your consideration, and dedicate it to your protection.</P>
<P>And because (in point of integrit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e and duty) I hold my selfe bound <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o bring the truth neerer to your knowledge, or rather home to your
<PB REF="3"/>
vnderstanding; May it please you to be informed, that about some three yeares since, at the first sitting of the last high Court of Parliament, when our King was so earnest in proposing the match of our Noble Prince his Sonne, with the <HI>Infanta</HI> of <HI>Spaine;</HI> When the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> cou∣lourably presented (though not really intended) to be d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>epely affected to entertaine and embrace the said motion; When Coun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>Gondmar</HI> (his Ambassador) made shew to be a zealous solicitour, and a most actiue and officious stickler for compassing and finishing it; When our Romish Catholiques became passionately, and insultingly confident of the free tollera<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lon of their Religion, and in the skie-reaching mountaines of their ambitions and superstitious hopes, were already preparing to erect their Groues and Altars, to set vp their Idols and Images, and consequently to introduce their Pope and his Masse in the Temples of our God; when all Prisons were vnlocked and open to all pernitious Priests and dange∣rous <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>esuites, and that many others <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> (Caterpillers and Vipers) came flocking and swarming from diuers parts of <HI>Europe,</HI> to poison and eate cut the soules of our people, with their Idolatrous doctrine of Antichrist, and to with-draw their hearts and consciences from their Alleagiance and Fideli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie, to their naturall Prince and Countrey, purposely (with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> treachery then Religion) to subiect them to a forraigne power and iurisdiction. When the Emperour had beaten the King of <HI>Bohemia</HI> from <HI>Prague,</HI> and the Duke of <HI>Bauaria</HI> with the assistance of the Swords, Soulders, and Treasure of the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> had in a setled truce as∣saulted and taken many Townes in the <HI>Palatinate,</HI> contrary to their pro∣mises to our King, and of his Maresties to the Prince his Sonne in Law, and contrary to the Publique peace of <HI>Germany</HI> aend Christendome. Then, then it was, (that to pull off the Maske of <HI>Spaines</HI> ambition and ma∣lice, who with the fire of this match sought to set <HI>England</HI> all flaming in a mournfull and miserable combustion) thereby to bury her glory in the dust, and her safety in the cinders of her subuersion and ruines) that as <HI>Prometheus</HI> fetch'd fire from heauen, so the fire of my zeale to the good of my Prince and Country, likewise fetch'd from thence this Royall con∣sultation for the discouery of our apparant and imminent dangers, and in knowing them, to know likewise how to preuent them; Which re∣soluing to m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke publiq<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e; because it solely re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ded to <HI>Englands</HI> pub∣lique <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and prosperitie: I contrary to my expectation (but not to my feares,) saw my hope<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> nip<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> in their blossoms, and my desires stis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed in their births, because the Seas of our Kings affection to <HI>Spaine</HI> went so
<PB REF="3" MS="y"/>
loftle, and the winder were so tempestious, that it could not possibly be permitted to passe the Pikes of the Presse: When albeit my zeale and fi∣delity againe and again infused new audacitie and courage to my resolu∣tions, to see it receiue the light yet it was imposible for mee or it, to bee made so happy, because I sawe <HI>Allureds</HI> honest letter, <HI>Scots</HI> loyall <HI>Vox Populy,</HI> D. <HI>Whiting,</HI> D. <HI>Euerard,</HI> and <HI>Clayto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s</HI> zealous Sermons, and others, suppressed and silenced, as also <HI>Wards</HI> faithfull picture, which yet was so innocent, as it onely breathed foorth his fidelity to <HI>England</HI> in si∣lent Rethorique, and dumbe eloquence. Wherevpon inforced to take a lawe from the iniquitie of the time, (with much reluctation and more greife) I bushed vp my said Consultations in silence, &amp; because I could not serue my Prince and Countrie in that Booke of mine: I therfore then renewed my constant resolution and zeale to serue them in my most seruent prayers, and my most religious and zealous wishes, the which I haue euer since faithfully and constantly performed.</P>
<P>Sitting thus to behold the constant inconstancie of the World, Which presents as many different accidents to our knowledge, as obiects to our eye; and being Iealous, Vigelant, and attentiue, to that which did, or which might any way appertaine to my Soueraigne and his Princely po∣steritie, to his Dominions and Subjects; I was enforced to see (O that I had beene so happie, as not to ban<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> seene) the perfidious progresse of <HI>Spaines</HI> now trecheries, and vsurpation vpon many countries of <HI>Eu∣rope;</HI> for first his Cousen <HI>Leopaldus</HI> hath deuoured the Dutchy of <HI>Cleaues</HI> and <HI>Iulleirs:</HI> then he and his forces haue taken many other free Townes, and whole Bishoprickes in the Countries of <HI>Luxembourg,</HI> and L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>Marke,</HI> as also in the frontiers of <HI>Swisserland</HI> and <HI>Loraine;</HI> Then he and his factor the Duke of <HI>Bauaria</HI> (for him) hath finished his absolute Conquest of the <HI>Pallatinate</HI> (that dainty, rich and fertile Prouince of <HI>Germany</HI>) the dowry of our onely Princesse, the inheritance of the Prince her Husband, and the Patrimonie of their Royall issue, wherein the honour of our King, and his three famous Kingdomes, doe most ex∣treamely suffer.</P>
<P>I saw him conquer the chiefest Cities, Forts, and Passages of the Gri∣sous, and hath brought their liberties and liues to their last gaspe and periode; yea, to the mercilesse mercy of his not generous but bloody sword; which being vnder the protection of the French King. doth likewise cast a wonderfull stay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e and blemish on the lustre of his honour and Crowne, if he speedily take not his reuenge thereof; by leauing these his honest <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as free as he found them, and as great <HI>Henry</HI> his
<PB REF="4"/>
Father left them. And after the Triumphes and treacherous progres∣sion of the house of <HI>Austria</HI> in <HI>Germany.</HI> The King of <HI>Spaine</HI> hath now made a body of his, and the Imperiall forces, and this Summer intends to play his bloody prize for the totall ruine and subuertion of the Nether∣lands, who (to the eye if the world, and to humaine iudgement) must shortly sinke if the two Kings of great <HI>Brittaine</HI> and <HI>France</HI> doe not make them swim; by speedily sending them braue succours and assistance in this their vrgent necessity.</P>
<P>And wherevnto tends all this treacherous ambition, and formidable vsurpation and greatnes of the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> but to cut out a passage with his sword, and to make his troopes &amp; Regiments fly o're the Alpes, for his erecting and obtaining of the Westerne Empire: And wherevnto tends it I say, but to make his territories and Dominions to encirculiz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> great <HI>Brittaine</HI> and <HI>France,</HI> yea to be their Cloyster, and to make and esteeme those two famous Monarchies, but onely as a fatall Church-yard to burie and interre themselues in.</P>
<P>But Illustrious and genero<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s Sirs, it this all the malice and treacherie which <HI>Spaine</HI> hath offered towards <HI>England;</HI> O no, nothing lesse, for vpon that Iournie (which was as dangerous as suddaine) of our Prince into <HI>Spaine</HI> (then whome the world hath not a brauer:) Hath not the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> dealt treacherously with him about his match with the <HI>Infants</HI> his Sister, yea haue they not in his Princely person, violeted the Lawes of Hospitality, and the priueledges of Princes (when being vn∣der his owne roofe) by attempting to tye him to formes, which were dia∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>etrally opposite to his honour; yea, to be so audatiously impudent, as with much violency and virulency to seeke to put a rape vpon his Conscience, and Religion, and proffered inforcement of his Conuersion to Popery; as if their <HI>Infanta</HI> had bin to him more pretious then his soule, or that he had bin so wretchedly grounded and instructed in pietie, that his Highnesse would haue forsaken his God purposely to haue obayed &amp; adored the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> who is not, nor cannot be a greater King then he is a Prince.</P>
<P>And to step yet a degree further; was it not a hellish pollicy, and a diabolicall designe and resolution of the Counsell of <HI>Spaine,</HI> to aduise our Prince vpon his returne into <HI>England,</HI> to waerre vpon the Protestants, and to proffer him an Army to suppresse and exterminate them. The Pro∣t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>stants, I say, who are those by whome our King his Father raingeth, and without whom his Maiesty can neuer subsist nor raigne; nor his Highnesse sucessi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ely aspire, or hope to aspire to his Crownes and King∣domes
<PB REF="4"/>
after him, sith they are the life, the vigour, the heart, and the soule thereof. And will our King, and our Prince, our Parliaments, and our Protestants of <HI>England,</HI> then euer forget this inueterate rage, and infernall malice of <HI>Spaine</HI> against them? as also the rest of their im∣perious and insulting cariage towards his Highnesse, and towards Great <HI>Brittaine,</HI> as if they priz'd i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> at so low a rate, and made their boundlesse ambition so excessinely ouer-valew their owne <HI>Spaine?</HI> that that were in the <HI>Crisis</HI> of her weakenesse and misery, and this in the prime and verti∣call point of her power and glory? And when his Highnesse pressed them for the restitution of the <HI>Pallatinate,</HI> which they had often promised to the King his Father, then they temporized so cunningly, and subtillized so trecherously with him, that euery day brought forth new delayes and dif∣ficulties, till in the end they had made the cure worse then the disease, and hauing taken firme footing therein, were enforced to vnuaile and vnmask their dissimulation, and faintly and coldly to affirme, that they would treat with the Emperour for the restitution thereof, but could not promise it: Thus hauing abused, first our King the Father, and then our Prince the Sonne, they haue now likewise betrayed and ruined our Princesse the Daughter in their finall Conquest, and resolute detention of the Prince her Husbands <HI>Palatinate,</HI> that Princesse I say, whose Royall and sublime vertues, make her the honour of her time, the ornament of her sexe, and the Phaenix Princesse of the world. Whereunto adding the absolute breach of the Match long since prophetically delacerated, and cast in Heauen by the Princely and Royall Authors of this Consultation, and since the same breach here on Earth likewise so happily confirmed by the King, as also by the Prince: so all these premisses considered, hath not <HI>En∣gland</HI> reason to hate <HI>Spaine,</HI> in regard <HI>Spaine</HI> hates it? especially be∣cause of these two maine ensuing points, and important considerations?</P>
<P>First, for that the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> is a greater, and more professed Enemy to our sacred King, and his Royall posteritie, then either the Em∣perour, or Duke of <HI>Baua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ia,</HI> and is to be held and esteemed of vs.</P>
<P>Secondly, that therefore to denounce Warre to him, and to make it good as soone as it is denounced, is as Honourable as necessary, and as iust as honourable for <HI>England;</HI> As vpon New-yeares day last I made these two points apparant and manifest to the King; in my Discourse intituled <HI>Votiuae Angliae,</HI> which I sent his Maiestie in the behalfe and fauour of the Prince <HI>Palatine</HI> his Sonne in law, for the restoration of his <HI>Palatinate.</HI></P>
<P><PB REF="5"/>Hauing thus (with as much disdaine as griefe) seene his inueterate malice towards great <HI>Brittaine,</HI> towards our King and his Royall poste∣ritie, and consequently the eminent dauger whereinto our profound secu∣ritie hath throwne and precipitated vs in particular; and vnderstanding likewise how the said King of <HI>Spaine</HI> with <HI>Xerxes,</HI> threatens the Seas and Mountaines of <HI>Europe</HI> in generall; Being as well in heart as tongue an Englishman, and therefore knowing by Grace, what I owe by Nature to my Naturall Prince and Countrey (like <HI>Cressus</HI> his dumbe Sonne) I would not, I could not be silent thereat, but must expose this Consultation of <HI>Vox Coeli</HI> to the light and sight of the world: I meane to the light of your knowledge, and the sight of your considera∣tion, vnder the secure Target, and safe shelter and Sanctuary of your auspicious protection.</P>
<P>To you therefore great <HI>Brittaines</HI> greatest Palladines and Cham∣pions, to you the inuincible Bulwarke of our King and his Royall Proge∣ny, and the inexpugnable Cittadel and <HI>Acrocorinth</HI> of our Estate: To you I say the Conscript Fathers of our supreamest Senate; doth it in dutie present it selfe, and in humilitie prostrate it selfe; which when your first leasure hath curiously read, and your best zeale carefully and maturely considered: Then by all that true English bloud which strea∣meth in your heart and veynes, by all the loue whic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> your Countrie beares you, and by all the dutie and affection which reciprocally you owe to your Country: I both request and coniure you, To tell our King that it is no∣thing for his Maiestie to haue made a braue and generous Declaration of Warres against <HI>Spaine,</HI> except hee speedily second it with execution, without which it will proue a vaine <HI>Fantasma,</HI> and an abortiue <HI>Embrion:</HI> Tell him, that it were the last Acts of <HI>Augustus,</HI> which embellished his raigne, and that old <HI>Pericles</HI> made the greatnesse of his generositie and courage, to reuiue and flourish on his Tombe, when hee caused the <HI>Athenians</HI> to warre vpon the <HI>Pelloponessians:</HI> Tell him that <HI>Philo∣paemenus</HI> affirmeth, that Peace is the best time to meditate of warre. Tell him that to transport Warre into <HI>Spaine,</HI> is to auoide and preuent it in <HI>England,</HI> as <HI>Hannibal</HI> said to King <HI>Antiochus,</HI> that the only way to make warre against the Romanes, was to begin it in the heart and bo∣wels of the Dominions of <HI>Rome,</HI> and so to vanquish <HI>Italy</HI> by <HI>Italy.</HI> Tell him that <HI>Plutarch</HI> affirmes there is no action so royall or magnifi∣cent in a King, as to take Armes to assist and reuenge his Confede∣rates vniustly oppressed and ruined, much more his owne Royall children,
<PB REF="5"/>
and that if the <HI>Palatinate</HI> be too farre, that <HI>Flanders</HI> and <HI>Brabant,</HI> are but the skirts and Suburbs to <HI>England.</HI> Tell him that <HI>Agesilaus</HI> said, that words are feminine, and deeds masculine, and that it is a great point of honour, discretion, and happines for a Prince, to giue the first blowe to his Enimies. Tell him that Spaniards hate vs; why then should we loue them? that we can beat them at our pleasures, why then should we feare them? Tell him that if it goe not well with <HI>Holland,</HI> it must needs goe ill with <HI>England;</HI> and that if wee doe not preuent their ruine, that wee cannot secure our owne danger. Tell him that in matters of warre, it is dangerous to make a stand, shamefull to retire, and glorious to aduance. Tell him that <HI>Philip</HI> of Spaine is of <HI>Pyrrhus</HI> his minde, who said, that hauing deuowred and conquered all <HI>Europe,</HI> he would end his dayes in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ollity and pleasure in <HI>Macedonia.</HI> And therefore that it is time, yea high time to strike vp our Drums against him, aswell because our saftie, as our honour inuites vs to it.</P>
<P>And now turning from his Maiestie, to you the Illustrious and famous body of this great and famous Court of Parliament (whereof the King is the head) to you, I say, who are the creame and flower of his Subiects: O hold it no disparagement tha I tell you; that sith in all matters of Order, Policie and reformation, that delayes and protractions proue still dangerous, many times fatall: That you beware least as your Con∣sultations flie away with the time; That occasion and opertunitie flie not away with your Consultations, sith time must be taken by his forelocke, and then as <HI>Iulius Caesar</HI> saieth, we haue winde and tide with vs.</P>
<P>Thinke what a happines, what a glorie it is for <HI>England</HI> to haue wars with <HI>Spaine,</HI> sith <HI>Spaine</HI> in the Lethirgie of our peace, hath very neere vndermined our safetie, and subuerted our glory; And let vs dispell those charmes of securitie, wherein <HI>England</HI> hath beene too long lul'd and en∣chanted a sleepe: And if feare &amp; pusillanimitie, yet offer to shut your eyes against our safetie, yet let our resolution and courage open them to the im∣minency of our danger; that our glory may surmount our shame, and our swords cut those tongues and pennes in pieces, which henceforth dare ei∣ther to speake of peace▪ or write of truce with <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
<P>No, no; to take the length of <HI>Spaines</HI> foote aright, we must doe it with our swords, not with our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ecks, for the first will assuredly establish our safe∣ty, and the second infaliby ruines it. Wars, Wars, then ye (with cheere∣full hearts and ioyfull soules) let vs prepare our selues for Warrs: That our great <HI>Brittaine</HI> (the beautie of <HI>Europe</HI> as <HI>Europe</HI> is the glory of the
<PB REF="6"/>
world) lie no longer exposed to the apparant danger, and merciles mer∣cy of this Castilian Rat, of this Crocodile of <HI>Italy,</HI> of this vulture of <HI>Germany,</HI> and af this woolfe of <HI>Ardena;</HI> but let vs all signaliz our fi∣delities to our Soueraigne by our courage, and immortaliz our zeale to our Country by our valour and resolutions herein: That we may all be of <HI>Alcibiades</HI> his opinion, that the bed of honour is the best death, that there is no better recompence of death then glory, nor no richer glory, then to dye for our Prince and Country.</P>
<P>And here I had imposed silence to my penne, and infused a period to this my Epistle, had not the dignitie of your places, the quality of your im∣ployments, the nature of the time, and the consideration that I am an Englishman, commaunded me to insert and annex these few lines, by the way either of a supplement, or a post-script.</P>
<P>Although I can adde nothing to your affection and care, for the good of our Country, yet giue me leaue (I beseech you) to substract this from mine owne fidelitie and zeale.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 That you be carefull that your warres (both by sea and land) be plentifully stored with money, powder and shot, which indeed is the veignes and Arteries, the sinewes and soule of warre.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 That you crye downe all gold and siluer Lace, and all silkes, Vel∣uets, and Taffities, and crie vp woole cloath, and blacke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and Corslets insteede thereof, that thereby <HI>England</HI> as a blacke and dismall cloud, may looke more martiall and terrible to our Enimies.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 That our English Romanists may be taught either to loue, or to feare <HI>England.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>4 That there be prouision made, and especiall care had to secure his Maiesties Coasts, Seas. and Subiect from the Ships of warre of <HI>Dun∣kerke</HI> and <HI>Ostend,</HI> by whome otherwise they will be extreamely indoma∣ged and infested.</ITEM>
<ITEM>5 That by some who'some Statute and Order, you cleanse the Citties and Countrie, the Streets and highwaies from all sort of Beggers, by pro∣uiding for their labour and reliefe, whereby many hundred thousand Christian soules will pray vnto God for his Maiesty, and to power downe his blessings vpon all your Designes and Labours, whereby without doubt our Warres will succeed and prosper the better.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>I will no further vsurpe on your patience: But here (withdrawing the Curtaine of this Preface) inuite your eyes and thoughts to the sight and consideration of this consultation,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>S. R. N. I.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="introduction">
<PB N="1" REF="6"/>
<HEAD>The introduction,</HEAD>
<P>HEauen being Gods Throne, and the Earth his Footstoole, it is impossible any thing can be here spoken and acted, but will there be heard, reuealed and detected; for not onely our hearts but our thoughts, not onely our tongues but our in∣tents, lye open and are obuious and transparent, to the glorious, and relucent eyes of Gods most sacred Maiestie, who being the sole Ar∣chitector, and preseruer both of Heauen and Earth, rules that by his presence, this by his prouidence, and both by his power; and that wee Men are not by many thousands degrees so great in his eyes, as the smallest Pysmires are in ours; who lookes still in our Designes and Actions, sometimes with approbation; now with pitie, then with contempt, and anon with Choller and indignation, being himselfe the prime President, the great Moderator, the mighty Councellor, the eternall and euerlasting Iehouah; who can and will giue Lawes to all the Kings and Princes of the earth, as they doe to their subiects by their subordinate, and yet transcendent power, drawne from his most sacred Maiestie of Heauen, as the Starres who actually deriue their light, and borrow their lustre from the refulgent beames, and glorious body of the Sun.</P>
<P>And as this great God seated in his Coelestiall throne of Glory, with his All▪seeing and sacred eyes beholds in Heauen the thoughts and actions of men here on Earth: so likewise out of his indulgent mercy and prouidence, he likewise giues the same authority and po∣wer to his Angels, Saints and Martyrs, to doe the like; who clad in white Robes, the Ornaments of sanctity and purity, with Palme branches in their hands, the Emblemes of Peace and Ioy, and Crowns and Coronets on their heads, the rewards and markes of Glory, Fol∣low the Lamb Christ Iesus wheresoeuer hee goe, still singing these ioyfull <HI>Io Peans</HI> and <HI>Epithalamians</HI> of <HI>Haleluiah,</HI> and Glory be to God on high, Peace on earth, and good will towards men.</P>
<P>By vertue of which Diuine priuiledges, the maske of <HI>Spaines</HI> boundlesse Ambition being discouered and pull'd off, in supporting the Pope, and seeking the increase of his spirituall Iurisdiction, whereby his Holinesse in Exchange, may enlarge that of <HI>Spaines</HI> temporall Monarchie, so as that shall haue feete to goe, and these
<PB N="2" REF="7"/>
wings to flie to the height of earthly greatnesse; whereby the <HI>Ca∣tholique</HI> Kings ayme, out of the ruines of <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Germany,</HI> to erect another Empire in the west, and endeauour by degrees to make most of the Kingdomes and Free Estates of <HI>Europe</HI> become Prouin∣ces vnto Spaine; as, some by force, some by policie, some by treache∣rie, and now <HI>England</HI> by the match of the <HI>Infanta</HI> his Daughter, with our most Illustrious and Royall Prince <HI>Charles</HI> (next to his Royall Father King <HI>Iames,</HI> our most dread Soueraigne) the hope of <HI>En∣glands</HI> life, and the life of it's ioy and hope.</P>
<P>I say the newes of these proiects and resolutions of <HI>Spaine,</HI> hauing with as much fortunary as celeritie, passed the cloudes, and peirced the Vaults and windowes of Heauen, it fast arriued there, to the vn∣derstanding of that immortall Mayden Queene <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> whose heart euer loued <HI>England,</HI> as her soule did Heauen, and of whose flourishing wellfare and prosperity I cannot truely auerre, whether she still remaine more iealous or ambitious? whereat grieuing with as much disdaine, as she disdained with griefe, and knowing that her Nephew and God-sonne Prince <HI>Henry,</HI> participated and burned in her zeale, that the insatiable and blood-thirsty ambition of <HI>Spaine,</HI> might not erect his Trophees vpon the Tombe of <HI>Englands</HI> down∣fall, and the ruines of her subuersion, shee speedily acquaints him with it, whome although heauen had purified and deuested of his Earthly passions, yet such was this young prince, his neuer dying zeale to <HI>Englands</HI> euer liuing glory that his Highnesse could not re∣fraine from looking red with anger, and pale with feare, at the re∣port and knowledge thereof. They consult hereon and hold it both expedient and necessary to acquaint other English Princes herewith, especially those whome they knew stood deeply and sincerely affe∣cted to <HI>England.</HI> So Prince <HI>Henry</HI> acquaints his Mother Queene <HI>Anne</HI> herewith, and Queene <HI>Elizabeth</HI> her Brother King <HI>Edward</HI> 6. and both their Father king <HI>Henry</HI> 8. who so vppon aduise here∣of, could not refraine to looke on <HI>England</HI> with the eyes of affe∣ction and pitty, and on <HI>Spaine</HI> with those of indignation and con∣tempt. So these fiue great Princes &amp; Queenes prepare themselues to Consult on this most important busines, when loe they are suddenly met and assayled, with a doubt of no meane consequence and consi∣deration <HI>viz.</HI> Whether, or no, they should admit &amp; receiue Queene <HI>Mary</HI> into this their Consultation, whom not her <HI>Romane</HI> merits, but
<PB N="3" REF="7"/>
the prayers of the <HI>Protestants</HI> had brought to Heauen; When at first they considering that in heart and soule, she alwayes loued, and pre∣ferred <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Spain</HI> before <HI>England;</HI> they resolued to exclude her, but at last (vpon riper and more mature deliberation) considering that she knew many secrets of <HI>Spain,</HI> wherof peraduenture they were ignorant; as also that from her innate and inueterate malice to <HI>Eng∣land,</HI> shee might (either in iest or earnest) bewray something that might turne and redound to the good of <HI>England,</HI> they all consented she should be aduertised hereof, and so admitted; which was instant∣ly performed; and as the rest of these Royall Princes enuied <HI>Spaines</HI> ambition, and pitied <HI>Englands</HI> dangers; So to speake the truth, and no more, Queene <HI>Mary</HI> (still resembling herselfe) both in her spee∣ches and lookes testified the contrary; Vowing that as she loued <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hi∣lip</HI> the II. the Father, so she would still honour <HI>Philip</HI> the III. his Son.</P>
<P>Thus these three Princes, and three Queenes, not daring to con∣sult in Heauen on any thing, without permission of the Superiour powers, they all repayre to the sacred throne of the Lambe, (of that Great Maker and conductor of Heauen and Earth) whose Tribunall is enuironed with more sparkling and burning Sunnes, then we see Starres in the Firmament; and who is waited and attended on by many millions and Meryades of Angels; Where in signe of Gods glory and their humilitie, these Royall personages fall on their faces to his blessed feet, and so proffer vp their Petition to his heauenly Maiestie to haue authority, and place giuen them to Consult on this important businesse betwixt <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
<P>Their Petition read and considered, God out of the profunditie of his immense affection and fauour, towards the prosperity of <HI>England,</HI> (Wherein for the space of well neere One hundred yeares, his Sa∣cred Maiestie hath seen himselfe truely serued and glorified) ratifies their request, and approues and authoriseth their sitting; When de∣parting from Gods most sacred Throne; they were by a full Quire of Angels with Trumpets and Tymbrels in their hands, vshered into the golden Starre-Chamber of Heauen, which was purposely pre∣pared for them; when taking their seuerall seates, the doore shut, and guarded by <HI>Englands</HI> Tutulary Angell, with a naked brandished sword in his hand, all thinges being hushed vp in silence, and all heauenly duties and ceremonies performed, these sixe Royall perso∣nages begin their Consultation in this manner.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="consultation">
<PB N="4" REF="8"/>
<HEAD>The Consultation.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>BEfore we descend to speake of <HI>Spaines</HI> ambition and Enu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e towards <HI>England,</HI> or the Match now in question betwixt <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Spaine,</HI> with the dangers which threaten, and presage vs will ensue thereof, it will not be impertinent, rather necessary; that we mount vp the steps of this last century of yeares, and so take a cursory, though not a curious suruey, with what Ambition and Cru∣eltie, and Treachery, the Kings of <HI>Spaine</HI> from time to time, haue knocked at most Kingdomes and Estates of <HI>Europe;</HI> in the vnfol∣ding and dilating whereof, you must not expect much light from me, rather I from your selues, sith as your yeares so your raignes succeeded me.</P>
</SP>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<HEAD>Nauarre.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>ANd as you all know my yeares were so few and my raigne so short, that neither these, nor this, made me capable to diue into the affaires of Princes and Kingdomes, and yet I must confesse it was both with griefe and pitie, that I reade, with what vsurpation and trechery, <HI>Ferdinand</HI> King of <HI>Arragon</HI> depriued <HI>Iohn</HI> of <HI>Albert,</HI> and <HI>Katherine</HI> his Queene of their flourishing Kingdome of <HI>Nauarre,</HI> who for meere griefe and sorrow dyed immediatly after, hauing no other claime nor title to this Kingdome, but an insatiable desire of Empire and Dominion, which the <HI>Aragonois,</HI> and <HI>Castil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣ans</HI> wonne with their Swords.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but <HI>Nauarre</HI> lay fit and commodious for the Prouin∣ces of old <HI>Castille, B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>iscay,</HI> and <HI>Galicia,</HI> besides, the Kings of <HI>Spaine</HI> are the <HI>Catholique</HI> Kings, and therefore it is both proper and naturall for them to be Vniuersall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is indeed both naturall and proper to them to bee ambi∣tious and tyrannicall, for I am confident, that as Catholique as they are, they loue Earths Empire, better then Heauens Glory; and sure I cannot but lament to see <HI>Nauarre</HI> made a Prouince to <HI>Spaine,</HI> which more is the griefe of Christendome, and the shame of the Royall line of <HI>Burbon,</HI> now the <HI>French</HI> Kings, whose patrimonie and inheri∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> it is, and will not King <HI>Lewes</HI> recouer it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="5" REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had Great <HI>Henry</HI> his Father liued, he would vndoubtedly haue conquered <HI>Nauarre</HI> with as much glory, as it was lost with shame and pitie; yea, the Turrets of <HI>Pampelone,</HI> and <HI>Fonteraby,</HI> had long since cast off the ragged Staffe, to beare out the three Flower <HI>de Luces.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>So might King <HI>Lewes</HI> his Sonne too, if the <HI>Pope</HI> and <HI>Ie∣suites</HI> diuerted not his thoughts from that honourable and glorious Enterprise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Surely it is against the lawes of Conscience, and the rules of Religion, for the Kings of <HI>Spaine</HI> thus to vsurpe <HI>Nauarre,</HI> or were they so iust, as they pretend they were holy, they would restore and not retaine this Kingdome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O the Cath<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lique Kings are too wise to commit such grosse errours of State, as to restore; for it is Conquest and Possessi∣on, and no way restitution, which af<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oords them best melody; Be∣sides, sith they are the <HI>Catholique</HI> Kings, they cannot be irreligious much lesse vncharitable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then Daughter, the Kings of <HI>Spaine</HI> are of <HI>Pirrhus</HI> and <HI>Lysande<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s</HI> minde, whose limits and confines of their Countries they held so farre, as their Swords and Lances could extend them. Which being so, they are only <HI>Catholique</HI> in title, not in effect, much lesse in heart or soule, for if Vsurpation bee Religion, I know not what is Heresie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>The <HI>Pope</HI> may, but our Sauiour <HI>Christ,</HI> neuer authorized or approued Vsurpation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the Kings of <HI>Spaine</HI> know the <HI>Popes</HI> will and plea∣sure, as they doe Gods, and this beliefe I am sure is both <HI>Catholique</HI> and <HI>Apostolicall.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, see with how much Ignorance and wilfulnesse, with what blinde zeale and po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re implicit faith, my Sister is perpetually lincked to <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>If so Vsurpation be <HI>Romes</HI> Doctrine, and <HI>Spaines</HI> delight and practise, my soule did well to make me hate the one, and detest the other.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<HEAD>The West Indies, or new Spaine.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>BVt leaue wee <HI>Nauarre</HI> weeping and groaning vnder the burthen of the miserable seruitude to <HI>Spaine;</HI> O how since
<PB N="6" REF="9"/>
<HI>Columbus de Cortez,</HI> and <HI>Pizarro,</HI> (with as much iudgement as for∣tunacy) discouered to <HI>Castille</HI> the rich <HI>America,</HI> and in it the Gold and Siluer Mines, which hath giuen wings to his Ambition to flie to the height of this earthly Greatnesse, wherein wee see <HI>Spaine</HI> seated and founded; How it hath both grieued and amazed me to vnder∣stand, how at <HI>Cuba, Hayta, Peru, Panama,</HI> and <HI>Mexico,</HI> and in all these vast Iles and spacious Continents, that the <HI>Spaniards</HI> with a more then hellish Cruelty, haue slaine such infinite Millions and Meryades of those poore <HI>Indians,</HI> whereby in a manner they haue wholly depopulated these populous Countries, and not onely made riuers but whole seas of their Bloud; and of whose inhumane and bloudy Cruelty, I may iustly say; that as all former ages cannot shew the like President, so our posterity will difficulty beleeue it. And yet behold the horrible Hipocrisie of these insulting and vsurping <HI>Castillians;</HI> for demaund them the reason of these their bloudy and execrable Massacres, of those poore armelesse and harmlesse <HI>Indians,</HI> and of the rooting out and exterminating of all their Princes and No∣bility, they with as much falshood as impiety will affirme, that sith their King is the Catholique King, so this is to plant the Catholique faith in the remote, and new found Worlds of the World; whereby we may obserue, that Religion must still be the pretext, and cloke of their bloudy Vsurpation, when Heauen and Earth knowes and sees, that it is first gold, then a greedy desire of Dominion and Empire, which is the true cause, and sole obiect thereof.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if that bloudy resolution, against these huge numbers of poore Indians tooke place in the heart and councell of <HI>Charles</HI> 5. must it needes follow that the like inhumanity and cruelty should liue in this of <HI>Phil.</HI> 2. and <HI>Phil.</HI> 3. his Sonne and Grand-childe: so as this bloud-thirsty malice of spleene and gall against these poore In∣dians, must be heriditary to the Kings of <HI>Spaine,</HI> as now by custome and intrusion, (and by the ignoble coniuencie of the Princes Ele∣ctors) the ambition to enioy the Empire of <HI>Germany,</HI> is to the house of <HI>Austria,</HI> from whence they are descended.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<PB N="7" REF="9"/>
<HEAD>Portingall.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>MY royall Father obserued well, that Religion was onely the pretext, but wealth and Empire the sole ob∣iect of <HI>Spaines</HI> ambition; for although <HI>Charles</HI> the 5. vsurped those places of <HI>America</HI> from the Indians, who indeede knew not Christ; yet what Religion or Catholique was that of <HI>Philip</HI> the 2, his Sonne, vnder hand to precipitate, and throw <HI>Se∣bastian</HI> King of <HI>Portingall,</HI> into the vnnecessary and vnfortunate warres of <HI>Affrica</HI> against the Moores, where hee losed his life with his ambition: and then after his decease, to worke so on the impotency, feare, and ignorance, of olde King <HI>Henry</HI> his suc∣cessour, as (contrary to the lawes of Iustice and Nature) to enforce him to illigitimate <HI>Don Anthony</HI> the Prior of <HI>Crato,</HI> who was the first and neerest heire vnto that Crowne and Kingdome, thereby to exclude him as indeede hee did, or if he had not an itching and longing desire to swallow and deuoure that Kingdome of <HI>Portin∣gall;</HI> which all Christendome and <HI>Rome</HI> her selfe knew was still more Catholique then <HI>Spaine;</HI> yea, and then when hee had ingaged his Royall word to the rest of the Pretendants, as the aforesaid <HI>Don Anthony,</HI> the Dukes of <HI>Sauoy</HI> and <HI>Parma, Katherine</HI> of <HI>Maedicis</HI> (Queene mother of <HI>France</HI>) and <HI>Katherine</HI> Dutchesse of <HI>Braganca;</HI> that hee with them would stand to the sentence of the Chamber of <HI>Lisbone,</HI> to know to whom the right of that Kingdome most pro∣perly and lineally descended. That then this King <HI>Philip</HI> the 3. for∣gat his conscience to God, and his promise to these Princes (fearing others right, and distrusting his owne) brought an Army to the gates of <HI>Lisbone,</HI> ere the Pretendants, or <HI>Portingalls</HI> themselues dreampt thereof, or had meanes or leasure to defend themselues, wherby such was his insatiable ambition, vsurpation, &amp; couetousnes, that in a plaine and setled peace, hee deuoured this rich and noble Kingdome; making it not onely tributary but a Prouince to <HI>Spaine.</HI> And was this also Religion, or to plant the Catholique faith? or rather was it not manifest treacherie, and apparant vsurpa∣tion, such if <HI>Don Anthony</HI> had not, all the world knowes, the Dutches of <HI>Braganca</HI> had more right to this Kingdome then King <HI>Philip.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="8" REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, that policy King <HI>Phil.</HI> learnt of the Emperour <HI>Charles</HI> 5. his Father, who when himselfe, and King <HI>Francis</HI> the first of <HI>France.</HI> contended for the Empire of <HI>Germany,</HI> whiles <HI>Francis</HI> was bribing of the Electors, <HI>Charles</HI> brought an Armie into the field and so enforced them to elect and choose him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must confesse I euer held the <HI>Portingalls</HI> to be zea∣lous and good Romane Catholiques; but as <HI>Nauarre</HI> lay fit for <HI>Bis∣cay</HI> and <HI>Galicia,</HI> so <HI>Portingall</HI> lay exceeding comodious for <HI>An∣doulosie;</HI> and if my husband King <HI>Philip,</HI> had not seconded his right of descent by the law of his sword, perhaps he might haue had a bad neighbor in <HI>Portingall,</HI> which he and his counsell timely fore-see∣ing they as wisely preuented. And howsoeuer, although he hated <HI>Don Anthonie,</HI> yet I know he loued the Dutches of <HI>Braganca</HI> well; but When we speake of Crownes and kingdomes, Religion will make his surprise of <HI>Portingall</HI> a matrer of State, though to speake truth, State can neuer make it a matter of Religion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>How Well King <HI>Phillip</HI> loued the Dutches of <HI>Braganca,</HI> I know not, but this I am sure of, that both <HI>Monsieur de Boysise Monsieur de Bissea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>x,</HI> and <HI>Monsieur de Marais,</HI> (Ambassadours with King <HI>Iames</HI> my Husband; for the two last French Kings, <HI>Hen∣ry</HI> 4. and <HI>Lewes</HI> 13.) tolde me, that <HI>Philips</HI> hatred and rage was so great against <HI>Don Anthony,</HI> that he begged his body, which lyes in a Coffin of Lead, in the <HI>Cord-liers</HI> Church at <HI>Paris,</HI> to be deliuered his Ambassadours, and so sent him into <HI>Spaine;</HI> but as they said, these two most Christian <HI>Kings</HI> their Masters answered <HI>Philip,</HI> that there was little Religion, lesse charity, to take vp, and remoue the ashes of a dead Prince and King, as was <HI>Don Anthony,</HI> and so his body still remeanes in <HI>Paris.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>If <HI>Spaine</HI> were so malicious to a dead Prince, how ought those that are liuing to beware and take heed of him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>As a guilty conscience can neuer finde <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>est, so it may be that King <HI>Philip</HI> was afraid of a second <HI>Don Anthony,</HI> as of a second <HI>Se∣bastian.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>But King <HI>Philip</HI> 3 his sonne, hath farre more reason to feare <HI>Don Anthony</HI> his two Princely sonnes, <HI>Don Emanuel,</HI> and <HI>Don Chri∣stopher,</HI> and of <HI>Don Emanuell,</HI> his two generous and Illustrious Sonnes, <HI>Don Maurice</HI> and <HI>Don Lewes,</HI> all foure liuing who are fa∣m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>os, and Royall reserued Peeres of Shipwracke of that Royall
<PB N="9" REF="10"/>
Kingdome and blood of <HI>Portingall.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but they are poore, and want friends and meanes to ad∣vance their iust title to that Crowne if they haue any.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Their right and title to <HI>Portingall</HI> is iust, and therefore can∣not, and should not dye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>If the French forces had met mine at the <HI>Groyne, Peneca,</HI> or <HI>Lisbone,</HI> or had the <HI>Portingals</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>isen, my <HI>Norris, Drake,</HI> and noble <HI>Essex,</HI> in despight of <HI>Philip</HI> and his forces, had pluck'd the Crowne of <HI>Portingall</HI> from his head, and set it on King <HI>Anthonies.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no: <HI>Don Anthonies</HI> Sonnes are beloued of the Nobili∣tie of <HI>England, France,</HI> and the <HI>Netherlands,</HI> and <HI>Don Emanuels</HI> wife, is Sister to that valiant and incomparable Captaine <HI>Maurice</HI> of <HI>Nas∣saw,</HI> Prince of <HI>Orenge.</HI> So if fortune smile, and a fauourable gale blow, these disinherited <HI>Portingall</HI> Princes may one day proue pricks and thornes to the sides of <HI>Spaine.</HI> For all <HI>Portingall</HI> knowes, that their veines and hearts streame with pure <HI>Portingall</HI> blood; yea, with the remainder of the royall blood of that Kingdome, which <HI>Philip</HI> 3. his last entertainment (together with the Prince his sonne) at <HI>Lisbone,</HI> had almost found true: but that his Maiestie departed with as much feare, secresie, and shame, as he came with resolution, popularitie, and glory: in the interim, these <HI>Portingall</HI> Princes re∣maine prodigious and ominious Commets to <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did <HI>Spaine</HI> thinke so, it would quickly make these Prin∣ces ride Poast into another world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>If <HI>Spaine</HI> should send these Princes Poast into another world, either by the b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cke doore of poyson, by the wicket of a Pon∣yard, and not by the great and fore-dore of Nature, it would draw the fists of most Christian Prince, about King <HI>Philips</HI> eares, and make all <HI>Portingall</HI> solemnize their Funerals with their swords drawn, and their Cities gates shut.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede I haue heard that the Commons, and especially the Nobillitie of <HI>Portingall</HI> begin extreamly to distaste the imperious pride and ambitious carriage of the Spaniards, as many of them let not to say boldly and publiquely, that <HI>Phillip</HI> enioyes the King∣dome by vsurpation and n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t by right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not by right? Why Pope <HI>Gregory</HI> 14. approued his Title and confirmed his Conquest of the Kingdome of <HI>Portingall.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>So did not our Sauiour Christ, whose Successour and Vicar
<PB N="10" REF="11"/>
the Pope pretends himselfe to be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>In the meane time <HI>Spaine</HI> domineeres at her Conquest of <HI>Portingall,</HI> and well shee may; for it is one of the fairest flowers of his Garland, and of the richest Diamonds of his <HI>Crowne.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8,</SPEAKER>
<P>But the other Kings of Christendome haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ust cause and reason to grieue and storme hereat; for as it was <HI>Portingals</HI> mis∣chance then to fall, and vaile Bonnet to <HI>Spaine,</HI> so it may be theirs to morrow; for to a Prince and people so greedy and ambitions of Em∣pire as is <HI>Spaine,</HI> all fish is good that comes to his hooke or net.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus <HI>Spaine</HI> deuoures Kingdomes as the <HI>Cyclope Polephe∣mus</HI> did passengers; for he surprizeth no more then he meetes with∣all, and yet will not Chirstendome beware of <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<HEAD>Italy.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVE haue past from <HI>Nauarre,</HI> the <HI>West Indies, &amp; Portin∣gal,</HI> &amp; now let vs come to <HI>Italy</HI> to see how <HI>Spain</HI> is be∣loued or feared of the Italians, &amp; how he hath behaued himselfe there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>In <HI>Italy</HI> the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> is nayled to the Pope, as most of the Colledge of Cardinals, and all die Iesuites are to him; yea, he hath the greatest and richest territories thereof, as the Kingdome of <HI>Naples,</HI> the Dutchy of <HI>Millane,</HI> and the Island of <HI>Cicily,</HI> and (in a mannet, the Marquesse of <HI>Monaco,</HI> and <HI>Finall,</HI> the Dukes of <HI>Mon∣toua, Parma</HI> and <HI>Vrbin;</HI> the Princes of <HI>Massa,</HI> and <HI>Piombino,</HI> with the States of <HI>Genoua</HI> and <HI>Luca,</HI> doe all march vnder his banner, and call onely on his name; yea, he hath so incircled the Pope as hee is rather his Prisoner, then his spirituall Father; for if his Patrimony of St. <HI>Peter</HI> be the Temple, his <HI>Naples</HI> and <HI>Millane</HI> is the Cloyster to impall it, so as he hath no impeachment or obstacle from making himselfe sole Lord of <HI>Italy,</HI> but the great Duke of <HI>Tuscany,</HI> and the prudent and potent Seignorie of <HI>Uenice.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but the Pope neede not feare the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s <HI>Spaine</HI> is the Popes hand, so the Pope is <HI>Spaines</HI> tongue: For the Catholike King is his Holinesse Champion; and his Holinesse the King of <HI>Spaines</HI> Oracle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had thought that the Popes alwayes loued the Kings of <HI>France</HI> better then those of <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no: there is reason to the contrary; for <HI>Spaine</HI> hath re∣ceiued <HI>Romes</HI> hellish and bloudy Inquisition, and <HI>France</HI> is so wise and couragious, as it reiecteth and disdaines it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="11" REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, there is another reason likewise; for although the former Kings of <HI>France</HI> were braue and victorious, yet king <HI>Lewes</HI> that now is feares the Pope and loues him not, whereas King <HI>Phillip</HI> of <HI>Spaine</HI> loues him, but feares him not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>If the Popes had not loued <HI>Spaine,</HI> they would neuer haue giuen him <HI>Naples</HI> and <HI>Cicily,</HI> nor permitted him to enioy that rich and populous Dutchy of <HI>Millan,</HI> which is the Patrimony of the house of <HI>Orleans,</HI> and is now fallen to the right of <HI>France.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Surely there is a great Vnion betweene the Popes and the Kings of <HI>Spaine,</HI> for <HI>Spaine</HI> makes the Pope ride on his pontificall Chaire, and the Pope makes <HI>Spaine</HI> flie in <HI>Phaetens</HI> Chariot, about the foure corners of Christendome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the Pope loued not <HI>Spaine</HI> so well, to giue him either the Marquisat of <HI>Anconitana,</HI> or the Dutchy of <HI>Ferrara,</HI> when he begged it of him by his Ambassadours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But did <HI>Spaine</HI> seeke <HI>Ferrara,</HI> and the Marca of <HI>Ancona</HI> of the Pope?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, and vpon good grounds and solid reasons too, for that lay commodious for <HI>Millane,</HI> and this for <HI>Naples,</HI> and both would serue as Bridges to passe into that braue and proud State of <HI>Venice.</HI></P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<HEAD>The State of Uenice.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>NOw you speake of the graue and Noble Venetians; as they haue long since pull'd off the Maske of <HI>Spains</HI> itching desire to deflowre their beautifull Adriatike Sea-Nimph: so they haue resolued no more to trust Spaniards. For of late (notwithstan∣ding their prudent decree to the contrary, grounded vpon some pri∣uate reasons of State) they both thinke in their hearts, and know in their soules and consciences, that it was onely the ambition and double Pistols of <HI>Spaine,</HI> that laid the foundation of the last trea∣cherous and execrable attempt against their Citie; and conse∣quently against their whole State, notwithstanding that some per∣fidious Frenchmen (degenerating from the honour of their Coun∣try and Ancestors) were corrupted and seduced (by the gold and flattering promises of <HI>Spaine</HI>) to be the chiefest Agents, and for∣lorne Hope in that damnable attempt; and to make this as cleare and apparent as the Sunne, That Illustrious and wise Senate well knowes, that at that very instant, and nick thereof, the Duke of <HI>Ossu∣na</HI> (Vice-roy of <HI>Naples</HI>) houered with his fleet &amp; Land-forces to lay
<PB N="12" REF="12"/>
hold and embrace that occasion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure Sister you wrong the Duke of <HI>Ossuna,</HI> and in him king <HI>Phillip</HI> his Master; for I haue heard that the said Duke did then Arme, vpon newes of a great Fleet of Gallyes comming from <HI>Con∣stantinople</HI> to <HI>Rhodes,</HI> vpon the irruption of intelligence betwixt the great Turke and the French King, for the escape of the Polonian Prince <HI>Coriski:</HI> for the which the Baron of <HI>Sancy,</HI> the French Am∣bassadour was at least confined, if not imprisoned at <HI>Constantinople,</HI> and that therefore for the safety of the Kingdome of <HI>Naples,</HI> it be∣hooued the said Duke to fortifie his Ports of <HI>Apulia, O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tranto,</HI> and <HI>Calabria,</HI> as well with Fleets as Regiments.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>The King of <HI>Spaines</HI> Ministers neuer want pretexts and euasions for their designes; but if the Duke of <HI>Ossuna</HI> for affir∣ming hereof, should sweare <HI>Botto D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>os,</HI> and <HI>par la Sanctissima Uir∣gina,</HI> till he were damn'd, yet that wise Senate, and especially the Councell of <HI>Tenn,</HI> will neuer beleoue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but <HI>Ossuna</HI> and the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> his Master, shall giue me leaue to ioine in opinion with the prudent Venetians; and there∣fore I highly praise their fore-sight, and applaude their generositie, in keeping a braue Nauall Army on their Seas, and strong Garrisons in their Castles and Cities, for the security of their State, as also for k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eping of their Exchequer rich, and their Arsenall and Magasins a∣boundantly stored and furnished.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But hath <HI>Spaine</HI> offered the Signiory of <HI>Venice,</HI> no other wrongs and affronts but this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes: for although that prudent State say little, yet they remember, (and will not forget) how busie his Ambassadour and Agents were at <HI>Rome,</HI> to giue fire to the quarrell betweene Pope <HI>Paulus Quintus</HI> and themselues, about banishing the Iesuites from their State, and for imprisoning the Chanon of <HI>Vincensa;</HI> as also, how readily and earnestly they proffered the Pope, that a great Spa∣nish and Neopolitan Army should instantly enter their State, and put all to fire and sword.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And they likewise remember, how the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> (that thereby his Regiments mought fish in troubled waters, and get firme footing in their Country) hath often incens'd this Emperour <HI>Fer∣dinand,</HI> then Duke of <HI>Gratz,</HI> to inuade their frontier Townes in <HI>Fri∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> and the <HI>Trevisan,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Noua Palma Brescia, Pescara,</HI> and <HI>Veronae,</HI> are obsta∣cles and stops to the designes both of the Emperour, and King of <HI>Spaine;</HI> yea that wise Sate, is so watchfull and vigilent, that in time of peace they make their greatest preparation for Warre. And it were a blessed happinesse and a safe felicitie, for most Kingdomes and Estates of Christendome, if herein they would emulate and imi∣tate the example of these wise and valiant Venetians, which is neither to trust, much lesse to feare <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But as wise and as strong as the Venetians are, as their Church and Pallace of St. <HI>Marke,</HI> was not built in a day, so are not all the designes and resolutions of the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> and therefore a time may come, but I say no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I gesse at your minde! you would haue the State of <HI>Ve∣nice</HI> made a Prouince to <HI>Spaine,</HI> that thereby he may finde a way for his Fleetes, to conuey his Armies into high and lowe <HI>Germany.</HI> And if <HI>Spaine</HI> thinke so: <HI>Contareno</HI> the Venetian Ambassadour, resident with the King my Husband; and since him <HI>Donato</HI> likewise told me, that herein <HI>Spaine</HI> is deceiued in the Arithmetick of his ambition and vsurpation; and thus to reckon, is to reckon without his Hostesse, and without God.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<HEAD>Swisserland</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>BVt how doe the warlike Cantons of Swissers trust the King of <HI>Spaine?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>As they doe the Emperour <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> his brother <HI>Leo∣paldus</HI> and the rest of the <HI>Austrian</HI> Princes: for they knowe his am∣bition and their malice, and so neither feare nor loue these,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But they loue the double Pistols of <HI>Spaine,</HI> doe they not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, but they say the French Crownes of the Sunne are farre purer and truer gold, and therefore passe currenter with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>The <HI>Austrian</HI> Princes, and the <HI>Swissers;</HI> I haue still heard, are from Father to Sonne, hereditary and irreconcilable Enimies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, the Swissers drawe good vse and benifit hereof; for by this meanes they liue not in securitie as some other States doe; but are still armed and ready to march and followe their colours,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E,</SPEAKER>
<P>But there is no Warre would be so acceptable and plea∣sing to them as vp to <HI>Millane,</HI> or downe to the free Country, <HI>Bra∣bant,</HI> and <HI>Heynault;</HI> if <HI>France, Sauoy,</HI> and <HI>Uenice,</HI> would command
<PB N="14" REF="13"/>
them the first, and <HI>England, France,</HI> and <HI>Holland,</HI> ordayne and giue way to the second.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is not past is yet to come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, but the Councell of <HI>Spaine</HI> hath policy enough, to insinuate and temporize with all these Princes and States; and so to diuert their Designes, and frustrate their resolutions, if they were bent that way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>It hath indeede hitherto proued so by <HI>Spaine:</HI> for their po∣licy and treachery, hath purchased and gotten them more Countries, then either their valour or swords.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>These easie Conquests are still sweet and pleasing to <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, but they are neither honest nor iust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But hath not <HI>Spaine</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with the Swissers for their con∣fines and limmits?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, two wayes, next <HI>Germany</HI> by <HI>Leopoldus,</HI> and be∣twixt <HI>Losanno</HI> and <HI>Gray</HI> in the free County by the Archduke <HI>Al∣bertus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> will angle so long till he take.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But hath not <HI>Spaine</HI> attempted by his Ambassadours and Agents, to sowe discention and discord amongst these Heluetian Cantons; to oppose them one against the other, and so to debauch and withdraw them first from the French Kings seruice, and then to his owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes many times, but that tricke of <HI>Spaine</HI> is now growne olde and thrid-bare; so as the Swissers vowe to remedy the first, and the French Kings to preuent the second.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the Catholique King will watch those Swissers a good turne, and if the Ephinaerides of his en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie, ambition, and great∣nesse faile him not, either his <HI>Spinola,</HI> or his <HI>Pedro d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Tol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>do,</HI> shall one of these dayes dine with him at <HI>Berne, Friburg,</HI> or <HI>Soleurre,</HI> ere their Table-cloathes be layed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Sister, you are deceiued in the Swissers; for their Table-cloathes are alwayes nayled to their Tables; yea, they haue so great a quantity of Swords, Pikes, and M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>skets in a readinesse, to giue any Enemy of theirs a bloudy banquet, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t if <HI>Phillip</HI> King of <HI>Spaine</HI> dare assault them, they doubt not but to vse him as they haue formerly done <HI>Phillip</HI> Duke of <HI>Burgundy,</HI> whom they ouerthrew in
<PB N="15" REF="13"/>
three seuerall pitch'd battels, at <HI>Gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>son, Morat,</HI> and <HI>Nancy,</HI> where he losed his treasure, his men, and his life.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<HEAD>The Grisons.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>BVt how stand the Grisons affected to <HI>Spaine?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Spaine</HI> through the vicinity of <HI>Millane,</HI> doth so often knocke at their doores, that if they keepe them not fast shut, they know, or at least feare that he will shortly enter by the <HI>Uolta∣line</HI> and <HI>Chiauena.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O though of late they made a shew of resistance, yet the gold of <HI>Spaine,</HI> the neighbourhood of <HI>Millane,</HI> the Fort <HI>Trents,</HI> but chiefly their owne credulity and security, hath almost brought them to the King of <HI>Spaines</HI> lure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>This people were both warlike and wise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Spaine</HI> will briefly make them fooles and cowards if they will hearken vnto him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how Nephew? pray be not bitter against <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st <HI>Spaine</HI> will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them vp in peace and secu∣rity till matters be ripe, or else he will engender factions, and sowe discords among themselues, either <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>or Religion, or ranke, or be∣twixt them and their dearest friends the Swissers; and so when hee sees all things ready, and the Iron hot, then he will march, and strike, and not faile to vnite and annex the Cantons of the Grisons to <HI>Mil∣lane,</HI> as he hath already done <HI>Millane</HI> to <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>If the Grisons at any time lose the Swissers friendship, or their owne vigilancy and generosity, it will not be long, ere they shake hands with their liberty and liues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q: M.</SPEAKER>
<P>So <HI>Spaine</HI> hopes, for if warre cannot worke, and effect it, they make no doubt but peace shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>If the Grisons hearken to the Charmes of <HI>Spaine,</HI> they are halfe lost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>If they hearken not to <HI>Spaine,</HI> they are wholly vndone, but if they listen to <HI>Spaine,</HI> all will be well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea Daughter, I beleeue for the Spaniards, but not for the Grisons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q E.</SPEAKER>
<P>To trust to <HI>Spaine,</HI> is to rely on a broken staffe, and to har∣bour a serpent in our owne bosomes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>To trust to the promises of <HI>Spaine,</HI> is to commit our selues
<PB N="16" REF="14"/>
to the mercy and protection of a Lyon who will deuoure vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Grisons will see, and say the contrary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>So will I say, if I see the contrary; till when, I feare the Gri∣sons will buy their peace, as well with teares as bloud.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<HEAD>Sauoy.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>BVt how doth <HI>Sauoy</HI> brooke <HI>Spaine?</HI> for I take it this pre∣sent Duke <HI>Charles Emanuell,</HI> married this King <HI>Phill.</HI> 3. his second sister; the Infanta <HI>Katherina Michaela.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sauoy</HI> loues <HI>Spaine,</HI> as it hath deserued of it; for the noble and generous Duke thereof cries out; God de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>end me from such a brother in law as King <HI>Philip.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeue if the Catholique King offered that Duke any vnkinde office, it was nothing but because hee was so neere a neigh∣bour to <HI>Geneua▪</HI> as he and the Pope suspected his Highnesse, would turne Caluinist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas that good Citie of <HI>Geneua,</HI> why all the world knowes the Dukes loue to it, and its Religion, witnesse the Barron of <HI>Attig∣na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> and his Consorts, as also <HI>Terraill</HI> and <HI>Bastide;</HI> but if there were once a Spanish Garison in this Citie, <HI>Sauoy</HI> would soone know how to distinguish betweene good and bad neighbours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But it is the laughture of the world, to say that <HI>Spaine</HI> hates <HI>Sauoy,</HI> because he loues the Religion of <HI>Geneua.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet this is as true as many other of <HI>Spaines</HI> Colours pre∣texts and euasions, when he hath a purpose and plot to vsurpe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why wherein hath the King of <HI>Spain</HI> abused, or wronged the Duke of <HI>Sauoy?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>First, in being himselfe the chiefe cause and subiect, and then m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>king him the Instrument and executioner, to cut off the two noble heads of <HI>Biron</HI> in <HI>Paris,</HI> and <HI>D'Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>igny</HI> in <HI>Turin.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why the Catholique King is the vniuersall King, and therefore it is not strange, if in all Countries of the world, hee haue his farre fetch'd policies, Agents, and Instruments to make his stra∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>agems and resolutions take effect, for those who are obstacles to his will and pleasure; his verball friendship shall alwayes proue their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eall ouerthrow and subuersion; howsoeuer hee and his Ministers pretend, and make shew of the contrary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="17" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, let vs leaue <HI>Biron</HI> and <HI>D'Albigny</HI> in their Graues, for me thinkes it is a poore charity to take vp the ashes of the dead. And for our better information, let vs take a suruey of the courtesie, or rather of the cruelty that <HI>Spaine</HI> hath offered <HI>Sauoy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>None knowes nor can deliuer the particular truth thereof, so well as your Royall Sonn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Prince <HI>Henry.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I feare my Nephew will be too partiall in the deliue∣ry hereof, betweene the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> and the Duke of <HI>Sauoy,</HI> be∣cause I haue heard that of the two Princesses their daughters, hee preferd that of <HI>Sauoy,</HI> before this of <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no; my Nephew <HI>Henry</HI> is a iudicious and iust Prince, therefore I know he will not wrong <HI>Spaine</HI> to doe right to <HI>Sauoy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>He resembles <HI>King Iames</HI> his Father too well, who will still loue the <HI>King</HI> of <HI>Spaine,</HI> although therein he hate himselfe, therefore speake on faire <HI>Sonne.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>When <HI>Great Henry of France (my honoured Vncle)</HI> made warres vpon the present <HI>Duke of Sauoy</HI> for the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of his <HI>Mar∣quisat</HI> of <HI>Saluses,</HI> then this <HI>Phillip King of Spaine,</HI> (vnder the pre∣tence and shew to ayde the <HI>Duke</HI> his brother in Law against the <HI>French</HI>) sent him may troopes and <HI>Regiments</HI> of <HI>Spanyards</HI> for the preseruation of his <HI>State;</HI> when the <HI>Peace</HI> being made betwixt the <HI>King</HI> and the <HI>Duke,</HI> and the exchange for <HI>Saluses,</HI> with the Countries of <HI>Bresse</HI> and <HI>Gex</HI> ratified and accomplished; These <HI>Spanish Regi∣ments</HI> being quartered in <HI>Carboneres, Mountemellion, Sauillan, Pig∣norall,</HI> and other places of <HI>Sauoy</HI> and <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>iedmont,</HI> they vpon no request or assummons made them by the <HI>Duke,</HI> would depart thence, but being commanded the Contrary by the <HI>Count de Fuentes (Vice-roy of Millan)</HI> as he wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rom the <HI>King</HI> his Master from <HI>Spaine,</HI> they pe∣remptorily r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>solued and vowed to keepe firme footing, which they long time did, vntill at last that wise and <HI>Valiant Duke</HI> being there∣unto constrained for the securitie of his estate, whose eminent and vtter subuersion he apparantly saw before his eyes, he very nobly cut all their throats.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue me his <HI>Highnesse of Sauoy</HI> did well, for it was an act most worthy of his iudgement and generositie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the <HI>King of Spaine,</HI> the <HI>Dukes of Lerma, Pastramae, Denia, Albecurque, Tolledo,</HI> and all the Counsell of warre of <HI>Spaine;</HI>
<PB N="18" REF="15"/>
vow to haue their reuenge of this affront.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Spaine</HI> hath done his worst to <HI>Sauoy</HI> already, for as long as <HI>France</HI> loues <HI>Sauoy, Sauoy</HI> needs not feare <HI>Spaine;</HI> at least mine <HI>Au∣thors</HI> tell me so, who are that famouss <HI>Captaine,</HI> the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>Dedis∣guieres,</HI> his valiant son <HI>De Crequy:</HI> and <HI>noble Du Fremes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though this one wrong, be one too many, yet is these all wrongs that this <HI>King of Spaine</HI> hath offered this <HI>Duke of Sauoy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Madame, for although the Duke winke, and seemes (with father <HI>Aubigny</HI>) to haue the art of forgetfulnesse; yet he well remembers how <HI>Don Iuan de Faxis</HI> (<HI>Spaines Ambassadour</HI> in <HI>France</HI>) told <HI>Lullius, Arconas,</HI> and <HI>Alimes,</HI> his <HI>Highnesse Am∣bassadours</HI> at <HI>Lyons,</HI> that the <HI>King</HI> his Master would Conttibute towards the <HI>Exchange</HI> of the Marquisat of <HI>Saluces,</HI> conditional∣ly it remained on that side the <HI>Alpes</HI> from the <HI>French;</HI> and since how his <HI>Catholique Maiestie</HI> hath performed nothing. He remembers <HI>Spaines Plots</HI> vpon his <HI>Castle of Nice</HI> (the key not only of his Countries, but of <HI>Italy</HI>) when his <HI>Spanish Galleyes</HI> lay at <HI>Villa franca</HI> to bereaue him of his Children, Hee remem∣bers how the <HI>Spanish Cardinals</HI> oppose his precedency at <HI>Rome,</HI> with the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>Florence,</HI> and how the <HI>Catholike King,</HI> or his <HI>Vice-roy</HI> of <HI>Millan</HI> for him, was the <HI>match</HI> and <HI>Incendiary</HI> to set fire twixt the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>Mantoua</HI> and him, For the <HI>Marquisat</HI> of <HI>Montferrad.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>We may see what a kind brother in Law the <HI>King</HI> of <HI>Spaine</HI> is, and what it is to build vpon his alliance, affinitie, promises and assistance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>Sauoy,</HI> and the <HI>Princes</HI> his children haue now purchased the length of <HI>Spaines</HI> foote.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>They haue reason to haue it, for they were all enforced to take it with their Swords, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ikes,</HI> and Lances, at <HI>Cassallo, Uerceile,</HI> and other-wheres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>As long as <HI>Sauoy</HI> loues not <HI>Spaine.</HI> The Marquis of <HI>Lullius,</HI> and Monseur <HI>De <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> told me, it needes not feare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but as long as <HI>Spaine</HI> Knockes at the Gates of <HI>Sauoy</HI> and <HI>Piedmond,</HI> he may at last enter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sauoy</HI> hath reason to enter <HI>Millan,</HI> not <HI>Spaine Sauoy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But time and the policie and Swords of <HI>Spaine</HI> cut all do∣nations and rights in peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="19" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sauoy</HI> hath had warnings enough to beware of <HI>Spaine,</HI> and therefore as I euer loued that generous <HI>Duke,</HI> so I hope that he and the Illustrious and <HI>valiant Princes,</HI> his <HI>Sonnes,</HI> will neuer want arme of steele, and hearts of <HI>Diamonds</HI> to out-braue <HI>Spaine,</HI> who with such ambition and malice seekes to out-braue it.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<HEAD>France.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what sayes <HI>France</HI> of <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>My honoured Father▪ all the world knowes that <HI>Spaine</HI> hath euer loued <HI>France</HI> well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, too too well, and so well as <HI>France</HI> will neuer loue <HI>Spaine,</HI> much lesse trust it in requitall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why hath not <HI>Spaine</HI> reason to ballance and counter∣poise the power and greatnesse of <HI>France.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, but not to seeke to make that famous and flourishing <HI>Kingdome</HI> become a Prouince to <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Spaine</HI> neuer wisht it, much lesse attempted it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yeares, more often then <HI>France</HI> hath <HI>Prouinces,</HI> or <HI>Spaine Cities.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? who was the Author and Protector of the League, but first Spaine, then the Pope, and next the Deuill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that was onely to preserue Catholikes, and the Ca∣tholike Religion, and to exterminate and root out Heretickes, and was not this well done of the King of Spaine, sith he is the Catho∣like King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, now the least childe in France knowes that Religion was onely the pretext, but Empire and Dominion the obiect of that League. How els dared <HI>Mendoz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> (Spaines Ambassadour) in Paris seeke the Crowne of France for the Infanta of Spaine, or how els dared the Iesuites his Ministers, in their seditious Sermons, and per∣nicious Pamphlets aduance her right to the Crowne and Kingdome, when God and the world knowes she had none to it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, it was when God had caused that good Fryer <HI>Iames Clement,</HI> to kill that bad King <HI>Henry</HI> the third at Saint <HI>Clou,</HI> and when indeed that Kingdome was without a head, and then the King of Spaine had reason to aduance his Daughters Title to <HI>France,</HI> in right of her mother <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> (that Queene of Peace) notwithstanding the fundamentall power of the Salique Law to the contrary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are deceiued daughter, for it was a good King, and a bad <HI>Fryer</HI> (or rather a <HI>Diuell</HI> in a <HI>Fryers</HI> weed) to set handes on the Lords anoynted, but this arrow came out of the quiuer of <HI>Spaine,</HI> and <HI>Hell,</HI> for that bloody and execrable murther was no sooner per∣petrated, but then instantly followed the proposition of the <HI>Infantaes</HI> Title to <HI>France,</HI> which apparantly makes the murther to be <HI>Spaines,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was the Dukes of <HI>Mayene, Mercu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ur</HI> who drew the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> to assist the League and in it <HI>France.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, contrarywise it was the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> that de∣bouch'd and drewthese two Dukes, and with them almost all the <HI>Nobillitie,</HI> to f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rge and contriue this League, and in it to ruine <HI>France▪</HI> for already <HI>France</HI> was almost Spaine, and the <HI>Infanta</HI> had vndoub∣tedly borne the <HI>Crowne,</HI> if Great <HI>Henry</HI> his victorious sword had not pul'd off <HI>Spaines</HI> maske, and so cut her <HI>Title</HI> and its pretence in peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But see the equitie and iustice of King <HI>Philip,</HI> for when <HI>Henrie</HI> that Heriticke King came to the Crowne, he restored him <HI>Ca∣lais, Dourlans, Ualencienes, Blauet,</HI> and all other townes and Castles which he had formerly wonne and Conquered in <HI>France.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>But all this was not worthy thankes, for <HI>Philip</HI> alone re∣stored that which he could not, nor dared not to keepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay obserue farther, how religious King <HI>Philip</HI> was (in imitation of King <HI>Agesilaus</HI>) for he kept his faith inuiolable to∣wards <HI>Henrie</HI> 4. although he were an heritique King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay obserue how irreligious and treacherous King <HI>Philip</HI> was to King <HI>Henry</HI> 4. (in imitation of <HI>Antaxerxes,</HI> the Son of <HI>Xerxes</HI>) for he violated his faith and frindship towards him, in debaushing of <HI>Biron Marcanques, Loste,</HI> whose promises and gold made them <HI>Traytors</HI> to theit <HI>King</HI> and <HI>Country.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Surely I thinke it is incident, and I feare it will proue here∣ditary to the Kings of <HI>Spaine,</HI> to conquer more by treachery then by the sword.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E,</SPEAKER>
<P>But had <HI>Great Henrie</HI> liu'd, he would haue required, these courses of <HI>Spaine,</HI> as also that of <HI>Guyguard</HI> and <HI>Chastell;</HI> who (although the report runne otherwise) had their greatest light and encouragement from beyond the <HI>Pyreene</HI> mountaines; for to speake truth he in hart could neuer be drawne to loue <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, that <HI>Spaine</HI> knew full well, for when the <HI>French Iesuits</HI>
<PB N="21" REF="16"/>
<HI>his Ministers</HI> had vnlocked that mistery, they like bloody Schoole∣masters, so diuilishly instructed and fortified that monster of men <HI>Rauilliaek</HI> (their execrable and damnable desciple) that he soone sent him hither in a bloudy Coffin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you will not say that the <HI>King of Spaine</HI> was accessary to <HI>Henry</HI> the 4. his murther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but I will say that if the truth were knowne, the ope∣ning of that veyne would make many great Birds, yea and many learned ones too, bleede themselues to death, and peraduenture the wounds and scarres thereof, would bleede an hundred yeares hence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Marshall of <HI>Lauerdin</HI> whispered me a word concer∣ning this, which I shall neuer forget, onely he requested my secrecie therein: so the King of Spaines <HI>Lerma,</HI> and the Queene Mother of <HI>France</HI> her <HI>D'Anchre,</HI> his <HI>Mariano,</HI> and her <HI>Cotton</HI> shall giue mee leaue to thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Questionlesse it were the sinnes of that King, and the finger of Heauen that cut off the thred of his life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Questionlesse you are deceiued Sister, for it were the sinnes of <HI>France</HI> who made the Knife, and the treasons of <HI>Spaine</HI> and <HI>Rome,</HI> which made that Parracide <HI>Rauilliack</HI> performe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, in despight of <HI>Rome, Spaine,</HI> and Hell, that victori∣ous and glorious King is wafted hither in triumph, therefore leaue we him with God, and God with him, and let vs see since his de∣plorable death, how kinde King <HI>Philip</HI> of <HI>Spaine</HI> hath beene to King <HI>Lewes</HI> his sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>So kinde that hee hath matched King <HI>Lewis</HI> to his eldest Daughter, the Infanta <HI>Anna;</HI> and his eldest sonne, Prince <HI>Philip</HI> to the eldest Princesse of <HI>France</HI> Madame <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> that now these two mightie Kingdomes and Houses seeme to be but one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is faire to the eye of the world, but it will be excellent if the end of these matches proue fortunate for France.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who were the Match-makers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>S. P. Q. R. or to bee better vnderstood, <HI>Spaine,</HI> Pope and Queene Regent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>If King <HI>Philip</HI> of <HI>Spaine</HI> be Heyre as well to his Fathers ambition as to his Kingdomes, he will loue <HI>France</HI> so well as to push and fish for it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="22" REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>What force could neuer effect, he hopes those Marriages now will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed, the Snake lurkes vnder the fairest greene leaues, and the Aspick vnder the purest and sweetest Roses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Kings of the world know better how to dissemble then the Catholique Kings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>You speake Scripture, not tradition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you tradition not Scripture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what entertainement had the Infanta of Spaine in France?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Noble, Royall, Glorious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>What trayne of Spaniards brought shee with her into France.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very great trayne, for Monsieur <HI>de Marais</HI> (the French Ambassadour with the King my Father) tolde me that Monsieur <HI>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>elle</HI> (Maister of the Ceremonies to the French King) repor∣ted, that when the first of them were entring <HI>Paris</HI> at Saint <HI>Iaques</HI> Gate, that the l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st were but comming <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>owne the <HI>Pyrene</HI> Moun∣taines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what did all this rabble of Spaniards doe in France?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>To speake truth, they fell presently to skrewing and working themselues into the State, by begging and buying of Offi∣ces, Places, Pensions and Gouernments, both in Church and Com∣mon-weale, and by making Pensioners for Spaine, and consequently a bridge and passage for the King their Master to enter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how did the Parliaments, the Priuie Councell, and the Nobilitie of France brooke and digest this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, that is a question of state indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>As for the Parliaments and Priuie Councell, many of them are so Iesuitiz'd, as they are Spaniards in heart, though French in tongue, and therefore they were so farre from preuenting, as they gaue way to it, onely for the Princes and Nobilitie (some few ex∣cepted) they (resembling themselues) vowed and swore, that their swords should cut the Pennes and Tongues in pieces of any Spani∣ard whatsoeuer, that dar'd propose or attempt it, for they spake a∣loud, and affirm'd, the Florenti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es had taught them wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>A braue resolution of the French Nobilitie; for the greatest
<PB N="23" REF="17"/>
of a State haue alwayes the greatest interest in the State; those Princes and Nobles are therefore highly to bee applauded and prai∣sed: and such of the Priuy Councell and Parliament who tacitely are delinquents, and Traytors to their Prince and Countrey, deserue to be found out, arraig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed, and sacrificed to the good of the Com∣mon-weale, either with a sword, or a halter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what said the Clergy of France to this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sister, it is to be feared, as you wish and desire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why they out of passionate zeale, more then of zealous and sollid iudgement, approue of any Match for their King, so it bee not with a Protestant, and yet of none so well as of this with Spaine; demaund their reason, and they will answer you (with as much ve∣hemency as ignorance) that the King of Spaine is the Catholique King, and if you come further to particularize, they reply, that their Cardinals (who indeede are onely the Popes creatures) shall de∣liuer more at the estates Generall: So the Clergie bad the Spaniards welcome into France.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But where are the Firebrands and Incendiaries of the State, the French Iesuites, who indeed are the Fistulaes and Botches of a State, what entertainment gaue they to the young Queene and her Spaniards?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Surely Aunt, they crouched very low to the Queene; but in <HI>Cottons</HI> absence, <HI>Arnoux</HI> and <HI>Berrulla</HI> (their Tongue and Eare) whispered so secretly to her Maiestie, that I could neither gather nor vnderstand what they said, but I guest at it: onely they gaue faire words and actions to all the Spaniards in generall; and to the No∣bler and wiser sort of them in particular, they engaged themselues to keepe curious correspondence with the Catholique King, to whom they affirmed and swore by their <HI>Semie-God</HI> and sole Patron <HI>Ignati∣us Loyalla,</HI> they would beare true obseruance as the Marigold doth to the Sunne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are not these two Iesuites the French Kings ordinary Prea∣chers, and yet dare they doe it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Although <HI>Berrulla</HI> be the Father of the Oratory, yet he is in heart and soule a Iesuite, and <HI>Arnoux</HI> is the Arch-Iesuite of France, and the Kings Confessour, and yet they dare, and will doe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how did the Queene Regent entertaine the Spani∣ards?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Courteously and Nobly, because shee made the Match; which since she hath repented tho; yea, and the Duke of <HI>Mayene</HI> too, who concluded and finished it: And so did <HI>Villeroy</HI> likewise, although it were too late. But <HI>Sillery</HI> and <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Uair</HI> loue <HI>Spaine</HI> so well, as their courages are so masculine, that though they see their errors in perswading these matches, yet they rather persist then ac∣knowledge it, for like good cleare-sighted States-men, they haue wit enough to beare vp with the time, for otherwise they know the times will not beare vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how did the Commons of <HI>France</HI> entertaine the Spa∣niards?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly I thinke they will neuer be perswaded to like the fa∣shion of the little Hat, and great set Ruffe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Son <HI>Henry,</HI> pray answere Queene <HI>Mary.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>If we may iudge of <HI>Hercules</HI> by his foote, so we then may of <HI>France,</HI> by those of <HI>Paris</HI> (which is the eye, the heart, the soule thereof) where the Citizens in all streetes, and especially the Lakeyes at the Lourre gate, and the new bridge, still salute the Spa∣niards as they passe by, by these courteous Epithites, <HI>Boracho, Pan∣talones,</HI> and <HI>Bouriques.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>How long remained all these Spaniards in <HI>France?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>So long I warrant you, vntill they did all their Kings bu∣sinesse, and their owne too before they departed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>In truth so long, till all <HI>France</HI> was weary, and distasted of them and their proceedings, yea, so many yeares, that at last the King and Counsell were in a manner constrained to send them away by an Edict, as they themselues, not many yeares since, did the Moores.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>The banishing of the Moores was a good and wholesome Counsell of <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I assure you sister, the sending home of the Spaniards was as excellent one in <HI>France,</HI> for vpon the matter, they were but spyes, moaths, and drones,, and would haue proued so to <HI>France</HI> if they had continued there longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But were they all sent home, and none left at the Court of
<PB N="25" REF="18"/>
France to giue, and receiue packets too and fro for the Iesuites, the king of Spaines Factors and Agents.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, no assure your selfe, for the Councell of Spaine is too wise to commit so grosse and palpable an errour of State.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Therefore to cast the thicker mist, and to put the better varnish one the businesse, The Countesse <HI>De la Tour</HI> was left there with the title of gouernesse to the young Queene, and there is as much correspondencie betwixt her and <HI>Don Ferdinand de Geron</HI> (the Ambassadour of <HI>Spaine</HI>) as there is betwixt him and the French Iesuites.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus <HI>Spaine</HI> leaues alwaies a Sting behinde him, and I feare <HI>France</HI> will in the end finde it so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whereon is your suspition, and feare grounded?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon the apparant symptomes of the <HI>Lethargie, Feuer,</HI> or <HI>Consumption</HI> of <HI>France.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say right Madam, and the Noblest and truest hearted <HI>Frenchmen</HI> participate of your apprehension: for the Iesuites (being the Popes Factors, and the King of <HI>Spaines</HI> Oracles and Agents) haue already corrupted the Parliaments and Priuie Coun∣cell, who should bee her <HI>Illyum</HI> and <HI>Acrocorynth.</HI> They haue vndermyned and ruinated the <HI>Sorbone,</HI> heretofore her <HI>Palladium,</HI> once the Queene of <HI>Vniuersities:</HI> Who now as a mournfull Wid∣dow, sits with her haire dandling about her eares, and her teares trickling downe her cheekes, liuing onely in her shad∣dow or Ghost, or rather in her ruines; for the Genius and Soule, hath already made a transmigration to <HI>Clermont</HI> House; Yea, and to speake true <HI>French,</HI> in our <HI>English</HI> tongue, they by their deuilish <HI>Aphorismes</HI> and bloudie positions (vnder a false and hipocriticall shew of Learning and Pietie) doe poyson and corrupt the Youth and prime Wits of <HI>France,</HI> as the <HI>Iewes</HI> did the springs and fountaines in <HI>England.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Also, the Clergie of France degenerates from its Pristine candor and zeale to the good of France, and the glory of the French Church, for they receiue Lawes from the Popes <HI>Nuncio,</HI> and the Iesuites, to whom they should giue them. How else at the last generall Estates of <HI>Paris,</HI> and the assembly of Notables at <HI>Rouen?</HI> were they so vnwise, dishonest and cowardly, to re∣ferre themselues to the two Cardinals <HI>Perron</HI> and <HI>Gondye?</HI> who
<PB N="26" REF="19"/>
like good Cardinals, but bad Frenchmen (hauing onely their Bodies in France, but their hearts at Rome) in thankful∣nesse to the Pope for their red Hats, forgat themselues and their allegiance so much, as to prostitute and debase that fa∣mous Crowne, and flourishing Kingdome of <HI>France,</HI> to be de∣pendant to Rome in Temporall matters, notwithstanding the <HI>Pragmaticke Sanction,</HI> and the prerogatiues of the Crowne and Church of France to the contrary; whereat the Popes Nun∣cio at Paris laught with open mouth: So did the Colledge of Car∣dinals, and the Pope himselfe at Rome; and likewise the <HI>Ca∣tholike King</HI> in Spaine, with all that huge rabble of Iesuites, whiles all the Kings, Soueraigne Princes, and free Estates of Europe (Spaine and Italy excepted) greeued and lamented at it, with as much shame as wonde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed these are two maine points and reasons, that the greatnesse and genero<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ity of France declynes, and that Rome and Spaine will shortly sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uffie the Cards so well▪ as it must needs be made a Prouince to Spaine; for they both haue consulted, and finde, that what couldnot be effected during the Reigne of old <HI>Henry,</HI> may in these of young King <HI>Lewes</HI> his Sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is not impossible, rather likely, for France abounds in a moustrous height of Pride and Sinne: And the old Cleargie of France admit of so many new orders of Fryers and Nunnes, that almost all is out of order; and the seuenteene Millions which the Duke of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> left by accompt to the Queene Re∣gent, is all long since spent, and twice seuenteene more. So as al∣though the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> be still on foote, <HI>Monopolyes</HI> neuer so rife, the <HI>Finnances,</HI> or Exchequer drawne dry, and exhausted, yet the King is extreamely <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to his Nobilitie and Pensioners; and is not this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> King of Spaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Great <HI>Henry</HI> liued, he would haue remedied and pre∣uented these calamities.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>But his Sonne King <HI>Lewes</HI> is not so happy to doe it, no not his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, the Duke of <HI>Luynes</HI> so discreet and honest to aduise and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> thereunto.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> neglect thereof may make one, or both of them to repent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t, and peraduenture the kingdome too; for already the Com∣mons <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/>, and the Nobilitie would, but cannot remedy it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="27" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Spaine loues France, therefore France neede not feare Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Panthers skin is faire, yet his friendship is fatall, and his breath infections.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed if France loued not Spaine, it neede not feare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>King <HI>Philip</HI> loues King <HI>Lewis</HI> dearely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not halfe so well as he loues his Kingdome of France.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>In truth France hath reason to haue a vigilant eye ore Spain, for as long as shee sleepes in her bed of pleasure and securitie, per∣haps one of these dayes, Spaines Ambition may awake her with Drum, Trumpet and Cannon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no▪ not as yet, for if the king of Spaine were so ill ad∣uised, his Councell is not; for they like old experienced Foxes, will neuer permit him to discouer himselfe, much lesse his Resolutions, and least of all his Ambition and Sword, vntill the Sunne hath at∣tain'd the Meridian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not what my Nephew meanes by this Mathe∣maticall Riddle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was neuer greatly skild in the Mathematickes, and yet consuming my Youth, Yeares, and Cares for England, I haue rea∣son to vnderstand his knowledge. Wherefore Sister, sith hee is a Noble and famous Prince, let vs heare him, for he hath some mistery to reueale twixt France and Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>He loues France, and hates Spaine, and which is worse, hee was an Heretique, therefore his tongue can make no Spherall melody.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But his heresie hath brought him hither to heauen tho, and hee is a famous and Noble Prince: therefore Cosen <HI>Wales</HI> speake on of France and Spaine, for now wee are all resolued to heare you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>I gaue him my Fathers Name, and he inheriteth my reso∣lution and courage, and the King his Fathers wisedome, therefore he can neither flatter nor dissemble.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake on <HI>Henry.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know all men by these Presents, that if Spaine did see the Heart and Bowels of France weltring in its bloud, and flaming in the fire of an intestine Giuill warre, if it did see the Princes banded against the King, or the King against the Protestants,
<PB N="28" REF="20"/>
these rifeling of the Lourre, and of Paris, and his Maiestie be∣sieging of Rochell, Sancerre, Sedan, Nismes, or Samury, or denouncing warre to all those of that Religion. If it did see sixteene Parisian Tribunes, carrying away the Court of Parlia∣ment prisoners to the Bastille, and Chastellets the rebellious Ba∣rycadoes, and a bloudie Massacre in Paris; and generally in all the Cities of the Kingdome, if hee did see some Princes of the bloud (or two great Dukes as were <HI>Du Mayene</HI> and <HI>Mera∣ry</HI>) Captiuating and Deboshing the obedience and affections of the French Nobilitie, Clergie and Commons, and couering their pernitious designes and trecherous attempts, vnder the cloake of the holy League; If it did see Calais, Dourlaus, Amiens, Mont∣didier, Valencienes, Blauet, and Croyden, or other strong Ci∣ties, or Forts of France, bearing out the red ragged Crosse in∣stead of the three yellow Flower Deluces, and a second <HI>Mendo∣za</HI> for his Ambassadour, sate as premier President and Oracle in the Louare, Towne-house and Parliament, That then <HI>Phil∣lip</HI> the III. of Spaine loues his Sonne in Law <HI>Lewes</HI> the thir∣teene of France so well, that hee would vse him as King <HI>Phillip</HI> the second had an eager desire, and had almost done great <HI>Henry</HI> his Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Why how was that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. <HI>H.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Right as my Godmother Queene <HI>Elizabeth</HI> hath for∣merly told you, nothing but to depriue him of his Kingdome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>It were better that all the Iesuites were hanged, and the young Queene of France sent home to Spaine, with her Portion, to the King her Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>But wee see strange alterations in the Court of France, for some dare, but will not, and others would, but dare not informe the King hereof.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>France hath reason, yea, it is high time for her to looke to her selfe, for the Agents, Iesuits, and double Pistols of Spaine are busie, and their Swords and Pikes are not Idle. For whiles France playes the Theorie, Spaine playes the Practique.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<PB N="29" REF="20"/>
<HEAD>Of the Netherlands.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doth <HI>Spaine</HI> and the <HI>Netherlands</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gree?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Spaine hath so long inured and enforced the Hollanders to bloud and warres, as now at Sea and Land they are become such braue Souldiers and Marriners, as they feare not Spaine, and to loue Spaniards they vow it is impossible, much lesse to obey them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>It is pittie that King <HI>Phillip</HI> the second ended not the chastising and Conquest of these Heretique Hollanders, ere King <HI>Phillip</HI> the third began it, or that hee cannot reduce them to obedience, by ending these warres with more fortunacie, and lesse danger and dammage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Sister, it is pittie that these two Kings of Spaine, and the Archduke <HI>Albertus</HI> and <HI>Isabella,</HI> haue from time to time beene so ambitious, inhumane, cruell and reuengefull, to drowne the face of the Netherlands with many deluges of bloud, in seeking to pre∣serue their libertie, liues and Consciences from the cruell Tyrannie and Inquisition of Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed for this forty yeares, the Netherlands hath beene the Schoole and Theater of <HI>Mars,</HI> whereon there hath beene more braue souldiers and renowned Captaines flame, then in any Coun∣try of the world, or in many precedent Ages; and yet all this bloud is not capable to quench Spaines Ambition and Tyranny in seeking to deuoure those Prouinces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Hath not Spaine assaulted the Netherlands as well by Trecherie as Hostilitie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, witnesse the damnable Villaine <HI>Gerrard,</HI> who long since murthered <HI>William</HI> the famous Prince of <HI>Orange,</HI> their Lieute∣nant Generall, and Father to <HI>Maurice</HI> that valiant and incomparable Captaine, who now succeeds him in his Principalitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>O Sister, cast not so base an aspersion on King <HI>Phillip</HI> my Husband, to affirme hee was accessary to the murther of <HI>William</HI> Prince of <HI>Orange,</HI> much lesse authorised it or commanded it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>All the Ocean betweene Holland and Spaine, cannot wash off that Murther from your Husband King <HI>Phillip,</HI> for his proscription to murther him beares it, and his Lieutenant the Duke
<PB N="30" REF="21"/>
of <HI>Parma</HI> commanded the Count <HI>Assonuille</HI> to deale with <HI>Gerrard</HI> about this murther, who promised him twentie fiue thousand Crownes to effect it, which, O griefe to speake it, he did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But his valiant Sonne hath long since had reuenge for the death of his Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he haue not, he resolues to haue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But hath not Spaine since attempted, or broached any other Treason towards the Hollanders?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes very lately, for whilst Spaine is Spaine, Holland will neuer forget how neere he was to haue extinguished her liber∣tie, and surprized their State, by infecting and corrupting their Se∣cretary <HI>Barneuelt,</HI> a man of so profound wit, and deepe iudgement and experience in matters of State, as he was not onely the Oracle of the Netherlands, but the Ornament and wonder of Europe, ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of his time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, the fruites of Spaines Gold, and the effects of his boundlesse Ambition, for it is a common custome with him, if not by the maine, yet surely by the bye, to breake the necke of Great Princes, and free Estates, publique Ministers, whether they are great Souldiers or great Statesmen, or both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, the Web of this Treason was so cunningly wouen, and so subtilly and finely spun, as if the Netherlands had not broken <HI>Barne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>elts</HI> necke, he long ere this had assuredly broken the necke both of their libertie and State.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, <HI>Barnauelt</HI> is gone, and now Spaine needs not feare his policy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, <HI>Barneuelt</HI> being dead, and <HI>Maurice</HI> that famous Prince of <HI>Orenge</HI> liuing, Holland need not feare either the trechetie, or force of Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Nephew, I heare that the Vnited Prouinces of the Low-Countries will this Spring haue Warres with Spaine, for their peace is neere expired and ended.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>A braue, noble, and wise resolution of theirs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heretofore England taught the Hollanders wit and va∣lour, and now they resolue to shew England the way to those two Vertues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the Gold and Siluer of Spaine w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll preuaile against them, and weigh them downe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="31" REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the Hollanders had Ships enough of their owne, and Gold, Siluer, and Men from England, therefore they disdaine to feare Spaine, nay rather they vow before the next Summer to make Spaine feare them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, see, a handfull of men dare attempt that against Spaine, which Great Brittaines huge infinitie will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet their cause and reason is Englands, <HI>viz.</HI> their Con∣sciences, Liues and Countries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray God England and France interpose not to crosse the Warres, and seeke to conclude a Peace betwixt Holland and Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the Hollanders are resolued to make King <HI>Iames</HI> a large Offer, to protect them against Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But King <HI>Iames</HI> loues Spaine too well, and therefore will not hearken to, or regard their proffer, for his Maiestie is resolued not to protect them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>The more is the pitty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>The more my griefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>And without griefe or pitty, the more is my ioy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>I protected the Netherlands in despight of Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Spaine went neere by your <HI>Leicester,</HI> to betray both you and them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>If King <HI>Iames</HI> would now protect the Netherlanders, how easily might he refetch backe <HI>Flushing,</HI> the <HI>Brill,</HI> and the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, how easily did his Maiestie depart with them to the Netherlands?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>It infinitely reioyceth me to vnderstand the Hollanders braue resolution and forwardnesse to haue warres with Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But there is a secret tricke to coole their courages which they least thinke of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how Daughter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, to Pistoll this Prince of <HI>Orenge,</HI> as they did his Fat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heauen forbid it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>God defend it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, 'tis but one for another; for he knowing <HI>Barna∣uelt</HI> a Traytor to his Countr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y because a Pensioner to Spaine, caused the Lords States, to put him to death, why then (in exchange
<PB N="32" REF="22"/>
and requitall) should not a Pensioner of Spaine either poison, or pistoll the Prince of <HI>Orange?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>These Diabolicall resolutions and bloudy Positions come from Hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thither they goe that professe and practise them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>The King of Spaine is too religious to authorise so exe∣crable a Murther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the Pope as holy as he is will pardon it, and yet the World, I hope, knowes, that the K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>of Spaine cannot be so religious as his Holinesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>It were good then for Holland to be carefull of their Prince of <HI>Orange</HI> his life, as all the world knowes his Excellency is of their safetie and preseruations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And it will likhwise behooue them to obserue withall (as I hope they doe) how subtilly and trecherously <HI>Spinola,</HI> takes their neighbour Townes for the Emperour, and keepes them for the King of Spaine his Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if the Warres goe on 'twixt Holland and Spaine; as I hope they will, it will be needfull for Spaine to haue a speciall care of his West-Indies from the Holland Fleetes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wherefore only Spaines West-Indies, or rather why not all the worlds West-Indies; sith their red and white earth sets all the Would on fire and in Combustion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Surely, ere this Summer passe, and the next appeare, the Hollanders vow to haue a heaue at them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I hope the contrary, for the West-Indies is the maine and onely prop of Spaine, which if once found out, and taken away from them, will quickly make the greatnesse of his Ambition and Empire totter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Till when, all other Kingdomes and Estates of Christen∣dome may thinke themselues exempt from Spaines feare, but shall neuer be from his danger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Holland perfectly and apparantly knowes, and it were a greater happinesse for the rest of Europe, if they would here∣in imitate their Generositie, Valour and Wisedome, who stand on their Guards with their swords drawne, and their Match lighted ready to giue fire; as being constantly and vertuously resolued nei∣ther to loue, trust, nor feare Spaine.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="place">
<PB N="33" REF="22"/>
<HEAD>ENGLAND.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But now leaue we all other Countries, and come wee to England, from whence being descended, wee by the Lawes of Na∣ture, are eternally obliged to honour and loue it; yea to preferre it and its prosperitie and glory to all other Countries of the world; wherefore let vs see Spaines Ambition and Enuy towards it; and how he hath from time to time borne himselfe to the English.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is no Kingdome in the world, that Spaine loues better then England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor no people vnder the Sunne that it hates more then Englishmen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>For <HI>Peter</HI> King of <HI>Castille,</HI> most ingratefully and basely a∣bused our famous and generous <HI>Edward</HI> the Blacke Prince, (the Or∣nament of Armes, the Glory of England, and the Honour of the World) and his whole Army in Spaine, after that he had inthroni∣sed and seated the said <HI>Peter</HI> in his Kingdome, and with his Victori∣ous Armes expel'd <HI>Henry</HI> the Bastard, who Vsurped it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>If Spaine had not loued England and Englishmen, King <HI>Philip</HI> would neuer haue married mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee loued you well Sister, but your Kingdome farre bet∣ter, for you were the Obiect of his zeale, but England that of his Ambition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> hee hated you more then euer he loued <HI>Mary.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet I dare truly affirme, that King <HI>Philip</HI> loued my Kingdome farre more then euer he hated my Per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>To speake truth Daughter, he neither loued you, nor <HI>Ma∣ry</HI> his wife and Queene, but only England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I haue heard that if he had neuer married my Aunt <HI>Mary,</HI> shee had neuer lost <HI>Calais,</HI> nor consequently, England, France.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though that Match were vnfortunate to England in the losse of <HI>Calais,</HI> yet it was fortunate in that <HI>Philip</HI> and <HI>Mary</HI> had no Children.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>If we had had any Males, England had beene long since a Prouince to Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="34" REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>God knew so much, and therefore preuented it, wherein I qle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>se his Mercy and prouidence, as also your sterrilitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aunt, and I your resolution in speaking it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Kings of Spnine are the greatest <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd most potent Kings of the World.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, in Ambition and ostentation, but not in power, for I proued it not so, I found it not so, I left it not so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>You Madame found Warre with Spaine surer and safer then Peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, farre more safer, and farre more profitable too for England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I wonder that King <HI>Iames</HI> my Husband so delights and drownes himselfe in his peace with Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but Spaine findes both policy and reason enough to full King <HI>Iames</HI> a sleepe in the Cradle of Peace and Security.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q E.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neuer feared Spaine lesse, then when I loued it not, no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> more then when it made greatest shew to loue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the King my Father neuer loued it more, then now when he feares it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But is it possible King <HI>Iames</HI> feares Spaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes so, for else he would neuer loue it so excessiuely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Nicholas Bacon</HI> my Chancellor on his Death-bed wrote me a Letter, that the Glory and Conseruation of England consisted in holding Spaine at Rapiers point; and will not his sonne Sir <HI>Fran∣cis,</HI> the now Chancellor tell his Maister so much?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, he is otherwise imployed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But tell mee Daughter, was Spaine euer treacherous to your Person?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Almost euery yeare Spaine hatched mee a new Treason, witnesse <HI>Parry, Babbington, Williams, Yeorke, Lopez,</HI> and infinite o∣thers, who sought to lay violent hands on my Person and Life, but that God in his infinite mercy and prouidence still protected and de∣fended me, to their owne confusion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>But King <HI>Phillip</HI> 2. chiefely discouered his loue to England, in the treacherous attempt of his huge Armado of 88. (tearmed by the Pope) in a brauery (The <HI>Inuincible Fleete,</HI>) at what time his ambition and greedy desire of Vsurpation, so farre ore-swayed him and his Councell, as he thought to haue made an absolute Conquest
<PB N="35" REF="23"/>
of England; but hee was deceiued of his hopes; for God looked on England with his indulgent eye of pitty and compassion, and on that great and mightie Nauall Army with contempt and dete∣station.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q: E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea God was so gracious to England, and so mercifull to mee, as not only my Ships and People, but the Windes and Waues fought for my defence, and that of my Countrey, against the pride and malice of Spaine, who grew mad with anger, and pale with griefe, to see this his great and warlike Armado beaten, foyled, and confounded, in the midst of their glory and ambition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6,</SPEAKER>
<P>But Sister, was this all Spaines malice and trechery towards You and your State?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, for I had forgotten how before that, his Maiestie in Spaine and his Lieutenant the Duke of <HI>Alua</HI> in Flanders, embarg'd and confisk'd a world of Goods and Ships that belon∣ged to my Subiects, contrary to all Lawes of Conscience and Na∣tions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And no other?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, King <HI>Phillip</HI> beg'd my Kīngdome of Ireland of the Pope, and so assisted the Rebels, and made a confederacy with them for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>he Conquest thereof from me, bringing in first <HI>Stukeley,</HI> then <HI>Don Iuan</HI> of <HI>Aquila,</HI> into that Kingdome to the same effect: But Heauen alwayes laught at their ambition, vsurpation, and treche∣rie, which still proued as vaine, as impious and vniust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet see the iustice of the Cause, and the equitie of your Armes; for <HI>Essex</HI> landed at <HI>Calez,</HI> and in despight of Spaine tooke and rifled it, beating and sinking their best and greatest Ships, in a manner without any shew of defence or resistance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but now the times are altered and changed, for then Spaine was poore and England rich, and now England is poore and Spaine rich: Likewise Spaines warres parsimonie, and frugalitie, makes his Men Souldiers; and our Peace, Pride, and superfluitie, hath made our Souldiers either Courtiers or Co∣wards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>France knew that I found Souldiers in England when I tooke Tourney and Bouloigne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Spaine felt that English were Souldiers, when my <HI>Drake</HI> beat them on my Seas and Coast in 88. my <HI>Norris</HI> at Croyden
<PB N="36" REF="24"/>
in 94. my <HI>Essex</HI> at <HI>Calais</HI> in 96. and my <HI>Montioy</HI> at Kingsale in 1600.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But when England was delighted in Combats, Warres, and Victories, and now in Stage-playes, Maskes, Reuels and Ca∣rowsing, so as their courages are become as rustie as their Swords and Muskets, which serue to grace the walls and not the fields, ex∣cept in poore Musters, and sleight Trainings, and that but once a yeare, which vpon the whole, is more for ostentation then Seruice: Moreouer, then Englands Nauy-Royall could giue a Law to the Ocean, and now time and negligence hath almost made all these ships vnseruiceable, who lye rotting at Chatam and Rocesther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here Queene <HI>Mary</HI> hath reason, for now she is in the truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>What (Sister and Brother) my Royall-Nauy lye r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tting, who are the Bulwarkes and Walles of England, and when I left them were capable to beate the power and pride of Spaine to shi∣uers? O this grieues me! but I beleeue not that my wife and pru∣dent Successour King <HI>Iames</HI> will suffer or permit it, I pray, God-son and Nephew Prince <HI>Henry,</HI> resolue me hereof.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed Madam, I confesse I haue seene so much my selfe, when God knowes I grieued to see it; neither did I faile to put the King my Father often in remembrance thereof; and his Maiestie still promised me to new build and repaire that Royall Fleete, to which number I added my <HI>Prince-Royall,</HI> a ship, who had she many fellowes, England needed not feare all the Fleetes of the World; but although the old Lord Admirall hath not beene carefull for the preseruation of the Nauy, yet the new one is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he be not, I grieue for the Fleet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q E.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I lament it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I pittie it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I bewaile it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q: M.</SPEAKER>
<P>And not to dissemble, both <HI>Gondomar,</HI> King <HI>Phillip</HI> his Master, the Pope, my selfe, and all the Romane Catholiques of Eng∣land reioyce hereat, for the Impotency and destruction of this Royall Nauy, is the Harbinger to prepare the way, and a step for <HI>King Phillip</HI> to mount the Throne of Estate, to plucke off King <HI>Iames</HI> his Crowne, and to place and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ettle it on his owne head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Ships, my Ships: God knowes they were still deare to me, because still necessary to England. Where is my <HI>Drake,</HI>
<PB N="37" REF="24"/>
where my <HI>Cumberland,</HI> my <HI>For bisher,</HI> my <HI>Grinuille,</HI> my <HI>Cau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣dish,</HI> my <HI>Haukins,</HI> my <HI>Rauliegh,</HI> and the rest: Alas, they want me, and king <HI>Iames</HI> and Englnad wants them; for when they liued, and I raigned, our valour could stop the progression of Spaine; yea my ships domineerd in his Seas and ports, and their Clouds of smoke and fire, with their Peales of thunder, strueke such such amaz∣ment to the harts, and terrour to the courages of Castille and her faint-hearted <HI>Castillians,</HI> that euery Spanish Bird kept his owne Nest, not powerfull enough to defend themselues, much lesse to of∣fend any; and lest of all England, who was then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n her Triumphes, in her lustre, in her glory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Grieue no more (deare Aunt) for the Nauy Royall of England; for although <HI>Nottingam</HI> were remisse and carelesse here∣in, yet braue <HI>Buckingham</HI> hath of late yeares set a new face on that Fleet: and makes it not onely his delight, but his glory to re-edifie and reforme them; yea there is not a yeare passes him, but hee brings some new forth from their Dockes, and puts in other old, al∣though <HI>Cranfield</HI> (resembling himselfe) bites his lips at the charge thereof, because he affirmes he hath other occasions to disburse, and pay away the Kings Treasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nephew <HI>Wales</HI> I am glad to heare that <HI>Buckingham</HI> is so carefull of England▪ Fleet-Royall, and in very deed, his Ambition, Care, and Zeale herein, will infallibly purchase him much loue and honour of the whole Kingdome, especially if he continue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H: 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinks Scotland annexed and vnited to England, should make it farre the stronger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how can King <HI>Iames</HI> say England and Scotland is strong, when he feares the powers of Spaine, and will not know or beleeue his owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea it were much honour to the King, and happinesse to his Kingdomes and Subiects, if in any poynt (knowing the weake∣nesse thereof) he would fortifie and reforme it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>And it were a great happinesse for most Kingdomes and free Estates of Europe, if they would follow the examples of the Venetians and Hollenders, who will neither trust, nor loue, much lesse, feare Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And among the rest, if England would follow it, they should drawe securitie out of danger, whereas now her apparant
<PB N="38" REF="25"/>
danger is drawne and deriued from her apparant security.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that the King my Husband would thinke hereof.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that the King my Father would make vse hereof.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that King <HI>Iames</HI> my Heire and Successour would not hearken or beleeue the contrary hereof.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But this were the way to haue warres with Spaine, and King <HI>Iames</HI> I vnderstand, is resolued to liue and dye in peace with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Warre cannot be bought at a cheape rate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But it is pitty that peace should be bought at too deare and dishonourable a rate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue alwayes beene enformed, that England still gets by her warres with Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>I got by my warres with Spaine, and Spaine lost by it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Father and his Subiects lose by his Peace with Spaine, and Spaine gets by it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>When England hath lost her selfe, she can lose no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Sister, your death was the death of the Popes hopes, and of Spaines pretences to England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>But they both seeme to reuiue and bud forth a fresh, if the Match betweene my noble Brother P. <HI>Charles,</HI> and the Infanta of Spaine take effect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>May Heauen deny the first, and the King your Father ne∣uer consent to the second.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>So shall Spaine euer feare England, but neuer England Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I hope the contrary; for in these dayes the King of Spaines Gold and his Ambassadour Count <HI>Gondomar</HI> act wonders in England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath <HI>Gondomar</HI> propounded this Match to King <HI>Iames?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>O long since, and hee hath vowed to weare out his red leather Coach and greene Buckram Litter, but he will see an end of it this Parliament.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought indeede it was not for nothing, that he makes <HI>Aesops Fables</HI> his daily pocket guest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doth King <HI>Iames</HI> relish this Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Exchequer is poore, and King <HI>Philips</HI> Indies rich, and therfore his Maiestie likes it so well, as he will hearken to no other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="39" REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doth Prince <HI>Charles</HI> himselfe like this motion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not how my Brother likes it, but for my part I should euer haue preferred a Daughter of <HI>Franc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> to that of <HI>Spaine,</HI> and I hope the Match will not succeede, because my noble Brother Prince <HI>Charles</HI> is wise, valiant, and generous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how doth the braue and graue Parliament sauour this Spanish Match?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q▪ A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fewe loue it, most feare it, But as the Match, so the Par∣liament is not yet ended.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>This would be musicke indeede for the Romane Catho∣liques of <HI>England,</HI> if it should take effect; for the very first newes thereof, made them flap their wings, as if they were ready to crowe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, for they hope, and which is more, they know, that if it proue a Match, That the <HI>Infanta</HI> will soone introduce the Masse, and Vsher in the Pope; therefore they haue reason to reioyce at it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> will not giue the summe which my Father King <HI>Iames</HI> demaunds, will not they make it vp?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q E.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is probable and credible, That their Holy Father the Pope, and themselues will stretch both their Purses and Credites to knit the Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? hath <HI>Gondomnr</HI> such power with King <HI>Iames,</HI> to hope to see this Match effected?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes; for his Maiestie saith, that his Master is an ho∣nest King, and hee a wise Seruant: The first all the world knowes; and the second, I hope <HI>England</HI> shall shortly feele, at least, if all hookes take.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. <HI>H.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed if <HI>Gondomar</HI> can effect this match, it is the direct way for him to be a <HI>Grande</HI> of <HI>Spaine,</HI> and to procure a red Hat for his Sonne or Nephew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was the Duke of <HI>Monteleone</HI> so rewarded for his <HI>French</HI> Matches?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee is already a <HI>Grande</HI> of <HI>Spaine,</HI> and hath the promise of a Hat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then Count <HI>Gondomar</HI> need not feare, for hee hath as much policie as the Duke of <HI>Monteleone,</HI> though not so much o∣st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ntation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who made and concluded the match with King <HI>Philip?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Selfe and the Parliament.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="40" REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Sister, put in <HI>Woolsey</HI> and <HI>Gardyner,</HI> and leaue out the Parliament; for you onely proposed it them but for forme, and had secretly concluded it before hand your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Suppose I did, I might doe it of mine owne authority, and prerogatiue Royall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you offered no faire play to the Parliament, though in asking their aduise when the Contracts were ready to be sealed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I had reason to follow mine owne Iudgement, not their Passions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nay Daughter, you contrariwise followed your owne passion, not their Iudgements, and so God gaue limits to <HI>Phi∣lips</HI> Ambition, and your owne desires, by making you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>orsake Earth, and he Eng<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>and.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But wise King <HI>Iames</HI> is opposite to my Sister <HI>Mary,</HI> as well in Religion as sexe; and therefore, I hope, nay, I assure my selfe, he will first consult this Match with his Parliament, ere he conclude it with <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>If the voyc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of the Parliament be free, and not enforced, I make no doubt but the Pope, the King of <HI>Spaine, Gond<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mar,</HI> and all our Recusants will come short of their hopes for the Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Daughter, what benefits proposed you to the Parliament, by your Match with Spaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strength, Profit, Honour, which England, King <HI>Iames,</HI> and Prince <HI>Charles</HI> will likewise now finde if the Match hold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>As for strength, if <HI>England</HI> would know its selfe, it neede not expect or hope for any from <HI>Spaine:</HI> for Spaines assistance hath alwayes proued fatall and ruinous, to those who haue vsed it; And if England would assume the ancient generosity of her Ancestors, and forsake her new fangled pride and prodigality: Wee know it is strong enough to beat Spaine, and all his Kingdomes and Prouinces, and no way so weake, to feare that Spaine should make England a Prouince; for it were farre safer for England and Englishmen, if they wore worse cloathes, and had better hearts and swords, and if they were more martiall and lesse effeminate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>For Profit, what Indies is richer then England? for if En∣gland want money, herselfe is still more powerfull and capable to inrich it selfe, if it would be lesse vaine, and more frugall and in∣dustrious, &amp;c. what is a few hundred thousand Pounds to England,
<PB N="41" REF="26"/>
if England be thereby exposed to the danger of Spaine? or that it b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> againe fetcht from them by the Bye, as it was brought in by the Maine? for was profit euer cheape when it was bought with losse and repentance, with teares and blood? or shall not euery Ducket be weighed and counterpoised downe with a farre greater preiudice and inconueniency: for if the Match hold, will not our Recusants looke a loo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e? will not <HI>Spaniards</HI> bee so ambitiously insolent to at∣tempt to out-looke <HI>English?</HI> will not the Pope steale in by degrees, and the King of Spaine breake in either like a torrent or a thunder∣bolt, when his factors and agents haue made all things ripe and in a readinesse? will this be <HI>Englands</HI> profit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>For Honour, <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Scotland</HI> were Free, Royall, and ancient Monarchies; when indeed <HI>Spaine</HI> was not <HI>Spaine,</HI> but dis∣ioynted and disseuered Prouinces: yea, for Pompe, State, and Glo∣ry, our Princes were Kings, when their Kings were scarce Princes, nor their Princes Nobles: Therefore GREAT BRITTAINE by the Match can conferre and adde honour to <HI>Spaine;</HI> but not <HI>Spaine</HI> to GREAT BRITTAINE.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could neuer yet affect the match of Spaine, for either of the two Princes my Sonnes: for the <HI>Spaniard</HI> is by nature as tre∣cherous as proud, and although <HI>Northampton</HI> perswaded me thereto, yet I loued true-hearted <HI>Salisbury,</HI> who alwayes diuerted me from it; as (in the depth of his Allegiance, and the profunditie of his wisdome and Iudgement) well fore-seeing they would proue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>atall and rui∣nous to England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is strange to see with what insatiable desire and Ambi∣tion, <HI>Spaine</HI> couets <HI>England;</HI> for hee hath already attempted it by trechery, by force, and now by the Match of his Daughter the <HI>In∣fanta</HI> to Prince <HI>Charles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>You meane King <HI>Philip</HI> the 2. and not this present King <HI>Philip</HI> the third; And as <HI>Don Iuan de Taris</HI> (the Ambassadour of Spaine) told King <HI>Iames</HI> at his first comming to the Crowne of En∣gland, that the Ambition and malice of <HI>Spaine</HI> to <HI>England,</HI> dyed with that Prince, and was interred and buryed with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But was this King <HI>Philip</HI> the third and his Councell, neuer acquainted with that horrible Gunpowder Treason, whereby it was intended and resolued, that England should haue beene blowne vp, ouerthrowne, and ruined in a moment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="42" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>O no, he is too Catholique a King to haue hearkened, much lesse to haue approued that Passionate plot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>You might haue said, that execrable and damnable plot of Treason, but that you will seeke to diminish and extenuate Rome and Spaines Treasons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>You infinitely wrong the Pope, and King of Spaine, to suspect, much lesse to beleeue, that they were acquainted with that Powder plot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>No? went not <HI>Faulkes</HI> (that hellish Incendary) once to Rome about it, and the younger <HI>Winter</HI> twice to <HI>Vallidolide.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, about some other businesse it may be, although I must confesse it was very immediatly before that Treason was discouered.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gondomar</HI> told me, that both the Pope and King of Spaine abhord that Treason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I feare they abhord it, for griefe it tooke not effect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>If euer this King <HI>Philip</HI> hated England, yee may be sure now he loues it; for else he would neuer seeke to match his Daugh∣ter to it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>What force and treachery cannot effect, now affection in the match shall. Wherein King <HI>Philip</HI> is of <HI>Lysanders</HI> minde, who when the Lyons skinne will not serue, he will sowe on a peece of the Foxes tayle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>So he come into England, he cares not by which way he ariue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. <HI>H.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>So the Daughter come not into England, England neede not feare the comming of the Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Count <HI>Gondomar</HI> will beate his head and his horse shoes, but he will bring in the Daughter, and already his hopes and the pro∣babilities are great, for he is exceeding great and familiar with King IAMES.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Else he could neuer haue gotten open the Prison dores for the Romane Priests and Iesuites.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. <HI>H.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Nor haue made <HI>Raleighs</HI> head to caper beyond his body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor haue kept back an Army from my Sonne and Daugh∣ter the King and Queene of <HI>Bohemia,</HI> when so many hundred thou∣sand valiant English Souldiers desired and longed to haue serued them in their warres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Nor haue shipt away so great a quantitie of Ordnance for Spaine, which one of these dayes will returne bullets to our hearts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="43" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor haue procured a gallant Fleete to secure the Coast of <HI>Spaine,</HI> against the Turkish Pyrates, vndeer coulour of going to <HI>Ar∣gier</HI> and <HI>Barbary.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>That Fleete was fitter to haue gone to <HI>Mexico.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>So indeed it might haue returned with glory and Gold, whereas now I feare it will with losse and repentance, I will not say with shame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I know by Experience, it is an excellent thing for England to fight with Spaniards, but not to ioyne with Spaniards against others.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should not our English Fleetes goe for the West Indies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q▪ <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>If this proposition be broached, then <HI>Gandomar</HI> will run madde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E▪ 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>What difference is there betwixt the East and West Indies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>As much as there is betweene Pepper and Siluer, or white Feathers and yellow Gold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but <HI>England,</HI> neere this twenty yeares hath lost those golden times of going to the Gardens of <HI>Hesperides.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And now <HI>Holland</HI> after ten yeares tryall, and patience, re∣solues to finde them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now we speake of <HI>Holland:</HI> It againe exceedingly grieues me, that <HI>England</HI> goes from <HI>Holland,</HI> in that it will not protect it a∣gainst <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>And truely it is my ioy and comfort to vnderstand it; for the farther <HI>England</HI> goes from <HI>Holland,</HI> I am sure the neerer <HI>Spaine</HI> comes to <HI>England.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, if the Match hold, <HI>Holland</HI> can expect no assistance from <HI>England;</HI> for the Pope, the King of Spaine, <HI>Gondomar,</HI> the Ie∣suites, and English Recusants, will in few yeares so shuffle and deale the cards, as England shall not bee able to assist herselfe, much lesse her Neighbours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why that is the way, in a few more yeares, to make <HI>En∣gland</HI> a Prouince to <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, yea, there is the mysterie; for if the match with <HI>Spaine</HI> hold, the conquest of <HI>England</HI> will vndoubtedly follow, &amp; then <HI>Gon∣domar</HI> can be no lesse then <HI>Vice-roy</HI> or great Commander of <HI>England,</HI> for the King and Councell of <HI>Spaine</HI> will iudge him worthy of this
<PB N="44" REF="28"/>
honour, because he hath deserued it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>It were better Spaine were Hell, and <HI>Gondomar</HI> Vice-roy to the Diuell, as he is now Ambassadour to the Catholicke King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>But is it possible that the <HI>King</HI> of <HI>Spaine</HI> hath so little Iu∣stice and charity, and so much vanitie and ambition to desire it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>The <HI>Kings</HI> of <HI>Spaine</HI> make this the tenth Article of their Creed, that the Rules of Empire and State ought to giue Lawes, but not to receiue any.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>But this is contrary to the Lawes of the <HI>KING</HI> of <HI>Kings.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But in the Counsell of Spaine, the Rules of State are al∣waies too sublime and powerfull for those of Religion; yea the Pope will easily dispence with the <HI>King of Spaine,</HI> to make a Conquest of England, either by treachery, hostilitie, or the match: for it is a∣gainst an Heriticke <HI>King</HI> and people, who refuse to enter into the bo∣some of the Church, and therefore lawfull in it selfe; because it tends to the Catholique cause, the displanting and rooting out of Heretikes, and the establishing and pres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uation of the Romane Catholikes in England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Those giddy and passionate Romane Catholiques of En∣gland, who disire to fish in troubled waters, who delight in nothing but in innouation and nouelty, and who make a May-game of Consci∣ence, and an Ape of Religion, may peraduenture flatter themselues with the false sunne-shine of these hopes; but those of them whose hearts are better lodged, and whose eyes and iudgements can see far∣ther and clearer: Those I say who know by the Lawes of Grcae and Nature, what they owe to GOD, to their lawfull Prince and Coun∣try; those remember, that the Duke of <HI>Medina Sydonta</HI> said in eighty eight (who was then Generall of the Spanish Fleete) that his Commission was not to distinguish of Religion; but to make a pas∣sage with his Sword, ore both Religions without exception, that thereby the King his Master might haue the easier way, and fairer passage to the Crowne and Kingdome of <HI>England:</HI> Therefore wee neede no perspectiue Glasse, or Spectacles to see, that it is not the establishing of the Romane Religion, but of himselfe in <HI>England,</HI> whereat the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> still aymes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Count <HI>Gondomar</HI> is wise enough to prouide a play∣ster for that sore, for hee in netling the Nobler sort of Catholiques
<PB N="45" REF="28"/>
with the match, hath in plaine tearmes giuen the lye to the Duke of <HI>Medina</HI> his speech, and therefore he hopes they will beleeue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>The nobler and more passionate and factious sort of them may beleeue <HI>Gondomnr</HI> herein, but the wiser, temporate, and consci∣ous will not; and yet the Feminine Gender, are Masculine sticklers and solicitors for him, as hee and the Iesuites are for the King his Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, the Romane Catholikes of England haue reason to beleeue <HI>Gondomar;</HI> sith King IAMES loues him well, as hee esteemes his speeches Oracles and Scripture; and who with the quintessence of his <HI>Castillian,</HI> or rather <HI>Galician</HI> braine, hath now brought matters to this passe, that no sincere aduise, honest Letter. Religious Sermon, or true picture can point at the King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> but they are called in; and their Authors imprisoned (in sted of rewarded) though neuer so honest and loyall Subiects.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But me thinkes that this is no subtill policie of <HI>Gondamar;</HI> for the more he striues to suppresse the truth, the more it will flou∣rish and preuaile; For (for the good of England) if one penne, or tongue bee commaunded to silence, they will occasion and set tenne at libertie to write and speake; as Grasse or Cammomell, which the more it is depressed, the thicker it will spread and grow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But hath not <HI>Gondomar</HI> reason to strike whiles he findes the Iron hot, and to take the benefit of the floud, before the ebbe come or the tide be spent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed they say, hee reports that this Summer time, the ayre of <HI>London</HI> and <HI>Islington</HI> is not sweete enough, either for his Fistula, or perfumed braine, and that hee hath thereforefore gotten leaue of his Maiestie, to lodge in a part of his Pallace of <HI>Greenwich,</HI> which stands in so pure an Ayre, vpon the pleasant Christall Riuer of <HI>Thames.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were a presumptuous part of <HI>Gondomar</HI> indeed, to as∣pire to lodge in that pleasant, and Royall Pallace of <HI>Greenwich.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q▪ <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>But if it bee so, I thinke it is not to lodge there himselfe, but onely to square out the <HI>Infanta's</HI> Lodgings, her Chamber of Presence, and a Plot to build her Grace a Chappell against shee come, whereof <HI>Iones</HI> Sir <HI>Innigo</HI> hath already the Modell in his braines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="46" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>If King IAMES my Father lodge <HI>Gondomar</HI> this Sum∣mer in <HI>Greenwich,</HI> the next, King <HI>Philip</HI> himselfe will hope to lye in <HI>White-Hall.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E▪ 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay soft▪ first let his Daughter the <HI>Infanta</HI> come, for shee must breake the Ice, ere his Catholique Maiestie will dare aduenture to come passe the Seas hither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Aduenture to come? why wherefore else, saith Count <HI>Gondomar,</HI> lyes King IAMES his Fleete at <HI>Alciant,</HI> and <HI>Carthage∣na,</HI> but to transport her for <HI>England</HI> this Summer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Vntill I am enforced to vnderstand, that that Fleete is at <HI>Lisbone, the Groyne,</HI> or Saint <HI>Andera,</HI> I will not beleeue it, but then I will feare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>So the Heretike Protestants of <HI>France</HI> feared their Spa∣nish matches, and yet we see they prosper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>It is the end which crownes the beginning, not the begin∣ning the end of a worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>What speake you Sister of the <HI>French</HI> matches with <HI>Spain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> to this of <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Spaine?</HI> for all the World knowes, that the Estates of <HI>England</HI> and <HI>France,</HI> are Diametrically opposite in point of Religion; for <HI>France</HI> hath fortie Papists for one Protestant, and <HI>England</HI> fortie Prot-stants for one Papist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>But those Protesting Heretikes of <HI>England,</HI> will sing an∣other tune, when they see the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> hath made their Coun∣trey his Prouince.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heauen forbid, that euer <HI>England</HI> should sing the tune of <HI>Spaines</HI> Ballad, or <HI>Spaine</HI> liue so long to make <HI>England</HI> see that dis∣mall and bloudy day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E▪</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>It were farre better, that Prince CHARLES were mar∣ried to an <HI>English</HI> Milke-maid, and the <HI>Infanta</HI> of <HI>Spaine</HI> mewed vp for a Nunne in a Cloyster.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, for how can my Sonne Prince CHARLES thinke the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> loues him, when he sees that vnder-hand he is a mortall and professed Enemy to his Brother and Sister, the King and Queene of <HI>Bohemia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>You mistake Madame; for it is the Emperour <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> and not King <HI>Philip</HI> that is their mortall Enemy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>If <HI>Philip</HI> had not (vnder-hand) powerfully assisted <HI>Ferdi∣nand,</HI> His Imperiall Maiestie, had neither had legs to goe, nor wings
<PB N="47" REF="29"/>
to flie into <HI>Prague,</HI> and yet the King my Father will not asist his Son in Law, King <HI>Frederick.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Yes to recouer the <HI>Pallatinate</HI> if that were lost; But <HI>Gon∣dam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r</HI> through his slye crouches, and sugred insinuations, hath ex∣torred a hope, and some say wrested a promise from King IAMES not to assist <HI>Bohemia,</HI> but I hope the contrary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will <HI>Spinola</HI> restore those townes he hath taken in the <HI>Pallatinate.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gondomar</HI> promised that <HI>Digby</HI> shall bring that home vn∣der his hand and seale, onely he sayes, tis fit that <HI>Spinola</HI> should be sa∣tisfied for his charges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats an old baffle and tricke of Spaine, which vpon the matter, will proue but a flat denyall. Therefore if King IAMES please to hearken to my advise, I would send an Army thither and re-fetch these Townes of the <HI>Pallatinate</HI> from <HI>Ferdinand, Phillip, Albertus,</HI> and <HI>Bauari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> with the point of the sword, in despight of <HI>Spinola, Tilly,</HI> and <HI>Cordo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>a.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I were againe liuing in England, I would so worke with the King my Father, that this resolution of Queene <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> should neuer dye, but spedily bee put in execution; for it is the sa∣fest, cheapest, shortest, and honourablest way for England; yea what would not England doe for my deare and Royall Sister of Bo∣hemia, if the King my Father would giue it the word of command?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But content your selfe Nephew▪ Count <HI>Gondomar</HI> hath promised that his Master King <HI>Phillip</HI> will giue King <HI>Iames</HI> content for his Townes of the Pallatinate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>So <HI>Gondomar</HI> promised his Maiesty, that <HI>Spinola</HI> should neuer attempt the <HI>Pallatinate,</HI> and yet we see the contrary, and be∣ing false in this, how, or what reason haue we to beleeue him to bee true in the match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>England must beleeue him sith the King doth, and will. And herein I both triumph and glory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus my Royall Father intreates; where he should com∣mand, and loues Spaine, where he hath farre more reason to hate it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>And this is my truest griefe and deepest affliction, that King <HI>Iames</HI> will still delight in contemplation, when (if his Maiesty will not) all the world sees, that King <HI>Phillip</HI> is (vnder-hand deepe in actiō.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="48" REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be that <HI>King Iames</HI> thinkes <HI>King Phillip</HI> to be of <HI>Han∣niballs</HI> minde, who more feared <HI>Fabius</HI> not fighting. then <HI>Marcellus</HI> fighting, or of <HI>Pompe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>▪ or</HI> of <HI>Marcus Crassus</HI> their opinion, who were more afraid of <HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cero's</HI> gowne, then of <HI>Caesars</HI> sword.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing lesse; for <HI>King Phillip</HI> loues <HI>King Iames</HI> his Gowne and pen, yet no way feares his sword.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if King <HI>Iames</HI> inherited my resolution as he doth my Kingdomes, I would make Spaine feare his sword, and <HI>Rome</HI> either loue or obey his pen, and neuer consent to a Peace, much lesse to the match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>But why should <HI>King Philip</HI> feare <HI>King Iames</HI> his sword, sith he neuer yet knew the way to drawe ir: or why should his Ca∣tholike Maiesty feare the Counsell of England sith it is apparant to all the world; that the eliment and delight of their King, is bookes, not battailes, the pen, not the pike.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? know you not Daughter that King IAMES hath lately established a Counsell of Warre, and whereunto think you tends that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>M.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>To peace I hope, or rather, assure my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then Sister you are of neere intelligence with <HI>Gondomar;</HI> for not long since in one of his dispatches to Spaine, he wrote the LL. of that Councell, that they should not doubt nor feare of the Counsell or warre of England; for it was (said he) but a scarre-Crow to feare, not to hurt, and would onely serue as a Vane on a house top, rather for ornament then vse. But if King IAMES were of my minde, his Counsell of warre should strike rather then threaten; and send a Royall Army into the bowels and heart of <HI>Ca∣stille</HI> ere they thought it could be ready to depart from the Ports of England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not into <HI>Castille;</HI> for then the peace were quite broken betwixt ENGLAND and SPAINE.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. <HI>H.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Why then into <HI>Bohemia,</HI> the <HI>Pallatinate;</HI> The <HI>Netherlands,</HI> or the States of <HI>Uenice,</HI> or wheresoeuer the <HI>Castillians</HI> Regiments di∣sturbe the publique peace of Christendome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see no reason to the contrary, but England should be as soone in Armes and action as Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>But it is the inchanting melody of the match, that brings
<PB N="49" REF="30"/>
England out of tune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But in this proposition and parlee of the match, the King and Counsell of Spaine, speake faire termes, and giue reall not verball content to <HI>King Iames.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>E.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>So did <HI>Philip</HI> your Husband, and his Father by his Em∣bassadours to mine at <HI>Bourbourg,</HI> thereby to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ulle me a sleepe when his great Armado was in a manner ready to weigh Anchor, and set Sayle from <HI>Lisbone,</HI> to inuade me and my England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>King <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>Iames</HI> knowes Spaines affection and <HI>Gondo∣mars</HI> sincerity to him, and consequently to England in seeking this Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. <HI>A.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>But England knowes neither the affection of the Mai∣ster, or the sincerity of the Seruant, and therefore hath reason, though not to feare yet to suspect both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>It rather thinkes King <HI>Philip</HI> of <HI>Pericles</HI> his opinion and Ambition, who desired that the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>land in the port of <HI>Piree</HI> mought be remoued, sith it was a moate and beame in his eye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>The morall is, that <HI>Philip</HI> would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> England a prouince to Spaine, but if the Match hold not; Spaines Ambition, <HI>Gondo∣mars</HI> policie▪ and both their treacherie will proue too weeke to per∣forme so strong an execution.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q▪ M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then the King of Spaine will hate <HI>Gondomar,</HI> as much as he vaunts the King of England loues him: But I must count <HI>Gondomar</HI> hath liued too long to dote, or be made a Child in his old age.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. <HI>H.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, <HI>Gondomar</HI> is too young to dot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, and too old to be a child, therefore he is confident and sure that the Match will hold; but withall, he saieth the Parliament must be ended, ere these Royall Nuptiall cerimonies can begin, and I thinke so to.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed this <HI>Castillian</HI> Embassadour now sailes before winde and tide, vnder fore▪ sayle, and maine top-sayle, but very shortly he hopes to hoyst vp top and top-gallant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. <HI>H.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>He may chance to packe on so much sayle, that he may at last crack the maine Mast of his policy, or the maine stay of his hopes, or be so busie and violent in the solicitation of this Match, as he himselfe may giue himselfe a Shotte, which may sinke either his reputation, or iudgement, or both, betwixt winde and water.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="50" REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Intruth I found his predicessour <HI>Mendoza</HI> too busie and dangerous in my State, and therefore I forbad him my presence, and discharded him my Kingdom, whereat I know not whether he, or the King his Master, more grieued, or my Counsell and my Countrey reioyced.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gondomar</HI> hath had time enough to know my Husband King <HI>Ianes,</HI> but it seemes King <HI>Iames</HI> hath not yet enough deeply pryed into <HI>Gondomar.</HI> In a word I know his Maiesty hath heard his tongue, but not seene his hart, much lesse the designes and resoluti∣ons of the King and Counsell of Spaine, which are inuelloped and hood-winked vnder the Mysterie of this match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed I haue read that King <HI>Phillip</HI> King of <HI>Macedon</HI> went neere to haue betrayed <HI>Arisbes King</HI> of <HI>Molesses</HI> of his Kingdome, vnder treating a Match with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but that <HI>Phillip</HI> of <HI>Macedon</HI> was a Heathen <HI>King,</HI> and this <HI>Phillip</HI> of Spaine is the Catholike <HI>King,</HI> therefore <HI>King Iames</HI> need not feare his sinceritie in the Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sith you are so religious Sister, pray say, how doth the Inquision of Spaine like to Match their <HI>Infanta</HI> to an Heretique Prince, for so I know they terme my Noble Nephew Prince <HI>Charles.?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? <HI>Digby</HI> could haue resolued you of that long since, for he knowes that the sacred and reuerend Inquisition of Spaine loue England, but not the match; our Countrie, but not our Religion and people; and yet in hope to roote out Heretikes, and to plant England with Romane Catholiques, they oppose not the Match, but rather giue way to it and approue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But can Royall <HI>King Iames,</HI> and his Illustrious Sonne Prince <HI>Charles</HI> obserue their Religion and Conscience, in consenting to this Matcb, or haue the Clergie of England warrant enough Au∣thenticall, out of the word of God to say <HI>Amen</HI> to it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, for <HI>King Iames</HI> (though not the Prince and Cler∣gie) will now make Religion and Conscience Handmaydes to wait and attend the State.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>But his Maiesty should doe farre better to defend the Faith (whereof he is the defender) and therein the State, which professeth the true and sincere Religion of Christ and his Apostles,
<PB N="51" REF="31"/>
sith Plety is the preseruer of Kingdomes, and all our actions whatso∣euer should tend to the glory of God; which is the banishing of Ido∣latry and Superstition, with their effects and causes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why pray, what Marriage so religious as for Prince <HI>Charles</HI> to match with the Catholique King his Daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sister you haue still Religion in your tongue, but I feare we shall finde none in your heart, for pray what places haue you of diuine Scripture, to authorize and approue this Match of Prince <HI>Charles</HI> with the <HI>Infanta,</HI> sith they are of a different Religion and Beliefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I confesse I haue none to approue it, so I am sure you all cannot alleadge any one to oppose and contradict it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I produce <HI>Gen. Ch.</HI> 24. <HI>Ch</HI> 16. against it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I, <HI>Exod. Ch.</HI> 34. <HI>Iudg. Ch.</HI> 17.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I, <HI>Iosh. Ch.</HI> 23. 2. <HI>Chron. Ch.</HI> 21.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I, 1. <HI>Kings Ch.</HI> 11. <HI>Chap.</HI> 16.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I, <HI>Ezra. Ch.</HI> 9. <HI>Nehem. Ch.</HI> 13.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, whatsoeuer you say this Match (notwithstand∣ing) tends to Gods glory, and the good of the Catholique and Apo∣stolique Church, and in the end you shall finde, that <HI>Gondomars</HI> po∣licie and <HI>Spaines</HI> Ambition will triumph ore your Scripture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>This match tends onely to bring in the Pope into our Churches, and the King of Spaine into our estate; for that is the ayme of the first, the Ambition of the second, and the obiect and hopes of both, and I feare a few yeares will proue it so; if in time it bee not remedied and preuented: which GOD of his mercie graunt, for 'tis true all the wheeles of <HI>Gondomars</HI> Art and inuention, are at worke to effect and accomplish it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Pope I must confesse (as Christs Vicar Generall on Earth) desires that England were Catholique, but for the good King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> hee hath Kingdomes enough of his owne, and there∣fore lookes not after <HI>England,</HI> onely he desires to see the Match con∣summated.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, the King of <HI>Spaines</HI> tongue hath so long watred, and his mouth gaped for <HI>England,</HI> that after Spaine, hee wisheth England were his, aboue all the Countries of the World, and his Ca∣tholique Maiestie is very confident, that this Match will giue a maine stroke to the businesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="52" REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he once haue England, hee will presently assume the Title of Emperour of the West, as King <HI>Philip</HI> his Father was re∣solued to doe a little before his death; yea, his Ambition was so violent, as hee missing of England, would haue proclaimed himselfe Emperour of Spaine; and had not his Councell diuerted and pre∣uented him he would haue sailed to <HI>Mexico,</HI> and there inuested and intituled himselfe Emperour of <HI>America.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I haue heard that <HI>Gondomar</HI> hath giuen the King of Spaine his Maister good hope of England; for 'tis certaine that hee not long since wrote to the Dukes <HI>Lerma</HI> and <HI>Pastranna,</HI> that the re∣port of the strength of England resembled those huge Pageants and Colosses erected at <HI>Rome,</HI> as the Caesars past from the <HI>Meluine</HI> bridge to the Capitoll in triumph, who were outwardly glorious, and within filled onely with strawe and poore combustable stuffe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed, it is the shame and weaknesse of England, that Spaine is no better acquainted with its strentgh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>And tis my griefe, that Spaine should see Englands weak∣nesse, and not feele its strength.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but it is the Spanish Match which will giue fire to En∣gland, and make her welter in her miseries, and flame in her calami∣ties and afflictons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, that Match will keepe the Temple of Englands peace from firing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, as <HI>Erostratus</HI> did that of <HI>Diana</HI> of <HI>Ephesus,</HI> which in one day consumed all the wealth that rich <HI>Asia</HI> had bin many yeares and ages getting.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>As Religion is the powerfullest passion of our Soule, so there is no stronger lincke of Friendship then Conscience, and there∣fore I hope my Sonne <HI>Charles</HI> will not consent to match the <HI>Infanta</HI> of Spaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>But one of his chiefest Vertues is his obedience to the King his Father; for although the Prince be his Son, yet hee knowes he is his Subiect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>All the world cannot better teach the Prince my Sonne to obey the King his Father, then already hee knowes and doth; but I could wish that King <HI>Iames</HI> my Husband, would not inforce his affe∣ction to this Spanish Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he marry the <HI>Infanta,</HI> she may proue a false and vnsecret
<PB N="53" REF="32"/>
Secretary to the Prince her Husband, and a dangerous Princesse to the State: for hee giuing her his heart, his Highnesse can hardly re∣serue any corner for himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, then euery Spanish Traytor and English Rebell will shroud themselues vnder the authority and greatnes of the Princesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>So if England match with Spaine, Spaine vndoubtedly will in a short time ouer-match England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>And infallibly take the Crowne from it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>Borrow it peraduenture, to see it, not to weare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare to weare it, neuer to returne it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, for once gone, it is gone for euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then shall Englands strong men fall vpon the edge of the Sword; her Virgins bee defloured and murthered, her Wiues defiled and slaine in sight of their dying Husbands; and their Chil∣dren and young Babes shall haue their braines dashed out against the walles in sight of their dead Parents.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P H.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, then shall our Nobilitie and Gentrie, dye vpon the swords of those barbarous <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> and those who escape and sur∣uiue their fury, shall bee fettered and led Captiues and Slaues to worke in the Mines of <HI>Peru</HI> and <HI>Mexico.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then shall our Priests who are now cloathed in the white robes of Righteousnesse, bee drowned in those of their owne scarlet blood: No Church, no Temple, no Preaching, no Sacraments, but all couered with the thicke fogges of <HI>Romes</HI> superstitious Idolatries, and Aegyption darknesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, then the King my Husband, the Prince my Sonne, my excellent Daughter the Queene of <HI>Bohemia,</HI> her Princely Poste∣rity, and if <HI>Spaine</HI> possibly can, all <HI>Great Brittaines</HI> blood Royall shall be rooted out and exterminated; as if they neuer had beene, or at least no remembrance left of them, or of the Name of GREAT BRITTAINE.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>This were musicke indeed for <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Spaine</HI> to dance at, and for <HI>Gondomar</HI> to laugh himselfe to death for ioy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I hope God of his mercy will confound all those who wish or desire it, whether it be <HI>Gondomar,</HI> the Iesuites, Englands Re∣cusants, Spaine, the Pope, or the Diuell.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="conclusion">
<HEAD>The Conclusion of the Consultation.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>But heere let vs make a stand, and shut vp our Consulta∣tion;
<PB N="54" REF="33"/>
and sith so many millions of imminent dangers, desolations and miseries attend and hang ouer the head of England by this Match of Spaine; let vs goe to suffrages and <HI>Votes,</HI> that plurality may giue sen∣tence whether it shall be a Match yea or no; for what wee conclude, I make no doubt but our great God with his owne voyce will ratifie and confirme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8. Q. M. E. 6. Q. E. P. H. Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whereunto we all consent and agree.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am against the Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E. 6.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am against the Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P. H.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am against the Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. M.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am for the Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. E.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am against the Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. A.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am against the Match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H. 8.</SPEAKER>
<P>Daughter <HI>Mary,</HI> wee are fiue against you one, therefore the Match of <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Spaine</HI> hath end <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> beginning, and is ab∣solutely cast without <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<P>And now let vs breake vp our Consultation; and againe repaire to the Throne of the Lambe, (of our sacred God both of Heauen and Earth) to acquaint his Diuine Maiestie with all the particulars there∣of, and therein his Heauenly pleasure and Commaund; When the Angell opening Heauens Starre-Chamber, a great concourse and af∣fluence of Saints and Angels (singing most Diuinely) conduct them to the blessed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ribunall, where the whole newes of their Consulta∣tion, being already arriued to the vnderstanding of the Almightie; It pleased his Diuine and Coelestiall Maiestie, to call foorth Queene <HI>Mary</HI> whom hee sharply reproues and checkes, in louing <HI>Spaine,</HI> to bee so vnnaturall to hate her natiue Countrey of <HI>England.</HI> Then he infinitely disproues the Match of Prince <HI>Charles,</HI> with the Infanta of <HI>Spaine;</HI> as derogating from his Diuine Glory, and <HI>England</HI> safetie and prosperitie; and so to conclude very ioyfully and cheerefully ap∣proues of their Consultation; which for the more grace and autho∣ritie he makes and reputes as his owne. When Commaunding these three Princes, and two Queenes (for Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eene <HI>Mary</HI> was now put by and excluded) to send vnto <HI>England</HI> (by its owne Tutulary An∣gell) foure seuerall printed Copies of this their Consultation; The first to be deliuered to King IAMES; the second to Prince CHARLES
<PB N="55" REF="33"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>is Sonne; the third, to the High Court of Parliament; and the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ourth, to the Lords of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell, the which in his Sacred presence was speedily performed and effected; When a great shout of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oy, and an Vniuersall plaudity being hereunto giuen by all the Angels, and Host of Heauen▪ These fiue Royall Personages followed the Lambe CHRIST IESVS where hee went.</P>
<P>This Consultation thus ended, Queene <HI>Mary</HI> biting the lip at her checke and disgrace; and grieuing to see the Match of the <HI>Infanta</HI> with Prince CHARLES thus vnexpected dash'd; and consequently the Pope frustrated of his hopes, and the King of <HI>Spaine</HI> of his Ambiti∣ous desires; Shee calls <HI>Mercury</HI> to her, and with all possible speed sends him away likewise to <HI>England,</HI> with these two ensuing Letters which shee had written, the one to Count <HI>Gondomar,</HI> the other to all the Romane Catholiques of <HI>England.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB N="56" REF="34"/>
<HEAD>Queene MARY, To Count <HI>Gondomar</HI> Ambassador for <HI>Philip</HI> the III. King of <HI>Spaiine,</HI> resident with IAMES, <HI>King of</HI> Great BRITTAINE.</HEAD>
<P>YOur Excellencie may vnderstand, that I haue dispatch'd <HI>Mercurie</HI> to you in <HI>England,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> aduertise you of a Consulta∣tion held here in Heaven, by my Father King <HI>Henry VIII.</HI> my Brother King <HI>Edward VI.</HI> my Sister Queene <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> Queene <HI>Anne,</HI> Prince <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nry,</HI> and my selfe, concerning your Masters pre∣tences &amp; hopes of <HI>England,</HI> by the Match of the <HI>Infanta</HI> his Daugh∣ter with Prince <HI>Charles,</HI> which all the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fiue haue opposed as pre∣iudiciall and dangerous, and my selfe maintayned as profitable and Honourable for <HI>England;</HI> for louing <HI>Philip</HI> the Father, I must and will euer honour <HI>Philip</HI> his Son; They haue likewise ript vp and vnmasked <HI>Spaines</HI> former Ambition, Cruelty, and Treacherie, as well towards <HI>England,</HI> as other Kingdomes and States of <HI>Europe,</HI> the discouery and relation whereof, I could neither silence nor pre∣uent▪ your Excellencie must giue me leaue to signifie, that I feare your Secretaries are not so honest, as your selfe Politique; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>or you are here by these Princes brought on the Stage in your naked and natu∣rall Colours, therefore I could wish y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>u to be more modest and not so busie; Onely to the vtmost of your m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rtall power, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the knot of this Mat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h, for if it holde, the heart of <HI>England</HI> will be soone bro∣ken, or if the contrary, it will infallibly breake the necke of the King your Maisters generall hopes and pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ences, and also of your owne particular credit and reputation, as well in <HI>England,</HI> as <HI>Spaine;</HI> you haue many eyes ouer you, and although your sweet words and promises <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ull King <HI>Iames</HI> asleepe, you will neuerthelesse goe neere to be circumuented, by those <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> seeke to circumuent. If you can bring in the <HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fanta,</HI> doubt you not but she will vsher in the Pope,
<PB N="57" REF="34"/>
and consequently hee the Catholique King your Master; For▪get not to continue, and sor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>efie your Intelligence with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣minaries and Iesuites of <HI>England,</HI> as also with the Catholique Ladies of that Kingdome, and especially, with those of the No∣bler ranke, and who are most powerfull at Court, for they may open a passage for your Master when none else dare. At any hand vse the prime of your Art and Inuention, to keepe the King of <HI>Eng∣land</HI> poore, and be sure to riuet this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> to his Maiestie, that there is no Vertue so Royall and Magnificent in a Great King, as Li∣beralit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e. I am sorie to heare that <HI>Englands</HI> Nauie Royall, doth so prosper and flourish; In which regard and Consideration the King your Master shall doe well to build store of new Ships in <HI>Biscay, O∣stend,</HI> and <HI>Dunke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>k;</HI> for if <HI>Spaine</HI> master <HI>England</HI> at Sea, <HI>Eng∣land</HI> can neuer withstand <HI>Spaine</HI> by Land; for now the <HI>English</HI> are Effeminate, and you <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> Souldiers. I doubt not but by this time, there is such order taken in <HI>Spaine,</HI> that the English Fleet at <HI>Alicant,</HI> and <HI>Car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>agena,</HI> shall returne home with lesse, shame and repentance, whereby you may teach them that it is onely proper for <HI>Spaniards,</HI> to Domineere at Sea, and that the Sea and Maritine actions, are now <HI>Spaines,</HI> no longer <HI>Englands</HI> Element.</P>
<P>So whiles <HI>England</HI> lyes gasping, on her bed of Peace and securi∣tie, let the King your Master prouide for Warre; Continue to sowe D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uision in the Church of <HI>England,</HI> and rather augment then dimi∣nish your Pensions to you know wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>m. If <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Army to goe out of <HI>England,</HI> either for <HI>Bohemia,</HI> the <HI>Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>atinat,</HI> the <HI>Netherlands,</HI> or <HI>Venice,</HI> deale so eff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ctually with King <HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mes,</HI> that either it be so small as it can <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> great <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to Catholiques, or be a m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>anes to cause them to sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> so long▪ that it bee impossible to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>od for Protestants. I commend <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Excellen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ies poli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y, in being sharpe, and bitter against those, who either Speake, Write, or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, against the King your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and his pretenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s, for now you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nour and feli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>itie, to see your selfe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to King <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> his E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re, and his Maiestie to your Girdle the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>f th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>se will terrific others▪ Be sure to bee intimately <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with all
<PB N="58" REF="35"/>
Factious &amp; Discontented Catholikes, for they will proue fine Agents and Instruments to execute your Masters Commands. I am glad to see King <HI>Philip</HI> so sleight and dis-respect King <HI>Iames,</HI> as hee hath not this many yeares sent him an Exraordinary Ambassadour, espe∣cially, now for Treating and Concluding this Match; for the more you and he Debase the Honour and vnder value the Reputation of <HI>England,</HI> the more you aduance and prise that of <HI>Spaine.</HI> But that which grieues mee most, is, because GOD himselfe hath opposed and Confirmed the breach, and delaceration of the Match; but I hope that for the <HI>Catholike</HI> Kings sake, our Holy Father the <HI>Pope,</HI> and our blessed Mother the <HI>Church,</HI> will so interpose their Prayers to his Sacred and Diuine Maiestie, that very shortly hee will reuoke and change his Resolution, and relish that which hee now distasteth. Through your zeale and industry, I likewise doubt not, but (be∣fore a few yeares bee past and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ouer) to see <HI>England</HI> made a Prouince to <HI>Spaine;</HI> her Nobilitie most murthered, and the rest ca∣ryed away Slaues to worke in the Mines of <HI>Peru,</HI> and <HI>Mexico;</HI> the Pope installed; all Heretikes rooted out either with Fire or Halter. Let your Excellency proceed, as you haue well and happily begun, and feare not but you shall enioy your wishes, the King your Master his hopes, and myselfe and all the <HI>Romane</HI> Catholikes of <HI>England</HI> our desires. In the meane time I kindly greet and salute your Excellency, and bp your next Dispatch for <HI>Spaine,</HI> fayle not to signifie that I kisse the Catholiks Kings hand.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Written and sent from Heauen.</DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Your Excellencies Friend:
MARY Queene.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB N="59" REF="35" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>Queene MARY, To the <HI>Romane</HI> Catholikes of <HI>England,</HI> of both Sexes, and of all Rankes.</HEAD>
<P>MY Heart on Earth, and my Soule in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, hath euer so deeply affected you and your Religion, as to the vtmost of my power, I will neuer admit, that any adu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rse accident, or stratagem what soeuer, shall endomage you or preiudice it: to which end by <HI>Mer∣cury</HI> (Whom I haue purposely sent vnto you) I would not faile to aduer∣tise you of a Consultation which hath beene here held, by my Father <HI>Henry VIII.</HI> my Brother <HI>Edward VI.</HI> my Sister Queene <HI>Elizabeth,</HI> Queene <HI>Anne,</HI> Prince <HI>Henry,</HI> and my <HI>Selfe;</HI> tending to the safety and glory of <HI>England,</HI> to the vnmasking of <HI>Spaines</HI> pretentious Ambition and Treachery to many Estates of <HI>Europe,</HI> and more especially to the vtter breach of the Match betwixt <HI>Prince Charles</HI> and the <HI>Infanta</HI> of <HI>Spaine,</HI> which two last points alone, I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and defended, but they all most violently contradicted and opposed. In which consultation (I write it as∣well with Griefe as pittie:) Cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t <HI>Gondomar,</HI> hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eene narrowly both sifted and censured, and all his Actions brought on the Table, and made apparant and obuious to the dimmist Eye, to the weakest Iudge∣ment and vnderstanding, the which I haue now signified his Excellency by a particuler Letter; wherein I haue prayed him to haue a more Iealous and curious eye ouer his Secretaries, as I know <HI>England</HI> hath ouer him; And to the end your Soules and Consciences may haue Spirituall food and Consolation, I wish and exhort you to put all your Wits on the tenter-hooks to bring in the <HI>Infanta;</HI> or else neuer expect the Pope, and consequently not the Catholike King. For else all your intelligence with <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Spaine,</HI> your correspondence with the <HI>Iesuites</HI> and Count <HI>Gondomar,</HI> will not preuaile, nor your Poyson Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>iard, or Powder take eff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ct, if the Match doe not; and because King <HI>Iames</HI> wants money, and his Ex∣chequer drawne drie and exhausted, if he stand on a greater summe then the Catholike King can, or will giue, you shall doe a most acceptable ser∣uice to our Blessed Father the Pope, and to our Holy Mother the Church; That you Lords and Knights Morgage your Manners and Plate, and you Ladies and Gentle-women p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>wne your Ringes and Iewells to make vp the expected Summe; For the Match once consum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ted, you know, and Count <HI>Gondomar</HI> can perfectly teach you, a thousand wayes to refetch it, with a ioyf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll and golden Interest; I highly
<PB N="60" REF="36" MS="y"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and applaude your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oy, when you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Bohemia</HI> won, and the <HI>Pala<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣nate</HI> assaulted; towards which Victories and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Contributions gaue a great stroke, which although <HI>Ferdinand</HI> for the pre∣sent cannot recompence; yet doubt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> <HI>Phillip</HI> sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tly &amp; fut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rely will; Sit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> his Ambassadour <HI>Gondomar</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>akes him confident, that you are as fast nayled to his Scepter, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> his Catholicke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is to the Popes triple Crowne. Bee you still the eyes of Count <HI>Gondomar,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> him still con∣tinue your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, for you can neuer desire a better <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> then him∣selfe, nor a stronger Protector then the King his Master. But in very deed, I much feare that this great Parliament, will teach the Protestants of <HI>England</HI> wit, and you <HI>Romane</HI> Catholickes repentance. If <HI>Holland,</HI> the <HI>Palatioate,</HI> or <HI>Venice</HI> be in the Field, be you not Idle in your Houses or in <HI>England;</HI> for although <HI>Douer</HI> bee shut, you shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ports enough open, for it is for the Progression a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d Aduancement of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Cause, and for the Seruice of the Great Catholike King, and if all things hit well, you shall not repent your selues of your Valour &amp; Generosi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie employed and spent in his Seruic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>. What though God <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> here approued of this Consul∣tation against the Match; yet his great <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Pope, will confirme the Match against the Consultation▪ Therefore make you your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with the Pope, and doubt not, but his Holinesse, both can and will at his pleasure, make his with his God; Howsoeuer bee ruled, and beleeue in the Pope, who is the Head of the Church; For you know out of the Church, there is no Saluation. I like well, that there daily Trauels some of your wisest Gentlemen for <HI>Spaine,</HI> and now you see there is no feare to bring <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ome Priests and Iesuites, for Count <HI>Gondomar</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ath found out the Art and Mysterie, to open the Doores of <HI>Wisbich,</HI> the <HI>Gatehouse,</HI> and the <HI>Clincke</HI> at his pleasure. To liue Idle is Effemin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>te and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bee you there∣fore <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your selues) still b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sie and in action, for as in matters of Religi∣on and Pietie, so in th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>se of the State the P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>actique is alwayes more Ho∣nourable then the Theorie. In a word, as long as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Kings raigne in <HI>England,</HI> your zealous Catholikes shall there finde but little Peace, and lesse Ioy; and yet I must need<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> confesse, that God se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mes to b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>are a particu∣ler affection to King <HI>Iames,</HI> out withall you know the second meanes must bee vsed, w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ich (I write to my comfort) I see his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> neglects; So <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>f <HI>Gondomar</HI> continue in <HI>England,</HI> and the M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tch dyë not, then I hope a little time will worke all things to the best. T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll when I salute you all, and will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>till pray▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> you for the Prosperitie of the Great cause.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Written and sent from Heauen.</DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Queene MARY.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="36"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

