<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Tvvo letters the one being intercepted by the Parliaments forces, which was sent from Sir Hugh Cholmley to captain Gotherick, imployed in the Parliaments service; advising him to quit Wrestle-Castle, or else to secure Captain Carter, and to make himself master of it, and keep it for His Majesties service. The other Captain Gothericks honest advice, in answer to the said Sir Hugh, detesting so treacherous and unworthy an act. Ordered by the Commons in Parliament. That these two letters be forthwith printed and published: H: Elsyinge, Cler. Parl. D: Com.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Cholmley, Hugh, Sir, 1600-1657.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A79532</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing C3924</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E60_4</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99872026</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99872026</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">155319</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A79532)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155319)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 11:E60[4])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Tvvo letters the one being intercepted by the Parliaments forces, which was sent from Sir Hugh Cholmley to captain Gotherick, imployed in the Parliaments service; advising him to quit Wrestle-Castle, or else to secure Captain Carter, and to make himself master of it, and keep it for His Majesties service. The other Captain Gothericks honest advice, in answer to the said Sir Hugh, detesting so treacherous and unworthy an act. Ordered by the Commons in Parliament. That these two letters be forthwith printed and published: H: Elsyinge, Cler. Parl. D: Com.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Cholmley, Hugh, Sir, 1600-1657.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gordricke, William. Captain Gothericks honest advice in answer to Sir Hugh Cholmley.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons. aut</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>8 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London] :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Edw. Husbands.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>Iuly 12, 1643.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>"Captain Gothericks honest advice in answer to Sir Hugh Cholmley." -- p. 6-8.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Gordricke, William.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Jonathan Blaney</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A79532">
<STC T="W">C3924</STC>
<STC T="T">E60_4</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99872026</BIBNO>
<VID>155319</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
TVVO LETTERS THE ONE Being Intercepted by the Parlia∣ments Forces, which was sent from Sir <HI>Hugh Cholmley</HI> to captain <HI>Gotherick,</HI> imploy∣ed in the Parliaments service; Advising him to quit <HI>Wrestle</HI>-Castle, or else to secure captain <HI>Carter,</HI> and to make him∣self master of it, and keep it for His Majesties service.</P>
<P>THE OTHER Captain <HI>Gothericks</HI> honest advice, in answer to the said Sir <HI>Hugh,</HI> detesting so treacherous and unworthy an act.</P>
<P><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="license">
<P>ORdered by the Commons in Parliament, That these two Letters be forthwith printed and published:</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>H: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D: Com.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P>Printed for <HI>Edw. Husbands.</HI> Iuly 12. 1643.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="2"/>
<OPENER><PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I Am here at <HI>Weiton,</HI> vvhere I am en∣tertained vvith strange nevvs, which is that Captain <HI>Hotham</HI> is prisoner in Hull; Sir <HI>John Hotham</HI> driven out by the Townsmen, and coming this day to Beverley was first stopped by <HI>Boyn∣ton,</HI> then beaten from his horse, woun∣ded and sent prisoner to Hull: your fa∣ther and his other Officers are in the same condition; I thought fit, out of the acquaintance I have with you, and love I bear to your Family, to give you this Advertisement, that you might the better think for your own safety, which to my understanding cannot be, but ei∣ther by quitting <HI>Wrestle</HI> Castle, and
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
drawing as many men as you can after you, or else seizing on <HI>Carter,</HI> and ma∣king your selfe Master of that place, which if you do not one of these, as∣sure your selfe you will be made a pri∣soner by <HI>Carter:</HI> you may think this a Stratagem; but upon my Faith I write nothing but what is averred by persons of credit, which comes now purposely from <HI>Beverley</HI> to give me this Adver∣tisement: you have an opportunity both to secure your selfe and perform the duty you owe to His Majestie as a Subject; and if in the mannaging of it I can do you any service, you shall find me most really; Sir,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your affectionate Friend, Hu: Cholmley.</SIGNED>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
<P>I Am now here at <HI>VVeighton,</HI> but pur∣pose this night to march (God permit∣ting) with my Forces towards <HI>Beverley:</HI> Jf you can certainly make your selfe Ma∣ster of the Castle, it will be the better course: What you resolve on, do present∣ly, for J am confident else <HI>Carter</HI> will have Jnstructions to seize on you.</P>
<P>To his much respected Friend, Cap∣tain <HI>Gothericke</HI> at VVrestle Ca∣stle, These.</P>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Captain <HI>Gothericks</HI> honest advice, in an∣swer to Sir <HI>Hugh Cholmley.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I am at Wrestle-Castle, where I received your Letter; I am so far from entertaining your Motion, as I am thereby incensed to imagine you (upon just grounds) nothing my friend: Sir, my affection to you makes me acquaint you with our passage, in my late observations; which is, that your fame in the rendring up your trust in Scarbrough hath left so ill a sent behinde, in the opinion of the County, as were able to deterre any honest man from treading your steps; neither have I (praysed be God) so little of a Gentleman an honest man, or a good subject, as to be invited to treachery. For your newes from HULL, my Fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her and the
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
rest of the Officers are in the same station they formerly were in; Sir JOHN HOTHAM by re∣port is fled the Towne, no man knowing of it: For your advice to me, I am (assure your selfe sir) more honest then to rescent it: For Captaine CARTER he hath approved himselfe so reall to me, in every thing as it would ren∣der me odious, even to my selfe to entertaine your motion; for the oppertunity to secure my selfe▪ I am confident a good cause, and a good conscience, is the cheifest security; both which, if your advice (or rather device) were prosecuted, <HI>I</HI> should be deprived of.</P>
<P>Give me leave J beseech you sir to certifie my advice, by way of answer to you; there can be no way more happy for you, as J con∣ceive, more secure to your person, estate, or render you more a friend to your Country, then to draw away with you those Protestants, whom you misled by fair and specious preten∣ces of being the KINGS friends, when indeed it is to be the popish parties friends; (with whom as this, so all trecherous plots are hatch∣ed) and returne to that cause which you have deserted, and which J am confident your con∣science
<PB N="8" REF="5" MS="y"/>
tells you is honest, (to wit) the KINGS and Countries cause; for which you have ex∣perience, we did and still doe fight, hereby you shall ingage him (that really wisheth your conversion) to professe himselfe continually,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Sir, your Servant in Gods Cause, William Gordricke.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>VVrestle Castle, <DATE>28. of Iune; 1643.</DATE></DATELINE>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<P>Sir, I beseech you remember me to Captain <HI>Br: Bushell,</HI> who knowes my Resolutions to be as reall, as I have a∣boue specified.</P>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FJNJS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

