<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">To the High Court of Parliament. A dilemma, from a parallel. Humbly presented. Published according to order.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A83525</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing E237A</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E341_10</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R200905</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99861526</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99861526</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">113663</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A83525)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113663)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E341[10])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">To the High Court of Parliament. A dilemma, from a parallel. Humbly presented. Published according to order.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647,</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I).</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[12] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London, :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Matthew Simmons for Henry Overton, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Alley,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1646.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Wing attributes this to Thomas Edwards.</NOTE><NOTE>Printed in two columns. The left contains selections from Edwards' "Gangræna"; the right, selections from various documents by Charles I. The anonymous author of the postscript uses the parallel to criticize Edwards.</NOTE><NOTE>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</NOTE><NOTE>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 22th".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647. --  Gangraena.</TERM><TERM>Christian sects --  England --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A83525">
<STC T="W">E237A</STC>
<STC T="T">E341_10</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99861526</BIBNO>
<VID>113663</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>TO THE HIGH COURT OF PARLIAMENT.</P>
<P>A DILEMMA, FROM A PARALLEL.</P>
<P>HUMBLY PRESENTED.</P>
<Q><BIBL>2 TIM. 3. 1.</BIBL>
<P><HI>Perillous times shall come; for men shall be, &amp;c.</HI></P></Q>
<Q><P><HI>Multi Christum osculantur, pauci amant.</HI> <BIBL>Bucocl.</BIBL></P></Q>
<P><HI>Published according to Order.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>Matthew Simmons</HI> for <HI>Henry Overton,</HI> and are to be sold at his Shop in <HI>Popes-</HI>head Alley, 1646.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE PARALLEL.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>Gangraena</HI> playes <HI>REX.</HI></HEAD>
<BIBL>(2<SUP>d</SUP> par. Cor. 4. p. 201.)</BIBL>
<P>FOr a conclusion of this Corallory, O that any <HI>particular members of Par∣liament</HI> who are for pre∣tended <HI>liberty of Conscience,</HI> a Toleration of <HI>Sects,</HI> fa∣vourers of <HI>Sectaries,</HI> and out of those principles hin∣der <HI>all they can</HI> the setling of Religion and Govern∣ment by civill sanction, would often and sadly me∣ditate upon this Scripture, and be wise now (whilest there's time) thus to serve the Lord, lest suddenly, when they least thinke of it, they perish from the way, and God make them examples, for adhering so <HI>pertinaciously</HI> to the <HI>Secta∣ries,</HI> and that party. They may read in <HI>Ecclesiasticall Stories,</HI> what hath befallen Princes for not serving the <HI>Lord</HI> in feare, and kissing his <HI>Sonne;</HI> and they see before their eyes the ma∣ny evills that hath be∣fallen
<PB REF="3"/>
the <HI>King,</HI> and the great straights to which he hath been reduced for favouring too much the <HI>Popish,</HI> and <HI>Prelaticall</HI> party against the mind and humble desires of both his <HI>Kingdomes:</HI> and can <HI>particular per∣sons</HI> think (who are not <HI>Kings,</HI> but under that title <HI>of Judges)</HI> that they can prosper long in standing for a <HI>Sectarian faction</HI> a∣gainst the mind of <HI>both Kingdomes,</HI> and that the <HI>Kingdomes</HI> will not see and <HI>de∣sire to understand how it comes about?</HI> and <HI>by whose meanes</HI> it is, that we having taken a <HI>Covenant</HI> for uni∣formity in <HI>Doctrine, Government, &amp;c.</HI> and for extirpating of <HI>He∣resie, Schisme,</HI> and the <HI>Parliament,</HI> ha∣ving declared in some Declarations and Re∣monstrances against <HI>Anabaptists, Brow∣nists,</HI> preaching of men not <HI>ordained,</HI> and against leaving particular persons and
<PB REF="3"/>
<HI>Congregations</HI> to their owne Liberty; that yet all things should be done <HI>quite con∣trary,</HI> with an <HI>high hand?</HI> For may not now who ever will both preach and ga∣ther <HI>Separated</HI> Chur∣ches, print and act against <HI>Presbyteriall</HI> Government, and for <HI>all sorts of Sectaries?</HI> Yea, such persons are <HI>countenanced, preferred in all places,</HI> and to <HI>all kinds of Offices</HI> and imployments (which makes many turne <HI>In∣dependents,)</HI> and the most zealous cordiall men against Sectaries are <HI>displaced,</HI> or dis∣countenanced, or ob∣structed, &amp;c. These things doe seeme <HI>strange</HI> and against all reason, that the Par∣liament, <HI>professing and declaring one thing,</HI> yet <HI>the quite contrary in all things of this na∣ture should be done dai∣ly in Citie and</HI> Coun∣try. In the <HI>worst times,</HI> when the <HI>King</HI> was most misled by the Counsels of Pre∣lates
<PB REF="4"/>
and evill men a∣bout him, there were not actions <HI>more con∣trary</HI> in many <HI>Ministers of State</HI> and other per∣sons to <HI>Proclamations</HI> and <HI>Declarations,</HI> then are now to <HI>Ordinances, Declarations,</HI> and votes of <HI>Parliament;</HI> and yet wee heare of <HI>few</HI> cen∣sured or made exam∣ples. Now <HI>the people</HI> every where say, these things could not be, persons durst be thus bold to do these things but that they know they have some <HI>great ones</HI> to backe them, and stand by them; and <HI>the people enquire after, and speake who they be, and question∣lesse will represent these things as unsufferable,</HI> and most dishonoura∣ble to the <HI>Parliament,</HI> and they will humbly desire these things may bee remedied by the power and wisdome of the Parliament: and therefore O that all such would be wise in time, be wise now, desert the <HI>Sectaries,</HI> further the worke so
<PB REF="4"/>
much the more as before they have <HI>hindred it,</HI> for there is an emphasis and weight in that Adverb <HI>now,</HI> sig∣nifying they should do it <HI>speedily,</HI> be∣cause the same opportunitie will not be alwayes given, and the <HI>Psalmist</HI> hints they may yet do it profitably, if they make hast; but if any do per∣sist and go on, <HI>working day and night,</HI> rolling every stone to <HI>uphold that party,</HI> he that strikes through <HI>Kings</HI> in the day of his wrath, will not spare them, and they shall finde by sad experience: when his wrath is kindled but a little, Blessed are all they that put their trust in him.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>In the Kings Declaration con∣cerning the <HI>Militia.</HI></HEAD>
<P><HI>WE have been told that we must not be jealous of our great Counsell of both Houses of Parliament. Wee are not,—but of some</HI> turbulent, seditious, <HI>and</HI> ambitious na∣tures, <HI>which (being not so cleerly discerned) may have an</HI> influence upon the actions of both Houses.</P>
<P>In the Kings Answer to the Decla: of the <HI>Lords</HI> and <HI>Com:</HI> of the 19 of <HI>May,</HI> 1642.</P>
<P><HI>And we call Almighty God to witnesse, all our complaints and jealousies, which have never been causless, nor of our Houses of Parliament: (but of some</HI> few Schismaticall, Factious, and Ambitious Spirits,—</P>
<P>In the Kings Answ: to the 19 Propositions.</P>
<P><HI>Wee would not be understood, that we intend to fix this Designe upon both or either Houses of Parliament, wee utterly professe against it,—But we do beleeve, &amp; accordingly professe to all the world, that the malignity of this Design—hath proceeded from the</HI> subtil informations, mischievous practices, and evill Counsels of ambitious turbulent Spirits, disaffected to Gods true Religion, and the unity of the Professors thereof.</P>
<P>In the Kings Answ: to the 19 Propositions.</P>
<P><HI>But that without any</HI> shadow <HI>of a fault ob∣jected, onely perhaps because they follow their</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
Conscience, <HI>and preserve the established</HI> Lawes, <HI>and agree not in such</HI> Votes, <HI>or assent not to such Bills, as some persons,</HI> who have now too great an influence even upon both Houses, <HI>judge or</HI> seeme <HI>to judge to be for the publick good, and as are agreeable to that</HI> Utopia of Religi∣on and Government, <HI>into which they endea∣vour to transforme this Kingdome.</HI></P>
<P>In the Kings Declar: of <HI>Aug.</HI> 2. 1642.</P>
<P><HI>We well know the combination entred into by severall persons for an alteration in the go∣vernment of the Church—and observed that those men</HI> had greatest interest, and power of perswading of both Houses, who had en∣tred into such Combination, <HI>yet—we be∣leeved, even those men would either have been converted in their</HI> Consciences, <HI>by the cleernesse and justnesse of our actions, or would have ap∣peared so unseasonable, or been discovered so</HI> sedi∣tious, <HI>that their malice and fury would not have been able to have done mischiefe; [After∣ward] When such</HI> licence is given to Brow∣nists, Anabaptists, Sectaries, and whilst Coach-men, Feltmakers, and such Mecha∣nick persons are allowed and entertained to preach by those who thinke themselves the principall members of either House; <HI>when such barbarous outrages in Churches, and hea∣thenish irreverence and uproares even in the time of Divine Service, and the Administration of the blessed meanes of advancing Religion, the preaching of the word of God, is turned into a licence of libelling, and reviling both Church and State, and venting such seditious positions, as by the Lawes of the Land are no lesse then Trea∣son,</HI> and scarce a man in reputation and cre∣dit with these Grand Reformers, who is not notoriously guilty of this, whil'st those Lear∣ned,
<PB REF="3"/>
reverend, painfull, and pious Preach∣ers, who have been and are the most emi∣nent and able assertours of Protestant Reli∣gion, <HI>are (to the unspeakable joy of the Adver∣saries to our Religion)</HI> disregarded and op∣pressed.</P>
<P>In the Kings Answer to the Declar: of the Lords and Com: of the 21 of <HI>June,</HI> 1642.</P>
<P><HI>This all men are bound to beleeve, though they see the Protestant Religion, and the</HI> Professors thereof miserably reproached, and in dan∣ger of being destroyed by a vitious and ma∣lignant party of Brownists, Anabaptists, and other Sectaries, (the principall Ring∣leaders of whom, have too great a power, even with some Members in both our Houses of Parliament) <HI>our Authority despised, and as much as in them lies, taken from us, and reviled in Pulpits and presses by persons immediately in their protection, and recommendation.</HI></P>
<P>In the Kings Answer to the Declaration of the Lor: and Com: of 19 of <HI>May,</HI> 1642.</P>
<P><HI>What</HI> a strange <HI>time are we in, that a few</HI> impudent malicious <HI>(to give them no worse terme) men should cast such a strange mist of er∣rour before the</HI> eyes of both Houses of Parlia∣ment, <HI>as that they either cannot, or</HI> will not <HI>see how manifestly they injure themselves, by main∣taining these visible</HI> untruths?</P>
<P>In the Kings Declar: of <HI>August.</HI> 12. 1642.</P>
<P><HI>We were able to discover that—there was, still a</HI> faction of a few ambitious, disconten∣ted and seditious persons, <HI>who under pretence of being enemies to Arbitrary power, and of com∣passion towards those, who out of tendernesse of Conscience could not submit to some things enjoy∣ned, or commended in the Government of the Church, had in truth a desire (and had entred
<PB REF="4"/>
into a Combination to that purpose) to</HI> alter the Government both of Church <HI>and</HI> State.</P>
<P>The former Declaration begins thus.</P>
<P><HI>Tis more then time now after so many injuries and indignities offered to our Royall person—to vindicate our Selfe from those wicked and damnable Combinations and Conspiracies which the implacable malice and</HI> insatiable ambition of some persons <HI>have contrived against us.</HI></P>
<P>In the Conclusion of that Declaration.</P>
<P><HI>Our quarrell is not against the Parliament, but against</HI> particular men, <HI>who first made the wounds, and will not now suffer them to be hea∣led, but make them deeper, and wider, by contri∣ving, fostering, and fomenting mistakes and jea∣lousies betwixt body and head, us and our two Houses of Parliament; whom we</HI> name, <HI>and are ready to prove them guilty of high Treason.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Wee desire that the Lord</HI> Kimbolton, <HI>M<SUP>r</SUP></HI> Hollis, <HI>M<SUP>r</SUP></HI> Pim, <HI>M<SUP>r</SUP></HI> Hampden, Sir <HI>Arthur Haslerigge, M<SUP>r</SUP></HI> Stroud, <HI>M<SUP>r</SUP></HI> Martin, <HI>Sir</HI> Hen∣ry Ludlow, <HI>Alderman</HI> Pennington, <HI>and Capt.</HI> Venne, <HI>may be delivered into the hands of Ju∣stice to be tryed by their Peeres, according to the knowne Lawes of the Land.</HI></P>
<P>In the Kings Answer to the Declaration of the 26 of <HI>May,</HI> 1642.</P>
<P><HI>But wee doubt not all our good Subjects doe now plainly discerne through the maske and vi∣zard of their Hypocrisie, what their Designe is, and will no more looke upon the Framers, and Contrivers of that</HI> Declaration, <HI>as upon both Houses of Parliament; (whose freedome and just Priviledges wee will alwayes maintaine, and in whose behalfe wee are as much slandred as for our Selfe) but so a</HI> Faction of Malignant, Schismaticall, and ambitious persons, <HI>whose designe is and alwayes hath been to alter the
<PB REF="4"/>
whole frame of Government, both of Church &amp; State, &amp; to subject both King and people to their own law∣less arbitrary power &amp; government.</HI></P>
<P>In the Kings Answer to the De∣claration of the Lords and Com: of 26 of <HI>May</HI> 1642.</P>
<P><HI>For the Contrivers of that De∣claration, (though they have no minde to be Slaves) they are not unwilling to be Tyrants: (what is Tyranny, but to admit no rule to Governe by but their own wills?) and we know the misery of</HI> Athens <HI>was at the highest, when it suffered under the Thirty Tyrants.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="conclusion">
<P>From the foregoing Parallel, ariseth the DILEMMA: That either the HIGH COURT OF PARLIA∣MENT is chargeable with <HI>Obstinacy</HI> and <HI>Hypocrisie</HI> a∣gainst God and the publick Good: (a thing horrid to apprehend) or, The <HI>Author</HI> of the Pamphlet fore-mentioned, is as guilty of the breach of <HI>Parliamenta∣ry Priviledge,</HI> and sedition against the <HI>Kingdome,</HI> as the <HI>Contrivers</HI> of the <HI>Kings</HI> papers have been by the <HI>Par∣liament</HI> declared to be.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="postscript">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>TO THE LORDS and COMMONS Assembled in PARLIAMENT; <HI>A POSTSCRIPT.</HI></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">N</SEG>OW the <HI>Adversary</HI> of yours and this <HI>King∣domes</HI> welfare <HI>(Right Honourable)</HI> sees he can∣not keep the <HI>field</HI> against you any longer, he findes it best to recruit himselfe, by working his <HI>broken Swords</HI> into <HI>Pen-knives,</HI> and betake himselfe to his <HI>Study.</HI> He remembers how keen the <HI>Royal Stile</HI> was, and how neare it came to the heart of the <HI>Parliament;</HI> when He expressed greatest confidence in the <HI>Par∣liament,</HI> and onely struck at some particular <HI>Members;</HI> thus in Answer to your Declaration <HI>of the 19 of May, 1642. We shall never [and we hope our people will never] account the contrivance of a few factious, seditious persons, (a Malignant partie who would consecrate the Common-wealth to their owne fury and ambition) the wisdome of Parliamen.</HI> The Honourable House of <HI>Commons</HI> in their late <HI>famous Declaration, of the 17. of Aprill, have discove∣red that there are still the same spirits stirring, and humours working though under other disguises and upon other grounds.</HI> Since this dis∣covery, these spirits doe not blush to proceed according to the first beginnings, and to reflect the like crimes on the <HI>Parlia∣ment,</HI> under the persons of some <HI>particular Members,</HI> and this done by men professing great <HI>Zeale</HI> for you, and that <HI>now</HI> after
<PB REF="5"/>
you have almost brought this Kingdome (by the good hand of God upon you) to feast upon the remembrance of the fore-passed <HI>gall</HI> and <HI>wormewood,</HI> and to satiate it selfe with the fat of securitie, Truth and Peace. But (as <HI>Solomon</HI> speaks) <HI>a Foole is never so troublesome as when he is filled with meat;</HI> even so now, Ingratitude hath taken the Ballance into her hand, and <HI>Fancy</HI> sits upon the beame, and judgeth that the Talents of precious mercies which by you (Noble Senatours) we enjoy, are light in respect of some still wanting: neither can all you have done be pawne enough of adding them hereafter; no nor any thing you can say though never so solemnly, and there∣fore cannot obtaine the <HI>Credit,</HI> much lesse the <HI>Obedience:</HI> as to have your <HI>Declaration</HI> in that kind published; and because they despaire in a way of duty to obtaine their desires, have <HI>now</HI> borrowed the pen of Insolency out of the hands of Malig∣nity, and as these formerly stiled you <HI>Rebels, Traitors,</HI> Schis∣matiques, &amp;c. and another Party acted to a frenzie of zeale, wrote you, <HI>Antichristian, Popish,</HI> tyrannous: So these here spoken of expresse themselves of you, as <HI>Fautors</HI> of <HI>Errour, Se∣ctaries, Anarchy, intolerable Toleration:</HI> unlesse you put life in∣to, and take it from what they point you to.</P>
<P>Now this sheet of paper hath humbly presented to your Honours, the <HI>Designe</HI> and <HI>Language</HI> of <HI>these in Parallel</HI> with the <HI>former,</HI> aspersing the <HI>Honour</HI> and enervating the <HI>Authority</HI> of Parliament under the Notion of accusing some particular Members; and that done with expressions so high and dange∣rous, whether respect be had to the <HI>Consciences</HI> of the people <HI>over awed,</HI> or to the <HI>safety</HI> of the <HI>State at this time,</HI> especially, <HI>thereby</HI> imperilled: that hence there seemes naturally to issue (by your Wisdomes to be considered) the fore-mentioned DILEMMA.</P>
<P>For though he lay it on <HI>some Members</HI> onely, and grants that <NOTE PLACE="marg">The proofe of the result of the <HI>Dilemma</HI> from the Pre¦mises.</NOTE> the <HI>Parliament hath ordained,</HI> &amp;c. yet whilest he addes, <HI>that all things are carried with a high hand contrary, and persons dange∣rous</HI> to Church and State, <HI>Sectaries, &amp;c. countenanced, and preferred in All</HI> places and to <HI>All</HI> kind of Offices, and that the Parliament <HI>professeth one thing, yet the quite contrary in all things,
<PB REF="6"/>
in Citie and Country,</HI> seeing this could not be done but by the <HI>Authority</HI> or <HI>connivence</HI> of the Parliament, what doth he but plainly insinuate what before he labour'd covertly to hide? That this is the <HI>Authors</HI> true meaning, you may please to re∣flect on his <HI>Epistle</HI> before the first part of his <HI>Gangraena</HI> to both <HI>Houses of the Parliament;</HI> particularly, in the <HI>fift page,</HI> where what he here chargeth upon <HI>particular Members,</HI> he there layes upon <HI>both Houses,</HI> as in these words; <HI>You have most Noble Sena∣tours done worthily against Papists, Prelates, scandalous Ministers, Images, Altars, Crucifixes, Ceremonies, &amp;c. But what have you done against other kinds of growing evills, Heresie, Schisme, disorder, Seekers, Anabaptists, Antinomians, Brownists, Libertines, and other Sects?</HI> in the seventh page thus. <HI>Now Right Honourable, though you have made Ordinances against Anabaptists, Brownists, other Sects,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>and upon complaint have troubled some Sectaries,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>yet notwithstanding there is a strange and unheard of bearing with them, as I beleeve all things considered never was the like under any Orthodox, Christian Magistrate and State;</HI> p. 9. <HI>Yet I doe not say your Honours have done these things, for there are matters of this nature you heare not of: and upon complaints that have come im∣mediately to your Houses, there hath been some redresse; yet such things are done by Committees, or persons under your power and Govern∣ment, and no effectuall wayes taken to prevent, discover or reme∣dy these things. Now I humbly submit to your deep Judgement, whether God account not men guilty of that which is committed by others under them.</HI> [Nay to take off all scruple touching his meaning, his next words fasten the charge upon your selves] <HI>as also whether it will not be interpreted by men, that there is cer∣tainly great countenance and favour above, or else persons below durst not doe as they doe.</HI> So page 10. <HI>Reformed Churches abroad say, why may not the King as lawfully tolerate Papists one false Religion, as the Parliament suffer all Sects to grow?</HI> And lastly, page 11. <HI>Know God is a righteous God, and will require it at your hands, vi∣sit and be avenged for these things. Let no man flatter you with your great prosperity and successe,</HI> &amp;c. where the very charge and threatning that he denounces in his <HI>second part</HI> against some <HI>particular Members,</HI> is charged upon <HI>both Houses joyntly.</HI> And
<PB REF="6"/>
why now he should endeavour to cast that <HI>odium</HI> upon <HI>parti∣cular Members</HI> which he before charged upon the <HI>whole,</HI> (though this also fall upon the whole) the Reason may be to make the <HI>Designe</HI> at once both more <HI>dangerous</HI> and more <HI>feeble;</HI> for whil'st it was in <HI>generall</HI> the reverence of so <HI>great a Court</HI> might justly awe the People, whereas now some <HI>particulars</HI> be∣ing singled out, he might with more <HI>colour</HI> and <HI>possibility</HI> ex∣cite, and stir up the people to appeare against them. Now for this to be done not by any <HI>considerable number</HI> of men by way of <HI>humble Petition,</HI> upon <HI>indispensable necessity,</HI> but by a <HI>private</HI> per∣son, and that not in a Petition <HI>first</HI> presented unto you, that your Wisdomes might have judged whether it were fit for <HI>pub∣like</HI> view, but in a <HI>Book</HI> written purposely for the branding of <HI>Sectaries, Hereticks,</HI> and the <HI>worst</HI> of men; and that without <HI>suffi∣cient proofe</HI> in a thing of so <HI>high a nature.</HI> There seems necessarily to arise from hence the double evill expressed in the latter mem∣ber of the Argument, <HI>viz.</HI> an unlawfull <HI>breach of Parliamentary Priviledge;</HI> and a most perilous Introduction to the ruine of the <HI>Parliament</HI> it selfe by raising the <HI>people</HI> to <HI>sedition</HI> against it. For as the King upon the <HI>like distinction</HI> of some Members from the rest, demanded six of your Honourable Members to Justice, as a Prologue to the Tragedy. If now the <HI>People</HI> should by such a <HI>pestilent Booke,</HI> be <HI>Alarm'd</HI> on <HI>groundlesse misprisions</HI> to declare against certaine of your <HI>Members</HI> as insufferable in their pra∣ctises; though under notion of Petitioning against them, it may be doubted whether afterward first <HI>six,</HI> and then <HI>sixteen,</HI> and after that sixty shall not be demanded, yet with pretence held out before the people of all honour and obedience to the Parliament.</P>
<CLOSER>The Lord, whose work you doe, teach your understandings, comfort your hearts, strengthen your hands, and cover your Heads in this day of Battaile.</CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

