<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The vote, or A poeme royall, presented to His Maiestie for a new-yeares-gift. By way of discourse 'twixt the poet, and his muse. Calendis Ianuariis 1642.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Howell, James, 1594?-1666.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A86640</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H3128</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E238_7</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R212574</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99871178</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99871178</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">158225</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A86640)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158225)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 41:E238[7])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The vote, or A poeme royall, presented to His Maiestie for a new-yeares-gift. By way of discourse 'twixt the poet, and his muse. Calendis Ianuariis 1642.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Howell, James, 1594?-1666.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 11, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London, :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Thomas Badger,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1642.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Signed on p. 11: Iames Howell.</NOTE><NOTE>An imprint variant of the edition with Humphrey Mosley given as publisher in imprint.</NOTE><NOTE>Annotation on Thomason copy: "By James Howell".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Pip Willcox</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Pip Willcox</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A86640">
<STC T="W">H3128</STC>
<STC T="T">E238_7</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99871178</BIBNO>
<VID>158225</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE VOTE,
OR
A POEME ROYALL,
PRESENTED
TO HIS MAIESTIE
for a New-yeares-Gift.
By way of Discourse 'twixt the <HI>Poet,</HI>
and his <HI>Muse.</HI></P>
<P>Calendis Januariis 1642.</P>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed by <HI>Thomas Badger,</HI> 1642.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<DIV2 TYPE="body of poem">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>POEMA</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Στρηνετικον.</HEAD>
<L>THe world's bright <HI>Eye, Times</HI> measurer, begun</L>
<L>Through watry <HI>Capricorne</HI> his course to run,</L>
<L>Old <HI>Ianus</HI> hastned on, his temples bovnd</L>
<L>With Ivy, his gray haires with hollie crownd;</L>
<L>When in a serious quest, my thoughts did muse,</L>
<L>What Gift, as best becomming, I should chuse,</L>
<L>To <HI>Britaines Monarch</HI> (my dread Soveraigne) bring</L>
<L>Which might supply a <HI>New-yeares</HI> offering.</L>
<L>I rummag'd all my stores, and search'd my cells</L>
<L>Where nought appear'd, god wot, but bagatells:</L>
<L>No farre fetch'd Indian gemme, cut out of rock,</L>
<L>Or fishd in shels were trusted under lock,</L>
<L>No peece which <HI>Angelo's</HI> strong fancy hitt,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Titians</HI> pensil, or rare <HI>Hyliards</HI> witt,</L>
<L>No Ermines, or black-sables, no such Skinnes,</L>
<L>As the grim Tartar hunts, or takes in ginnes:</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="3"/>
No Medails, or rich stuff of Tyrian dye,</L>
<L>No costly Boules of frosted argentry,</L>
<L>No curious Land-skip, or some Marble peece</L>
<L>Dig'd up in <HI>Delphos,</HI> or else-where in <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>No <HI>Roman</HI> Perfumes, Buffs, or Cordouans</L>
<L>Made drunk with Ambar by <HI>Moreno's</HI> hands,</L>
<L>No arras, or rich carpets freighted o're</L>
<L>The surging Seas from <HI>Asia's</HI> doubtfull shore,</L>
<L>No Lions cub, or beast of strange aspect,</L>
<L>Which in <HI>Numidia's</HI> fiery womb had slept,</L>
<L>No old <HI>Toledo</HI> blades, or Damaskins,</L>
<L>No Pistols, or some rare-spring'd Carrabins,</L>
<L>No <HI>Spanish</HI> Ginet, or choyce stallion sent,</L>
<L>From <HI>Naples,</HI> or hot <HI>Afrique's</HI> continent,</L>
<L>In fine, I nothing found, I could descry</L>
<L>Worthy the <HI>hands</HI> of <HI>Caesar</HI> or his <HI>eye.</HI></L>
<L>My wits were at a stand, when, loe, my <HI>Muse</HI></L>
<L>(None of the Quire, but such as they do use</L>
<L>For laundresses or handmaids of meane rank</L>
<L>I knew sometimes on <HI>Po</HI> and <HI>Isis</HI> banks)</L>
<L>Did softly buzz.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let me something bring,</L>
<L>My hansell the New-yeare to <HI>CHARLES</HI> my King,</L>
<L>May usher in bifronted <HI>Ianus</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Poet.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou fond foole-hardy <HI>Muse,</HI> thou silly Thing,</L>
<L>Which 'mongst the shrubbs &amp; reeds do'st use to sing,</L>
<L>Dar'st thou peck up, and the tall Cedar clime,</L>
<L>And venture on a King with gingling rime?</L>
<L>Though all thy words were <HI>perle,</HI> thy letters <HI>gold,</HI></L>
<L>And cut in <HI>rubies,</HI> or cast in a mould</L>
<L>Of <HI>diamonds,</HI> yet still thy lines would be</L>
<L>To meane a gift for such a Majestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muse.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le try; and hope to passe without disdaine</L>
<L>In New-yeares-gifts the <HI>mind</HI> stands for the <HI>maine,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Sophy,</HI> finding 'twas well meant, did daigne</L>
<L>Few dropps of running water from a swayne,</L>
<L>Then sure 'twill please my <HI>Liege,</HI> if I him bring,</L>
<L>Some gentle dropps from the <HI>Castalian</HI> spring.</L>
<L>Though Rarities I want of such account,</L>
<L>Yet have I something on the forked <HI>mount.</HI></L>
<L>Nor i'st the first, or third accesse I made</L>
<L>To <HI>Caesar's</HI> feet, and thence departed glad.</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="4"/>
For as the Sun with his <HI>male</HI> heat doth render</L>
<L><HI>Nile's</HI> muddy slime fruitfull, and apt t'engender,</L>
<L>And dayly to produce newe kinds of creatures</L>
<L>Of various shapes, and thousand differing features,</L>
<L>So is my fancy quickned by the glance</L>
<L>Of <HI>His</HI> benigne aspect and countenance,</L>
<L>It makes me pregnant, and to superfaete,</L>
<L>Such is the vigor of <HI>His</HI> beames and heate.</L>
<L>Once in a <HI>Vocall Forest</HI> I did sing,</L>
<L>And made the <HI>Oke</HI> to stand for <HI>CHARLES</HI> my King,</L>
<L>The best of trees, whereof (it is no vant</L>
<L>The greatest <HI>Schooles</HI> of <HI>Europe</HI> ring and chant)</L>
<L>There you shall also find Dame <HI>ARHETINE,</HI></L>
<L>Great <HI>Henries</HI> daughter, and Great <HI>Britaines</HI> Queene,</L>
<L>Her name engraven in a Laurell tree,</L>
<L>And so transmitted to Eternity.</L>
<L>For now I heare that <HI>Grove</HI> speake's besides mine,</L>
<L>The language of the <HI>Loire,</HI> the <HI>Po,</HI> and <HI>Rhyne,</HI></L>
<L>(And to my <HI>Prince</HI> (my sweet <HI>Black Prince</HI>) of late,</L>
<L>I did a <HI>youthfull</HI> subject dedicate.)</L>
<L>Nor do I doubt but that in time, my <HI>Trees</HI></L>
<L>Will yeeld me fruit to pay <HI>Apollo's</HI> fees,</L>
<L>To offer up whole Hecatombes of praise</L>
<L>To <HI>Caesar,</HI> if on me he cast his rayes.</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4"/>
And if my lamp have oyle, I may compile</L>
<L>The <HI>moderne Annals</HI> of great <HI>Albion's</HI> Isle,</L>
<L>To vindicat the truth of <HI>CHARLES</HI> his raigne,</L>
<L>From scribling Pamphletors, who story staine</L>
<L>With loose imperfect passages, and thrust</L>
<L>Lame things upon the world, t'ane up in trust.</L>
<L>I have had Audience (in another straine)</L>
<L>Of <HI>Europes</HI> greatest Kings, when <HI>German</HI> maine</L>
<L>And the <HI>Cantabrian</HI> waves I crossd, I drank</L>
<L>Of <HI>Tagus, Seine,</HI> and sate at <HI>Tybers</HI> bank,</L>
<L>Through <HI>Scylla</HI> &amp; <HI>Charybdis</HI> I have steerd,</L>
<L>Where restlesse <HI>AEtna,</HI> belching flames, appeerd,</L>
<L>By <HI>Greece,</HI> once <HI>Palla's</HI> garden, then I pass't,</L>
<L>Now all ore spread with Ignorance and wast.</L>
<L>Nor hath faire <HI>Europe</HI> her vast bounds throughout</L>
<L>An <HI>Academe</HI> of note I found not out.</L>
<L>But now I hope in a successefull <HI>prore,</HI></L>
<L>The Fates have fix'd me on sweet <HI>Englands</HI> shore,</L>
<L>And by these various wandrings true I found,</L>
<L><HI>Earth</HI> is the common Mother, every ground</L>
<L>May be one's Countrey, for by birth each man</L>
<L>Is in this VVorld a <HI>Cosmopolitan</HI></L>
<L>A free-borne Burgesse, and receives thereby</L>
<L>His denization from Nativity:</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
Nor is this VVorld, at best, but a huge <HI>Inn,</HI></L>
<L>And men the rambling passengers, wherin</L>
<L>Some warm lodgings find, &amp; that as soone</L>
<L>As out of Nature's closets they see no one,</L>
<L>And find the table ready layd; but some</L>
<L>Must for their commons trudg, and shift for roome:</L>
<L>VVith easie pace some clime <HI>Promotions Hill,</HI></L>
<L>Some in the <HI>Dale,</HI> do what they can, stick still.</L>
<L>Some through false glasses smiling <HI>Fortune</HI> spy,</L>
<L>VVho still keeps off, though she appeares hard by:</L>
<L>Some like the Ostrich, with their wings do flutter,</L>
<L>But cannot fly, or soare above the gutter,</L>
<L>Some quickly fetch and double <HI>Good-Hopes Cape,</HI></L>
<L>Some ne're can do'tthough the same cours they shape:</L>
<L>So that poore mortals are so many balls</L>
<L>Tossd, some o're line, some under Fortune's walls.</L>
<L>And it is Heavens high pleasure Man should lye</L>
<L>Obnoxious to this partiality,</L>
<L>That by Industrious ways he should contend,</L>
<L><HI>Nature's</HI> short pittance to improve and mend.</L>
<L>And <HI>Industry</HI> ne're fail'd, at last, t'advance</L>
<L>Her patient sonnes above the reach of <HI>Chance.</HI></L>
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poet.</SPEAKER>
<L>But whither rov'st thou thus?</L>
<L>Well; since I see thou art so strongly bent,</L>
<L>And of a gracious looke so confident,</L>
<L>Go, and throw down thy selfe at <HI>Caesars</HI> feet,</L>
<L>And in thy best attire thy <HI>Soveraigne</HI> greet,</L>
<L>Go, An auspicious and most blissefull year,</L>
<L>Wish <HI>Him,</HI> as e're shin'd o're this Hemispheare,</L>
<L>Good may the <HI>Entrance,</HI> better the <HI>middle</HI> be,</L>
<L>And the <HI>Conclusion</HI> best of all the three,</L>
<L>Of joy ungrudg'd may each day be a debter,</L>
<L>And evry morne still usher in a better,</L>
<L>May the soft gliding <HI>Nones</HI> and evry <HI>Ide,</HI></L>
<L>With all the <HI>Calends</HI> stil some good betide,</L>
<L>May <HI>Cynthia</HI> with kind looks, &amp; <HI>Phoebus</HI>'s rayes,</L>
<L>One cleere his Nights, the other <HI>guild</HI> his dayes.</L>
<L>Free limbs, unphysick'd health, due appetite,</L>
<L>Which no sauce else but Hunger may excite,</L>
<L>Sound sleepes, and sanguine dreames, which represent,</L>
<L>Symptomes of health, and the next dayes content;</L>
<L>Cheerfull and vacant thoughts, not always bound</L>
<L>To Counsell, or in deep Ideas drown'd:</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="6"/>
(Though such late traverses and tumults might</L>
<L>Turne to a <HI>lump of care</HI> the ayriest wight)</L>
<L>And since, while fragile flesh doth us array</L>
<L>The humors still are combating for sway,</L>
<L>(Which were they free of this reluctancy</L>
<L>And counterpoys'd Man would immortall be)</L>
<L>May sanguine ore the rest predominat</L>
<L>In <HI>Him,</HI> and their malignant flux abate.</L>
<L>May his great <HI>Queen</HI> (in whose Imperious eye</L>
<L>Raigne's such a world of winning Majesty)</L>
<L>Like the rich Olive, or Falernian Vine,</L>
<L>Swell with more <HI>gemms</HI> of <HI>Cions</HI> masculine;</L>
<L>And as <HI>Her</HI> fruit sprung from the <HI>Rose</HI> and <HI>Luce,</HI></L>
<L>(The best of stemmes Earth yet did e're produce)</L>
<L>Is tyed already by a <HI>Sanguine</HI> lace</L>
<L>To all the Kings of <HI>Europe's</HI> highborne race,</L>
<L>So may they shoot, their youthfull <HI>branches</HI> o're,</L>
<L>The surging seas, and <HI>graffe</HI> with evry shore.</L>
<L>May home-Comerce, and Trade encrease from farre,</L>
<L>That both the <HI>Indies</HI> meet within his barres,</L>
<L>And bring in Mounts of Coyne <HI>His</HI> mint's to feed,</L>
<L>And <HI>Banquers (Trafique's chiefe supporters</HI>) breed,</L>
<L>Which may enrich his Kingdomes, Court and Towne,</L>
<L>And ballast still the Coffers of the the Crowne,</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="6"/>
<HI>For Kingdoms are as ships, the Prince his chests</HI></L>
<L><HI>The ballast, which if empty, when distress't</HI></L>
<L><HI>VVith stormes, their holds are lightly trimm'd, the keele</HI></L>
<L><HI>Can run no steedy cours, but tosse and reele.</HI></L>
<L>May his <HI>Imperiall Chamber</HI> alwayes ply</L>
<L>To his desires, her wealth to multiply,</L>
<L>That <HI>she</HI> may prize his royall favour more</L>
<L>Than al the wares fetch'd frō the great <HI>Mogor,</HI></L>
<L>May the <HI>Great Senat</HI> with the subjects right</L>
<L>Put in the Counter-scale, the <HI>Regall might</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>flowrs of th'Crown,</HI> that they may propp each other,</L>
<L>And like the Grecian's <HI>twin</HI> live, love together.</L>
<L><HI>For the chief glory of a people is</HI></L>
<L><HI>The power of their King, as Their is His.</HI></L>
<L>May <HI>He</HI> be still within him selfe at home,</L>
<L>That no just <HI>passion</HI> make the <HI>reason</HI> rome,</L>
<L><HI>Yet</HI> Passions <HI>have their turnes, to rouse the Soule,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And</HI> Stirre <HI>her slumbring Spirits not</HI> controule,</L>
<L><HI>For as the Ocean besides ebb and flood,</HI></L>
<L><HI>(VVhich Nature's greatest</HI> Clerk <HI>ner'e understood)</HI></L>
<L><HI>Is not for sayle, if an impregning wind</HI></L>
<L><HI>Fills not the flagging can vas, so a mind</HI></L>
<L><HI>Too calme, is not for Action, if desire</HI></L>
<L><HI>Heat's not it selfe at</HI> passion's <HI>quickning fire,</HI></L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="7"/>
<HI>For Nature is allow'd sometimes to muster</HI></L>
<L><HI>Her</HI> passions, <HI>so they only blow, not bluster.</HI></L>
<L>May <HI>Iustice</HI> still in her true scales appeare,</L>
<L>And <HI>Honor</HI> fix'd in no unworthy spheare,</L>
<L><HI>Unto</HI> whose <HI>palace all accesse should have</HI></L>
<L><HI>Through vertues Temple, not through</HI> Plutos <HI>Cave.</HI></L>
<L>May his true subjects <HI>hearts</HI> be his chiefe <HI>Fort,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Their</HI> purse <HI>his</HI> treasure, <HI>and their</HI> Love <HI>his</HI> Port</L>
<L>Their <HI>prayers,</HI> as sweet Incense, to draw downe</L>
<L>Myriads of blessings on <HI>his Queene</HI> and Crowne.</L>
<L>And now that his glad presence, did asswage,</L>
<L>That fearefull tempest in the <HI>North</HI> did rage,</L>
<L>May those frogg-vapours in the <HI>Irish</HI> skie,</L>
<L>Be scatter'd by the beames of Majesty,</L>
<L>That the <HI>Hibernian</HI> lyre give such a sound,</L>
<L>May on our coasts with joyfull Ecchos bound.</L>
<L>And when this fatall planet leaves to lowre,</L>
<L>VVhich to to long on Monarchies doth powre</L>
<L>His direfull influence, may <HI>Peace</HI> once more</L>
<L>Descend from Heaven on our tottering shore,</L>
<L>And ride in triumph both on <HI>land</HI> and <HI>maine,</HI></L>
<L>And with her milke-white steedes draw <HI>Charles his waine,</HI></L>
<L>That so for those <HI>Saturnian</HI> times of old,</L>
<L>An age of <HI>Pearle</HI> may come in lieu of <HI>Gold.</HI></L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="7"/>
Be all his thoughts borne perfect, and his <HI>hopes,</HI></L>
<L>In their events fall out beyond their scopes,</L>
<L><HI>Vertue</HI> still guide his course, and if there be</L>
<L>A thing as <HI>Fortune</HI> Him accompanie.</L>
<L>May no ill <HI>Genius</HI> haunt <HI>him,</HI> but by's side,</L>
<L>The best protecting Angell ever bide.</L>
<L>May <HI>He</HI> go on to vindicate the right</L>
<L>Of holy things, and make the Temple bright,</L>
<L>To keep that <HI>Faith,</HI> that Sacred <HI>Truth</HI> entire</L>
<L>Which <HI>He</HI> receiv'd from <HI>Salomon</HI> his sire.</L>
<L>And since we all must hence, by th'Iron Decree,</L>
<L>Stamp'd 'mongst the black Records of <HI>Destinie,</HI></L>
<L>Late may his <HI>life,</HI> his <HI>Glory</HI> ne're weare out,</L>
<L>Till the <HI>great yeare</HI> of <HI>Plato</HI> wheele about.</L>
</SP>
<CLOSER>So prayeth
The worst of Poets,
to
The best of Princes,
yet
The most loyall
of
His Votaries and Vassalls,
<SIGNED>Iames Howell.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="endnotes">
<PB REF="8"/>
<LIST>
<ITEM><LABEL>a</LABEL> <HI>Arthetine,</HI> id est, Vertuous.
Anagram of <HI>Henrieta.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>b</LABEL> The Parlament.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>c</LABEL> Hippocrates.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>d</LABEL> King Iames.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

