<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the City of London in Common-councell assembled: to the Right Honorable the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled. Together with their answers to the said petition.</TITLE><AUTHOR>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A86813</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H3538</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E437_11</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R202508</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99862762</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99862762</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">114938</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A86813)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114938)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 69:E437[11])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the City of London in Common-councell assembled: to the Right Honorable the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled. Together with their answers to the said petition.</TITLE><AUTHOR>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Everard, John.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>England and Wales. Parliament.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>12 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London] :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Richard Cotes, Printer to the Honorable City of London,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1648.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Includes a statement by John Everard regarding a plot to disarm and plunder the city.</NOTE><NOTE>The replies are dated 27 April 1648.</NOTE><NOTE>Quire B is in two settings; B1r last word is (1) "suspected" or (2) "suspe-".</NOTE><NOTE>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 27".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Conspiracies --  England --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Pip Willcox</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Pip Willcox</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A86813">
<STC T="W">H3538</STC>
<STC T="T">E437_11</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99862762</BIBNO>
<VID>114938</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE HUMBLE
PETITION
OF THE
Lord Major, Aldermen, and
Commons of the City of <HI>London</HI>
in Common-councell assembled:
TO THE
RIGHT HONORABLE
THE
<HI>LORDS</HI> and <HI>COMMONS</HI>
IN
Parliament Assembled.
Together with their <HI>ANSWERS</HI>
to the said Petition.</P>
<P>Printed by RICHARD COTES Printer to the
Honorable City of LONDON, 1648.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="petition">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE
RIGHT HONORABLE
THE
LORDS
IN
PARLIAMENT ASSEMBLED</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">The humble Petition of the Lord Major, Aldermen,
and Commons in Common-councell assembled.</HEAD>
<OPENER>Humbly sheweth,</OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hat they had lately presen∣ted
unto them an informa∣tion
from one <HI>John Everard,</HI>
a true Copie whereof is
hereunto annexed, whereby
he doth give intimation of
some Speeches that passed from certain per∣sons
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
at <HI>Windsor,</HI> of an intention to disarm
the City, and then to Plunder the same:
And that divers reports to that effect have
been brought unto us by Letters and other∣wise
from divers parts of this Kingdom, and
from Forain parts: Which Reports, toge∣ther
with the present Drawing and Conti∣nuing
of the Army so near the City; and
the encrease of the number of Souldiers in
the Tower, hath been, now is, and will be
occasion of great fears, and a great decay of
Trade, and an enhauncing of the Prizes of
Victuals within this City: The which fears
are much encreased by the taking and keep∣ing
down of the Chaines within the same.
And the Petitioners doe humbly conceive,
That their danger is encreased, and their
strength much abated by the disuniting of
the command of the Forces of the City, and
the Parts within the late Lines of Communi∣cation,
and the weekly Bills of Mortality.
For the removing of which Feares, and
obtaining of those things which may con∣duce
to the safety of the Parliament and of
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
this City; The Petitioners doe humbly
pray,</P>
<P>That consideration may bee taken of the
information given by the said <HI>John Eve∣rard;</HI>
and that upon a further examination
thereof, such course may be taken therein
as your Honors shall think fit.</P>
<P>That the Chaines within the City of
<HI>London,</HI> which were lately pulled down,
may forthwith bee repaired and set up
again: And that the Army may be spee∣dily
removed to a further distance from
the City.</P>
<P>That by an Ordinance of Parliament,
Major Generall <HI>Skippon</HI> (who was long
since chosen, and still by Act of Common-councell
is continued Major Generall o∣ver
the Forces of the City) may be appoin∣ted
to be Major Generall within the late
Lines of Communication, and the weekly
Bils of Mortality; By which meanes he
may the better be enabled to reunite the
Forces within the City, and the said late
Lines of Communication, and weekly
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
Bills of Mortality, for the better defence
of the City, and the Places adjacent: And
likewise for the preservation of the Par∣liament,
to whom the City do resolve to
adhere according to their Solemn League
and Covenant.</P>
<CLOSER>And your Petitioners shall pray, &amp;c.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="oath">
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The Information of <HI>John Everard,</HI>
Concerning some Speeches that passed
from certain persons at Windsor, of an
intention to Disarm the City of <HI>London,</HI>
and then to Plunder the same.</HEAD>
<P><HI>IOhn Everard</HI> maketh Oath, That he having some oc∣casion
of businesse at <HI>Windsor</HI> upon Thursday the 20
of <HI>April,</HI> 1648. as he did lye in Bed, did heare some
Gentlemen discourse in the next Chamber, the number
of whom he cannot tel, but by their discourse they could
not be lesse then three or four; And that he doth beleeve
they were all Officers of the Army under the command
of his Excellency the Lord <HI>Fairfax;</HI> one of them was
Quartermaster-generall <HI>Gravener</HI> as he supposeth; ano∣ther,
one Colonell <HI>Ewer,</HI> or some such name: And
after some merry discourse, they began to be serious,
and propounded what they thought fit to bee done
in reference to the present exigencies of the Kingdome,
upon which subject they discoursed an houre or more:
They made no doubt of the comming in of the <HI>Scots;</HI>
and with the same confidence beleeved that the City of
<HI>London</HI> would joyne with the <HI>Scots;</HI> For the preven∣ting
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
of which, they could find no way but to Disarm the
City both Friend and Foe: And afterwards, they said,
they would intimate that those who were the Friends
of the Army, should come forth into the Fields, and
there they should be armed: And that they should have
the power of the City of <HI>London</HI> put into their hands,
to keep the rest of the Citizens in awe: And that they
should be maintained at the Charge of the City, so long
as it should bee thought fit to continue them. And be∣cause
that Money is the sinews of Warre, having which,
they doubted not but to procure Men enow, if there
were occasion to use them: And therefore for the pre∣sent
advancement of the same, if need were, (this City
being Disarmed) they would make them advance a Mil∣lion
of Money, or else plunder them: And the Party
that spake this, said, Hee had acquainted Commissary-generall
<HI>Ireton</HI> with it. All which, or to the like effect,
was spoken in this Deponents hearing.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>John Everard.</SIGNED>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<P>Copia vera.</P>
<CLOSER><DATE>23. Aprilis, 1648.</DATE>
Jur. coram
<SIGNED>Jo. Warner <HI>Major.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="answer">
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>Die Jovis, <DATE>27. April. 1648.</DATE></HEAD>
<P>MAster Sheriffs, and Gentlemen of the Common-councell
of the City of <HI>London;</HI> The Lords have
commanded me to return Thanks to the Lord Major,
Aldermen, and Common-councell of the City of <HI>Lon∣don,</HI>
for the good affections that they have expressed in
this their Petition, asserting the resolutions of the City
to adhere to the Parliament according to their solemn
League and Covenant.</P>
<P>They likewise have commanded me to assure you,
That it hath ever been a principall part of their care to
prevent any danger or inconveniency that might threa∣ten
the disturbance of the quiet of the city of <HI>London,</HI>
or tend to the decay of the Trade thereof, though to
their great grief these late troubles have much hindred
the successe of their endevors therein; which care they
are fully resolved still to continue to the utmost of their
power. And they assure you, That it never entred into
their thoughts to have the City of <HI>London</HI> to be disar∣med:
And they hope there can be no such intentions in
any others who wish well to the safety of the Parliament.</P>
<P>As to the report which hath been brought unto you by
one <HI>Iohn Everard,</HI> they will put it into a further exami∣nation,
that they may be satisfied of the truth or falshood
of it: and except there be further proof of it, they hope
such a report shall not render the Army to be suspected
<PB N="10" REF="6"/>
of any such design, considering the many former and
late experiences that the Parliament and City have had
of the fidelity and good services of the Army.</P>
<P>As to the particular of setting up the Chaines within
the City, they doe fully leave it to the Lord Major,
Aldermen, and Common-councell, to doe therein as
they shall think fit.</P>
<P>To the last particular concerning Major Generall
<HI>Skippon,</HI> he being a member of the House of Commons,
the Lords can resolve nothing therein, without a joynt
concurrence of that House; but they will take it further
into their consideration.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Joh. Brown,</SIGNED> Cler. Parliamentorum.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="order">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>Die Jovis, <DATE>27 Aprilis, 1648.</DATE></HEAD>
<P>THe House being informed that divers Aldermen and Citi∣zens
were at the doore, they were called in, and Alder∣man
<HI>Bide</HI> one of-the Sheriffes of the City of <HI>London,</HI> after
some short preamble, acquainted the House that he was com∣manded
by the Lord Major, Aldermen and Commons in Com∣mon-councel
assembled, the representative Body of the City of
<HI>London,</HI> to present a Petition to the House: The Petitioners
being withdrawn, the Petition was read, and an information
annexed of one <HI>John Everard</HI> taken upon oath before the Lord
Major, 23. of <HI>Aprill,</HI> 1648. The Petition was intituled, The
Humble Petition of the Lord Major, Aldermen and Commons
in Common-Councell assembled.</P>
<P>Ordered upon the question by the Commons in Parliament
assembled, That this House doth approve of the desires of the
City, concerning Major Generall <HI>Skippon.</HI></P>
<P>Resolved, &amp;c.</P>
<P>That the desire of the Petitioners concerning the Chaines be
granted, and that the Committee of the <HI>Militia</HI> do see it done.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>Harbottle Grimston</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Major Generall <HI>Skippon</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Knightley</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>John Evelyn</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Bond</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Doddridge</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>Henry Mildmay</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>John Corbet</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Colonell <HI>Harvey</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>Robert Harley</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Prideaux</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Miles Corbet</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>John Ashe</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Colonell <HI>Ven</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Swynfon</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Boyse</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Alderm. <HI>Pennington</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Blakiston</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Vassall</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>Tho. Soame</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Alderm. <HI>Atkin</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>Greg. Norton</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Erle</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Reynalds</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Long.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>Martin Lumley</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Grove</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Scuwen</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Dove</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>Rob. Pye.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Bulkley</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Major Gen. <HI>Browne</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Commissary <HI>Ireton</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Colonel <HI>Purie</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. <HI>Say.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<PB N="12" REF="7"/>
<P>This Committee or any five of them are appointed to ex∣amine
the information given in by Mr. <HI>John Everard,</HI> mentio∣ned
in this City Petition, The information given in by Mr.
<HI>Walker</HI> a Member of this House, and that he doe name unto
the Committee the Reporter of it to him; and all other in∣formations,
Forrain or other, that concern the same businesse;
and have power to send for parties, Witnesses, Papers, Records,
and they are to meete upon it to morrow at two <HI>p<SUP>t.</SUP> merid.</HI>
in the Court of Wards, and the care of this businesse is more
particularly referred to Alderman <HI>Pennington</HI> and Mr. <HI>Doddridge.</HI></P>
<P>Resolved, &amp;c.</P>
<P>That the thankes of this House be returned to the Citizens
for their good affections exprest in their Petition.</P>
<P>Mr. Speaker is appointed to acquaint the Citizens, That the
drawing of part of the Army so neere the City was occasioned
by Orders given out in the time of the late Tumult; That the
House will take that businesse into serious consideration, and
doe that therein which may be for the good and safety of the
Parliament and City so farre as thereby they may receive satis∣faction.</P>
<P>The Sheriffes, Aldermen and other Citizens were again cal∣led
in, and Mr. Speaker by the command of the House, acquain∣ted
them with the Resolutions and Proceedings upon the Pe∣tition,
and did give them the thanks of this House for their ve∣ry
good affections exprest in the Petition to the Parliament.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>H. Elsynge</SIGNED> Cler. Parl. D. Com.</CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

