<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A remonstrance of divers remarkeable passages concerning the church and kingdome of Ireland, recommended by letters from the Right Honourable the Lords Justices, and Counsell of Ireland, and presented by Henry Jones Doctor in Divinity, and agent for the ministers of the Gospel in that kingdom, to the Honourable House of Commons in England:</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A87629</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing J943</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E141_30</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R202619</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99862846</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99862846</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">115024</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A87629)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115024)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 25:E141[30])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A remonstrance of divers remarkeable passages concerning the church and kingdome of Ireland, recommended by letters from the Right Honourable the Lords Justices, and Counsell of Ireland, and presented by Henry Jones Doctor in Divinity, and agent for the ministers of the Gospel in that kingdom, to the Honourable House of Commons in England:</TITLE><AUTHOR>Jones, Henry, 1605-1682.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 80 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Godfrey Emerson, and William Bladen, and are to be sold at the signe of the Swan in Little-Brittain,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1642.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>The first leaf bears the license to print (lacking on film).</NOTE><NOTE>In this edition C4r ends "twentieth".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A87629">
<STC T="W">J943</STC>
<STC T="T">E141_30</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99862846</BIBNO>
<VID>115024</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A REMONSTRANCE OF Divers Remarkeable Passages concer∣ning the Church and Kingdome OF IRELAND, Recommended By Letters from the Right Honourable the Lords Justices, and Counsell of <HI>Jreland,</HI> And Presented By HENRY JONES Doctor in Divinity, and Agent for the Ministers of the Gospel in that Kingdom, TO The Honourable House of Commons IN ENGLAND:</P>
<P><HI>London,</HI> Printed for <HI>Godfrey Emerson,</HI> and <HI>William Bladen,</HI> and are to be sold at the signe of the <HI>Swan</HI> in <HI>Little-Brittain.</HI> 1642,</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To our very assured loving Friend, Master <HI>Lenthall</HI> Esquire, Speaker of the Honourable the Commons House of Par∣liament in the Kingdom of ENGLAND.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Here hath been presen∣ted unto us, a Remon∣strance of the deplora∣ble estate of this Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> and the la∣mentable Condition of the Clergy therein, occasioned by the present Rebellion; The Remonstrants de∣siring our Letters in the Represen∣ting of the same to the honourable House of Commons in <HI>England;</HI> unto whose grave and wise conside∣ration they do apply themselves.</P>
<P><PB REF="3"/>
We shall not need to say much in a matter, so much speaking it self, and the experience we have of the true sence they have of this distract∣ed State, gives us great assurance, that they will take to heart this our mise∣rable Church, and Gods servants therein, reduced unto unexpressable extremities, both Church and State being now involved in one common calamity.</P>
<P>The bearer hereof, <HI>Henry Jones,</HI> Doctor in Divinity, is intrusted by the Clergy to negotiate in their be∣half, and we have intreated him to solicite the cause of the poor robbed English, expressed in our Letters to you of the fourth of this moneth.</P>
<P>We therefore do crave leave to recommend him in this imploy∣ment to that Honourable House, he
<PB REF="3"/>
being a Person who is able to say much in this businesse, having been some while a Prisoner in the hands of the Rebels, and observed much of their proceedings, and being in∣trusted with others, as a Commissi∣oner to take the examinations out of which the Remonstrance now to be by him offered to that Honourable House, is extracted.</P>
<P>As for himself, he hath suffered much in his private fortunes by these troubles, and in respect of his Abi∣lities and Learning, and Painfulnesse in his Ministry, he deserveth favour and encouragement; Besides we have found him very diligent, and for∣ward in attending all occasions, for promoting the publike services here by timely and important intelli∣gence given to us of Occurences, du∣ring
<PB REF="4"/>
his imprisonment with the Re∣bels; and since especially in his in∣formation made to us of the approa∣ches of the enemy to <HI>Drogheda,</HI> when we could not conceive they would rise to that boldnesse, by which in∣formation (amongst others) we had the opportunity of sending thither the present Garrison, without whom it might have been in danger of sur∣prising; And so we remain from His Majesties Castle of <HI>Dublin</HI> the seventh day of <HI>March,</HI> 1641.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your very assured<LB/>
loving Friends<LB/>
<HI>W. Parsons, Jo. Borlace,<LB/>
R. Dillon, Ad. Loftus, J. Temple,<LB/>
Cha. Coote, Tho. Ratherham,<LB/>
Fran. Willoughby, Rob. Meredith.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="document">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<OPENER><SALUTE>To the Honorable Assembly of the Knights, Citizens, and Burgesses in the Com∣mons House of Parliament, in the Kingdom of ENGLAND.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><HI>The undernamed in the behalf of themselves and their brethren, the poore dispoiled and distressed Ministers of the Gospel in</HI> Ireland, <HI>with the Widdowes and Orphans of such,</HI></P>
<P>Humbly represent their lamentable Condition,</P>
<P><HI>Shewing,</HI></P>
<P><HI>THat by the instigation of Popih Priests, Friers, and Jesuites, with other fire-brands and Incendiaries of the State; partly such of them as have been resident here in this Kingdom of</HI> Ire∣land <HI>before, partly flocking in from Forraign parts, of late in multitudes more then ordinary; and chiefly by such of them as resorted hither out of the Kingdom of</HI> England: <HI>And out of that ancient and known hatred the Church of</HI> Rome <HI>heareth to the reformed Religion; As also by reason of the surfet of that freedome and indulgence, which through Gods forbearance for our tryall, they of the Popish faction have hitherto enjoyed in this Kingdom: There hath been beyond all paralell of former ages, a most bloudy and Antichristian combination and plot hatched, by well-nigh the whole Romish sect, by way of combination from parts forraign, with those at home, against this our Church and State; thereby intending the utter extirpation of the reformed Religion, and the professors of it: In the room thereof, setting up that idoll of the Masse, with all the abominations of that whore of</HI> Babylon: <HI>This also ayming at the pulling down and defacing the present state and go∣vernment of this Kingdom under his Sacred Majesty, theirs, and our undoubted Soveraign; and introducing another form of rule ordered and moderated by themselves, without dependance on his Highnesse, or
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
the Kingdom of</HI> England, <HI>whence have proceeded such depredations of of the goods, and such cruelties exercised on the persons and lives of the loyall Subject; such wasting and defacing of all Minuments of civility, with such prophanation of holy places, and Religion, that by the most barbarous and heathenish Nations, the like could not in any age be found to be perpetrated.</HI></P>
<P><HI>All which doth daily appear unto us your Suppliants appointed to enquire upon oath of the premisses, and other particulars depending thereupon, by vertue of a Commission to us directed under the great Seal of this Kingdom of</HI> Ireland, <HI>bearing Date the three and twentieth day of</HI> December, <HI>in the seventeenth year of his Majesties Reign; and by one other Commission further enlarged concerning the premisses, Dated the eighteenth of</HI> January, <HI>in the year aforesaid. Copies whereof, toge∣ther with the Copies of such and so much of the Depositions as answer to the particulars of this our Remonstrance we have hereunto annexed; that both the validity of our proceedings, and the truth of this our sayd Remonstrance may the better appear.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ʋpon view of all which, it doth very evidently appear, that in the present most dangerous designe against this Kingdom, the Popish faction therein hath been confederate with forraign States, If we may rely upon the report made therof by the conspirators themselves, and their adherents here, whereof the following examinations are full.</HI></P>
<P>IT being confessed that they had their Commission for what they did from beyond the Seas. <NOTE N="A" PLACE="foot"><HI>Iohn Day</HI> Com. Cavan, exam. <HI>Feb.</HI> 8. 1641. ex. 1.</NOTE> That from <HI>Spain</HI> they did ex∣pect an Army before <HI>Easter</HI> next, consisting, if of none others, yet of the <HI>Irish</HI> Regiments, and Commanders serving in <HI>Flanders,</HI> and else where, under that King; together with a great quantity of Powder, Ammunition, and Arms, for a great number of men to be raised in <HI>Ireland.</HI> This Kingdome (as they make up their esti∣mate) being able to make up the body of an Army of two hundred thousand, or more. <NOTE N="B" PLACE="foot"><HI>Lucy Spell,</HI> Com. Lowth, ex. <HI>Feb.</HI> 5. 1641. ex 2. <HI>Iohn Biggar,</HI> Com Dublin, exam. <HI>Ianu.</HI> 29. 1641. ex. 3. <HI>Iohn Monatgómry,</HI> Com. Monaghan. exam. <HI>Ianu.</HI> 26. 1641. ex. 4. <HI>Patr. Bryan,</HI> Com. Fer. <HI>Ianu.</HI> 29. ex 5. Doctor <HI>Iones, ex.</HI> 6. <HI>George Cottingham, ex.</HI> 78.</NOTE> From <HI>France</HI> also they looke for ayd. <NOTE N="C" PLACE="foot"><HI>Iohn Biggar,</HI> and <HI>Iohn Montgomery</HI> Praed.</NOTE> Being in all this further encouraged by Bulls from <HI>Rome;</HI> some of these Rebels requiring to the Popes use, and in his name, the yeeld∣ing
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
up of such places of strength as they had beleaguered. <NOTE N="D" PLACE="foot"><HI>Edmond. Welch,</HI> Com. Rs. <HI>Ianuary.</HI> 22. exam. 7.</NOTE> In all which respects, and in allusion to that League in <HI>France,</HI> they terming themselves the Catholike Army, <NOTE N="E" PLACE="foot"><HI>Lucy Spell praed Feb.</HI> 5.</NOTE> and the ground of their war the Catholike cause. And to this purpose hath this pre∣sent year, 1641. been among them proclaimed a year of <HI>Jubilce,</HI> and Pardons before hand granted, of all sins of what sort soever that shall be therein committed, tending to this great work. <NOTE N="F" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Edgworth Esq.</HI> Com. Lengford, <HI>Feb.</HI> 23. ex. 8.</NOTE> Excommunications also thundred against any that shall refuse to joyn therein. <NOTE N="G" PLACE="foot">Edm. Walsh.</NOTE></P>
<P>It doth secondly appear, that they had their correspondents in <HI>England,</HI> for raising the like Rebellion there; this not being a re∣port made to us from one part, but confirmed from all places of this Kingdome, whence the passage hath not beene stopped by the present obstructions. <NOTE N="H" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Brooks,</HI> Com Cavan. <HI>Ian.</HI> 5. ex. 9. <HI>Grace Lovet,</HI> Com. Ferm <HI>Ian.</HI> 5. ex. 10. <HI>Eliza. Coats,</HI> Com. Fer. <HI>Ian.</HI> 4 ex. 11. <HI>Nicholas Willoughby,</HI> Com. praed. <HI>Feb.</HI> 23. ex. 12. <HI>Thomas Crant.</HI> Com. Cavan <HI>Feb.</HI> ex. 13. <HI>Io. Biggar</HI> Com. Dublin, <HI>Ian.</HI> 29. <HI>Eliza. Parker,</HI> Com Catherlagh. <HI>Ian.</HI> 13. ex 14. <HI>Ocker Butts</HI> Com. Wex. <HI>la.</HI> 25. <HI>Lucy Spell,</HI> ex. 15.</NOTE></P>
<P>That thirdly, they reported themselves to have had the like partie in <HI>Scotland;</HI> that the <HI>Scots</HI> joyned with them <NOTE N="I" PLACE="foot"><HI>Edw. Denman,</HI> Com. Ca. <HI>Ian.</HI> 27. ex. 16</NOTE> and were their friends. <NOTE N="K" PLACE="foot"><HI>Thomas Crant.</HI> Com. Cavan, <HI>Feb.</HI></NOTE> That the like troubles were to be raised in <HI>Scotland.</HI> <NOTE N="L" PLACE="foot"><HI>Thomas Crant, Patr. Bryan,</HI> Com. Fer. <HI>Ian.</HI> 29. G. <HI>Cottingham, ex.</HI> 78.</NOTE> That the <HI>Scots</HI> were joyned with them in Covenant, not to leave a drop of <HI>English</HI> bloud in <HI>England,</HI> as they the <HI>Irish</HI> Rebels would do the like in <HI>Ireland.</HI> For which they pretended a writing signed with the hands of the prime Nobility of <HI>Scotland.</HI> <NOTE N="M" PLACE="foot"><HI>Geo. Fercher,</HI> Com. Per <HI>Ian.</HI> 4 ex 17 <HI>Eliza. Dickinson,</HI> Gom. paerd <HI>Ian.</HI> 3. ex. 18.</NOTE> And that the Tower of <HI>London,</HI> the Castle of <HI>Edenborough,</HI> and the Castle of <HI>Dublin,</HI> were to be surprised all upon one day. <NOTE N="N" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Shorter.</HI> Com. Fer <HI>Ian.</HI> 5. ex. 19.</NOTE></P>
<P>As for that part of that cursed Faction within this Kingdom of <HI>Ireland,</HI> the Actors therein acknowledge it to be a plot of many years, some say two, <NOTE N="O" PLACE="foot"><HI>Thomas Knowles,</HI> Com. Fer. <HI>Ian.</HI> 3. ex. 20.</NOTE> some eight, <NOTE N="P" PLACE="foot">Patr. Bryan.</NOTE> some 14 or 17 years. <NOTE N="Q" PLACE="foot">Mr <HI>Iohn Cardiff,</HI> ex. 21.</NOTE> A plot wherein all the Popish Nobilitie and men of quality were
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
interessed; <NOTE N="R" PLACE="foot"><HI>Ge. Cottingham. Edw. How,</HI> Com Fer. <HI>In</HI> 29. ex. 22. <HI>Tho Knowls. Geo. Cooke,</HI> Com Cavan <HI>Ian.</HI> 22. ex. 23. <HI>Io. Gesso<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> Com. <HI>Cilk, Ianu.</HI> 8. ex. 24.</NOTE> and by Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neale;</HI> that Arch-Rebell, it is professed, that what he did, was by the consent of the Parlia∣ment of <HI>Ireland,</HI> <NOTE N="S" PLACE="foot"><HI>Iohn Gregg,</HI> Com. Arm. <HI>Ian.</HI> 7. ex. 25.</NOTE> thereby intending the Popish members therof.</P>
<P>Notwithstanding all which, that this appeareth to have been a long-laid conspiracie; yet these Traytors for giving some colour to their Rebellion, pretend as if the occasion moving them there∣unto were new, unexpected, and pressing, so that with the safety of their lives, and duty which they owed God and their Country; they could not do lesse then they have done: falsly pretending that there was a plot layd in this Kingdome, grounded on a pre∣tended Act passed in the Parliament of <HI>England,</HI> for the cutting off of all the Nobilitie and others the Papists in <HI>Ireland,</HI> <NOTE N="T" PLACE="foot"><HI>Hen. Reynolds,</HI> Com Cavan, <HI>Ian.</HI> 4. ex. 26. <HI>Iohn Mountgomry.</HI> Dr <HI>Jones Tho. Crant Charles Crafford,</HI> Com. Meath, <HI>Ian.</HI> 22. ex 27.</NOTE> and all this to be done in one day; <NOTE N="V" PLACE="foot">Grace Lovet.</NOTE> and that to be on the 23 or 24<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>November</HI> now last past; for preventing whereof, they laid (say they) this their counterplot a full moneth before, <HI>viz.</HI> on the 23 of <HI>October.</HI> <NOTE N="W" PLACE="foot">Dr <HI>Iones. Io. Wood,</HI> Com Wick. <HI>Feb.</HI> 17. ex. 28</NOTE>.</P>
<P>For effecting which their wicked and devillish design, the sayd Conspirators and Traitors have entred into a most accursed Cove∣nant, and bound themselves by an oath of confederation, the same being subscribed by the hands of the chiefest Rebels, and certaine men being appointed to administer the same to all such as shall ei∣ther offer themselves, or be pressed to serve as Souldiers in that cause; others also being sent abroad, and in chief, the Popish Pri∣mate <HI>Reily,</HI> <NOTE N="X" PLACE="foot"><HI>Henry Stile,</HI> Com. Monagh, <HI>Ianu.</HI> 10. ex. 29.</NOTE> who hath compassed far and neer, to draw into this conspiracy such as had not before been there withall acquainted. As also to satisfie any scruples, if any were that did or might retard any from entring thereinto; the Popish Clergie being observed for the most forward advisers and putters on of the people in this way. For whereas many of the Rebels seemed no give eare to a Proclamation of grace, Dated the first of <HI>November</HI> 1641. they were forbidden by their Priests, assuring them it would be their undoing. <NOTE N="Y" PLACE="foot"><HI>Kath. Crant.</HI> Com. Meath, <HI>Ianu.</HI> 5. ex. 30.</NOTE> Hence it is that these Rebels are so hardned in their
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
course of wickednesse, that they professe against accepting of any quarter, and that they will not accept of any but a generall Par∣don. <NOTE N="A" PLACE="foot">Edm. Walsh.</NOTE> Others again disclaiming any Pardon, casting out words to the dishonout of his Sacred Majesty, as if his Royall word and Seale were not to be relyed upon. <NOTE N="B" PLACE="foot"><HI>Patr. Bryan. Hugh Madden,</HI> Com. Wickloe, <HI>Feb.</HI> 23. ex 31.</NOTE></P>
<P>And yet for making the more plausible introduction into their said wicked Rebellion; the Conspirators aforesaid, have traite∣rously, and impudently averred and proclaimed, that their autho∣ritie therein is derived by Commission from his Highnesse. Some∣times at distance, making offer to shew a large Patent or Commis∣sion with a broad Scale, giving out that in that their power did appear. <NOTE N="C" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Wright,</HI> Com. Fer. <HI>Ian.</HI> 12. ex. 32.</NOTE> Others taking upon them to read (some forged wri∣ting) to that purpose. <NOTE N="D" PLACE="foot"><HI>George French,</HI> Com. Kildare, <HI>Feb.</HI> 1. ex. 33.</NOTE> All which they stick not publikely in Market-places to proclaim; <NOTE N="E" PLACE="foot"><HI>Iane Mansfield,</HI> Com Meath, <HI>Ianu.</HI> 3. ex. 34. <HI>Henry Palmer,</HI> Com. Wexford, <HI>Ian.</HI> 12. ex. 35.</NOTE> falsly also reporting, that his Highnesse was among them in the North of <HI>Ireland,</HI> riding up and down disguised, and with glasse eyes desiring not to be dis∣covered. Others againe pretending their Commission to be from the Queens Highnesse, and professing themselves her Soul∣diers, and that what they did, was under the hands of the best of the Nobility of <HI>England;</HI> which yet in favour of the <HI>English,</HI> they did not (say they) execute to the full. <HI>(G)</HI></P>
<P>All which they falsly reported, to the end, that thereby they might distract the mindes, and discourage the hearts of the true Subject, and that therein they might gain more upon such as they desire to draw into their party; or if any should for a time stand aloose as Newters, to win a better opinion with them, then to be accounted Traytors, or their enterprise a Rebellion.</P>
<P>Whereas it is apparant, that Allegiance or Obedience to his Majesty, is not the thing they ayme at, the contrary being plainly confessed and professed by themselves; now that they are entred as far as they can into their diabolicall practise; and that their con∣federates are for the most part declared and drawn unto an head.</P>
<P>For some of them, to the making way for their Trayterous in∣tentions <NOTE N="F" PLACE="foot">Ocker Butts.</NOTE>
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
have given out, That the King was dead, and that the young King was gone to Masse: <NOTE N="G" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Perkins</HI> Com. Cav. I a. 8. ex 36.</NOTE> That they would have the Prince in <HI>Ireland,</HI> whom they would make their Vice-Roy, tutor∣ing him in the Romish religion; And that the King should live in <HI>Scotland</HI> <NOTE N="H" PLACE="foot"><HI>Lucy Spell. Rog. Holland,</HI> ex. 77.</NOTE>: sometimes, That the Duke of <HI>York</HI> should live with them.</P>
<P>But others more fully unvizard themselves, professing, That they would have a King of their own, and him Crowned within a fortnight <NOTE N="I" PLACE="foot"><HI>Tho Mid∣dleborough</HI> Co. Fer Ia. 4. ex. 37. <HI>Alice Tibbs</HI> Co. praed. Ia. 4 ex 38. <HI>Avis Bradshaw</HI> Co. praed. Ia 4. ex. 39.</NOTE>. That they had him already <NOTE N="K" PLACE="foot"><HI>Richard Knowles</HI> Co. praed. Ia. 10 ex. 40.</NOTE>: And that it was from their new King that they had their Commission so much spoken of <NOTE N="L" PLACE="foot"><HI>Robert Barton</HI> Co. praed. Ia 5. ex. 41.</NOTE>: Declaring also their new King according to their severall fancies; Some being for the Earl of <HI>Tyron</HI> <NOTE N="M" PLACE="foot"><HI>Hu. Culm</HI> Co. Mon. Ia 22. ex. 42. <HI>Marth. Culm</HI> Co. praed. Feb. 14. ex 43.</NOTE>; others for Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neal</HI> <NOTE N="N" PLACE="foot"><HI>Eliz. Gough</HI> Co. Cav Feb. 8 ex. 44.</NOTE>: If perhaps these two be not intended for one and the same, thus we finde the said Sir <HI>Phelim</HI> honoured with the style of, His Majesty <NOTE N="O" PLACE="foot">Io. Greg</NOTE>: Others yet being rather for the Lord <HI>Maguire</HI> <NOTE N="P" PLACE="foot"><HI>Anne Gill.</HI> Co. Fer Ia. 29. ex. 45.</NOTE>; there being some that said they had a conse∣crated Crown for the best deserver <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>George Cottingam.</HI> ex. 78.</NOTE>.</P>
<P>But of His sacred Majesty, how contemptuously do they speak? Let your King (say they) fetch you out again <NOTE N="Q" PLACE="foot"><HI>Eliz Vause</HI> Co. Leitrim Feb. 9. ex. 46.</NOTE>: These being their words to some of His Majesties Subjects, oppressed by them; We care not for the King of <HI>England,</HI> say others <NOTE N="R" PLACE="foot"><HI>Nicholas Michael</HI> Co. Cav. Ian. 15. ex. 47.</NOTE>; a third, That neither King nor Queen shall govern <HI>Ireland</HI> any longer, for they would govern it themselves <NOTE N="S" PLACE="foot"><HI>Andr. Foster</HI> Co. Wickloe. Feb 17. ex. 48.</NOTE>; And that their Religi∣on should flourish in despight of King or State <HI>(T).</HI></P>
<P>In all which, having broken thorow the due bounds of their Al∣legiance, their vain and ambitious thoughts rove without know∣ing any limits. It will not now content them to settle anew, and mold again this Kingdom to their own Modell, by calling of Parliaments, making Laws, and appointing their own Gover∣nours <HI>(V).</HI> Thus discourse they of the modestest sort: but they will,
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
with the assistance of <HI>Spain</HI> and <HI>France,</HI> set footing in <HI>England,</HI> and after that in <HI>Scotland</HI> <NOTE N="W" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Mountgomery. Nath. Hig∣ginson,</HI> Com. Ferm Ia 7. ex. 51. <HI>George Cottingam.</HI> ex. 78.</NOTE>; where all things being setled to their desires, the whole Forces of <HI>Ireland,</HI> in way of retribution, and acknowledgement of gratitude, are intended for the King of <HI>Spain,</HI> against the <HI>Hollanders</HI> <NOTE N="X" PLACE="foot">Dr. <HI>Iones.</HI></NOTE>.</P>
<P>Unto which their disloyalty to theirs and our most gracious So∣veraign, they have added expressions of unheard of hatred to His <HI>Brittish</HI> Subjects of this Kingdom; banishment or slavery are the greatest favours that would be afforded them; But their generall profession is for a generall extirpation, even to the last and least drop of English blood <NOTE N="Y" PLACE="foot"><HI>Anne Marshall,</HI> Co. Ferm. Ian. 3. ex 52 <HI>Iathuell Maw,</HI> Co Fer. Ian. 3. ex. 53 <HI>Iane Mans∣feild.</HI></NOTE>: Which, that it may be drayned to the full, such of the English as cannot prescribe a settlement in this Kingdom for two hundred yeers, are to be cut off, and that not∣withstanding they be of the Romish Sect: It being to that end provided, That such as do revolt to their part, should, for the pre∣sent, be accepted of; yet so disposed, as being drawn into the List of their Army, they should be set upon the most dangerous Enter∣prises, so either to be made away, or to serve their own turns of them: And what the Sword cannot, for the present, effect, an Inquisition, like that in <HI>Spain,</HI> for finding out the <HI>Jewish</HI> and <HI>Moorish</HI> blood, shall in time thorowly accomplish <NOTE N="Z" PLACE="foot">Io. Biggar.</NOTE>. As for the future, their Covenant is, That no English should ever set footing again in <HI>Ireland</HI> <NOTE N="A" PLACE="foot">Hugh Madden.</NOTE>; Even the very Language must be forgotten, none being to speak English, under a penalty <NOTE N="B" PLACE="foot">Iohn Mountgomery. Hu. Culme. Marth. Culme</NOTE>. But that which exceeds all, Not an English Beast, or any of that breed must be left in the Kingdom <NOTE N="C" PLACE="foot"><HI>Rich. Cleybrock.</HI> Co. Wex. his exam. taken at the Councell Table, ex. 54</NOTE>.</P>
<P>And as we finde the hearts of these men in their tongues, so in their actions, doing what they professe; and being in both beyond all measure profane and heathenish in their impious words and be∣haviours towards God, and the holy Scriptures, Religion, and the places of Gods publike Worship.</P>
<P>Blaspheming our God, bidding his servants, whom they had first <NOTE N="T" PLACE="foot"><HI>Rich. Witlon</HI> Co. Wickloe. Ia. 11. ex. 49.</NOTE> <NOTE N="V" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Biggar. Tho. Crant. Edw. Taylor.</HI> Co. Wexford, Feb. 23 ex. 50</NOTE>
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
stripped naked, to go to their God, and let him give them clothes <NOTE N="D" PLACE="foot"><HI>Marg. Farmen,</HI> Co Fer. Ia. 3 ex. 55. <HI>Marg. Leadly,</HI> Co. Fer. Ia. 3.</NOTE>.</P>
<P>Breaking into Churches, burning Pulpits, Pues, and all belong∣ing thereunto, with extreme violence, and expression of hatred to our Religion, and triumphing also in their impiety <NOTE N="E" PLACE="foot"><HI>Hen. Fisher,</HI> Co. Wickloe, Ia. 25. ex. 56.</NOTE>.</P>
<P>Professing, That not one Protestant should be left in the King∣dome <NOTE N="F" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Greg.</HI> with infinite others▪</NOTE>: Dragging some Professors thorow the streets by the hair of the head, into the Church; where stripping, whipping, and cruelly using them, they added these taunting words; If you come tomorrow, you shall hear the like Sermon <NOTE N="G" PLACE="foot"><HI>Adam Glover,</HI> Com. Cav. Ia. 4 ex 57.</NOTE>.</P>
<P>How have our sacred Books of holy Scriptures been used? Gods Book hath been, O horrible! cast into, and tumbled in the Kennell; thence taken up, and dashed in the faces of some Profes∣sors, with these words, I know you love a good lesson, this is an excellent one; come to morrow, you shall have as good <NOTE N="H" PLACE="foot">Adam Glover.</NOTE>.</P>
<P>They have torn it in pieces <NOTE N="I" PLACE="foot"><HI>Eliz. Taylor,</HI> Com. Fer. Ian. 8. ex. 58.</NOTE>, kicked it up and down <NOTE N="K" PLACE="foot">Io. Mountgomery.</NOTE>, treading it under foot, with leaping thereon, they causing a Bag∣pipe to play the while <NOTE N="L" PLACE="foot"><HI>Hen Palmer,</HI> Com. Wex, Ia. 12.</NOTE>; laying also the leaves in the kennell, leaping and trampling thereupon, saying, A plague on it, This Book hath bred alltne quarrell, hoping within three weeks all the Bibles in <HI>Ireland</HI> should be so used, or worse, and that none should be left in the Kingdom <NOTE N="M" PLACE="foot"><HI>Edw Slack,</HI> Com. Fer. Ia. 4. <HI>ex.</HI> 59.</NOTE>: and while two Bibles were in burn∣ing, saying that it was hell-fire that was burning <NOTE N="N" PLACE="foot"><HI>Edward Dean,</HI> Com. Wickloe, Ia. 7. <HI>ex</HI> 60. <HI>Roger Holland, ex.</HI> 77.</NOTE>; wishing they had all the Bibles of Christendome, that they might use them so.</P>
<P>But what Pen can set forth, what Tongue expresse, whose Eye can reade, Ear hear, or heart, without melting, consider the cruel∣ties, more than barbarous, dayly exercised upon us by those inhu∣mane, blood-sucking Tygers!</P>
<P>Stripping quite naked Men, Women, and children, even chil∣dren, sucking upon the Brest <NOTE N="O" PLACE="foot">Io. Greg.</NOTE>, whereby multitudes of all sorts in the extremitie of that cold season of Frost and Snow have
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
perished. Women being dragged up and down naked, <NOTE N="P" PLACE="foot"><HI>Katherine Bellew,</HI> Com. Mona. <HI>Feb.</HI> 5. <HI>ex</HI> 61</NOTE> Wo∣men in child bed thence drawn out, and cast into prison. <NOTE N="Q" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Wisedome, Com.</HI> Arm. <HI>Feb.</HI> 8. <HI>ex.</HI> 62 <HI>Roger Holland ex.</HI> 77.</NOTE> One delivered of a childe while she was hanging. <NOTE N="R" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Wisedome. <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Tayl<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, Com.</HI> Arm. <HI>Feb.</HI> 8 <HI>ex,</HI> 63</NOTE> One ripped up, and two children taken away, and all cast unto, and eaten by swine. <NOTE N="S" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io Mandevile, Com.</HI> Dublin, <HI>Feb.</HI> 3 <HI>ex</HI> 64</NOTE> One other stabbed in the breast her childe sucking. <NOTE N="T" PLACE="foot"><HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g Stocks, Com.</HI> Fer <HI>examined by directions from the Councell Bo<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd, ex</HI> 65</NOTE> An Infant cruelly murthered, whom they found sucking his dead mother slain by them the day before. <NOTE N="V" PLACE="foot"><HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ynold Gri<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fith, Co.</HI> Arma. <HI>ex.</HI> 74</NOTE> A childe of 14 years of age taken from his mother, in her sight cast into a Bog-pit, and held under water while he was drown'd. <HI>(W)</HI> The forcing 40 or 50 Protestants to renounce their profession, and then cutting all their throats. <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Alex. Creig<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hton.</NOTE></P>
<P>What should we speak of their murthers, <NOTE N="X" PLACE="foot"><HI>Ad. Glover, Ro. Barton,</HI> with infinite others.</NOTE> their hanging, half-hanging, and that oft times reiterated; they delighting in the tortures of the miserable. <NOTE N="Z" PLACE="foot"><HI>Io. Gregg. Alexander Creig<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hton, ex</HI> 76. <HI>Richard Skinner, Co. K<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ore, Feb</HI> 8.</NOTE> Hence some being left wounded, in vain crying out that they might be dispatched. <NOTE N="A" PLACE="foot">Iohn Gregg</NOTE> This being purposely done, that these wretches might languish in their mise∣rie; their tormentors affirming that their Priests commanded them so to do. <NOTE N="B" PLACE="foot">Nath. Hi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>genson.</NOTE> What should we speake of those 30 or 40 burnt in one House, and 50 in another. <NOTE N="C" PLACE="foot">Thomas Crant</NOTE> the denying of bu∣riall to the dead, <NOTE N="D" PLACE="foot">Adam Glover. Io. Mountgomery</NOTE> whereby Christians have been eaten by Dogs, and Dogs tearing Children out of the wombe; the bloudy beholders relating such things with boasting and great rejoycing: <NOTE N="E" PLACE="foot">Thomas Crant Marga. Stocks</NOTE> And to make perfect the measure of their cruelty, Two were said to be buried alive, <NOTE N="F" PLACE="foot"><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Mountgomery. Mary Woods, Com. Ki<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dare, Feb.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>3 <HI>ex</HI> 66.</NOTE> and others that had been long buried, digged up; they saying that the Churches could not be Conse∣crated, while Hereticks bodies or bones lay therein. <NOTE N="G" PLACE="foot"><HI>Thomas <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> Kildare, <HI>Feb</HI> 15. <HI>ex.</HI> 67. <HI>Mary Woods. Reb. Collis, Co.</HI> Kild. <HI>Feb.</HI> 23. <HI>ex.</HI> 68.</NOTE></P>
<P>The cruell usage of those 48 poore prisoners in the Gaole of <HI>Monaghan.</HI> <NOTE N="H" PLACE="foot"><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tile. Hugh Culme.</NOTE> Of those in the County of <HI>Armagh,</HI> after drow∣ned 
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
in the River of the <HI>Ban,</HI> to the number of 80, <NOTE N="I" PLACE="foot">Io Mountgomry.</NOTE> or 100. <NOTE N="K" PLACE="foot">W. Clerk.</NOTE> or 196, <NOTE N="L" PLACE="foot">Mr <HI>Philip Tayler</HI></NOTE> as it is diversly reported, those 45 drowned toge∣ther. <NOTE N="M" PLACE="foot">Io. Mountgomry.</NOTE> And those 179 burnt in one house. <NOTE N="x" PLACE="foot"><HI>Cha. Camp∣bell, ex.</HI> 75.</NOTE> All these we refer to the reading of the severall depositions concerning them hereunto annexed.</P>
<P>But how can that be forgotten, or where shall it be beleeved, which we hear to have been done in the Church of <HI>Newtown</HI> in the County of <HI>Fermanagh;</HI> where a childe of <HI>Thomas Strettons</HI> was boyled alive in a Caldron: A thing which as one bare reports we durst not, so neither can we now with confidence enough present it to that your honourable Assembly, nor can we averre it for true, otherwise then as by concurring examinations we finde them so∣lemnly deposed, whereunto we desire to be referred. <NOTE N="N" PLACE="foot"><HI>Marga. Parker</HI> of <HI>Newtown, Com.</HI> Fer. <HI>Ian.</HI> 19. <HI>ex.</HI> 69. <HI>Elizabeth Bursses</HI> of the same. <HI>ex.</HI> 70.</NOTE> To which may well be added, the forcing of one <HI>Duke Wade</HI> to drinke unto drunkennesse, and then hanging him therein, to take a full revenge both on body and soul. (p)</P>
<P>Of which their aforesaid many and barbarous cruelties, each day doth afford us variety of new instances. This City of <HI>Dublin</HI> being the common receptacle for these miserable sufferers. Here are many thousands of poore people, sometimes of good respects and estates, now in want and sicknesse, whereof many daily dye, notwithstanding the great care of those tender hearted Christians (whom God blesse) without whom all of them had before now perished.</P>
<P>In all which, as our sufferings are generall, the hatred of the enemy being expressed to the whole Nation, and to all the profes∣sors of the truth. So in chief and above all others <NOTE N="O" PLACE="foot"><HI>Alex. Creighton. ex.</HI> 76. <HI>Geo. Cottingham, ex.</HI> 78.</NOTE> do we finde it with the deadliest venome spit against the persons of us the Mini∣sters of the Gospel, towards whom their rage is without bounds.</P>
<P>Of this we see enough in the miserable condition of M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>George Cottingham,</HI> a Batchelor in Divinity, and a painfull labourer in the Lords Vineyard. <NOTE N="P" PLACE="foot"><HI>Henry Boyne, Com.</HI> Tiron, <HI>Feb.</HI> 16. <HI>ex.</HI> 71.</NOTE> The like we see in the cruell murther of M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Blyth,</HI> slain with sir <HI>Pheliom ô Neals</HI> safe conduct in his hands, <NOTE N="Q" PLACE="foot">Hugh Culme. Henry Stile.</NOTE>
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
it being lift up by him unto heaven, as a witnesse of his treachery. <NOTE N="Q" PLACE="foot">Io. Cardiff.</NOTE> The same we finde in the murther of M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Thomas Grafford,</HI> and M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>William Fullerton.</HI> <NOTE N="R" PLACE="foot"><HI>Eliz. Trafford, com.</HI> Long f. <HI>Ian.</HI> 8. <HI>ex.</HI> 72. <HI>William Cleark.</HI></NOTE> Lastly, that among a multitude, we may content our selves with a few; We see it in the cruelty exer∣cised upon M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Sharpe</HI> the Minister of <HI>Kells.</HI> <NOTE N="S" PLACE="foot"><HI>Geo. Cooke. Margery Sharpe, com.</HI> Meath, <HI>Ian.</HI> 29. <HI>ex.</HI> 73.</NOTE> Of all which, the following examinations shall speak morefully.</P>
<P>Such of us as have best escaped the hands of these Tyrants have been turned out of all. We, with such other of our brethren, ours and their wives and children coming on foot hither, through waies tedious and full of perill, being every minute assaulted, the end of one but leading to the next danger, one quite stripping off, what others had in pity left. So that in nakednesse we have recovered this our City of refuge, where we live in all extremity of want, not having wherewithall to subsist, or to put bread in our mouthes.</P>
<P>Of those of our brethren who have perished on the way hither, some of their wives and children do yet remain. The children also of some of them, wholly deprived of their parents, and left for des∣serted Orphans. All of us being exposed to apparent ruine, if not speedily relieved.</P>
<P>This <HI>our most miserable condition therefore, and of our</HI> Brethren, <HI>and of this our whole distressed</HI> Church of Ireland, <HI>We do in most hum∣ble manner Remonstrate and lay downe at the feet of that your</HI> Pious, Charitable, and Honorable Assembly.</P>
<P>Praying, <HI>That we and all of us your Suppliants, together with our</HI> Brethren, <HI>may finde a place among others in your tender considerations, and never exhausted bounty. So, and in such manner as to your</HI> Wise∣domes <HI>shall be esteemed most fitting.</HI></P>
<P>Humbly <HI>desiring that we who have borne the</HI> burthen and heate of the day, <HI>may not be cast off, not having what to</HI> eate, or what to put on.</P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="10"/>
That <HI>the</HI> Ministry <HI>may not in our wants be rendred despicable to our own, as it hath suffered despight from our</HI> Adversaries.</P>
<P>And <HI>that the rather we may finde this</HI> Admittance <HI>into your</HI> Cha∣rity, <HI>in that our sufferings are professed by our enemies to proceed (which we glory in) from that your</HI> zeal <HI>for the Church of</HI> God.</P>
<P>God Almighty <HI>blesse and further those your Honorable and pious de∣sires and designs, and</HI> Restrai<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>the fury of our Adversaries, for which we desire the prayers of our Brethren. And He grant, that of his goodnesse all of them may be long preserved from knowing what we suffer, other∣wise then by a</HI> Brotherly and compassionate fellow feeling.<LB/>
which are the daily prayers of</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Your Honors Servants</HI><LB/>
and <HI>Votaries,</HI><LB/>
Henry Iones. Roger Puttocke.<LB/>
Iohn Watson. Iohn Sterne.<LB/>
Henry Brereton. Randall Adams.<LB/>
William Hitchcoke. William Aldrich.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="statements">
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>The severall Commissions where∣upon the following examinations are grounded; out of which the foregoing Remonstrance hath been extracted.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="statement">
<P>CHARLES By the grace of God, King of <HI>England, Scotland, France,</HI> and <HI>Ireland,</HI> Defendes of the Faith, &amp;c. <HI>To Our</HI> welbeloved <HI>Henry Jones,</HI> Dean of <HI>Kilmore, Roger Puttock, William Hitchcock, Randall Adams, John Sterne, William Aldrich, Henry Brereton,</HI> and <HI>John Watson</HI> Clerks, greeting. <HI>Whereas</HI> divers wicked and disloyall people have lately risen in Arms in severall parts of this Kingdome, and have Rob∣bed and spoiled many of our good Subjects, Brittish, and Pro∣testants, who have been seperated from their setled habitations, and scattered in most lamentable manner. And forasmuch as it is needfull to take due examination concerning the same. <HI>Know</HI> ye, that We reposing especiall trust and confidence in your care, diligence, and provident circumspection, have nominated and appointed you to be Our Commissioners; And do hereby give unto you, or any two or more of you, full power and Au∣thoritie from time to time to call before you, and examine upon oath on the holy Evangelists (which hereby we authorize you, or any two or more of you, to administer) as well all such persons as have been so robbed and spoiled, as all the witnesses that can give testimony therein, what robberies and spoiles have beene committed on them, or any other to their knowledge, since the two and twentieth of <HI>October</HI> last, or shall hereafter be com∣mitted on them, or any of them, what the particulars were, or are, whereof they were or shall be so robbed or spoiled; to
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
what valew, by whom, what their names are, and where they now, or last dwelt that committed those robberies, or what day or night the said robberies or spoiles committed, or to be com∣mitted, were done; what traiterous or disloyall words, speeches, or actions were then, or at any other time uttered or committed by those Robbers, or any of them, what violence or other lewd actions were then performed by the sayd Robbers, or any of them, and how often: and all other circumstances touching or con∣cerning the said particulars, and euery of them. And you Our sayd Commissioners are to reduce to writing, all the examina∣tions, which you, or any two or more of you shall take as afore∣said: and the same to return unto Our Iustices, and Councell of this our Realm of <HI>Ireland,</HI> under the hands and seales of you, or any two or more of you as aforesaid. <HI>Witnesse</HI> Our Right trusty and wel-beloved Councellors, Sir <HI>William Par∣sons</HI> Knight and Baronet, and Sir <HI>John Borlase</HI> Knight, Our Iustices of Our said Realm of <HI>Ireland.</HI> At <HI>Dublin</HI> the three and twentieth day of <HI>December,</HI> in the seventeenth of our Reigne.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Carleton.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="statement">
<P>CHARLES By the grace of God, King of <HI>Eng∣land, Scotland, France,</HI> and <HI>Ireland,</HI> Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. <HI>To</HI> Our Wel-beloved, <HI>Henry Jones</HI> Dean of <HI>Kilmore, Roger Puttock, Wil∣liam Hitchcock, Randall Adams, John Sterne; Wil∣liam Aldrich, Henry Brereton,</HI> and <HI>John Watson</HI> Clerks, Greeting. <HI>Whereas</HI> divers wicked and disloyall people, have lately risen in Arms in severall parts in this King∣dome, and have robbed and spoiled many of Our good Subjects, Brittish, and Protestants; who have been seperated from their setled habitations, and scattered in most lamentable manner;
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
and many others have beene deprived of their Lands, Rents, goods, and Chattles. And forasmuch as it is needfull to take due examination concerning the same. <HI>Know</HI> ye, that We reposing especiall trust and confidence in your fidelities, care, and provident circumspection, have nominated and appointed you to be Our Commissioners; and do hereby give unto you, or any two or more of you, full power and authority, from time to time, to call before you and examine upon oath (which We here∣by authorise you, or any two or more of you, to administer on the holy Evangelists) As well all such persons as have been so Robbed and spoiled, or deprived of their Lands, Rents, goods, or Chattles, as all the witnesses that can give testimony therein, what Robberies and spoiles have been committed on them, or any other to their knowledge, since the two and twentieth of <HI>October</HI> last, or shall hereafter be committed on them, or any of them; what Lands, Rents, goods, or Chattles, whereof any person, or persons were or shall be so robbed, spoiled, or deprived; to what valew, by whom such robberies or spoiles were committed, what their names are, and where they now, or last dwelt that committted those robberies, or spoiles, on what day or night the said robberies or spoiles committed, or to be committed were done; what Traiterous or disloyall words, speeches, or actions were then, or at any other time uttered or committed by those robbers, or any of them; and what unfitting words or speeches concerning the present Rebellion, or by occasion thereof were spoken at any time, by any person or persons whatsoever; what violence or other lewd actions were then performed by the said Robbers, or any of them, and how often, what numbers of per∣sons have been murthered by the Rebels, or perished after∣wards in the way to <HI>Dublin,</HI> or other places whither they sled or retired for refuge, either by way of defence, or other∣wise. What person, or persons, Clergimen, or other Prote∣stants have become Papists since the said two and twentieth day
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
fled or retired for refuge, either by way of defence, or other∣wise. What person, or persons, Clergimen, or other Prote∣stants have become Papists since the said two and twentieth day of <HI>October</HI> last, and all other circumstances and things touching, or concerning the said particulars, and every of them, either before the three and twentieth of <HI>October,</HI> or since. And for the better performance of this service, all Incumbents, Curats, Parish-Clerks, and Sextons of Churches in this Kingdome, are hereby required to give in to you Our said Commissioners, to the best of their knowledge, the names and numbers of the poore so spoyled, who have beene buried in their respective Parishes, and hereafter in and about <HI>Dublin,</HI> they are to give in weekly Bills under the hands of the Ministers, or Church-wardens of such Parishes, of such of the said persons as shall be so buried in the said Parishes. And you our said Commissioners, or any two or more of you, as aforesaid; are to reduce to writing all the Examinations which you, or any two or more of you shall take as aforesaid, and the same to return to our Iustices, and Councell of this Our Realm of <HI>Ireland,</HI> under the hands and Seals of you, or any two or more of you, as aforesaid. <HI>Witnesse</HI> Our right trusty and wel-beloved Councellors, Sir <HI>William</HI> Parsons Knight and Baronet, and Sir <HI>John Borlase</HI> Knight, Our Iustices of Our Realme of <HI>Ireland.</HI> At <HI>Dublin,</HI> the eigh∣teenth Day of <HI>January,</HI> in the Seventeenth yeare of Our Reigne.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Carleton.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="examinations">
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
<HEAD>Examinations taken before us His <HI>Majesties Commissioners thereunto appointed, by vertue of a Commission to us, or any two or more of us, directed under the great Seal of</HI> Ireland: <HI>Dated the</HI> 23<SUP>th</SUP> <HI>day of</HI> December, <HI>in the</HI> 17<SUP>th</SUP> <HI>yeare of his Majesties Reigne. And by vertue of one other Commission directed as aforesaid, bea∣ring Date the</HI> 18<SUP>th</SUP> <HI>day of</HI> January, <HI>in the yeare aforesaid.</HI></HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> John Day <HI>of</HI> Drumleiff <HI>in the County of</HI> Cavan, <HI>Weaver.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That the Rebells bad him open the doors of his House, otherwise they would fire his House; and they said that they had a Commission from the Queene, and from beyond the Seas for what they did, And that they would not suffer an English-man to stay in the land.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE><HI>Jur.</HI> 8. <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Day.</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Aldrich.</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Lucy Spell <HI>of</HI> Drogheda <HI>in the County of</HI> Lowth.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duly sworn deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That at <HI>Bal∣lendary</HI> where she was prisoner three weeks, and lodged in <HI>John Parsimers</HI> house; during which imprisonment, she saw one time <HI>John Malon</HI> a Fryar; who taketh upon him the title of Chaplain to the Catholike Army in <HI>Ireland;</HI> together with <HI>Mi∣chael Murffy, Garret Newgent</HI> of <HI>Drogheda</HI> Marchant, <HI>John Griffin,</HI> and <HI>Patrick Griffin</HI> of the same, Merchants, <HI>Roger Belin</HI> of the same, Merchant, with others in their company; and heard them in their conference say, we will shortly have the Prince of <HI>England</HI> here
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
in <HI>Ireland,</HI> and make him Vice-Roy, and we will tutor him, and bring him up in the Catholike Religion, and the King himselfe shall live in <HI>Scotland;</HI> and before <HI>Easter</HI> day next, we shall have an Army out of <HI>Spain,</HI> and then we will go all into <HI>England,</HI> and with the helpe of the Catholikes there (all whose names the said Fryar said that he had). we will put all the Puritans and Prote∣stants to the sword.</P>
<P><HI>The marke—of the said</HI> Lucy.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE><HI>Jur.</HI> 5. <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>William Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> John Biggar <HI>of</HI> Miltown <HI>in the County of</HI> Dub∣lin, <HI>Clerke.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate being duely sworn deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That these words were spoken by the Rebells, especially by <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 3.</NOTE> their Leader. (For the third of <HI>December) Edmond Eustace</HI> of <HI>Bal∣lymore-Eustace,</HI> that they did give us but our owne Law. For whereas there was an Act made by the Councell of <HI>England,</HI> in the abs<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce, and without the consent or knowledge of the King, for the expelling, banishing, and putting away the Papists out of England, and seizing of their goods; which when they had there effected, would have brought the like over hither, for extirpation of the Irish Nation that are Papists. These considerations for the defence of the Religion, the Queens person, and by the Kings license, moved them to take Arms, having the <HI>Scots</HI> for a presi∣dent; they have also vowed not to leave an English-man in <HI>Ire∣land.</HI> The Kingdome they will have in their own hands, Lawes of their own, and a Deputy of their own, without molestation or interruption of any other Nation.</P>
<P>This night, at the Widdowes house of one <HI>Lawrence Purcell,</HI> I met with one <HI>George Staples,</HI> who for late years had taught the Children of the chiefe of the Gentry in our parts. Having beene formerly acquainted with him, he began to examine me what course I intended to take, I told him I could not tell, untill I came to <HI>Dublin,</HI> and therefore I desired to have his counsell and advise.
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
He began after this manner. You intend to go to <HI>ublin</HI> saith he, if you do, you must go speedily; for within two dayes the <HI>Irish</HI> Army will be before <HI>Dublin,</HI> so that you cannot passe; if you should get so much favour as to passe, yet when you come to <HI>Dub∣lin,</HI> you will not be admitted to come within the Gates; and in the Suburbs there are sixe or seven score dying daily for want of food, so that there will be no abiding place for you, If you in∣tend to go for <HI>England,</HI> the least childe you have will not be car∣ried under twenty shillings, and you (saith he) have not one pen∣ny; if you should finde so much friendship as to passe <HI>gratis,</HI> there are such a multitude of people that are gone out of this Kingdom, that <HI>England</HI> being but a small Island, and Populous of it selfe, is not able to receive you; if you should be received, there can be no long continuing place for you, for the Papists are striving in <HI>Eng∣land</HI> as well as here; the Queene being fled into <HI>France</HI> for some abuses offered her own Person, her Servants and Chaplains, which indignities the King of <HI>France</HI> intending to revenge, hath leavied an Army of 40000 men to invade <HI>England,</HI> and the Cardinall in <HI>Flanders</HI> hath leavied the like number, to the like end and purpose, therefore it will be no purpose to go thither. Lord, M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Staples</HI> (said I) what shall I do then? If you stay here, you must do as they do, and turn to Masse; yet they will not trust you (sayd he) fearing least if the King of <HI>England</HI> should ever be able to bring an Army into this Country, the turn-coat English should joyne with them, and cut the Irish throats in a night, as the English once did the <HI>Danes</HI> in <HI>England.</HI> Therefore whosoever of the English should turn to the Romish Church, they would also compell to take Armes and place them in the Front, and eminent place of danger, that so they might fall. And for hereafter, when they had gotten the Kingdome into their own hands, which they make no question but to have in a short time (having all the Forts, Castles, and strong-holds in <HI>Ireland</HI> in their own hands already, but the Castle of <HI>Dublin,</HI> and <HI>Drogheda;</HI> and these two places they would not for many thousand pounds have gotten, for reasons known un∣to themselves) but when they have once obtained them, and the Kingdome; those English that have not fallen by the sword, the ho∣ly Church hath so ordered it, that they shall be cut off by the In∣quisition, so that they will not leave an English-man alive, whose
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
Ancestors hav<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not been here for 200 years, with many other like words.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE><HI>Jur.</HI> 29. <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Biggar.</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> John Mountgomery, <HI>late of</HI> Clounish <HI>in the County of</HI> Monaghan, <HI>Gent.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn,e deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That in their journey, and Marching within the County of <HI>Monag∣han,</HI> the Rebells murthered of his knowledge, at the least foure∣score Protestants, and committed a number of other wicked bar∣barous and notorious Robberies and actions, and by their owne relation, robb'd, stripped naked, kill'd and drowned 45 of the <HI>Scots</HI> at one time; and that the same Robbers also murthered Mr <HI>Blyth,</HI> and Master <HI>Mathew</HI> (two constant Protestant Preachers within the County of <HI>Tiron)</HI> and murthered one Master <HI>Fullerton,</HI> Parson of <HI>Loughall</HI> in the County of <HI>Armagh;</HI> and neere foure∣score more English more of Protestants, by drowning, and throw∣ing them all over the Bridge of <HI>Portdown</HI> in the said County, into the River <HI>Bann.</HI></P>
<P>And further saith, that the Rebells aforesaid, or some of them confessed unto him, and so he was told also by divers Scottish-men, that they the same Rebells when they came to <HI>Armagh, Monaghan,</HI> and <HI>Dungannon,</HI> set all the prisoners at liberty, and that they broke open and defaced the Church of <HI>Armagh,</HI> and burned the pewes, pulpit, and the best things in the said Church.</P>
<P>And this Deponent whilest he was with the same Rebells, saw them to pull in peeces, kick up and down, deface and spoyl all the Protestant Bibles, and other protestant books that they found in any place where they came; neither this Deponent, nor any other protestant prisoner nor other, durst so much do as to save, or looke upon any of them in their sight; nor would they willingly suf∣fer any one to speak the English tongue.</P>
<P>And further, it was pretended that it was agreed in the Parlia∣ment House of <HI>England,</HI> thet the Nobility and Gentry of <HI>Ireland,</HI> should be sent for to <HI>Dublin,</HI> unde, colour of passing Patents of their Lands; and there should be imprisoned, untill such time as they should either go to the Protestant Church, or should be put
<PB N="21" REF="14"/>
to death: And if they should go to the Church, yet not to be re∣leased untill they had given security that their followers should go to the Church also; otherwise, to bring them in to be censured.</P>
<P>And further saith, That when the Rebells of the County of <HI>Monaghan</HI> had surprized, or had command of all that County, some of them said that they would be governed by the <HI>Roman</HI> Law, and some by the <HI>English</HI> Law, which they knew better. And said fur∣ther, That when they had taken <HI>Dublin</HI> and <HI>Drogheda, Derry</HI> and <HI>Knockfergus,</HI> which they did not doubt but to conquer before <HI>Candlemas</HI> then next, they would have a Parliament, and would settle a Government, but would have no Protestants amongst them; but that they would suffer English or Scottish to be Depu∣ties, Lords Justices, or Judges, so that one of the Irish Nation might be joyned with them, and so that all should go to Masse.</P>
<P>And the same Rebells publikely and generally also said, That they made no account but to keep <HI>Ireland</HI> for ever, in regard they had of their own Souldiers two hundred thousand fighting men, besides labourers; and they expected from the King of <HI>Spain,</HI> ac∣cording to his promise fifteen thousand souldiers, and Arms and money fit for them: and from the King of <HI>France,</HI> some Ayd, be∣cause the Queen of <HI>England,</HI> his sister, was so deprived of liberty of religion.</P>
<P>And the same Rebells also further said, in this Deponents hear∣ing, That in all forraigne parts it was agreed and resolved that all Protestants or others that would not go to Masse, should be put to the Sword.</P>
<P>And this Deponent further saith, That he did hear <HI>Neale mac Kenny,</HI> Baron of <HI>Trough,</HI> neer <HI>Glaslock,</HI> a notorious Captain of the Rebells, say, That the King had sent directions from <HI>Scotland,</HI> that Sir <HI>Pbelomy Roe ô Neale,</HI> Knight, should be Generall of all His Majesties Forces in <HI>Ireland,</HI> against the English; and that he the said <HI>Neale mac Kenny</HI> should be Governour of the three Counties of <HI>Tyrone, Armagh,</HI> and <HI>Monaghan;</HI> And that therefore he the said <HI>Neale mac Kenny,</HI> and the rest of the Irish Forces would, after their conquest of <HI>Ireland,</HI> go into <HI>England,</HI> and there, by the assistance of the English papists, also conquer the same; And that from thence they would go into <HI>Scotland,</HI> and by the like assistance subdue that Kingdom, and settle their religion in all places.</P>
<P><PB N="22" REF="15"/>
And further saith, That he, this Deponent was in the County of <HI>Armagh</HI> credibly informed by some cots, and the same was con∣fessed and confirmed to be true by some of the Irish, That one <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Keoon,</HI> neer <HI>Cregance,</HI> in the said County, and his Souldiers, did take a Scottish-man, and a woman, and tortured them, by hanging them up in a Rope to confesse their moneys; but still before they were dead, let them down again.</P>
<P>And saith further; That o<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <HI>Bryan mac Erowny,</HI> a Ring-leader of Rebells in the County of <HI>Fermanagh,</HI> and his souldiers, killed one <HI>Ensigne Lloyd,</HI> and <HI>Robert Workman,</HI> both of the same County, Gentlemen, and four of their servants; one of which they having wounded, but not to death, they buried quick. And this Depo∣nent was credibly informed, That the daughter in law of one <HI>Ford,</HI> in the Parish of <HI>Clonnish,</HI> and County of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> being delivered of a childe in the Hills; the Rebells, who had formerly killed her husband and his father, killed her also, and two of her children, and suffered their dogs to eat up and devour her said new born childe, which they found with her in that place. And saith further, That <HI>Cole, mac Bryan, mac Mabon</HI> the Colonell and his souldiers did kill and murther at <HI>Mellifant,</HI> at the Lord <HI>Moores</HI> house, 18 of the said Lord <HI>Moors</HI> servants, and would not suffer the greater part of them to be buried, but to lie upon the ground, and be devoured by Dogs, Crows, and revenous Creatures. And this Deponent had, and hath seen and observed the like to be done by the Rebells since this Rebellion began, within the County of <HI>Mo∣naghan,</HI> to divers other Protestants that they had murthered.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE><HI>Jur.</HI> 26 <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>John Mountgomery.</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Iohn Sterne,</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>William Hitchcocke,</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Roger Puttocke,</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>VVilliam Aldrich,</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Hen. Brereton.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Patrick ô Bryan, <HI>of the Parish of Galoon, in the County of</HI> Fermanagh.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That <HI>Do∣nagh, mac Guye,</HI> of the County aforesaid, said, That it was <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 5.</NOTE> against his will that this was begun; but seeing he had put to his hand, he would not give out; for if I should come in, I should be used like <HI>Tyron,</HI> who was persecuted, notwithstanding his many pardons. <HI>Con oge mac con mac Hugh, mac Mabon,</HI> of <HI>Aghneholagh,</HI>
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>
and County of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> said, That the King knew of this Re∣bellion, and that it was as hot in <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Scotland</HI> as here, at the same time. And he further said, That all the Nobles of this Kingdom which were papists, had a hand in this plot, as well as my Lord <HI>Maguire,</HI> and <HI>Hugh oge mac Mahon,</HI> and that they expected Ayd out of <HI>Spain,</HI> by one <HI>Owen Roe ô Neal, viz.</HI> 10000 men, and Arms for as many. <HI>Item,</HI> the said Deponent further saith, That he heard Colonell <HI>Plunckett</HI> say; That he knew of this plot eight yeers ago: but within these three yeers he hath been more fully ac∣quainted with it: the cause of this Deponents knowledge is, that he was sent with a Letter unto the said Colonell <HI>Plunckett,</HI> from Mr. <HI>Nicholas VVilloughby,</HI> and heard the same from the said <HI>Plunckett</HI> as aforesaid.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Patrick ô Bryan.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ion.</HI> 29. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Henry Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Sierne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="deposition">
<HEAD><HI>The Deposition of</HI> Henry Jones, <HI>Doctor in Divinity, and Dean of</HI> Kilmore.</HEAD>
<P>I <HI>Henry Iones,</HI> Doctor in Divinity, in obedience to His Majesties <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 6.</NOTE> Commission; requiring an Accompt of the losses of His loyall subjects, wherein they suffered by the present Rebellion in <HI>Ireland:</HI> Requiring also a declaration of what trayterous words, projects, or actions were done, said, or plotted by the actors or abettors in that Rebellion; Do make, and give in this following report of the premisses, to the best of my knowledge. As for the present Rebellion, howsoever the first breaking out of this fire into a flame, began first on the 28 of <HI>Octob.</HI> 1641, yet was it smoking, as may well be conjectured for many yeers before; God having given us many and apparant grounds for the discovery of it, had they been duely considered, or fully prosecuted to a discovery, of which kinde we finde these following four particulars:</P>
<P N="1">1. The first, That about three or four yeers since, amongst ma∣ny Books brought into <HI>Limrick</HI> from forraign parts and seized upon by the Reverend Bishop of that Sea, as prohibited, being thereunto authoriz<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d by the State, One had a written addition to the first part, which was printed, the Manuscript containing a dis∣course of the Friars of the <HI>Augustine</HI> Order, sometimes seated in the Town of <HI>Armagh,</HI> in <HI>Ʋlster,</HI> But by reason of the times, and
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
that Present resident (as that writing imported) in the City of <HI>Limrick</HI> in <HI>Munster,</HI> That while it flourished at <HI>Armagh,</HI> it was protected, and largely provided for by the then Earl of <HI>Tyrone:</HI> Since whose expulsion out of <HI>Ireland,</HI> that Convent was also de∣cayed, and driven to those distresses it did for the present undergo; but that within three yeers (this is, as I remember, the time limit∣ed) <HI>Ireland</HI> should finde, that he had a sonne inheriting his fathers vertues, who should restore that Kingdom to its former Liberty, and that Convent to its first lustre, or words to that effect. This was related unto me by that zealous and learned Prelate Doctor <HI>VVebb,</HI> now Bishop of <HI>Limrick,</HI> who saw and read the said pas∣sage; purposing as his Lordship told me, to send that book to the Lord President of <HI>Munster,</HI> to be taken into further consideration.</P>
<P N="2">2 Hereunto was added a second passage, about the same time at <HI>Limrick</HI> aforesaid; where a Popish Priest gave out, that within three years there should not be a Protestant in <HI>Ireland,</HI> or words to that purpose, with some other materiall circumstances which I do not now remember; yet all so concurring with the former, or the first with this (for which preceded I know not, Both being about one time) that it was thought fitting to be considered of, the sayd Priest being sent unto the Lords at <HI>Dublin,</HI> and he com∣mitted to the Castle.</P>
<P N="3">3 The third, did agree with the two former, and fell out about the same time in the County of <HI>VVestmeath,</HI> in the Province of <HI>Limster;</HI> where <HI>VValter Newgent</HI> of <HI>Rathaspeck</HI> in the said County, eldest Son to <HI>VValter Newgent</HI> Esquier (a man of great fortunes) upbraiding an Irish Protestant, who was the Parish Clerk of <HI>Ra∣thaspeck</HI> aforesaid, with his Religion; and both speaking Latine, the said <HI>Newgent</HI> uttered these words; <HI>Infratres annos venient tem∣pus, &amp; potentia in Hibernia, quandò tu longè</HI> (likely meaning <HI>diu.) pendebis in cruce propter diabolicam vestram Religionem.</HI> (The party to which this was spoken feared the power of the man) durst not speak of it, only in private. Yet being called upon and exami∣ned juridically, upon oath he deposed these words. And being demanded whether the words were in <HI>Hiberniam,</HI> or <HI>Hibernia;</HI> the first importing an Invasion, the other, an Insurrection at home: He deposed the latter, having time given him to consider of it. These Examinates were sent to Sir <HI>George Radcliffe; Newgent</HI> was
<PB N="29" REF="16"/>
sent for, and committed to the Castle of <HI>Dublin,</HI> and remained in long durance, but after was dismissed.</P>
<P N="4">4. Hereunto was added a fourth, about the same time near the <HI>Naas,</HI> about 12 miles from <HI>Dublin,</HI> where a popish Priest newly arrived out of <HI>Flanders,</HI> did make his addresse to the then Lord Deputy, and informed his Lordship of an intercourse of Letters between the Earl of <HI>Tirone,</HI> with others in <HI>Flanders,</HI> and the po∣pish Primate of <HI>Armagh, Rely;</HI> concerning an Invasion within a short time intended upon <HI>Ireland;</HI> the said Priest offering (so his person might be secured) to direct such as should be thereunto appointed to the place, where the said Letters were in the custo∣die of the said <HI>Rely: Rely</HI> was thereupon sent for, together with the popish Vicar generall of <HI>Armagh,</HI> as I remember it; both were committed to the said Castle of <HI>Dublin,</HI> but soon after released, and the Informer dismissed, with x. l. and a suit of clothes, or some such reward.</P>
<P N="5">5. Hereunto may this be further added another, not so plain as the former; That about the same time the Lord Baron of <HI>Dun∣sany</HI> did ride disguised throughout all the parts of <HI>Mounster,</HI> pre∣tending to satisfie his curiosity in the knowledge of places and persons: He not being discovered untill his return at the Birr, where having offerd himself to be bound for one in his company, he writ himself in his own stile; being loth to leave under his hand a testimony of his disguised person, and assumed name.</P>
<P>Hereunto may be added, a motion made by the Recusant party in the Parliament of <HI>Ireland,</HI> for hindring the sending away of certain Colonels with their forces raised in the Kingdom, and pretended to be for service in foreign parts, many wondring it should proceed from them; but therein, considering these their former practises, their intentions may be discovered to be far dif∣ferent from what others conceived thereof, who assented there∣unto: The imploying of so many thousands abroad, being a great weakning of the forces they purposed for this their soon after following Rebellion.</P>
<P>To descend now from the antecedents of this treason, to the falling in thereupon; and lastly, to the consequents, &amp; what ther∣by hath been intended, supposing it to succeed, and that it attained the desired effect, which by them was not doubted of. And first,
<PB N="26" REF="17"/>
for the entrance thereinto: Howsoever that the ground-work were long since laid, yet would they not have it so to seeme: But new occasion must be found, as the sole cause of their breaking out, this being intended for the satisfying the mindes of such of their own, as have not hitherto bin acquainted with the depth &amp; mystery of this Iniquity, that they might not stand amazed at the suddennesse of the undertaking, or stand off from joyning with them, the worst part of their designes, it being an apparent Rebel∣lion. The fittest means for this, must have bin by casting aspersions on the present Governmēt, which if long tolerated, would prove extremely dangerous, not onely to their Religion, but their lives and posterity. For effecting hereof, reports were cast out, that in the Parliament of <HI>England,</HI> the cutting off of all the Papists in <HI>Ire∣land,</HI> of what degree soever, was concluded upon, the execution of that Resolution being committed to the Counsell in <HI>Ireland;</HI> The Lords (said they) had laid down a day for this work, being the 23 of <HI>Nov.</HI> then next following, and now last past, or thereabouts. For the better, more secure, and more secret managing of this pretended plot, such of the popish Nobility and Gentry of both Houses as appeared in Parliament at <HI>Dublin,</HI> should be secured. And for the drawing together of the rest, amongst other preten∣ces, this alledged to be one, That his Majesties rents were pur∣posely omitted, and not called upon in Easter-Term with that earnestnesse as formerly; and that such as made default should be summoned to appear in Michaelmas-Term at <HI>Dublin,</HI> and there surprised; such of them as were in the Country, wanting the heads, being easily cut off. They say that this pretended plot, was I know not how discovered to them: So that for the safety of their lives, and profession, they were inforced to stand upon their guard, and to counter-work that day of the 23 of <HI>Nov.</HI> laid for their destruction, by their declaring themselves in arms on the 23 of <HI>Octob.</HI> a moneth before. The serious part of this Discourse was related to me by a Friar intimate in their Counsel, and by a priest a popish Vicar generall, therby to give me satisfaction, and to ju∣stifie their proceedings, whose names I do for the present for∣bear, in respect of his Majesties service.</P>
<P>By others also it was informed, That this plot was mainly in∣tended in that Session of Parliament, next after the Earl of <HI>Straf∣fords</HI>
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
beheading, and the manner concluded upon in the popish private meetings, which were then observed to be frequent, and by some suspected might prove dangerous, and that for discove∣ry of what provision of armes and amunition our store of <HI>Dublin</HI> afforded (it being by some suspected, that most was sent before to <HI>Carrickfergus)</HI> one of the popish faction, in the house of <HI>Commons</HI> put one of the Protestant members to move, that some of the Earle of <HI>Straffords</HI> men had cast out some threatning words a∣gainst the Parliament in revenge of his Lord, which could not be conceived to end in lesse than a blowing up of the whole Houses of Parliament, the store lying under them: whereupon a Committee of both Houses, many of them prime Papists, were appointed to make search in all the corners in the Store: amongst these the Lord <HI>Mac Guire</HI> was one who was observed, without occasion to be liberall in disposing of money to some of the Officers of the Store, in a way more than was ordinary with him.</P>
<P>The last Session of Parliament being prorogued, and the time drawing nigh for putting their designe in execution, there was a great meeting appointed of the heads of the Romish Cler∣gie, and other Lay-men of their faction, said to bee at the Abbey of <HI>Mullifarvan,</HI> in the Countie of <HI>Westmeath,</HI> where is a Con∣vent of <HI>Franciscans,</HI> thereof openly and peaceably possessed for many yeares last past: the day of their meeting being also on their Saint <HI>Francis</HI> day, about the beginning of October last, but the time and place I cannot confidently affirm, yet howsoever the severall opinions and discussions are as follow, like as I have received it from the said Fryer, a Franciscan, and present there being a Guardian of that Order, where among many other things there debated; the question was what course should bee taken with the English, and all others that were found in the whole Kingdom to be Protestants. The Coun∣cell was therein divided.</P>
<P N="1">1. Some were for their banishment, without attempting on their lives; for this was given the Instance of the King of <HI>Spaines</HI> expelling out of <HI>Granado,</HI> and other parts of his Domi∣nions, the Moores to the number of many hundreth of thou∣sands: all of them being dismissed with their lives, wives and
<PB N="32" REF="18"/>
children, with some part of their goods (if not the most part) that this his way of proceeding redounded much to the honour of <HI>Spaine,</HI> whereas the slaughter of many innocents would have laid an everlasting blemish of cruelty on that State, that the like usage of the English their neighbours, and to whom many there present owed (if no more) yet their education; would gaine much to the cause, both in <HI>England</HI> and other parts: That their goods and estates seized upon, would bee sufficient without medling with their persons, that if the contrary course were taken, and their blood spilt, beside the curse it would draw from heaven upon their cause: It might withall incense and provoke the neighbour Kingdome of <HI>England,</HI> and that iustly taking a more severe revenge on them and theirs, even to extirpation if it had the upper hand.</P>
<P N="2">2 On the otherside, was urged a contrary proceeding to the ut∣ter cutting off all the English Protestants, where to the instance of the dismissed <HI>Moores,</HI> it was answered, that that was the sole Act of the King and Queene of <HI>Spaine,</HI> contrary to the advise of their Councell, which howsoever it might gaine that Prince a name of metcy, yet therein the event shewed him to be most un∣mercifull, not onely to his owne, but to all Christendome be∣side. That this was evident in the great and excessive charge that <HI>Spaine</HI> hath beene since that time put unto by these <HI>Moores</HI> and their posterity to this day. All Christendome also hath and doth still groane under the miseries it doth suffer by the piracies of <HI>Algiers, Sally,</HI> and the like Dennes of theeves. That all this might have beene prevented in one houre by a generall Mas∣sacre, applying that it was no lesse dangerous to expell the English: That these Robbers and banished men might againe returne with swords in their hands, who by their hard usage in spoiling might bee exasperated, and by the hope of recovering their former estates, would bee incen∣sed farre more than strangers that were sent against them. Being neither in their persons injured, nor grieved in their estate, that therefore a generall Massacre were the safest and readiest way from freeing the Kingdome of any such feares.</P>
<P N="3">3. In which diversity of opinions, howsoever the first pre∣vailed
<PB N="33" REF="18"/>
with some, for which the Franciscans (saith this Frier, one of their Guardians) did stand, yet others inclined to the se∣cond: some again leaning to a middle way, neither to dismisse nor kill.</P>
<P>And according to this do we finde the event and course of their proceedings. In some places they are generally put to the sword, or to other miserable ends: some restrain their persons in durance, knowing it to be in their hands to dispatch them at their plea∣sures; In the mean time, they being reserved either for profit by their ransome, or for exchange of prisoners, or gaining their own pardons by the lives of their prisoners, if time would serve, or by their death (if the worst did happen) to satisfie their fury. The third sort, at the first altogether dismissed their prisoners, but first having spoiled them of their goods, and after of their raiment, exposing the miserable wretches to cold and famine, whereby many have perished by deaths, worse then sword or halter.</P>
<P>Hitherto of their Counsells, and the effects of them. Now for their intentions, all being reduced, which God forbid, into their power; and thereof do they as by some Law, give such pe∣remptory conclusions, that it may well be wondred the thoughts of men professing themselves wise, should be so vain: and herein I do still follow mine Informer.</P>
<P><HI>First, their loyalty to his Majestie shall be still reserved. Thus say they of the modest sort: But both his Revenues and Government must be reduced to certain bounds: His Rents none other then the an∣cient reservations before the plantation, and the Customes so ordered, as to them shall be thought fitting.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Secondly, for the Government, such as would be esteemed loyall, would have▪ it committed to the hands of two Lords Iustices, one of the ancient Irish race, the other of the ancient British inhabi∣tants in the Kingdom; Provided that they be of the Romish pro∣fession.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Thirdly, that a Parliament be forthwith called, consisting of whom they shall think fit to be admitted, wherein their own religious men shall be ass stants.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Fourthly,</HI> Poinings <HI>Act must be repealed, and</HI> Ireland <HI>declared to
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
be a Kingdom independant on</HI> England, <HI>and without any reference un∣to it in any case what soever.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Fiftly, all Acts prejudiciall to the Romish Religion, shal be abolish∣ed; and it to be enacted, That there be none other profession in the King∣dom but the Romish.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Sixtly, that onely the ancient Nobility of the Kingdom shall stand, and of them, such as shall refuse to conform to the Romish Religion to be removed, and others put in their room; howsoever the present Earl of</HI> Kildare <HI>must be put out, and another put in his place.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Seventhly, all plantation lands to be re-called, and the ancient pre∣priators to be re-invested in their former estates, with the limitations in their Covenant expressed; That they had not formerly sold their inte∣rests an valuable considerations.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Eightly, that the respective Counties of the Kingdom be subdivided, and certain bounds or Baronies assigned to the chief Septs and others of the Nobility; who are to be answerable for the Government therof: And that a standing Army may be still in being, the respective Governours being to keep a certain nūber of men to be ready at all risings out (as they term it:) They also being to build and maintain certain fortresses in places most convenient within their precincts! And that these Gover∣nours be of absolute power, onely responsible to the Parliament.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Lastly, for maintaining a correspondencie with other Nations, and for securing the coasts. That also they may be rendred considerable unto others, a Navie of a certain number of Ships is to be maintained: That to this end five houses are to be appointed one in each province, account∣ing</HI> Meth <HI>for one of them: That to these houses shall be allotted an an∣nuall pension of certain thousands of pounds to be made up of part of the lands appropriate to Abbeys: And a further contribution to be raised in the respective provinces to that end: That these houses are to be as∣signed to a certain</HI> Order of Knights, <HI>answerable to that of</HI> Malta, <HI>who are to be sea-men: And to maintain this Fleet, that all prizes are to be apportioned; some part for a common bank, the rest to be divided; to which purpose the felling of woods serviceable for this use, is to be for∣bidden: The House for this purpose to be assigned to the province of</HI> Leinstor, <HI>is</HI> Kilmainham, <HI>or rather</HI> Howth, <HI>the Lord of</HI> Howith <HI>being otherwise to be accommodated, provided be joyn with them; that place being esteemed most convenient, in respect of situation, which they have small grounds to hope for.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="31" REF="19"/>
For effecting of all which, they cast up the accounts of the forces of this Kingdom, That it is able to make up readily, two hundreth thousand able men, wanting onely Commanders, and some expert souldiers for the present with arms and ammunition: of all which, they expect a speedy supply out of <HI>Flanders,</HI> their own Regiments there exercised, being to be sent over, and some shipping from <HI>Spain</HI> allotted for service: That this Kingdom be∣ing setled, there are thirty thousand men to be sent into <HI>England,</HI> to joyn with the French and Spanish forces, and the service in <HI>England</HI> performed, joyntly to fall upon <HI>Scotland,</HI> for reducing both Kingdoms to the obedience of the pope; which being fi∣nished, they have ingaged themselves to the King of <HI>Spain</HI> for as∣sisting him against the <HI>Hollanders.</HI></P>
<P>And for drawing their followers to some head, and for giving the fairer glosse to their foul Rebellion, it is to be admired, what strange and unlikely rumours of their own devising they cast abroad; sometimes that many sail of Spaniards are landed now at one port, then at another: That <HI>Drogheda</HI> was taken at such a day and hour, with all the circumstances at large, and Let∣ters to that purpose dated from <HI>Drogheda</HI> by the Rebels that besieged it: That <HI>Dublin</HI> was taken: And being infinitely am∣bitious of gaining the Earl of <HI>Ormond</HI> to their part, for the greater countenance to their cause, giving out that he was their own; which was so long beleeved by the said followers, until that no∣ble Earl giving daily those honorable Testimonies to the contra∣ry, and they finding it to their cost, though with the hazard of his own person, further then his place might well allow; they are now otherwise satisfied, and place him in the rank of their mortall enemies, together with that terrour to them, Sir <HI>Charls Coot,</HI> and others.</P>
<P>And thus have I laid down all that I have heard to me related, omitting what I finde others more largely to insist upon. All which their treacherous, vain, and ayry projects God disappoint.</P>
<P>As for my own private sufferings by the present rebellion, I refer them to another Schedule, this being so far taken up.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Deposed before us, <DATE>March 3. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Hen. Jones.</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Roger Puttock.</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>John Sterne.</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Iohn Watson.</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>William Aldrich.</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>William Hitchcock.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Edmund Welsh <HI>of</HI> Moylerstown, <HI>in the Kings County.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That <HI>Piers Fitz-Gerald</HI> of <HI>Ballisonan,</HI> in the said County, taking his Pe∣ternell <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 7.</NOTE> ready cocked, presented the same to this Deponents brest, saying (when this Deponent offered to draw his sword) that it was in vain for him to strive against so many, and so disarmed him, and took from him his sword and dagger, with eight Guns, with cer∣tain Powder and Lead, alleadging, that there was an Excommuni∣on from the chief of their Church, against any of his Religion that would not do the like; and if he had not done so, and that soon, some of his neighbours would have had his head; and that they would never ask any Quarter, nor accept of any pardon. And these trayterous words were then and there spoken, and these hostile and outragious acts committed as aforesaid: all which this Deponent upon oath averreth.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Edmund Welsh.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><DATE><HI>Iur.</HI> 22 <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>VVilliam Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> John Edgworth, <HI>Esquire, high Sheriff of the County of</HI> Longford.</HEAD>
<P>THis examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That he sending abroad to know what the meaning of this Insurre∣ction <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 8.</NOTE> was, word was brought him by one <HI>Thomas Stafford,</HI> once a servant to this examinate, that he heard there was a Commission come from his Majesty to the Irish, by which they had power to destroy the <HI>English</HI> in this Kingdom, and in so doing, to revenge the wrong done to his Majesty by the Puritans of <HI>England,</HI> who had not onely taken away his prerogative, but had also deposed him, and put up the Palsgrave in his stead: this examinate discour∣sing further with the said <HI>Stafford,</HI> asked him if there were not a great meeting of Friers and priests about the the third or fourth of <HI>October</HI> last, being Saint <HI>Francis</HI> day, at the Monastery of <HI>Multefarnam,</HI> in the County of <HI>VVestmeath:</HI> to which the said <HI>Stafford</HI> answered, There was: and being further asked by
<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
this Examinate what was the meeting for, he answered he did not know; onely thus much, That some of the Friers told him that this was a yeer of <HI>Iubilee,</HI> and that there was a plenary Indulgence or Bull (as he termed it) from the <HI>Pope,</HI> for all the sins committed, and all that should be committed this yeer of <HI>Iubilee.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Iohn Edgworth.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Febr.</HI> 23. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVilliam Aldrich.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> John Brooks <HI>of</HI> Ballyheys, <HI>in the County of</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 9.</NOTE> Cavan, <HI>Yeoman.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That by some of the Rebells this Deponent, and other English Prote∣testants were threatned to be presently murthered, unlesse they would presently be gone: And if they went to <HI>Dublin,</HI> they should finde small relief there; if for <HI>England,</HI> as little there; for <HI>England</HI> was in the same case. And further said, That they had long paid Rents to the English, but they would make them pay it back again: further alleadging, That what they did, they had au∣thority for the same from the King, or words to that eff<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ct.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Iohn C Brooks his mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><DATE><HI>Jur.</HI> 5 <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn VVatson.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Grace Lovett, <HI>wife to</HI> Fran. Lovett <HI>of</HI> Ballew-hillan, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 10.</NOTE> <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That <HI>Patrick mac Collomac Donnell, Edmond mac Donnell,</HI> and the rest of their company, the 25. day of <HI>October</HI> last, entred into severall parcells of Land, and outed this Deponent and her children; as also took away the Lease, Writings, Will, and Escripts that this Deponent had, that concerned the estate of the severall par∣cells of Land.</P>
<P>And further deposeth, That she heard one of the Company of Captain <HI>Rory Magwire</HI> (who, as this Deponent heard, was a Friar) say, That it was well that this Deponent was come into their Company to save her life; for if she should go for <HI>Dublin,</HI> it would be as bad; And if she went for <HI>England,</HI> it would be worse (for said he) we have the Kings broad Seal for what we do: And for the reason of our rising, it is because the Puritans preferred a
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/><PB N="36" REF="21"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/><PB N="33" REF="21"/>
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
Petition against us, and could not let us enjoy our Religion quiet∣ly, for we stand for our lives; And if we should not have done this, we had all lost our lives upon one day, or words to that effect.</P>
<P>And further this deponent saith, That she this deponent, her husband, and four children, were all stript naked by the said Re∣bels, belonging to the said Captain <HI>Rory,</HI> the said 25. day of <HI>October</HI> last, at <HI>Newtown</HI> alias <HI>Castlecool.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Grace <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Lovets</HI> Mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Jan.</HI> 5. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Jones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Elizabeth Coats <HI>of</HI> Drumully <HI>in the County of</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 11.</NOTE> Fermanagh <HI>Widdow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis examinate duely sworne, deposeth, <HI>inter alia.</HI> That she heard some of the Rebellious company, say, and ask the Eng∣lish Protestants that were there robbed, what they intended to do, or whether to go, saving unto them: if they went for <HI>Dublin,</HI> that was taken by the Lord <HI>Magwire</HI> upon Saturday before, and there they should finde small relief, if for <HI>England,</HI> or <HI>Scotland,</HI> it was as bad there, as here; saying further, that what they did, they had the Kings Commission for it.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Elizabeth M Coats</HI> her Mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed this fourth of</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>before us,</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Randal Adams,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Watson.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Nicholas Willoughby <HI>of the</HI> Carrow <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>Esquire.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 12.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That <HI>Con oge mac Mabon</HI> said, that all the Counties in <HI>Ireland</HI> were in action, or rebellion, as well as <HI>Monaghan</HI> and <HI>Fermanagh,</HI> and that there was warre in <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Scotland,</HI> between the Papists and them.</P>
<P>And moreover he said, That the Irish were certainly enformed that there was a course to be suddainly taken with them, to make them go to Church, or else to loose their lives, and that they had seen some writing, or letter to that effect; and said that <HI>Owen mac Art ô Neal</HI> was come out of <HI>Spain,</HI> and landed about <HI>Strangford,</HI>
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
or that side, and that he had brought store of Arms and men with him, and that there were many Redshanks come over out of the Highlands in <HI>Scotland,</HI> to take their parts.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Nicholas Willoughby.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Febr.</HI> 23. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Jones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVill. Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Thomas Crant <HI>of</HI> Cavan <HI>in the County of</HI> Cavan. <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 13.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That the said <HI>Donnagh mac Gwire</HI> expressing, that he was not made privy to the generall Cause, untill two or three dayes afore the day came, if he had been made of the Councell, he would advise other wayes, then to take up Arms; but that now it was so, his hand was in, and that he would not take it cut, and that if the Lord of <HI>Eveskillin</HI> was ill used, we should be farre worse; and that if he suffered, we should all be destroyed, not one should escape, and that for his part he would never lock for pardon, for that he knew well enough, that they could pick a fault in any pardon, after that he was come in, to destroy him, for that how many pardons soever the Earl of <HI>Tyren</HI> had, as yet they did him no good: Therefore he would not trust to any, but would stand out to defend his Country with his bloud, Expressing that the Scots were, and had been alwaies their friends, and that they had a Covenant to shew, whereby it might appear the fair correspon∣dency between them, the Irish, and the Scors in <HI>Scotland;</HI> which covenant imported, that the Irish should never take part with the English against the Scots; and that the Scots should never take part with the English against the Irish; And that it was so cove∣nanted between many of the Lords of <HI>Scotland,</HI> and many of the Lords, and their Gentry of <HI>Ireland;</HI> and that <HI>Hugh mac Mahon</HI> had the Covenant to shew;</P>
<P>Saying, That he was more a Papist then a Protestant, and that the Puritan Parliament of <HI>England,</HI> was the cause of all this, that they had laid a plot, that at the next Sessions of Parliament, here in <HI>Ireland,</HI> that the Papists of the house should be all committed to the Castle, or murdered, and the Protestants were to murder all the Papists throughout the Kingdom, and that they having intelli∣gence of that; Therefore they did begin first, and would now
<PB N="36" REF="23"/>
continue, and that all the whole Kingdom did rise, as they did the self same day the 23. of <HI>October,</HI> and that all the Papists in <HI>England</HI> did so that same day, rise in Arms against the Protestants; and also that some Papist Earls and Lords in <HI>Scotland,</HI> did likewise so too; So that there was warres in <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Scotland,</HI> as there was here in <HI>Ireland.</HI></P>
<P>Divers Women and Children murdered, lying unburied till dogs spoiled their Corps, Women with childe murdered, and some dyed for cold, after being stript forth of their cloaths, lying unburied, that dogs gnawed their Children forth of their Wombs, which this examinate heard some of the vulgar people report with a cheerfulnesse.</P>
<P>Also there he heard reported by <HI>Con oge mac Con mac Hugh mac Mahon, Patrick oge mac Rosse Magwyre,</HI> that upon <HI>Christmas-</HI>day, they with a matter of a 1000. men, went down to <HI>Eneskillin</HI> fiedge, and there they burnt the house of <HI>Lisgoole,</HI> where into was come of Men, Women, and Children, a matter of fifty souls of Scots, who they burnt all in the house, except Master <HI>Iames Dunbarre</HI> and his Sister, whom they gave quarter to; and took them forth of a Window, and keepe them prisoners; as also they had burnt a Castle called <HI>Tullin;</HI> wherein was a matter of thirty or forty souls of Scots, and that as yet they could not do any good on <HI>Moone-</HI>Castle, nor of <HI>Eneskillin.</HI></P>
<P>A poor Man was met withall, by a couple of Irish Women, who knockt him in the head, and killed him, the Lord of <HI>Dunsany</HI> sent for the Women, examined the reason why they did so, they an∣swered, that <HI>Barnaby Reyly</HI> was hanged at <HI>Dublin,</HI> and they did it to revenge his death, the Lord of <HI>Dunsany</HI> committed them to pri∣son, what since is done with them, this examinate knoweth not.</P>
<P>At my being at <HI>Racaine,</HI> I heard it credibly reported, that on the Sunday before <HI>Christmas-</HI>day, that after <HI>Edmund mac Mulmore ô Rely</HI> had pillaged Bishop <HI>Bedle</HI> of <HI>Kilmore,</HI> and sent him with his two sonnes to <HI>Cloughwater</HI> Castle to restraint; That the Romish Bishop <HI>Mac Swine,</HI> came to the Church of <HI>Kilmore,</HI> and there did consecrate it anew, and set up an Altar there, and so said Masse, and there liveth in the Bishops house.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thom. Crant.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>13. <HI>Febr.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVill. Aldrich.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Elizabeth Parker <HI>late of</HI> Battydust <HI>in the County</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 14.</NOTE> <HI>of</HI> Catherlagh, <HI>VViddow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That when she and others were wishing themselves in <HI>England?</HI> What should you do in <HI>England,</HI> for it was as bad as in <HI>Ireland;</HI> Besides, the Seas were very dangerous; and <HI>Comerfords</HI> Wife further said, that the Queens Priest was hanged in <HI>England,</HI> which was the cause of the insurrection in this Kingdom, or to that effect.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>13. <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Elizabeth Parker.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn VVatson.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Ockar Butts <HI>late of</HI> Bollganreagh <HI>in the County</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 15.</NOTE> <HI>of</HI> Wexford, <HI>Gentleman.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That one of the Rebels of the said company, being (as he said) the Leader or Commander over them, spake these words, <HI>viz.</HI> That they had full power and commission from their Generall, to execute such and the like exploits against the Protestants; and that we should have no longer respite to remain in this Kingdom, then untill the next day following; And that then all Protestants should have generall warning to depart this Kingdom upon pain of death. And they then made question, whether we should be permitted to land in any part of <HI>England,</HI> or no. And that such straight Com∣mission was granted, and sent over unto their Generall by the Queen, and some of the best Nobility of <HI>England.</HI> And also that they did not neer execute towards us Protestants, the tenure and rigour of their said Commission; protesting with great prophane oathes, That they shewed much favour unto us.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Oekar Butts.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 25. 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram nobis,</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Iohn VVatson,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Edward Denman <HI>of</HI> Belturbut, <HI>in the Coun∣ty of</HI> Cavan, <HI>Merchant.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 16.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate du<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly sworn deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That he ask∣ing <HI>John Rely</HI> why they did not meddle with the Scots, he said the Scots did joyn with them.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Jurat. coram nobis.</HI> <DATE>27 <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Edward Denman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Watson,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Randall Adams.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="38" REF="24"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of Geo. Fercher of</HI> Toneheye, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fer∣managh, <HI>Clerke.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 17.</NOTE> <HI>Con oge mac Mabon,</HI> of the County of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> and Baro∣ny of <HI>Dartrie,</HI> did say, That what they did against the English, was done by Commission from His Majesty; and that all the Scot∣tish Nation was joyned with them in a Covenant, for the extirpa∣tion of the English; and to that effect he said he was able to let me see the Earl of <HI>Argile</HI> his Hand, together with the Hands of the greatest part of the prime Nobility of <HI>Scotland.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 4. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Randall Adams.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Geo. Fercher.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Elizabeth Dickinson, <HI>neer</HI> Clounish, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That some of <HI>Rory Magwire</HI> his Company did, in the hearing of this De∣ponent, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 18.</NOTE> say, That the Scots were to leave never a drop of English blood in <HI>England,</HI> and that the Irish had command to leave never a drop of English blood in <HI>Ireland;</HI> and that they were the Queens Souldiers. And further sayeth not.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 3. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Eliz. Dickinson.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> John Shorter <HI>of</HI> Callahill, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fer∣managh.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That they asked this Deponent whither he would go (to whom he <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 19.</NOTE> answered, For <HI>England)</HI> then said they, This day <HI>Dublin</HI> Castle is taken, the Tower of <HI>London,</HI> and Castle of <HI>Edenborougb;</HI> and you have but four and fourty hours to live, and then both English men and women, and children shall be slain.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 5. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVilliam Aldrich.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iobn Sborter.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="39" REF="24"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Thomas Knowles <HI>of</HI> Newtown, <HI>alias</HI> Castle-cool, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>Yeoman.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That <HI>Hugh mac Mabon,</HI> and one <HI>Patrick Magwire</HI> told this Deponent, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 20.</NOTE> That they had Commission from His Majesty for what they did; and that the same doings was done thorowout the whole King∣dom at that time, their plot having been working for two yeers last past; and that certainly God had a great hand in the same; all places of the Protestants abode being taken and yeelded, except three, <HI>viz. London-Derry, Eneskellin,</HI> and another Town, this De∣ponent now not remembring the name; and that those Towns could not long withstand their Forces, because the Lord <HI>Magwire</HI> had taken <HI>Dublin</HI> Castle (as they said) the Saturday before, other∣wise if it had not been taken, and that their plot had been disco∣vered, the said Lord <HI>Magwire</HI> had been with them again upon Sa∣turday aforesaid.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 3. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Tbo. Knowles.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> John Kerdiff, <HI>Rector of the Parish of</HI> Diserte reagh, <HI>in the Barony of</HI> Dungannon, <HI>and County of</HI> Tyrone.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, <HI>inter alia,</HI> deposeth, and saith, That the Trayterous actions committed, and words spoken by the <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 21.</NOTE> Rebells against the Protestants, were as followeth:</P>
<P><HI>October the</HI> 23, <HI>and</HI> 24, <HI>they surprised these Forts,</HI> Viz.</P>
<P><HI>Dungannon, Charlemont, Castle Caufield, Mountjoy, Munnymore, Castle Blaney, Monagban, Newry;</HI> in a word, all the chiefe Forts in the Counties of <HI>Armagh</HI> and <HI>Tyrone<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> and ransackt every Town and house which belonged either to English-man or Scottish.</P>
<P>They murthered the very first day Mr <HI>Mader,</HI> Minister of the Parish of <HI>Donoghmore,</HI> by some of the <HI>Donellies:</HI> within a while after, they murthered Mr. <HI>New,</HI> Curate to Mr. <HI>Bradley,</HI> of the Church of <HI>Ardtra,</HI> by one of the The Mi∣nister of <HI>Dungannon</HI> (Mr. <HI>Blyth)</HI> with eight more, were murthered, being first stript, and after driven out of the Town, under colour of Conduct; and within half a mile to the Town murthered Mr. <HI>Blyth,</HI> holding Sir <HI>Phelomies</HI> protection in his hand, as if he would
<PB N="40" REF="25"/>
call Gods vengeance down on such treacherous truce-breakers.</P>
<P>It was also related to me, that Mr. <HI>Fullerton,</HI> Minister of <HI>Lough∣gale,</HI> and Master <HI>Morgan Aubery</HI> were kild at the Bridge of <HI>Port of Downe,</HI> at which time about eighty or an hundred of the Inhabi∣tants of <HI>Loughgale</HI> were cast into the River and there drowned.</P>
<P>Many more Murthers were committed on the English and Scotch.</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Robberies.</HEAD>
<P>Master <HI>Bradley</HI> was robbed to the value of one thousand pounds, and whilest he was robbing, Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neal</HI> and his company passed by, and soone after he was turned out naked out of his house; the Rebels neither leaving Dublet, Coate, Hat, nor Shirt, with him. His Wife is falne into an extream frenzey by these out∣rages.</P>
<P>Master <HI>Dunbarre</HI> Minister of <HI>Donoghemie,</HI> with his Wife, and five or six small Children, with an old Father and Mother, were all of them stript and robbed of whatsoever Goods, or wearing Cloaths they had; so that for a while the man was distracted, and after compelled to tye some straw about his thighs, to cover his naked∣nesse, and was whipt as I was certainly informed, and what is be∣come of him, his wife, or children, no man in the County could tell me, though I lived within three miles of him.</P>
<P>Master <HI>VVright,</HI> Archdeacon of <HI>Dromore,</HI> had his house which cost him much, burnt; I saw himself, his wife, and two children, in extream misery at <HI>Charlemont,</HI> from whence they journied to <HI>Kinard.</HI></P>
<P>Master <HI>Robinson,</HI> Minister of <HI>Kinard,</HI> and his wife, lived mise∣rably at <HI>Loughgale,</HI> having nothing left to satisfie nature, but what they could procure by others distressed like.</P>
<P>Master <HI>Hasting,</HI> Minister of <HI>Tullaniskin,</HI> was turned out of his lodging, and stript starke naked, and clad in beggars Cloaths, no a Shoe to his Foot, in which state he came to the house, wherein I was lodged, where the people of the house durst not give him lodging, fearing least he should be murthered; for twice the next day, there was search made for him.</P>
<P>Sir <HI>VVilliam Brumley</HI> had his Town and Castle burned, and all his goods taken away.</P>
<P>What shall I say more, All the English and Scotch in the Coun¦ties
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
of <HI>Armagh</HI> and <HI>Tyrone</HI> (a few onely excepted) were not left worth a farthing.</P>
<P>At <HI>Armagh</HI> Archdeacon <HI>Maxwell</HI> related, That about fourty men, women, and children were drowned at <HI>Cor</HI> Bridge, neer <HI>Glaslough;</HI> the children going merrily hand in hand, as to a place of refuge; and one of their company having license to pray, pray∣ed so effectually, that one of his Executioners went frantick with the conceit of his impious fact.</P>
<P>The words which I took notice of, were these: Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neal</HI> told, in my hearing, That he had Commission for what he did, not only from most of the chief of the Nobility of this Kingdom, but from his Majesty; and had also Letters to that pur∣pose from the Earl of <HI>Argile.</HI></P>
<P>And that their intentions were onely for the liberty of their Religion, and for the recovery of their Lands, which should appear by the Law of the Land to be unjustly held from them.</P>
<P>Colonell <HI>Plunket</HI> told us at <HI>Armagh,</HI> That seeing this exploit was begun, he was one of the chief plotters thereof, and was seven yeers emplyed in the compassing of it.</P>
<P>Frier <HI>Malone</HI> of <HI>Skerries</HI> did take the poor mens Bibles, which he found in the Boat, and cut them in pieces, and cast them into the fire, with these words, That he would deal in like manner with all Protestant and Puritan Bibles.</P>
<P>At Master <HI>Connors</HI> house (where the Frier was) they had <HI>Hanmors</HI> Chronicle, out of which they animated the Rebells with the Story of the <HI>Danes</HI> Discomfiture by the Irish, though for the most part unarmed, and paralelled the History with these times.</P>
<P>This Frier acknowledged that he was fourteen yeers employed to bring this designe to passe.</P>
<P>At <HI>Donga<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>non</HI> they reported of a Vision seen a little before this Insurrection began, A woman compassing about the Town with a Spear in her hand; when any would approach her, she would seem to go from them; when any would go from her, she would draw neer unto them: The like, they say, appeared before <HI>Tyrones</HI> former Rebellion.</P>
<P>At <HI>Armagh,</HI> Colonell <HI>Pluncket</HI> told us of another Vision
<PB N="42" REF="26"/>
seen at <HI>Lisneigarvey,</HI> which he and about twenty more beheld, after the Battle (wherein the Irish lost very many of their men, and most of their Arms) There was an house set on fire at the end of the Town; by the light of which fire, they discerned a number of Horse-men riding to and fro; the number seemed to the Colonell, to be about a Thousand, or Fifteen hundred: Upon which relati∣on, I was bold to enquire whether they seemed their own, or their enemies: he answered, That sometime they conceived them their own, other while their enemies.</P>
<P>Yet I believed they could hardly seem their own, because a∣mongst them they had not neer so many Horses. I further desired to know what they supposed them to be: he said, They were conceived to be Fayries, or such like.</P>
<P>At <HI>Ardtra</HI> we were set upon by some of the Scots (of whom <HI>Robert Stewart,</HI> brother to the Lord of <HI>Castle-Stewart</HI> was chief▪) who took some of the goods out of the house, and many of our horses and Arms from us.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Jurat. ult.</HI> <DATE><HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Kerdiff.</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Edward How, <HI>of the Parish of</HI> Galoon, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>Clerke.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That he heard <HI>Donagh mac Quire</HI> say (when <HI>Hugh mac Mahon,</HI> of the County <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 22.</NOTE> of <HI>Fermanagh</HI> excused my Lord <HI>Magwire,</HI> and said, that others had perswaded him of late to stirre in this action) That my Lord <HI>Magwire</HI> knew of it long before, and all the Nobility and men of quality that were papists in this Kingdom: Moreover I heard <HI>Con¦oge mac Con mac Hugh mac Mahon,</HI> of <HI>Aghnebolah,</HI> and County of <HI>Monaghan</HI> say, That if my Lord Lievtenant had not been put to death, they had not made this Insurrection. Further I heard him say, That there was an Act made by the present Parliament of <HI>England,</HI> That all Papists there, or else-where in this Kingdom, should go to Church, otherwise be hanged at their own doors, and therefore they would begin with us, lest we should begin with
<PB N="43" REF="26"/>
them here, as they did in <HI>England;</HI> for he said they had hanged a Jesuite in <HI>London,</HI> which was the Queens Chaplain. And further this Deponent cannot say.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 29. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Edw. How.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> George Cook, <HI>late of</HI> Lissnegney, <HI>in the Coun∣ty of</HI> Cavan, <HI>Yeoman: And of</HI> John Cook <HI>his son.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THe Deponent being duly sworn, <HI>inter alia,</HI> deposeth And further saith, That as he and his wife and chil∣dren <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 23.</NOTE> fled away towards <HI>Dublin,</HI> they met at <HI>Kells</HI> with a Pro∣testant Minister, by name Master <HI>Sharpe,</HI> who had three children, and carryed two of them on his back; whom the Rebells percei∣ving to be a Protestant Minister, did most barbarously hack, cut in pieces, and murther, thrusting into his body three or four pikes together, and threw him into a ditch of water, where they left him: but because the Deponent fled to save his life, he cannot tell what became of the said Ministers poor children. And the Depo∣ponent <HI>John Cook</HI> further saith, That the same night one <HI>Tir∣logh Brady</HI> took away the Deponents fathers goods: he the said <HI>Tirlogh</HI> told the Deponent, That that action was a great Rebel∣lion, and that all the papists in <HI>Ireland</HI> were in Rebellion against the King and Counsell, and that the Lord <HI>mac Guire</HI> had then taken the Castle of <HI>Dublin;</HI> And that the Protestants must be ba∣nished out of the Kingdom, and the papists would have the same themselves. And about the same time one <HI>Tirlogh ô Gowen alias Smith,</HI> a popish priest, demanded the Key of the Church of <HI>Lara</HI> of this Deponents brother: which being delivered unto him, he the said <HI>Tirlogh</HI> said, that the papists would have their Churches Lands and Kingdom from the English, and be no more slaves to the English as they had been, or else they would lose their lives.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE><HI>Jan.</HI> 22. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>George Cooke.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVilliam Aldrich.</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Cooke.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="44" REF="27"/>
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> John Jesop <HI>of</HI> Cloynmoore <HI>in the County of</HI> Kildare. <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 24.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, desposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That he hath credibly heard, that all the Papists in the County of <HI>Wex∣ford,</HI> and <HI>Kilkenney,</HI> and in all the Counties of <HI>Ireland,</HI> are Actors, Abettors, or at least secret well-wishers unto this Rebellion.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Iohn Iesop.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>8. <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram nobis.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton,</ITEM>
<ITEM>W<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll. Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> John Greg <HI>of</HI> Levileglish <HI>in the County of</HI> Ar∣magh <HI>Yeoman.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 25.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That His Wife and five small Children are in the Rebels hands, who were most cruelly stripped before he left them, even to the childe that sucked the brest; further he saith, that his said Wife being stripped to the skin by one of the Donnells, was by him most cru∣elly beaten with his drawn Sword in a triumphing and rejoycing manner, and with singing.</P>
<P>Further he saith one Captain <HI>Art ô Neal,</HI> of the Parish of <HI>Le∣vileglish</HI> aforesaid, Gentleman, who pretended friendship to him, said that unlesse he would take up Arms, and go to Masse, there was no hope of his life, unto whom he replyed, that that was great cruelty, neither to suffer him the said <HI>Gregg</HI> to live a slave a∣mongst them, nor suffer him to passe into his Native Countrey, unto whom the said Captain replyed, that neither of those requests would be granted, affirming that it was intended by them, not to leave an English Protestant alive in this Kingdom, and that there was no hope of peace for tenne yeers to come.</P>
<P>He further saith, That in the aforesaid Parish, there were divers English-men, most cruelly murthered, some twice, some thrice hanged up, and others wounded, and left half-dead, crying la∣mentably for some to come and end their misery by killing them out.</P>
<P>And further he saith, That the names of the chiefest of the Re∣bels in those parts, are <HI>Phelomy ô Neal</HI> of <HI>Kinnard</HI> in the County
<PB N="45" REF="27"/>
of <HI>Tyron,</HI> Knight, and <HI>Turlagh ô Neal</HI> Esquire, his Brother, and one Colonell <HI>Pluncket,</HI> and Captain <HI>Manus oge ô Caban</HI> of the County of <HI>Armagh,</HI> Gentlemen, and <HI>Redmond ô Mullan,</HI> of the <HI>Grange</HI> in the County of <HI>Tyron,</HI> Gentleman, and <HI>Patrick ô Mullan</HI> now of <HI>Armagh,</HI> Gentleman, who wrote Proclamations in His Majesties Name.</P>
<P>And further he saith, That he heard by credible English-men, that the said <HI>Phelomy ô Neal</HI> affirmed, that his taking up Arms was by His Majesty, and the Queens consent, and the Parliament in this Kingdom; and further that one Captain <HI>Shane ô Neal,</HI> in the County of <HI>Tyron,</HI> stiled the said <HI>Phelomy ô Neal,</HI> with the title and stile of His Majesty.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Iohn Greg.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>7. <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram nobis.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Will. Hitchcock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Henry Raynolds <HI>of</HI> Cornemuekley <HI>in the Coun∣ty of</HI> Cavan, <HI>Yeoman.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 26.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That he heard one whose name, as he thinks is, <HI>Ferdoragh</HI> (an Irish Priest) say that they had the Kings hand for what they did, and the cause of there rising, was because, there was a Statute made in <HI>England,</HI> that all papists should go to Church before a certain time, or be banished.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Hen. Raynolds.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us.</HI> <DATE>4. <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Io. Watson.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Charles Crafford <HI>of</HI> Navan <HI>in the County of</HI> Meath, <HI>Gentleman.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 27.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That the reason generally given by them for their doing, was, that they had found a Letter, wherein the English had resolved to hang the Irish at their doors, if they would not go to Church; and that therefore they would begin with the English first.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Charles ▪ Craffords</HI> Mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>22. <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Roger Puttock,</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Io. Sterne,</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Ioh,</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>VVatson,</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>VVill. Aldrich.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="46" REF="28"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> John Wood <HI>of</HI> New-Rath <HI>in the County of</HI> Wicklow, <HI>Gentleman.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 28.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That these words were spoken by <HI>Nicholas Byrne, James mac Cahire,</HI> and divers other of the Rebels, that they were discontented Gentle∣men; and having their Lands unjustly taken away by the Plantati∣on, could not have any satisfaction, but by the Sword; Therefore it was their Colonell <HI>Luke Tooles</HI> pleasure, that all Protestants should depart the Kingdom upon pain of death: And for <HI>Dublin</HI> if that did stand out long with them, they made no question to burn it; but if they could take it, and not fire it, so they might have the head of my Lord <HI>Parsons,</HI> and three or four more of the chiefest of the City, all the rest should fare so much the better.</P>
<P>And they further said, That there was an Act of Parliament in <HI>England,</HI> that all papists in <HI>Ireland,</HI> should upon pain of death, either go to Church, or be banished the Kingdom by such a day of the moneth, which as I take it, was by the 24. of <HI>November;</HI> And therefore they desired liberty of conscience, and to enjoy all that Land which there predecessors did formerly enjoy. For why should not they have there demands, as well as the Scots.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>John Wood.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>17. <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Stern,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Randall Adams.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Henry Steel, <HI>Curate of</HI> Cluntubbrid.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That when they <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 29.</NOTE> were imprisoned in the Dungeon in the County Goal, (all the robbers and rogues first set at liberty) they remained there in a most miserable estate, there being in number, about forty eight, more or lesse, where they had no roome to stand or lye.</P>
<P>And further deposeth, That he by Gods great mercy being en∣larged, his wife yet prisoner in <HI>Castle-Blaney,</HI> he came away with one Master <HI>Barnewell,</HI> and being in a place called <HI>Cabret,</HI> where one Master <HI>Fleming</HI> liveth, whose Daughter is married to the Lord <HI>Magwire,</HI> he heard the servants of the house, and other Irish relating that this <HI>Magwire,</HI> and the popish Primate, whose Sirname is <HI>Rely,</HI> were a long space travelling through the King∣dome
<PB N="47" REF="28"/>
together, to perswade them all to condiscend to this most inhumane plot, and this <HI>Rely</HI> was then at this <HI>Flemings</HI> house.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Hen. Steel.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed this</HI> <DATE>10. <HI>of Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Will. Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Katherine Graunt <HI>of</HI> Navan <HI>in the County of</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 30.</NOTE> Meath, <HI>Widdow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That the whole Town and Corporation of the <HI>Navan</HI> made good pre∣paration for the entertainment of the Northern Rebels in victuals and drink for them; very many of them went to the Rebels be∣fore they came to Town, and generally all of them, met them with great joy, and welcoming of them when they came to Town.</P>
<P>She further deposeth, That she heard the Priest that came with the Rebels from the North, (and the Priest of the <HI>Navan,</HI> Master <HI>Fay</HI> among them, as she verily beleeveth) all charging divers of the Captains not to go back, nor come in upon the Proclamation of pardon, that came from the State; for if they did, they were all undone.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Kath. ▪ Graunts</HI> Mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed this</HI> <DATE>5. <HI>of Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Hugh Madden, <HI>late of</HI> Kirreke <HI>in the County of</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 31.</NOTE> Wickloe, <HI>Gentleman.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That after he had been first besiedged, by at least eight hundred of the Rebels, having conference with some of them, they then gave out in words, that that businesse which they had begun, they would pursue till it were effected, and would not look for a par∣don for the same, or to that effect.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Hugh Madden.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>23. <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Iohn VVatson,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="48" REF="29"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> John Right, <HI>late of</HI> Newtown, <HI>alias</HI> Castle-c<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ol, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>Butcher.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That <HI>Rory</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 32.</NOTE> <HI>Magwire</HI> shewed to him, and others whom he then robbed, a Parchment or paper with a great Seal affixed, which he affirmed to be a Warrant from the Kings Majesty for what he did. And he further deposeth, That when he and his neighbours then rob∣bed, complained of their miserable condition, being robbed and stripped: the said <HI>Rory</HI> replyed, That if they were not content with what was done, they should see worse within a few dayes.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Iohn Right.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jurat.</HI> <DATE><HI>Jan.</HI> 5. 1641.</DATE> <HI>coram nobis.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Randall Adams,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne,</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> George French <HI>of</HI> Karbery, <HI>in the County of</HI> Kildare.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That he <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 33.</NOTE> demanded of the Rebells why they dealt so with <HI>VVilliam Coleman;</HI> to whom <HI>Luke Brumingham</HI> answered, That they had a Commission from His Majesty for what they did; and <HI>Gerald Fitz Gerald</HI> of <HI>Carbery</HI> aforesaid read the Commission: that was a suppo∣sed Commission from His Majesty to take away all English mens goods.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Geo. ▪ French his mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>1 <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>cor.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Randall Adams.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Jane Mansfeild, <HI>lately of the Parish of</HI> Castle-Jordan, <HI>VVidow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That she <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 34.</NOTE> coming towards <HI>Dublin,</HI> in her way coming to one Master <HI>Philip Fitz-Gerralds</HI> house, neer <HI>Miltowne,</HI> in the County of <HI>Kil∣dare,</HI> this Deponent heard him utter these words: We are like to have great troubles, but we must all rise in Arms, and not leave an English-man in <HI>Ireland;</HI> and that the King was on their side in the North among them.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Jane Mansfeild.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed</HI> <DATE>3 <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="49" REF="29"/>
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Henry Palmer <HI>late of</HI> Fetherd, <HI>in the County of</HI> Wexford, <HI>Brick-layer.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate being duely sworn <HI>inter alia,</HI> deposeth; That <HI>Dermot mac Dowling Cavanagh,</HI> Head of the Rebells there, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 35.</NOTE> and his company, said to this Deponent with others, Be gone you English dogges; for we do onely take your goods now, but worse shall follow: And they went into the Church, and cut the Pulpit-Cloth and the Ministers Books in pieces, and strewed them about the Church-yard, and caused the piper to play whilest they danced and trampled them under their feet, and called the Minister dog, and stript him out of his clothes: And that they wounded seve∣rall persons that were in the Castle of <HI>Fetherd,</HI> and the Town there; of which, some, by reason of their wounds, cold, and want, died. And what clothes this Deponent had left, being but mean, coming to <HI>Dublin,</HI> were also taken from him: And the Irish denyed them lodging and relief, insomuch that they were constrayned to lie out of doors naked all night. And further saith, That one <HI>Welsh</HI> of <HI>Killcullen</HI> Bridge, in the County of <HI>Kil∣dare,</HI> Inne-Keeper, after that this Deponent was robbed and strip∣ped, told this Deponent, That he the said <HI>VVelsh</HI> knew, that the King was in the North of <HI>Ireland,</HI> and rode disguised, and had glassen eyes, because he would not be known.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Henry Palmer.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>12 <HI>January,</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram nobis,</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> John Perkins, <HI>of</HI> Sleigkogh, <HI>in the County of</HI> Cavan.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duly sworn deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That they said that the King was dead, and that the young King went to <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 36.</NOTE> Masse; and they were the Queens souldiers, and we were Tray∣tors. And the said words were affirmed by <HI>Cormack mac Cloney,</HI> Parish-Priest of <HI>Killan.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Iohn</HI> I. P. <HI>Parkins his mark.</HI></SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE>8 <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="50" REF="30"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Tho. Midlebrook <HI>of</HI> Leagne Caffry, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>Yeoman.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That on the 26 day of <HI>October</HI> last, he heard <HI>Cahell Boy mac Dermott</HI> say, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 37.</NOTE> That within one fortnight they should have a new King of <HI>Ice∣land</HI> Crowned one of the <HI>ô Neals,</HI> or words to that effect: which words were spoken by the said <HI>Cahell,</HI> in the presence of <HI>Alice Tibs,</HI> this Deponents sister, and <HI>Avis Braishaw,</HI> wife of <HI>Iohn Braishaw.</HI> And further, that he hoth heard that the Rebells had murthered about threescore English Protestants (that lived in good manner within the said parish.) And further saith, That there cannot be so few as one hundred English Protestants (that lived in good manner within the said parish) perished and dead since the said Re∣bells did banish and drive them from their habitations.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 4. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry Brereton.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Tho.</HI> I. <HI>Midlebrook.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>his mark.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Alice Tibs <HI>of</HI> Ringvilly, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fer∣managh, <HI>widow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That she heard <HI>Cahell Boy mac Dermott</HI> of <HI>Killrout,</HI> in the County afore∣said, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 38.</NOTE> Yeoman, say, That <HI>Dublin</HI> Castle was taken, and that they could afford the English two or three Barrells of Powder; and that the Irish within one fortnight would have a new King, or words to that effect: which words he spake in the hearing of this Deponent, <HI>Avis Braishaw,</HI> wife to <HI>Iohn Braishaw,</HI> and <HI>Thomas Milebrooke,</HI> the five and twentieth day of <HI>October:</HI> And did after hear another Irish man (whose name she knoweth not) say, That it was pity that any of the English or their breed should be suffer∣ed to live, for fear they should grow strong again; or words to that effect.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>This deposed before us,</HI> <DATE>Jan. 4. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Alict ƲV. Tibs</ITEM>
<ITEM>her mark.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="51" REF="30"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Avis Braishaw, <HI>late of</HI> Agheruskie Moore, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter aliae,</HI> That she <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 39.</NOTE> heard <HI>Cahell Boy mac Dermott</HI> of <HI>Kilrout,</HI> in the County afore∣said, say, That <HI>Dublin</HI> Castle was taken, and that they could af∣ford the English three or four Barrells of Powder, and that the Irish would have a new King within a fortnight after: which words, or to that effect, he spake in the hearing of this Deponent, <HI>Tho. Midlebrook,</HI> and <HI>Alice Tibs,</HI> the 25 day of <HI>October</HI> last.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>This deposed before us,</HI> <DATE>Jan. 4 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Avis ƲƲ Braishaw</ITEM>
<ITEM>her mark.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Rich. Knowles <HI>of</HI> Newtowne, <HI>alias Castle-Cool, in the County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>Yeoman.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That there <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 40.</NOTE> is one hundred of the said parishioners (that lived in good rank and fashion) since they were driven out of their habitati∣ons, and banished by the said rebellious Irish (being all English Protestants) perished and dead: And this Deponent is the rather confident that there is one hundred or more dead, by reason they dayly die in such abundance; this Deponent well knowing the said parishioners, being his neighbours; and this Deponent be∣ing a Butcher by Trade, had some dealing with the most of them.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Deposed this</HI> <DATE>10 <HI>of</HI> Jan. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Iohn VVatson:</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Aldrich.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Rich.</HI> R. <HI>Knowls his mark.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Robert Barton <HI>of</HI> Newtowne, <HI>alias</HI> Castle-cool, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>Black-smith.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>iuter alia,</HI> That some <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 41.</NOTE> Irish Rebells neer unto <HI>Virginia,</HI> in the way towards <HI>Rells,</HI> did strip this Deponent, and said, That they had a new King, and Commission from him for what they did. And further deposeth, That he heard that Captain <HI>Rory,</HI> or some other of his Company, had murthered of the said parishioners, to the number of fourty, or thereabouts.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE>Jan. 5. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Iohn Brereton,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="52" REF="31"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Hugh Culme <HI>of</HI> Leitrim <HI>in the County of</HI> Mo∣naghan, <HI>Gentleman.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 42.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That he was told that one <HI>Art mac Mahown,</HI> who lived in the Parish of <HI>Tehollan,</HI> said that they which spoke English, should pay 10<SUP>s</SUP> to the King; the party to whom he spoke it, desired to know what King desired it, his answers was, what other King, but the Earl of <HI>Tyrone.</HI></P>
<P>And this Deponent heard one <HI>Thomas mac Aleares</HI> wife, of the same County and Parish, say, that Captain <HI>Bryan mac Mahon</HI> of <HI>Tehollan,</HI> said he would hang any that would speak English. And heard the priest <HI>mac Clerey</HI> of <HI>Tehollan</HI> say, that all the English in <HI>Monaghan</HI> must be hanged, I asked him why, he said, meat was soarce, and they would not be at the charge to keep us.</P>
<P>And heard more by very honest men, that Mr. <HI>Cottingham</HI> Mi∣nister of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> being in a Dungeon bolted, desired for Gods sake to get a little straw to lye upon, being put to such extre∣mitie.</P>
<P>And that Mr. <HI>Richard Blaney</HI> Justice of Peace in the County of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> was hanged in this manner.</P>
<P><HI>Art Roe mac Bryan Sanaght</HI> of <HI>Hislough</HI> in the County of <HI>Mo∣naghan,</HI> Marshall to the Rebels, came to Mr. <HI>Blaney</HI> to the Dun∣geon, and desired him to come out to speak with him, when he came out to him, he led him to my Lord <HI>Blaneys</HI> Orchard in <HI>Mo∣naghan,</HI> and said to him, do you remember, how you hanged my Brother, and made me flye my Country for three yeers; but I will hang you before you go, but if you will, you shall have a priest, he said no, but he desired to have Master <HI>Cottingham,</HI> the Minister of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> but they would not, but hanged him there, and flung him in a Ditch, and he was two dayes unburied.</P>
<P>And this Deponent heard that there was one <HI>Luke VVard</HI> a Scotchman, which had indicted a man, the quarter Sessions before this rising, the same man came to him where he was in the Goal, and carried him to an Alehouse, and made him drunk, and when he had done, carried him into the backside and hanged him, after
<PB N="53" REF="31"/>
he was cut down, they flung him into a River, and I could never hear that he was buried.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Hugh Culme.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 25. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<P>I heard Master <HI>Mountgomery,</HI> Minister, and Master <HI>Hollis</HI> with severall other men of good worth, report, that the Sunday before this rising of the Rebels, that there was seen a Sword hanging in the ayre, with the point downwards, the half seeming to be red, and the point turned round.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Hugh Culme.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of Mistresse</HI> Martha Culme <HI>of</HI> Leitrim <HI>in the</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 43.</NOTE> <HI>County of</HI> Monaghan.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That she be∣ing by the R<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bels forced from her dwelling, and robbed of all her goods, she was enforced to shift from place to place, for safe∣guard of her life: particularly at <HI>VVilliam Boy, Flemings</HI> house, in the Parish of <HI>Tehollan,</HI> in the County of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> where she did hear the said <HI>Fleming</HI> in detestation of the cruelty of the Rebels, to relate that while Sir <HI>Phelomy ô Neal</HI> did lye with his forces before the <HI>Ogber,</HI> in the County of <HI>Tyrone,</HI> the Irish women would follow after the Irish Rebell Souldiers, and put them forward in cruelty, with these and such words, spare neither man, woman, nor childe, God so pitty your souls, as you pitty them, intending those words, to cruelty.</P>
<P>This Examinate further saith, That in the said Flemings house, one <HI>Art mac Patrick mac Toole Boy mac Mahon</HI> of the Barony of <HI>Balline Cargy</HI> in the said Parish, speaking to this Examinate in Irish, she desired he would deliver himself in English, for she un∣derstood not Irish, he answered in English, that such as spake English, should forfeit ten shillings to the King, what King saith this Examinate have we, that will not allow the speaking of Eng∣lish, what King saith he, but the Earl of <HI>Tyrone,</HI> she asked where the Earl was, he answered in the North, where he was landed
<PB N="54" REF="32"/>
with 40000. Spaniards, whereof 10000. were then with Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neal.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Martba Culme.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Feb.</HI> 14. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Elizabeth Gough <HI>late of</HI> Ballanenagh <HI>in the</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 44.</NOTE> <HI>County of</HI> Cavan <HI>Spinster.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, deposeth, <HI>inter alia.</HI> That the Irish purposed to have a King of their own in <HI>Ireland,</HI> and that <HI>Phelomy ô Neal</HI> should be he.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Elizabeth▪ Gough her</HI> Mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Feb.</HI> 8. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Jones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Anne Gill <HI>of</HI> Newtown <HI>in the County of</HI> Fer∣managh, <HI>Widdow.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 45.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That when <HI>Rory Magwire</HI> had taken the Church at <HI>Newtown,</HI> aforesaid, he the said <HI>Rory</HI> (in the presence and hearing of this Deponent, and a great many of his neighbors, the Kings Majesties loving Subjects) gave forth that it was to no purpose for them to fly to <HI>Dublin,</HI> for succour, for <HI>Dublin</HI> was taken by the Lord <HI>Magwire,</HI> who was to be King of <HI>Ireland.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Anne L Gill</HI> her Mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>29. <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Stern,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVilliam Aldrich.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Elizabeth Vause <HI>late of</HI> Creigs toune Longh∣field <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 46.</NOTE> <HI>in the County of</HI> Leitrim, <HI>Widdow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That when this Deponent asked why the Rebels so robbed them, they asked again who sent you over, and being answered, that God and the King did it, they the said Rebells, said let your King fetch you out again.</P>
<P>And saith further, That the said Rebels burned divers houses, and two Children, and one old Man in them; and that very many Protestants that fled for safety and succour to the Castle of Sir
<PB N="55" REF="32"/>
<HI>James Craige</HI> Knight, being neer them, were there famished, star∣ved, and dyed, for want of means.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Eliz.▪ Vause</HI> her mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>9. <HI>die Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Nicholas Michael <HI>of</HI> Farnan <HI>in the County of</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 47.</NOTE> Cavan.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That the par∣ties that robbed this Deponent, said they have an Irish King amongst them, and they regarded not King <HI>Charles</HI> the King of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Nich. ʒ Michaels▪</HI> mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 15. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>VVill. Hitchcock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Andrew Foster <HI>of</HI> Mocredin <HI>alias</HI> Caryetsfort <HI>in the County of</HI> Wickloe, <HI>Gentleman.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 48.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That the Rebels said, that they would within a week burn <HI>Dublin,</HI> and that neither King nor Queen should govern <HI>Ireland</HI> any lon∣ger, for they would govern it themselves.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Andrew Foster.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>17. <HI>Febr.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>VVilliam Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Richard Witton <HI>of</HI> Kilnane <HI>in the County of</HI> Wickloe, <HI>Miller.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 49.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That <HI>Luke Burne</HI> Gentleman of <HI>Kilnane</HI> said, he would have their religi∣on flourish, no thanks to King or Subject.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Rich. Witton.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed this</HI> <DATE>11. <HI>of Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Will. Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVill. Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="56" REF="33"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Edward Taylor <HI>late of Saint</HI> Margarets <HI>alias</HI> Raven <HI>in the County of</HI> Wexford, <HI>Clerk.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 50.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That one <HI>Piers Synnot</HI> of <HI>Ballyvodogg</HI> in the said County, and his sonne <HI>David,</HI> and other their complices before this Rebellion burst out, did dispossesse this Deponent of his Goods and Church livings, into which he was long since invested by His Majesties presentati∣on, for which abuse this Deponent impleaded some of them in this last Parliament at <HI>Dublin,</HI> and a little before the beginning of this said Rebellion, he shewed the said <HI>David</HI> an Order from the said Parliament, for this Deponents quiet enjoying his said Church Livings, and restitution of the profits thereof, by them wrongfully detained, to which the said <HI>David Synnot</HI> answered, That he cared not for that and that it was no Parliament, but meet him at <HI>Dublin</HI> in <HI>Michaelmas-</HI>Term next and question him if he durst, for then they would have a Parliament of their own, in which Parliament he said, the Deponent durst not complain, or words to that effect.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Edward Taylor.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>23. <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram nobis,</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Nathaniel Higginson <HI>of the Castle of</HI> Knock∣ballymore <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>Gentleman.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 51.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That the Rebels then said, that they had a Commission, or Broad-Seal from the King for what they did, and that when they the said Rebels had vanquished, or over runne this Kingdom, they would go over into <HI>England,</HI> where they would have the assistance of <HI>Spain</HI> and <HI>France,</HI> for over running the same.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Nath. Higginson.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>7. <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Anne Marshall <HI>of</HI> Castle-Waterhouse <HI>in the</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 52.</NOTE> <HI>County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>Widdow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That some of the Rebels, most cruelly murthered <HI>VVilliam Marshall,</HI>
<PB N="57" REF="33"/>
husband unto this Deponent, giving him sixe severall mortall wounds, then said, that the Scots were at that time sent to leave never a drop of English bloud in <HI>England,</HI> and that the Irish now had authority, and command from the King, to leave never a drop of English bloud in <HI>Ireland.</HI></P>
<P>And further deposeth, That the common speech of the said Rebels was, that they were the Queens souldiers.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Anne Marshall.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE>3. <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Jathniell Mawe <HI>of</HI> Ferringrin <HI>in the County of</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 53.</NOTE> Fermanagh, <HI>Gentleman.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That he heard some of the Rebellious Irish company say, that there should not be one English man, Woman, or Childe, left within this King∣dom, and that they had the Kings Broad-Seal for what they did.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Iathniell Mawe.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 3. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVill. Aldrich.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Richard Cleybrook <HI>of</HI> Ballyellis <HI>in the County</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 54.</NOTE> <HI>of</HI> Wexford <HI>Farmer.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, desposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That he heard <HI>Luke Toole</HI> say, that he intended soon after to march to <HI>Killeothery,</HI> and take it, and afterwards to come to <HI>Dublin,</HI> and take the Castle there, and that he would not leave an English Man, nor English Woman in the Kingdom, but they all should be banished, and that he would not leave any English beast a live, nor any of the breed of them.</P>
<P>He saith also, That he heard the said <HI>Luke Toole</HI> say, that he would have his own Religion setled in this Kingdom, And that he would pull the Lord <HI>Parsons</HI> Hat from his Head.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Richard ▪ Cleybrook</HI> his mark.</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Coram me. Ia. VVare</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="58" REF="34"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Margaret Farmeny, <HI>and</HI> Margaret Leadly, <HI>VViddows, both of</HI> Acrashaniey, <HI>in the Parish of</HI> Clowish, <HI>and County of</HI> Fermanagh.</HEAD>
<P>THese Deponents duely sworne <HI>inter alia,</HI> depose, That on the <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 55.</NOTE> 23 day of <HI>October</HI> last, the Rebells in that County, to the num∣ber of an hundred, or thereabouts, robbed the Deponents of their goods and chattells, and bound their hands behinde them, urging them to confesse money. And that the said Rebells bound one of the Deponents husbands, and led, and dragged him up and down in a rope, and cut his throat in her own sight with a Skean, having first knockt him down, and stript him. And at the same time mur∣thered 14 persons more, all English Protestants; the said Rebells then alleadging, That they had the Kings broad Seal to strip and starve all the English, and that they were his souldiers. And as the Deponents fled for succour towards <HI>Dublin,</HI> they were strip∣ped on the way by the Irish seven times in one day, and left stark naked, being aged women of 75 yeers old: and the Rebells that saw the Deponents naked, bid them go and look for their God, and let him give them clothes.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>3 <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Henry Fisher <HI>of</HI> Powerscourt, <HI>in the County of</HI> Wicklow.</HEAD>
<P>THis examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That <HI>Luke</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 56.</NOTE> <HI>Toole,</HI> chief of the Rebells in those parts, said, That there was landed at <HI>Wexford</HI> nineteen thousand of the Spanish enemy: where∣upon they leaped and danced for joy.</P>
<P>And this Examinate further deposeth, That <HI>Bryan Linch</HI> of <HI>Powerscourt,</HI> revolted and fell from the protestant Religion, to Masse; and the said <HI>Linch,</HI> with severall other Rebells, entered the parish Church of <HI>Powerscourt,</HI> called <HI>Staggonnell,</HI> and burnt up pues, pulpits, chests, and Bibles belonging to the said Church, with ex∣treme violence and triumph, and expression of hatred to Religion:
<PB N="59" REF="34"/>
And this convert <HI>Linch</HI> strongly laboured to have this Deponent hanged.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Hon. Fisher.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 25. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVill. Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Adam Clover <HI>of</HI> Slonosy, <HI>in the County of</HI> Cavan.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That this De∣ponent and his company that were robbed, observed, That 30 <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 57.</NOTE> persons, or thereabouts, were then most barbarously murthered and slain out-right; and about 150 more persons cruelly wounded, so that traces of blood issuing from their wounds, lay upon the high way for 12 miles together, and many very young children were left and perished by the way, to the number of 60, or thereabouts, be∣cause the cruell pursuit of the Rebells was such, that their pa∣rents and friends could not carry them further. And further saith, that some of the Rebels vowed, That if any digged graves wherein to bury the dead children, they should be buried therin themselves; so the poor people left the most of them unburyed, exposed to ravenous beasts and fowl, and some few their parents carried a great way to bury them, after they were dead, and some were hid in bush∣es, that the Rebells should not finde them. And this Deponent fur∣ther saith, That he saw upon the high-way a woman left by the Re∣bells stripped to her smock, set upon by three women, and some children, being Irish, who miserably rent and tore the said poor English woman, and stripped her of her smock in a bitter Frost and Snow, so that she fell in labour in their hands and presence, and both she and her childe miserably died there.</P>
<P>And this Examinate further deposeth, That <HI>Iames ô Rely</HI> of, or neer to the Parish of <HI>Ballyheys,</HI> Yeoman, and <HI>Hugh Brady,</HI> of, or neer the parish of <HI>Ʋrnagh,</HI> and divers others of the Rebells, did then often take into their hands the Protestant Bibles, and wetting them in the dirty water, did five or sixe severall times dash the same on the face of this Deponent and other protestants, saying, Come, I know you love a good lesson, here is a most excellent one for you, and come to morrow, and you shall have as good a sermon as this; and used other scornfull and disgracefull words unto them.</P>
<P><PB N="60" REF="35"/>
And further saith, That one <HI>Owen Brady,</HI> of the parish of <HI>Ar∣magh,</HI> Gent. being one of the principall Guard to <HI>Philip mae Hugh mac Shane ô Rely,</HI> did take divers protestants (as they went by their Court of Guard to the Church) by the hair of the head, and in other cruell manner, and dragging them into the Church, there stripped, robbed, whipped, and most cruelly used them, saying, If you come tomorrow, you shall hear the like Sermon; or to that effect: with other scornfull and opprobrious words.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE>Ian. 4. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Randall Adams.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The mark of</HI> Adam Glover.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Elizabeth Tayler, <HI>wife of</HI> Iohn Tayler <HI>of the</HI> Newtowne, <HI>alias</HI> Castlecool, <HI>in the Parish of</HI> Drumuly, <HI>and balf-Barony of the Coole and County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>weaver.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duely sworn, deposeth, That <HI>(inter alia)</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 58.</NOTE> she and her said husband, with the rest of their neighbours, fled for the more safety of their lives, into the Church of the <HI>Newtown,</HI> being a fair Church, new built by the inhabitants of that parish, and there remained untill the Munday following, being the 25 of <HI>October</HI> last, when about ten of the clock in the forenoon Captain <HI>Rory mac Quire,</HI> brother to the Lord <HI>Magwire,</HI> where they so were, came, accompanied with a great multitude of Irish, to the number of 1000 persons, and upwards; which they not being able to resist, upon his faithfull promises that they should quietly enjoy their own, and receive no harm, they let him and his company into the said Church; wherein to he had no sooner entred, but in contempt of God and his sacred Word, he went up into the Pulpit, and took down the English Bible that was there, and rent and tore the same in pieces, and he and his company trampled the same un∣der their feet; and then perfidiously fell upon the English, and rifled and stript them naked, and turned them out of the town, and fired and burnt the same down.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Eliz▪ Tayler her mark.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE><HI>Ian.</HI> 8. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="61" REF="35"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Edward Slack <HI>of</HI> Gurteen, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fer∣managh, <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 59.</NOTE> <HI>Clerk.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THe Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That on the 24 of <HI>October</HI> last, the Rebells in the County of <HI>Fermanagh</HI> aforesaid, took his Bible, opened it, and laying the open side of it in a puddle of water, leapt and trampled upon it, saying, A plague on't, this Bible hath bred all the quarrell, and they hoped that within three weeks, all the Bibles in <HI>Ireland</HI> should be used as that was, or worse; and that none should be left in the Kingdom; and also that the said Rebels burnt this Deponents house, and after some other Rebels cut and wounded him twice in the head.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Edw. Slack.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Deposed before us,</HI> <DATE>4. <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Jones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVill. Aldrich.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Edward Dean <HI>late of</HI> Oghram <HI>in the County of</HI> Wicklow <HI>Tanner.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 60.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That the Irish Rebels made Proclamation, That all English men and women, that did not depart the Country within twenty four houres, should be hanged drawn and quartered, and that the Irish houses, that kept any of the English children should be burned.</P>
<P>And further saith, That the said Rebels burned two Protestant Bibles, and then said, that it was hell fire that burnt.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Edw. Dean.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>7. <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram nobis.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Watson.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Katherine Bellew <HI>alias</HI> Bedlew, <HI>late of</HI> Blit∣tock <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 61.</NOTE> <HI>in the County of</HI> Monaghan, <HI>Widdow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duely sworn <HI>(inter alia)</HI> deposeth, That one Mistresse <HI>Elcock,</HI> who being in Child-bed, was neverthe∣lesse carryed away to prison, together with the Lady <HI>Blaney,</HI> and her seven children.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>The mark of the said Katherine.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jurat.</HI> <DATE>5. <HI>Febr.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>coram nobis.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>VVill. Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="62" REF="36"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> John Wisedome <HI>of</HI> Ardmagh <HI>Parish, Clerk of the</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 62.</NOTE> <HI>Cathedrall there.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That at <HI>Lough∣gall</HI> in the County of <HI>Ardmagh,</HI> the Engilsh being promised a safe conduct by the Rebels, from garrison to garrison, till they came to the next Haven, and there to take shipping for their own Coun∣try, by the way some of them were murthered, <HI>viz.</HI> Master <HI>Willi∣am Fullerton,</HI> Parson of <HI>Loughgall,</HI> and two or three others, as the Deponent heard, the rest which they found at <HI>Loughgall,</HI> and about the Countrey there, to the number of eightscore persons, which they drowned at <HI>Port a Down</HI> Bridge, as the Deponent is informed by one <HI>William Pitchfork</HI> that was present at their suffering, but escaped himself, being begged by an Irish Rebell to be his servant, And about the same time, they fired many in one house neer <HI>Ardmagh.</HI></P>
<P>And this Deponent further saith, That Master <HI>Roger Holland</HI> related to him, that he was told by one <HI>John Babe</HI> an Owner of a Boat in <HI>Carlingford,</HI> That Mistris <HI>Holland</HI> was hanged at <HI>Carling∣ford,</HI> and delivered of a childe while hanging.</P>
<P>And further this Examinate saith, That he was credibly infor∣med by Master <HI>Franklin</HI> of <HI>Dublin,</HI> who came part of the way towards <HI>Dublin</HI> in the Deponents company, That at the <HI>Newry</HI> a man was carryed out, and so wounded, that he was laid for dead, but after recovering, he was again set upon, and murthered, and his wife also having her belly ript up, and two children fell out.</P>
<P>And the Examinate further saith, That at the <HI>Corr</HI> in the Coun∣ty of <HI>Armagh,</HI> there were drowned at once one hundred and twenty persons, men, women, and children, which the Deponent heard from Master <HI>Holland</HI> aforesaid.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>John VVisedome.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>8. <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram nobis.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Philip Taylor <HI>late of</HI> Port a-Down <HI>in the County of</HI> Armagh, <HI>Husbandman.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 63.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworne, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> That about the 24. of <HI>October</HI> he was taken prisoner at <HI>Port a-Down</HI> afore∣said
<PB N="63" REF="36"/>
by <HI>Toole mac Cann</HI> now of <HI>Port a Down</HI> Gentleman, a notori∣ous Rebell, and a Commander of a great number of Rebels, to∣gether with those Rebels, his souldiers to the number of an hundred persons, or thereabouts; at which time the Rebels first took the Castle and victualled it, then they assaulted and pillaged the Town, and burnt all the houses on the further side of the water: and then the said Rebels drowned a great number of English Pro∣testants, of men, women, and children in this Deponents sight, some with their hands tyed on their backs.</P>
<P>And this Deponent further saith, That the number of them that were drowned then, amounted to an hundred ninety and sixe Persons, as this Deponent hath been credibly informed, And the same Rebels then also threatned to shoot to death one Master <HI>Tiffin</HI> a zealous Protestant Minister there, and discharged a peece at him accordingly, but as it pleased God, they mist him, and at length he escaped from them.</P>
<P>And the Deponent further saith, That the said Rebels kept this Deponent in prison at <HI>Port a-Down</HI> aforesaid, for the space of seven weeks, and set a horse lock upon his leg, but at length he got a passe from the said <HI>Toole mac Cann,</HI> and so got away from them: But whilest he stayed there, many poor Protestants were by the Rebels murthered in severall places about <HI>Loughgall.</HI> And they also that time stript of the cloaths of one Master <HI>Iones</HI> a Minister at <HI>Segoe</HI> neer <HI>Port a-Down</HI> aforesaid, who afterwards escaped from them to the Town of <HI>Lisnegarvey.</HI></P>
<P>And the Deponent further saith, That he hath credibly heard, that one Master <HI>Fullerton</HI> a Minister, and another in his company were also murthered by the Rebels, before the drowning of the Protestants aforesaid, and that the Rebels aforesaid killed a Dyers wife of <HI>Rossetrever</HI> at <HI>Newry,</HI> and ript up her belly, she being with childe of two childrrn, and threw her and the children into a ditch, and this Deponent drove a Sow away that was eating one of the children.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Sig: Philip Taylor.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>8. <HI>Febr.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>William Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Watson.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="64" REF="37"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> John Mandefield <HI>late of</HI> Miltown <HI>in the Coun∣ty of</HI> Dublin, <HI>Barber Chirurgeon.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 64.</NOTE></HEAD>
<P>THe Deponent being duly sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That some of the Rebels in that County did strike his Wife, and stab her with a Skean <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n the breast, when she had a young childe sucking on her, which wound this Deponent being a Chirurgeon with much difficulty healed.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Iohn Mandefield.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>3. <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram nobis.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Will. Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Margaret Stoaks, <HI>the wife of</HI> Hugh Stoaks <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 65.</NOTE> <HI>late of</HI> Clonkelly <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh.</HEAD>
<P>THe said Deponent being duely sworn, <HI>inter alia</HI> deposeth, That whilest she was in the said County, she heard credibly among the Irish, and observed by their discourses one with another, That the Castle of <HI>Lissegoal</HI> neer <HI>Eniskillin</HI> (which belonged to the Lord <HI>Hastings;</HI> and wherein one Master <HI>Segrave</HI> dwelt, was burned by the Rebels, with all the English and Scots that were therein, which were very many; and that almost all the English and Scots that dwelt in <HI>Mageryboy,</HI> were likewise killed and rob∣bed by the Rebels, and that there was a woman, who when the said Castle was a fire, let down through a Window her young childe whom she gave suck unto, and after leapt out of the Window her∣self, which the Rebels observing, presently killed the said woman, and the next morning finding the young childe alive, sucking the dead mothers breast, they cruelly murthered the childe.</P>
<P>This Deponent further saith, That as she was coming on the way to <HI>Dublin</HI> at <HI>Ballybayes,</HI> she heard for certain, that handicrafts∣men and tradesmen, and others of the English that were remaining at <HI>Belturbart,</HI> were killed and murthered by the Rebels, about the last of <HI>Ianuary</HI> last past; and the Rebels hanged the men, and drowned the women and children.</P>
<P>The Deponent further saith, That when the Rebels, or any of them had killed any English man in the Country, many others of them would come one after another, and every of them would in most cruell manner, stab, wound, and out him, and almost mangle
<PB N="65" REF="37"/>
him, and to shew their further malice, would not suffer, nor per∣mit any to bury them, but would have them to lye naked for the dogs, beasts, and fowles of the aire to devoure them.</P>
<P>The Deponent further saith, When they had so killed the Eng∣lish, they would reckon up and accompt the number of them, and in rejoycing and boasting manner would often say, That they had made the divell beholding to them in sending so many souls to him to hell.</P>
<P>The Deponent likewise saith, <HI>inter alia,</HI> That as she was coming towards <HI>Dublin</HI> about <HI>Dunshaghlin,</HI> the Rebels that were in Garrison there, said unto her, That if they thought she and her children, had but one drop of English bloud in them, they would kill both her and her children.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Margaret Stoakes.</SIGNED>
<SIGNED>Jurat. coram, Gerrardo Louther.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Mary Woods <HI>late of the Town and County of</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 66.</NOTE> Kildare, <HI>Widdow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis examinate being duly sworn and examined, <HI>inter alia,</HI> saith That since the beginning of this present rebellion, she hath been stripped and robbed of her goods by the Rebels in those parts, since which time the bodies of severall deceased Protestants buried in the Church there, were taken up, and thrown away into filthy places, exposed to be devoured of dogs, and other beasts, which was done partly by the commandement or direction of <HI>James Dempsie</HI> a priest, <HI>Peter Sarsfield, Thomas fitz Gerald, Iames Flatis∣bury,</HI> and <HI>Iohn Leighe,</HI> Esquires, and others, whom she knoweth not.</P>
<P>And further saith, That the said Rebels and others about that Town, did of late first strip her husband of cloaths, and after stabbed him, and after that shot him, and last of all most barba∣rously buried him alive, where he remained with earth upon him above an hour before the breath went from him.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Sig: prae: Anne VVoods.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>23. <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram nobis,</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Joh. VVatson,</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="66" REF="38"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Thomas Huetson <HI>of the Town and County of</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 67.</NOTE> Kildare.</HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duely sworn, and examined deposeth, That <HI>(inter alia)</HI> about a moneth, or three weeks since, one <HI>Iohn Courtis</HI> of <HI>Kildare</HI> aforesaid, Weaver, and <HI>Martin Courtis</HI> his sonne, <HI>Walter White</HI> of the same labourer, <HI>Bondventure Berry</HI> of the same own, the reputed son of <HI>William Berry</HI> of the same town, a popish Priest, and <HI>Thomas Berry</HI> of <HI>Kildare</HI> aforesaid, neer kinsman to the said Priest, and divers other Rebells of the Irish, did in the Cathedrall Church of <HI>K<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ldare</HI> aforesaid, dig the graves of <HI>Dominick Huetson,</HI> this Deponents brother, who had bin buried about twenty moneths before; and <HI>Christian Huetson</HI> the Deponents Grandmo∣ther, who had bin buried about a week before, and took their Corps out of the same Graves, and Church, and laid them both in a hole which they digged up for that purpose, within a Garden, out of the walls of the Churchyard; which was done by the command or procurement of <HI>Rosse mac Geoghegan</HI> titular Bishop of <HI>Kildare, Iames Dempsie</HI> the popish Vicar generall there, the foresaid <HI>William Berry</HI> Priest, <HI>Dominick Dempsie</HI> guardian to the Fryars there, <HI>Iames Flanagan</HI> a Fryar, <HI>Bryan ô Gormooley</HI> a Fryar, and other Fryars, whose names he now remembreth not.</P>
<P>And the Deponent also saith, That the said <HI>Berry</HI> the Priest brought this Deponent before the said Titular Bishop, and infor∣med him, that the Deponent was looking in at the Church Win∣dow when the Corps of his said Brother, and Grandmother were taking up, and that he there writ down the names of those parties that so took them up, and so desired to know what must be done with this Deponent; Who answered, That if he found that report to be true, or that this Deponent should do any thing against their Catholike cause, he would imprison and hang him.</P>
<P>And this Deponent further saith, That the parties above named with divers others of the Town of <HI>Kildare,</HI> said, that they could not sanctifie, nor hallow the said Church of <HI>Kildare,</HI> untill the Heretikes bones were removed out of it.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thomas Huetson.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>15. <HI>Feb.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVilliam Aldrich.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="67" REF="38"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Rebecca Collis, <HI>late of the Town and County of</HI> Kildare.</HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duly sworn and examined, deposeth, That <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 68.</NOTE> since the beginning of this Rebellion, she and her husband have been robbed and despoiled of their goods by the Rebells in those parts. And further saith, That about <HI>Christmas</HI> last, the titular Bishop of <HI>Kildare,</HI> the <HI>Guardian,</HI> and other priests and Friars there, did take away the Chapter-Chest belonging to the Cathedrall Church of <HI>Kildare,</HI> and did cause the same to be carryed to the house of <HI>Peter Sarsfeild</HI> of <HI>Tully</HI> Esquire. And shortly after a consultation had amongst the said <HI>Peter Sarsfeild, James Flatishury, Thomas Fitz-Gerald, Iohn Leigh,</HI> Esquires, <HI>Iames Dempsie,</HI> Vicar generall to the said Titular Bishop; By whose di∣rections or command, the dead bodies of divers deceased Protestants were digged out of the Church of <HI>Kildare,</HI> and cast into a filthy ditch, to be devoured by beasts and dogs.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>23 <HI>Febr.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>coram nobis.</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Rebecca Collis.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Will. Aldrich.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Margaret Parkin <HI>of</HI> Newtowne, <HI>in the County of</HI> Fermanagh, <HI>widdow.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duely sworn and examined, deposeth <HI>inter</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 69.</NOTE> <HI>alia,</HI> That by the information of divers credible persons, she understood that the Rebells boyled a young childe to death in a great Ketle, in the Church at <HI>Newtown</HI> aforesaid.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>29 <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Margaret Parkin.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Aldrich.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Elizabeth Bairsee <HI>of</HI> Newtown, <HI>in the County of</HI> nagh.</HEAD>
<P>THe Deponent being duely sworn, <HI>(inter alia)</HI> deposeth, That <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 70.</NOTE> she was credibly informed by a great number of people of <HI>Newtown</HI> aforesaid, That about the 23 of <HI>October</HI> last, or since, the Rebells did boyl a childe of one <HI>Iohn Strettons,</HI> about 12 yeers old, to death.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>19. <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Elizabeth Bairsee.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="68" REF="39"/>
<HEAD><HI>The examination of</HI> Henry Boyne <HI>late of</HI> Mullaghtean <HI>in the County of</HI> Tyrone, <HI>Clerke.</HI></HEAD>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 71.</NOTE> THis Deponent being duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> And further saith, That as he was come to his own house, he found there an Irish woman that was come (out of good will) from <HI>Donaghmore</HI> about sixe miles distant from his said house, to tell the Deponents wife, That it were best for the Deponent to be gone, least he might be killed (for as the said wo∣man related) the Rebels there had cut of one Master <HI>Madders</HI> head a Minister, and that there chief malice was against Church-men.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Hen. Boyne.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>16. <HI>Febr.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Sterne.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Elizabeth Trafford, <HI>late wife of</HI> Thomas Traf∣ford, <HI>late Vicar of</HI> Ballincormock <HI>in the County of</HI> Longford, <HI>Clerk.</HI></HEAD>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 72.</NOTE> THis Deponent being duely sworn, deposeth <HI>(inter alia,)</HI> That since the beginning of this rebellion, the Rebels in those parts robbed and stript her, and her said husband of all their goods and cloaths: And then one of the Rebels called <HI>Iohn Raynolds,</HI> stabbed her husband with a sword, whereof he lay languishing three houres, and then the Rebells stabbed him into the throat, and wounded him in the head, so that he dyed, and then turned her and her poor children naked away, exposed to hunger and cold. And at the same time, The said Rebels or some of them, stabbed and killed one <HI>Francis Marshall</HI> Merchant, <HI>Matthew Baker</HI> Vintner, <HI>Iohn Smith, Thomas Allen, Iohn</HI> a Butcher, and another who was a Sadler, another that was a Millner, and by report divers others.</P>
<P>And further deposeth, That the Rebels said, that it was the Kings pleasure, that all the English should be banished, and loose their goods, because the Queens Priest was hanged before her face.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Iur.</HI> <DATE>8. <HI>Ian.</HI> 1641.</DATE> <HI>Coram,</HI></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Henry Iones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn VVatson.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Eliz. Trafford.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="69" REF="39"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Margery Sharp, <HI>late wife to</HI> John Sharp <HI>of Kells, in the County and Diocesse of</HI> Meath, <HI>Minister of Gods Word.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duely sworn and examined, deposed <HI>inter alia,</HI> That And <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 73.</NOTE> further deposeth, That her said husband was by the Rebells in those parts wounded, that he was deprived of his life; but in such a blessed manner, that God gave him strength to pray unto him, and to expresse himself; and being ready to die, another company of Irish Rebells came and wilfully murthered him in the same place where they found him, being coming towards <HI>Dublin</HI> to seek for refuge: And after breath was departed from him, this Deponent sought to have him buryed in Christian Buryall, which the Por∣treiffe or Suffraigne of the <HI>Navan</HI> would not admit, but sent to cause the Grave to be made in the same place where he was mur∣thered. And further saith, That before her said husband was mur∣thered, he carryed away, for fear of the Rebells, a good number of his best Divinity Books, and divers Bonds, Specialties, and Wri∣tings. And she further saith, That the souldiers under the com∣mand of the Rebell Capt. <HI>ô Rely</HI> meeting with him, stripped him of all his clothes, and inforced him, being naked, to trample and tread upon his said Books and papers in the water to spoil them, and then the said Rebells threw them away, and tossed many of them in the winde.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Sign. praed. Margery.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>29 <HI>Jan.</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Reynold Griffith, <HI>late of</HI> Tandergee, <HI>in the County of</HI> Armagh.</HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia.</HI> And further saith<SUP>1</SUP>, That neer the <HI>Newry</HI> severall Rebells took <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 74.</NOTE> from this Deponents wife a childe of hers of 14 yeers of age, and drowned it in a bog or pit, and held it down before her face with a sword whilest the said childe was a drowning.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Reynold Griffith, and Eliz. his wife.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE><HI>Jan.</HI> 6. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<PB N="70" REF="40"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Charles Campbell, <HI>late of</HI> Shamulloghe, <HI>in the Parish of</HI> Clonnlsse, <HI>in the County of</HI> Monaghan, <HI>Gentleman.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duely sworn and examined, deposeth <HI>in∣ter alia,</HI> That the said Deponent likewise, whilest he <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 75.</NOTE> was amongst the Rebells, observed these severall passages ensuing, <HI>viz.</HI> First, the burning of the Castle of <HI>Lisgowle,</HI> in the County of <HI>Fermanagb,</HI> containing the number of sevenscore persons, men, women and children, whereof none escaped death, except one man who was taken prisoner; which cruelty severall of the <HI>mac Mahons,</HI> and <HI>mac Guires</HI> did confesse to this Deponent; one <HI>Casse∣dy</HI> a Frier, being the chief instrument thereof. Another priest al∣so, one <HI>Philip mac Enany</HI> told this Deponent, that it was no sinne to kill all the Protestants, for that they were all damned already. And the said Deponent was an ocular witnesse of the hanging and killing of thirty persons in one day, at <HI>Clonnisse,</HI> by <HI>Patrickoge mac Rosse mac Guire, Rory mac Mahon, Patrick mac Aperson ô Con∣nelly,</HI> and severall others, the said Deponent being likewise upon the Ladder, with a Wyth about his neck, ready to be cast off, but delivered by the intercession of the said <HI>Rory mac Mahon</HI> and his wife: Afterwards this Deponent, with <HI>Robert Aldrich,</HI> and <HI>Mat∣thew Brown,</HI> being then prisoners with the said Deponent, were sent unto the siege of <HI>Drogheda,</HI> by Captain <HI>Rory mac Mahon</HI> his wife, conducted by an hundred Rebells, or thereabouts; where they remained for the space of three weeks, untill this Deponents escape: In which time aforesaid, one <HI>Ever mac Mahon,</HI> brother to Captain <HI>Redmond mac Mahon,</HI> told this Deponent, That there was not a Romane Catholique in <HI>Ireland,</HI> that could dispend ten pounds <HI>per an.</HI> but was accessory to the rebellious plot. This De∣ponent likewise heard severall of the <HI>mac Mahans</HI> affirm, That the Earl of <HI>Antrim</HI> was also guilty of the said plot. And this Depo∣nent was credibly informed, that with Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neal</HI> were con∣versant the Lord of <HI>Gurmanston,</HI> the Lord <HI>Nettervyle,</HI> the Lord <HI>Lowth,</HI> with many other the chief Gentry of the <HI>Pale;</HI> and did see the Lord of <HI>Dunsany</HI> frequent the said Rebells company; and that the Countyes of <HI>Meath</HI> and <HI>Lowth</HI> did furnish the Rebells
<PB N="71" REF="40"/>
there, with all sorts of Victualls, and such necessaries.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Cb: Campbell.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Jur.</HI> <DATE>2 <HI>Martii,</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>John Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>VVilliam Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Alexander Creigchton, <HI>late of</HI> Glasloghe, <HI>in the County of</HI> Monaghan, <HI>Gent.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Deponent being duely sworn and examined <HI>(inter alia)</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 76.</NOTE> deposeth. And further saith, That when he this Depo∣nent was so robbed by the Rebells, they imprisoned him and his brother in law, <HI>Andrew Lesk, Alexander Bailie, James Anderson, Iohn Mewrhead</HI> his son, <HI>Alexander Ballengall,</HI> and his son <HI>VVilliam,</HI> and kept them there in <HI>Glaslock</HI> Castle for 14 dayes, or thereabouts, in great misery, neither suffering their wives or friends to come and bring them relief: From thence the Rebells sent them to the Gaole of <HI>Monaghan</HI> for 14 dayes more, where they were in no lesser misery than before: From thence they were sent back to <HI>Glaslock</HI> aforesaid, and there <HI>Art mac Bryan ô Samogh mac Maghan,</HI> did gather all the whole British prisoners, aswell those afore-na∣med, as others, to the number of 22 or thereabouts, and sent them to <HI>Corbridge:</HI> But in their going, another Company, by the directi∣on of the said <HI>Art mac Bryan,</HI> way-layd them, and slew 16 of them, and the next morning murthered 46 more English at <HI>Cor∣bridge</HI> aforesaid; where this Deponent escaping with his life, was admitted to go to Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neal,</HI> who gave him a Protection for himself, his wife, and childe. And then this Deponent heard the said Sir <HI>Phelim</HI> say, That he would make no man account for what he did, And that he had his Majesties Commission for what he did under the great Seal of <HI>England:</HI> And being asked who did put Master <HI>Richard Blany,</HI> Senescall to the Lord <HI>Blany,</HI> and one of the Knights of the Shire to death, because it was reported that one <HI>Art mac Bryan ô Samagh mac Maghan</HI> put him to death; He answered, Let not that Gentleman be blamed, for my hand signed the Warrant for his hanging, for the persecuring of my cousen <HI>ô Rely.</HI> And further saith, That there were killed by the name or Sept of the <HI>ô Hughes,</HI> 12 Families of men, women, and children of English and Scotish protestants; and that <HI>Edmond
<PB N="72" REF="41"/>
Boy ô Hugh,</HI> Foster-brother to the said Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neal,</HI> did at <HI>Ki∣nard,</HI> at the entry of the said Sir <HI>Phelims</HI> gate, shoot to death with a brace of Bullers, behinde his back, the Lord <HI>Cawlfeild:</HI> And that night after killed seven Families of English men, women, and children that lived on the Land of the said Sir <HI>Phelim.</HI> And as this Deponent hath heard, there were above twenty Families slain betwixt <HI>Kinnard</HI> and <HI>Armagh</HI> by the Rebells: And after the repulse given at <HI>Lisnegarvy, Shane oge mac Canna,</HI> and a Company of Rebells under his command, marched thorow all the Ba∣rony of <HI>Trough,</HI> in the County of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> and murthered a great number of Brittish protestants; amongst others, Ensigne <HI>Peirce,</HI> Gentleman, <HI>Ambrose Blany,</HI> Gentleman, <HI>William Chal∣lengwood,</HI> Gentleman, and <HI>William</HI> his sonne; <HI>David Dray∣nan,</HI> Gentleman, <HI>Andrew Carr,</HI> Weaver, <HI>John Lasley,</HI> Labourer, and his wife.</P>
<P>And this Deponent heard it credibly reported amongst the Rebells at <HI>Glaslogh</HI> aforesaid, That <HI>Hugh mac ô Degan mac Guire,</HI> a priest, had done a most meritorious act in the parish of <HI>Glanally,</HI> and County of <HI>Fermanagh,</HI> in drawing betwixt 40 or 50 of the English and Scottish there to reconciliation with the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> and after giving them the Sacrament, demanded of them whether Christs Body was really in the Sacrament or no; and they said, Yea. And that he demanded of them further, Whether they held the Pope to be supreme Head of the Church, they like∣wise answered he was; And that thereupon he presently told them they were in a good faith: and for fear they should fall from it, and turn hereticks, he and the rest that were with him, cut all their throats.</P>
<P>And this Deponent further saith, That the wife of Master <HI>Luke Ward</HI> told him, That the Rebells had forced her husband to be drunk in drinking of his part of 3<SUP>s</SUP> in drink; and that they when he was so drunk, hanged him: And she shewed this Depo∣nent the place where he was executed.</P>
<P>And saith also, That the Rebells pulled up, and took away the <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in the Church of <HI>Monaghan</HI> up to the Quire, and carried them <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the Goal, and made fires with them for the Friers; And that the <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ls did at <HI>Glaslock</HI> aforesaid, burn two or three Bibles or Ser∣<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> Books: And heard them say, they would never lay down
<PB N="73" REF="41"/>
arms, till their Church were put into its due place, and that all the plantation lands were given to the right owners; and that if they had once gotten the City of <HI>Dublin</HI> taken, they would hold it no rebellion to follow the Kings sword, in doing any act they pleas∣ed: And this Deponent heard <HI>Brian ô Hugh,</HI> Priest to the said <HI>Phe∣lim ô Neale</HI> say, That they had fifteen hundred thousand of the Irish bloud, to maintain their wars begun: And the said <HI>Alexander</HI> further deposeth, That about the beginning of <HI>Feb.</HI> last, one <HI>Ensigne William Pew</HI> of <HI>Glaslogh</HI> in the County of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> being strip∣ped, robbed, and expulsed by the Rebels, was seven times in one day taken up and hanged on a tree, and taken down again for dead every time by <HI>Patrick Duff, Mac Hugh, Mac Rosse,</HI> a Captain of the Rebels near <HI>Monaghan:</HI> which cruelty was practised by the instigation of <HI>Patrick Mother mac Wade,</HI> who had informed, that the said <HI>William Pew</HI> had monies; the confession and knowledge whereof was intended to be extracted by the foresaid hard usage.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Iur. primo Martii,</HI> <DATE>1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Alexander Creichton.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iohn Sterne.</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> Roger Holland <HI>of</HI> Glaslogh, <HI>in the County of</HI> Monaghan.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duly sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That during his imprisonment, he was credibly informed, that there were <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 77.</NOTE> 38 persons, men, women, and children drown'd, being thrown over into the river of <HI>Corr-</HI>bridge in the County of <HI>Armagh;</HI> and also saith, That Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neale,</HI> under pretence of sending a Convoy with many of the English of <HI>Loghgall,</HI> and thereabouts, the said Convoy did drown at the Bridge of <HI>Pontie-Down,</HI> 68 persons, as he is credibly informed: And likewise, that he did see 14 or 15 kill'd by the Irish as he passed in the country.</P>
<P>And further saith, That Friar <HI>Malone,</HI> when this Examinate arrived at <HI>Skerries,</HI> that his Company shot one shot at the Vessel; and that the said Company asked whether we had a Passe or not, which we told them we had; whereupon they replyed, That if we had not, we should all suffer: But so soon as we shewed them our Passe, they made much of us, &amp; told us that we should take no hurt; which they performed the next day, being Christmas-day.</P>
<P>The said Friar took a boat, to go to the boat to see whether
<PB N="76" REF="42"/>
there were a leak in our Vessell or not, and searching for the leak, he found some Bibles, and other Prayer-Books, which said Books he cast into the fire, and wished that he had all the Bibles in Chri∣stendom, and he would serve them all so, and demanding of him what was the reason, he answered, That it was fitting for every man to have the Bible by rote, and not to misinstruct them which should have it by rote: and the said <HI>Roger</HI> sitting by him alone, de∣manded of him, what might be the reason of their going out in such manner, as in killing and robbing the English, and perswa∣ding him to make peace; he replyed, unlesse all men that had estates lost, by the Kings giving them unto great men, that were little worth in former times, unlesse they had their estates given under the Kings Broad-Seal, that they would never yeild; And withall, that it they had not the Duke of <HI>York</HI> for their Governour and Ruler in this Kingdom, and to be a Papist, they would never yeild as aforesaid. And further said, That they would have the whole Kingdom to themselves, and that they have been about this plot this seventeen yeers past, but never had so fit an opportunity as now they had.</P>
<P>And the said <HI>Roger</HI> saith further, That being in company with Colonell <HI>Pluncket</HI> at <HI>Newry</HI> and <HI>Carlingford,</HI> the said Colonell told the said <HI>Roger</HI> and many others, that this said plot was for these se∣venteen yeers past in plotting, and that the said Fryar <HI>Malone</HI> and himself, and one of the Lord of <HI>Trimbortons</HI> sonnes, which is a Fryer, with many others of the Nobility of the <HI>Pale,</HI> and in the North, knew it of long time, but that others of the Nobles knew not of it, but of late; but as for the rest they have known of it the space and yeers aforesaid: And that they said they would have their Religion or not any, or else that they would loose both their lives and estates, for in strength they were able enough, for he said all the Irish would not fail, but stick close to them, for they fought for God and their Country, for certain they knew that there cause was just, and that God would not see them suffer, and that they were sure of <HI>Dublin,</HI> for there was not any thing done, but that they had such friends, that they heard out of <HI>Dublin</HI> every day, and as for Sir <HI>Phelomy ô Neal</HI> he made no accompt as he said, of all <HI>Ireland</HI> to be his own, and others, for that was there intents.</P>
<P>And further saith, That at <HI>Carlingford,</HI> when the foresaid <HI>Roger</HI>
<PB N="77" REF="42"/>
was there three or four dayes, Sir <HI>Con Magenis</HI> sent his Warrant, to send away all such prisoners as came from <HI>Newry</HI> over to <HI>Green Ca∣stle;</HI> which Warrant was directed to one <HI>Jo. Babe</HI> Provost Mar∣shall, directed by Sir <HI>Con Magenis:</HI> which Provost Marshall, ac∣cording to his direction, sent them away: which prisoners were sent, for the releasing of some prisoners that were taken at <HI>Down-Patrick:</HI> but no sooner came the aforesaid prisoners unto <HI>Green-Castle,</HI> but they were all cut off: And the next day following, the said Sir <HI>Con Magenis</HI> sent a Convoy with all such prisoners as were there left; and what became of them, this Examinate cannot tell.</P>
<P>And further saith, That an owner of a Boat in <HI>Carlingford</HI> told him, that one M<SUP>ris</SUP> <HI>Holland</HI> was hang'd; and as she was hanging, was delivered of two children; and further cannot say.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Jurat: this</HI> <DATE>4 <HI>of March,</HI> 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Roger Holland.</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="examination">
<HEAD><HI>The Examination of</HI> George Cottingham, <HI>Parson of</HI> Monaghan.</HEAD>
<P>THis Examinate duely sworn, deposeth <HI>inter alia,</HI> That about <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ex.</HI> 78.</NOTE> the 30 day of <HI>October,</HI> this Examinate, with most of the Eng∣lish, was cast into the Dungeon, which was a place of that noy∣somenesse, by reason of great heaps of mens excrements, that had been there a long time, that they were almost stifled; the Dungeon was so little, and the people so many, being some fourty eight per∣sons, that they were fain to lie one upon another; so that the Ex∣aminate, after he had been some seventeen dayes, sometimes in the Dungeon, sometimes in the Goal, got such a loosenesse, with cold and hard lodging, that he was not able to go, but as he was carried betwixt men. During their continuance in this miserable restraint, no meat was allowed the prisoners by the Rebells, nei∣ther would they scarce suffer either their wives or friends to see or speak with them; but oftentimes, both in the night and day, seve∣rall of the Rebells came to the prisoners with swords, and Skeans drawn, with Pistolls cocked, to the great terrour of the prison∣ers: and some came often and scarched them; and if they found any silver, either more or lesse, they took it from them, and stripped them of their clothes, in the very Dungeon, and left
<PB N="76" REF="43"/>
many almost naked, with few or no rags to cover them: And when these prisoners were set at liberty, soon after many were murther∣ed with Skeans, some drowned, and some hanged: Master <HI>Richard Blaney,</HI> who was prisoner in another place, being bolted with Irons, was taken forth suddenly, and hanged, and cast into a kinde of a Boggie place, without Buriall, stark naked. The same day one Master <HI>Luke VVard</HI> was taken and hanged in the same Town of <HI>Monaghan;</HI> in the beginning of the night, and was never told he should die; but being taken by one <HI>Patr: oge ô Connelley,</HI> was brought into a house in Town; and there <HI>Patr:</HI> gave him worth 12<SUP>d</SUP> or more of drink, as though no hurt were intended, presently went to the back side, and called out the said <HI>Luke VVard,</HI> and with others of his company laid hold on him, and hanged him, and after threw him into a little River, where he lay naked and unburied: The next morning many of those that were let out of prison, being almost starved and famished, were murthered with Skeans, and others drowned: Master <HI>Oliver Peirce,</HI> Ensigne to the Lord <HI>Blaney,</HI> murthered with Swords and Skeans; Master <HI>John Francis, Edward Lewis, Richard Bollard,</HI> and <HI>VVilliam Iones,</HI> murthered with Skeans and Swords; and many others pursued, who escaped that night: <HI>Thomas VVest</HI> was never heard of since. A poor English-man unknown came stragling to the Towne, having escaped from some other place, was hanged.</P>
<P>Some of those that were imprisoned, were sent out of the Town of <HI>Monaghan,</HI> to <HI>Glaslough,</HI> where they had lived formerly; and there they, with others, to the number of fourty, were cast into a River at the edge of the County, men, women, and chil∣dren: In the mean time, so many as escaped were in great misery and fears, dayly hearing, that not an English man, woman, or childe should be left alive; that there was the like stirre in <HI>Eng∣land</HI> and <HI>Scotland;</HI> and that never a Protestant must be suffered to live in any of the three Kingdoms; and that the Seas wre full of Spanish and French Shipping; and that all the Irish in other parts, were coming homewards to help to subdue the English in <HI>Ireland,</HI> and then they were to be in <HI>England</HI> before <HI>May</HI> for the same purpose; and the like to be done in <HI>Scotland</HI> also. It was usually reported that none must bear rule in <HI>Ireland,</HI> but onely the
<PB N="77" REF="43"/>
Natives; and that all the Lands which were enjoyed by any of the British, must forthwith be taken from them; which was according∣ly done in all parts hereabouts.</P>
<P>It was frequently noysed and reported, That the Kings Maje∣sty was dead, or not to be had; and that there was a Crown con∣secrated for some other that should deserve it best; and when af∣terwards it was reported His Majesty was in <HI>England,</HI> it was said that Sir <HI>Phelim ô Neal</HI> was made Generall by His Majesties appointment; and that there were others that had command by the same appointment.</P>
<P>We dayly heard of most cruell murthers of prisoners on all sides of us, besides what we saw committed in our own Town: in some places neer were hanged sometimes 17, sometimes 22 at a time; as at <HI>Clownish,</HI> and <HI>Carrick mac Rosse.</HI> And within seven miles were murthered some 25 men, women, and children in the night; and every hour we expected the like usage, being often threatned that not any English should be left in <HI>Ireland.</HI> Con∣voyes were sent with many, pretending to bring prisoners safe to such places as they were desired to go, and were most pitifully murthered and drowned by the way by such as conveyed them, others were turned out without any Convoy, and so mur∣thered.</P>
<P>About six weeks since, I, my wife, and four small children, with some other English, were turned out of the Town of <HI>Mo∣naghan,</HI> about three of the Clock in the afternoon, the Drum beating, and <HI>Art Roe mac</HI> S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Patrick mac Art Moyl,</HI> who is chief Governour there, went before, and declared that we must be gone forthwith, and not suffered to return, on pain of death; when we were assured, that not past a quarter of a mile before us, there were men with Swords and with Skeans, lying in wait to mur∣ther and strip us, of which we were fully assured; but it pleased God we escaped that time, by means of one <HI>Bryan mac Hugh mac Rosse mac Mahon,</HI> about a week after we had leave to come as far as within a mile of <HI>Drogheda,</HI> called <HI>Bewley;</HI> neer unto which place are encamped many Rehels, which came from towards <HI>Monaghan,</HI> and other places of the North; at which place S<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Phe∣lim ô Neal</HI> was, where might he perceived by the Speeches of the Rebels, that they were very confident to take <HI>Drogheda,</HI> and <HI>Dublin,</HI>
<PB N="80" REF="44"/>
but during this Examinates remaining there, were driven off the Walls, which they assayed to assault with scaling-Ladders, on Sun∣day last was a sennight, in the morning before day, and many prai∣sed be God, run from the Walls, and left some of their Muskets and Pikes behinde them, as they related amongst themselves, from thence this Examinate was sent into <HI>Drogheda,</HI> and a Prisoner re∣leased thence for him, and from thence is gotten to <HI>Dublin</HI> by Sea with his Wife and four small children, neer famished and starved, being left quite destitute of all relief for the present.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>George Cottingham.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE><HI>Iura.</HI> <DATE><HI>Martij</HI> 4. 1641.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Jones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Will. Aldrich.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<P><HI>And whereas the sufferings of the loyall Subjects of this Kingdom of</HI> Ireland, <HI>do consist as in the cruelties exercised on the Persons, so in the spoiling and robbing them of their Estates, Fortunes, and Livelyhoods, whereof the said severall Commissioners, do authorize, and require a strict inquiry to be made. And whereas in the foregoing</HI> Remonstrance, <HI>Depredation of the Goods of the Subjects, is one part of the Charge laid to these Rebels, and humbly offered by the</HI> Remonstrants <HI>to be conside∣red off by the Honourable House of Commons in</HI> England.</P>
<P><HI>They the said</HI> Remonstrants <HI>and humble</HI> Petitioners, <HI>for the forti∣fying of that their</HI> Allegation, <HI>do here withall present the generall Summes of such Counties, as have answered to that particular from the</HI> 30. <HI>of</HI> December <HI>last past, untill the</HI> 8. <HI>day of</HI> March, 1641. <HI>The whole amounting unto above six hundred thirty five thousand three hundred seventy five pounds, four shillings and nine pence; the Persons thereunto appearing, being in all hitherto examined but six hundred thirty seven: whereas this by the following considerations may be readily conceived hardly to be the five hundreth part of the full losses of the whole Kingdom.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>I.</HEAD>
<P>For first, Out of the whole Province of <HI>Munster,</HI> containing these following large and rich Counties, <HI>viz. Tipperary, Limerick, Cork, Kerry</HI> and <HI>Clare,</HI> no one hath yet appeared.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="section">
<PB N="81" REF="44"/>
<HEAD>II.</HEAD>
<P>Out of the whole Province of <HI>Connaght,</HI> containing these Counties, <HI>Roscomon, Mayo, Galway, Sligoe</HI> and <HI>Leitrim,</HI> There have only eleven out of <HI>Leitrim</HI> given in their losses being—1352<SUP>l</SUP>—04<SUP>s</SUP>—08<SUP>d</SUP></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>III.</HEAD>
<P>Out of the Province of <HI>Ʋlster,</HI> these alone have appeared themselves, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>1</CELL>
<CELL>s</CELL>
<CELL>d</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL ROWS="7">Out of</CELL>
<CELL><HI>Lowth,</HI> 6. Examinates</CELL>
<CELL ROWS="7">Their losses</CELL>
<CELL>4332</CELL>
<CELL>01</CELL>
<CELL>04</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Cavan,</HI> 113. Examinates</CELL>
<CELL>47418</CELL>
<CELL>07</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Fermanagh,</HI> 94. Examinates</CELL>
<CELL>26947</CELL>
<CELL>10</CELL>
<CELL>08</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Armagh,</HI> 8. Examinates</CELL>
<CELL>03802</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>08</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Tyron,</HI> 2. Examinates</CELL>
<CELL>01667</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>London-Derry,</HI> 1. Examinate</CELL>
<CELL>01911</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Monaghan,</HI> 31. Examinates</CELL>
<CELL>36181</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
<CELL>08</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<P>None appearing out of the Counties of <HI>Down, Antrim,</HI> or <HI>Donegall.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>IV.</HEAD>
<P>Fourthly, For the Province of <HI>Leinster,</HI> the number of the Examinates is as followeth,</P>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL>1</CELL>
<CELL>s</CELL>
<CELL>d</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL ROWS="11">In the</CELL>
<CELL>County of <HI>Dublin,</HI> 72. Exam.</CELL>
<CELL ROWS="11">Their losses</CELL>
<CELL>120032</CELL>
<CELL>15</CELL>
<CELL>03</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>County of <HI>Kildare,</HI> 57. Ex.</CELL>
<CELL>098967</CELL>
<CELL>17</CELL>
<CELL>04</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>County of <HI>Wickloe,</HI> 65. Ex.</CELL>
<CELL>132457</CELL>
<CELL>14</CELL>
<CELL>02</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>County of <HI>Wexford,</HI> 38. Ex.</CELL>
<CELL>062519</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>04</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>County of <HI>Catherlagh,</HI> 16. Ex.</CELL>
<CELL>010270</CELL>
<CELL>01</CELL>
<CELL>08</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>County of <HI>Kilkenny,</HI> 5. Ex.</CELL>
<CELL>008312</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>County of <HI>Meath,</HI> 46. Exam.</CELL>
<CELL>033678</CELL>
<CELL>14</CELL>
<CELL>03</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>County of <HI>VVestmeath,</HI> 7. Ex.</CELL>
<CELL>003512</CELL>
<CELL>12</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Kings</HI> County, 9. Examinates</CELL>
<CELL>011525</CELL>
<CELL>04</CELL>
<CELL>08</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL><HI>Queens</HI> County, 14. Exam.</CELL>
<CELL>018884</CELL>
<CELL>15</CELL>
<CELL>09</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>County of <HI>Longford,</HI> 28. Ex.</CELL>
<CELL>016440</CELL>
<CELL>10</CELL>
<CELL>08</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>V.</HEAD>
<P>Fifthly, Of those Counties that have come in, one being consi∣dered with another, not the five hundred part hath appeared, there being of them,</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<LIST>
<ITEM><PB N="80" REF="45"/>
1. Many imprisoned, or besieged by the Rebels.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Many gone into <HI>England,</HI> before the beginning of this com∣motion, and since.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Multitudes murthered, and none hitherto appearing for them.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. Many thousands by reason of the danger of the wayes, not daring to appear.</ITEM>
<ITEM>5. Many being sick and weak, by reason of their sufferings, so not able to appear.</ITEM>
<ITEM>6. Many there are who (in time) purpose to give in the parti∣culars of their losses, but for the present forbear being in many respects not prepared for the doing thereof.</ITEM>
<ITEM>7. Lastly, of such as have given in their particulars, few can de∣pose to the full of their losses, wanting the help of their Papers torn from them, or of their Agents, who could in∣form them of their Estates, they being remote in the Coun∣try, and there imprisoned, or besieged, or by reason of the danger of the wayes, not daring to adventure from such places of safety, as they have betaken themselves unto, if perhaps they have not altogether perished by the hand of the enemy.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<P><HI>The same Consideration may also induce any to beleeve that of the o∣ther particulars in the said</HI> Remonstrance, <HI>either for words blasphemous against God, impious against Religion, or traiterous towards His sacred Majesty, or for Actions, wicked, cruell, or barbarous, or for discovery of the minds and intents of these conspirators, and their adherents, the least part hath been set forth in the said</HI> Remonstrance, <HI>and Examina∣tions thereunto annexed; and yet that alone is sufficient, and more then enough to set forth the miserable condition of the poor distressed Church, and miserable wasted Kingdom of</HI> Ireland.</P>
<P><HI>Of all which we the Commissioners aforesaid, do herein give up a true report attested under our respective hands this seventh of March.</HI> 1641.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><LIST>
<ITEM>Hen. Jones,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Roger Puttock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Watson,</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Sterne,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Aldrich,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Randal Adams,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hitchcock,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hen. Brereton.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<PB REF="45"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

