<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Elias redivivus: a sermon preached before the honorable House of Commons, in the parish of Saint Margarets West minster, at the publike fast, March 29, 1643. By John Lightfoote, preacher of the Gospel at Bartholomew Exchange, London.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Lightfoot, John, 1602-1675.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A88141</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing L2053</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E99_11</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R20324</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99863269</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99863269</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">115459</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A88141)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115459)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 17:E99[11])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Elias redivivus: a sermon preached before the honorable House of Commons, in the parish of Saint Margarets West minster, at the publike fast, March 29, 1643. By John Lightfoote, preacher of the Gospel at Bartholomew Exchange, London.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Lightfoot, John, 1602-1675.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 50, [2] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by R. Cotes, for Andrew Crooke, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Greene Dragon, in Pauls Church-yard,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1643.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Running title reads: A sermon preached at a fast before the Honourable House of Commons.</NOTE><NOTE>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Gibbons not [illegible]"; "Aprill 21".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke I, 17 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Pip Willcox</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Pip Willcox</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A88141">
<STC T="W">L2053</STC>
<STC T="T">E99_11</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99863269</BIBNO>
<VID>115459</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>Elias Redivivus:
A
SERMON
PREACHED
Before the Honorable House
OF
COMMONS,
In the Parish of Saint Margarets West
minster, at the publike Fast,
March 29, 1643.
By JOHN LIGHTFOOTE,
Preacher of the Gospel at <HI>Bartholomew Exchange, London.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by <HI>R. Cotes,</HI> for <HI>Andrew Crooke,</HI> and are to be sold
at his shop at the signe of the Greene Dragon,
in <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard. 1643.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO
THE HONORABLE
the House of
COMMONS
Assembled in PARLIAMENT.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Right Honourable,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>HE great Councell of <HI>Ierusalem</HI>
sate neare the Temple,<NOTE PLACE="marg">R. Sol. in Ex. 21</NOTE> and the
greatest managings of the Councell,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 2. 46.</NOTE>
were the matters of Religion.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Talm. in Sanhed. cap. Dine. mam∣monoth.</NOTE> Such
hath been the posture of your desires,
and such the bent of your indea∣vours
in all your sitting: And as it is ingratitude in
any degrees of men not to serve you, who strive so much
to preserve the State, so especially is it in the Ministers
of the Temple, since you labour so much also to serve the
Temple. Obedience to your commands is the lowest ex∣pression
of such a service, because it is so naturally due,
yet is it the highest that my meannesse can reach unto;
Readinesse being joyned to that obedience: These are
<PB REF="3"/>
the two mites that I can tender unto your <HI>Corban,</HI> and
the two Turtles that I have to offer at your Altar, not
having a better or more valuable gift and offering to
bring, your Noblenesse will please to accept of the gift
because of the heart of the giver given with it, and like
him whom yee represent, to account. <HI>To obey, to be
better then Sacrifice, and to hearken, better then
the fat of Rams.</HI> What in obedience to your command
was humbly presented to your eares and hearing not long
agoe, is now upon the like command in the same obedi∣ence
and humility presented to your eyes and reading. If
it shall finde acceptance with you, it secureth me a¦gainst
al thought or care of inferiors displeasure or excep∣tions.
I most humbly and submissively cast it, my selfe,
and all that I am or can at the feete and disposall of your
honourable House: and because short discourse best fit∣teth
your great occasions, cease to trouble you with more
words: but shall never cease to solicite the Throne of
grace for continued defence and blessing upon your per∣sons
and indeavours; that the Law-giver may never
faile till <HI>Shiloh</HI> come as we desire amongst us: And so
ever prayeth,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your most unworthy, but truly
devoted Servant, John Lightfoote.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>A
SERMON
Preached before the
Honorable House of Commons, at
the Publike Fast holden, March 29.
1643. In the Parish Church of
S. Margarets Westminster.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><BIBL>LUKE, 1. 17.</BIBL>
And he shall goe before him in the Spirit and power of
Elias to turne the hearts of the fathers to the chil∣dren,
and the disobedient to the wisedome of the just.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>F ever <HI>the Hearts of the Fathers</HI> had
need to be <HI>turned to the children,</HI>
that need is now, and if ever the
<HI>Disobedient</HI> had need to be redu∣ced
<HI>to the wisedome of the just,</HI> that
need is now also: but where is <HI>the
Spirit,</HI> and where <HI>the power?</HI> where an <HI>Elias,</HI> or
<PB N="2" REF="4"/>
where a <HI>Baptist</HI> to do the worke? For if ever those
searching and trying times, which were spoken of
so long agoe by our Saviour in the twelfth of <HI>Luk.</HI>
and the three and fiftieth have overtaken any Na∣tion,
they have overtaken this of ours: <HI>Five in one
house, and they divided, three against two, and two a∣gainst
three. The Father divided against the Sonne,
and the Sonne against the Father; the Mother against
the Daughter,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Mat. 10. 36.</NOTE> <HI>and the Daughter against the Mother;
the Mother in law against her Daughter in law, and
the Daughter in law against her Mother in law. And
a mans enemies are they of his owne houshold.</HI> And if
ever those irregular and exorbitant behaviours,
which were spoken of so long agoe, by the Pro∣phet
<HI>Esay,</HI> in the third of <HI>Esay</HI> and the fifth, have
over-runne and forraged any people, they have
done so by this of ours. <HI>The people oppressed every
one by another, and every one by his neighbour: the
child behaving himselfe proudly against the ancient,
and the base against the honourable.</HI> These are our
sorrows, but where our remedy? this our misery,
but where our redresse? For the <HI>divisions of Reuben,</HI>
there are great thoughts of heart, but who can
helpe them? for the divisions in the Church, for divi∣sions
in the State, divisions in families, divisions in
opinions, divisions in affections, (the Lord keepe
them out of your two Houses) divisions in every
division,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Antonio di Guevarra in Rel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>x de los princip. lib. 1. cap. 2.</NOTE> but who can heale them? As the <HI>Hoste at
Nola</HI> in the story, who when hee was commanded
by <HI>the Romane Censor</HI> to go &amp; call the good men of
the City to appeare before him, went to the
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
Church-yard, and there called at the graves of the
dead, <HI>Oh yee good men of Nola come away, for the Ro∣mane
Censor cals for your appearance:</HI> for hee knew
not where to finde a good man alive. So in these
distractions and distempers of this our Land, if we
would finde out a joyner of hearts and a moulder
of humours, that could peece againe the disunited
affections, and forme againe the unfashioned de∣meanours
of men towards men, we might goe and
looke for the mansion of <HI>Elias,</HI> or go and knocke
at the grave of <HI>John the Baptist,</HI> and call them to
come to such a cure as this, for they once have
wrought so great a cure; but who can doe it that
is now alive? Oh how happy were the case with
us, if <HI>the Spirit and power of Elias</HI> were as ready
to be found in your two Houses as they were once
to be found in <HI>John</HI> the <HI>Baptist,</HI> and as they are
to be seene in the words of the text.</P>
<P>But as the Arke and the Ephod at the sacking of
<HI>Nob,</HI> they which should alwayes have remained
together, were by that dolefull accident parted
asunder, and kept at distance: even so these two
which God once joyned together in <HI>Elias</HI> and in
the <HI>Baptist,</HI> and which the holy Ghost hath joyned
together in the words of the text, some evill
Counsell hath put asunder, so that <HI>the Spi∣rit</HI>
is with you, but <HI>the Power</HI> removed a great
way off. What our Saviour saith concerning of∣fences,
<HI>It cannot be but offences will come, but woe to
him by whom the offence commeth:</HI> so may wee
dolefully concerning this, It is our misery that
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
this divorce is come among us, but woe to that
Counsell by whom the divorce first came, it had
beene good for that Counsellour had he never
beene borne.</P>
<P>How happy are those dayes which are spoken
of by the Psalmist, when <HI>mercy and truth are met
together, and Righteousnesse and Peace doe kisse each
other?</HI> And how happily should we hope to see
those dayes, and those things in this Land to meet,
if we could but see these two to meete againe that
are now so unhappily removed to distance? Well,
all that we can doe is to seeke to drive them toge∣ther
with our prayers, and as Moses for the <HI>Vrim
and Thummim</HI> upon Levi, so we for these united
upon you to pray in publike, and to pray in private,
to pray on the Lords day, and to pray on other
dayes; and it is to be a maine petition on this so∣lemne
day of humiliation, that as the Lord hath
put <HI>the Spirit of Elias</HI> into your hearts, so that he
would put <HI>the Power of Elias</HI> into your hands, that
as he hath made you willing, so would he also
make you able, <HI>to turne the hearts of the Fathers to
the children, and the disobedient to the wisedome of
the Righteous.</HI></P>
<P>The words of the text are the last words of the
old Testament, there uttered by a Prophet, here
expounded by an Angell: there concluding the
Law, and here beginning the Gospell: <HI>Behold,</HI>
saith Malachi, <HI>Mal. 4. 5. I will send you Eliah the
Prophet:</HI> And <HI>hee</HI> saith, the Angell, <HI>shall goe before
him in the Spirit and power of Elias.</HI> And <HI>hee shall
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
turne the hearts of the Fathers to the children,</HI> saith
the one; And <HI>to turne the hearts of the fathers to the
children,</HI> saith the other. Thus sweetly and neerely
should the two Testaments joyne together, and
thus divinely would they kisse each other, but that
the wretched <HI>Apocrypha</HI> doth thrust in betweene:<NOTE PLACE="marg">The Apocry∣pha injurious to the two Te∣staments.</NOTE>
Like the two<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">1 King. 6. 27.</NOTE> Cherubims in the Temple Oracle,
as with their outer-wings, they touch the two sides
of the house, from <HI>In the beginning,</HI> to <HI>Come Lord Je∣sus,</HI>
so with their inner, they would touch each o∣ther,
the end of the law with the beginning of the
Gospell, did not this patchery of humane inventi∣on
divorce them a funder.</P>
<P>It is a thing not a little to be admired,<NOTE PLACE="marg">How the Apo∣crypha came into request.</NOTE> how this
<HI>Apocrypha</HI> could ever get such place in the hearts,
and in the Bibles of the Primitive times, as to
come to sit in the very Center of them both: But
to this wonderment there may be some satisfacti∣on
given, namely because that these bookes
came to them from among the Jewes, as well as
the old Testament and the new. And because
that the Jewes alone, and alone so long, had had
the knowledge of Divinity and Religion among
them, the converted Gentiles could not but give
their writings extraordinary esteeme. And be∣cause
the <HI>Talmud</HI> not being yet written, the world
was not acquainted with the vanity and straine of
Jewish learning, those insuspecting times did
swallow these bookes, as not tasting as yet
how unsavoury that was, nor distinguishing these
to be of the same tast. It is therefore more to be
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
admired,<NOTE PLACE="marg">How it conti∣nued.</NOTE> that when the <HI>Talmud</HI> was written, and
the impious and ridiculous doctrines and fables of
the Jewish schooles laid open to the world, that
then these bookes which shew themselves to be of
the very same stampe in many things, should not
onely not be refused out the Bibles and out mens
good conceit, but also get better and further foot∣ing
in the same: but to this wonderment some sa∣tisfaction
also may be given: namely that super∣stition
begun then to grow in the Church every
day more and more, and it became a Religion to
doe as their forefathers had done before, and to
retaine what they had retained, be it whatsoever
it would, and of what ungroundlesnesse soever.</P>
<P>But it is a wonder to which I could never yet
receive satisfaction, that in Churches that are re∣formed,
that have shaken off the yoke of supersti∣tion,
and unpinned themselves from off the sleeve
of former customes or doing as their ancestors
have done: yet in such a thing as this, and of so
great import, should doe as first ignorance, and then
superstition hath done before them: It is true in∣deed
that they have refused these bookes out of the
<HI>Canon,</HI> but they have reserved them still in the <HI>Bi∣ble:</HI>
as if God should have cast <HI>Adam</HI> out of the
state of happinesse, and yet have continued him in
the place of happinesse. Not to insist upon this,
which is some digression, you know the Counsell
of <HI>Sarah</HI> concerning <HI>Ismael,</HI> and in that she out∣stripped
<HI>Abraham</HI> in the Spirit of Prophecy,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Vid. R. Sol. &amp; R. Menal. in lo.</NOTE> <HI>Cast
out the bond-woman and her sonne, for the sonne of the
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
bond-woman may not be heire with the sonne of the
free.</HI></P>
<P>In the words of the text you may see your owne
worke and taske: and those two things that you
have so long laboured under, and that we have so
long longed after, <HI>Reconciliation</HI> and <HI>Reformation.</HI>
You may behold in a part of the text, <HI>Reconciliati∣on</HI>
in these words, <HI>To turne the hearts of the fathers
to the Children:</HI> and <HI>Reformation</HI> in the other, <HI>and
the disobedient to the wisedome of the just.</HI> These
are the two hands of our master which is in hea∣ven,
or rather the two good things in his hands,
after which we his servants have looked so long,
and doe looke this day, and cannot be taken off
till he give them to us. These are the hands of
your two Houses, or rather the two great gifts
which we wait till God put into your hands to
conveigh them towards us. These are the two pil∣lars,
<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 King. 7. 21.</NOTE> <HI>Jachin</HI> &amp; <HI>Boaz, Firmenesse</HI> and <HI>Strength,</HI> that we
long to see set up at the doore of that Temple that
you are in building: And these are the two twins
for which the <HI>Tamar</HI> of our <HI>England</HI> is in travaile
and is pained to be delivered, if there be but
strength to bring them forth.</P>
<P>These two things contained in the latter part of
the text, are set forth and illustrated by two cir∣cumstances
in the former: First, by the party and
the function of that party that must performe so
great a worke, those included in these words, <HI>He
shall goe before him:</HI> Secondly, the qualifications
and indowments of that party for the function, and
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
for the worke, that expressed in these; <HI>In the Spi∣rit
and power of Elias.</HI> The party rare, the functi∣on
honourable, his indowments singular, his
worke divine, <HI>He shall goe before him,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P>We will take up the words according to this
Division, but not according to this order: for as
in nature the agent is before the action, and as in
the text, the workeman is named before the
worke, so are they fit to be considered, and so
will we take them into our handling, and so shall
we take them as they lie in the text, and first of the
first, <HI>He shall goe before him.</HI></P>
<P>Who are meant by the <HI>He</HI> and the <HI>him</HI> in this
part of the text the dimmest eye that is, will easi∣ly
judge and discerne, upon its owne reading,
namely <HI>John the Baptist,</HI> and <HI>our Saviour Christ.</HI>
Two that were in a very neere relation one to ano∣ther
by nature, for they were kinsmen according
to the flesh, but of a neerer and of a higher relati∣on
in regard of their function, for they were they
that began the Gospell, or the one begun &amp; the o∣ther
perfected; &amp; they were they that were the two
great Prophets of the new Testament, or the one
greater then a Prophet, and the other greater then
a man. I cannot omit that which is not, nor can∣not
be omitted by any expositor it is so plaine up∣on
the <HI>him</HI> in this part: namely, that in the verse
next before, he is called the God of <HI>Israel, He
shall turne many of the Children to the Lord their God,</HI>
and in this verse and in this whole passage hee is
shewed to be Christ, of whom is spoken which gi∣veth
<PB N="9" REF="7"/>
a pregnant and undeniable proofe that Christ is
God, against the wicked <HI>Arius</HI> that held him for a
Creature.</P>
<P>The <HI>Baptist</HI> went before our <HI>Saviour</HI> in divers parti∣culars;
in his conception, in his birth, in his preaching,
in his death. For the miraculous conception and birth
of <HI>John,</HI> went before the more miraculous conception
and birth of <HI>Christ;</HI> his powerfull Preaching, before
the others more powerfull; and his renowned death,
before the others more renowned. But the words doe
not meane so much his going before him in time, as his
going before him in Ministery, nor his appearing before
him in the world, as his appearing before him to do him
service, as a servant doth before his Master to provide
for his entertainement; and so the words following doe
explaine it, He shall goe before him, <HI>To make ready a
people prepared for the Lord:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luk. 10. 1.</NOTE> And so the seventy Disci∣ples
are said to be sent before our Saviour <HI>two and two
before his face,</HI> that is, to prepare men for his receiving
against that he himselfe should come.</P>
<P>All the Prophets went before our Saviour in their
Ministery, in their divers generations, but <HI>John</HI> in a
more speciall manner above them all. They like <HI>Balaam</HI>
in the <HI>foure and twentyeth of Numbers,</HI> did behold him,
but not now, did foretell him, but not neere; but he
beheld him face to face, and he told of him standing
by. And hence it is, that our Saviour cals him more
then a Prophet, <HI>Mat.</HI> 11. 9. nay as much or more then
any meere man that was naturally borne of a woman:
<HI>More then a Prophet,</HI> because he went before Christ as
his forerunner; and as great as any that was ever borne,
because he was the beginner of the Gospell. The Mi∣nistery
<PB N="10" REF="8"/>
of <HI>John the Baptist,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">The Ministry of <HI>Iohn</HI> the be∣ginning of the Gospell.</NOTE> and the publishing of the
Gospell, like time and the motion of the heavens, began
together, and in one and the same instant. So hath
<HI>Marke</HI> conjoyned them, in the very beginning of the
Gospell, <HI>Mark. 1. 1. The beginning of the Gospell of Je∣sus
Christ, As it is written in the Prophets, Behold, I send my
messenger before thee.</HI> So likewise, in the first of the <HI>Acts</HI>
and the two and twenty, <HI>Peter</HI> proposing a Disciple to
be chosen in stead of <HI>Judaas, Of these men,</HI> saith he, <HI>which
have companyed with us all the time that the Lord Jesus
went in and out among us, beginning from the Baptisme of</HI>
John: And so in the tenth chapter of the same booke
of the <HI>Acts,</HI> and the thirtie seventh. <HI>The word you know
which was published throughout all</HI> Judea, <HI>and began from</HI>
Galilee <HI>after the Baptisme which John preached.</HI> And one
place for all. <HI>Mat. 11. 13. All the Prophets and the Law
Prophesied untill John,</HI> and from him began the Gospell.
So that what some of the Fathers say concerning <HI>Mala∣chi,</HI>
That he was <HI>Limes Judeismi &amp; Christianismi,</HI> we
may not unfitly say, concerning him, that he was the
bounds of Judaisme and Christianity, the limits from
whence the Law and the Prophets tooke their conclusi∣on,
and the Gospell, and the kingdome of Heaven
their beginning.</P>
<P>Now as the ministery of <HI>John</HI> consisted of two di∣stinct
and considerable parts,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The Ministery of <HI>Iohn,</HI> of two parts.</NOTE> <HI>Preaching</HI> and <HI>Baptizing,</HI>
[like as the gift of Prophecy had consisted in times be∣fore,
of a double spirit, or to speake more properly, of
a double power of one and the same spirit, <HI>to foretell
things to come and to worke miracles;]</HI> so by both these
did he begin the Gospell, and by both these did he goe
before our Saviour. These were, as it were the two
<PB N="11" REF="8"/>
hands with which he laid the foundation, and began
to build up the <HI>Fabricke</HI> of the Evangelicall Temple.
And these two hath <HI>Marke</HI> joyned together in his rela∣tion,
as <HI>John</HI> did in the exercise of his function, <HI>Mar. 1.
4. John did Baptize in the Wildernesse and preach the Bap∣tisme
of Repentance.</HI></P>
<P>By both these he began the Gospell, and first by
his Baptisme: for,</P>
<P>First,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Baptisme used under the law.</NOTE> Baptisme was used in the times before and un∣der
the Law, but it was to admit Proselytes to the reli∣gion
of the Jewes: But the Baptist now commeth with
a Baptisme to admit the Jewes to another Religion be∣sides
their owne. <HI>Jacob</HI> in <HI>Gen.</HI> 35. when he is to enter
and admit the remnant of <HI>Sichem</HI> that escaped the sword
into his family and Religion, he doth it by Baptisme.
<HI>Put away,</HI> saith he, <HI>the strange Gods that are among you, and
be cleane and change your garments,</HI> where, by the se∣cond
injunction,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ab. Ezr. in Gen. 35.</NOTE> <HI>Be cleane, Aben Ezra▪</HI> well observeth
is meant the washing of their bodies in water, and in∣deed
nothing else can so properly be meant,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Tom. 1. p. 317. Asure blah. perek 13.</NOTE> which
what was it else but a Baptizing? And so <HI>Rambam</HI> or
<HI>Maimonides</HI> in his Epitome of the Talmud, relateth
from thence,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 King. 5. 15. 16.</NOTE> that in the times of <HI>David</HI> and <HI>Solomon,</HI>
when Heathens came into the Jewes religion by thou∣sands
(for a hundred three and fifty thousand of them
helped to build the Temple) they were admitted there∣into
by Baptisme, or by being washed, and not by cir∣cumcision.
Thus was Baptisme used in <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">49/8 Vid. R. Sol. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arch in Ex. 24.</NOTE> those ancient
times, and used to induct the Gentiles into the Church
and Religion of the Jewes: But now comes <HI>John</HI> with a
baptisme of another <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd, namely, to enter the Jewes in∣to
another Church and religion then their owne, and so
<PB N="12" REF="9"/>
by his baptisme doth he begin the Gospell.</P>
<P>Secondly, And so also did he by his preaching: For
whereas the law called for absolute and exact perfor∣mance,
and cryed <HI>a curse on him that confirmed not all the
words of the Law to doe them, Deut. 27. 26. John</HI> com∣meth
in another tenor, like God in the still voyce, and
instead of challenging the strict performance of works,
he Preacheth the gentle doctrine of Repentance; that
whereas they could not do what the Law required, they
should repent for that they had broke the law, and thus
is the rigorous and terrible tenor of the law, changed
into the sweete and comfortable doctrine of <HI>Repentance,</HI>
and thus both by Baptizing and Preaching, doth <HI>John</HI>
begin the Gospell.</P>
<P>And so by both also did he <HI>goe before</HI> our Saviour:
By baptisme to admit men into Christ against he
should come, and by his Preaching to let Christ into
men when as he came: By his baptizing to make way for
Christ his comming among men, and by his Preaching
to make way for men their comming unto Christ: And
so much is intimated by the words that next and imme∣diately
doe follow the text, <HI>To make ready a people pre∣pared
for the Lord.</HI> This might be taken onely for an
elegancy such as the Scripture useth, to quicken expres∣sions,
by repetitions, but it hath its proper vigour and
significancy, and in the two severall words denoteth
the two distinct fruits of the ministery of the Baptist in
her two parts: His <HI>Baptisme,</HI> to <HI>make</HI> men <HI>ready</HI> to looke
for Christ that was now in comming; and his <HI>Preaching,</HI>
to have them <HI>prepared</HI> for his receiving when hee came.</P>
<P>The observation that we may take up from hence is
this,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Observ.</NOTE> <HI>That Christ when he came to shew himselfe in the world
<PB N="13" REF="9"/>
had need of a powerfull, and a Spirited forerunner:</HI> He was
the expectation of the Gentiles. <HI>Gen.</HI> 49. 10. He was
the expectation of the <HI>Samaritans. John</HI> 4. 25. He was
the expectation of the Jewes. <HI>Luk.</HI> 19. 11. He was the
expectation of all nations. <HI>Hag.</HI> 2. 7. And yet when he
came that was so expected, he had need of a Harbin∣ger
to goe before him, and a strong forerunner to make
his way; and all this too little too. For <HI>when he came
amongst his owne, his owne received him not.</HI> Joh. 1. 11.</P>
<P>The Jewes sansie concerning the cloud of glory, that
conducted <HI>Israel</HI> through the Wildernesse, that it did
not onely shew them the way, but also plane it, that it did
not onely lead them in the way in which they must goe,
but also fit them the way to goe upon: That it levelled
all the mountaines and smoothed all the rockes, that it
cleared all the bushes, and removed all the rubs. No
lesse preparatives were required for our Saviours com∣ming
to make way for him, in the entertainement of
men, or to make way for men to the entertaining of
him: And so hath the Scripture exprest it in termes not
much different: <HI>Every valley shall be filled, and every
mountaine and hill shall be brought low; and the crooked
shall be made streight, and the rough wayes shall be made
smooth: Esay 40. 4. Luk.</HI> 4. 5.</P>
<P>There were two maine things that lay betwixt the
Jewes and Christ at his appearing, that were most like∣ly
to keepe them asunder, and to hinder the accesse of
each to other, and so they did. And those were <HI>their
corruption in manners,</HI> and in behaviour, and <HI>their corrup∣tion
in doctrine,</HI> and in religion; the former like rough
wayes that must be smoothed, and the latter like crook∣ed,
that must be streightned; and both being such as
<PB N="14" REF="10"/>
must be helped, or little hopes they can come to
Christ.</P>
<P>First. As for their corruption in manners, had we
not evidence enough thereof in the Scripture, that layes
it open, we have sufficient in their owne writers. They
were <HI>a generation of vipers;</HI> so <HI>John</HI> cals them, <HI>Mat. 3.
7.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Jews corrupti∣on in manner.</NOTE> They were <HI>a wicked and adulterous generation;</HI> so our
Saviour cals them, <HI>Mat.</HI> 16. 4. seeming to allude to
the Phrase of <HI>Hosea,</HI> the <HI>children of fornications, Hos. 1.
2.</HI> They were a people stiffenecked and of uncircumci∣sed
hearts and eares: so <HI>Stephen</HI> cals them <HI>Act.</HI> 7. 51.
And to spare more, our Saviour makes them as it
were the common shore of all vengeance, and conse∣quently
the sincke of all iniquity, <HI>Mat. 23. 35. That
upon you may come all the righteous blood shed upon the earth
from the blood of righteous</HI> Abell, <HI>unto the blood of</HI> Zacha∣rias.</P>
<P>To these Characters of their manners given by Scrip∣ture,
we may adde the confession of their owne Au∣thours
in their writings. The <HI>Talmud in Sanhedrim,</HI> in
the eleventh chapter hath these words.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Talm. Sanh. pag. 97.</NOTE> <HI>R: Juda saith, In
the generation in which the son of</HI> David <HI>shall come, The
house of the Assembly shall be a stews, the wisedome of the
Scribes shall faile, they that feare sin shall be despised, and
the face of that generation shall be like dogs.</HI> Saint <HI>Paul</HI>
hits them with their owne title, <HI>Beware of dogs, beware
of the concision, Phil.</HI> 3. 2. and so doth <HI>John</HI> seeme also
to doe,<NOTE PLACE="marg">R. Dav. Kimek on Isay 59.</NOTE> <HI>Without are dogs. Rev.</HI> 22. 15. Such another
testimony doth <HI>David Kimchi</HI> give out of the <HI>Rabbins</HI> on
<HI>Easy 59. 16. Rabbi Johanan saith,</HI> saith he, <HI>The Son of</HI>
David <HI>commeth not, but either in a generation all holy, as
it is written, Thy people shall all be righteous, and inherit
<PB N="15" REF="10"/>
the Land for ever: or in a generation all wicked, as it is
written, He saw that there was no man, and wondred that
there was no intercessor.</HI> Too pregnant and wofull expe∣rience
shewed that the latter was onely true, and their
owne behaviour at our Saviours comming, confirmeth
the glosse to prophesie truly, that their manners then
should be most corrupt.</P>
<P>Secondly, and so was also their Doctrine: and that
withall in a twofold relation. 1. In regard of the opi∣nion
that they held concerning the legall rites that were
amongst them before: and 2. in regard of the opinion
that they held concerning Christ, who was now in
comming.</P>
<P>1. They were so glewed to the Ceremonies of <HI>Mo∣ses,</HI>
and so bewitched with the Traditions of the Fa∣thers,
that it was an impossibility in humane reason to
thaw them asunder.</P>
<P><HI>Paul</HI> speaking of his owne doting upon these, spea∣keth
the affection of his whole Nation in this particu∣lar,
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iews vehement addiction to their traditions and legall rites.</NOTE> <HI>I was exceedingly zealous of the Traditions of the Fa∣thers,</HI>
Gal. 1. 14. <HI>Stephen in</HI> Act. 6. 14. for but spea∣king
of the abolishing of the Customes of <HI>Moses,</HI> must
lose his life, though he spake but what <HI>Moses</HI> himselfe
had spoken before, and what an Angel had spoken after
<HI>Moses,</HI> &amp; though his face when he was to answer for these
things, shone like the face of <HI>Moses,</HI> and was like the
face of an Angel. But what need I to insist upon parti∣culars?
If you looke throughout all the <HI>Acts</HI> of the A∣postles,
you shall finde that almost in every place where
the Gospel came among the Jewes, this was the maine
obstacle that ever lay in the way to hinder the freedome
of its passage, the fixednesse of that people and Nation
<PB N="16" REF="11"/>
to their Ceremonies and Traditions. Let one place
suffice for many, <HI>Act. 21. 28. The Jewes of</HI> Asia <HI>laid
hands on</HI> Paul, <HI>crying out; Men of</HI> Israel <HI>helpe, this man
teacheth all men every where against the people, and the law,
and this place.</HI></P>
<P>The preaching of the Gospel goeth against their
heart, because it goeth against their Customes, and he
that speaketh against that people, law, and place, is
sure to be spoken against himselfe, for they were so pin∣ned
unto the rites of those three, that there must be no∣thinking
of their removal. And thus were they most cor∣rupt
in opinion concerning the Ceremonies of the Law
which they had used of old.</P>
<P>2. And so also were they concerning Christ when he
should come. They expected him to appeare in the
world as an earthly Conqueror, like <HI>Naaman</HI> the <HI>Syrian</HI>
by the Prophet <HI>Elisha;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2 King. 5. 11.</NOTE> <HI>He thought he will surely come out
and stand,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Jewes miscon∣ceit concerning the Messias.</NOTE> <HI>and call upon the name of the Lord his God, and
strike his hand over the place and recover the Leper;</HI> and he
only sent him this plaine and simple message, <HI>Goe wash in</HI>
Jordan <HI>and be cleane:</HI> So they by Christ, they conceited,
Surely he will come with great worldly pompe, and
make his way with a conquering sword, he will destroy
many people even as earthly Princes doe, and seate his
people in <HI>Canaan</HI> againe in more prosperity and pompe
then ever:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Esay 53. 2.</NOTE> and he on the contrary, came in the forme of
a servant, he had no forme nor comelinesse in the eies
of men that they could desire him: he appeared in a
posture of humility and lowlinesse, riding upon an Asse,
and upon a Colt,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Zech. 9 9.</NOTE> the Fole of an Asse. And how farre
were they from intertaining such a Christ as this, when
they expected one of a quality so infinitely different?
<PB N="17" REF="11"/>
Who could beleeve that the title over our Saviours
head upon his Crosse, should be a stumbling blocke un∣to
the Jewes feete? And yet was it so at that very time
when they fixt it there, and so it hath beene ever since,
and so it is at this very day, <HI>Jesus of</HI> Nazareth <HI>King of the
Jewes.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">John 7. 42.</NOTE> They looked for the <HI>Messiah</HI> to come from <HI>Beth∣lehem,</HI>
and they knew him but for <HI>Jesus of Nazareth.</HI>
And they expected a pompous <HI>King of the Jewes,</HI> and
how farre was he from such a King. And thus <HI>they
knew not him,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts 13. 27.</NOTE> when he came from <HI>Galilee, nor the voices
of the Prophets</HI> what they meant by his Kingdome,
and thus were they very farre unlikely to receive him
when he came.</P>
<P>These three things then being thus considered, and no∣tice
taken how farre this people of the Jewes were gone
away both in life and doctrine, what corruption they had
contracted in their manners, what doting upon their an∣cient
Customes, and what misprision concerning Christ,
it is no wonder if he that came to reforme these things
that were so farre amisse, had need of a spirited and a
powerfull forerunner, to make some way for him against
he came.</P>
<P>And as it was at our Saviours comming in the flesh,
so also is it at his comming in the spirit: Whensoever
Christ is to be brought in among a corrupt and irregular
people, in the power and purity of his Word &amp; Gospel,
great hinderances doe ever offer themselves to stop the
way, and they had need of great forerunners to cleare
them thence.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Dan. 9 26.</NOTE> A <HI>Jerusalem</HI> is never built street and wall,
but those times are troublous: &amp; a Reformation in a cor∣rupted
State is never wrought but with these opposals.
The very same things doe make the waies rough and
<PB N="18" REF="12"/>
unpassable for Christs comming now, in his worke and
power, that made it then when he came in the flesh.
These three are as <HI>the net upon</HI> Mispah <HI>and the snare upon</HI>
Tabor, <HI>Hos.</HI> 5. 1. as the ambushes that the Idolatrous
Priests laid upon those Mountaines to catch up all the
passengers that should go to <HI>Jerusalem</HI> to worship the true
God, these catch up men that they come not at Christ.
These are the <HI>Korah, Dathan,</HI> and <HI>Abiram,</HI> that are ever
ready to oppose the <HI>Moses</HI> and <HI>Aaron</HI> that seeke to work
good in the Congregation; and the <HI>Jannes, Jambres</HI> and
<HI>Egyptians,</HI> that affront them in the worke of the Lord.
And hence is it no wonder, that that worke of the same
nature, that you have had so long in hand, hath gone so
slowly and so heavily on. For,</P>
<P>1. How truly is the morall of that Story concerning
<HI>Anomon</HI> in 2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 12. come to passe in these dayes of
ours? First, he was sicke for love of his sister <HI>Tamar,</HI> and
having used her at his pleasure, he was then as sicke for
hate. So hath it beene with us of this Land: we were
sicke but a while agoe for a Parliament, and nothing
would cure us if we had not that, like <HI>David</HI> we longed
and longed againe for this water of <HI>Bethlehem</HI> that is be∣side
the gate, and could not rest till we had got it, and
yet when we have obtained it, and that not without the
hazard of your lives, we now cast it upon the ground,
and care not for it: We are now as weary of this <HI>Manna</HI>
which God hath sent us, as we were desirous of it be∣fore
it came. What should be the reason of mens such
crossenesse and contrariety in their affections, as to will
and to loath, to desire and to detest the same thing, with
the same earnestnesse, in so short a time? Why, that in
the Prophet,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Jer. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>1. 9.</NOTE> <HI>You would have healed</HI> Babel, <HI>and she will not
<PB N="19" REF="12"/>
be healed.</HI> Men are affrighted I know not how at the ru∣mor
of a Reformation, because they are afraid to be
stripped off their carnalities and corruptions. Like a
simple Patient, that in an eating and corroding sore, if
the Surgeon can abate his paine, he likes it well, but to
cut out any proud dangerous and corrupting flesh, that
he will not endure: Just so hath it been with us. Whilest
you eased us of the paines of those pressures, that did
pinch, and took off the yoke from off our neck that glad
so sore, it pleas'd us well, and you had our liking; but to
be restrained any whit from our former &amp; beloved sen∣sualities,
to be straitned any thing of the extravagancies
of our former wayes by the reines of a Reformation, oh
this goes to the quicke, and we cannot indure it, <HI>Durus
sermo,</HI> a hard businesse, who can abide it? Our Saviour
hath told us long agoe, that parting with an old acquain∣tance
bosome sinne is as pinching to flesh and blouds,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth. 5. 29. 30.</NOTE> as
to pluck out an eye and to cut off a hand, and we see it
true by too wofull experience, by mens unseparable∣nesse
from their delights, they carrying them, and they
them, and will not be parted, to perdition. The Vine,
Olive,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Judg. 9. 9.</NOTE> and Figtree in <HI>Jothams</HI> Parable, will not leave
their wine, fatnesse, and sweetnesse, to gaine a King∣dome,
<HI>Herod</HI> his <HI>Herodias</HI> to save his soule, nor men of
corrupt manners, the corruption of their manners for a
blessed Reformation.</P>
<P>This is the first adversary that you have in your way,
that seeketh to crosse the glorious work that you have
in hand. And there is a second which is like to this, as a
twinne of the same wombe, and as bad as it, and that is
corruption in opinion concerning ancient Customes,
and a fixednesse to what our forefathers have used be∣fore.</P>
<P><PB N="20" REF="13"/>
2. Custome, as it is commonly said, is a second na∣ture,
and men cannot easily leave that which they have
long used themselves, and they will not easily leave that
which they have seene and knowne to be used by their
Predecessors. The <HI>Ephraimites</HI> in the booke of <HI>Judges,</HI>
that had beene brought up to say<NOTE PLACE="marg">Judg. 12. 6.</NOTE> <HI>Sibboleth</HI> all their life,
cannot say <HI>Shibboleth</HI> to save their life, but they perish
two and forty thousand. Famous and fearfull is the sto∣ry
of <HI>Rabodus</HI> [some call him by another name] who
when he was so farre perswaded from his Heathenisme
into Christianity, that he had one foote in the water to∣wards
being baptized, and there asking whither his
forefathers were gone that were not Christians nor
baptized, whether to Heaven or Hell, and it being an∣swered
to Hell, he puls his foote back againe out of the
water, with words to this purpose, <HI>That he would goe whi∣ther
his ancestors were gone,</HI> and so he resolved to be
what his Ancestors had beene. This, the more is the
pity, is the <HI>ultima Analysis</HI> of the Religion of too many
thousands in this Land and time; men and women are
too commonly and generally pinned in opinion and in
practice of religious things upon the customes and usage
of ancient times, and they are loth to be parted from
them: The woman of <HI>Sychar</HI> was zealous for the Tem∣ple
upon Mount <HI>Gerizim,</HI> but the best reason she can
give for that her zeale, is but this, because <HI>her, Fathers
worshipped in that Mountaine,</HI> Joh. 4. 20. <HI>Laban</HI> in the
marriage of his daughter <HI>Leah,</HI> will rather follow cu∣stome▪
then either conscience, or his owne promise and
covenant: He had agreed with <HI>Jacob</HI> for <HI>Rachel,</HI> and for
<HI>Rachel</HI> had <HI>Jacob</HI> served, but when it commeth to the
point of performance he suborneth <HI>Leah,</HI> and deceives
<PB N="21" REF="13"/>
him with her, and what is his reason? Why, <HI>it was not
the custome of the Countrey, to give the younger before the
elder,</HI> Gen. 29. 26. How the predominancy of this hu∣mour
in the diseased body of this Church doth cause us
to cast up againe the wholesome Physicke of a Refor∣mation,
it is knowne too well. The confession of the
Prophet may be taken up concerning us, and with ad∣dition,
<HI>We have sinned with our forefathers,</HI> nay we are
resolved so to doe still. The errours that the ignorance
and dulnesse of former times did admit into the wor∣ship
of God and profession of Religion, we are resolved
to retaine because they were the Customes of former
times.</P>
<P>3. And thirdly, a maine obstacle in the way of
Christs powerfull comming among a people, and in the
way of your worke that seekes thus to bring him, is a
corruption of opinion that men have concerning Christ
or Religion it selfe. Religion to carnall men must be a
little gawdy, or else it cannot be a pleasing Religion: as
the Virgin <HI>Mary</HI> must be a Lady, or she is not thought
fit to be a Saint. The simplicity and plainenesse of the
Gospel, spoiles its intertainment with sensuall minds.
And <HI>Antichrist</HI> by putting his Religion in so gorgeous
clothes hath gained so much upon them, and stollen
mens hearts thorough their eyes. God did once indeed
comply with the grosse dulnesse of the Jewes, that he
might winne them, and because they could not goe fur∣ther
in Religion then they were led by the eyes, he gave
them such a one as suited to them, and because it was
so with them once, carnall men would have it so still.</P>
<P>These are the three sonnes of <HI>Anak</HI> with whom you
have had so long to wrestle, and with whom you have
<PB N="22" REF="14"/>
to combate still, before you can bring our <HI>Israel</HI> to the
desired <HI>Canaan.</HI> I may say againe, that it is no wonder that
this worke in your hands goes so slowly on, when three
such Giants doe seeke to hinder it. You have to fight
not with flesh and bloud, but with principalities and
powers, with the strong holds of Satan in the hearts of
men. Oh that we could finde out some such powerfull
forerunners to goe before you, as might cleare the way
for your readier passage! Where might we get so skil∣full
a Mustian as could calme these evill spirits that thus
disturbe all? It is farre from my skill to advise you
what to doe in these respects: But to you others that sit
by, and are spectators how these Worthies labour under
these opposals, this may shew what need you have to
drive on the great and weighty workes that they have
in hand with the earnestnesse of your prayers. Their
hands, like those of <HI>Moses,</HI> it is no wonder if they be
weary with holding up so long in so great imployments,
these must be the <HI>Aaron</HI> and <HI>Hur</HI> that must support
them that they fall not quite. Me thinke we may even
see written in the very things that they are in managing,
they are so weighty, what <HI>Paul</HI> inserts to so many of his
Epistles, <HI>Brethren pray for us;</HI> And Brethren pray for
them. I will conclude all in the words of the Psalmist,
<HI>Let my tongue cleave to the roofe of my mouth:</HI> nay, let
me change the number, for I know you will joyne with
me in the saying, Let our tongues cleave to the roofes
of our mouthes: if we forget the Parliament in our best
devotions. And so have I done with the first part that I
named, <HI>the Person and his function</HI> that must doe the
worke; now I come to the qualification of that per∣son
for that worke and for his function, <HI>He shall goe be∣fore
<PB N="23" REF="14"/>
him in the spirit and power of</HI> Elias.</P>
<P>We meete in this part with two severall parties,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The second part.</NOTE> <HI>Elias</HI>
and <HI>John,</HI> men exceedingly renowned in their genera∣tions,
and exceeding great reformers in their times. <HI>E∣lias</HI>
in the middle of the times of the Law, and <HI>John</HI> in
the beginning of the times of the Gospel. We might
deale with them as the Prophet <HI>Ezekiel</HI> doth with his
two sticks with the names written upon them,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ezek. 37. 19.</NOTE> <HI>Judah</HI> and
<HI>Joseph:</HI> First, we might take in either hand one, and
treat of them severally, then might we take them both
into one hand, and in our handling they might become
one; but we will take up such things concerning them
onely, as shall be most materiall to be considered, and
most sutable to the present times.</P>
<P>And first, we may lay this position, and the text will
warrant it,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Observ.</NOTE> <HI>That</HI> Elias <HI>shall never come to live and continue
upon earth againe.</HI> The Prophet <HI>Malachi</HI> indeed deliver∣eth
it in such termes as if he should come once againe.
<HI>Behold, I will send you</HI> Eliah <HI>the Prophet:</HI> And the <HI>Septua∣gint</HI>
have driven the naile to the head to make this sense
the surer, for they have added, <HI>Behold, I send you</HI> Elias
<HI>the</HI> Tishbite: yet the Angel <HI>Gabriel</HI> in the text doth tell
us, that <HI>Elias</HI> himselfe is not to come in his owne soule,
but another in his spirit, nor he in his owne person, but
it was <HI>John Baptist</HI> was to come in his power. And so
our Saviour,<NOTE PLACE="marg">De Elia praete∣rito vid. R. Lev. Gersh in 1 Reg. 27. De vent. vid. R. <HI>Dav.</HI> Kimeh. in Mal. 4.</NOTE> <HI>Matth. 11. 14. And if you will receive it,
this is</HI> Elias <HI>which was to come:</HI> and <HI>Matth. 17. 12. Elias,</HI>
saith he, <HI>is already come,</HI> which his Disciples doe truely
understand of <HI>John the Baptist.</HI> The Jewes, as they do
erroniously hold that the <HI>Messiah</HI> is not yet come, so doe
they hold also that <HI>Elias</HI> shall personally come before
<PB N="24" REF="15"/>
his comming: And it is no wonder that they erre that
errour mistaking the meaning of <HI>Malachi,</HI> when so ma∣ny
Christians doe erre the same error with them, though
they have an exposition by an Angel, and by our Savi∣our
upon that Prophecie. <HI>Jansenius, Maldonate,</HI> and o∣thers
of the same nest, Jesuites and Papists, explaining
these words that we have in hand, doe resolve, that
they are more fitly to be applied to <HI>Elias</HI> his second com∣ming
which is yet to be, then to his comming in the
dayes of <HI>Ahab:</HI> and they glosse them thus, <HI>He shall goe
before Christ at his first comming,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Sic etiam Bed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o &amp; Amb. Epiph. &amp;c. Haeres 70.</NOTE> <HI>in the spirit and power
that</HI> Elias <HI>shall goe before him in at his second.</HI> A glosse
much like that senselesse one of the Sect in <HI>Epiphanius,</HI>
upon these words in <HI>Gen. 1. 27. God created man in his
owne image,</HI> whereon they seemed to hold, that the body
of man was made after the Image of God, and that
<HI>Christs</HI> humane shape was the copy for the shape of <HI>A∣dam,</HI>
whereas <HI>Adam</HI> was not made a man after the like∣nesse
of Christ, but Christ was made man after the like∣nesse
of <HI>Adam.</HI> Even so is it with these expositors. They
either make <HI>John Baptist</HI> his going before Christ, a pat∣terne
of <HI>Elias</HI> his doing the like, whereas <HI>Elias</HI> in the
Prophet and in the text is a patterne of <HI>John:</HI> or else
they make <HI>Elias</HI> who is to come (no one can tell when)
the copy or paterne of the <HI>Baptist</HI> already come, which
is more then ridiculous. Nor is it so much to be won∣dred,
that these men of corrupt judgements and minds,
should erre this same errour with the Jewes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Vid. Cornel. à Lapide in Apoc. 11. 3. Aleazer, ibid.</NOTE> when we
finde so many of the Fathers to have erred in the same
opinion also, and to <HI>Elias</HI> they have added <HI>Enoch,</HI> and
both these, they say, must come before the comming
of Christ, for these they hold to be the two witnesses in
the 11. of the <HI>Revelation.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="15"/>
It is true indeed that some ones shall come in the spi∣rit
of <HI>Elias</HI> toward the end of the world,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The two wit∣nesses, <HI>Rev. 11▪</HI></NOTE> according to
that description in the <HI>Revelation,</HI> but no expectation of
<HI>Elias</HI> himselfe, nor no description of <HI>Enoch</HI> at all. The
two witnesses in that place are plainely charactered and
decyphered forth by the emblems of <HI>Moses</HI> &amp; <HI>Elias. They
have power to shut up Heaven that there be no raine,</HI> vers. 6.
Here is apregnant intimation of <HI>Elias:</HI> &amp;, <HI>They have power
over the waters to turn them into bloud,</HI> there is as pregnant
a one of <HI>Moses.</HI> These two men doe meete more then
once mentioned together in the Scriptures. They are
named together in the conclusion of the Prophets, <HI>Mal.
4. 4. Remember the Law of</HI> Moses <HI>my servant,</HI> and in <HI>v. 5.
Behold I send you</HI> Elias <HI>the Prophet.</HI> They appeared toge∣ther
and attended our Saviour at his transfiguration,
<HI>Matth.</HI> 17. 3. They are thought on together in that de∣scription
of the two witnesses, as they also agreed toge∣ther
in this, that the one was the giver of the Law at the
first, and the other the restorer of it when it was decay∣ing:
the one was the great Prophet of the Jewes, the
other the great Prophet of the Gentiles,<NOTE PLACE="marg">A ministery in the spirit and power of <HI>Moses</HI> and <HI>Elias</HI> at the Jewes conver∣sion.</NOTE> as shall be
touched anon. When therefore the Jewes and the Gen∣tiles
shall be knit together into one Church upon the
fulnesse of the one and the conversion of the other, then
shall God raise up a powerfull Ministery to them both
united, as in the spirit of <HI>Moses</HI> and <HI>Elias,</HI> (the time of
their preaching is alluded to the time of our Saviours,
three yeares and a halfe) and Antichrist shall rise up
against them,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Tropicall phrases.</NOTE> and persecute some of them to the death.</P>
<P>By the way as we goe, it is not immateriall to be ob∣served,
how things signifying and things signified doe
often in Scripture beare one and the same name: some∣time
<PB N="26" REF="16"/>
the thing signifying is called by the same name of
the thing signified. As at the making of the first Covenant
<HI>Exod. 24. 8. Moses sprinkled the bloud of the Covenant upon
all the people,</HI> Heb. 9. 19. That is, upon the <HI>twelve Pillars,</HI>
which he had set up to represent the people, <HI>vers.</HI> 4. as he
had set up an Altar also to represent God: For to besprin∣kle
so many hundred thousands severally, it was impos∣sible
in so short a time as he imployed in that worke.
And so in the second Covenant in the bloud of Christ,
the Bread and Wine that represent his body and bloud,
are called by the very names of his body and bloud.</P>
<P>Sometimes the thing signified is called by the name of
the thing signifying, as <HI>Hos. 3. 5. Afterward shall the chil∣dren
of Israel returne, and seeke the Lord their God and</HI> Da∣vid
<HI>their King,</HI> that is, <HI>Christ their King,</HI> which was sig∣nified
by <HI>David:</HI> And so in the matter that we have in
hand, the Prophet <HI>Malachi</HI> cals the Baptist <HI>Elias,</HI> because
he was so neerely represented and typified by <HI>Elias.</HI> To
them that hold that <HI>Elias</HI> shall personally come againe
indeed, we may justly propose these two or three queres.
First, how shall a glorified bodie converse with bodies
laden with corruption and mortality? Observe at the
transfiguration of our Saviour, when the glorified bo∣dies
of <HI>Moses</HI> and <HI>Elias</HI> appeared to him, the Disciples
were so uncapable and unfit for conversing with them,
that some of them spake they knew not what.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 9. 33.</NOTE> Consi∣der
the disproportion that is betweene Angels and men,
if I may so call it, in regard of converse, the one spirits,
the other bodies, how can these two be familiar toge∣ther,
if an Angel take not on him a visible shape? There
is not so much distance indeed betwixt bodies glorified
and bodies mortall, yet is there so much as is sufficient
<PB N="27" REF="16"/>
to spoyle the converse of each with other.</P>
<P>Secondly, What should <HI>Elias</HI> doe in his person
here? If <HI>to preach:</HI> our Saviour hath told us, <HI>that
if men would not hearken to</HI> Moses <HI>and the Prophets,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Luk. 16. 12.</NOTE> <HI>they
will not be perswaded though one rose from the dead:</HI> And
may we not inferre? If men will not hearken to <HI>Moses,</HI>
the Prophets, the Evangelists, and the Apostles; they
will not beleeve though <HI>Elias</HI> came from heaven,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gal. 1. 8.</NOTE> <HI>To
Preach the Gospel?</HI> If another then what was preached
by Christ and his Apostles,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Cor. 4. 7.</NOTE> then is he accursed though
he be <HI>Elias.</HI> If the same: why, that treasure is carried
in earthen vessels, and not in vessells already glorified.
<HI>To destroy Antichrist?</HI> This indeed is the common opi∣nion:
<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Thes. 2. 8. vid. Chald. Par∣on Esay. 11. 4. in edit. Buxtorf.</NOTE> but <HI>Paul</HI> hath told us that <HI>the Lord shall doe it with
the Spirit of his mouth, and the brightnesse of his comming.</HI>
Such questions as these might be proposed to that opi∣nion,
that is indeed of much like nature with this, but
of farre more strangenesse, namely that that would
bring Christ from heaven againe, to live personally on
earth a thousand yeares. First, what should Christ that
is in heaven, blessed for ever, doe a thousand yeares
upon earth that is cursed? The very first lesson that
God taught <HI>Adam</HI> after he had taught him the lesson of
Christ, was this, that he should not expect Christs
kingdome upon earth, for that he cursed, <HI>Gen.</HI> 3. 17.
Secondly, how strange and improbable is it to con∣ceive,
that Christ who in his humane frailty had a
kingdome, which was called and was <HI>the Kingdome of
Heaven,</HI> should now in his immortall glory come and
possesse a kingdome on earth? An opinion according
to the censure of <HI>Eusebius,</HI> raised upon the misconstru∣ction
of a place in the last booke of the New Testament,
<PB N="28" REF="17"/>
as this about <HI>Elias</HI> was of a place in the last booke of
the old.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Easeb. hist. Ec∣cles. lib. 3. cap. 39.</NOTE> For thus speaketh he concerning <HI>Papias,</HI> the
first father of this conceit: <HI>The same Author also,</HI> saith he,
<HI>sheweth that other things came to him by unwritten tradition
which containe certaine strange Parables of our Saviour and
new doctrines of his, and some other things stuffed with le∣gendary
fables. Among which he averreth that the king∣dome
of Christ, after the resurrection of all flesh from the
dead, shall continue and endure upon this earth, after a hu∣mane
and bodily manner, for a thousand yeares: Which opi∣nions
I beleeve that he did entertaine, because he misunder∣stood
the Apostolicall interpretations, which were delivered
by them under hidden figures, and obscure Parables. For he
was a man, as may be guessed by his writings of a very shal∣low
wit. Yet was he the Author of the like error to most Ec∣clesiasticall
men, who cited this mans antiquity for the defence
of their part: as</HI> Irenaeus, <HI>and whosoever else is of the same
opinion with him.</HI></P>
<P>I will not censure nor condemne the opinion, but re∣ferre
it to superiour examination, onely this I cannot
but say of it, that I doe not remember that ever I heard
or read of an opinion of so extreame and monstrous
strangenesse, that in so short a time, hath gotten so
great a beliefe and so large an entertainment, and nei∣ther
tongue or pen hath stirred against it. It is our hope
and prayer, that once you may have liberty and leisure
from the great rent in the whole peece of the State to
looke upon the rippings in the seames of the Church,
that such opinions as this and others may be taken ei∣ther
by you or by your authority into examination, be∣fore,
like <HI>Joab</HI> and <HI>Abishai</HI> the sons of <HI>Zerviah,</HI> they
grow too strong, and defie a tryall.</P>
<P><PB N="29" REF="17"/>
<HI>The Spirit and power of Elias</HI> is held by some to meane
but one and the same thing, <HI>his powerfull Spirit.</HI> So
indeed sometime runneth the sense of the Hebrew stile.
As in that answer of our Saviour, <HI>Joh. 14. 6. I am the
way, the truth, and the life,</HI> the scope of the question
that occasioned it seemeth to call it to such a sense, <HI>I
am the true and the living way.</HI></P>
<P>Others distinguish the meaning with the words, and
by <HI>the Spirit of Elias</HI> understand patience and tolerancy
of persecution, and by <HI>the power,</HI> the prevalent and ef∣ficacious
virtue of his ministration. But we need not
to goe farre for interpretations, when either the words
are of no great difficulty, or what they be of, will easi∣ly
be explained by the Scripture it selfe.</P>
<P>By <HI>Elias his Spirit</HI> then are we to understand, not his
owne within him,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Joh. 10. 41.</NOTE> but the Spirit of the Lord or of Pro∣phecy
upon him:<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 King. 2. 15.</NOTE> And so his spirit is said to be upon
<HI>John,</HI> as <HI>Moses</HI> his spirit was upon the <HI>Elders,</HI> and the
spirit of the same <HI>Elias</HI> upon <HI>Elisha.</HI></P>
<P>By the <HI>power of Elias</HI> upon the Baptist, is not meant
the power of miracles,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Num. 11. 25.</NOTE> for <HI>John</HI> wrought none, wher∣as
<HI>Elias</HI> did many, but his power of preaching for the
conversion of many unto God. So that whereas the
ancient Prophets of the Law, and among them <HI>Elias,</HI>
had a double power of the Spirit upon them, <HI>To fore∣tell
things to come, and to worke miracles;</HI> so had <HI>John</HI> the
first Prophet of the Gospell, a double power, but of
another nature and a better. He foretold not things to
come, but he explained those that had him foretold;
and he wrought not miracles upon bodies, but he was
miraculously powerfull upon soules.</P>
<P>Now, should we come to compare <HI>Elias</HI> &amp; the <HI>Baptist</HI>
<PB N="30" REF="18"/>
ther we should finde them agree in many parallels: as
that they both came in very corrupt times, that they
both restored religion very much in that corruption,
that they were both persecuted exceedingly for that re∣storing,
<HI>Elias</HI> by <HI>Ahab</HI> and <HI>Jezabell,</HI> and <HI>John</HI> by <HI>He∣rod</HI>
and <HI>Herodias;</HI> and divers other agreements, upon
which not to insist, because they bee obvious to
every eye,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Observ.</NOTE> this collection may we take up from the
words in hand, That <HI>Elias</HI> is a proper and pregnant
patterne for Reformers.</P>
<P>As when <HI>Moses</HI> was making the Sanctuary and the
appurtenances,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 26. 40. &amp; 26. 30. <HI>&amp;</HI> 27. 8. Heb. 8. 4. 5.</NOTE> God often cals upon him to make all
things according to the patterne which was shewed him
in the mount: So in this like worke of yours which you
have in hand can you platforme out a reformation by a
better patterne then by <HI>Elias,</HI> since you will not doe it
but by some patterne from the Mount? A man that in
the text is a copy to <HI>John the Baptist</HI> in his reforming:
And a man that in his owne time <HI>restored all things,</HI> as
our Saviour saith of him, <HI>Mat.</HI> 17. 11. And fitly then
may he be a patterne for these times of ours.</P>
<P>He restored perishing religion, &amp; the decaying law:
he restored forgotten Prophecy, and as the Jews hold,
forsaken Circumcision: for of Circumcision doe they
understand those words of <HI>Elias</HI> himselfe, <HI>They have for∣saken
thy Covenant, 1 King.</HI> 19. 14. And of <HI>Elias</HI> the re∣storer
of Circumcision they misunderstand those words
of the Prophet,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Vid. <HI>R. D.</HI> Rim∣chi in Reg. <HI>&amp; in</HI> Molach.</NOTE> <HI>The Angell</HI> or <HI>Messenger of the Covenant,</HI>
Mal. 3. 1.</P>
<P>But I stand not here as a Surgeon over his Anato∣my,
to reade unto you a Lecture of reforming, upon the
<HI>Sceleton</HI> of <HI>Elias,</HI> it were beyond good manners, as it is
<PB N="31" REF="18"/>
beyond my skill: Let me addresse my selfe to you that
sit by and are spectators of these Worthies as they la∣bour
in their worke, in a word or two of application,
and that according to the two words that are before us,
<HI>the Spirit of Elias and his power.</HI></P>
<P><HI>1. By the Spirit of Elias,</HI> I told you, is understood
the Spirit of God that was upon him: Now as the Apo∣stle
saith, <HI>x Cor. 12. 4. the Spirit was but one, but the gifts
were diverse.</HI> For looke in the fourth of the <HI>Acts,</HI> and
the thirty first, it is said of the Apostles there, that when
they had prayed the place was shaken and <HI>they were fil∣led
with the Holy Ghost.</HI> And so they had beene some
dayes before, namely on Pentecost day, <HI>Act.</HI> 2. 4.
Now they having beene filled then, how can they be
said to be filled againe? Why▪ then with the gift of
tongues, and now with the gift of holy boldnesse, for,
for that it was they prayed, ver. 29.</P>
<P>Among the diverse gifts then of the holy Spirit,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Elias</HI> his zeale.</NOTE> that
<HI>Elias</HI> had, this is not the last nor the least that made
him renowned, <HI>His extraordinary zeale for the Lord of
Hostes.</HI> So much expresseth he concerning himselfe,
1 <HI>King.</HI> 19. 10. 14. And so much seemeth our Saviour
to aime at, in his answer to his two disciples that would
have fire fetched from heaven, as <HI>Elias</HI> had done, <HI>Ye
know not,</HI> saith he, <HI>what manner of spirit ye are of,</HI> Luk. 9.
55. of a zeale beyond your warrant, and you would be
forward you know not how. The thing that you may
take notice of from hence is this, That no true reforma∣tion
can be expected which is not carried on with a spi∣rit
of zeale. The workes of God must be wrought with
his Spirit, &amp; they that desire to forward his glory, must
do it with a holy forwardnesse. It is the honour of <HI>Levi,
<PB N="32" REF="19"/>
Deut.</HI> 33. 9. that when he was about the imployment of
the Lord, he was so zealous in it, that he forgot all ci∣vill
relations, <HI>and said unto his father, and to his mother,
I have not seene him, neither did he acknowledge his bre∣thren,
nor knew his owne children.</HI> And so our Saviour in
the third of <HI>Marke,</HI> when his mother and kindred would
have taken him off from preaching, for they said <HI>he
will faint,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, he is besides himself, in the <HI>Syriack. Arab. vulg. Lat. Ital.</HI> of <HI>Deodate,</HI> the <HI>Spanish</HI> hath it, he go∣eth out of his calling &amp; estate, <HI>in marg.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> in the Lxx. <HI>Gen.</HI> 45. 26.</NOTE> or <HI>he is beside himselfe,</HI> be it whether it will, for
the originall word will beare both, he was so zealous in
the worke in hand, that he would not owne them that
came to hinder it. For <HI>he answered, saying, Who is my mo∣ther,
and who are my brethren?</HI> Marke 3. 33.</P>
<P>2. The power of <HI>Elias</HI> in Reformation was ex∣ceeding
much, and he did wondrous things in what he
did, but yet he left exceeding much undone, which he
could not helpe, and abundance of corruption, which
he could not remove. He tooke away <HI>Baalim,</HI> but he
could not take away the golden Calves, he destroyed
the Prophets of the one, but he could not destroy the
Prophets of the other.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 King. 18. 19 40.</NOTE> Foure hundred and fifty Pro∣phets
of <HI>Baal</HI> perished by his meanes at <HI>Carmel,</HI> and yet
are there foure hundred false Prophets left that seduce
<HI>Ahab</HI> to goe to <HI>Ramoth.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 King. 22. 6.</NOTE> Thus impossible is an utter exti∣pation
of all corruption out of a State and Church that
is corrupt.</P>
<P>Lay these two now together in the two scales of an
unprejudicate judgement, and they will helpe very well
to ballance and to poize a right your thoughts and cen∣sures
concerning these Worthies that are toyling in our
worke. Some thinke they have beene too forward, o∣thers
thinke they have beene too slow; some, that they
have done too much, others that they have done too
<PB N="33" REF="19"/>
little; some complaine of too much zeale, and some of
too little reformation. To the former may be answe∣red,
that <HI>Elias</HI> must be zealous if he will reforme; to the
latter, that <HI>Elias</HI> cannot utterly purge out all corruption
though he be <HI>Elias;</HI> and to both together, that in stead
of murmuring against them, it were farre fitter to be
thankfull to God for them, for that he hath put so much
zeale into their hearts, and so much reformation already
into their hands, as that we see more already then we ex∣pected
ever to have seene: The same Lord continue the
same <HI>Spirit</HI> unto them, and increase the <HI>Power,</HI> that their
hearts and their hands may hold up and grow strong,
that we may see the salvation of the Lord exerted by
them; for the reconciling of the disaffected, and the
reducing of the disobedient. And so I passe to the third
part of the text, the worke of the Baptist, <HI>to turne the
hearts of the fathers to the children, &amp;c.</HI> The case was
wofull when father and sonne had need of a reconciler
to make them friends, yet was it theirs then, and so is it
ours now.</P>
<P>It was a very hard taske surely to <HI>John</HI> the <HI>Baptist,</HI> to
turne the hearts of the fathers to the children, or to doe
this worke, for I finde it a very hard taske and trouble
to expositors to finde out and to resolve, who these
fathers and children were.</P>
<P>Some by <HI>the fathers</HI> understand the Jewes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Vid. Carthis.</NOTE> and by <HI>the
children,</HI> Christ and his Apostles, as <HI>Luke</HI> 11. 19. and
that <HI>John</HI> turned the hearts of the fathers to the chil∣dren,
when he brought the Jewes to imbrace their Do∣ctrine;
but how can the other part be made good with
this glosse, that he turned the heart of Christ and his A∣postles
to the Jewes?</P>
<P><PB N="34" REF="20"/>
Some render it thus, <HI>He shall turne the heart of the fa∣thers
to the Children</HI> by the right understanding of the
Scriptures, and <HI>the disobedient to the wisdome of the righ∣teous</HI>
by the obedience of faith. An exposition that
leaveth us as farre to seek who were the fathers and who
the children, as we were before.</P>
<P>Others therefore come nearer the letter,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Maldon. in Lec.</NOTE> and expound
it from the difference that was at that time in opinions
among the Jewes, the father it may be a Pharisee, and
one sonne a Sadducee, and another an Essaean, and <HI>John</HI>
by bringing them all to the entertainment of the Go∣spel,
extinguished that division which opinions had set
betweene them. It is true indeed that these three Sects
were among the Jewes at the <HI>Baptists</HI> comming,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Joseph. Antiq. lib. 18. cap. 2.</NOTE> the
three Shepheards which were to be destroyed in one
moneth, <HI>Zach.</HI> 11. 8. but for any such division in Sect
betwixt father and sonnes, it is but a conjecture, and it
cannot be so certainly averred.</P>
<P>But furthest off of all other glosses, and the most im∣proper,
is that of <HI>Jansenius</HI> and others of his feather,
which yet they hold to be the nearest and the proper∣est
of all, and that is this. That <HI>John</HI> turned <HI>the hearts
of the children to the fathers,</HI> when he brought the Jewes
to whom he preached, or those of his owne time, to im∣brace
the faith and doctrine of the Patriarchs that had
beene before: and <HI>the hearts of the fathers to the children,</HI>
when by reducing them thus to that faith, he occasioned
that those holy men in <HI>Limbo</HI> did beginne to affect
them, and take them to heart, which they had not done
before. I will not stand to examine or convince this
exposition, for it is not worth the labour, you your
selves have confuted it in thought I know as soone as
<PB N="35" REF="20"/>
heard it.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Fathers and Children, Jews and Gentiles.</NOTE> The most genuine and reall meaning of the
words that we have in hand I conceive to be this. That
by <HI>the Fathers</HI> are to be understood the Jewes, and by
<HI>the Children</HI> the Gentiles; and by <HI>Johns</HI> turning each o∣thers
heart unto others, his winning them both joyntly
and unanimously, to the knowledge and profession of
Christ and of the Gospel, and by the tie of that to the
joynt communion one with another. And I am made
confident and imboldened to entertaine this exposition
as the very meaning of the place upon these reasons.</P>
<P>1. Because the Church of the Gentiles is stiled by the
name of the children of the Jews, cōmonly and constant∣ly
in the Prophets: as <HI>Esay 54. 13. All thy children shall be
taught of the Lord,</HI> and 60. 4. <HI>Thy sonnes shall come from
farre, and thy daughters shall be turned at thy sight,</HI> and 62.
5. <HI>As a young man marrieth a Virgin, so shall thy sonnes
marry thee.</HI> And in very many other places.</P>
<P>2. Because it was a speciall and peculiar worke and
office of the Gospel to unite and tie the Jew and Gentile
into one: so saith the Apostle, <HI>Ephes. 2. 14. Christ is our
peace, who hath made both one,</HI> and the Gospel the meanes.
And then must it be the worke and office of the <HI>Baptist</HI>
who began the Gospel.</P>
<P>3. Experience and the History it selfe confirmeth
this our exposition; for as the Gospel in its owne nature
and promulgation belonged to the Gentiles as well as
the Jewes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">John 1. 7.</NOTE> and as <HI>John</HI> came for <HI>a witnesse that all through
him might beleeve,</HI> the one Nation as well as the other,
so did he baptize and convert some of the one as well
as the other,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ioseph Ant. lib. 18. cap. 7.</NOTE> Romane Souldiers, as well as Jewish Pha∣risees,
and make them both according to the phrase
which <HI>Josephus</HI> useth of him, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>to con∣vent
or knit together in his Baptisme.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="36" REF="21"/>
4. This exposition maketh <HI>John</HI> the more fully to
resemble <HI>Elias,</HI> who was a Preacher and a Prophet to
the <HI>Gentiles</HI> as well as to <HI>Israel,</HI> nay the first Prophet of
the <HI>Gentiles.</HI> This our Saviour toucheth, <HI>Luke 4. 25.
Many widowes were in</HI> Israel, <HI>in the dayes of</HI> Elias, <HI>but
to none was he sent, saving to one in</HI> Sarepta <HI>a City of</HI> Zi∣don:
and the men of <HI>Nazareth</HI> though but plaine and
rusticke simple men, yet did they quickly understand it
of preaching to the <HI>Gentiles,</HI> which put them into an
anger, and our Saviour into a danger. Nor can we
thinke that the holy and zealous Prophet, residing in
that Heathen City two or three yeares together, as ap∣peareth
by the text, would live there idlely and doing
nothing, but that he preached there as well as he had
done to <HI>Israel</HI> whilest he was among them, for he was
every where jealous for the Lord of Hosts. I would
this were but seriously thought on, in mens expounding
the prophesie about the two witnesses in the <HI>Revelation,</HI>
which we touched before. For if they would but see <HI>E∣lias</HI>
there which is so plainely emblemed and pictured
out, and withall but consider that <HI>Elias</HI> was the first Pro∣phet
of the <HI>Gentiles,</HI> it would helpe to settle an interpre∣tation
to that place, which now hangs exceeding loose
in diversity of opinions.</P>
<P>This being then the proper and onely meaning of
the words in hand, that <HI>John</HI> by his preaching should
turne <HI>the hearts of the</HI> Jewes <HI>to the</HI> Gentiles, <HI>and of the
Gentiles to the</HI> Jewes; and by his Baptisme should as it
were tie them up together; the observation or collecti∣on
that we may take up from hence is this, <HI>That true Re∣ligion
is the truest reconciler:</HI> There is no peace-maker
like the Gospel, but it is among them that are true pro∣fessors
of the Gospel.</P>
<P><PB N="37" REF="21"/>
Nor is there any breed-bate like the Gospel neither:
And so saith our Savioar, <HI>Suppose you that I am come to
give peace on earth? I tell yee nay, but rather division,
Luke</HI> 12. 51. which he speaketh out more plainely by
another Evangelist: <HI>I came not to send peace, but a sword,
Matth.</HI> 10. 34.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 3. 15.</NOTE> But this is betweene the two seeds, be∣twixt
whom God hath set enmity, and there can be no
reconciliation, the seed of the Woman and the seed of
the Serpent: but to the children of the same father,
God, and of the same mother, the Church, the Gospel
is the sweet messenger of peace, and the sweete peace maker.</P>
<P>A deadlier hate could not be betwixt man and man,
then was of the Jew toward the Gentile. They reputed
them as Dogs, and so our Saviour useth their common
phrase,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth. 15. 26.</NOTE> <HI>It is not good to take the childrens bread and give it
to Dogs:</HI> they reputed them as swine, and accordingly
they render that verse of the eighteenth Psalme, <HI>the
Boare out of the Wood doth waste it, and the wild beast of
field doth devoure it:</HI> they abhorred their society, nay
they abhorred the very mention of their conversion,
<HI>Luke 4. 28. Act.</HI> 22. 22. And yet when true Religion
commeth in, &amp; seiseth both the Jew &amp; Gentile, the hate
is forgotten,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts 11. 18.</NOTE> the feud is gone, and the deadly enemies
are the nearest friends. Much like as it is reported con∣cerning
<HI>Cairo</HI> in <HI>Egypt,</HI> that if the Plague rage never so
much over night, that they die by thousands, yet if the
River <HI>Nilus</HI> come flowing in the next day, the mortali∣ty
is ceased, and there dieth not one: Even so is it with
Religion: Be there never so much bitternesse and heart∣burning
betwixt man and man, never so much conten∣tion
and contestation betwixt neighbour and neighbour,
<PB N="38" REF="22"/>
if the power of Religion doe but once flow in and seise
them both, the Plague is ceased, the malignity gone.</P>
<P>This is that that cries downe the partition wals of all
divisions: this is the great tie of mens affections, yea, it
is the greatest; this is the matrimony of soules, making
two men to be of one spirit, as the other doth a man and
a woman to be one flesh. It is Christ which is the tru∣est
cause of making men offended, to be reconciled in a
good sense, as he was the occasion of <HI>Herods</HI> and <HI>Pilates</HI>
being so in a bad. With what spleene and rancour did
<HI>Saul</HI> set for <HI>Damascus</HI> against the professors there? yet
when Christ comes into him by the way, no greater
friend then <HI>Paul</HI> to them when he comes neare them.
For,</P>
<P>1. Religion is a speciall and soveraine meanes to
calme,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Reas. 1.</NOTE> tame, and cicurate those exorbitant affections
and extravagant humours that breed division and main∣taine
it.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Esay 11. 6, 7.</NOTE> The Prophet <HI>Esay</HI> describing the power of the
Gospel in the Christian Church saith, that it shall bring
the Wolfe to dwell with the Lambe, the Leopard to
lie downe with the Kid, the Calfe and the young Lion
to feed together, and the Cow and the Beare to goe in
company. His allusion is to the carriage of the beasts in
the Arke of <HI>Noah:</HI> before they came in thither, the Li∣on
was ravenous, and the Lambe his prey, the Leopard
and the Beare devouring, and the Kid and the Calfe a∣fraid
to come neare them: but when they were come
within the Arke, there was no such thing, all bloodinesse
and rapine was laid aside, and the Lambe and Lion
couch together, and the Lion now as harmelesse as the
Lambe. So is it in the Church, and so is it by the pow∣er
of Religion: those humours and passions of men
<PB N="39" REF="22"/>
which before have beene bloudy, cruell, proud, selfe∣willed,
dissentious, and rebellious, if once the power∣full
operation of Religion get in among them, it quels
these Rebels, quenches these firebrands, reduces these
extravagants, and like the dispossessed in the Gospel,
makes him to sit calmely and quietly, and in his right
mind, whom none might come within the compasse of
before without a danger.</P>
<P>2. Religion doth center mens affections in the center
of unity God himself,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Reas. 2.</NOTE> and those things that concerne
God, that they cannot separate: It is an old saying, <HI>Quae
conveniunt in uno tertio conveniunt inter se; Those things
that agree in a third thing agree among themselves:</HI> Then
how many third things are there in which true Christi∣ans
meete as lines in a Center, that must needs hold
them together and make them agree? S. <HI>Paul</HI> hath
reckoned them to our hands in the fourth to the <HI>Ephesi∣ans,</HI>
the fourth, fifth, and sixth verses. They meet in one
body, in one spirit, in one hope of their calling, in one
Lord, one faith, one Baptisme, in one God and Father
of all.</P>
<P>3. Religion maketh conscience of living in division
and giving offence;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Reas. 3.</NOTE> It dares not offer its gift at the Al∣tar,
till it and the offended be reconciled. It dares not
suffer the Sunne to goe downe upon its wrath, nor will
eate that meate that shall offend a weake brother: And as
the Father in another sense, accounts it as desperate to
sleepe in malice, as to goe to bed in a den of lions. The
use that we may make of this may be double, and brief∣ly
thus, because I know not your houres and occasions
and I feare to offend.</P>
<P>First,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Use 1.</NOTE> this may direct us very well in the choosing of
<PB N="40" REF="23"/>
a friend. Would we have one that shall be true to us? let
us look out such a one as is true to God: Would we have
one that shall be faithfull in our little things, in our af∣faires?
let us seeke out such a one as is faithfull in the
great thing, in Religion. As his Counsell was, to agree
to <HI>Gregories Austen</HI> if he were humble,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Acts and Mon. old edit. <HI>pag. 10<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></NOTE> so be it our holy
policy to tie to that man in friendship that is religious:
and as <HI>Jehu</HI> to <HI>Jonadab, 2 King.</HI> 10. 15. If we light on
a man whose heart is right towards the Lord as we de∣sire
a friends heart should be to us, let us fixe on that
friend, and give him the hand.</P>
<P>Secondly, this also may shew us who cannot be our
friend: and with whom it is impossible to have unity
and amity, namely with the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI> which is
cleane <HI>Antipodes</HI> to us in Religion.</P>
<P><HI>Is there peace,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Use 2.</NOTE> <HI>Jehu?</HI> saith <HI>Joram</HI> to him. No, there is
no peace, where whoredomes and witchcrafts are so
many.<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 King. 9. 22.</NOTE> <HI>No communion can be betwixt Christ and Belial,</HI> or
betwixt Religion and Idolatry:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Belial, <HI>i. e.</HI> an Idol.</NOTE> for so I conceive the
word <HI>Belial</HI> signifieth throughout the Scripture.<NOTE PLACE="marg">The children of <HI>Belial, i. e.</HI> Ido∣laters.</NOTE> The
enmity that God himselfe fixed at the very beginning
betwixt the seed of the Serpent and the seed of the Wo∣man,
must continue unreconciled to the very end: and
as <HI>quos Deus conjunxit,</HI> whom God hath joyned toge∣ther,
no man whatsoever must put asunder; so what
God hath parted and put asunder, no man must offer
to joyne together: Who are the seed of the Woman
and the seed of the Serpent, so plaine to be seene, as
Christ and Antichrist? and he that will seeke to make
conjunction of <HI>Rome</HI> and us, will marry light and dark∣nesse,
God and the Devill, Christ and Antichrist toge∣ther,
and make a friendship betwixt those, betwixt
<PB N="41" REF="23"/>
whom God himselfe hath doomed an enmity while the
world endureth.</P>
<P>We blesse God that hath brought us out of her fa∣miliarity
and friendship to be now her haters and hated
of her: and we blesse the time when we first fell from
the society and converse of <HI>Egypt,</HI> to be her enemies
and at distance with her: And we blesse you and your
endeavours, that strive so much and so constantly to
keepe us cleare of re-ingagements. And may the worke
prosper in your hands, and you in the worke, to hold
us still at our proper distance to the feed of the Serpent,
and to keepe us at enmity where God hath set it▪ but
for turning <HI>the hearts of the fathers to the children,</HI> and
the reducing of <HI>the disobedient to the wisedome of the just,</HI>
it is our prayer still and still, as it was before, that you
may have the power of <HI>Elias,</HI> or the <HI>Baptist,</HI> as you have
the spirit: and so I come to the last part of the text,
and the second part of <HI>Johns</HI> worke in his Ministration,
<HI>To turne the disobedient to the wisdome of the just.</HI></P>
<P>These words as they lie in our <HI>English</HI> Translation
doe shew no great difficulties, but being examined in
the Originall, they are not so very easie. A man scruple
that appears in both, is this; That the Angel undertaking
to quote the Prophet should so far now decline from his
text:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Difference of allegation.</NOTE> In the former part that we have newly handled,
he followeth him punctually and <HI>verbatim, He shall turne
the hearts of the fathers to the children,</HI> so saith the Pro∣phet,
and so the Angel; but now that he should have
taken up the other part in these words, <HI>And the hearts of
the children to the fathers,</HI> he changeth them into this
clause,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Reason of it▪</NOTE> <HI>And the disobedient to the wisdome of the just.</HI> But
to this may be answered. 1. That the Angel is not so
<PB N="42" REF="24"/>
punctuall to cite the very letter of the Prophet as to give
the sense. And so we may observe it to be usuall in the
new Testament, in its allegations from the old. And
that he giveth the same sense, or a true interpretation of
the Prophet, we shall see as we goe. 2. It was not very
long after the Baptizing and Preaching of <HI>John,</HI> that
the Jews ceased to be a Church and Nation, nay even in
the time of him himselfe, they shewed themselves ene∣mies
to the Gospel, and to the Professors of the same,
for the generall or greatest part of them; therefore he
saith not that the hearts of the children the Gentiles,
should be turned to their fathers the Jewes, which
should cease to be fathers and to be a people, but <HI>to the
wisedome of the just.</HI> And thus in the first part of his
speech about turning <HI>the hearts of the fathers to the chil∣dren,</HI>
he intimateth the Jewes that should be reconci∣led
and united to the Gentiles in imbracing the Gospel:
and in this latter, by omitting to call them <HI>Fathers,</HI> he
giveth a touch of the hostility and evill minde that the
others of the Jewes should beare both to it, and to the
Gentiles that imbraced it. And now that we see the
reason and difference in the allegation, let us take up the
words that thus differ, every one single, and one after
another as they lie in order; and would the time permit,
every word would afford us matter profitably to insist
upon, but I will onely hint it as we goe along, for I feare
to offend in transgressing the time.</P>
<P>1. As in this clause he refuseth to use the terme of <HI>fa∣thers,</HI>
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Disobedient.</NOTE> for the reason mentioned, so doth he also of the
correlative <HI>children,</HI> because of his refusing of that.
And yet he coucheth the sense of that title under the
word <HI>disobedient,</HI> which in its most proper and naturall
<PB N="43" REF="24"/>
signification reflecteth upon untowardly children diso∣bedient
to their parents. For though there be a disobe∣dience
to any Superiour whatsoever, as to Kings, Ma∣gistrates,
Masters, and the like, yet is the obedience of
children to Parents the Originall from whence it re∣ceiveth
denomination, and that appeareth in that those
Superiours are called <HI>Fathers.</HI> As therefore the Angel
omitting to call the Jewes <HI>Fathers,</HI> insinuateth their op∣position
against the Gospel, so by terming the Gentiles
<HI>Disobedient</HI> in stead of <HI>Children,</HI> he sheweth what they
were before they imbraced it.</P>
<P>The vulgar Latine in stead of <HI>Disobedient</HI> readeth <HI>In∣credulous</HI>
or unbeleeving:<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Dis∣obedient or unbeleeving.</NOTE> which though the Greek word
doth sometime signifie, as might be evidenced in divers
instances, yet that it doth not so in this place may be
collected from these considerations. First, that the
speech is concerning children and fathers, as is apparent
in the clause preceding, and betweene them <HI>disobedi∣ence</HI>
is a more proper terme and notion then <HI>Inoredulity.</HI>
Secondly, that he saith not, <HI>He shall turne them to the
faith,</HI> which were the most proper if he spake of the un∣beleeving,
but to the <HI>wisdom</HI> of the righteous. And third∣ly,
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth. 1. 4.</NOTE> that the preaching of the <HI>Baptist,</HI> was more especi∣ally
the doctrine of repentance as his Baptisme was <HI>the
Baptisme of repentance,</HI> but the preaching of Christ was
the doctrine of faith. Therefore <HI>John</HI> saith onely, <HI>Re∣pent,
Matth.</HI> 3. 2. but our Saviour, <HI>Repent and beleeve,
Mar.</HI> 1. 15.</P>
<P>Now from this double signification of the Originall
word, and indeed also from the proper cause of the
Heathens disobedience,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Observ.</NOTE> we might observe, <HI>that a chiefe
and maine cause of disobedience is unbeliefe.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="44" REF="25"/>
It is a saying of the Jewes in their <HI>Talmud</HI> in the
Treatise <HI>Maccoth,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Rab. Abhuhabh in Ner. 1.</NOTE> <HI>that all those sixe hundred and thir∣teene
Commandements that God gave to</HI> Moses <HI>in Mount</HI>
Sinai, <HI>are reduced to this one in the Prophet</HI> Habakkuk,
<HI>The just by his faith shall live:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Hab. 2, 4.</NOTE> we may say something
the like concerning sinnes; that those hundreds and
thousands of transgressions that are committed in the
world, and all those various and numerous causes and
occasions from whence they proceed, they may all in
fine be traced and reduced to this one Originall, <HI>from un∣beliefe.</HI>
From whence is it that men doe violate the com∣mands
of the Law? because they will not beleeve the
threatnings upon the violation. And whence is it, that
men refuse the promises of the Gospel? because they
will not beleeve the certainty and excellency of those
promises.</P>
<P>2. The word <HI>Wisedome</HI> in this place doth signifie <HI>Re∣ligion,</HI>
as it doth in divers other places of the Scripture,
as <HI>Deut.</HI> 4. 6. Keepe therefore and doe the Statutes and
commandements of the Lord, <HI>for this is your wisedome:</HI>
that is, your Religion. And so likewise, <HI>Psal. 111. 10.
The feare of the Lord is the beginning of wisedome:</HI> that
is, the feare of the Lord is the entry into Religion. And
so may we finde the word to signisie in divers passages
in the <HI>Proverbs.</HI> And to this sense me thinkes <HI>Eliphaz</HI>
scoffeth religious <HI>Job</HI> in the fourth of that booke and the
sixth verse if it be looked into in the Originall.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: <HI>Folly▪</HI> Psal. 85. 9.</NOTE> <HI>Halo
jireatheca chislatheca, Is not thy feare</HI> or thy Religion be∣come
<HI>thy folly?</HI></P>
<P><HI>Religion is the onely wisedome,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Observ.</NOTE> <HI>and to be truly wise, is to
be truly religious:</HI> (which is the observation that we
might take up upon this word) But, where or what,
<PB N="45" REF="25"/>
saith this miserable comforter, is this religious wise∣dome
of thine become now? Thou hast beene thus
and thus precise and devout, thus and thus pious and
religious, and what is now become of all this great de∣votion,
but a fearfull affliction? <HI>Is not now thy Religion be∣come
thy folly?</HI></P>
<P>But there is yet a double scruple, and those no small
ones neither, in this small clause or parcell of <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,
<HI>To the wisedome.</HI></P>
<P>First, it is something harsh to translate the Greeke
word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, in this place to signifie <HI>To:</HI> for though it doe
sometimes signifie so, as Commentaries quote certaine
other places, to justifie that translation of it in this, yet
1. That is but rarely and but somewhat improperly
wheresoever it is so used; and 2. It cannot be imagi∣ned
that if the Angel intended that very sense of <HI>To</HI> in
this place, as to say, <HI>To the wisedome,</HI> but that he would
have used the word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, which he used immediately be∣fore
in the other clause, and say, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, as he had
said, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, and not have betaken himselfe to a con∣struction
of the preposition <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, harsh, scrupulous, and
unusuall. I conceive therfore that that little particle is to
be taken here, in its most proper, genuine and generall
sense, and as it is used millions of times in Greeke, Au∣thors
to signifie <HI>In:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. In the wisdome</NOTE> and to be interpreted <HI>in the wisdome.</HI>
And <HI>the wisedome of the righteous</HI> is not here to be
held the <HI>terminus ad quem,</HI> or the ultimate end to which
these <HI>disobedient</HI> Gentiles were to be converted; but the
<HI>medium per quod,</HI> the meanes or way through which
they were to be converted to God. For let the two
clauses of this speech of the Angel, or the parts of the
worke of the <HI>Baptist</HI> be laid in <HI>Antithesis</HI> or opposition
<PB N="46" REF="26"/>
against another, as naturally indeed they lie, the one
aiming at the Jewes as the proper subject, and the o∣ther
at the Gentiles, the subject as proper, and then will
it appeare very plainely, that two severall acts were to
be performed by the <HI>Baptist</HI> as concerning the Jewes
and their conversion. First, that he should turne their
hearts or affections to God, as it is laid downe in the
verse preceding; <HI>He shall turne many of the children of</HI>
Israel <HI>to the Lord their God.</HI> And secondly, that he should
turne their hearts and affections also to the Gentiles, as
it is in this, <HI>He shall turne the hearts of the fathers to the
children.</HI> According therefore to this double worke of
<HI>John</HI> upon the Jewes in that part of the Angels speech,
must the like duplicity be looked for in this that concer∣neth
the Gentiles, and to be understood though it be
not expressed. For the Angel in this part purposely
changeth his stile, and neither calleth the Gentiles <HI>chil∣dren,</HI>
but <HI>disobedient,</HI> because they generally were so be∣fore
the comming of Christ, nor the Jewes <HI>fathers,</HI> be∣cause
they ceased to be so shortly after, as was touched
before, nor mentioneth he the Gentiles turning to God,
but includeth it, partly he had set that as the chiefest
bent and worke of the <HI>Baptist,</HI> to turne men to God,
and partly he involveth it in this phrase, <HI>in the wisedome
of the righteous.</HI> So that this being the meaning of the
Angel, as I doubt not but it is, it may afford us this Ob∣servation,
<NOTE PLACE="marg">Observ.</NOTE> <HI>That there can be no true conversion unto God,
but in the true Religion, or in the wisedome of the just.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, the word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, which commeth next
unto our handling, will afford a twofold consideration.
1. That it is not without divine reason, that <HI>the hearts of the
Gentiles</HI> are not said to be turned to the Jewes, as on the
<PB N="47" REF="26"/>
contrary it was said of the Jews to the Gentiles, but that
they should be turned <HI>in the wisedome of the righteous.</HI>
For the enmity and feud, detestation and aversenesse
that was betwixt Jew and Gentile, and Gentile and
Jew,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The cause of a <HI>Jews</HI> hatred of a <HI>Gentile.</HI></NOTE> proceeded not from the same cause and Originall.
The Jew abhorred the Gentile not of ignorance, but
of scorne and and jealousie, partly because they stood
upon their owne priviledge of being the people of God,
which the other were not, and partly because they were
provoked with suspition, that the other might be the
people of God when they should not be. And there∣fore
when the reconciliation is to be wrought betweene
them, it is said, that their hearts or affections should be
<HI>turned</HI> to them, for they were pointblanke and diametri∣cally
against them before. But the Gentile abhorred a
Jew out of ignorance, because of his Religion, hating
him as a man separate from, and contrary to all the men
in the world, accounting that to be but singular and
senselesse superstition, which was indeed the divine com∣mand
and wisedome, whereby he sequestred that peo∣ple
for his owne from all other people on the earth. So
that a Gentile did not so much detest the person of a
Jew for himselfe, as for his Religion and profession,
which, ignorant as the Heathen were, they understood
not what it meant. Therefore when the Gentiles must
be brought to knit and to unite to the Jewes, it must be
<HI>in the wisedome of the righteous,</HI> or in the imbracing of
that Religion, which the righteous ones among the
Jewes professed, and which the Gentiles, till they knew
and understood what it meant, accounted but vanity,
singularity and folly.</P>
<P>2. It is remarkable that the Angel doth forsake the
<PB N="48" REF="27"/>
proper and common word used to signifie <HI>wisedome,</HI>
which is <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. and taketh up <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, which is of a some∣thing
stricter and stranger use. And so doth the Syriack
relinquish <HI>Hhechmetho</HI> its ordinary word that it useth
for <HI>wisdom,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 2. 2. 4, 5, 6 Rev. 13. 16. &amp;c.</NOTE> and fixeth upon <HI>Jedhangro</HI> a word more sin∣gular,
and of more peculiar importance. The Originall
word then that we have in hand, doth not onely import
the wisedome or Religion of the Jewes, but also the
Gentiles attaining to the knowledge, and apprehension
of that Religion and wisedome with them. Not onely
the theory and practise of the Jewish Nation in their
religious profession, but the Heathens reaching to the
understanding of those mysteries in that Religion and
profession, which they had accounted such vanity and
senselesnesse before. So that this word considerately
looked into will afford us this collection:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Observ.</NOTE> <HI>That it is not
enough to imbrace the true Religion in outward profession,
but we are to have understanding, and to be acquainted
with the doctrine and principles of that Religion.</HI> For the
Heathen to turne to the <HI>wisedome of the righteous</HI> Jewes
in an outside profession, and an ignorant religiousnesse,
was a poore conversion, as good as none, a worke un∣fit
the paines of the <HI>Baptist;</HI> but their true turning, and
his powerfull worke is when they are brought to im∣brace
that Religion in the knowledge and understan∣ding
of the mysteries of it. Ignorance was never the
mother of any devotion but of a Romish devotion,
which is as good or as bad as none.</P>
<P>And lastly, there is some doubtfulnesse also in the
last word <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, for it may be indifferently translated
<HI>of righteous things,</HI> or <HI>of righteous men:</HI> But it is the
more undoubted that persons and persons are rather
<PB N="49" REF="27"/>
here compared together then persons and things: in the
former part of this work of the <HI>Baptist,</HI> there are fathers
and children, and in this part it is most like that they are
answered with persons againe, disobedient children and
righteous fathers, and the meaning of the Angel to be
this, that as the Jews the fathers in the imbracing of the
Gospel, shall be turned to God, &amp; reconciled to the Gen∣tiles,
so the Gentiles the children, in the wisdome of the
righteous, or in the imbracing and understanding of the
Religion professed by the righteous ones that had bin &amp;
were among the Jewes, should be turned to God and in
affection to the Jewes. And hereupon might we take
up this observation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Observ.</NOTE> <HI>that the faith of the holy Jewes un∣der
the Law, and of the holy Gentiles under the Gospel,
was one and the same:</HI> They that went before Christ in
the one, and they that followed Christ in the other, did
both cry <HI>Hosanna to the Sonne of</HI> David, did both ob∣taine
salvation, by the same Saviour and by the same
way.</P>
<P>And so have I gone with the words as farre as I dare
be bold upon the time, your patience and occasions: I
will but put this last clause together which I have thus
taken peece-meale, and laid asunder, and so have I done.
<HI>The disobedient to the wisedome of the righteous▪</HI> the Hea∣then
to the knowledge of the true Religion: Me thinkes
in these words we may behold the condition of this
Land as it hath beene in ancient times, and as it is in
these of ours. We were once <HI>Loammi,</HI> no people of the
Lords, and utter aliens from his congregation: we sate,
and that not very long agoe, in darknesse and in the
shadow of death, and it is no wonder if we might be
called <HI>Disobedient:</HI> But God who is good to all, and
<PB N="50" REF="28"/>
whose tender mercies are over all his workes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 145. 9.</NOTE> hath come
in unto us and shone upon us. He hath discharged us of
the name of Heathens, oh that we could discharge our∣selves
of the title of <HI>Disobedient!</HI> he hath brought us
<HI>into the wisedome of the righteous,</HI> unto the knowledge of
the Gospel, and of salvation, oh that we could drive on
through that to God! He hath made us more <HI>Israel</HI> then
<HI>Israel</HI> it selfe, and whereas we were once the furthest off
of any Nation from this <HI>wisedome,</HI> he hath brought this
<HI>wisedome</HI> to us, to no Nation nearer. Now what thank∣fulnesse
doth so great a mercy call for, for its bestow∣ing?
and what prayers for its continuance? Blessed be
the Lord God of <HI>Israel</HI> which thus hath visited his peo∣ple
with his Gospel, and redeemed them out of the dark∣nesse
of superstition. And the blessing of the God of
<HI>Israel</HI> be still upon his own gift, that it may continue and
still flourish among us: Let not the Candle which he
himselfe hath lighted be ever put out: Nor let the Can∣dlesticke
which he himselfe hath placed, be ever moved
out of its place: Let scattered Popery never cloud us a∣gaine,
nor superstition overwhelme us. Let Religion
and the Gospel be in all our borders, and peace and
truth in all our times. And to these our prayses, and to
these our prayers let all the people say <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Amen</HI> and <HI>Amen.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="license">
<PB REF="28"/>
<HEAD>Die Mercurii <DATE>29. Martii. 1643.</DATE></HEAD>
<P>IT is this day Ordered by the Commons House of
Parliament, that Sir <HI>Edward Littleton,</HI> a Member of
the said House, doe returne thankes to Mr. <HI>Lightfoote,</HI>
for the great paines he tooke in the Sermon he preached
this day at Saint <HI>Margarets</HI> in the City of <HI>Westminster,</HI>
at the intreaty of the said House, it being the day of pub∣like
Humiliation; and that he intreat him to Print his
Sermon: And it is Ordered that no man shall Print the
said Sermon but who shall be authorized under the
handwriting of the said Mr. <HI>Lightfoote.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>H. Elsyng <HI>Cler. Parl. D. Com.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="appointment to print">
<P>I appoint <HI>Andrew Crooke</HI>
to Print my Sermon.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>John Lightfoote.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

