<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Anthropolatria; or The sinne of glorying in men, especially in eminent ministers of the gospel. Wherein is set forth the nature and the causes of this sinne, as also the many pernicious effects which at all times this sinne hath produced, and with which the church of Christ is still infected. With some serious disswasives from this sinne, and directions to prevent the infection thereof. A discourse usefull, and in these times very seasonable. / By John Tombes, B.D. and preacher of Gods word at the Temple.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Tombes, John, 1603?-1676.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A94728</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing T1792</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E282_13</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R200049</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99860852</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99860852</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">158483</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A94728)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158483)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E282[13])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Anthropolatria; or The sinne of glorying in men, especially in eminent ministers of the gospel. Wherein is set forth the nature and the causes of this sinne, as also the many pernicious effects which at all times this sinne hath produced, and with which the church of Christ is still infected. With some serious disswasives from this sinne, and directions to prevent the infection thereof. A discourse usefull, and in these times very seasonable. / By John Tombes, B.D. and preacher of Gods word at the Temple.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Tombes, John, 1603?-1676.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[4], 19, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London, :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by G. Miller for John Bellamy at the signe of the three golden-Lions in Cornehill hear the Royall-Exchange,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1645.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 9th".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-06.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Deadly sins --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Pride and vanity --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Latta</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A94728">
<STC T="W">T1792</STC>
<STC T="T">E282_13</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99860852</BIBNO>
<VID>158483</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>ANTHROPOLATRIA;
OR,
THE SINNE
Of glorying in Men,
ESPECIALLY
In Eminent Ministers of the Gospel.</P>
<P><HI>Wherein is set forth</HI>
The Nature and Causes of this Sinne,
AS ALSO
The many pernicious effects which at all times this
Sinne hath produced, and with which the Church
of CHRIST is still infected.</P>
<P>WITH
Some serious disswasives from this Sinne, and Directions
to prevent the infection thereof.</P>
<P>A Discourse usefull, and in these times very seasonable.</P>
<P>By JOHN TOMBES, B. D. and Preacher of
Gods Word at the <HI>Temple.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by <HI>G. Miller</HI> for <HI>John Bellamy</HI> at the Signe of the three
golden-Lions in Cornehill near the Royall-Exchange, 1645.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="excerpt">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>M<SUP>r</SUP> Gataker in his Answer to M<SUP>r</SUP> Walkers Vindication, pag. 85.</HEAD>
<P>I Love not siding in Gods Church, among Christs Ministers especially, I love
not, I am for this man, and I am for that man: I am for this side, and I am for
that side. The Apostle himselfe liked it not, 1 <HI>Cor. 1. 12. Rom.</HI> 16. 18. I love not
holding the faith of Christ with respect of persons. Another Apostle forbids it,
<HI>Iames</HI> 2. 1. I love not that any be tied to follow any one man, or any number of men
whatsoever in all things. The Apostles themselves required it not in matter of fact,
1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 11. 1. nor may any now living in matters of faith. Hence proceeded schismes,
1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 3. 3. and 11. 18, 19. and factions, and uncharitabble censures, many
times of those as unsound, that are it may be, more sincere, have at least as good
a share in Christ, as those that so censure them. And surely if the words heresie
and heretick were rightly understood, or if they be so taken (as I suppose them
to be constantly used in Scriptute; nor doe I thinke that the contrary can be ea∣sily
evinced) the one for faction, <HI>Acts</HI> 5. 17. and 15. 5. and 24. 5, 14. and 26. 5.
and 28. 22. 1 <HI>Cor. 11. 18, 19. Gal.</HI> 5. 20. the other for a factious person, <HI>Tit.</HI> 3. 10.
none I feare will be found more truly guilty of heresie, or better to deserve the title
of heretick, then those, who (therein concurring with the Papists, whom yet they
professe most to abhorre) are so prone to contemne all as hereticks, and tainted
with heresie in their sence, that is, as men cut off from Christ, and having no in∣terest
in him, who doe not in all matters of practise comply, or in all points of
doctrine concurre with themselves. Or their side, Lord, let me never be: let my
soule never enter into their secret. Neither is it, nor shall ever be my desire, either
so to pin my faith upon the sleeve of any part or party, or to engage my judgement
to any meere mans or mens opinions (the Pen-men of holy writ only excepted)
as to admit hand over head, whatsoever he or they shall hold and maintaine: nor
yet againe to refuse or reject any truth, which by the light that God shall be pleased
to send me, I shall be able to descry in the writing of any, though otherwise never
be erroneous or unsound.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To my worthy Friend M<SUP>r</SUP> James Russel
Merchant.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ome years are elapsed, since I tooke notice, and became
sensible of that sin which this Tract here declaimes a∣gainst.
Being driven by men, but led by the marvel∣lous
providence of God to this City, I observed my
feares did not deceive me; but as then I did divine, so it is come to
passe, that this sin hath filled this City with rents and errours; where∣by
the spirit of supplication and walking humbly with our God, the
spirit of love, minding the publike, and seeking one anothers good
hath left us, and instead hereof an evill spirit of censuring, scoffing,
insulting on weaknesses, wrangling, maintaining particular parties,
projecting how to promote selfe ends with neglect of the publike,
evill jealousies and reports of one another, and which is to be feared,
inward rejoycing at one anothers harmes, hath overtaken even a
great number of those, who a few yeares agoe seemed to be of another
temper. I have now out of a deepe sense of the evils this sin hath
brought upon us, resolved to publish this Treatise, as a monitory to
men, to avoid this idolizing of men, as an evill savour that may
infect them, and to purge it out of their spirits as an evill humour
that may engender dangerous fevers in their soules, and is likely
to make this generation worse and worse; And as a forerunner to
such Works as God shall enable me to publish, for clearing of the
truth to those that in this time are deceived, by their dependence on
their admired Teachers: The memorable kindnesses which you
have been pleased to exhibit to me in my low estate, and the cordiall
affection I perceive you beare to the prosperity of Christs King∣dome,
engage me to present this Sermon to you, as for your use, so for
some testimony of his gratitude, who desires to approve himselfe</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours in the service of Christ,
JOHN TOMBES.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>From my Study at the Temple
<DATE>this 8<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>May,</HI> 1645.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="table of contents">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Contents.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>§ <HI>I.</HI> THe state of the City of Corinth.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>II.</HI> The state of the Church of Corinth.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>III.</HI> That glorying in men is a sinne.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>IIII.</HI> That glorying in men which is here forbidden, is glorying
in the Teachers of the Church.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>V.</HI> The conceit, that here the Apostle useth a figure of fi∣ction
of persons.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>VI.</HI> This conceit is refuted, and it is proved, that glorying in
true Apostles is here forbidden.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>VII.</HI> The objection to the contrary, answered.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>VIII.</HI> What glorying in true Teachers is here forbidden, declared
negatively.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>IX.</HI> What glorying in true Teachers is here forbidden, declared
affirmatively.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>X.</HI> Reasons of the prohibition, taken from the nature of this sin.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>XI.</HI> Reasons of the prohibition, taken from the causes of this sin.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>XII.</HI> Reasons of the prohibition, taken from the many pernitious
effects that follow upon this sinne.</ITEM>
<ITEM>§ <HI>XIII.</HI> Application the first, in a discovery of this evill, as still in∣fecting
the Church of Christ.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Application the second, in a serious disswasive from this sin in these
times, with some directions to prevent the infection thereof.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="treatise">
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>ANTHROPOLATRIA;
OR,
The Sinne of glorying in Men,
Especially in eminent Ministers of the Gospell.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>1 COR. 3. 21.</BIBL>
<Q><P>Therefore let no man glory in men, for all things are yours.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ I.</HEAD>
<HEAD>The state of the City of Corinth.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">F</SEG>Or a more perspicuous understanding of this Scrip∣ture,
something is to be premised concerning the
City and Church of <HI>Corinth.</HI></P>
<P>The City was seated on the necke of Land,
which parts <HI>Peloponesus</HI> from the rest of <HI>Greece,</HI>
very convenient for traffique, by reason of the
meeting of two Seas there, whence it is tearmed by <HI>Horace, bima∣ris
Corinthus, Corinth that was washed by two Seas;</HI> the one fit
to bring in Commodities from <HI>Italy, Cicily,</HI> and other Countries
towards the South and West, the other fit to bring in Commodi∣ties
from <HI>Asia, Macedonia,</HI> and other Countries towards the East
and North. By reason of which conveniencies, and the Grecian
games exercised neare to it,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Theog. Gnom.</NOTE> which drew a great confluence of peo∣ple
thither, and some other causes, that City grew very populous
and rich, and this made them (as usually it doth) luxurious and
proud:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Eò quod legati appellati erane superbius, Ci∣cer. orat pro lege Manilia.</NOTE> whereby they became insolent, and by their haughty spee∣ches
provoked the <HI>Romans</HI> to destroy that City under the Conduct
of L. <HI>Mummius:</HI> but being in <HI>Augustus Caesars</HI> time reedified,
it recovered quickly its former beauty and wealth.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="section">
<PB N="2" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>§ II.</HEAD>
<HEAD>The state of the Church of Corinth.</HEAD>
<P>TO this City in his travailes to preach the Gospell of Christ,
came S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Paul, Acts</HI> 18. 1. in the dayes of <HI>Claudius,</HI> ver. 2.
and continuing there a great while, much people were added to the
Lord, and a flourishing Church there planted, which being after
watered by <HI>Apollos,</HI> so fructified, that as S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Paul</HI> testifies, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 1.
5. <HI>they were in every thing inriched by Christ in all utterance, and
in all knowledge, so that they came behind in no gift,</HI> ver 7. But as
formerly their earthly riches made them wanton, and insolent, so
now their spirituall gifts made them vaine and contentious: for
instead of a holy imploying and improving their gifts to the ho∣nour
of the giver, they abused them in vaine ostentation of them∣selves,
and glorying in their teachers, which drew them into
schismes and divisions, <HI>one saying, I am of Paul, another, I am of
Apollo, another, I am of Cephas, another, I am of Christ,</HI> ver. 12.
whence they were drawne into factions,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Con in <HI>Tit.</HI> Epist. 1. ad Co∣rinth. edit. à Patric. <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unio. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> insomuch that as <HI>Hierome</HI>
saith, <HI>unusquis{que} eos quos baptizaverat suos putabat esse, non
Christi; each baptizer counted those he baptized his owne, not
Christs;</HI> and <HI>Clement</HI> (if we have his genuine Epistle) that they
jussed out some that deserved well, and hoysed up others that were
light enough, and that numerous Church in stead of being a well
compacted body, became like a dismembred Absyrtus, mangled
into many pieces by reason of their schisme. To remedy which
evill as tending to the scattering of the Church, and blemishing of
the Christian profession, the Apostle bends himselfe in the fore part
of this Epistle, using sundry arguments to shew the absurdity of it,
and in this verse now read unto you, disswades them from that sin,
which was the root of their factious divisions, in these words,
<HI>Therefore let no man glory in men, &amp;c.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ III.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Glorying in men is a sinne.</HEAD>
<P>WHich speech seemes to be a conclusion inferred from the
words fore-going, <HI>ver.</HI> 18, 19, 20. concerning the folly
and vanity of mens thoughts, and containes, 1. A prohibition, <HI>Let
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
no man glory in men;</HI> 2. A reason of this prohibition, <HI>for all
things are yours;</HI> Which is amplified, <HI>ver.</HI> 22, 23. My businesse
will be at this time, to handle the Prohibition, and the Reason so
farre only as it referres to the thing here prohibited; and that the
marke at which we shoote may appeare to you, let the fixed point
be this; <HI>Christians may not glory in men;</HI> if they doe, its their sin,
and that no small one in Gods sight. God hath so ordered our cal∣ling,
saith the Apostle, 1 <HI>Cor. 1. 29. that no flesh should glory in his
presence;</HI> and therefore <HI>ver. 31. According as it is written, he
that glorieth let him glory in the Lord;</HI> Which seemes to be taken
from <HI>Jer. 9. 23, 24. Thus saith the Lord, let not the wise man glory
in his wisedome, neither let the mighty man glory in his might;
let not the rich man glory in his riches, but let him that glorieth
glory in this, that he understandeth and knoweth me, that I am
the Lord, which exercise loving kindnesse, judgement and righ∣teousnesse
in the earth, for in these things I delight saith the Lord.</HI>
Like unto which is that <HI>Isa. 2. 22. Cease ye from man whose breath
is in his nostrils: for wherein is he to be accounted of?</HI> But because
the Apostles words, though generall in forme, as forbidding all glo∣rying
in any men, yet are speciall in the accommodation, as forbid∣ding
glorying in Ministers; therefore I conceive necessary to en∣quire,
1. What glorying in men is here forbidden by the Apostle;
2. Why such glorying is thus forbidden.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ IIII.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Glorying in men here forbidden, is glorying in the
Teachers of the Church.</HEAD>
<P>THe Greeke word translated [<HI>glory</HI>] doth sometimes signifie
the inward esteeme, joy, content, complacency and confidence
we have in a thing, especially when 'tis superabundant, though it
be not outwardly expressed, but for the most part, it notes a full
joy, confidence, esteeme or acquiescence, expressed by words, or o∣ther
signes. Glorying in men, is either when the persons glorying,
and gloried in, are the same, or when they are divers; the former
is, when a man glories in himselfe, and then it is, when a man out
of high esteeme of his own excellency or power, expresseth confi∣dence
in himselfe, or praise of himselfe, which is commonly the vice
of vaine boasting, though it may be sometimes for just cause, as
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 11. 18. But in this place the latter, to wit the glorying in
other men is forbidden, as the reason shewes, for they were not to
glory in some as peculiarly theirs, because all were theirs. And so
to glory in men, is to glory in other men, whom we conceive to
have singular excellency, and our selves to have some proper interest
in them, or relation to them, and accordingly to boast of them,
and the conceived property we have in them. Thus men glory in
their Ancestours, Princes, Generals, Teachers: And the glorying in
this last sort of men particularly as Teachers or Preachers of the
Gospell, is here forbidden, as the occasion of this precept shewes;
for this precept was given upon occasion of their glorying men∣tioned,
<HI>chap.</HI> 1. 12, and the first instance, <HI>ver.</HI> 22. is of eminent
Teachers of the Church, <HI>Paul, Apollos, Cephas;</HI> so that the glorying
here forbidden, is the having, and expressing of high esteeme and af∣fection
towards the Teachers of the Church.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ V.</HEAD>
<HEAD>The conceit, that here the Apostle useth a figure
of fiction of Persons.</HEAD>
<P>BUt then we are further to consider,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Chrys. in 1 Cor. 1. 12. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> whether the Teachers in
whom the Apostle forbids glorying, were the true Teachers or
Apostles, or the false; For there is a conceit in many and eminent
interpreters, that the <HI>Corinthian</HI> sectaries, did not glory in the
names of <HI>Paul,</HI> or <HI>Apollos,</HI> or <HI>Cephas</HI> themselves, but that they
gloried in some false Apostles, the authors of their schisme, but the
Apostle in reproving their schisme,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Hieron.</HI> in 1 Cor. 1. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. sub nomine A∣postolorum Pseudo-aposto∣los tangit.</NOTE> useth the names of the true A∣postles,
as it were under the vizard of the true Apostles concealing
the false: The ground of this conceit, is that speech which S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Paul</HI>
useth, 1 <HI>Cor. 4. 6. And these things brethren I have in a figure
transferred to my selfe and Apollo for your sakes: that ye might
learne in us not to thinke of men</HI> [so our translation adds] <HI>above
that which is written, that no one of you be puffed up for one a∣gainst
another.</HI> Which they understand, as if the Apostle had said,
when I spake of <HI>Paul</HI> and <HI>Apollos,</HI> I used a scheme or figure cal∣led
<HI>fictio personarum, the faining of persons,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Chrysest.</HI> in 1 Cor 1. 12. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> such as the Lawyers
use, when they put the names of <HI>Titius</HI> and <HI>Sempronius,</HI> for some
other men whose case is propounded. And that the Apostle saith,
he had transferred to himselfe the arrogance of the false Apostles,
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
being unworthy to be named, or that he might not offend them,
or that his speech might be lesse grievous to the <HI>Corinthians:</HI> to
this end, that ye might learne in us, that is in our taking it upon us,
not to thinke of men, that is of the false Apostles, above that
which is written, and that no one of you be puffed up with pride,
for one in the extolling of one against another to his contempt.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ VI.</HEAD>
<HEAD>This conceit is refuted, and it is proved, that glorying
in true Apostle is here forbidden.</HEAD>
<P>COncerning which interpretation, <HI>Parcus Com. in 1 Cor.</HI> 1. 12.
speakes thus; <HI>Miror verò hoc loco, omnes fere interpretes
fictionem statuere, quasi quod in pseudo-apostolos competebat,
Paulus ad Apostolorum personas transferat.</HI> That is; <HI>I mar∣vaile
that in this place all Interpreters almost conceive a fiction,
as if the Apostle</HI> Paul <HI>had transferred that to the persons of the
Apostles, which did agree to the false Apostles.</HI> And indeed that
such a fiction should be here made, I conceive to be against plaine
and evident reason. For first if this be so, then it is to be conceived
that the <HI>Corinthians</HI> did not indeed call themselves by the name
of <HI>Paul,</HI> but by the name of some false Apostle, in whose place in
this Epistle S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Paul</HI> hath put his by a fiction. But he that shall
reade <HI>Chap. 1. ver.</HI> 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. may easily perceive by
the relation of this schisme from those of <HI>Cloe,</HI> that the Apostle
intended to set downe a history of that they did, now in narra∣tions
of facts done, no man useth such a fiction. 2. He useth the
name of Christ without a fiction, <HI>ver.</HI> 12. in the same relation:
surely then the names of those Apostles too. 3. To make it yet
clearer, he useth arguments to disswade them from these schismes
in his name. And to cleare himselfe as no occasion or abettour of
them, though his name were used, he alledgeth a thing or acci∣dent
meerely personall, <HI>ver.</HI> 14, 15, 16, 17. 4. When <HI>chap.</HI> 3, 4▪ he
speakes againe of their schisme, he adds to convince them of the
evill in patronizing the schisme by their name, <HI>ver. 5. 6. Who then
is</HI> Paul? <HI>and who is</HI> Apollo? <HI>but Ministers by whom ye believed,
even as the Lord gave to every man. I have planted,</HI> Apollo <HI>wa∣tered;
but God gave the increase.</HI> Now these things cannot be
conceived as tralatitious, for it is said, <HI>they were Ministers by
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
whom they believed, and as the Lord gave to every man, and
that he planted, and</HI> Apollos <HI>watered, but God gave the increase.</HI>
Now these things are true of <HI>Paul</HI> himselfe and <HI>Apollos</HI> himselfe,
as we reade, <HI>Acts</HI> 18. not of any false Apostles. 5. To which I
adde, that I find nothing of the false Apostles, or of disswading
from hearkning to them in this Epistle, but in the second.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ VII.</HEAD>
<HEAD>The objection to the contrary answered.</HEAD>
<P>AS for the objection from 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 4. 6. it is grounded upon an
interpretation that is not congruous to the words of the A∣postle:
For 1. the Apostle is supposed to have put his and <HI>Apol∣lo's</HI>
name instead of the false Apostles, to avoid offence of them, or
conceit of their unworthinesse, but the Apostle sayes, he had trans∣ferred
those things to himselfe and <HI>Apollo's</HI> for the <HI>Corinthians</HI>
sake, not for the false Apostles. 2. He saith he did it to teach them
modesty. Now how the Apostles taking on him their arrogance
might teach them modesty, it is hard to conceive: What modesty
is it to transferre anothers crime on himselfe? But what then are
the things transferred on himselfe and <HI>Apollos,</HI> and how did he
transferre them? <HI>Pareus</HI> conceives they were that which he had
said, <HI>chap. 3. 7. That he which planteth is nothing, and he which
watereth is nothing;</HI> I adde those things which he had said, <HI>chap.</HI>
4 1. <HI>That they were Ministers of Christ, and stewards of the my∣steries
of God.</HI> These things saith he <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, that is, as they
conceive translated by a figure of Rhetoricke: but in that sense I
find it not used any where in the Apostle. I find it used▪ 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 11. 13,
14, 15. signifying the counterfeiting of an habit like a Stage player,
in which sence the Noune <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> is used, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 7. 31. and the deriva∣tive
<GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, 1 <HI>Cor, 14. 30. Rom.</HI> 13. 13. is translated from the
habit of apparell, to the fashion of manners. And <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> is
used, <HI>Phil.</HI> 3. 25. for Christs transmutation of our bodies. I con∣ceive
that in this place the Apostle useth by a Catachresis <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>
for <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, and that he meanes no more but an application
or fashioning of those things he had said, without any change or
translation from any other to himselfe, <HI>that in them they might
learne, not to think of Teachers above that which is written, to
wit,</HI> Mat. 23. 11, 12. <HI>and that no one be puffed in arrogance for one,</HI>
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
that is for the extolling of one <HI>against another,</HI> that is to the despi∣sing
of another.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ VIII.</HEAD>
<HEAD>What glorying in true Teachers is here forbidden,
declared negatively.</HEAD>
<P>BUt what then is the glorying in the true Teachers here for∣bidden?</P>
<P>To this I answer, 1. Negatively, 2. Affirmatively. Negatively
I say, 1. That it is not the magnifying of the Apostles above other
Ministers, by ascribing to them an eminent, and extraordinary au∣thority
in assuring us of the will of God, and in establishing the
Churches. For as they had doubtlesse singular power in working
miracles and in giving the holy Ghost, so had they infallible gui∣dance
of the Spirit of Christ in what they taught, according to our
Saviours promise, <HI>Joh. 16. 13. Howbeit when he, the Spirit of
truth is come, he will guide you into all truth, for he shall not
speake of himselfe; but whatsoever he shall heare, that shall he
speake, and he will shew you things to come.</HI> 2. That it is not the
giving of that regard to the true Teachers, which is due to them as
Ministers of Christ. For the Elders that rule well, are to be ac∣counted
worthy of double honour, especially they who labour in
the word and doctrine, 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 5. 17. 3. That it is not the proper
love to esteeme of, and rejoycing in some as our fathers in Christ,
as the Apostle calls himselfe, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 4. 15. for which cause 'tis like∣ly
<HI>Paul</HI> told <HI>Philemon, that he did owe himselfe unto him,</HI> Philem.
v. 19. 4. That it is not the desire of having, or rejoycing that we
have men of best gifts: For if it be lawfull <HI>to covet earnestly the
best gifts,</HI> 1 Cor. 12. 31. it is lawfull to desire those that have the
best gifts.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ IX.</HEAD>
<HEAD>And affirmatively.</HEAD>
<P>AFfirmatively I say, here is forbidden inordinate glorying in
men which are Teachers, and this is sundry wayes; 1. When
some Teachers are gloried in peculiarly, as if they were the only
Teachers worth the hearing, none else to be regarded. And that
this is the speciall branch of glorying in men here forbidden, is
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
manifest from the Apostles reason why the <HI>Corinthans</HI> should not
glory in men: <HI>because all were theirs, whether Paul, or Apollos,
or Cephas.</HI> It may seeme that some of them accounted <HI>Paul</HI> the
only Teacher, for his singular knowledge in the mystery of Christ,
of which we reade, <HI>Ephes.</HI> 3. 3, 4. Some delighted only in <HI>Apollos,</HI>
because of his eloquence, of which we reade, <HI>Acts</HI> 18. 24. Some
magnified <HI>Peter,</HI> as <HI>non-paril,</HI> whether by reason of his fervency
and zeale, or his seeming dignity among the Apostles, which
seemes to be intimated, 2 <HI>Cor. 12. 11. Gal.</HI> 2. 9. Now this branch
of inordinate glorying in men, the Apostle doth studiously forbid,
as considering that this was the egge out of which their conten∣tions
were hatched, and perhaps foreseeing that in time, out of it
would spring Prelaticall greatnesse, and Antichristian tyranny;
therefore the Apostle forbids this, 1 <HI>Cor. 4 6. that they should be
puffed up for one against another▪</HI> so it is usuall for hearers to take
an inordinate affection, to have an inordinate esteeme of some
Preachers, and thereupon to count them theirs, to glory to be
their followers, disdaining all others as not to be named with
them, though Teachers of truth: because they have an high con∣ceit
of their learning, wit, eloquence, holinesse or the like quality.
2. When the so-magnified Teachers, are esteemed not as servants
to a higher Master, but as Masters themselves. And that thus it
was with those <HI>Corinthians,</HI> it may be gathered in that the Apo∣stle
doth so diligently admonish them to looke higher then him∣selfe
or <HI>Apollos,</HI> that they might not esteeme them authours of
their faith. Thus 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 1. 13. he expostulates with them, <HI>Is
Christ divided? was Paul crucified for you? or were ye baptized
in the name of Paul?</HI> And <HI>chap. 2. 1, 5. when I came to you, I
came not with excellency of speech or of wisedome, that your faith
should not stand in the wisedome of men, but in the power of God:</HI>
and chap. 3. 5, 6, 7. <HI>who then is Paul? and who is Apollos? but
Ministers by whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every
man. I have planted, Apollos watred, but God gave the increase;
so then, neither is he that planteth any thing, neither he that wa∣tereth,
but God that gives the increase:</HI> and 1 Cor. 4. 6. <HI>that ye
might learne in us, not to think above that which is written.</HI> Now
this sin is very incident to many hearers, when they admire some
Teachers wit, eloquence, zeale, holinesse or the like quality, to as∣cribe
their conversion, edification to them; to praise them super∣latively,
<PB N="9" REF="7"/>
to assume their names, forgetting that they are but Gods
instruments, and Christs servants, and that their graces come not
from the abilities of the Teacher, but the power of Christ. Where∣fore
the Apostle, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 4. 7. expostulates thus with these <HI>Corin∣thians:
for who maketh thee to differ from another? and what hast
thou that thou didst not receive? now if thou didst receive it, why
doest thou glory as if thou hadst not received it?</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ X.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Reasons of the prohibition, taken from the nature of this sinne.</HEAD>
<P>NOw the reasons why this inordinate glorying in men is here
forbidden are many, some from the nature of the sin, some
from the causes of it, some from the effects.</P>
<P>The first I shall take from the text it selfe, <HI>because all things
are yours; ye are Christs, and Christ is Gods,</HI> and therefore ye be∣have
your selves unworthy of the great bounty of Christ unto you,
in giving all the Ministers of the Gospell to be yours for your good,
when ye glory in some, and unthankfully despise others. and ye
doe unbeseeming your priviledge who are Christs, not <HI>Pauls,</HI> when
ye account <HI>Paul</HI> the master of your faith, not Christ; magnifie him
as the principall, who is but a subservient instrument. It is un∣thankfullnesse
to a bountifull Prince, when he bestowes many Lord∣ships
on his favourite, if he should regard one of them only, as if
the rest were nought worth: it is an unthankfull and unworthy
part if a Prince by his servant convay a Lordship, the receiver
magnifie the servant and not the Master: so it is in this case when
Christ hath been so liberall, as to give gifts to men in large mea∣sure,
some Apostles, some Prophets, some Evangelists, some Pa∣stors
and teachers, <HI>Ephes.</HI> 4. 11. for the use of his people, to dote
on one, and to ascribe to him that which is due to Christ the su∣preame
donour: for hereby the bounty of Christ is lessened, and
the honour due to him substracted. 2. There's injury done both to
Christ, and to the despised Teachers. To our Lord Christ, in that
the glory that belongs to Christ alone to be the authour of, and to
have the dominion over our faith is ascribed to men: for whereas
our Lord Christ forbad even the Apostles, <HI>Matth. 23. 8, 9, 10.
that they be not called Rabbi: for one is your Master even Christ,
and all ye are brethren; and call no man your father upon the
<PB N="10" REF="8"/>
earth, for one is your Father which is in Heaven: Neither be ye
called Masters; for one is your Master even Christ:</HI> by this
glorying in some Teachers they are made Rabbies, fathers on earth,
and Masters. For what is it to make a man a Rabbi, a father on
earth, a Master, but to glory in him as the authour of our faith; to
esteeme him as the only Teacher, to depend upon his mouth as if
he were another <HI>Pythagoras,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, that he hath said were e∣nough?
now what is this lesse then to unchaire Christ, and to lift
up man into his seate, to deprive the shepheard and bishop of our
soules, and substitute another in his roome? It is in effect all one as
to thanke the Axe for building the house, and to passe by the Car∣penter.
For as <HI>Moses,</HI> so <HI>Paul,</HI> were but <HI>faithfull in Gods house
as servants, but Christ as a Sonne over his own house, whose house
we are,</HI> Heb. 3. 5, 6. 'Tis injurious also to the despised Teacher, in
that he is contemned, whom Christ hath honoured to make a Tea∣cher
of truth, a servant of his: but this we shall further consider
when we speake of the reasons from the effects of glorying in men.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="11" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ XI.</HEAD>
<HEAD>From the Causes of it.</HEAD>
<P>THe Causes hereof minister also reasons unto us of the prohibi∣tion
of it. For whence comes it that there is such evill glory∣ing
in men, but from a spirituall dotage, or childishnesse in under∣standing,
inordinate affection in the will? Therefore are men glo∣ried
in, because they are over esteemed, over loved, either for their
supposed eloquence, or learning, or zeale, or spirituall graces, or au∣thority,
or power, or benefiting them, or suiting with their fancies,
or some such like cause. The admiring mens persons is oft <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,
<HI>Jude</HI> 16. by reason of some advantage or benefit: now all
these Causes doe import some errour or perversenesse of the soule,
which are alwayes evill.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Zanch.</HI> Tom. 4. lib. 1. cap. 11. Thes. 4. Tollat Deus <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as idolo∣latrias ex ec∣clesiâ, nam ado∣rare homine<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> &amp; eorum pla∣ci<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a idololatria est.</NOTE> Yea 'tis no small evill to admire men
when we should magnifie Christ, to delight in the picture instead
of the prototype, to glory in the servant in the place of the Ma∣ster;
in <HI>Zanchius</HI> his judgement it is no lesse then idolatry. Assu∣redly
it is an earthly affection, it is but <HI>wisedome of the flesh,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,
not of Gods Spirit, and <HI>therefore enmity against God:</HI> ad∣verse
to his Law, 1 <HI>Cor. 3. 4. In lowlinesse of mind, each man is
to esteeme others better then himselfe:</HI> yet <HI>no man is to think of
<PB N="11" REF="8"/>
another,</HI> no not of an Apostle, <HI>above that which is meet,</HI> 1 Cor. 4. 6.
In charity we are <HI>to seeke, not our own, but every man anothers
wealth, to believe all things, to hope all things:</HI> yet not to seeke
the elevation of one, to the disparagement of another, to <HI>be puffed
up for one against another,</HI> or to conceive of one above that he is
to a derogation of Christs prerogative.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="12" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ XII.</HEAD>
<HEAD>From the many pernicious effects that follow upon it.</HEAD>
<P>BUt the evill of this sin is most cleerely seen in the pernicious
effects that are consequent upon it, which are many: As 1. it
is a direct cause of schismes: so it was among these <HI>Corinthians;</HI>
their glorying in <HI>Paul, Apollos, Cephas,</HI> made them say, <HI>I am of
Paul, I am of Apollos, I am of Cephas:</HI> it causeth the people to
divide themselves one from another, under different Teachers, in
whom they glory: and it causeth Teachers to sever those that af∣fect
them, from other teachers whom they affect not so much:
for <HI>occasio facit furem,</HI> advantage to doe evill is a great incitement
to attempt it. Sundry are the causes of schismes, sometimes the
pride, tyranny, heterodoxie of the Teachers, and then they are ju∣stifiable
in the people, the power of Pastors not being Lordly, but
fatherly, <HI>pedo non sceptro,</HI> not in a compulsory, but a directory
way: sometimes the causelesse hatred or contempt of the people
towards some Pastors; the vaine esteeme, light affection towards
others causeth a schisme; and then the Pastours are free, the people
are under the guilt. And it is no small sin, whether from the Pa∣stours
or peoples priding in guifts that a schisme is made; whereas
the end of Gods Spirit in bestowing of guifts is, that <HI>there might
be no schisme in the body,</HI> but <HI>that the members should have the
same care one for another,</HI> 1 Cor. 12. 25. Now schismes are contra∣ry
to Christian unity and love, cause great alteration of heart in
one member from another, substraction of mutuall helps, hin∣derance
in the growth of the body, neglect of praying one for ano∣ther;
yea bitternesse, disdaine, hatred, and the effects of these, decli∣ning
of society, excommunicating each other, and at last violence,
and bloud, and these are bad enough.</P>
<P>2. The prohibited glorying in men, doth expose the Christian
profession to obloquy and contempt▪ for whereas it is the honour
<PB N="12" REF="9"/>
of the Christian profession, <HI>that they have one body, one spirit, one
Lord, one faith, one baptisme, one God and Father of all,</HI> Ephes. 4.
5, 6. by the glorying in some Teachers afore others, the Christian
society is made like the severall Schooles of Philosophers, some fol∣lowing
<HI>Plato,</HI> some <HI>Aristotle,</HI> some <HI>Zeno,</HI> some <HI>Epicurus;</HI> their do∣ctrines
accounted but as the proper opinions or placita of severall
teachers; not proceeding from one and the same Spirit of God, but
singularity of conceit; and zeale for them is conceived to arise, not
from a certaine knowledge of heavenly truth, but from strength of
fancie, and peculiar humour: which thing is a great stumbling block
to those that are without, keeping them back from embracing the
truth, and an occasion of laying open the profession of it to derision.</P>
<P>3. By glorying in men, as there is an over high esteeme of the
guifts of some, so there is an undervaluing of the guifts of others:
which thing as it is an unworthy abuse of those various guifts Christ
giveth to his Church, so doth it inferre an injurious imputation to
the Spirit of God by whom they are bestowed. For as it is said,
Prov. 17. 5. <HI>Who so mocketh the poore, reproacheth his maker who
made him such:</HI> so it may be said by parity of reason; he that des∣piseth
those that are of small guifts, reproacheth the Spirit of God,
as if he were defective in his guifts; whereas the variety of guifts,
and the bestowing of them in different measures, sets forth the full∣nesse
and freenesse of Gods Spirit, <HI>who worketh all those, dividing
to every man severally as he will,</HI> 1 Cor. 12. 11.</P>
<P>4. By the inordinate glorying in some, and despising of others,
the despised persons are often discouraged and disheartned, to the
detriment of the Church of God, and the grievance of the despised.
For the remembrance of contempt, is apt to cause dejectednesse
and griefe of heart, which alwayes benums a mans spirit, and enfee∣bles
him, and clogges him in his work: Thus the heart is made sad,
which should not be made sad; and the sparke that should be
blowne up by incouragements that it may flame forth, is extin∣quished,
and <HI>the Spirit quenched,</HI> contrary to the Apostles war∣ning,
1 <HI>Thes.</HI> 5. 19 20.</P>
<P>5. By glorying in Teachers, it falls out that they are puffed up
and perverted: much experience hath confirmed this as true, that
popular applause hath filled Teachers with vaine glory, and made
them adulterate the word of God to please their auditors. S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Paul</HI>
tells us of the false Apostles among the <HI>Galatians,</HI> Gal. 4. 17. <HI>that
<PB N="13" REF="9"/>
they did zealously</HI> (in shew) <HI>affect them, but not well: intending
to ex<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lude him, that they might affect them.</HI> It is no strange thing
that Teachers perceiving the lightnesse of their auditors, and their
itching eares doe sometimes <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>handle the word
of God deceitfully,</HI> instead of ministring <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>the sin∣cere
milke of the word,</HI> as it is called, 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2. 2. sometimes flatte∣ring
pleasingly, when they should reprehend sharpely; sometimes
balking the vice, they should freely convince of; sometimes inven∣ting
new formes of Teaching, new opinions, sublimate conceites
to fit the desires of the people; making the <HI>Lesbian rule</HI> of their
fancies, the measure of their teaching, and this is a grand evill.</P>
<P>6. This glorying in men, begets an aptnesse to receive their er∣rours,
to imitate their actions, which is the seed of heresies and su∣perstitions:
for admiration and doting love to a person, easily
drawes the admirers to a blind obedience, implicit faith in them,
to an inslaving of their judgements, so as <HI>jurare in verba Magi∣stri.</HI>
It is observed by an historian, that afore the miscarriage of
<HI>Conrade</HI> the Emperour, and <HI>Lewis</HI> the French King, in their expe∣dition
to the Holy Land,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Fuller.</HI> of the holy war, <HI>lib. 2. ch.</HI> 3.</NOTE> to which S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Bernards</HI> Sermons perswa∣ded,
the people were too much transported with an high opinion
of him and his directions; as if that arrow could not misse the
marke that came out of S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Bernards</HI> bowe. Any thing is easily
received from him that we over-much love. Affection makes men
take downe falsities, as the rowling in sugar doth make the sto∣macke
swallow bitter pills:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Cicero lib. 2. de oratore. Advers. haeres▪ cap. 15.</NOTE> as it befell <HI>Fusius,</HI> who so admired
<HI>Fimbria's</HI> eloquence, that he imitated withall his ill-favoured faces
and broad speaking. And God doth often leave the admired Tea∣chers
to erre, for triall of the people, as <HI>Vincent. Lixin.</HI> observes,
alleadging the speech of God, <HI>Deut.</HI> 13. 3. and the admirers of them
to receive errour, according to his just judgement.</P>
<P>7. Adde hereunto, that this gloring in men makes mens endea∣vours
remisse in things necessary, earnest in things vaine; that time
and labour that should be employed in the maine duties of godli∣nesse,
in seeking the advancement of Christs Kingdome, righteous∣nesse,
peace and joy in the Holy Ghost, is often bestowed in magni∣fying
those in whom they glory, upholding their party, promoting
their opinions: whence it is, that such as are followers of those in
whom they glory, constant hearers of them, much in commenda∣tion
of them, have their sayings and tenents <HI>ad unguem,</HI> declare
<PB N="14" REF="10"/>
much zeale in their way, yet prove but unskilfull in the chiefe do∣ctrines
of Christian religion, defective in the power of true godli∣nesse,
in the mortifying of corruptions, such as pride, impatience,
self-conceitednesse, rashnesse, covetousnesse; and in the practice of
righteousnesse, mercy, meeknesse, diligence in their own businesse
and the like; in the provoking one another to love and good works.</P>
<P>8. On the contrary, the word of God though soundly and truly
delivered, is neglected, being either not heard, or without fruit,
when it is spoken by such a Teacher as they affect not, but disdai∣ned,
censured, contemned. The prejudice against one, through com∣parative
extolling of another, causeth the teaching of the sleighted
person, though orthodox, holy, learned, to be passed over, to be cen∣sured
as barren, dry, hungry stuffe, though it be the true word of
God, as if no teaching were wholesome meate, but such as is wet
with their affected Teachers spittle, I meane his phrase, method,
action, elocution; as if <HI>fides aestimanda esset ex personis, non perso∣nae
ex fide,</HI> as <HI>Tertullians</HI> phrase is, or as if <HI>our faith stood not in
the power of God, but in the wisedome of men,</HI> as the Apostle
speakes, 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 2, 5.</P>
<P>9. By this meanes the rule of Christianity is changed; for where∣as▪
the rule and ground of our faith and obedience is the word of
God as Gods word, through the addicting themselves to some
mens authority, Gods truth stands at their devotion for its accep∣tance:
hence they that of old gloried in the Pharisees as their Rab∣bins,
regarded not Gods commands, but as pleased the Pharisees,
and they that this day glory in the Pope, or the Church as they call
it, regard the Scriptures so farre only as the Pope or Church allow
them, and they that depend on their magnified Teachers of any
other sort, doe regard the word of God, but as it beares their image,
or comes from their mint; and so as it was said of the heathens al∣lowing
or disallowing of gods by their Senates decree, <HI>Deus non
erit Deus, nisi homo velit, God shall not be God, unlesse man will;</HI>
it may be said in this case, Gods word shall not be Gods word, un∣lesse
man will.</P>
<P>10. Lastly, They that glory in men, are either inconstant in their
affections, as experience often shewes, they that one while would
pluck out their eyes for him whom they magnifie, will at another
time revile and hate him: for mens minds are mutable, and the
best of men are but men, that is, imperfect, and will be so found,
<PB N="15" REF="10"/>
and therefore will not alwayes satisfie, or else if they be still affe∣cted,
yet they be but mortall, and the sorrow for their losse will be
excessive, more then should be for a creature, an arbitrary instru∣ment;
for immoderate affection to a thing while we have it, causeth
immoderate sorrow for it when we loose it.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="13" TYPE="section">
<HEAD>§ XIII.</HEAD>
<HEAD>In a discovery of this evill, as still in festing the Church of Christ.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="application">
<P>THe first use hereof is to endite those that are guilty of this sin of
glorying in men,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Applic.</NOTE> of a breach of a Statute of Christ against his
Crown and dignity, and the peace of his Church. In the Apostles
time you see the <HI>Corinthians</HI> found guilty of it, and condemned as
carnall. 1 <HI>Cor. 3. 4. for while one saith, I am of Paul, and another
I am of Apollo, are ye not carnall?</HI> but the sin died not with them.
After ages have yeelded us woefull fruits of this evill roote, chiefe∣ly
in the Papacie: The glorying in the first Roman Bishops who
were most of them holy Martyrs for Christ, begat such an high e∣steeme
of that See, that other Bishops and Churches began to e∣steeme
too much of their counsels and orders, as if they were a rule
for them to follow; which caused them quickly to take too much
on them, and the Christian Emperours and people to ascribe too
much to them; insomuch that quickly from a parity with other
Bishops, they got above them to a Patriarchate, and from a parity
with other Patriarkes, to a Precedency, and at last mounted up to
the throne of universall Episcopacy▪ whence it is that at this day
they that subject themselves to the Bishop of <HI>Rom,</HI> are become
the most deepely guilty of the sin of glorying in men of any that
ever were;<NOTE PLACE="marg">He teacheth in his book a∣gainst K. <HI>Iames</HI> under the name of <HI>Tor∣tus,</HI> and in his apology for it, that all are bound by an implicit oath in Baptisme to the Pope as Christs Vicar.</NOTE> for they ascribe an infallibility to him, a Power above
Councels, so that his determination is to be held as certaine, though
a generall Councell of all the Pastours of the Christian world
should gainesay it, his decrees and decretals are held as or<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cles
equall to the holy Scriptures, a power to interpret Scriptures un∣erringly,
to declare points of faith, to canonize Saints, to pardon
sins, to deliver out of Purgatory fire, with many more, whereby he
is <HI>exalted above all that is called God, or is worshipped,</HI> as was fore∣told,
2 <HI>Thes.</HI> 2. 4. nor doe they blush at the name of Papists being
derived from the Pope of <HI>Rome,</HI> but defend it, as <HI>Bellarmin. de
Nat. Eccl. cap.</HI> 4. And as all Papists in common are guilty of this
<PB N="16" REF="11"/>
sin, so in speciall the severall sects of Schoolemen and Friars,
Franciscans, Dominicans, Nominals, Reals, some glorying in <HI>Sco∣tus,</HI>
some in <HI>Aquinas,</HI> some in <HI>Occham;</HI> and that with so much
pertinacie and devotion, that they will not swerve in the least point
from their chiefe Master; insomuch, that as I remember <HI>Bannes</HI>
the Dominican disputing about an article in Philosophy, <HI>Com. in
Arist. de gen. &amp; corrup.</HI> expresseth his dislike of one that dissen∣ted
from <HI>Aquinas,</HI> saying that he was not a Thomist, but an
Anti-thomist. Nor doe Protestant Divines dissemble, but com∣plaine
of this malady among themselves, as being the cause of that
miserable rent, which hath been, and is still continued between
those Pastours and Churches which are distinguished by the names
of Lutherans and Calvinists, which although it be disavowed by
the chiefest Writers of the reformed Churches, and by the Chur∣ches
in their publike confessions, yet it is not denied, but that it
hath tainted too many in them. <HI>Zanchius</HI> complaines against this
evill,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Epist. ad Ant∣verp. praefat. tom. 7. operum.</NOTE> calling it <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, a worshipping of men, and relates
with indignation the speech of one at <HI>Geneva,</HI> who being asked
why he would not sometimes heare <HI>Viret</HI> a worthy Preacher there,
answered, <HI>that if Paul should preach at the same time with Calvin,
he would heare Calvin;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Calvin Epist. 289. us{que} adeo <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> est ut vel cre∣pidas ejus ado∣randas putet.</NOTE> and another complaines in his Epistle to
<HI>Calvin,</HI> of a certaine person that was so <HI>affected to Luther, that
he thought his very shooes should be adored.</HI> I would to God
such exorbitancies had kept beyond the seas, and that this sin of
glorying in men had not crept into this Land, into this City. The
signes and symptomes of it are too manifest, disparaging some Prea∣chers
injuriously, extolling others immoderately, disdainefully
withdrawing from some without just cause, inordinately running
after others without sufficient reason; swallowing downe the
dictates of some without chewing, loathing the wholesome food
which others present, without tasting. And have not the fruites
been among our selves, evill divisions, janglings, evill censuring, and
such like? scoffing, contempt, hardning of themselves among our
adversaries? Brethren, if there be any guilty of this sin here pre∣sent,
let him now know it to be his sin, and that no small one, and
let him be humbled for it, and repent of it, that he may obtaine
pardon: possibly some godly persons may have fallen into it, not
knowing it to be a sin, but sure I am, no one that feares God, will
dare to allow himselfe in it being convicted that it is his sin.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="application">
<PB N="17" REF="11"/>
<HEAD>Application 2. In a serious disswasive from this sin in these times,
with some directions to prevent the infections thereof.</HEAD>
<P>2. Wherefore in the second place, give me leave to admonish
you, that you take heed of it. It is an evill that usually doeth
follow those Churches to which God bestowes excellent gifts,
and worthy Teachers; and doubtlesse the Lord hath inriched this
City with this most desireable kind of riches above all places of
the earth; so that this City may be said in this respect, to be si∣tuated
under the line, and the inhabitants here to be without sha∣dow.
Great and many lights God hath given to you, and that in
many successions a long time, <HI>uno avulso non deficit alter,</HI> when
one is removed, God supplies you with another. But to what end
is it? not that you should magnifie them, but use them to bring
you nearer unto God, not to glory in the gift, but to rejoyce in
the giver, reverence and make use of them, but reserve to their
Lord his owne prerogative: may not you justly feare that God
will take them away from you, when you give his due to them?
we blame not a father if he remove a servant from his child, when
a child doeth inordinately affect him, to the deminution of his re∣spect
to the father; nor can we God, if he subtract a good thing
which we abuse: the best way to have good things continued by
God, is to use them for God, and to esteeme them for his sake;
but to set our hearts only on him that gave them. Besides doth
not our glorying in men bring us into bondage to them? doth it
not insensibly draw upon us an adherence to their errours, if God
for our triall suffer them to slip into any, or if they have none, to
a dangerous and unsound disposition to receive them if they hap∣pen.
We stand much for our Christian liberty, and there is great
cause we should, it is a pretious thing dearely bought, and is it
not one part of our Christian liberty, that <HI>we be not the servants of
men, 1 Cor.</HI> 7. 23. It concernes us then much, that we labour to
get such a firme constitution of soule, that neither through weak∣nesse
of understanding, nor through foolish affection we endan∣ger
our selves to hang on men, and so to bring our consciences in
bondage to them. We account the yoake of Bishops to have
been a grievous yoake, and that justly; if <HI>Hierome</HI> be not mista∣ken,
it was first occasioned by this sin of glorying in men;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Com on <HI>Tit.</HI> 1.</NOTE> and
it may be feared least this sin may occasion the keeping it on our
<PB N="18" REF="12"/>
necks: for is it not alleadged, take them away, men will follow
whom they please, so many schismes will be as Preachers? Any
of these reasons, much more all of them, should be a sufficient
caveat unto you to warne you of this. I might presse this mo∣nition
further, from the nature, causes and effects of this sin before
shewed; but I will hasten to shut up all with a few directions to
prevent it.</P>
<P>1. Endeavour to have ample thoughts of Christ, his eminency,
his fullnesse; the more high thy thoughts be of Christ, the lower
will thy conceits be of men, the larger comprehension thou hast
of him, the lesse wilt thou doate on his servants. A Courtier
when he is by himselfe drawes mens eyes after him, but when he
is with the King he is scarcely observed. If thou behold Christ as
the great Prophet of the Church, <HI>in whom are hid all the trea∣sures
of wisedome and knowledge,</HI> Christ will only be gloried
in his servants only respected as his instruments and attendants.
Remember <HI>that he is made to us of God, wisedome, righteous∣nesse,
and sanctification, and redemption; that as it is writ∣ten,
he that glorieth might glory in the Lord,</HI> 1 Cor. 1. 30, 31.</P>
<P>2. Have a right esteeme of all true Pastours and Teachers as the
Ministers of Christ, so the Apostle requires, 1 <HI>Cor. 4. 1. Let a
man account of us as Ministers of Christ, and Stewards of the
mysteries of God,</HI> neither make more of them nor lesse. Heare
them as messengers from Christ, not for their singular abilities,
but for their message sake; respect them not only for their ex∣cellent
wit and elocution, but for their faithfullnesse: note and
retaine not only fine speeches, but every solid truth, that is from
God, least while thou taste the dainty sawce, thou neglect the so∣lid
nourishment of thy soule; whoever he be that preacheth
Christ truly, heare him gladly, and receive him respectfully for his
Masters sake.</P>
<P>3. Make a fruitfull use of the gifts of every true Teacher, get
somewhat by all, and then thou wilt not glory in some, and dis∣parage
others; if thou didst profit by them, God should have glory
and every Minister due esteeme. It is in truth the vanity of the
hearers minds, their fullnesse that makes them slight Mannah, and
cry for Quailes, that they cannot affect a good Teacher if he be
not excellent; the despising of the Teacher, is commonly us'd
as a cloake of their owne unteachablenesse and disobedience,
<PB N="19" REF="12"/>
get an hungry soule after the word, and then every wholesome
truth will be welcome to thee: Remember that <HI>every gift of
the Spirit is given to profit withall, and should be received to
that end.</HI></P>
<P>4. Lastly, Be well grounded in knowledge, and constant in pra∣ctise
of what thou hast learned: <HI>Have thy senses exercised in the
word of righteousnesse, that thou mayest be able to discerne
both good and evill, Heb.</HI> 5. 14. and so thou shalt be
fitted to profit by every godly Preacher, and
inslave thy selfe to none, <HI>nor glory in
man, but in the Lord.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

