<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The declaration and protestation of the Kings Army in South-Wales, concerning their dread soveraign the King; as also touching His Majesties freedome, honour, and safety. Assented to and taken by Col. Poyer, and the rest of the Kings party in South-Wales, and now dispiersed into the severall counties of North-Wales, where it is now taking by the Cavalieres in the severall counties thereof. John Poyer. Likewise, a declaration of Sir Tho: Glenham, Sir Marmaduke Langdale, and the rest of the Kings party in the north of England, concerning their present design for the Kings Majesty.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A96526</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing W2247</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E438_13</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R204126</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99863819</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99863819</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">161654</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part.  Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A96526)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161654)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 69:E438[13])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The declaration and protestation of the Kings Army in South-Wales, concerning their dread soveraign the King; as also touching His Majesties freedome, honour, and safety. Assented to and taken by Col. Poyer, and the rest of the Kings party in South-Wales, and now dispiersed into the severall counties of North-Wales, where it is now taking by the Cavalieres in the severall counties thereof. John Poyer. Likewise, a declaration of Sir Tho: Glenham, Sir Marmaduke Langdale, and the rest of the Kings party in the north of England, concerning their present design for the Kings Majesty.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Wilkinson, Jonathan.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Glemham, Thomas, Sir, d. 1649.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Poyer, John, d. 1649.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 6 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by R.W.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>MDCXLVIII. [1648]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Includes a letter signed by Jonathan Wilkinson, and a protestation signed by John Poyer and three others.</NOTE><NOTE>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 4th".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-06.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Captivity, 1647-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Royalists --  Great Britain --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2007-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Elspeth Healey</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2007-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Elspeth Healey</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2008-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A96526">
<STC T="W">W2247</STC>
<STC T="T">E438_13</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99863819</BIBNO>
<VID>161654</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
DECLARATION
AND
PROTESTATION
OF
The Kings Army in South-Wales, Concerning their Dread
Soveraign the King; as also touching His Majesties
Freedome, Honour, and Safety.</P>
<P>ASsented to and taken by Col. <HI>Poyer,</HI> and the rest of the
Kings party in <HI>South-Wales,</HI> and now dispiersed into
the severall Counties of <HI>North-Wales,</HI> where it is now taking
by the Cavalieres in the severall Counties thereof. JOHN POYER.</P>
<P>LIKEWISE,
A Declaration of Sir <HI>Tho: Glenham,</HI> Sir <HI>Marmaduke Lang∣dale,</HI>
and the rest of the Kings Party in the North of
<HI>England,</HI> concerning their present Design for
the Kings Majesty.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI>
Printed by R. W. MDCXLVIII.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>An exact
RELATION
Of the
ROYALISTS
Proceedings in the North of
ENGLAND.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Honoured Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>SInce my last, there hath happened strange accidents in
these parts, the Royalists are become Masters of the
strong frontier Garrison the town of <HI>Beiwick,</HI> and
have posses'd themselves thereof; for a party consisting of
three troops of Horse and Dragoones, commanded by Sir
<HI>Thomas Glenham,</HI> Sir <HI>Marmaduke Langdale,</HI> and Captaine
<HI>Woogan,</HI> on Satterday night last in the evening, on a sudden,
entred <HI>Mary</HI> gate Port, and marched downe the great street
towards the town Hall, where they made a stand, dividing
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
themselves into three parties, for the better securing of the
town and the Bridge. Sir <HI>Marmaduke Langdale</HI> advanced to∣wards
the Bridge with a party of Horse and Dragoons, for
the securing of that place, and Sir <HI>Thomas Glenham,</HI> and cap.
<HI>VVoogan</HI> made good the streets with the other party; so
that they soon became masters both of Town and Forts, &amp;
immediatly cleered the streets of all persons whatsoever:
yet notwithstanding this sudden Alarm, the Mayor of the
town was very active and forward, and endeavoured to get
strength to oppose them, but could not, by reason of their
sudden possessing themselves of all the three Ports, and <HI>Megs</HI>
Mount: He was forced to his house, together with divers
Aldermen, and other well-affected of the towne, where they
were all surprized and taken. From thence, the Cavalry
marched to the Committee, where they took them also, ex∣cept
some few that escaped. Sir <HI>Thomas Glenham</HI> and <HI>Lang∣dale</HI>
have taken a view of the whole town, and are now for∣tifying
the same. They are raising a great Sconce or halfe
Moon upon K<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ngs Mount, for the c<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eering the Rampiers, and
command of the Seas. They are also repairing the Battery
upon Megs Mount, and making a Spur or Hornworke neer
the Castle and the Bridge, for cleering the River and Sands
upon <HI>Northumberland</HI> side. We hear that they intend to dis∣arme
all the Inhabitants that will not adhere to them, and
declare for the King. They have summoned (in his Maje∣sties
name) most of the Inhabitants about the townes adja∣cent,
and holds them close to their tacklings. They give out
high speeche, concerning Tinmouth and Newcastle. But of
this, more by the next.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Morpoth <DATE>the 1. of May
1648.</DATE></DATELINE>
Your assured friend,
<SIGNED>Jonathan Wilkinson.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Copy of a Letter from Newcastle.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>OUr new Governour Sir <HI>Arthur Haslerig</HI> is exceedingly well
appro<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed of by the well affected in these part<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. He i<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> v<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry care∣full
to strengthen this Garrison and Tinmouth, three Companies of
Major Gen <HI>Skippons</HI> Regiment are come hither: he is also very care∣full
to appease any tumults or insurrections, which are likely to a∣rise
in any of these parts.</P>
<P>From Scotland we heare, that the Parliament have passed their
Declaration, which is to be published, to give satisfaction to that
Nation in generall: the contents thereof are, the d<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ngers and duties
in relation to Religion, and the King and Kingdom. But because,
that in the points of Religion, the Parliament forgot to consult with
the Commissioners of the Church (who were in the nature of our
Assemb<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y of Divines in England) untill the said Declaration was
fully concluded and vote<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, many of the best affected, and others did
protest against it.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Newcastle <DATE>29. April, 1648.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>the Committee of this county upon a letter from Sir <HI>Arthur Ha∣slerig</HI>
met yesterday to consider of his desire to them, to meet the
Gentlemen of the other Northern Counties at Richmond, May 2. to
consider of put<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing their parts into a posture of defence, The Com∣mi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tee
of Durham have resolved to do something in relation there∣un<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.
The Cavaliers are very hi<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="broken" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> expectation of the Scots and
Scottish-English to come into England, and begin to give big
words to incense the Kingdom. The Prentices of Y<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rk should have
risen in a tumultuous manner, about the time of the mutiny at <HI>Lon∣don,</HI>
upon pretence of putting out the City Journymen that are not
free.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>York <DATE>the 29. of Aprill, 1648.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A Declaration of the present proceedings of the
Estates of the Kingdom of Scotland.</HEAD>
<P>THE Parliament of <HI>Scotland</HI> having finished
their Declaration it hath passed by a major part
in the vote vpon the question. But the Marq. of <HI>Argyle</HI>
and other Lords and Members of Parliament, to the
number of 60. protested against it, and caused their pro∣testations
to be entred, except they took the advice of
the Kirk, and had their concurrence therein Yet never∣thelesse
the Parliament proceeded vpon it, and putting
it again to the question, passed it vpon the vote by 41,
voyces so that Forces are to be raised. But the Marq.
of Argyle, and the rest of the other party, with the Mi∣nisters,
are resolved, that if they do march into <HI>England</HI>
upon that <HI>Declaration,</HI> that they will follow with ano∣ther
Army in the Rear of them, and that they have as∣surance
from the old Army, which consisteth of about
2500. Foot, and 1000. Horse, to joyne with them, they
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
cleave fast to the Clergy. The other party gives out,
that Prince <HI>Charles</HI> is to come over hither, and the
Marq of <HI>Montrosse</HI> with him, to lead the Army into
<HI>England</HI> when it is raised, and to hinder others from
falling in their Rear. The Parliament of <HI>Scotland</HI>
have almost finished their Demands which they intend
to send to the Parliament of <HI>England,</HI> it is said, they
consist of these heads, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P>2. That the Kings Majesty be brought from the
Isle of Wight to one of his houses neer <HI>London.</HI></P>
<P>2. That Chutch-Government may be setled ac∣cording
to the solemn League and Covenant of
both Kingdoms.</P>
<P>3. That Sectaries may no longer be incouraged
but quite abolished.</P>
<P>And lastly, touching the five Bills sent to the
King without their consent.</P>
<P>These Proposals, with some others, are said to bee
fully resolved vpon, and that the Committee of Estates
have made choice of one Colonell <HI>Marshal</HI> to be spee∣dily
dispatched for <HI>England,</HI> and to present the same
to both Houses of Parliament assembled at <HI>Westmin∣ster.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
BY Letters from Wales it is further advertized, that a party
of about 3 Troopes of Hor<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e commanded by Col. <HI>F<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>emming</HI> (a
Gentleman of valour and resolution) which being on a sudden too
deeply ingaged with <HI>Poyers</HI> Forces, were not only over powred, but
ingaged in a place of disadvantage, where relief could not come un∣to
them nor they make good their retreat: so that Col. <HI>Flemming</HI>
was slain, and few with him escaped. This is all we know for tru<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h
in that businesse, and as for that report, that others of col. <HI>Hortons</HI>
Forces were routed, and their ammunition was taken, and they pur∣sued,
&amp;c. there are no letters which do expresse it, neither doe wee
know any other grounds for it, then mens humours, which often
times speak as they would have it.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The Protestation.</HEAD>
<P>WEE whose Names are subscribed do declare, that we wil
use our utmost endeavours, to bring the King to a
personall treaty with his Parliament, with freedome, honour, and
safety, to the end, that the just prerogative of the King, privi∣ledge
of Parliaments, Lawes of the Land, and liberty of the peo∣ple,
may be all maintained and preserved in the proper bounds,
and the protestant Religion, as it now stands, established by the
Lawes of the Land, and restored throughout the Kingdom, with
such regard to be had to tender consciences, as shall be allowed
by Act of Parliament.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Assented to by
<LIST>
<ITEM>Colonell John Poyer,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Captain Powell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Colonell Powell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Captain Smith.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED>
<DATE>May 4. 1648.</DATE>
<SIGNED>Imprimatur G. M.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

